Stanford University.
General relativity,
GR.
For some reason that I don't know,
special relativity is never called
SR.
General relativity is often called GR.
My guess is a good many
of you know a little bit
about general relativity,
but I'm starting at the beginning
and my own taste in the matter
is to start pretty much where Einstein started.
It's not that I can't get past my love affair
with Einstein,
it's not that.
It just seems to me the
right way to approach the subject,
to begin with the equivalence principle,
begin with the basic simplest facts
that you can think of.
And that's what I'm going to do.
You know,
I probably said this before,
but it was a pattern of Einstein's thinking to
start with a really,
really simple elementary facts that
almost a child could understand
and deduce these incredibly
far reaching consequences of them.
And personally I think that's the
way to go about teaching it,
to start with the simplest
things and deduce the consequences.
So I will begin with the equivalence principle.
What is the equivalence principle?
The equivalence principle is the principle that says that
gravity is in some sense the same thing as acceleration.
So we want to get that on the
table,
say what it means,
give an example or two about how Einstein used it,
and then
go on from there to asking what kind of
mathematical structure does a theory have to have in order
that the equivalence principle be true.
What are the kinds of
mathematics that have to describe it?
I'm sure most of you know that general
relativity is a theory not only about gravity,
but it's
a theory about geometry.
So it's kind of interesting to start
at the beginning and ask what is
it that led the man to say
that gravity has something to do with geometry.
Okay,
so gravity equals acceleration.
What does that mean?
And I'm going to take you back,
we're going to go through a very elementary derivation
of what that means.
It's not that this derivation is important,
but it's worth formalizing.
Formalizing means making equations that say the words.
You all know that if you're in
an accelerated frame of reference,
an elevator accelerating upward or downward,
you feel
an effect of gravitational field.
Okay,
so you're going to take the equation and you're going to
say that gravity is in some sense the same thing as acceleration.
Children know that because they feel it.
You know that,
you can probably even explain to me why that's true,
but it's worth making
a little bit of,
sort of overkill,
but making mathematics out of it and then seeing what
that mathematics is talking about.
Okay so,
let's imagine the Einstein thought experiment.
Somebody in an elevator.
The elevator got promoted to a rocket ship.
And I'm going to show you some later textbooks,
but I've never been in a rocket ship.
I have been in an elevator,
and so I know what it
feels like to be in an elevator.
And let's think of an elevator.
An elevator is moving upward,
and maybe moving downward,
in which case this velocity vector
here is negative.
But let's draw just a velocity vector.
This is not a cable pulling it up,
or it could be a cable pulling it up,
but it's just a
velocity vector.
Okay,
the velocity vector is up.
And there are two coordinate frames.
One coordinate frame is at rest on the earth,
and let's call it z.
I use the z coordinate
for the vertical coordinate of space,
and down here someplace is z equals
zero.
Could be the surface of the earth,
doesn't matter.
Now in the elevator there's also a coordinate system,
and that coordinate system is being
measured.
It's arbitrary,
but we'll do it anyway.
It's being measured from the floor of the elevator,
and so the same physical point,
let's say it's a point over here,
has a z coordinate,
and it has a z prime coordinate,
and z prime is measured from the floor.
Now the height of the floor of the eleph- elephant,
not the elephant,
the elevator.
The floor of the elevator,
its height relative to z equals zero,
let's give a name,
let's
call it l.
Okay?
Okay.
And l is clearly a function of time.
We're going to be interested in the following question.
If we know the laws
of physics in the frame z,
surely we can figure out them in the frame
z prime,
and we're going to do that.
Now one warning,
not warning,
but one fact about today's lecture.
At least in the start,
I'm going to ignore special relativity.
This is tantamount to saying that we're
pretending that the speed of light is infinite.
Or we're talking about motions which are so
slow that the speed of light can be regarded
as infinitely fast.
In fact,
you might say,
if general relativity is
the generalization of special relativity,
how did Einstein get away
with starting thinking without special relativity?
And the answer is something like this.
Special relativity has to do with very high velocities.
Gravity has to do with heavy masses.
There's a range of situations where gravity
is important where high velocities are not.
So Einstein started out thinking
about gravity for slow velocities,
and then combined it
with special relativity to think about
the combination of fast velocities and gravity.
And that's the general theory.
But let's see what we know just from slow velocities.
Okay?
Let's begin with inertial reference frames.
Let's suppose that z prime,
both z and z prime,
are inertial reference frames.
That means they're related by uniform velocity.
Uniform velocity.
And that means that L of t
can just be taken to be vt.
The height of the elevator relative to the floor.
Not the floor,
but relative to the ground,
is just given by a uniform velocity,
v times
t.
I've chosen the coordinates such that at t equals zero,
they line up.
At t equals zero,
both z and z prime are equal to zero.
And now the elevator is rising,
and the height is proportional.
The height of the floor is proportional to vt.
And then we can write down what
the connection between z prime and z is.
Z prime,
this distance,
is just z.
Okay?
Minus L.
Now L is a function of time.
So it's z minus L of t.
If we know what L of t is,
this is a kind of coordinate transformation.
What about t prime?
What about time in the elevator?
We also ought to ask
how time behaves in the elevator.
If we're going to forget special relativity,
we're going to have to do something about it.
Then we can just say t
prime and t are the same thing.
We don't have to think about
Lorentz transformations and that sort of thing.
So the other half of the coordinate transformation
would be t prime is equal to t.
They're just the same thing.
And finally,
we could also put another coordinate in here.
Later on,
we'll be interested in the coordinate x going this way.
There's also one coming out of the blackboard y.
And as long as the elevator is not sliding,
it's not sliding horizontally,
then x prime and x can
be taken to be the same.
It's true.
I've sort of offset the elevator relative to this axis,
but I didn't have to do that.
I could have put the z
axis right down the middle here,
in which case I would say that
x prime is the same as x.
That's a coordinate transformation.
It's a coordinate transformation
of the spacetime coordinates.
It's rather trivial.
Only one coordinate,
namely z,
is involved in any interesting way.
We can,
if we like,
put a prime here,
because t prime and t are the same thing.
Okay,
now,
if I set L of t equal to vt,
then this is very simple.
Minus vt.
Good.
Now let's ask about a law of physics.
Let's take the law of physics,
Newton's law of motion,
f equals ma.
And what is a?
a is z double dot.
The second time derivative of z with respect to time.
That's called the acceleration,
the vertical acceleration.
This,
of course,
is the z component of force.
Let's forget about the x component of
force and the y component of force.
They're not interesting in this context.
Whatever force is exerted,
now this is the formula in the z equation,
the z frame.
This is z.
We can imagine in the z frame
that there are forces acting on a particle.
This could be a particle over here.
There are forces acting on it.
What do those forces do?
Well,
there could be some charge in here,
exerting forces on a charged object in here.
It could just be a
force due to a rope hanging
of the particle from the ceiling.
Any number of different kinds of forces
could be acting on
the particle over here.
And we know that its equation of motion
in the original frame of reference is just
f equals m z double dot.
What is the equation of motion in the primed frame?
Well,
this is very easy.
All we have to do is
figure out what the original acceleration is
in terms of the primed acceleration.
What is the primed acceleration?
The primed acceleration is obviously z prime double dot.
And z prime double dot,
z prime acceleration,
is just gotten by differentiating this twice.
But if I differentiate vt twice,
I get nothing.
It's linear in t.
Differentiate it twice,
you get nothing.
And you simply find z double prime,
z prime double dot is just z double dot.
The acceleration and the two
frames of reference are the same.
Now,
I know you know this.
I know you know all about this.
But I wanted to,
you know,
sort of formalize it
to bring out some points,
in particular,
the point that we're doing a coordinate transformation.
And we're asking how laws of physics
change in going from one frame to another.
So now,
what can we say about the Newton's law
in the primed frame of reference?
Well,
we can now just substitute.
f equals m z double dot prime.
And what do we find?
We find that the law,
Newton's law,
in the primed frame is exactly the same
as Newton's law in the unprimed frame.
That's not surprising.
They're moving with uniform velocity relative to each other.
If one of them is an inertial frame,
the other is an inertial frame.
Newton taught us that the laws of physics
are the same in all inertial frames.
So that's a sort of formalization of the argument.
Now let's go to an accelerated reference.
An accelerated reference frame,
L of t will be increasing in an accelerated way.
And so,
an accelerated way would be to put here
one half the acceleration times t,
times t squared,
excuse me,
and let's call the acceleration g,
little g,
for obvious reasons.
Let's call the acceleration little g.
If you don't know what the obvious reason is,
you'll find out in a minute.
All right,
now,
this is a uniform acceleration.
If I differentiate L twice,
the first time,
let's do it,
if I differentiate it once,
I get L dot,
and that's just gt.
Notice that this says that the velocity
of the floor increases with time.
It's not steady velocity.
And L double prime,
L double dot,
is just equal to g.
So this elevator is uniformly accelerated upward,
and the equation connecting
the coordinate transformation now
is different.
It's minus one half gt squared.
So that's my new coordinate transformation
to represent the relationship between coordinates
which are accelerated relative to each other.
I'll continue to assume that in the z coordinates here,
the laws of physics are exactly what Newton taught us.
Let's ask what the laws of physics are now
in the prime frame of reference.
We have to do this operation over again,
but we know the answer.
If we differentiate twice here,
we get this thing differentiated twice,
plus,
or minus in this case,
just g.
The second time derivative of this is just minus g.
All right,
so the primed acceleration
and the unprimed acceleration differ by amount z,
g.
And now we can write Newton's equations
in the primed frame of reference.
Z double dot,
if we just transpose the g to the other side,
g plus,
looks like this.
And now we can substitute,
and it says that f is equal to m
times z prime double dot
plus m,
g.
And so we find,
as expected of course,
there's nothing here unexpected,
that in the primed frame of reference,
it looks like,
ooh,
do I have something wrong?
Somehow I think I have the wrong sign.
Minus g,
must be minus g.
What did I do?
Did I do something wrong?
Z prime,
hmm?
Z double dot is z double prime dot plus g,
is that right?
Yeah.
Okay.
Right.
Oh,
sorry,
okay.
It's fine.
Right,
I want to shift it to
the other side of the equation,
of course.
Minus mg on the other side of the equation.
Why do I want to
shift it to the other side?
Because I want to make
it look like a Newton equation.
Mass times acceleration is equal to something,
and that's something I call the
force in the primed frame of reference.
And you notice,
as expected,
the force in the primed frame
of reference has an extra term,
a sort of fictitious term,
which is just the mass times the acceleration of the,
of the elevator.
Now what's interesting,
of course,
what's interesting about it is it
looks exactly like the force law
of a particle at the surface of the Earth
or at the surface of any kind of gravitating system,
uniform gravitational field.
It looks like a uniform gravitational field,
but let me spell out in
what sense it looks like gravity.
The special feature of gravity is
that gravitational forces are proportional to mass.
That has a deep implication.
The deep implication is since the equation is,
the equations of motion are F equals mA,
and if the force itself is somehow proportional to mass,
then the mass cancels,
and the acceleration and the total motion of the system,
of the object,
doesn't depend on its mass.
That's a characteristic of gravitational forces,
that an object moving in a gravitational force,
small object in gravitational force,
its motion doesn't depend on its mass.
An example,
for example,
would just be the motion
of the Earth about the Sun
is independent of the mass of the Earth.
If you know where the Earth is at some instant,
and you know how fast it's moving,
then you can predict how it moves
without regard of what the mass is.
All right,
so here's an example of a fictitious force,
if you like,
if you want to call it that,
mimicking the effect of gravity.
I think most people before
Einstein considered this largely an accident.
Just,
people knew it.
They certainly knew that the effect of acceleration
mimicked the effect of gravity,
but they didn't pay much attention to it.
It was Einstein who said,
look,
this is a principle,
this is a deep principle of nature,
that gravitational forces cannot be distinguished
from the effect of an accelerated reference frame,
from the effect of looking at
physics in an accelerated reference frame.
That physically they are the same thing,
but they are not distinguishable.
Now,
that's,
we're going to have to discuss that a little bit,
whether we really believe that quite
in as much detail as I said,
but before we do that,
let's draw some pictures
of what these various coordinate transformations look like.
Let's first take the case where
L is just equal to Vt.
L equals Vt,
that was x prime,
is equal to x minus Vt,
or z prime,
did I say x?
Z,
I mean.
Z.
Z prime.
Alright,
here is,
vertically I plot time,
horizontally I plot z,
that's z,
not z prime,
and let's put in some guidelines,
here's,
of course the vertical axis is z equals zero,
here's z equals one,
here's z equals two,
and so forth.
Here's z equals three.
Three.
Now let's put in,
and here of course is z equals zero.
Now let's put in z prime equals zero.
Z prime equals zero is
the same as z equals Vt.
Z equals Vt is a trajectory
that moves upward to the right,
and looks like,
this.
How about z prime equals one?
Z prime equals one looks like this,
z prime equals two looks like that,
z prime equals three looks like this,
and this is the nature of the coordinate transformation
that relates the primed and the unprimed reference frame.
Every point has a coordinate t and z,
has a pair of coordinates t and z,
and also an x incidentally,
but I've dropped it,
a t and a z and a y,
and the z prime and the
z coordinates are related in this way,
also t prime is equal to t.
Let's put in t prime equals t.
So,
that's called a linear transformation,
straight lines go to straight lines.
Not surprising,
since Newton tells us that particles move in straight lines,
in an inertial frame of reference,
and what is a straight line in one reference?
In one frame,
there had therefore better be a
straight line in the other frame.
They move in straight lines not only in space,
but in spacetime.
Okay,
now let's do the same
thing for the accelerated coordinate system.
Where is it?
Z,
z prime is equal to
z minus one half gt squared.
So let's look at z prime equals zero,
the trajectory of the origin of the z prime coordinates.
That's the same as z equals one half gt squared.
That's a parabola.
Okay,
it's a parabola lying on its side.
Why?
Because,
um,
I've inter,
well,
because,
because it's a parabola lying on its side.
So it looks like,
it looks like this.
That's the trajectory.
It's accelerating,
it's going faster and faster and faster.
Incidentally,
I could run this back into the past.
A uniform accelerated,
acceleration upward,
forever and ever,
would correspond to something moving downward,
decelerating,
and then going up and going back up.
Okay?
So if I wanted to continue this,
to make a full uniformly accelerated trajectory out of it,
it would look like this.
Z comes down,
then goes back up,
up and down.
All right,
what about z prime?
This is,
this now is z prime equals zero.
What about z prime equals one?
Well,
that's just a shift of this parabola,
which I always have trouble drawing.
It always,
I don't know,
it always gets cramped somehow.
Z prime equals two looks like this.
These parabolas seem to be getting narrower and narrower,
but that's only because I'm not good at drawing.
I'm not good at drawing them.
Each one is just shifted relative
to the previous one by one unit.
And the point is,
of course,
not surprisingly,
straight lines in one frame are
not straight lines in the other frame.
They're curved lines.
And so one would say,
did I write the wrong thing here?
That was,
yeah,
one half gt squared.
gt squared over two.
That's the coordinate system here.
This is a curvy linear coordinate transformation.
So something Einstein understood very early
is there's a connection between gravity
and curvy linear coordinate transformations of space-time.
That special relativity was all about linearity.
And so what we're talking
about here is linear transformations,
transformations which took uniform
velocity to uniform velocity.
Lorentz transformations are of that nature.
Take straight lines in space-time
to straight lines in space-time.
But if we want to mock up gravitational fields
through their effect on,
through the effects of acceleration,
we're really talking about transformations
of the coordinates of space-time,
which are curvy linear.
And so what Einstein realized is that if you,
that,
yeah,
okay,
I said it.
I don't need to say it again.
Let me just give you one example.
This sounded,
this sounds extremely trivial.
Doesn't it?
It sounds very trivial.
We all knew it.
And I think every physicist when Einstein said it
probably also knew it and said,
oh,
yeah,
well,
big deal.
But Einstein was very clever.
He realized this could answer questions
that nobody knew how to answer.
So let me give you one example.
I've used this in this class a number of times,
but we're going to do it anyway.
An example of a question that Einstein answered this way.
The question had to do with what is the influence
of gravity on light?
Now,
at that time,
around 1907 or something,
when Einstein first thought about these things,
maybe even 1905,
he started thinking about gravity.
Most physicists would have answered,
there is no effect of gravity on light.
Light is light.
Gravity is gravity.
A light wave moving near a gravitating object
just moves in a straight line.
That's the law of light,
that it moves in straight lines,
and there's no reason to think that gravity
has any effect on it.
But Einstein said,
no.
If it is true that this is a principle,
the equivalence between acceleration and gravity,
then acceleration is a principle.
Then gravity will affect light.
And the argument was very simple.
Again,
one of these arguments which
you could almost explain to a child.
Let's start out with a light wave,
a light beam,
whatever it is.
This is x now,
not z.
z is vertical.
Let's start out with a light beam
that's moving horizontally,
starting out at t equals zero,
at t equals zero,
the velocity of the elevator is zero.
At t equals zero,
the velocity begins to build up from t equals zero.
the two frames of reference are matched,
they're both at rest relative to
each other at t equals zero.
And a flashlight beams a beam of light this way.
Okay.
Now,
in the unprimed frame of reference,
the z frame of reference,
we know how the light wave moves.
Or at least Einstein said,
in the frame of reference without any gravity,
because there is gravity on the surface of the Earth,
what am I talking about?
We shouldn't be,
for our purposes now,
the Earth is so light that it
doesn't make any gravity of its own.
All of the gravity is due to the acceleration.
All of the gravity is due to the acceleration,
or the apparent gravity.
And so we said,
well,
in the frame of reference
at rest where there is no gravity,
we know what the light wave does.
The light wave just moves horizontally across here.
All right.
If we could write down,
again,
I want to write the equations just to illustrate.
What is the equation of this light beam?
Well,
it's first of all x horizontal,
is equal to the speed of light times the time.
Let's make this distance here L.
Different L.
X is equal to ct.
That's how our light moves.
And also z is equal to zero.
Z doesn't change in the unprimed frame of reference.
It just moves horizontally.
So that's the equation of the light beam.
But now let's plug in the primed frame of reference.
In the primed frame of reference,
z is equal to z prime plus tg squared.
So we have that z prime
plus g t squared over 2
is equal to zero.
That's the equation of the light beam.
X is still just equal to ct.
And that's it.
So here we see what the light beam is doing
in the primed frame of reference.
Namely,
it's moving on a curved trajectory.
If we were to calculate its vertical component of velocity,
we would discover it looks like that.
I say in the primed frame of reference,
gravity is pulling the light beam down.
You say,
no,
no.
It's just that the elevator is accelerating upward.
And that makes it look like the
light beam moves on a curved trajectory.
And Einstein said the same thing.
This proved to him that
the effect of a gravitational field
on a light ray was to cause it to curve,
was to cause it to bend.
And that was something that no
other physicist knew at the time.
So,
clever.
Okay.
But up till now,
what we've learned,
the thing that I want to abstract out of this,
is that it's interesting to think about
curvilinear coordinate transformations.
When you do think
about curvilinear coordinate transformations,
Newton's laws do change,
or the form of Newton's laws change.
And one of the things
that happens is apparent gravitational fields
materialize
that are physically indistinguishable
from ordinary gravitational fields.
Well,
are they really physically indistinguishable?
Not really.
Let's talk about real gravitational fields,
namely gravitational fields of gravitation,
gravitating objects like the sun or the earth.
Here's the sun or the earth.
And the gravitational acceleration,
doesn't point vertically on this blackboard,
it points toward the center.
So,
there's gravitational fields pointing radially inward.
It's pretty obvious that there's no way
that you can do a coordinate transformation like this,
which will remove the effect of the gravitational field.
Yes,
if you're in a small laboratory here,
and that laboratory is allowed
to simply fall toward the sun,
or whatever it happens to be,
then you will think in that laboratory
that there is no gravitational field.
But there is no way
globally to introduce a coordinate transformation
which is going to get rid of the fact
that there's a gravitational field
pointing inward toward the center.
If you make a transformation like this,
it might get rid of the gravity over here,
for this infalling object,
but the same transformation on this side
will just increase the gravitational field.
So,
no,
there is no way to get rid of it.
We know there's no way to get rid of it.
And one way to understand why
you can't get rid of it
is because if you think of an object
which is not very,
very small in this gravitational field,
let's suppose it's...
Okay.
My favorite 2,000 mile man.
The 2,000 mile man is falling in the gravitational field.
Well,
let's start him out differently first.
Let's start him out falling feet first.
Okay.
Because he's large,
not the point mass,
the different parts of him
feel different gravitational fields.
The further away you are,
the weaker the gravitational field is.
And so his head feels a
weaker gravitational field than his feet.
Okay.
His feet are being pulled harder than his head.
Guess what?
He feels like he's being stretched.
If he's freely falling,
he can't distinguish this
from a stretching feeling,
but he knows that there's a gravitating object there.
That gravitating object cannot be
removed by...
And the sense of discomfort that he has
cannot be removed by going to a falling reference frame.
These are,
of course,
tidal forces.
Tidal forces cannot be removed by...
If he's very small,
of course,
if he's very small,
then his feet and his
head feel the same gravitational force.
What happens if he's sideways falling?
Well,
if you look at this gravitational field,
you can easily see that
there's a component
of the gravitational acceleration,
gravitational force on his feet,
which is pointing upward here,
just because this vector has an upward component,
and this one has a downward component,
so he'll experience a sense of compression.
And that sense of compression is,
again,
not something that you can remove
by coordinate...
by any coordinate transformation.
It's an invariant fact.
Being squashed to death is an invariant fact.
It's not something you can make go away
by doing a coordinate transformation.
So...
So it is not true
that gravity is equivalent to
going to an accelerated reference frame.
Einstein,
of course,
knew this.
I mean,
he was no fool.
He knew this.
So what he really said is that
small objects for a small length of time
cannot tell the difference between
a gravitational field and an accelerated frame of reference.
But that then raises the question,
if I present you with a force field,
for example,
the force field associated with uniform acceleration
is just a vertical force field pointing downward
and uniform everywhere.
It's a consequence of
this nonlinear coordinate transformation.
But,
nevertheless,
it behaves,
for an observer using these coordinates,
like a gravitational field.
But with other kinds of coordinate transformations,
you can make the gravitational field look more complicated.
Other kinds of coordinate transformations,
for example,
transformations
which affect the x-coordinate also,
for example,
they can make the gravitational
field bend toward the x-axis.
Supposing you simultaneously accelerate along the z-axis
while oscillating back and forth in the x-axis.
Your frame of reference is oscillating backward and forward
along the x-axis and accelerating along the z-axis.
What kind of gravitational field do you see?
A very complicated one.
It's got a vertical component,
and it has a time-dependent oscillating component.
along the x-axis.
So by appropriate coordinate transformations,
you can make some
pretty complicated apparent gravitational fields.
If I tell you what the gravitational field is everywhere,
how do I determine if it's
just a sort of fake gravitational field
coming from doing a coordinate transformation
using a frame of reference
with various kinds of accelerations in it?
Or is it a real genuine gravitational field?
Well,
if it's just Newtonian gravity,
there's an easy way.
You just calculate the tidal forces.
You calculate whether that gravitational field
will have an effect on an object
which will cause it to squeeze and stretch.
If it does,
then it's a real gravitational field.
If you discover that that gravitational field
has no such effect on any object,
no tidal force,
no tendency to distort a freely falling system,
a system which is in free fall,
then no matter where it is,
drop it here,
wherever you drop it,
if it doesn't have such a tidal effect,
then it's not a real gravitational field.
Yeah?
It seems like you could simulate the tidal force.
For example,
if you had to put a rocket engine
at a speed in his head
and have it more powerful than...
Say that again?
It seems like you could simulate
even the tidal forces.
Suppose you had a rocket engine on its feet
that has a greater thrust at one on its head.
It doesn't matter.
In the unprimed frame of reference,
there is no gravitational field.
So there's no way that there can be
a distortion of the gravitational field.
There's no distorting effect on you or anybody else
because you can calculate it in the unprimed frame,
and there was no gravitational field.
So the question then is,
how do you know when it's possible
to make a coordinate transformation
that removes the gravitational field?
How do you know when
it's just an artifact of coordinates
or when it's a real physical thing
due to some gravitating mass,
for example?
That's a question.
Question?
Yeah.
Just,
this is intuition,
and it's probably way off the mark,
but in a situation where you have one body
creating a gravitational field,
what happens if you go to an angular coordinate system?
In terms...
Right.
Good.
Of course,
that...
We don't even know
if we're going to need
to have a gravitating object there.
We could have no gravitating object
and go to polar coordinates.
I think that's what you're talking about,
right?
Okay?
Now,
that means we have two coordinates,
r and theta.
Supposing we didn't know that these were polar coordinates.
All we knew was there was a coordinate r
and a coordinate theta,
and I gave you...
I told you how a particle moves
theta and r
as a function of time.
How would the particle move,
meaning to say,
what would theta of t
and r of t...
How would they behave
as a function of time?
And I would plot that.
I would look at it and see
what kind of motion the particle had,
theta and r as a function of time.
So let's guess.
Let's suppose a particle moves across here.
What happens to r?
Well,
r starts decreasing,
decreasing,
and incidentally,
theta is increasing.
Well,
I take it back.
It's decreasing.
It's going this way.
But theta is evolving,
and meanwhile,
at the same time,
r is decreasing,
decreasing,
until it gets to here,
and then it goes back out.
This person who was using polar coordinates
and didn't know it,
would say there must be a repulsive force
repelling the particle away from r equals zero.
And that repulsive force is...
We know what it is.
It's a centrifugal force.
It's a centrifugal force of having some angular momentum.
But nevertheless,
if you didn't know where you got these coordinates from,
you would say,
my God,
look what's happening.
r is coming in and going back out.
Effectively,
there is some kind of repulsive force.
That repulsive force would be proportional to the mass.
Centrifugal force is proportional to mass.
And you'll say,
this is an interesting situation.
There's a radial outward gravitational field.
In every respect,
it would behave as if there was a gravitational field
pushing things outward from the center.
Maybe you might think there's some matter out there.
That wouldn't be right.
But a ring of matter out there pulling it,
that wouldn't be right.
But you would have discovered a force on an object
which pulls it out.
And it pulls it out proportional to the mass.
And you would say,
I found something new.
I've discovered kind of anti-gravity
pulling me away from the center.
So basically,
any kind of coordinate transformation you do,
if the coordinate transformation is nonlinear,
in other words,
doesn't take lines to lines,
will produce effectively
some kind of effective fictitious force.
What are the fictitious forces here?
Centrifugal force,
Coriolis force,
all those kinds of things.
And they all have the character of gravitational forces.
But again,
again,
somebody in a small laboratory moving along here
would not experience any sort of distorting effect,
clearly,
because we can always
study it in the inertial frame,
the linear,
the nice linear reference frame,
and there are no distorting effects.
So it follows that by a coordinate transformation
you can get rid of these fictitious forces.
The question is,
if I just give you a gravitational field,
how do I know if
I can get rid of them?
Well,
the answer is calculate things like tidal forces.
But,
yeah.
Isn't that only true?
I'm not sure if you go in with two bodies
and you assume that there exist more than two bodies.
You could have one that's below the trajectory,
another that's in the same position,
another on the third and top of the next slide.
Say that again?
No,
I don't understand.
I think the analysis that you gave only holds
if you've got two bodies.
No.
So if you had three bodies,
for example,
one that's above the trajectory,
the same distance as the point down below it,
so it's a mirroring that could be applied
to t that you've got in x equals ct.
Yeah,
it cancels out the other one.
And then if you had a third
that's where the big sun is,
for example,
the two that offset one of them would cancel out.
There's nothing making a gravitational field here.
This is just an artifact of a coordinate system.
Now,
I'm trying to give you a
four-body example where I don't think
you have the tidal forces.
If you have four bodies,
making a gravitational field?
Well,
there certainly will be tidal forces
for something falling in over here.
As it's passing.
Hmm?
謝謝
I'll start with this first.
Yeah,
if there are four objects
over here creating a gravitational field,
and one of them,
and somebody gets close to one of them,
they can forget the other ones,
and they'll experience a tidal force.
So,
what do you do?
You try all possible coordinate transformations.
Coordinate transformations means coordinate
transformations of space and time,
and rewrite the equations of motion,
and see if you can find the coordinate
transformation that eliminates all of the fictitious forces.
If you can,
then you say there's no real gravitational field there.
If you can't,
you say,
yes,
there was a real gravitational
field that could not be eliminated.
Now,
Einstein,
yeah.
What is the way to compute tidal forces?
Oh,
you take a chunk,
a mass of some kind,
an object,
a crystal,
and you put the crystal into the
gravitational field and you let it fall,
and you ask whether there are
stresses and strains on the crystal
which squeeze it one way
and stress it the other way.
Yeah.
And these would be detectable things.
So,
coming back to the centrifugal thing,
so let's say our 2,000-mile man is on a merry-go-round.
He's on a merry-go-round.
Okay,
this was not a merry-go-round.
This was just a use
of coordinates which were not the...
Right.
So,
I mean,
couldn't you kind of come up with something,
like his feet are going to
be moving with that centrifugal force
that is 2,000 miles away and doesn't feel it.
So,
don't you end up with something like that?
No,
no,
okay.
No,
no.
When I say there is no effective tidal force,
I mean for a freely falling object.
If you have a freely falling
object that's not being held in place
by ropes or pulleys or anything else,
it's just allowed to free fall,
then no.
No.
If there was a carousel rotating,
here it is,
rotating,
and somebody is in free fall,
they will appear to move very oddly from the
point of view of the person on the carousel,
but in the reference frame of the,
you know,
at rest relative to the Earth,
they move in nice straight lines,
and they feel no tidal forces.
So,
if you calculated the effect of
the tidal force in either frame,
you would find it zero.
In other words,
tidal force means effectively distorting stresses,
distorting stresses on matter that squeeze it and pull it.
Simplify it.
Does it give you a headache
or doesn't it give you a headache?
The answer is if you were in free fall,
if you're stuck on the carousel,
you might get a headache,
but you're not stuck on the carousel,
you're moving in free fall,
you get no headache.
So,
going back to what you were saying
about trying to transform the tidal forces away.
Yeah.
Okay.
I'm looking at your little
picture of the guy over there.
Yeah.
So,
if he's facing that direction,
he's going to get squeezed.
If he's rotated 90 degrees,
he's going to get stretched.
Could you be clever and
maybe tilt him a little bit?
You're going to tilt him at 45
degrees so he gets stretched and squeezed.
No,
no,
wait,
wait.
Let's put it,
okay.
This is not just a 2,000 mile man.
He's also 1,000 miles wide.
Okay?
He gets stretched and squeezed.
He gets stretched and squeezed,
and there's simply no way to get rid of it.
You have to look at all directions at once.
So,
if someone...
One question.
I think you're saying that because of tidal forces,
the equivalence crystal doesn't hold.
Well,
it means it has to be stated carefully.
It means it has to be stated carefully.
And,
um,
stating it carefully would say something like,
if you take a sufficiently small system,
small means such that the grav...
the gravitational field across it doesn't vary much.
If the gravitational field,
if it's small enough that the gravitational field
doesn't vary between one part of the system and another,
that is when the equivalence principle holds with accuracy.
Right.
Einstein knew all of that.
He,
uh...
And so he asked himself the question,
what kind of mathematics goes into,
um,
trying to answer this kind of question?
Now,
the other element
that came into it
was special relativity.
And he knew from the work of Minkowski
that special relativity had a geometry associated with it.
The geometry
had the property,
that it had a kind of length associated with it.
The length was called proper time.
Proper time or proper distance doesn't matter.
And I'm just going to
remind you about that very quickly.
In special relativity,
there is an invariant notion
of the space-time difference between a pair of points,
or a pair of neighboring points,
for example.
We're taking a rest now from gravity,
and we're coming back to special relativity.
And the only thing we're
going to use about special relativity
is that space-time has a geometry.
The geometry is the geometry discovered by Minkowski,
and it has a length element.
A length element means any pair of points
with x and t.
I'm going to use x and t now.
Of course,
there's also two other coordinates,
but let's concentrate on x and t.
And the space-time difference,
or distance between two points,
is called ds squared.
Depending on who's writing the equations,
they will either write ds squared or d tau squared.
And they only differ by a sign.
d tau squared is what?
Anybody remember?
d t squared minus d x squared,
yes?
Where does the speed of light go into this
if we wanted to put it in?
Is it the x squared over c squared,
or the x squared times c squared?
I can never remember.
d squared over c squared.
I think it's over c squared.
But we can always get rid
of this one over c squared
by redefining x.
Instead of calling it x,
call it x over c,
and it just becomes x squared then,
or just instead of x,
x over c.
And that in itself is a coordinate transformation.
So you can always bring this coordinate interval
to this form,
this being called proper time.
And some physicists like to use
the s squared,
which is exactly the same,
except by sign.
It's the x squared minus the t squared.
Einstein knew about this geometry,
and he realized that this question up there,
what kind of coordinate,
are there coordinate transformations
which can remove the effect of tidal forces,
was very similar to a certain mathematics problem
that had been studied at great length by Riemann.
Namely,
the question of deciding
whether a geometry was flat or not.
Geometry of a page is flat.
The geometry of a hemisphere is not flat,
or a sphere is not flat.
And he realized that there
was a great deal of similarity
in the two questions
of whether a geometry is flat,
whether a space-time has real gravitational field in it.
They were very similar.
So let's talk about that a little bit.
This minus sign here,
Riemann had never dreamt about.
Riemann had not thought about geometries
which have a minus sign here.
He was thinking about geometries which were similar
to Euclidean geometry.
What's the right formula in Euclidean geometry?
I think we want to start with the mathematics
of Riemannian geometry,
and we're not going to spend
a huge amount of time on it,
but we're going to spend a
little bit of time on it.
What's the corresponding thing for Euclidean geometry?
And now let's just say
there are a bunch of x's.
This could now be x1.
This could be x2.
There could be another x3 coming out here.
And supposing there's a little interval here
characterized by a dx,
and let's call it m.
m represents whether it's x1,
x2,
or x3.
This is not x1 squared.
This is x1,
x2,
and x3.
And if I prescribe for you
a set of,
in this case,
three dx's,
three components,
three components of a little shift,
what's the difference,
the distance between these two points?
And we all know it's just Pythagoras'
theorem.
In any number of dimensions,
it's the same.
The square of the distance,
and let's call it s now,
the square of the spatial distance between those two points
is just equal to dx1 squared plus dx2
squared plus dot dot dot,
however many there are.
If the space is three-dimensional,
then there are three of them.
If the space is two-dimensional,
there are two of them.
If the space is 26-dimensional,
there are 26 of them,
and so forth.
That is the formula for Euclidean distance on the Euclidean,
in the Euclidean space,
for the distance between two points.
Now,
Gauss had already understood that on curved surfaces,
the formula for the distance between two points
was more complicated in general than this.
Two-dimensional surfaces.
And Riemann generalized this to arbitrary dimensions,
however many dimensions you have,
and what was known from the theory of surfaces
is that the right formula
for the distance between two points,
first of all,
before we talk about it,
let's suppose we have some kind of surface.
Curved surface.
What we mean by it
being curved is not clear yet.
But some sort of arbitrary surface,
where it looks like it's curved,
where it has a...
no particular shape to it,
but we have every reason to think
it's got something that we might call curvature.
Okay.
So,
the first thing we do with it
is we put some coordinates on it.
We want to be able to quantify various statements,
and so we want to introduce some coordinates onto it.
We just lay out some kind of coordinates.
We don't worry at all about whether the coordinate axis
is straight lines or not,
because for all we know,
if the surface is a real curved surface,
there probably won't even be things
that we can call straight lines.
So,
we just lay out some coordinates,
and we call them x's.
Now we take two neighboring points.
Here's two neighboring points.
They're again related by a shift of the coordinates.
This shift over here is again called dxm.
But now for an arbitrary curved surface
with arbitrary coordinates,
coordinates of arbitrary kind of complexity,
the formula is not as simple as this.
It has similarities with it,
but it looks...
Any geometry,
curved or otherwise,
and incidentally,
this formula also applies
to flat geometries if you take curved coordinates.
If you take a flat geometry
like the surface of the blackboard
and you introduce some curved coordinates,
some curvilinear coordinates,
and you ask what is the distance between two points,
then in general,
the distance...
the square of the distance between two points
will be a quadratic form
in these little coordinate separations.
A quadratic form means
that you have a matrix,
gmn,
m and n could run from one to three,
for example,
and you just combine together gmn dx dx.
Just as I've written it here,
you've seen these kind of things before.
And in general,
g will depend on position.
Do you know an example?
How about distance in...
How about distance on the surface of the Earth
between two points characterized by longitude and latitude?
Do you know the formula
for the distance between two points?
You have...
No,
it's ds squared...
Okay,
so...
Theta...
Which one is which?
Latitude.
Theta is latitude squared.
It's the square of the radius of the Earth,
d theta squared and then what's the other one,
remember?
Hmm?
Well,
it's a d phi squared.
But it can't just be d phi squared.
If you look at the Earth,
phi goes this way,
theta goes this way.
A given amount of d phi can be
a big distance if you're near the equator,
and the same amount of d phi
is a small distance near the North Pole,
or the South Pole.
So there's something else that goes in here,
which has to do with how close to
the North Pole or South Pole you are.
Sine theta?
Sine theta squared.
Not sine of theta squared,
but sine squared of theta.
Now here's an example.
Here's an example of distance
not just being d theta squared plus d phi squared,
but having some coefficient functions in front.
Now in this case,
the interesting coefficient function is sine theta squared.
In general,
if you use arbitrary coordinates on the sphere,
you'll discover a much more complicated formula.
But it will always be something
which will involve the coordinates quadratically.
There'll be d theta squared terms,
there'll be d phi squared terms,
there'll be d theta times d phi terms,
there will never be d theta cubed terms,
there will never be things linear,
everything will be quadratic like this,
and you'll get some general formula,
which will involve
a matrix,
and a little separation of the x.
Excuse me,
don't we normally measure latitude from the equator,
so we can get cosine?
Say that again?
We don't measure latitude from the equator.
Sorry,
we do measure latitude from the equator.
Oh,
I'm sorry,
maybe,
let's see.
Yeah,
if you measure latitude from the equator,
it would be cosine squared.
Is that what you were getting at?
Yeah,
that's correct.
If latitude is measured from the equator,
it's cosine squared.
If it's measured from the north pole,
it would be sine squared theta.
So,
good point.
You're right.
But the important point is here,
that the formula for the distance
of a differential separation
involves functions
which sit in front of these quadratic expressions
in terms of the differential distances.
Okay.
And as I said,
this is just a very simple example.
More general examples would have
more complicated functions,
there might be a complicated function,
not necessarily complicated,
but a function in front of d theta squared,
there might be a function
in front of d phi squared,
and there may also be
a d theta d phi term.
All possibilities,
all those possibilities are included
by saying there's a general matrix here,
an M-N matrix,
which multiplies the differentials.
This,
yeah?
Supply with,
to macro distances,
not differential distances,
because that formula applies for any distance,
right?
Which one?
No,
it applies for,
no,
the reason it doesn't apply for arbitrary distances
is because you have to specify what point theta
you're talking about,
and it's only good for distances
nearby that point theta.
Yeah.
Okay,
the answer is,
in general,
for curvy linear coordinates,
it only applies,
if you want to know,
first of all,
if you want to know the distance between two points,
you better define it.
Take some arbitrary curved surface.
I don't know how to draw it.
It's got bumps and hills
and all kinds of things in it.
What do you even mean
by talking about the distance
between this point and that point over here?
Well,
you could mean something.
You could mean the shortest distance.
You could mean,
put a peg in here and a peg here,
and pull a string as tight as you can
between the two points,
and that would define one notion
of distance between the two points.
Of course,
there might be two answers.
One might go around the hill one way,
and one might go around the hill the other way.
So,
in general,
but think about it for a minute.
Even if there's only one answer,
a unique answer,
it's complicated.
You have to know the geometry
everywheres in between.
You have to know the curves and the hills,
not only to calculate the distance,
but to know actually where it is.
Where to place the string.
If I put another hill in over here,
the string would have to go differently.
So the notion of the distance
between two points
is a complicated one.
But the notion of the
distance between two neighboring points
is not so complicated.
Or for small distances
between the points.
So basically what you can imagine doing
is you're building the geometry
out of a sort of
bunch of tinker toy
or vector sets,
tinker toys or whatever,
a bunch of little units
of given length
and you're piecing them together
to form
a geometry.
If the little pieces
that you're putting together
are correct,
correctly chosen,
you might be able to put
it doesn't mean they're all of equal length,
but you might be able to put it together
into a flat plane.
I mean they're all of the same length,
the fact that you can put them back together
into a flat plane.
But if the pieces
are chosen in some particular way,
in other words,
the lengths of the pieces,
which is equivalent to saying
that the metric tensor here,
this is the metric tensor,
if the metric tensor has a particular property,
it may be that those pieces
can be laid out,
little differential elements can be laid out
and flattened onto a flat plane.
In that case,
the geometry is said to be flat.
We'll define it more carefully later.
But it may also be that the pieces
are chosen in a way that you can't
lay them out onto a flat plane.
They may be,
the pieces might be
the little elements that you would get
by,
you know,
by
sort of triangulating the sphere
in some way.
Then there would be the other thing
that would be no way,
given their length,
given,
you know what their length is,
the length of each one of these,
and you know that they can
be laid out on a sphere
without stretching them,
without breaking them,
then it's true that you cannot
lay them out on a plane.
Such a surface is not flat.
So the question is,
if I gave you the length
of each little stick here,
without building the thing,
how could you tell me
whether it's a flat space,
or whether it's an intrinsically curved space
that cannot be flattened out
and laid out on a flat plane?
Let's say it more precisely.
Given g m n of x,
given g m n of x,
given,
let's give it its name,
it's called the metric tensor,
as a function of position
in some set of coordinates,
keep in mind there are many sets of coordinates,
and in every set
of coordinates,
the metric tensor
may look different,
may have different components.
But I give you one set of coordinates,
and I give you one metric tensor,
I tell you what it is,
in effect,
I've told you the distance
between every pair of neighboring points,
and I ask you,
is this flat,
or is it not flat?
In fact,
what do I even mean
by asking if it's flat?
Measure pi,
calculate pi.
That's one way?
Yeah,
you can do that.
I know it's not flat,
but I know what you mean.
That's good,
that's very good for a two-dimensional surface,
not so great for higher-dimensional surfaces.
Yeah,
that's right,
that's one way of doing it.
Actually,
that's not so easy to do
with these differential little things here,
because they're so small
that the deviation
from pi is going to be higher order.
But,
yeah.
Alright,
so what's the mathematics
of taking a metric tensor and asking
if the space is flat?
Now,
what does it mean for it to be flat?
What it means to be
flat is that you can find
a coordinate transformation,
a different set of coordinates,
in which
the interval,
the distance formula,
is just the x1 squared plus the x2 squared
plus the x3 squared
as it would be in Euclidean geometry.
That's the definition
of a flat space.
The space is flat,
if g m n
is just
a bunch of zeros and ones
as if it were just the Pythagorean theorem,
but if a
coordinate transformation can make it look like that.
So,
in that sense,
it has a
vague similarity,
it turned out not to
be a vague similarity at all,
a very close parallel,
between the question of whether you can
find a coordinate transformation
which removes gravitational fields,
the question is,
can you
find a coordinate transformation
which removes the
curvy character of the metric tensor here?
Alright,
in order to answer that question,
the geometric question here,
we have to do some mathematics.
And the mathematics
is central to relativity,
we cannot
get away without doing it,
you cannot
understand relativity without it,
and the mathematics is tensor analysis.
Tensor analysis and a little bit of
differential geometry.
It,
uh,
it's annoying.
It's annoying because it's got all these
indices floating around,
and different coordinate
systems,
so it's mildly
annoying,
but once you get used
to it,
it's really very simple.
It is really,
really simple,
and it was actually made simpler by Einstein,
by the famous Einstein summation
convention,
which means you didn't have to write
summation symbols all over the place.
Question?
Yeah.
Going back to that,
uh,
distance on the sphere,
the equation
where it's cosine of
whatever it is,
that assumes that that little interval
is flat,
otherwise it's...
Yeah,
it's,
yeah,
that's right,
we
assume that small enough...
Yeah,
that's exactly
right.
In both Riemannian
geometry and Gaussian
theory of surfaces,
it is
always assumed that if you look at a
small enough piece,
that a small
enough piece
looks flat.
The technical
statement is a small piece
located at some point can be
well approximated by the tangent
space.
The tangent space
would be the flat tangent
to the,
uh,
to the surface.
But it's not flat.
They assume it's flat,
but
it's not flat,
so that equation
is...
Is the question...
Yeah,
that's right.
But it's a question of orders
of differentials.
It's a question of orders of differentials.
Now,
the differentials aren't
really lengths,
they're limits of small lengths,
and they're defined in
such a way that the square of a small
thing is zero.
So,
there is a technical
mathematics to small differentials.
Hmm?
So,
is there a constraint that the function has to be
continuous?
Yeah.
Because if you take
two points at the edge of a crevice,
it just,
you know,
geometry matters
a lot.
Depends on what you mean by a crevice.
Yeah,
no,
you're right.
Um,
No,
the metric tensor can always be taken
to be continuous.
It's often derivatives
of the tensor,
which are not
continuous,
but
I don't know what a
crevice means.
A crevice does not
mean a crease.
That's,
of course,
a crease.
Alright.
This space here is as
flat as this space.
In fact,
it's exactly the same space
thought of in terms
of differential geometry.
The distance,
alright,
let's be careful.
Let's say
exactly what we mean.
The distance between any
two points
on here,
between two neighboring
points,
doesn't mean the
distance
um,
between
these points if you go through
the
the page.
It means the
distance in the surface.
The distance in the
surface,
and that distance
between these two points doesn't
depend on whether you fold the page
or not.
It's exactly the same with the page
folded as with the page unfolded.
The right
terminology is we're interested
in the intrinsic geometry
of the page.
The intrinsic
geometry means those aspects
of the geometry which
only depend
on what's going on inside
the surface and not
how the surface is embedded
in three dimensions.
These are different embeddings
of the same surface.
Alright,
all sorts of different embeddings
of the same surface.
But the intrinsic relationships
between the points on the surface
are independent of how we
bend the surface.
So we're talking about
intrinsic geometry.
Geometry
that would be measurable
by a little creature that only gets
to move around on the surface and
doesn't get to look out of the surface.
What if we tried diagonalizing the metric?
What about diagonalizing it?
You can't diagonalize,
in general,
you can't diagonalize it everywhere
simultaneously.
Diagonalize it
you mean find a set of coordinates that
diagonalizes it.
Yeah,
you can't do
that at a point.
At any point
you can diagonalize it,
but you can't diagonalize it everywhere
simultaneously.
That's the point.
So you can't tell by looking at a point
whether a surface is flat.
Uh...
Right.
Looking at a point
it'll always look flat.
One more question.
Could you say,
again,
the
determination of whether a space is flat
is equivalent to determining whether
there's a coordinate transform that takes
an accelerated frame to a...
Forget,
we're dropping now the question
about gravity for the moment.
I started by explaining to you
that there's this mathematics problem
of deciding how to find out
if there's a gravitational field
or if the gravitational field can be removed
by coordinate transformation.
Now we're talking about a problem that
sounds similar,
and in fact is similar.
How do you tell
given a space
whether it is flat?
And the answer is you look for a
coordinate transformation
which turns
GMN
into what?
What's the GMN for
Cartesian coordinates?
Scalar?
And that would mean?
Identity matrix.
Yeah.
Or the Kronecker delta symbol,
yes?
Everybody remember the Kronecker delta?
Delta MN?
This is the formula
for the interval
in Cartesian coordinates for a flat
geometry.
Remember what delta MN is?
Delta MN is just a matrix,
diagonal matrix,
everywhere
is equal to one,
off-diagonal,
everywhere equal to zero.
Okay?
So,
what we would say
is that flat space
in Cartesian coordinates
the metric tensor is just the
Kronecker delta symbol.
In curvilinear coordinates that's not true.
In curvilinear coordinates
this could be more complicated.
So I give you a metric,
I give you a metric tensor
and I ask you,
can it by coordinate transformation
be reduced to this?
If yes,
the space is called flat.
If no,
the space
is called curved.
Of course,
the space could have some portions
which are flat.
And on those portions
it could be that there's
a set of coordinates where
in that region,
the metric
tensor can be chosen to be
the Kronecker delta.
But it's called flat if it's everywhere
is flat.
Everywhere is flat.
Alright,
so that's a mathematics
problem.
Given a GMN
of x,
how do you decide if there's a coordinate
transformation
which will change it into
the Kronecker symbol?
To answer that,
we have to understand
better how things transform
when you make
coordinate transformations.
And that's the subject of tensor analysis.
This analogy between
tidal forces
and curvature
is not an analogy.
It's a very precise
equivalence
that in general theory of relativity
the way that you diagnose
tidal forces
is by calculating the curvature tensor.
The way you define
a flat space
is a space where the curvature tensor
is zero everywhere.
And so it's a very precise
correspondence
that gravity
really is curvature.
But we'll come to it
in a minute.
As we get to it.
Okay,
so
obviously the first question we would like to ask
in
trying to determine
whether we can transform
away
GMN of x and turn it
into the trivial delta
Mn of x.
The first question to ask is
how does
Mn of x transform
when you change coordinates?
So as I said,
for that we have to introduce notions of
tensor analysis
which are rather easy.
Sometimes
they're a bit of a notational nuisance
because of all the indices
and you can get confused by them
but I hope you won't.
Okay.
So let's begin
with a simpler thing than GMN of x.
Let's just start.
Let's suppose there are two sets of coordinates.
There's a set of coordinates
x,
M
and I could call the other coordinates
x prime
but then I'm going to have a horrible notation
where we'll have
x prime M
oh boy,
it looks like x prime M
x prime 1
would be x11
let's keep away from that
let's not do that and let's
call the two sets of coordinates
x and y
it's not x,
y,
z type y
it's just x1,
x2,
x3,
x4
however many
and y1,
y2,
y3,
y4
two sets of coordinates
x and y
and of course
they're related
because if you know the coordinates
of a point
you know the set of coordinates
then in principle you know where the point is
and therefore you know its coordinates
in the other coordinate system
so we might write
that x
the coordinates x,
M
are functions of y
and what I mean by functions of y here
is I mean functions of all
of the components of y
and likewise
y,
M
are assumed to be known
functions of the x's
y,
M of x
means y,
M of x1,
x2,
x3
I just don't want to write all of the
labels in there
we have
two coordinate systems
each one being a function
of the other
and let's ask the question
how these differential
elements here
transform
in other words
given the x,
M
we have a function of x,
that means
given a pair of points
neighboring to each other
and a little
d x,
M
differential distance between them
differential separation between them
what's the corresponding
differential separation
of the y coordinates
this is the differential
separation of the x coordinates
what's the differential separation
of the y coordinates
a little bit of calculus will tell you the answer
d y
m
is equal
to the change in y
m
when you change
any one of the
x coordinates by a little bit
let's call it d x,
P
times d x,
now what does this mean
first of all
this formula is
simple
summed
over P
this just says
that the change in y
some particular
component is the
sum of changes in y
if you change x1 a little bit
times the change in x1
plus change x2 a little bit
times the change in x2 and so forth
so this is a standard calculus formula
the differential change in a quantity
when you change the coordinates
from one set of coordinates to another
now
right here we have
the first example
of the transformation of a tensor
d x and d y
what do they represent
they represent a little vector
an infinitesimal vector
in this sense
and the first thing
is that they represent a little vector
a vector going from one point
to a neighboring point
located at some point in the space
a vector
this
is the transformation
properties of the components
of this vector
this is the
transformation properties of the components
of what is called
a contravariant vector
simply means
a thing which transforms like this
I will now give you the definition
of a general contravariant vector
it's a thing that has components
the m
which
in the primed frame
when I speak about the primed frame
I'm speaking about the y frame
y coordinates
let's go back for a second
what are we talking about here
we have two sets of coordinates
let's just draw one set of coordinates
and we have a little vector
some place
and we are
interested in the components
of that vector
along the axes
prescribed by the coordinates
whatever those coordinates have to be
we're interested in the
in the components of the
little infinitesimal vector
along some of the components
specific axes
the axes which are locally
the axes associated with the coordinates
those are
these dy's and dx's
if I change coordinates
at this point here
there might be some other coordinates
and the components of
exactly that same vector
in the new coordinates
will be different
it's the same vector but different components
why?
just because the axes
are different
okay so this is telling you if I
tell you what the dx's are
for a specific vector over here
this tells you what the
dy's are
this is the transformation property
of the components of a vector
alright
quick question
diagram of those
curve coordinates
each one of those lines does that represent
all of the other coordinates being held
constant or just varying
yes
that's right
those lines represent lines
in a
they represent surfaces
strictly speaking
they represent surfaces strictly speaking
lines are surfaces of constant
coordinates of some kind or another
but on a two dimensional surface they're just lines
yeah so
if you change coordinates
you change the components of a
vector even though you're not changing the
vector the vector is a very definite vector
you're changing its
components because you're changing the coordinates
that you're relating
the vector to
okay a thing which
transforms in this way and I will now
write it in the primed coordinates
vm
is equal
to dym
by dxp
times
vp
this is the pth
component of a vector this is the mth
component of vector in the primed
reference frame
this is the transformation property
summed over p
this is the so called
transformation property of a
contravariant vector
we'll see why it
why we have to call it contra
I don't know why it's called contravariant
as opposed to
something else
but we'll see there are two different
kinds of vector indices
okay so there are many many
things which would transform in this way
for example
if this were just ordinary space of some
sort we were talking about the velocity of a
particle on the surface
let's suppose this was a surface
and we're talking about the components of
velocity along the surface
the components of velocity along
the surface would transform in this way
if you knew the velocity components
in one set of coordinates this would tell
you what the velocity was in the other set of
coordinates
so this is an example of transformation
properties
now the first thing that
Einstein's
great discoveries
was that you can leave out the summation
sign here and people
will figure it out by looking at the equation
and say
oh wait a minute this side
has no p
this side has p's
this equation doesn't make sense
what do I do with it?
well
it really means you sum over p
whenever there's a repeated index like that
that doesn't make sense from the left
side of the equation and it appears on the right
side of the equation it really stands for
summation over that index
quick question
here you're
assuming coordinates
that transform according to the
rules but could there be other
coordinates that don't transform that way?
I haven't
assumed anything I've just assumed there are two sets of
coordinates which are functionally related to each
other that's all
and you're assuming
some things you're assuming
a degree of continuity
you're assuming that the
functions are smooth enough that they can be
differentiated but aside from that
we're not making any
any deep assumptions
about the nature of these coordinates
alright so this is the transformation property
let's write it down over here
put it up in the corner
contravariant
transformations
oh
contravariant vectors
are defined
they're defined by their transformation
properties and here it is
the prime
m let's write
is equal
to the ym
by the xp
vp
this is v in the unprimed
coordinates this is in the primed coordinates
y
is really the primed coordinate
and x is the unprimed
coordinate as I said I've called it
y instead of x prime just to avoid
a miserable notation
with primes next to
indices okay
this is contravariant vector
good
now let's talk about
covariant vectors
another creature
completely different
this is a
gradient
the gradient if you have a function
let's suppose we have a function
let's think of it as a scalar function
a function that doesn't
have to be transformed it just has some
meaningful value at every point of space
let's call it s
then
the gradient is also a
kind of vector
what is the gradient the gradient is the
set of things the set of components
derivative with
respect to xm
of
s
where s is some scalar function
everybody know what a scalar is
a scalar is
a thing which doesn't transform it just has a
value at every point it has a well defined
value at every point it could be something
like the temperature it could be something like
um
the higgs field whatever it is
something which
uh
doesn't have components because it's just
a number at every point
the gradient of a scalar
is also a vector it's the gradient
vector but
it doesn't transform
the same way
as the
dx's it doesn't transform
as a contravariant vector it's easy to
figure out how it does transform
let's ask
given supposing we know this
can we compute
what the s
by dy
let's call this p here
let's call this p just for fun
can we compute what the
derivative of s
with respect to the y's is
again it's an elementary
calculus problem the elementary
calculus problem is
that the change in s when you change
ym a little bit
keeping the other ones fixed keeping all the other
components fixed is just
derivative of s with respect to x
and
times the derivative of xp
with respect to ym
what is this
what is this rule called
some version of the chain rule
that if you want to know how something
changes when you change y a little bit
then you first change x1 a little bit
and see how much x1 changes
when you change y
check change x2 a little bit
see how much x2 changes when you change
y
and see how much x2 changes
do the same thing with x3
and again this means sum over p
i'm not going to write the sum over p anymore
if there's a repeated index on this side
which just doesn't show up on this side
it must mean that it's summed over
so that's einstein's summation convention
it
made life a lot easier
for printers
and for other publishers
who didn't have to
put in
summation sum
all over the place
alright so let's see
how does this compare with this
this is now some primed variable
this is now in the primed
coordinate system
let's call the gradient here
let's call it w
this is w sub m
on the left
sorry,
w sub m on the left hand side
notice i'm putting the index
downstairs here
this index was upstairs
here i'm putting this one downstairs
this makes nice sense in a minute
this index is downstairs
why is it downstairs?
well,
it's downstairs
ym is equal
to
now
dxp
by the
ym
this is the primed y
this is the primed gradient
derivative with respect to y
that's equal to
dxp by the ym
now what is this thing over here?
this is w
sub p
it's the unprimed
gradient
it's the unprimed gradient
because it's differentiated with respect to the unprimed
variable
that's wp over here
here we have dxp by the ym
and here we have the
primed
gradient
this is different
it's different
if it is similar
the primed contravariant vector
has components
proportional to the unprimed
but with dy by dx
here we have dx by dy
okay
dy by dx
dx by dy
a thing which transforms this way
transforms means
that if you can calculate it in one frame
here's how you calculate it in the other frame
so
a thing which transforms this way
is called a covariant vector
so let's put that in here
objects which transform this way
now I can tell you right now
that if you're uncomfortable with this
and it doesn't ring a bell
and it doesn't
um
it doesn't feel
good to you
this is what you need to understand
it really is completely central
to the entire
subject of general relativity
where the indexes go
where the indices go
and how they transform
that's what relativity is all about
it's all about the transformation
properties of different kinds of objects
a vector is a special case of a tensor
tensor is a function of a vector
and the vectors are things which are defined
by the way that they transform
the way that they transform
means the way that they change
when you go from one set of coordinates
to another
it is,
so that is what you have to
get down if you want to understand general relativity
there's transformation properties
of
vectors and other objects
so here are the two
covariant and contravariant
so
I'll go back to the first point
excuse me
is that
partial
of x,
d,
partial of y
m
is that a lowercase m
yeah,
lowercase m
yeah
alright
and they just label the different coordinates
and notice there's no way in here
which I've told you whether this is
two dimensional space,
three dimensional space
four dimensional space,
could be anything
the dimensionality of the space
of course is the number of different components
p could run from one to four
it could run from one to three
it could run from one to two
but the formulas are exactly the same
in every dimensionality
the formulas for transformation properties
ok,
so this is
the notion of
covariant and contravariant
vector indices,
vectors
let's
talk about tensors now
or more complicated
kinds of objects
this is obviously complicated enough
but we have to go
yeah
what's the connection with the contravariant
and covariant vectors
nothing yet
nothing yet,
they're two different
kinds of objects
now later on
we will find ways
of taking any covariant objects
or any contravariant object
and constructing from it
a covariant object
and a kind of one to one correspondence
ok,
that's later
but for the moment
they're just different kinds of objects
basically the gradient operation
and the
this is characteristic of velocities
this is characteristic of
gradients or rates of change of things
so for the moment
they're different things
question?
the last time
you basically,
if I remember correctly
said when we lowered
the index
we changed the sign at the time
did we forget?
at the moment we're just dealing with Euclidean
we're not dealing with relativity
just coordinates in
ordinary space
we'll come to that
sign change when we
when we
when we come to it
yeah
when you say we're talking
about two different kinds of objects
that means we should not be thinking
in our heads,
oh these are the covariant components
or the contravariant components
well,
if you know what the connection is
yes you can,
but at the moment,
no
right
we'll find a way to relate every covariant
to a contravariant and then you can think
of basically a vector
as having either covariant
or contravariant representation
but we'll come to that
ok,
alright next step
let's talk about
tensors with more than one index
now
the pattern for tensors with more than one index
is just to imagine
products
let's suppose
there are two
contravariant vectors,
let's start with
two different contravariant vectors
let's call them V
and I suppose
I've already called it,
let's call it U
two different ones
and let's put them next to each other
and take the M component
of V
and the N component of U
and let's just call this
T M N
I think just for the sake of argument
let's suppose we're talking about three dimensional
space
so that M and N run over from
one to three
how many components does V M have
three
right,
how many components does U N have
three
how many components does T M N have
nine
right,
notice it matters
whether you put it M N
or N M
they're different things
V M N is not
the same as V N M
if you know what I mean
so where you put the index here
matters,
but there's a thing
called T M N
T M N is a special case
of a tensor
of rank two
rank two means that it has two indices
like that,
and in this case
there would be nine components
in four dimensions there would be sixteen components
in two dimensions there would be four components
and so forth
how does this thing transform
for example
V M and U N
could be the components
of these vectors
in the unprimed frame of reference
I think I want to
it's called T M N
so this is T in the unprimed frame of reference
and it's composed
out of the components
of the individual vectors
also in the unprimed frame of reference
well since I know how the individual
components transform
I can tell you how T transforms
so let's see if we can figure out
what T prime
M N is
well first of all
what does this mean
what is V prime
V prime is over here
and it's equal to
d Y M
by d X P
times V P
that's V M
or the primed version
V prime M
now what about
U prime
U prime,
same kind of formula
partial of
Y
N
with respect to let's call it
X Q
U Q
just look at the two pieces separately
d Y M by d X P
times V P
that's
V prime M
d Y M
by d X Q
times U Q
that is U
prime N
so I've just done this operation
same operation
but I've done them on the separate components
but now I can
just take this apart
put this V P over here
and what is this object
what is V P U Q
it's just T P Q
in the unprimed frame
so I found out how T transforms
not surprising
because it was just a combination of two
two vectors
and basically each index here
transforms
with a d Y by d X
type thing here
anything
which transforms like this
is called a covariant tensor of rank 2
for each index
there's an operation
for the M index
there's an operation d Y M by d X P
for the N index
there's a d Y N by d X Q
and then you multiply it by
T P Q
this is covariant
this is a tensor
with two contravariant indices
okay
alright
so I've got
two energies up here
M N R
P Q
what comes after Q
I've already used R
M N
M N L
L M N
what comes before P
no that's not good
P Q R
and what am I missing
I'm missing
d Y L
by d X R
this would be the transformation property of a rank 3
contravariant tensor
what kind of things
are there
which are these kinds of tensors
many many things
but in particular just products of vectors
products of components of vectors
we're going to see that this metric thing here
is a tensor
of covariant indices
so let's ask how things with covariant indices transform
here is the way
a single covariant index transforms
let's go back
and take the product of two of them
again
two different covariant tensors
Y
W prime M
times W prime
M
N
with covariant
covariant means that they're down
downstairs here
how does this object transform
well we know how the individual
not W
give me another letter
Z
not coordinate Z
but component Z
alright here's the rule
W prime M is equal
to this
the Xp by Dym
times
Wp
Z prime N
same game
Dxq
by Dyn
times Zq
alright so here I've discovered now a new
transform
property of a thing with two covariant indices
two downstairs indices
let's call it T M N
it's a different object
just using T for tensor
tensor with two lower indices
it transforms
this way
so this is
transformation property
of a thing with two covariant indices
I'll leave it to you to try to guess
what transformation might be
if there's one upper and one lower
we're not going to use it tonight
but
let's oh we're about finished
well I think I'll just do
one more simple thing here
before we finish
the question is how the metric
tensor transforms
and this is easy
supposing we want
the same interval
except expressed in terms of the Y coordinates
all we have to do
is write
that G
well
Ds squared
is equal to G M N
of X
I'm simply rewriting what I have here
but then what is Dx M in terms of Y's
it's partial of X M
and
with respect to Y
P let's say
times Dy P
you know
I'm getting really tired
I think we're going to do this next time
we're going to do this next time
the point however is
when we work out the transformation properties of G
we'll find out that it's tensor
it's a tensor with two covariant indices
and
then comes a question
given that
this is the transformation property of G
can we or can we not
find a coordinate transformation
which will
turn G M N
into delta M N
that's the mathematics question
it's a very hard mathematics question
in general
but
we'll
we'll find the condition
and you can find it at us at
stanford.edu