Stanford University.
Okay,
shall we begin?
Any questions before I begin?
Quick ones.
As I was saying,
a good notation will carry you a long way.
When a notation is good,
it just sort of automatically
tells you what to do next.
It means you can do
physics in a completely mindless way.
Just you know,
it's like having tinker toys.
It's pretty clear which end
the stick has to go into.
It has to go into the thing with the hole.
You can't try putting a hole into it.
You can't try putting a stick into a
hole or forcing a stick into a stick.
There's only one thing you can do.
You can put the stick into the hole,
and then the other end of
the stick can go in another
hole that gives you some more
holes that you can put sticks into.
And the notation of general relativity is much like that.
If you follow the rules,
you almost can't make mistakes.
Okay.
But you have to learn the rules.
The rules are the rules of tensor analysis,
or tensor algebra,
tensor analysis.
And the question which we're aiming at
now is to understand enough about tensor analysis,
metrics,
to be able to distinguish a fluid.
And to see that the fluid is really flat.
So we'll take the first example,
let's say it's a flat geometry.
Let's look at the geometry.
This is a flat geometry from a non-flat geometry.
Now,
that seems awfully simple.
Flat means like the plane.
Non-flat means with bumps and lumps in it.
And you would think we
could tell the difference very easily.
Sometimes it's not so easy.
For example,
as I mentioned last time,
if I take this page.
that page is flat.
If I roll the page like this,
it looks curved,
but it's not
curved.
It's exactly the same page.
The relationship between the parts of the
page,
the distances between the letters
on my page and so forth,
they don't
change,
at least not the distances
between the letters measured along the
page.
They don't change when I
do various things with the page.
So a folded page or
a,
I don't want to call it curved
because curved would be the wrong thing,
but a,
what's the right word for,
what's that?
Deformed?
Well,
it's not really,
no,
I don't want to use the word
deformed either.
Just a curl.
Let's call it curls,
where you don't stretch it and
you don't deform it.
That is not introducing curvature into a space.
Now,
technically it introduces
what's called extrinsic curvature.
Extrinsic curvature has to do with the
way a space,
in this case the page,
is embedded in a higher dimensional space,
three-dimensional space of this room.
Here's the page.
When the page is laid
out flat like that,
it's embedded in the embedding space in one way.
When it's
curled like this,
it's embedded in the same space in another way.
And one says that there is extrinsic
curvature.
The extrinsic has to do with the
fact that it's in an external space,
and it
has to do with how the space,
how this page is embedded in space.
But it has nothing to
do with the intrinsic geometry.
If you like,
you can think of the intrinsic geometry as
the geometry of a tiny little
bug that moves along the surface.
Cannot look out of the surface.
Only looks along the surface,
crawls along the surface.
He may have surveying instruments by
which he can measure distances along the
surface.
Can draw triangles.
Measure the angles of the triangles within the
surface,
and do all kinds of interesting geometric studies,
but never looks out
of the surface,
and therefore never detects or notices
the fact that it might be
embedded in the higher dimensional space in different ways
just learns about the intrinsic geometry
the intrinsic geometry meaning the geometry
that is independent of the way the surface is embedded
general relativity is about
and Riemannian geometry,
a lot of geometry,
is all about the intrinsic properties of the geometry
it doesn't have to be two-dimensional,
it can be any number of dimensions
and the basic thing which defines the
geometry and distinguishes it from other geometries
is to imagine sprinkling a bunch of points
I don't want to ruin my page here,
let's do it on the back of the page
sprinkle a bunch of points,
draw lines between them,
sort of triangulate the space
and then state what the distance
between every pair of neighboring points is
specify the distance between the two points
specifying those distances specifies the geometry
sometimes that geometry can be flattened out on the page
without changing the lengths of any of these little links
let me give you an example
if I draw a bunch of triangles
which are representing lengths
oops,
I'm not doing it very well
a triangular lattice
that's a triangular lattice,
it's built up out of triangles
and if every triangle is an equilateral triangle
this,
this are all equal
then in fact,
imagine that at the nodes here
we can,
you know,
what's the right word?
they're like hinges,
they're hinged
the hinging would allow us
to sort of fold this thing
but as long as we keep these lengths the same
and don't change them,
make them all equilateral triangles
this can always be laid
out on the desk as flat
on the other hand,
if we were to,
let's say
take several of these lengths,
all the ones coming into some point over here
this one,
this one and this one
six of them
and we were to double the size of them
then this point would have no choice
but to come up out of the blackboard
or into the blackboard
there would be a bulge at that point
and you can't push that bulge back
into the blackboard and flatten it out
without changing the lengths of the links
a curved space is basically one which cannot be folded
or flattened out
without distorting it
in fact,
and it's intrinsic property of the space,
not extrinsic
okay,
so our goal
which,
as I said last time,
matches closely the question
of whether there is a real gravitational field present
or whether the parent gravitational field
is just due to an artifact of funny coordinates
funny space-time coordinates
the question of whether a space is really flat
or whether
or whether it's really flat or really curved
or whether it's just we've presented that space
with curved coordinates
those two mathematical problems
is there really a gravitational field there
or is it just an artifact of curved space-time coordinates
or is the space of the
top of this table top really flat
even though it may look curved
because I introduced,
I won't draw on the table
but curved coordinates of various kinds
so the question is how do you
tell really if a space is flat
what are you given?
typically you're given the metric tensor
but before we go into that question
and it's a hard question
it's going to take us,
it probably won't get completely to the point of
of answering the question tonight
I have a question?
yeah
and I don't mean this facetiously
I really mean this sincerely
what is flat?
how do we define it?
that you care,
we're going to define it
we have not defined it yet in any mathematical sense
I tried to give you an intuition
it means you can flatten out on the table
but of course that's not good enough
I will tell you exactly what it means
I told you last time but I'll tell you again
alright what it means is the metric tensor
can be chosen to be just the Kronecker delta symbol
but we'll come to it
alright before we come to it
we need to understand a little bit about tensors
we've talked about them a little bit
but I want to formalize it tonight a little bit
tensors,
scalars and vectors
scalars and vectors are special cases of tensors
and tensors are the general category of objects
they have indices
and they transform
the most important thing is
that they transform when you go
from one coordinate system to another
in particular we're going to be interested in spaces
with quantities fields on them
so that every point in space
there may be some quantities associated with it
with that point
and those quantities will be tensors
there will be tensors
there are other kinds of quantities
also that will not be tensors
but in particular we'll be interested in tensors fields
a field is a thing which
can vary from point to point
and the simplest kind of tensor is a scalar
a scalar,
S of X
is a quantity at each point of space
where everybody in all coordinates agrees about its value
so the transformation properties
and going let's say from the Y from
the X coordinate to the Y X coordinates
XM to YM
in changing coordinates
the value of a scalar field
at a actual point of space
so space time but we will get to space time
the value of that scalar field does not change
so we can write that as
S prime of Y equals S of X
the prime here simply denotes the fact
that I'm talking about a quantity
in the coordinate system Y
without a prime it will
refer to the coordinate system X
there are two coordinate systems
here's the X coordinate system
these are the lines of constant X
so the surfaces of constant X
and then there's an every point
is labeled by a collection of X's
how many X's and Y's
well that depends on the dimension of the space
if the space is one dimensional
then one X just one coordinate
will label where you are in that coordinate
if it's two dimensional two coordinates
X1 and X2
or Y1 and Y2
if it's three dimensional three coordinates
X1,
X2,
and X3
or Y1,
Y2,
and Y3
and whatever the X coordinates are
the Y coordinates are different
but we assume there's a correspondence
that if you know the value of the X's
for a particular point
then the Y's
so let's write that Ym
where M runs from one to however many
is a known function
assumed to be a known function
of the X's
this stands for now
the whole set of X's
X1,
X2,
X3,
X4,
however many
and that we can invert the relationship
so that if we know the value of Y
of a point
we can also know what its X is
so that's a coordinate transformation of some kind
and that coordinate transformation can be
you know,
pretty complicated
we'll assume it's continuous
we'll assume we can differentiate
when we need to differentiate
but
nothing more special than that
okay,
so scalars transform trusses
trivially
if you know the value of S at a point
you know it no matter what coordinate system you use
next,
there are vectors
vectors,
and there are two kinds of vectors
we spoke about them last time
I'm going to tell you
now a little about the geometry
what it means
there are
contravariant vectors which have an index upstairs
and there are covariant vectors
I shouldn't really use the same symbol
because they're not the same thing at the moment
but let's just use the same symbol
V,
V for vector
with an index downstairs
the rules,
we'll write down rules for transformation in a moment
but let me first tell you a little
bit about the difference between covariant and contravariant
intuitively,
what it means
so let's suppose for a moment we're
located right at this point over here
we have some coordinates
these could be the X coordinates
and I'm going to draw them as straight lines
for the moment
because at the moment I'm not interested in the fact that
the coordinates curve and vary the directions from place to place
I'm mostly interested in the fact that
the coordinate axes may not be perpendicular
they may not be perpendicular
and what the implication of
non-perpendicularity is for these coordinates
furthermore
the distance,
let's call this,
we can call this X1
we can call this X2
they're not perpendicular relative to each other
they could be perpendicular relative to each other
but not necessarily
and the actual physical distance,
let's say measured in meters
from X equals,
here's X1 equals 0
here's X1 equals 1
here's X1 X2 equals 1
X1 equals 2
here's X1 equals 3
and so forth
here's X2 equals 1
the actual physical distance,
let's say measured in meters
or centimeters or whatever units are
between X equals 0 and X equals 1
is not necessarily one unit
they're neither perpendicular to each other
nor do these labels represent
actual physical distance along the axes
they're just names of points
here's the point X equals 0
and so forth and so on
okay,
now let's introduce some vectors
two vectors
not necessarily two
here I've drawn a two-dimensional space
there could be more axes
for each axis I will introduce a vector
which is basically a vector extending
one unit of coordinate space
along the particular axis
I'm going to give this vector a name
it extends from this point to this point
X equals 0 to X equals 1
and I'm going to call it E1
the 1 here stands for this 1
X1 and not X2 and not X3
in other words it's along the X1 axis
and there's another vector along the X2 axis
which I'll call E1
and this is E2
and these are vectors
these are vectors
and think of them as physical little arrows
and of course if there's a third coordinate
you point out of the blackboard
there's an E for that
and so forth and so on
in fact we can label these E sub I
E sub I,
they're little vectors
and as I goes from 1 to 3
or 1 to 4 or whatever it is
these go over the various directions
alright
now
next issue,
take an arbitrary vector
take an arbitrary vector,
let's call it V
an arbitrary vector
for example,
one over here
V
can be expanded
as a sum of coefficients times E1
plus other coefficients times E2
plus more coefficients times E3
in other words,
they can be expanded
as a sum of terms
the first one having E1
and the coefficient of E1
we'll call V1
plus V2
E2
plus V3
E3
now,
the things which are vectors in this formula
are the E's
the V's are actually numbers
but they are components
of the vector
they're components of V
and they tell you how much of
each kind of one of these vectors
are present in the sum
V1 E1 plus V2 E2
plus V3 E3 and so forth
these coefficients
these coefficients are called
the contravariant
and they're the components
of the vector V
it's just a name
now,
there's nothing in what I did
that required me to put the one here downstairs
and not upstairs in this one downstairs
it's a convention
to write it in this form here
alright,
so first of all
you see what the contravariant components are
they're the expansion coefficients
the numbers that you have to
put in front of these three vectors
to expand a given vector
next thing
let's define
the projection
of a given vector
onto
the x-axis and the y-axis
how do we do that?
its definition
is the dot product of the vector V
with the vectors E1 or E2
alright
let's think about the next thing
would be the dot product
of the vectors
of the vector V
with just the ordinary dot product
with let's say E1
let's start with E1
now,
if we were just using conventional Cartesian coordinates
perpendicular to each other
and if these really were unit vectors
if the distance representing each coordinate separation here
was one unit of whatever the units we're dealing with
then
these coefficients here
would be the same as these dot products
the dot products and the coefficients would be the same
however
when we have a peculiar coordinate system with angles
and with non-unit separations between
the successive coordinate lines here
this is not true
so let's see if we can
work out what V dot E1
incidentally
V dot E1
is called
V sub 1
with a covariant index
alright
notice how things fit together
we can also write this here as
V M E M
summation convention
Einstein's summation convention
this means V1 E1 plus V2 E2 plus V3 E3
notice I've concocted things
so that an upper index
always goes with a lower index
we're going to come back to that
it's called contraction of indices
but just notice that I've
done it in such a way
that the summation always involves an
upper index with a lower index
and by definition
this is the contravariant components of the vector V
the covariant components
are the dot products of the vector
with the
call these the basis vectors
we might as well call them by their name
these are called the basis vectors
and
the covariant components are the dot products of these
so let's see what we get
let's see if we can figure it out
let's plug in for V
its expansion here
and then take its dot product
with E
so what is this equal to?
this is equal to
V M E M
from here
and now we're going to dot it
into E1
but why fix E1?
let's just go over it
let's go for it right now
general
the general case
the dot product of V
with the nth basis vector
and this will be E sub n
E M dot E n
is something new
it's something new
let's isolate it
it has two lower indices
and it's the metric tensor
it is the metric tensor
let's
let's go a little bit further to see
what its connection with the metric tensor is
the length of a vector is the
dot product of the vector with itself
let's calculate the length of V
and we'll see various ways we can write it
it's V dot V
now
V dot V
let's calculate V dot V
from here
we can write that the first V
is V M E M
alright that's the first V
but then let's take its
dot product of the second V
the second V
is V n E n
I have to use a different index
for this summation than for this summation
I mustn't mix up the summation indices
this is V M E M
this means V 1 E 1 plus V
2 E 2 plus V 3 E 3
times V 1 E 1
plus V 2 and so forth
but now I can write this in the form
V M V n
times the quantity
E M dot E n
let's call this quantity E M dot E n
let's call it G M n
and now we have a formula
V M V n
G M n
this is the character of the metric tensor
the metric tensor tells you how
to compute the length of a vector
the vector could be just D x
D x m and D x n
and then we would just be computing the
length of a little interval between two neighboring points
G M n
and then we would just be computing the
length of a little interval between two neighboring points
okay so I just put
this all on the blackboard here
to give you a little picture of
the difference between covariant and contravariant indices
contravariant indices are the things that you use
to construct a vector out of the basis vectors
covariant indices are the dot
products with the basis vectors
they're different geometric things
but they would be the same
if we were talking about ordinary Cartesian coordinates
okay so that's
I just inserted that discussion in order
to give you some kind of geometric idea
of what covariant and contravariant means
and also what the metric tensor is
the metric tensor is constructed out of
these basis vectors by taking their dot products
but we'll come back to these things
yeah,
alright
this was just for you,
you know
you asked me to do it
I assume this is what you asked me to do
it is totally what I asked you to do
okay
the
so in orthogonal coordinates
the two sets of components
turn out to be the same
orthogonal and unit are separations between them
the two sets of coordinates are the same,
yeah
and that's also true in curvilinear coordinates
where the unit vectors are always orthogonal?
no
in curvilinear coordinates
typically in general
the coordinate directions are not orthogonal to each other
the coordinate directions,
you know
the direction along which one of the
coordinates increases keeping the other ones fixed
that's what we're talking about
those are typically not orthogonal to each other
but for some curvilinear coordinates they are
oh yeah
and so in that case the
components would also be the same
is that true?
not quite
not quite because there's also the question
of the length between neighboring coordinate lines
Cartesian coordinates not only mean that they're orthogonal
but also means that the separations are the same
here,
here
this is the same as this and this
so let me give you an example
where the coordinate axes are orthogonal to each other
but where the separations are not the same
polar coordinates
ordinary polar coordinates
the lines along which the radial coordinate increases
are just the radial lines
and the lines associated with the angular coordinates
are just circles
and clearly at every point
a circle is perpendicular to the
line passing through the same point
so these coordinates are
I didn't draw them very well
but these coordinates are orthogonal to each other
okay
but the separation distance between
let's call this theta equals 0 over here
and let's call this theta equals
theta 1 over here
the separation between these two points is not the same
as the separation between these two points
is not the same as
the separation between these two points
so these are not Cartesian coordinates
coordinates and according to the rough
definition I gave of these E's,
the E's
along the theta direction would be
increasing their length as you went up
here.
So it's more than just perpendicularity.
Perpendicularity and
equality of the distance unit along,
as you go,
a fixed separation in X.
There's
more than that in defining Cartesian coordinates.
Okay,
so now let's come to
tensor analysis.
Yes?
You used two different phrases.
One is you talked about covariant and contrarian vectors,
or tensors.
You talked about covariant and contrarian components.
Oh.
Yeah.
Before the metric tensor is introduced,
when we just have abstract
coordinates and vectors,
there are covariant vectors and contrarian vectors.
And they're different things.
dx would be a contrarian
vector and d phi by dx,
where phi would be some scalar,
that would be a covariant vector.
Different
kinds of things.
As we'll see,
once the metric tensor is introduced,
and I've introduced it here
by introducing these unit vectors here,
or these vectors here.
Once the metric tensor is introduced,
it's possible to make a correspondence
between the covariant vectors and the contrarian.
Such a way as to say every vector can
be either represented as covariant or by all contrarian.
But we'll come to that.
We'll come to it.
At the moment,
I should be only talking about covariant and contrarian.
Now,ретurning to foenman's fishery case.υχ
Okay,
now,
tensors are objects which are characterized,
the thing which characterizes a
tensor and makes it a tensor,
is the way that
it transforms under coordinate transformations.
We talked about this a little bit,
and let's go back,
I want to do it again.
V is some vector,
it has contravariant components,
and it has contravariant components in the
y coordinates and in the x coordinates.
If I change coordinates on here,
keeping the vector fixed,
not going to change the vector,
but change the coordinates,
I will change its components,
clearly.
So,
how do the covariants work?
Contravariant components change when I change coordinates.
Here's the rule.
This is the mth component of v prime,
where v prime means the components
of v in the y coordinates.
Prime means y.
Unprimed means x.
Alright.
V in the prime is x.
So,
the unprimed coordinates,
I'm basically reviewing what we said last time,
is given in terms of the
unprimed coordinates by dym by dxn,
vn.
This is the object in the unprimed coordinates,
in other words,
the x coordinates,
and it's gotten by multiplying
by dy by dx times v.
An example is d prime,
just dy,
dym.
That would be the primed version of a little
interval is obviously equal to dym by dxn times dxn.
So,
this is sort of the archetype of a contravariant.
this is the unprimed vector component,
and you can see that it
in fact transforms in exactly this way.
The covariant components,
a covariant component of a vector would be,
for example,
if you have a scalar,
s,
and you differentiate it with respect to y or x,
let's say y,
m.
This becomes the primed component of a vector.
So,
I would have the primed
covariant component of a covariant vector,
or the primed covariant component of the gradient vector.
This is the gradient of s,
and I've differentiated with respect to y,
not x.
So,
this is a primed component,
and this is equal to ds,
well,
let's write it this way,
ds by dxn,
dxn.
And this is equal to dxn by dy,
m.
Notice the difference.
Notice how the notation carries you along.
On the left-hand side,
I have a y with a superindex,
upstairs index m.
On the right-hand side,
I also have a y with a superindex m.
But on the right-hand side,
I'm going to have a dxn.
Of course,
A dxn upstairs has to
be balanced by a dxn downstairs.
And you'll get familiar with this.
You're allowed to contract indices,
one upstairs and one downstairs.
And you can see the pattern.
You can see the symmetry of this relationship here.
Likewise here.
Here we have a lower index corresponding to y,
the index m.
On the right-hand side,
I have something below the fraction bar.
Also,
dym.
And then above the fraction bar,
I have dxn.
But that's compensated for by another dxn downstairs here.
And again,
the ds.
So the notation pretty much carries you along.
This is the standard form for
the transformation property of contravariant components.
This is the standard form
for transformation properties of covariant.
And here's an example of contravariant.
From these two examples,
it looks like if we were
to just consider dimensionally what the y,
the covariant or the contravariant represent,
it would seem like the contravariant vector
is one where the units are of distance,
while the covariant are one over distance.
Is this true in general?
Not in general,
but I take your point.
And I think,
no,
it's not true in general.
V could,
for example,
be a velocity,
in which case it would
be a length per unit time.
Or it could be a force,
components of a force,
in which case it wouldn't be those kind of...
But units have to match.
So in here we have,
for example,
this could be a force on the right,
a force on the left,
and a y and a dy by dx,
which is dimensionless.
So this is the equation.
Perhaps they're both measured,
let's say,
in meters.
Should those all be partial differentials?
Should they all be what?
Partial differentials.
They're all partial differentials.
Why are they partial?
They're partial because there are several coordinates here.
There's x1,
x2,
x3,
and x4,
and this is the derivative of one of the y's
with respect to the x's keeping all the other x's fixed.
Correct?
All right.
So these are the transformation
properties of a covariant object,
and the corresponding thing for contravariant
would be the analog of this,
w prime m.
Oh,
sorry,
yeah,
w prime m.
I'm just using w and v to,
just to give different letters for things.
This is equal to dxn by dym vn,
sub-w,
wn.
Same pattern as over here.
Again.
The x by the y,
and so forth.
All right.
Yeah.
When you look at this,
you look at this and you say,
ooh,
there's a lower index here of type y.
Why?
Because prime means y.
All right.
So prime is associated with y.
There's a lower index here,
m,
which is of the y type,
and so there's got to be a lower
index below the fraction bar of the y.
So you have a lower index,
a lower index of the professor частrakye's 1918
and then you have a major vector here
which has two выс on the right of
And quite simple,
right?
So let's take an object
W
not this W now,
let's see,
yeah let's take
a tensor W,
maybe I should call it T,
let's call it W
W prime
in other words in the y-coordinates
it has two indices m and n
and I'm going to take one of
those indices to be an upstairs index and
another to be a downstairs index
contravariant and covariant
a tensor like this
could just be the product of
two vectors,
one with a contravariant index,
one with a covariant index
I won't bother writing everything
out but what makes this thing a tensor
is its transformation properties so let
me show you what the transformation
properties are
in the prime components again for each
index for each index
there's the same kind of
pattern this is a prime component
this is the index m
so there must be a dy
m upstairs
alright there's going to be a d x p downstairs
now what about this index here this
is a y index because it's primed
downstairs so there must be a dy downstairs
and therefore there's got to be a
d x and let's call it q upstairs
now when we multiply that we multiply that
by double the y and the y prime
and so on and so forth
the tensor in the unprimed frame
there's a p downstairs there's got
to be a p upstairs here
there's a q upstairs there's
got to be a q downstairs
so this tells me how a tensor of rank 2
with one contravariant and one covariant index transforms
for each index there's a dy by dx or dx
by dy and you simply track where the indexes go
so we're going to use your vector
here to find out where the indices go
M upstairs,
N downstairs,
N downstairs
We're going to have a W here,
unprimed W
It's going to have some components,
let's call them P and Q
and the P's and Q's have to balance
Alright,
this is very general
If I take a tensor with any number of indices,
oh incidentally,
let me do one other example
Supposing we have a tensor with two contravariant indices
Oh,
let's make it two covariant indices,
MN
Just as another example,
a tensor with two covariant indices
How does it transform?
Again,
there are downstairs Y's,
YM,
another downstairs YN
Again,
M and N go with Y
What do I put upstairs?
Well,
the only thing I put upstairs is X
Call this one P,
call this one Q,
and now this is WPQ
Alright,
so this is the transformation property
of a thing with two indices
purely covariant now
And the general pattern is the same
For every index,
you do the same thing,
either a dy by dx or a dx by dy
And you sum over repeated index,
indices
M and M are not repeated indices
They're on this side,
and they also appear on this side
But P and P are repeated,
and Q and Q are repeated
So this is a double sum
This is a double sum over P and Q,
because P and Q are repeated
Alright,
this is the basic notational device
Who invented it?
Einstein was the one who dropped the summation symbol to,
because he realized he didn't need it
I don't know,
Riemann,
Gauss was in there
I don't know who invented all of this notation
But it's very systematic
Alright,
so a tensor is an object
which is characterized by its transformation properties
Now,
notice something about tensors
If they are zero in one frame
Let's start with a scalar
If a scalar is zero in one frame,
it's zero in every frame
They're equal
Now,
supposing a vector is zero in some frame
Let's say the x frame
For a vector to be zero
It doesn't mean some component is equal to zero
It means all of its components are equal to zero
A vector is only zero if
all of its components are zero
If all of the components of
the contravariant vector vn are zero
Then obviously the transformation property is such that
all the components of the prime vector are zero
Likewise with any tensor
Where's the...
With any tensor,
if all of its components are zero in one frame
In one coordinate system
Then all of its coordinates,
its components are zero in every frame
That means that once you've written
down an equation in tensor form
You can always,
of course,
transfer everything to the left side of
the equation and set it equal to zero
If an equation of that
type is true in some frame,
it's true in every frame
And that's the basic value of tensors
They allow you to express equations of various kinds
Equations of motion,
equations of whatever it happens to be
In a form where the same exact
equation will be true in any coordinate system
And that's,
of course,
the same thing
And that's a deep advantage to thinking about tensors
There are other objects which are not...
We're going to come across some
of them which are not tensors
Which have the property that they may be zero
in some frames and not zero in other frames
All right,
frame means coordinate system now
So tensors have a certain invariance to them
Their components are not invariant
Their components change from one frame to another
But the statement that one...
that a tensor is equal to another tensor...
Wpq is equal to,
let's say,
tpq
Oh,
incidentally,
when you write a tensor equation
The components have to balance
It doesn't make sense to write
an equation like Wpq equals tpq
Oh,
you can write it
You can write it all you want
But...
Since this left side transforms
differently than the right side
Then even if this were true in one coordinate system
It would not be true in another coordinate system
The transformation properties of the two sides are different
All right,
so normally we wouldn't write equations like this
We might say in some particular coordinate system
Coordinate system of the blah blah blah kind
This might be true
But then if you change coordinates,
it won't be true
The kinds of equations which are true in every frame
Are ones in which the indices balance
They transform the same way
So it's true in one co...
yeah
What is it that's invariant?
The truth of the equation
If this is true in one equation,
in one coordinate system
Then it will be true in every coordinate system
Except for a vector,
at least the contrarian
Its magnitude will be the same
Oh,
its magnitude will be the same,
but if it's...
But it's...
The individual components in different coordinate systems
Look,
we can always write this as w minus t
w minus t equals zero,
right?
If every component of this
w minus t object is zero
Then it's true in every reference frame
So is there anything that analogies
to the magnitude of the vector?
No,
it's not the magnitude of the vector
It is the vector itself
It's one thing...
it's true that if the
magnitude of a vector is zero
In ordinary geometry,
the vector itself is zero
That will not be true in relativity
Does not follow from the
magnitude of a vector being zero
That the vector is equal to zero
The magnitude of a vector
and the vector itself are two
Two different quantities
The magnitude of a vector is a scalar
The vector itself is a complex
thing that points in a direction
To say that two vectors are equal
means that the directions are the same
And their magnitudes are the same
And a tensor of higher
rank is a more complicated object
Which points in several directions
It's got some aspect to it
that points in one direction and another
We're going to come to what
their geometry is like soon enough
But for the moment,
they're defined by the transformation properties
Okay
As I said,
the importance of tensors is that when
a tensor equation is true in one frame
It's true in every frame
Next
Operations on tensors
Things you can do to tensors that make new tensors
We're not at this point interested in
things that you can do to tensors
Which make other kinds of tensors
But we're interested in other kinds
of objects which are not tensors
We're interested in the things
we can do to a tensor
Operations we can do to them
Which will make new tensors
And in that way we can make a collection
of things out of which we can build equations
The equations being the same in every reference frame
Okay,
so let's write down
Some set of operations and then
I'll go through what they are
And how you do them
They're very simple
Well,
most of them are simple
The last one is not simple
Well,
first of all you can
multiply a tensor by a number
I didn't even write this down
You can take any tensor and
multiply it by a numerical number
It's still a tensor
I'm not even going to bother with that one
Okay
One
Addition of tensors
That's the first operation we'll talk about
Two
An addition of course includes also subtraction
If you multiply a tensor by
a negative number and then add it
It's subtraction
Multiplication of tensors
Makes tensors
Three
Contraction
And I'll tell you what that means
You may or may not
know the word at this point
But we will know the word soon
Contraction and four
Differentiation of tensors
But not ordinary differentiation
Covariant differentiation
And we will define that I think tonight
Covariant differentiation of tensors
I think those are the four basic processes
That you can do on
a tensor to make new tensors
Differentiation with respect to what?
Well,
differentiation with respect to position
These tensors might be things
which vary from place to place
And then they're called tensors
They live at a point
They have a value at a point
At the next point they have a different value
And learning to differentiate them is
going to be fun and hard
Not very hard,
a little hard
Okay,
adding tensors
You only add tensors if their indices
match and are of the same type
For example,
if you have a tensor T
M with a bunch of more upstairs indices
Contravariant indices and maybe
a collection of downstairs indices
And you have another tensor of the same kind
Plus S,
M
S does not stand for scalar here
Dot dot dot
Dot dot dot dot p
In other words,
they're equal to the same kind
Their indices are of exactly the same kind
This might be M,
N,
R and so forth
This could be P,
Q,
whatever
If the indices match,
then you are permitted to add them
And construct a new tensor
Which I'll just call T plus S
M dot dot dot dot dot dot p
In other words,
the tensor,
the thing which is just the sum of the indices
Defines a new tensor
Which is the sum of the two tensors
It's obvious that this transforms the right way
If T transforms by multiplying it by a
bunch of dx by dy's and dy by x's
And S transforms the same way
Then if you just factor out the,
you know,
the transformation coefficients
The dx,
dy's and the dy,
dx's
Then you can see easily that
the sum is also a tensor
Transforms as a tensor
You can do the same thing with minus,
incidentally
No difference
Also,
T minus S is a tensor
And this is the basis for saying that
tensor equations are the same in every reference frame
T minus S equals zero is a tensor equation
It's the equation that the tensor
T minus S is equal to zero
Okay,
next,
multiplication of tensors
Now,
unlike addition,
multiplication of tensors can be
done with tensors of any rank
Rank means the number of indices
And independently of whether those
indices are upstairs or downstairs
And here's the way it works
Let me start with an example
Multiplying two vectors
Supposing we have a vector with a cov-
Covariant index
And we multiply it by some other vector
To make it a life a little more complicated
Let's multiply it by a vector with a covariant index
This is a tensor
It's a tensor
With one upstairs index,
M
And one downstairs index,
N
You have to remember which one is which
Do not cross
If this is M,
this one is M
If this one is N,
that one is N,
and so forth
This is a tensor with one covariant
Sorry,
one covariant index
And one contravariant index
The set of values
The set of values,
one value of this thing for each
M and N
Define the components of a tensor with two indices
You could have done the same thing with some
Other vector
Let's continue to call it W
But one with another upstairs index
And this would have been some other tensor
With one upstairs and another upstairs index
I use upstairs and downstairs because
I constantly have to remind myself
Which one is covariant and which one is contravariant
And upstairs and downstairs are easier to
To think of,
but they're the same thing
And you usually
You can put a product
sign in here if you like
Just to keep track of the fact that you're multiplying
What's that?
You said multiply vectors
Are you plotting the vectors?
No,
this is not plotting the vectors
This is making
We're going to talk about that in a moment
This is making a tensor of different rank
Higher rank just by juxtaposing these together
How many indices,
how many components does this object have?
Well,
let's work in four
We're going to be interested in four dimensions
Or the space times
Let's say the number of indices is four
M runs,
the number of values that
M can take on is four
In three dimensions it would be three
But in four dimensions this
would have 16 independent components
16 independent components
Four for this and four for that
This would be a 16
Component object
It is not the dot product
The dot product only has one component
It's a number
Sometimes it's called the outer product
But it's just a tensor product
Just a tensor product of two tensors
And it makes another tensor
Typically a tensor of different rank
Than either one of them
The only way you can make
a tensor of the same rank
Is for one of the factors to be a scalar
A scalar is a tensor of a number
And a tensor is a tensor
And you can always multiply a tensor by a scalar
Take any scalar
Multiply it by Vm
And it's a tensor with one index upstairs
In other words,
multiplying any tensor by a scalar
Gives back a tensor of the same kind
Not the same tensor
It's multiplied by S
But of the same type
Of the same generic type
Same number of indices in the same place
That's the only situation
Where when you multiply a tensor by some other tensor
You get back a tensor of the same type
Generally you get back a tensor of higher rank
With more indices,
obviously
Where these tensors will come in
We'll find out where they come in soon enough
But so far this is just a notational device
So far think of it as a notational device
Okay,
everybody happy with it?
It's really easy
It's very hard to make mistakes
Are there any rules?
Like,
you know,
switching sides
And Vw is equal to Wv?
Yeah,
well okay,
let's be careful
Yeah,
let's take this one with two upstairs
Vm Wn is equal to Wn Vm
But it is not equal to
Vn Wm
Vm times Wn is the same as Vm times Wm
It doesn't matter which is,
you know
7 times 3 is 3 times 7
We're not doing quantum mechanics
Every multiplication of numbers
And components are numbers
Components are numerical values
So on the other hand
When you write this as a tensor
You must remember
That the first index refers to the V
And the second index refers to the N
You must remember your convention
That the first index here was associated with V
And the second index here was associated with W
But the transformation properties
Are just the transformation properties
Of a thing with two contravariant indices
Okay
Yeah,
there's nothing abnormal
About multiplying components of vectors
They are just numbers
And when you multiply two numbers
You can multiply them in any order you like
Same with adding them
Okay,
good
Incidentally,
how do we prove
That a thing like this is a tensor?
Well,
we just write down
The transformation property of V
And the transformation property of W
And that tells us what the transformation property
Of V times W is
And it's more or less manifest
I already gave some examples of it
That products like this
Continue to be tensors
Tensors with the appropriate index structure
So that's good
We have addition
We have multiplication
And now we're going to look at this
And then we have contraction
Okay,
contraction is also very easy
An easy algebraic process
But in order to prove that contraction leads to tensors
We need a little
Tiny little minor theorem
嗯
No mathematician would call this a theorem,
they would call it a,
maybe at most a lemma.
Okay,
here's what the theorem says,
or the lemma.
Consider the object,
the x,
b,
I've mostly used m and n's
and p's and q's for the indices.
I'm going to start using a's and b's,
there just aren't enough letters in the alphabet
to take them all from
the same range in the alphabet.
Take the x,
b by d,
y,
m,
multiply that by d,
y,
m by d,
x,
a,
and implicit in this formula
is a sum over y,
a sum over m.
Implicitly,
this means m.
Sum over m.
What is this object?
Anybody know what this object is?
This is the change in x,
b when you change y,
m a little bit,
times the change in y,
m when you change x,
a a little bit,
summed over m.
You change y,
1 a little bit,
then you change y,
2 a little bit,
then you change,
what does
that do to echo,
what is this thing?
I didn't hear you.
I didn't hear what you said,
but it's probably right.
Let me write down a slightly more general formula.
Let's take df of x,
or df,
df,
f is both a function of x and y,
I mean it's a function
of x,
but because x depends on y,
it's also a function of y.
df by d,
y,
m,
d,
y,
m by d,
x,
a.
You know what this is?
Yeah.
The change in f when
you change y a little bit,
times the change in y when you change
x a little bit,
what does that give you?
It gives you df,
dx with an index.
It gives you df by d,
x,
a.
This is the change in f when you change x,
a a little bit,
and it's been calculated
by a sum of steps where first you change y,
1 a little bit,
then you change y,
1 in response.
Then you change y,
2 a little bit,
in response to a change in x,
a,
and that gives you df,
x,
a.
Now,
what if f happens to be x,
b?
Then carrying out the formula,
it tells me that it's the derivative of x,
b with respect
to x,
a.
That looks like a stupid thing.
What does that mean?
Yeah.
What's the derivative of x,
b with respect to x,
a?
Chronic of delta.
Yeah.
What's the derivative of x,
1 with respect to x,
1?
No.
The derivative of x,
1 with respect to x,
1?
What's the derivative of x,
1 with respect to x,
2?
So this thing here is just the chronic of delta,
delta b,
a.
So only true for a private book?
No.
It's true for any set of coordinates.
Nope.
True for any coordinates.
Okay.
Notice it has one index upstairs and one index downstairs.
Delta b,
a.
We're going to find out that delta b,
a by itself happens to also be a tensor.
That sounds a little weird.
It's just a set of numbers,
but it is a tensor with
one upper and one lower index.
So it's true for any set of coordinates.
We'll probably come around to it eventually.
Okay.
That's the little lemma that we
need in order to understand index contraction.
So let's do an example of index
contraction and then define it more generally.
Darn it.
I have my lemma on the blackboard that I need.
Okay.
Let's do it over here.
All right.
Let's,
as an example,
let's take a tensor which is
composed out of v and w.
v has a contravariant index
and w has a covariant index.
Excuse me,
n,
n.
This is the tensor T,
m,
n.
And now what contraction means is
it means take any upper index
and any lower index,
combine them together,
identify them,
and set their numbers equal to each other.
In other words,
take v,
m,
w,
m.
This means v1,
w1 plus v2,
w2 plus v3,
w3 and so forth.
You've identified an upper index with a lower index.
You're not allowed to do this with two upper indices.
You're not allowed to do it with two lower indices.
But you can take an
upper index and a lower index.
And let's ask how it transforms.
All right.
So first let's write down the transformation properties
before we set the indices equal to each other.
v,
w,
m,
n prime.
The primed version of it is,
dy,
m by dx,
a,
dx,
b by dy,
n times v,
now let's see,
a,
w,
b.
Let's check and see if this equation makes sense.
The transformation properties as always have
for each index in the tensor
one of these dy by dx's or dx by dy's.
On the left hand side we have y's.
This is the y components of something.
And here we have an upstairs index m.
So we have a dy,
m by dx,
a.
Here the y index is a lower index.
So this one is lower.
dx,
b by dy,
n.
And then we multiply that by y.
And we multiply by the same tensor
except the tensor in the unprimed components.
a,
b,
the a,
b components.
This is the transformation property of the rank two tensor
with one index upstairs and one index downstairs.
The primed version of it
and the unprimed version of it.
Now let's set m equal
to n and contract the indices.
Contract means identify an upper and lower index
and sum over them.
So we now have v,
m,
w,
m.
How many indices does this object have?
What kind of object is this?
It's a scalar.
It has no indices.
There's no indices.
Well what about these indices?
No,
no,
these indices are summed over.
These are summed over.
This is not the one component
of something or the two component.
It's like a dot product.
The one component,
the two component,
the three component all added together.
The result has no components.
They're summed over.
All right,
let's see what it is.
All we have to do,
the primed component of it is equal.
Now all we have to
do is identify m and n.
dy,
m by dx,
a.
dx,
b by n.
dy,
m.
m and n have been identified.
v,
a,
w,
b.
And now here's where our little lemma comes in handy.
dx,
b by dy,
m.
That's the thing over here.
I've written them down in opposite order.
Here is dx,
b by dy,
m.
Here's dx,
b by dy,
m.
Here's dy,
m by dx,
a.
Here's dy,
m by dx,
a.
And so I have exactly this combination appearing.
And that's just delta ab.
So this monstrosity over here is just delta ab.
And delta ab is simply the
instruction to set a equal to b.
That's what it is,
a little machine which says set a equal to b.
And the result is that
this thing is equal to v,
a,
w,
a.
This says set a equal to b.
Okay,
I set a equal to b
or set b equal to a.
Sorry,
v,
a,
w,
a.
Set b equal to a.
And look what I have on the left.
On the left I have the contraction
of an upper index with a lower index.
It doesn't matter that I call it a.
That's not important.
I have the contraction of the upper index
with the lower index in the unprimed frame.
And that's what I have.
That's equal to the corresponding
quantity in the primed frame.
I could call this m if I like.
It's a summation index.
It doesn't care what I call it.
Okay.
What does this say?
This says that the object that I've made has no
components and it has the same value in every frame.
What would you call it?
You'd call it a tensor.
Ah,
you'd call it a scalar.
Excuse me.
You'd call it a scalar.
So by contracting two indices.
I make another tensor,
in this case a scalar.
It's easy to prove,
and you can do this yourself,
that if you take any
tensor with a bunch of indices.
like that.
Any number of them.
Take one index from the upper indices.
And an index from the lower indices.
Set them equal to each other.
Then I would have t,
How many indices does this object have over here?
One,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six.
Is it really a six indexed object?
No.
Because I've summed.
This is the number of indexes.
The r is not really an index anymore.
It's been summed over.
So this is a four index object.
I've taken a six indexed object.
In other words,
a tensor of rank six.
And by contracting an upper with a lower index,
I have lowered the rank of the tensor by two.
Yeah?
Why does it have to
be an upper and a lower?
Why can't it just be an upper and a lower?
Okay,
what you would find.
Good.
So let's do that.
Let's start with this expression over here.
Now,
these both have upper indices.
So this has to be d
y n by d x b.
And then we would have.
All right.
Do you recognize that?
This has two upper indices.
Here's the prime component.
And in both cases,
we have d y by d x,
d y by d x.
Okay?
Now supposing I set m equal to n in sum.
This is an illegitimate notation,
but let's do it anyway.
This object is not this object.
This has a d x,
d y,
d y by d x.
That's the thing which is delta a b.
This has a d y by d x,
d y by d x.
This is nothing in particular.
It's certainly not just chronic delta a b.
So since this is not chronic delta a b,
this does not become v a w a.
So the transformation of the function.
The transformation property of this thing over here with two upper
indices contracted like that is just some bastardized thing with no particular.
Is it the inner product?
No.
The inner product of two vectors
is one upper and one lower.
Right.
This is really kind of
a generalization of the inner product.
The contraction.
Yeah.
The contraction is the generalization of
the inner product of two vectors.
Yes.
That's exactly right.
Okay.
So what's the contravariance of one and two?
What must be contravariant?
We're going to be doing in a moment.
As soon as we introduce the metric pencil,
we'll talk about inner product of vectors.
And this also relies on each
index having the same range of values.
Otherwise,
it's .
Yeah.
Sure.
We're in some space of a given dimensionality.
So the range of values of the
index runs over the dimensionality of the space.
Can I ask a question about
something that came a while ago?
Yeah.
So when you mentioned that if you,
what you said about making the components all zero
and pushing everything to one side of the equation,
having that be,
when you could do that,
therefore you could write the same equation in any frame.
Zero is the same as zero in any frame.
Yeah.
So it seems to me,
and I want to know if this is right,
that what that really seems to depend on
is that these transformations are not the same.
They're linear.
It does.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
In other words,
by linear,
you mean that,
yes,
it depends on that they're linear.
Yeah.
Yes.
也順利
That's correct.
Okay,
we've defined.
Now let's come to the metric tensor.
The metric tensor plays a big role.
Here I've illustrated it by a particular construction,
the way that this em en is the metric tensor.
But let's define it on its own terms,
abstractly.
Again,
things we've done before,
but let's do them again.
Okay,
the definition of the metric tensor
is if we have a differential
limit,
let's say,
length element dxm,
which just represents the
components of a displacement vector.
Let's call it a displacement vector.
Go to a point in the space called x,
x1 to xn,
and now displace it and call that little vector dx.
It has components,
contravariant
components dxm,
the contravariant components
of a little displacement vector.
if you want to remember what they mean geometrically,
what they mean is these expansion
coefficients in terms of some basis vectors.
But it's easier once you get the hang of it,
just to proceed with the notation.
dxm is the contravariant components
of a little displacement vector.
Now we ask,
what is the length of that vector?
Well,
I haven't told you enough to
tell you what the length is.
The length of the vector.
This could be some arbitrarily shaped,
complicated space.
And specifying what the space is,
is in effect specifying what all
the lengths of the little elements are.
All right,
so we take the dxm,
and let's take the squared length.
It's always easier to start with a squared length,
Pythagoras'
theorem,
but Pythagoras'
theorem becomes the more,
in coordinates which are not orthogonal,
Pythagoras'
theorem,
takes a more complicated form.
It's still quadratic in the dx's,
but it involves a dxm,
and a dxn,
and a quantity gmn,
gmn.
In general this gmn will depend on where you are.
So it depends on x.
In particular if you have a
complicated curved space of some sort,
with curved coordinates,
and you pick some little dx over here,
then the length of it will
not only depend on the dx's,
but it will also depend on
where you are in the space.
And so this is basically the
most general thing you can write down,
which is quadratic.
Let's,
I'm going to stick with a case of four dimensions,
just because I have it firmly planted in my head,
four dimensions,
and we'll keep with that.
But how many independent components
are there of this gmn thing?
You know?
Six.
Ten.
See why.
Well,
to begin with there are sixteen.
There are four,
there are four x's.
You can multiply any one by any other one.
And so you start with sixteen.
Alright?
But,
dx1 times dx2 is exactly
the same as dx2 times dx1.
So there's no point in having
a separate g12 and a g21.
Set them equal to each other.
And then,
if you count,
you'll count that there are ten independent ones.
I was going to say it's three for three spaces.
Oh,
for three spaces it's six.
Yeah,
for three space,
for three dimensional space it's six.
Right.
Well,
here's what you count.
You know,
make a sort of matrix.
Sixteen entries.
Okay.
But,
the one,
here's,
let's see,
where are we?
Here's the 1,
1 element,
1,
2 element,
and so forth.
You might as well take the 1,
2 element and the 2,
1 element to be the same.
They both multiply dx1 times dx2.
Alright?
So,
we have an element for here,
and let's just cross it.
An element here,
an element here,
and an element here.
That's dx1 squared,
here's dx2 squared,
here's dx3 squared,
dx4 squared.
We have the 1,
2 element,
the 1,
3,
and the 1,
4,
the 2,
3,
4,
and the 3,
4.
But,
we don't need to count separately the 1,
2 and the 2,
1,
so we don't have to put anything,
any new ones down here.
How many are there?
10 independent components of Gmn.
As you say,
in 3 dimensions it would be 6.
How about in 2 dimensions?
The 2 diagonal elements and 1 off-diagonal,
which you can take to be
the same as the other off-diagonal.
Okay,
so,
10 independent elements
to the metric tensor.
So far,
we haven't proved it's a tensor.
I call it the metric tensor,
but let's now prove that it's a tensor.
Gmn.
Now,
the basic guiding principle
is that the length of the vector is a scalar.
We have a little vector somewhere,
everybody agrees on the length of it,
although they don't agree on its components.
That's the underlying principle about a metric space,
that the length of a vector is a scalar,
that everybody agrees about the length of the vector.
Okay?
So,
let's go from x coordinates,
what happened to our,
I thought I,
didn't I move this?
Oh,
well,
no,
I did move it,
but,
seems to me I've seen that before.
Alright,
so the length of the little dx vector,
here it is,
I'll write it again,
the squared length,
is gmn of x dxm dxn.
But now let's go to the y coordinate,
the y coordinates,
the primed coordinates.
This must be equal to gm,
let's call it,
oh,
let's call it g,
I don't know,
call it gpq,
I don't want to use the same index,
gpq dy,
dyp dyq.
Now,
there's something wrong,
this isn't quite right.
That's because this should be
the primed components of the tensor.
The tensor in the primed coordinates,
in the y coordinates,
y.
Okay,
let's rewrite this
by writing that dxm
is equal to partial of xm,
with respect to yp dyp.
The little differential element
of x separation
is the derivative of x with respect to y,
times the little change in y.
And let's do the same thing for dxn.
dxn is equal to partial of xn,
with respect to yq,
dyq.
And now plug these two expressions into here.
Okay,
so what will we get?
We'll get that this is equal to
gmn of x,
and now,
partial of xm with respect to yp,
partial of xn with respect to yq,
dyp dyq.
So,
look at this side over here,
and look at this side over here.
This has dyp,
dyq,
this has dyp,
dyq.
This object over here
must be g prime.
They play the same role.
This is the set of objects,
the pq objects,
which you multiply by dyp dyq,
to find the length of the vector.
And so we found the transformation property.
The metric tensor in the primed frame
is given by the metric tensor in the unprimed frame,
times our good old friends,
dx by dy,
times dx by dy.
This is just exactly the transformation property
of a tensor,
a tensor with two covariant indices.
So,
we discover that the metric tensor
is indeed really a tensor.
That's the first fact about the metric tensor.
It really is a tensor.
It transforms as a tensor.
And it has,
uh,
many applications.
Any questions about the metric?
We're going to say more about it in a minute,
but,
uh...
Okay,
let me go on.
We're getting a little bit late.
The metric tensor has two lower indices,
and that's because it multiplies
these differential displacements,
which have upper indices.
Okay?
Now,
the metric tensor,
is also just a matrix.
It's a matrix with,
uh,
m-n indices.
This is just a matrix,
g-m-n.
g-1-1,
g-1-...
I'll write it in,
uh,
for three-dimensional space,
g-3-3,
g-1-2,
g-1-3,
g-3,
uh,
2-3.
And it's...
and furthermore,
it's a symmetric matrix.
g-1-2 and g-1-2,
g-1-3 and g-1-3,
g-2-3 over here.
Yeah,
you can call this g-3-1,
but it might as well be
taken to be equal to g-1-3,
because...
dx-1 times dx-3 is the same as dx-3 times dx-1.
So you can just take the...
you can take it to be a symmetric matrix.
Now,
what do we know about symmetric matrices?
There's one more fact about this matrix.
Thought of as a matrix,
it has eigenvalues.
The eigenvalues are never zero.
And the reason that eigenvalues are never zero
is because a zero eigenvalue
would correspond to a little vector of zero length.
And there are no vectors of zero length in a,
uh,
you know,
all of...
every direction has a length associated with it.
What do you know about matrices which are symmetric
and don't have zero eigenvalues?
Do you know anything?
One,
they are Hermitian.
But they're also invertible.
In other words,
they have inverses.
The metric tensor has an inverse.
That means that there's a matrix
which when you multiply by the metric tensor,
by the metric matrix,
gives you the unit matrix.
I'm going to write the equation down,
and then we'll see what,
uh,
what it means.
The inverse matrix,
the inverse matrix to the metric tensor,
is also called G,
but you put the indices upstairs.
G,
M,
N upstairs.
G,
M,
N with indices upstairs
is also a tensor,
and it's defined by the property,
by the defining property
that as a matrix,
it's the inverse of the matrix with two lower components.
Now how do you write that?
This is the last thing we're going to do tonight.
How do you write the fact?
If we have two matrices,
let's just take two matrices,
A and B.
One is called A,
M,
N,
and the other is called,
uh,
B,
P,
Q.
How do we multiply two matrices together?
We multiply two matrices together
by identifying an index
and summing over the index.
And that gives us the product of the matrix,
the MQth product.
I'm going to write the equation,
and I think you'll recognize it,
but if not,
we're going to come back to it.
G,
M,
N
times G,
N,
let's call it P,
summed over N,
contracted.
This is a legitimate expression here
if G,
N,
P is truly a tensor.
If G,
N,
P is truly a tensor with the upstairs index,
then this is a legitimate product of two tensors
with the index N contracted.
Can you guess what the answer is for this product?
Equals...
Delta M,
P.
What is Delta M,
P?
That's a matrix,
thought of as a matrix.
It's the unit matrix,
the identity matrix.
It's the identity matrix.
What this equation says
is the product of the matrix G,
M,
N
with the matrix G,
N,
P with upper indices
is the unit matrix.
It identifies this object over here
as the inverse matrix to this.
This is called the metric tensor
with contravariant indices,
two contravariant indices.
This is the metric tensor with two covariant indices.
This is the metric tensor with one contravariant
and one covariant index.
But in any case,
the definition of this matrix over here
is just the inverse.
And the inverse is such that when you multiply it
with the original matrix,
you get the identity matrix back.
This will play an important role,
the fact that there is a metric tensor
with upstairs indices and downstairs indices.
And we'll come to it.
I think we'll quit for tonight.
I think we've done enough for tonight.
We'll talk just a little bit more
about the metric tensor next time.
And then we'll go on to the subject of curvature.
The subject of parallel transport,
curvature,
differentiation of tensors.
So far,
everything I've told you is easy.
It's just getting the notation
and following the notation.
The idea of a covariant derivative
is a little more complicated,
not much.
And,
um,
but it's essential.
We have to know how
to differentiate things in a space
if we're going to do anything useful.
In particular,
if we're going to study whether the space is flat,
we have to know how
things vary from point to point.
The question of whether a space is flat or not
has to do,
fundamentally has to do,
with derivatives of the metric tensor.
And the character and nature of the derivatives
of the metric tensor.
So the next time,
we'll talk a little bit about
tensor calculus,
differentiation of tensors,
and,
um,
and especially the notion of curvature.
I hope we get to curvature.
Yeah?
I'm a little confused about what space
these things are.
You've got the space you drew on the board originally.
Yeah.
And...
You've got the space coordinates
that we've been transforming about.
And at each point there...
Mm-hmm.
...there can be a value,
a scalar,
a vector,
a three-dimensional vector,
something.
But those things don't live in that space,
do they?
Well,
they're functions of position in the space.
That's right.
But then they have to live in their own space,
it seems.
But they have...
Yeah,
but remember that they have the space
that they live in has the same dimensionality
as the number of indices.
One,
two,
three is the dimensionality of the space,
and it's the same as the number of coordinates.
That's just my theory.
It's got to be like that,
or...
I mean,
I think you could instruct...
Yeah,
yeah.
...a math from the points of the three-dimensional space
to a two-dimensional space.
You could,
you could,
but these...
All right,
all right,
so what...
All right,
so let me give you another answer
to tell you what space these things live in.
Here is the curved or uncurved space that...
Well,
maybe,
that everything is a function of.
All right?
At every point on that space,
there is what's called a tangent space.
The tangent space has exactly the same dimensionality
as the space itself,
but roughly speaking,
you can think of it as...
a space of flat planes,
which are connected to every point.
At every point,
there is a tangent space.
The tangent space has the same dimensionality
as the space itself,
and a mathematician would say that these tensors
live in the tangent space.
I don't know if that helps you or not.
It does help.
It does help,
okay.
The tensors,
vectors,
and so forth,
live in the tangent space.
They have components in the tangent space,
and that's the mathematical way
to describe the space that they live in.
Question?
Yeah.
The delta...
Laura,
can't hear you.
I'm sorry.
Yeah.
The equation,
last equation you have there,
can only be the identity matrix
if M equals P.
Does it still make sense if
M is not equal to P?
No,
no,
no.
This is a symbol which is
0 if M does not equal P,
and 1 if M does equal P.
The equation makes sense for every M and P.
For example,
it says that G1n,
Gn2 is equal to 0.
It says that G1n,
Gn1,
whoops,
1 equals 1.
So there's an equation for each M and P.
Some of them say that the right-hand side is 0,
and some of them say
that the right-hand side is 1.
I understand that.
I'm asking,
you also said that it was the identity matrix,
and that's only true for that one case.
The...
M not equal to P also makes sense.
It's just not an identity matrix.
No,
no,
no.
You're missing...
no,
no.
This whole thing is the identity matrix.
It's not a particular component
of it is the identity matrix.
This whole thing is the matrix...
All right,
so let's write it out.
Let's write it out for 2 by 2.
2 by 2.
Two-dimensional space.
This would be G...
Let's...
Well...
The right-hand side is the matrix 1,
0,
1.
Okay?
Let's actually do it.
Okay.
Let's do it.
This is...
It's going to be a pain in the neck,
but let's write it out.
We start with a matrix which is G11,
with lower indices,
G12,
G...
I'll call it 2,
1,
but G21 is the same as G12,
and G22.
That's this matrix.
Now we multiply it by
another matrix whose indices are upstairs,
and this is G11,
G12,
G21,
G22.
Let's multiply it.
You don't need to do that.
What you have...
My point is that,
in that case,
m equals P.
In what case m equals P?
Why don't you thread down here your example,
m equals P.
And—
Here.
OK.
m is not equal to p.
Sorry.
In your example.
Which example?
Your,
like,
your two matrices.
These two?
Up,
down,
left,
right.
Here.
Okay.
m equals p.
Not the couple of angles.
I think the point is m and p
are all in three space or four space.
They're in the same space.
And that's why the matrix is going to be symmetric.
I'm not sure what you're worried about.
I'm going to write,
I'm going to now write
this equation in its full-blown glory.
Okay.
Right.
So what does it say?
It says that g11,
g11,
g11 plus g12,
g21.
This time.
This plus this times this is equal to 1.
It says,
I'm not going to write all of them.
It says g11 times g12 plus
g12 times g22 is equal to 0.
There's four equations here.
One for each entry.
Four equations.
The product of this times this is equal to 1.
The product of this times this is equal to 0.
And so forth.
I'm not sure what else.
I'm not sure what you're,
what you're.
What's the minus?
It's a sub・・・
No,
0.
No.
0 if you're not doing
this solution at the right place.
So 1 minus 0 times g,
1 minus,
no,
2.
Right ?
Yeah,
right.
These guys are over 1,
2,
3,
4.
And so it must written 3 by 2 or 3.
or go by 4,
they have to be the same?
Yeah.
They have to be because it's the same space.
Those are indices that go
between the same values.
Yes.
They go from 1 to 3.
Every single one of them runs from
in this case from 1 to 2.
In a three-dimensional case
they would run from 1 to 3.
Each of these would be
square matrices.
N by N
square matrices,
yes.
Is that what you're saying?
Okay,
yeah,
that's true.
They're all square matrices.
All N by N matrices,
right.
But they correspond to
four distinct equations,
well
some number of
distinct equations.
Some number of distinct equations,
each independent component.
Yeah.
Are they positive definite?
Do they have to be positive definite?
Yeah.
Now what do you mean
by positive?
Positive definite.
The eigenvalues for,
okay,
good.
For a conventional space
with a positive metric
where all distances are positive,
the answer is that it has to be
positive definite.
In the context that we will be coming to,
relativity,
they will not be positive definite.
And why is that?
Because if you remember from special
relativity,
the distance,
the space line,
the distance between two points
is t squared minus x squared minus y squared
minus z squared.
Or,
depending on convention,
x squared plus y squared plus z squared
minus t squared.
So the answer in relativity,
in general relativity,
is that it's not positive definite.
But if we were talking,
if we were Riemann,
talking about a conventional geometry
in which all distances are positive,
then the maximum distance between two points,
the metric would be positive definite.
Is that what you're asking?
Yeah,
okay.
But we,
at the moment,
we're just doing
ordinary geometry,
and we will come
to Lorentz geometry.
Lorentz geometry is nothing but throwing in
an extra sign,
the signs.
But we'll come to that.
It's worth learning first about differential geometry
and tensor analysis in the more conventional situation.
I don't quite understand why that can't be.
Why that can't be zero?
Why which can't be zero?
Zero eigenvalue in that context.
Why?
Why would the eigenvalue be zero?
None of the eigenvalues are zero.
That's what allows you to invert the matrix.
Mm-hmm.
Is it under the other one
that's stuck on the wall there,
that's hidden?
Underneath that one.
Underneath?
Yeah.
So we took four-dimensional space.
And then we got a 10-order matrix.
10 independent components.
Right.
So is that some way to inspire string theory
saying,
well,
we live in a 10-order matrix?
Absolutely no connection.
Well,
10 is 10,
but they're not.
No connection,
whatever.
Coming back to the question of invertibility,
is the metric tensor being invertible a property
of the Monnian geometry but not Lorentzian?
Because for the Lorentzian geometry,
it seemed like a vector on a light bulb.
That has a metric of zero.
But it's not an eigenvector.
It's not an eigenvector.
سلام
عليكم
an eigenvector of the metric.
The metric tensor,
for example,
in just two-dimensional space
would be 1 minus 1.
And that has eigenvalues 1 and minus 1,
no eigenvalues 0.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.