Stanford University.
General relativity has a
reputation for being very difficult.
I think the reason is that it's very difficult.
It's kind of calculationally intensive.
Intensive indices and symbols.
There are ways people have invented to
express things in sort of more condensed,
very,
very
neat notations.
But just learning them in itself.
It's a task that would take some time.
Things like fear binds,
forms,
spinners,
and twisters,
and all sorts of different kinds
of mathematical objects.
You could call many of them notation.
Notations.
Notational if you like.
And they do simplify the equations.
So I sometimes feel as if in
presenting these things the way I do,
that it's sort of like
Maxwell who wrote down every single equation of his...
How many Maxwell equations are there?
I think eight.
Eight.
Eight altogether.
We don't usually write all components of the equations.
We put them together into vector notation and so forth.
And if we're smart,
we can even avoid the indices
by inventing symbols like curl and
so forth.
And the same thing can be
done to some extent for general relativity.
But as I said,
the computational methods and techniques are harder.
And I'm not an expert in them.
I'm by no means an expert in them.
I'm not an expert in general relativity.
I know the subject.
I know how to use it.
But quite honestly,
when I go to do something using general relativity,
I go back to the
indices.
I can follow when somebody else uses the fancy methods.
But I can't do them myself.
It's not just that I can't do them myself.
It's not natural to me.
I wind up going back to
the same thing that we're doing here.
Indices.
Derivatives.
And so on.
The whole works.
And my feeling is it's the right
way to see it for the first time.
But it is a nuisance.
Indices all over the place.
Notations all over the place.
Too much of it.
Can't help it.
So some aspect of it,
you have to get over.
You have to get over that hump of tensor notation,
the indices,
and so forth.
And then it goes easier.
Then it goes more smoothly.
Until you come to do a calculation.
And then right back to the mess again.
Now,
if you're really interested in
doing computations in general relativity,
there
are packages.
There are,
you know,
you just put in the
metric as a function of position.
The metric tensor.
And out it will spit various tensors and Riemann tensors.
This kind of tensor.
That kind of tensor.
Einstein tensors.
And then you can say,
without even looking at the result,
you can say,
okay,
please,
Mr.
Computer,
set the Riemann tensors,
set the Einstein tensor equal to the energy momentum
tensor and tell me what comes out.
So yeah,
computers can do a lot better.
But as I said,
general relativity is hard,
and part of the hardness is just the complexity
of the notations.
That are necessary.
Incidentally,
the subject that we're studying
up till now is Riemannian geometry.
Riemannian geometry,
the geometry of curved spaces.
The geometry of smooth,
curved metric spaces,
they're called.
And I suppose we have Riemann to
blame for the complexity of the notation.
Actually,
he simplified it,
and Einstein simplified it further.
But nevertheless.
It is.
It is notationally and computationally intensive.
The basic concepts are really not so hard,
but we have to go through the mess before
we get to the concepts.
Or before we can express those concepts.
If there are no questions,
yeah?
I was wondering if you have a sense of
what are the active areas of research in general
relativity?
I know very well,
yeah.
Well,
yeah,
there are several.
The most active areas of research,
the ones which are really very,
very strongly active
among theoretical physicists,
is the quantization of general relativity.
The quantization of black hole physics,
that's probably the most active area.
There are astrophysics.
There are astrophysical areas,
where again,
black holes are very important.
Astrophysical areas are
entirely classical general relativity.
There's numerical relativity.
Numerical relativity means,
and usually for the
purposes of solving astrophysical problems,
numerically putting in various initial situations a
pair of black holes orbiting around each other.
And simply running the computer to find
out what happens by solving Einstein's equations.
And it's a very subtle business,
incidentally.
It is not that you just
put in the equations and grind.
It's much more subtle than that.
And numerical relativity is also a very hard subject.
The purpose,
for example,
being to find out how much
gravitational radiation and other kinds of things,
there's an entirely different kind of thing.
It's entirely classical.
Gravitational radiation is classical radiation.
When two black holes fall into each other,
bang,
a lot of gravitational radiation is produced.
Gravitational waves.
Why are we interested in them?
Well,
among other reasons,
because we have a chance of detecting them.
Anything you can detect is
a window into phenomena that you,
new phenomena.
So gravitational wave detectors may
be able to detect gravitational waves.
From the collision of two black holes.
There are,
it is estimated that there are a few collisions every
year of black holes that can be seen by gravitational radiation.
So there's a lot of different areas.
It's an extremely active area.
The equations of general relativity,
just the equations of general relativity,
and the equations of black holes
have been found to be useful,
extremely useful,
in condensed matter physics,
in fluid dynamics.
For having nothing to do with the black holes.
Nothing to do with black holes and gravity.
Same equations.
And so there's a heavy amount of activity in the areas
of applying the equations of general relativity to other areas of physics.
It's probably,
I would say,
probably the most active.
It went over the last,
over my career in physics,
from being a real backwater in physics.
Nobody studied general relativity very much.
1960s when I was a student,
except for the people who were really especially interested,
and were focused on questions of general relativity,
the bulk of theoretical physicists were not interested.
Then it started to become interesting in astrophysics,
and eventually it took over
questions of fundamental theoretical physics.
Why?
Because of a clash of gravity in general relativity.
Anyway,
I don't know.
For whatever reason,
it is probably now more important in the day-to-day
workings of theoretical physicists than almost any other subject.
That and quantum field theory.
And the connection between them.
Okay.
Let's,
um,
today will be the last day in
which we'll be studying Riemannian geometry as such.
Okay.
Without really discussing gravity.
Next time,
we will really get into gravity.
What does all of this have to do with gravity?
I told you a little
bit in the first lecture that,
uh,
that,
the problem of finding out
if there's a real gravitational field,
as opposed to just some funny coordinates
in which you're expressing space and time,
which leads to curved trajectories,
but not really curved trajectories.
The problem of finding out
there really is a gravitational field,
uh,
is a problem which is mathematically,
I would say very similar,
but I think I would,
uh,
I think I would go further than that.
I would say is identical to the problem
of finding out if a certain metric geometry,
geometry characterized by a metric tensor,
is flat or not.
A geometry which is flat,
let's say a two-dimensional geometry to begin with,
that means a surface of some sort.
A flat geometry is one
for which Euclid's postulates are correct.
There are parallel lines,
all the stuff you learned in,
uh,
Euclidean geometry
is called flat.
And it's characterized in terms of a metric tensor
by the statement not that the
metric has a very special simple form.
That's not the right statement.
The special form being the quantum vector.
The quantum vector is the
the
the've.
All those things exactly,
yeah they change
outcome,3
the question of
finding the
If that space is flat or not,
it's a somewhat difficult problem.
What you have to do is look at,
here's the bad way to do the problem.
The bad way to do the problem
is to search through all possible coordinate systems,
transform
the metric from the given form,
whatever,
however it's given,
the way it's presented
to you,
transform the metric to the new
coordinate system that you have constructed,
calculate
the new metric,
and ask whether it looks like a flat metric.
Now of course,
that will take an infinite amount of time,
you'll never get there,
so
you need a better technique.
And the better technique is
to search for diagnostic quantities.
Quantities which…
…which are built out of the metric,
the metric and its derivatives and so forth,
things
that you can calculate,
which,
if they are zero everywheres throughout the space,
that
says the space is flat.
If they're non-zero anyplace,
it says that the space is curved there.
The diagnostic quantity that does
that is called the curvature tensor.
Today's goal is to get to the…
…the curvature tensor of a Riemannian geometry.
And it's a complicated goal,
I warn you.
You've got to pay attention or else you'll fall asleep.
This is a very soporific subject.
I'll try from time to time to tell
a joke or whatever to keep you awake.
But on the other hand,
if you can follow it,
you've learned a lot.
And it is very interesting.
I think you'll find it very interesting.
I'll try not to make it too boring.
Okay.
I told my friend Barack Obama never to apologize,
and here I am apologizing already for being
boring.
Okay.
What do we start with?
We start with a space.
And a space means,
first of all,
a non-zero.
Number of dimensions.
The number of dimensions in
Riemannian geometry can be anything.
In principle you can even have a zero-dimensional space,
but that's pretty damn boring.
It's just a point.
A one-dimensional space is either an
infinite line or a closed curve.
If it's a closed curve,
what is it characterized by?
It's characterized by only one thing.
The total length of the curve.
Every curve is equivalent to every other curve.
But the total length is not equal
to the total length of the curve.
The total length is equal to
the total length of the curve.
So if you have a piece
of rope that closes on itself,
that has a certain length,
and
wiggle it in any kinds of ways,
or curve it in any kind of way,
it can always be mapped
or put on top of another piece of rope
of exactly the same length in a precise way without
stretching it.
The only thing that's really important is that
you're not going to have to make a single
one-dimensional space.
All the other one-dimensional spaces
are all equivalent to each other,
not quite.
They're characterized only by their length.
They're either infinite or they have a length l,
and every one of them have given length
l as identical to every
other one in its intrinsic properties.
A bug walking along a little piece of
rope cannot distinguish one geometry from the other
geometry.
All it can do is count the number of
steps that it takes them to go around the rope.
It leaves a marker someplace.
It goes around.
It goes around the rope until
it comes back to the marker.
It counts the number of steps,
and that's the only thing about that space.
Two-dimensional spaces begin to become more complicated.
There are flat ones.
There are curved ones.
A flat one is a plane.
A curved one could be a sphere.
It could be just a space with lumps,
the surface of the earth,
including the mountains and
the valleys and so forth.
It can even have weird topology,
the surface of a doughnut,
a torus.
Or you can poke another hole in the torus
and make a torus with two holes and so forth.
So by the time you get to two-dimensional spaces,
they're pretty complicated.
Nevertheless,
they are characterized by the metric tensor.
And the question of whether they're flat is a computation,
or as a first question,
find
something which distinguishes whether they're flat.
Find a quantity.
G-minus.
If g-minu,
g-m-n,
the metric tensor,
if it is not equal to zero,
that does not mean the
space is not flat.
It just means you may be in the wrong coordinates.
So you can't diagnose the space by
asking whether g-m-n is zero or not.
You want to find a quantity.
Let us call it r.
At the moment,
I'm not going to tell
you how many indices it has.
Some quantity.
Best it should be a tensor.
Because if it's a tensor and it's non-zero,
it's non-zero in every frame of reference.
We'd like to find some quantity called r.
R stands for Riemann,
incidentally.
Riemann was the first person who
asked this question and answered it.
Uh...
We want to find a thing called Riemann.
Riemann.
Such that,
if Riemann is equal to zero,
that implies that the space is flat and that there
exist coordinates such that...
Sorry,
did I say g-m-n not equal to zero?
I mean not equal to delta m-n.
g-m-n is equal to zero.
is an interesting space.
It's not very big.
Yeah,
GMN equals delta MN is what I meant.
And that's what we're going to search for.
The curvature tensor.
It is a tensor.
Let me just remind you about a few properties
of the metric tensor and what you do with it.
First of all,
GMN is by definition the thing
that's a function of position in general.
If it were not a function of position,
incidentally,
if it was a constant matrix,
a constant set of coefficients,
then it's very easy to find
coordinates in which GMN is delta MN.
You simply have to straighten out the angles.
So if GMN is not dependent on position,
then it's very easy to find
coordinates in which GMN is delta MN.
If it's just a set of coefficients,
a set of numerical coefficients,
then the space is definitely flat.
Alright,
so GMN is the metric tensor
and what do you do with it?
You take a little differential distance,
dxM,
multiply it by dxN.
Here's your little differential displacement.
It's characterized by a
set of differential coordinate shifts,
dxM,
dxN.
You multiply them together and that
gives you the square of the length
between the tail and the arrow
and the head of the vector.
That's equal to ds squared.
S standing for spatial distance,
I suppose.
Alright,
now,
the metric tensor is a tensor.
I think we proved that last time.
And the way you see that
is just by saying ds squared,
that's an invariant quantity.
All coordinates are invariant.
Let's call them coordinate systems.
All coordinate systems should agree about
the length of a given little vector.
And if we take that same ds squared and
write it in y coordinates instead of x coordinates,
the length has to be the same.
And that's sufficient to prove that GMN really is
a tensor and that it transforms like a tensor.
Okay,
next property of GMN is it has an inverse.
GMN is a matrix.
It's a matrix and it has an inverse.
The inverse satisfies the following equation.
G,
it's written again as a matrix.
When I say it has an inverse,
I mean it has an inverse as a matrix.
GMN is a matrix with entries.
And...
It has an inverse.
GMN,
which is written with upper indices.
They are,
in fact,
contravariant indices.
And the properties of GMN with upper indices
are such that if you multiply it by G,
let's call it nr,
and sum over n,
but I don't have to sum over n because Einstein tells me that
an upper and a lower index like this are automatically to be summed over.
This is the sum.
This actually corresponds to taking the matrix
GMN and multiplying it by the matrix Gnr.
And the resulting matrix is the unit matrix.
Why?
Because I told you that GMN is
the inverse matrix to this one here.
And the product then is the identity matrix.
And the identity matrix is the Kronecker delta.
And the Kronecker delta in general relativity,
or in Riemannian geometry,
is always written as a thing with
one upper index and one lower index.
At least if it's being treated as a tensor.
The Kronecker delta,
this is a thing to prove.
Prove that if you take the Kronecker delta,
and you transform it pretending it's a tensor,
you just get back the Kronecker delta again.
That's a thing that you can prove.
So,
these are tensor equations.
This is the meaning of saying the
GMN is the inverse matrix of Gnr.
And once you have that...
Oh,
there's another thing that is important.
In Riemannian geometry,
as opposed to Einsteinian geometry,
in Riemannian geometry,
all lengths are positive.
All lengths are positive.
Or the squares of all lengths.
More importantly,
the squares of all lengths are positive.
And all lengths are also positive.
But the squares of all lengths are positive.
And that says something about
the properties of the metric tensor.
What it says is that
there are no directions along which,
if you evaluate this,
you get anything which is not positive.
That's equivalent to a statement
about the eigenvalues of GMN.
It says all of the eigenvalues of it are positive.
All right?
But for our purposes now,
all lengths are positive.
It's the same thing.
And it does say something about the metric tensor.
It says it's positive definite.
That's the same thing as saying
all of its eigenvalues are positive.
That will change when we go
to the theory of real gravity.
That will go when we go to Einsteinian geometry.
All right,
the metric allows you to do something.
It allows you to raise and lower indices.
If you have a contravariant vector,
or better yet,
you have a vector which has contravariant components,
Vm,
contravariant means upstairs,
you can put it into correspondence
with another vector with covariant indices.
And it's really the same vector.
We talked about this a little last time.
I told you the difference
between contravariant and covariant indices.
And the way you construct the covariant components,
components are the words I'm looking for,
the covariant components of a
vector given its contravariant components
is just to multiply it by the metric tensor,
GmR,
and,
whoops,
well,
let's call it Gmn,
and sum over m.
This is now G sub n,
or V sub n.
Likewise,
this is something that you need to prove,
given a Vm with upper indices,
this,
if you like,
can be thought of as the definition
of the lower,
of the covariant component of a vector.
How do you go back?
Well,
you have to solve this equation,
but it's very easy to solve,
and I'll tell you what the solution is,
if you know the inverse matrix with upper indices.
Namely,
Vm is equal to Gmn Vn.
So if you know the upper indices,
if you know the covariant,
the contravariant components of a vector,
this is the way you build its covariant components,
and if you know the covariant components,
this is the way you build the contravariant components.
There's a little bit of a
proof here that you have to do,
namely,
there are,
you can see what we have to do,
you'll have to check that these
two are compatible with each other,
but they are.
Okay.
To what extent can you force the metric
to look like a flat metric?
To what extent,
assume the metric is not necessarily a flat metric,
that when I say flat metric,
I will mean,
not only is the space flat,
but that the coordinates are such
that Gmn is equal to delta Mn.
If that's the case,
if that's the case,
the space is definitely flat.
But to what extent,
given any space,
can you find coordinates such that
Gmn is equal to delta Mn?
Gmn might be,
for example,
the Kronecker delta over some limited region,
or approximately over some limited region,
equal to delta Mn.
Alright,
so here's a theorem.
There are coordinates at every point.
These coordinates are
coordinates which are good
in the immediate vicinity of a point.
They're not global coordinates,
they don't cover the whole space.
They're just good within the immediate vicinity of a point,
which means they're good up to some order
in little displacements away from this point,
namely second order.
Alright.
Coordinates called Gaussian normal coordinates.
Here's what you do.
Just first think of,
let's just think of it intuitively.
We have some curved surface.
We go to some specific point,
and we draw coordinate axes.
We draw coordinate axes,
and we keep those coordinate axes
as straight as we possibly can.
Later we'll learn that the term for
straight as possibly can curve is a geodesic.
But you make a straight curve as you can.
You have a little bug.
The little bug moves on this surface,
and
he moves following his nose,
going as straight ahead as he possibly can.
And that defines one coordinate axis,
then he comes back to a point,
and goes off in right angles,
does some surveying to figure out
where right angles to his little line are,
and goes off in another direction,
as straight as he can,
and then builds coordinates based on those.
The theorem says
that first of all,
at every point,
at every point you can choose coordinates,
as I said,
Gaussian normal coordinates,
such that,
first of all,
at that point,
g m n is equal to delta m n.
At x equals x zero.
This point is x zero.
You can do that in more than one way.
If you find coordinates in which it's true,
you can rotate the coordinates.
You can rotate the coordinates,
and if you rotate them,
that just corresponds to rotating the coordinates
in different axes and so forth.
So there's more than one way you can do it.
Next,
you can choose your coordinates,
you can straighten out these lines
to a degree
where the derivative of the metric,
with respect to any direction,
well,
let's put an x r here,
any direction,
the derivative of any component of the metric,
with respect to any direction in space,
can be set equal to zero.
That you do by choosing these curves
to be as straight as possible.
I'll tell you how you prove it in a minute.
It's actually very easy to prove.
It's just a counting problem
of counting how many variables there are
and how many equations there are,
but I'll show you in a minute.
Okay,
finally,
Yeah?
Is that just at x zero or throughout?
Say it again?
Is that...
No,
only at x equals zero.
At...
Sorry,
not at x equals zero.
It could be x equals zero.
At x equals x zero.
If you try to extend
that same coordinates
away from that point,
no matter how you try to extend them,
then in general,
unless the space is flat,
if you try to extend the coordinates
away from that point,
you'll find out that the derivatives,
the higher derivatives of g m n
are not equal to zero,
and in general,
for the general generic situation,
the second derivatives,
let's say with respect to some x r
and some other x s,
those in general cannot be equal to zero.
They cannot all be chosen equal to zero.
Except,
of course,
if the space is flat.
Okay?
So,
at a point,
there is no content really
in saying that the metric can be chosen to be
flat-like,
let's call this flat-like,
even up to first derivatives.
That can always be done.
It's in these second derivatives
that somehow the fact that the space is either flat
or not flat starts to show up.
First of all,
how do you prove this?
Well,
this is actually not hard.
Let's take our point of interest to be the origin.
Let's just take it to be the origin.
Let's set it equal to zero.
Now,
supposing we have some general metric
and some coordinates y
in which the metric has some,
some form,
not of this form here.
Let's look for some x's
which we're going to build,
which are going to be functions of the y.
Let's choose it in the following way.
At the place where x is equal to zero,
in other words,
at our origin over here,
let's also assume that y is equal to zero.
So the two sets of coordinates have the same origin.
That means that x will start out,
uh,
with just equal to y.
xm equal to ym.
And then,
in the next order,
we'll have some set of coefficients.
I'm simply,
I'm simply expanding x
in powers of y.
The next order will be something quadratic in y.
So let's put something quadratic in y here.
We'll call that cm.
And let's put here n and r.
And put xn,
xr.
That's the most general quadratic thing that I can write.
Oops.
Sorry,
y's.
Y's.
yn,
yr.
And then,
things may get more complicated later.
Okay.
How many such,
let's,
let's pick a number of dimensions of space.
Let's pick a number of dimensions of space.
Let's pick four dimensions of space.
How many such coefficients are there?
Well,
how many combinations yn,
yr are there?
The answer is ten.
Try counting them.
There's
y1 squared,
y2 squared,
y3 squared,
y4 squared.
and y3,
y4.
Did I miss any?
I think I have every possible thing here,
which is quadratic in y.
And there's one,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six,
seven,
ten,
ten of them.
So there are ten possibilities here.
How many components of the metric are there?
There are ten yn,
yr's.
So that means n and r
give you ten possibilities.
But then for each n and r,
you have an m.
That means there are forty independent coefficients here.
Forty independent coefficients.
The most general x that you can build
to quadratic order
has forty independent coefficients here.
Now,
how many independent components of g are there?
The answer is ten.
So how many equations does this correspond to?
Ten components,
and setting all of their derivatives equal to zero,
means that this is forty equations.
Forty equations,
forty unknowns,
and that allows you to be sure
that you can solve these equations
to quadratic order.
Solving them to quadratic order
is saying the same thing
that you can solve these equations,
but you'll fail at the next order.
You'll fail at the next order,
and here's the next order.
So it is always possible
to choose a metric
that has the property that
to quadratic order,
in other words,
the first derivative of the metric
is equal to zero,
and the metric is equal to a flat metric
at a point.
Excuse me,
I'm thinking something crucial here.
At the very beginning,
we have that equation with xn on the left
and y is on the right.
Does that represent an attempted coordinate transformation?
Yeah,
that's a coordinate transformation,
sure.
Yeah,
that's a coordinate transformation.
That's a coordinate transformation.
Yeah,
this is a coordinate transformation
which we're going to try to choose these c's
in such a way as to
make the derivatives of the metric zero.
You can always do it.
So every metric in that sense is flat
over a sufficiently small distance.
Question.
Is that saying it's locally flat?
That's saying it's locally flat.
That's the statement that it's local.
That's what being locally flat means,
yeah.
Yeah.
Intuitively,
it just says that any smooth surface
can be approximated over a small distance
by a plane that's tangent to it.
Right.
That's what that says.
Question.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
That can be solved because gmn is invertible.
Yeah.
You can't always solve for the equation necessarily.
Say it again.
You can't always solve for the equation.
Yeah,
I think in this case you can.
Yeah.
Yeah,
in this case you can.
There's...
Try it out.
Do it with 2x2 matrices.
Do it in a two-dimensional case.
And there's nothing special about four dimensions.
You'll find you can do it.
All right.
I don't want to try
to do it on a blackboard.
It's...
All right.
In any case,
it's a theorem.
It's a theorem that Gaussian
normal coordinates exist at every point,
at every point,
and they have this property.
All right.
Now,
the reason we introduce that is
because we want to give some meaning
to derivatives of vectors.
We've talked about some of tensors in general,
derivatives of tensors.
We've talked about various procedures,
various operations we can do on tensors
to make new tensors.
We can add them.
We can subtract them.
We can multiply them.
We can do all kinds of things.
Can we differentiate them?
In particular,
if we have a tensor,
which is a function of position,
that means all of its components are functions of position,
can we construct another tensor
which is in some appropriate sense
the derivative with respect to position
of the tensor that we have?
So let me show you why
this is a little bit complicated.
It's a little bit tricky.
You could just say,
well,
okay,
take the components of the tensor,
let's say covariant components,
and differentiate them,
and that gives you a new set of components,
which are the derivatives of the components.
That gives you the derivative of the vector.
It's true.
You can do that,
but what you get will not be a tensor.
Okay.
And let me show you why.
Can I ask one question?
Yeah.
Okay.
I think the way you had it received,
there are no first order terms.
This is first order.
You mean zeroth order.
Yeah.
That's right.
It's not that there are no zeroth order terms.
It's just I said,
let's choose the origins of the two
coordinate systems to be at the same point.
So that says wherever y is equal to zero,
x is equal to zero.
It was arbitrary,
but it doesn't cost anything.
Okay.
All right.
Let's look at a vector field.
A vector field,
a vector at every position.
And let's start with coordinates
which either the space is flat,
in which case I'll just
use flat ordinary Cartesian coordinates,
or the space is curved,
in which case these coordinates
here represent Gaussian normal coordinates,
as straight as possible,
so to speak.
And now let's take another coordinate system
and superimpose it on top of that.
These are not Gaussian normal coordinates.
They may be the coordinates that we started with.
And I'll represent those in green.
And they're curved relative to these coordinates.
For example,
the coordinate lines might look like that.
One of the coordinate lines.
The other one might look like this.
Or whatever.
All right.
Now,
before we ask how we differentiate a vector field,
vector field means a vector in every position here,
let's ask what it means,
what it would mean for the
vector field to be constant in space.
The problem here is because the space is curved,
it becomes hard to compare the
vector at one point and another point.
The coordinates,
if they can't be chosen to be everywhere flat,
then what exactly do you mean by saying a
vector over here is equal to a vector over here?
It doesn't really mean anything,
because to compare a vector over
here with a vector over here,
unless you have nice flat coordinates,
there's no unique way to do that.
So let's look at it for a moment.
If the space is flat,
really flat,
then I think I know what it means
for a vector over here to be the same
or to be equal to a vector over here.
It means it's equal.
It points in the same direction
and has the same length.
On the other hand,
does it say that,
I'm thinking about the green coordinates now,
let's think about the green coordinates.
In the black coordinates,
the components of this black vector and
this black vector are clearly the same.
In the nice Cartesian coordinates.
But what about the coordinates of this vector
here
and this vector over here
along the green axes?
In fact,
let's even,
let's take a special case.
Let's take this vector to be vertically up
so that we know that
it only has a y component
in the flat coordinates.
And let's assume that this vector over here
is equal to this vector at points
in the same direction in flat space.
Are its coordinates along the green axes,
are they the same as
the coordinates along the black axes?
No.
This coordinate along the green axis here
is different than the coordinate along the black axis here.
And in fact,
this vector would have both x and y components
along the green axes.
Whatever the green axes happen to be.
It has both kinds of components.
So it's clear that even
though the vectors are the same,
the components are not the same.
So you cannot judge when you have curvy linear coordinates,
and in general,
you will have curvy linear coordinates,
you can't judge by whether the components,
either covariant or contravariant,
you can't judge whether the vector is constant in space.
Right?
Another way to say the same thing
is that in one coordinate system,
the derivatives,
let's say with respect to
some coordinate xr
of the mth component of a vector,
might be zero in one coordinate system,
and not zero in another coordinate system.
It may even be the case that
all of the derivatives of vm
are zero in one coordinate system,
and not zero in the other coordinate system,
because the coordinates shift,
because the coordinate direction,
not because the vector is changing,
but because the coordinates are changing.
So this statement,
that the derivatives of a vector are equal to zero,
is not an equation
which is likely to be
the same in every reference frame.
Therefore,
it cannot be a tensor equation.
It's not a tensor equation.
And the derivative of a vector,
the components of a vector,
with respect to coordinates,
are not themselves components of a tensor.
They're not components of a tensor,
because they can be zero,
all of them,
in one frame of reference,
and not in another frame of reference.
If they were components of a tensor,
we would think of this as a rank two tensor,
an m-index and an r-index.
We might say,
look,
could this be a tensor tmr?
Well,
if it's a tensor tmr,
then if it's zero in one frame,
or in one coordinate system,
it's zero in every coordinate system.
But that's simply not true
of the derivatives of components of vectors,
not because the vector may change from point to point,
but because the coordinates,
the orientation of the coordinates change.
So,
we need a better definition
of the derivative of a vector
than just differentiating its components.
We need something which,
if it's zero in one frame,
is zero in every frame.
Okay,
so here's what we'll do.
Here's how we'll define the derivative of a vector.
First of all,
to define the derivative at a point,
you only need to look at nearby points,
right?
You only need to look at nearby points.
So,
the first thing you'll do
is to consider the derivative of a vector.
So,
let's say that we construct
Gaussian normal coordinates near that point.
Gaussian normal coordinates.
They're as straight as possible.
Then,
let's put this vector a little bit closer
just to indicate that it's like that.
Then,
pretending that the Gaussian normal coordinates
are really nice flat coordinates,
shift this vector so that its origin
is the same as the starting vector over here.
In other words,
shift it,
keeping its components fixed and constant
in Gaussian normal coordinates.
Alright,
so in the Gaussian normal coordinates,
I keep the components of this vector fixed,
and I compare it with this vector over here.
Just shift it down to here.
And the difference between these two
is the thing that I
will use to define the derivative.
The derivative will be the difference
between these two,
divided by the little separation along this axis here.
In other words,
to differentiate a vector,
differentiate it in Gaussian normal coordinates.
They are the ones which are closest of all
to Cartesian coordinates.
The derivatives in the Gaussian normal coordinates
define the derivative.
Okay,
now,
when you differentiate a vector
in general coordinates,
you'll get two terms.
The two terms come,
one term comes because the vector may be changing,
and the other term comes
because the coordinates are changing.
Coordinates are rotating out from under you,
even if the vector doesn't change,
and so forth.
If you work out this prescription,
take the derivative,
just the ordinary derivative in Gaussian normal coordinates,
and then re-express it in arbitrary coordinates.
Here's what you will find.
You will find that
the derivative,
which will now be called capital D,
along the r-axis
of the components of a vector vm
in arbitrary coordinates
are not just the derivative with respect to r
of vm,
but there's another term.
And the other term has to
do with the way the coordinates themselves
are changing from point to point.
And what it looks like is something,
it's proportional to v.
If you double the size of v,
you'll double this term here,
obviously.
So it's proportional to v.
It will have a v in it.
It does not have a derivative,
because this term doesn't come
from the fact that the vector
is changing,
it's coming from the fact that the coordinates are changing.
Let's put some indices and try to
see what kind of thing it could be.
Might have the t component here.
On the left-hand side,
we have indices r and m.
That means we have to have
some kind of object over here
that has index r and m.
Just to match the indices on the left-hand side.
On the other hand,
it's going to be proportional
to the components themselves of v,
so it's going to have some vt here.
This equation doesn't quite make sense.
There are two directions here,
there are three here.
You've got to soak them up,
you have to put another
index into this object here.
And in fact,
the standard convention is to put a minus sign there.
Okay?
This in fact is what you will get
if you take a vector,
differentiate it in Gaussian normal coordinates,
and then transform it to other coordinates.
In any other coordinate system,
what you will get
is the derivative minus a thing,
let's just call it thing for the moment,
times components of v themselves.
This is summed over time,
and you can see that vt
and the index structure on the left-hand side
is just r and m.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
That holds for an arbitrary coordinate system,
right?
That holds now for an arbitrary coordinate system,
but I haven't told you what gammas are,
what these gamma objects are.
Question.
What does that formula become
if it's Gaussian normal?
No,
in Gaussian normal coordinates,
it's just this.
Okay,
so the gammas come in because of...
Yeah,
the gammas,
yeah.
Right.
We're going to find that the gammas
are proportional to derivatives of the metric.
They have to do with the
metric changing from place to place.
They're going to be proportional
to the derivatives of the metric,
in Gaussian normal coordinates,
the derivatives of the metric are zero.
Okay,
that's the trick.
Use Gaussian normal coordinates to differentiate
because,
to first order,
the derivatives of the metric are zero.
Once you've differentiated it,
you can then transform the object
as if it were a
tensor to any frame of reference,
and the form will always be like this.
It will always be like this.
It will contain,
indeed,
a derivative,
but it will also contain another term
which will not be differentiated,
and it has to do with,
as I said,
it has to do with
the fact that not the vector
is changing from point to point,
but the fact that the coordinates
are changing from point to point.
These objects have various names.
This is called a connection.
It connects neighboring points
and tells you how to differentiate
something from one point to another.
It tells you,
basically,
how to compare
vectors at different points.
It tells you how to compare vectors
even though the coordinate system may be changing.
This is called a covariant derivative,
not because its index is downstairs.
It's called a covariant derivative for,
just because it's called a covariant derivative.
It's called a covariant derivative,
and it is a tensor.
It's a tensor in that if
it is zero in any frame,
it's zero in every frame.
So is that a generalization
of the conductive derivative?
You know,
I think it is.
I never thought about it that way.
But I think it is.
Yeah.
Whether it's connected with a
convective derivative,
no doubt it is.
No doubt it is.
I would have to sit down and think about it.
But there certainly are covariant derivatives
in fluid flow.
Right.
Okay.
So,
yeah.
This is called a covariant derivative,
and these symbols here go under two names usually.
They're either called the connection coefficients
or the Christoffel symbols.
Christoffel.
I,
Christ...
They've also been known on occasion
as Christoffel symbols.
They are pretty,
well,
they're not that complicated,
but they're complicated enough.
They're unlikable enough.
Okay.
Now,
one fact about them
that follows,
I'm not going to prove every single thing I say
because they're just too many little pieces,
but they're easy to check.
It follows from the definition,
namely the definition is you differentiate
in Gaussian normal coordinates,
and then you treat the object as a tensor
and transform it as a tensor with two indices.
It follows as a fact that,
and this is a theorem,
it's an easy theorem,
but it's a little too
intricate to do on the blackboard,
that this Christoffel symbol has a symmetry.
The symmetry of the Christoffel symbol
is that gamma t r m
is equal to gamma t m r.
It doesn't matter which order you put m and r,
they're the same.
That follows.
There are generalized remains
of Riemannian geometries.
They're called geometries with torsion.
Geometries with torsion,
the symmetry is not true.
But those geometries are not widely in use
in ordinary gravitational theory.
Ordinary gravitational theory is Riemannian geometry.
It follows from the principles that I laid out.
And gamma r m is equal to gamma m r.
You know...
So it's just the gamma that's the Christoffel symbol,
not the gamma.
The gamma.
You know,
doing the derivative
in these Gaussian normal coordinates,
which are almost flat,
or as flat as can be,
and then treating it as
an object in its own right,
it is very,
very similar to what we do
in gravitational theory
when we evaluate something in a freely falling frame
and then,
for example,
in a freely falling frame,
we calculated how light moved across an elevator.
And then we transformed it
to the frame of reference
in which the elevator was accelerating.
Okay.
That's closely related to the operations we're doing here.
We calculate something because we know how to do it
in coordinates which are as flat as possible.
That would be a freely falling frame in general relativity.
And then we transform it to any coordinates we like,
accelerated coordinates or anything we like.
And we translate the statement
from one coordinate system to another.
Here,
the notion of variation of
a vector from point to point
is done first in Gaussian normal coordinates
and then it's transformed.
And this is the form that
you'll get for the corresponding tensor.
All right.
We're not going very fast tonight,
so I want to move along.
All right.
Now,
for higher derivative tensors,
we'll need this tonight.
Sorry,
for higher rank tensors,
supposing we have a tensor
with more than one index,
m,
let's say,
n,
and we want to differentiate it,
covariantly differentiate it,
again,
in this case,
along the s-axis.
I don't know why I chose s instead of r.
Here I used r,
but I want to differentiate it along the s-axis.
Does everybody know what I mean d sub r here?
That means derivative with respect to xr.
Derivative with respect to xr.
d sub r.
That's a Gaussian normal?
Hm?
Yeah.
No,
no,
no.
That's in any coordinate system.
In any coordinate system,
d sub r will always mean d by dxr.
No,
but I mean,
in this...
The equation you said,
the Gaussian.
Which equation?
The one you...
The one you were talking about.
This one here?
Yeah.
No,
that's in any coordinate system.
In Gaussian normal coordinates,
this term isn't there.
you just differentiate.
In Gaussian normal coordinates,
everything is easy and ordinary.
The derivative of a vector is just the derivative.
Okay.
In arbitrary coordinates,
there's another term.
Okay.
You can work that out by transforming,
just by doing transformations.
Yeah?
Two things.
When you say that in normal,
Gaussian normal coordinates,
the full-variant derivative is just the derivative,
that's only at the point.
Yes,
yes,
yes.
Only at that point.
Right.
And question.
Are the Christoffel symbols,
are those...
Is that a 2-1 tensor or whatever?
No,
it is not a tensor.
Not a tensor.
This is...
This is intended to be a tensor.
We're going to try to choose
gamma so that this is a tensor.
This we know is not a tensor,
and therefore this cannot be a tensor.
Right.
No.
Gammas are not tensors.
In fact,
they're built up out of derivatives of the metric.
In a coordinate system in which
the derivatives of the metric are zero,
the Christoffel symbols are zero.
But a tensor,
if it's zero in one coordinate system,
is zero in every coordinate system.
So,
they can't be tensors.
And they're not.
Okay.
Let's just,
before we go and figure out what the gammas are,
we're going to work them out.
They're not that hard to work out.
There's a trick.
Let's write this down.
It's the analog of this,
except for every index in the tensor,
there is a term like this.
There is a term for every index,
and I'll show you how it works.
There is a Christoffel term for every index.
So,
for example,
we start out by hiding n.
Let's hide n and pretend
that this was just a vector.
Then we would write that this is
the derivative of t with respect to xs.
That's the first term here.
And then we would put a term gamma s,
n,
m,
let's see what I used here,
smt,
tm.
But now I expose the n here,
and I put it in on both sides.
But I'm not finished.
I have to do exactly
the same thing covering up m.
Cover up m.
I won't try to do it.
But I have another term here,
where m is passive,
n is active,
and so we get gamma s,
Look at the form of it for a minute.
Oh,
minus signs.
Minus signs are wrong.
Same as here.
Minus signs as here.
Notice if I covered up the second index,
t,
m,
n.
If I covered up every place the second index,
it would look exactly like
the covariant derivative of a vector.
If I covered up the first index,
it would look exactly like
the covariant derivative of a vector.
Say it again?
You're right,
this should be m,
t.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Paralleling this over here.
Alright,
notice in one of the terms,
t occurs in the first place,
and in the second term
it occurs in the second place.
So that's the form that the
covariant derivative of a tensor would take.
The rule is the same.
You go back to Gaussian normal coordinates,
and you just differentiate the tensor.
Just derivative.
None of this junk.
And then you transform it to arbitrary coordinates,
assuming that the result here is a tensor,
and this is what you get.
So it allows you to differentiate any tensor.
At the moment,
we're just dealing with tensors with covariant indices.
We'll come to tensors with
contravariant indices at some point.
Alright,
in particular,
let's apply this to the metric tensor itself.
But there's something special about the metric tensor.
In Gaussian normal,
in Gaussian normal coordinates,
its derivatives are all zero.
Yeah?
I'm sure you must have said this,
this is like a really fun little thing.
What's the covariant derivative for?
It's for differentiating things.
It's for comparing things at different points.
What are we going to use it for?
Field equations.
Field equations are going to be differential equations,
which represent our fields.
And they're going to change from one place to another,
but we want them to be
the same equations in every reference frame.
We don't want to write down equations
which are special to some peculiar reference frame.
We want to write down equations which are general,
so that if they're true in one frame,
they'll be true in all frames.
That means they have to be tensor equations,
and that means we have
to know how to differentiate tensors
to get other tensors.
So normally you have a derivative if
you multiply it by the corresponding infinitesimal.
You get the two.
So you can't change the partial derivative.
This is the partial derivative.
This is the partial derivative
with respect to the coordinate xs.
But I mean,
I'm trying to ask,
for the covariant derivative,
is there some differential you
would multiply times the covariant?
Yes,
yes,
absolutely,
absolutely.
Then what is that?
dx.
If you wanted to know how a thing
changes from one point to a neighboring point,
you would just multiply it,
multiply this by dxs.
But isn't that what the partial derivative is?
No,
no,
no.
I'll say it again.
The point is that the
components of the vector may change
even if the vector doesn't.
Or that,
right,
we have to keep that in mind.
So this is,
right,
but we'll see some examples about how it works.
Is representing effectively a distortion of the,
an out-of-flat distortion of the coordinates?
Yeah,
yeah.
It's an out-of-flat,
that's right,
it's an out-of-flat distortion of the coordinates.
It's there even in flat
space if you choose funny coordinates.
That's an important point.
It's there even in flat
space if you choose funny coordinates.
In fact,
if you choose any coordinates
in which the derivatives of the GMNs are not zero,
in which the coordinates,
you know,
vary from point to point in funny ways,
this will be there.
This is not really a feature necessarily of curved spaces,
it's a feature of curved coordinates.
Now,
okay.
So because the metric tensor is constant,
or at least has zero
derivative in Gaussian normal coordinates,
and the definition of covariant derivative
is to differentiate first in Gaussian normal coordinates
and then take what you get
and treat it as a tensor,
it must mean that the covariant
derivative of the metric tensor is zero.
That's what's going to allow
us to compute the Christoffel symbols.
Alright,
so let's write down that equation.
Here is the form for the different derivative,
the covariant derivative of any
tensor with two lower indices.
So let's apply it to the metric tensor itself.
ds of GMN is equal,
first term,
dG MN by dXS minus gamma T S M G
T N minus gamma T S N G M T.
All I've done is rewritten this equation,
and now I'm going to add that the covariant derivative
of the metric tensor is equal to zero.
Why?
Because the ordinary derivative
is zero in Gaussian coordinates,
in Gaussian normal coordinates.
Alright,
now,
let's write the same equation,
except permuting the indices,
interchanging S and M and so forth.
This is the equation for differentiating
with respect to S of GMN.
By inspection,
why am I doing this?
I'm doing this because I want
to get as much information out here
about things like this as I can,
and then try to see if there's
any way that I can manipulate the equations
to get to isolate and figure out what gamma is.
So it's,
you know,
people who are experienced at this sort of thing
look at it and say,
I know what to do.
If you don't know what to do,
I'll tell you what to do.
You do it once,
and then when your friend comes and asks you,
how do you find the Christoffel symbols,
you'll say,
I know what to do.
I'm experienced.
Okay,
so you do the same thing,
except now,
I'm going to interchange S and M.
Just permute S and M,
and that means we're going to write down
DM of GSN.
How do I do it?
I just do it by
interchanging or replacing S by M and M by S,
and that gives me derivative of G,
that's SN with respect to XM,
minus,
now,
interchanging S and M here doesn't change anything,
because S and M,
yeah,
from the symmetry here,
so this is the same thing,
gamma SMT,
GT,
let's see,
yeah,
we're just interchanging S and M,
GTN,
and then over here,
so we're interchanging S and M,
so this is gamma MNT,
GST,
and of course,
for exactly the same reason,
this is also equal to zero.
And finally,
there's one last possibility.
Here,
S is the odd man out,
M and N go together.
Here,
M is the odd man out,
S and N go together.
And the last one is DN of GSM,
and let's see,
I think I'll just copy it down,
equals D by DXN of GSM minus gamma SNT,
GTN,
no,
GTM,
minus gamma MNT,
MNT,
GST,
and that's equal to zero.
Now you stare at this for a few minutes.
You ask,
how can I either add these,
subtract these,
or do something clever that will isolate
only one of these terms with the gammas,
and then,
you know,
you can't do anything about it.
So I'll do this.
So that I don't have a horrible bunch of equations,
but basically only one equation.
So I'll tell you what to do.
Call this equation three,
call this equation two,
and call this equation one,
and add equation three to two,
and subtract one.
And we'll see what happens.
We'll see what happens.
First of all,
of course,
we will get these derivatives.
We'll get this derivative,
plus this derivative,
minus this derivative.
So let's put them down.
On one side of the equation,
I'm going to transpose all of
this junk to the other side.
Okay,
so on the left side of the equation,
we will get
DNGSM
plus DNGSM,
no,
DNMG,
ah,
ta-ta-ta-ta-ta.
DGSN
M,
that's this one,
and the last one is minus GMN,
sorry,
derivative,
GMN.
That's this plus this minus this,
or this plus this minus this.
Now,
how about on the other side?
Let's see,
there may be some things which cancel.
Let's hope there's things which cancel.
This comes with a minus sign,
this comes with a plus sign,
this comes with a plus sign.
So,
this and this are the same,
but they cancel because of the opposite sign.
No,
this and this are gone.
They are gone.
What else is gone?
GTSN,
ah,
here it is.
This one and this one come with opposite signs,
so they are gone.
We're left with two terms,
but they're the same.
So,
we're in luck.
We can write that this is equal to
twice,
we need over to the right hand side,
twice gamma MN,
T GST.
Well,
we still have,
we still don't,
we're still not there.
We would like to get gamma MN by itself.
Trying to find out what the gamma,
what the Christoffel symbols are.
That's our goal.
Figure out what they are in
terms of derivatives of the metric.
We're almost there.
First of all,
we can see that if all
the derivatives of the metric are zero,
the Christoffel symbol must be zero.
But how are we going
to get rid of this GST?
And the answer is,
GST has an inverse.
Basically,
you can just take this over to the other side,
but replace it by the inverse matrix.
So,
first of all,
let's put a one half.
And now,
put a bracket around this,
and take this GST over to the other side,
except in its inverse matrix.
So,
you can see that the
GST is in the inverse form.
And this is the correct formula.
This is the formula for the Christoffel symbol.
It looks pretty simple.
We'll look at it for a moment.
The M and N are symmetric.
Look at it.
M,
N,
if you interchange these two,
and here it's symmetric again,
has one negative term,
oops,
yeah,
one negative term,
two positive terms,
not very complicated.
The problem is there's a boatload of them.
When you think about four dimensional space,
and you let S and T and,
sorry,
and let all of these coefficients
range over from one to four,
there's just a lot of Christoffel symbols.
And it's that which makes
doing calculations in general relativity
a very tedious business.
Intrinsically,
there's nothing hard about it.
But,
in fact,
doing a calculation in some
sort of general relativity context
usually fills page after page
after page of nothing more complicated
than just computing these
derivatives and putting them together.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
I'm sorry,
I missed why all these equations are equal to zero.
Okay,
I'll say it again.
G is constant,
has zero derivatives in Gaussian normal coordinates.
I can't get that.
Oh,
yeah,
at that point.
All of this is at that one point.
Yeah.
But,
once it's true at one point,
it's true at every point.
To derive it at any point,
you go to Gaussian normal coordinates at that point.
So you say,
I want a formula appropriate to a particular point.
I go to that point,
use Gaussian normal coordinates,
and find out that this is what gamma is.
But once you know it at any point,
it's true at every point.
So this is the connection between gamma
and the derivatives of G at every point.
The thing is that this is not a tensor.
It's not a tensor,
and so it can be
zero in one frame of reference
and not zero in others.
For example,
in Gaussian normal coordinates at the point,
at that point,
this is equal to zero,
but in some other coordinate system,
it's not.
Um,
even more,
take ordinary flat space.
In flat space,
you can find coordinates
in which the G's are constant everywheres.
In flat space.
But you can also find other
coordinates in which they're not constant.
Polar coordinates,
the G's are not constant.
In Cartesian coordinates,
they are constant.
The Christoffel symbols can be non-zero
even if the space is flat.
In fact,
they generally are.
They are in polar coordinates.
Question?
Yeah.
Just to clarify,
do you represent the metric that
G has a 2x2 matrix in this?
Not a 2x2,
an nxn,
or a 4x4,
or whatever it is.
Whatever it is,
but here you're on the,
well,
whatever it is,
it's 4x4,
nxn.
Um,
that's clear,
but what is the Christoffel symbol?
Is the Christoffel symbol also nxn?
No.
It's nxnxn.
It's got three indices.
nxn,
now it's nxnxn,
but there's some symmetry.
So there's 40 components to it.
It has 40 components.
Everything always has 40 components.
m and n,
if you fix t,
fix t,
then gamma mn has 10 components.
Same 10 components for a symmetric tensor.
And then you let t run over all four components,
and that gives you 40.
So there are 40 independent Christoffel symbols.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
I just want to make
sure I understand what you said.
I agree that you proved
that at that one particular point,
and it's true at all points,
but for each point that you do it,
you have to use a different G.
You have to use the G
that's appropriate for the Gaussian normal coordinates.
No.
You have some coordinates,
which are general coordinates all over the place.
And I want to know
how to differentiate at that point.
So at that point,
I go to Gaussian normal coordinates.
I do my differentiating,
and then I relate it back to the coordinates
that are general coordinates which cover the whole space.
At each point,
at each point,
this is what you do.
With this formula.
No.
You take your curved coordinates,
whatever they are,
and then you say,
I want to know how
to compare vectors at neighboring points.
So I go to Gaussian normal coordinates at that point,
and it tells me how
to compare them at that point.
Here's what it tells me to do.
And those Gs are the Gs associated
with the Gaussian coordinates at that point?
No.
They're the Gs that are associated with any coordinates.
With Gaussian normal coordinates,
these are zero.
They're all zero at that point.
The derivatives are all zero at that point.
So no.
These are the coordinates that you began with.
You transformed the Gaussian coordinates,
derived all of this,
but then you're finished with it.
You're finished with the Gaussian normal coordinates.
Now you're finished with the Gaussian normal coordinates,
and you go on.
This was just a trick to...
The Gaussian normal coordinates were just a trick
to eliminate locally at each point
the variation of the metric tensor with position.
Right.
Good.
Is this equation the equation that
tells you that a space is flat?
It tells you what?
That your space is flat?
No.
No,
no,
no.
This does not tell you that the space is flat.
This is just...
This just tells you what gamma is.
If gamma is...
I assure you,
if gamma is zero everywhere,
it not only means the space is flat,
but it also means you've chosen Cartesian coordinates.
Didn't we get here by setting the derivative,
the covariant derivative of the metric tensor equal to zero?
And so that by itself is
not enough to tell you flatness.
No.
The covariant derivative of the
metric tensor is always zero.
That's not the same as saying
the metric is constant over space,
the metric tensor.
The statement that the metric tensor itself is constant
would be that the ordinary derivative is zero.
Right.
But the covariant derivative of the metric is always zero.
Why?
Because in Gaussian coordinates,
it's zero.
And if a tensor is zero in one space,
it's one coordinate frame,
and zero in every coordinate frame.
Add one more thing,
that covariant derivatives are tensors.
So this is conceptually tricky.
But at the end of the day,
the rule is calculate your Christoffel symbols
and replace ordinary derivative.
In many contexts,
replace ordinary derivatives,
with covariant derivatives.
You can write your equations in Gaussian normal coordinates,
then they just involve ordinary derivatives.
But if you want the same equations in general coordinates,
then you replace the
ordinary derivatives by covariant derivatives.
That's the rule.
Think about it.
Look,
this requires sitting down and thinking about it,
and understanding what we're doing.
We have not got the curvature yet,
so let's try to get to curvature.
Here we have the definition of...
Now,
let's talk about what curvature is.
It's easiest to start with two-dimensional curvature.
How do we probe for curvature?
Well,
let's draw...
Let's begin by drawing a space which is curved.
This sphere is obviously curved,
but I don't want to deal with a sphere,
I want to deal with a cone,
but not a cone.
But a cone with a round point at the top.
The top of a mountain,
but with the sides being nice and flat.
So that if you're away from
the top of the volcano up here,
I don't know,
it's not a volcano,
it's just a rounded cone.
On the sides here,
it looks cone-like.
At the top,
it's smoothed off,
it's been shaved off and made round.
Okay.
The first statement is,
such a cone is flat
everywheres except up near the top.
To see that,
just take the same space down here,
but continue it so that it
really does form a genuine cone.
Okay,
so now we have a cone.
It only differs from the space that we're talking about
up in this vicinity up here.
Now,
take the cone and slice it.
Slice it down here.
And open it up.
Alright,
this is...
Here's a cone.
Slice it down here.
And open it up.
It's clearly flat.
It's clearly a flat space.
But it's a kind of...
Question?
Okay.
Open it up,
and what does it look like?
It looks like,
depending on the angle of the cone up here,
it looks like a flat space,
but when you cut it and opened it up,
there was a piece cut out of it.
Missing.
A missing piece.
I don't have a scissor.
I should have brought a scissor.
I didn't bring a scissor.
Alright.
Take a piece of paper,
cut it,
cut out a wedge of a given angle,
and then glue it together,
and you make a cone.
And the cone has a tip up here.
The tip is clearly not flat.
But the rest of the cone is flat.
You cannot flatten this.
It's like a coffee filter.
You can't flatten it down on the table
without tearing it.
But if you cut it anywhere,
if you cut it and open it up,
you can lay it out and make it flat.
Scissors?
Hmm?
Okay.
Scissors?
Scissors.
Oh,
a scissor.
A scissor.
Oh.
Okay.
But now I have to cut my notes.
If you have a piece of paper,
somebody have a piece of paper,
we can do it.
Alright.
I've cut out a certain angle,
and now when I sew them together
or glue them together,
in this case it made a kind of flat cone.
I could wear it as a hat.
Okay?
If I cut out a bigger angle,
I'll make a more acute angle
at the top of the cone.
For example,
I can cut out a large angle.
I can cut out a little bit more.
I can cut out a larger angle.
And now when I sew it together,
it makes a pointy cone.
Except I can't really do it because...
Yeah,
I think you get the idea though,
huh?
Yeah.
It makes a pointier cone.
So the bigger the angle that you...
Thank you.
The bigger the angle that you cut out,
the bigger the deficit angle,
it's called the deficit angle
or the conical deficit.
The bigger the conical deficit,
the pointier the cone.
If the conical deficit is a very small acute angle,
it means the cone is very flat on top.
Okay?
All right.
Now,
let's think about...
Let's think about a vector,
a vector field on the space here,
which is constant.
Let's take a vector field which is constant.
What does it mean to be constant?
It means that it's pointing
in the same direction everywhere.
For simplicity,
let's take it to be positive.
It's pointing in this direction.
Something funny over here.
Over here,
it's along this line.
it's practically perpendicular to this line.
But remember,
when this...
When the...
When the cut is identified like this,
the line is the same line.
Let's do it.
Let's take a vector pointing over here,
here,
and here.
And now,
when we sew it together,
we discover that there's a funny jump in its direction.
It's pointing along the cut here,
and it's pointing in some funny direction here,
even though when you open it up,
you see they're all in the same...
Did you see that,
or was I hiding it there?
As you go around,
starting here,
pointing in the same direction
until you get around to
the other side of the cut,
in which case you find that
it's not in the same direction.
As the arrow was over here.
Nevertheless,
when I open it up,
they're all parallel.
So,
the tip of the cone
is such that if you carry a vector around,
when you get around to the other side,
it has been rotated.
It has been rotated
due to the conical deficit at the top.
Exactly the same will be true,
in this geometry over here.
If I take a vector along a given direction,
and I carry it around the mountain
in such a way that it's
always pointing in the same direction
if I opened it up,
by the time I get back to the other side,
it'll be pointing in some other direction.
That is because the top of the cone is curved.
That's the effect of curvature.
The effect of curvature,
a region of curvature,
has the property
that if you take a
vector pointing in the same direction
as much as you can do,
keep it pointing in the same direction
and take it around the region of curvature,
the vector will rotate.
The vector will rotate when it
goes around any region of curvature,
even though you took pains to make sure
that at every point,
you were moving it parallel to itself.
In other words,
you took pains to make sure that the covariant derivative
of that vector was zero,
but nevertheless,
when you came around to the other side,
it had shifted.
There's another way to say this,
which is actually more useful.
Here's the other way to say it.
It's equivalent.
If you have a curved space
and there's some curvature here,
there's some curvature here,
okay,
and you take a vector field
and differentiate it along one axis.
We're going to move it and differentiate it
to take,
you know,
differentiate it along one axis
and then differentiate it along a second axis.
We take the vector,
displace it a little bit,
and then displace it along some second axis.
We will...
the vector will change.
And how will the vector change?
It will change typically by
differentiating the vector along these two axes
in sequence.
You first differentiate the vector along one axis
and then differentiate it along the second axis
and there's a small change in the vector
due to these two derivatives.
So I go along here.
In other words,
if I take the difference of the vector,
of the vector over here and over here,
it consists of two changes,
a change to go from here to here
and a change to go from here to here.
And that change,
the total change in that vector
is proportional to a second derivative.
It would be true in any coordinates.
It would be true in any coordinates
that if you carried a vector
from here to here
and then from here to here
and then compared it with a vector
at this point over here,
what you would be calculating
is the second partial derivative
of the vector,
let's say derivative of Vn,
call this the
xs direction
and the xr direction.
And this would be,
let's see,
which derivative would it be?
It would be
derivative with respect,
it would be
covariant derivative with respect to r,
of the covariant derivative with respect to s,
of the vector and let's say
the mth component of the vector.
This operation says
you move the vector a little bit
along the s direction
and this one then says
you take the difference,
the little derivative,
and move it along the r direction
and the net result
is the change in the vector
going from here to here.
Done covariantly,
which means
that you could have done the same thing
in Gaussian normal coordinates
with just ordinary derivatives.
In Gaussian normal coordinates
you would just be doing this derivative here,
or two ordinary derivatives.
You could have also gone
in the other direction.
You could,
that is to say,
you could have gone first in the
r direction
and then in the s direction
and calculated the way the vector changes
from here to here.
That would be,
that would be
the opposite order of differentiation.
Ordinarily,
and in flat space in general,
these two are equal to each other.
This is just the fact that derivatives,
it doesn't matter which order you take them.
But it's not true in curved space.
In curved space,
this net,
the difference between these two,
these two operations,
can be thought of as taking the vector
around the closed loop.
The difference between these two operations,
taking the vector from here to here
and then from here to here,
minus the opposite direction
is essentially taking the vector
around the little closed loop.
Taking it around the little closed loop,
we discovered that when there's curvature
at the tip of the cone here,
you don't get back to what you started with.
In curved space,
covariant derivatives are not interchangeable.
In flat space,
they are interchangeable.
That's the way we test for whether
a space is flat or not.
We test whether
differentiating tensors,
in particular vectors,
in opposite order,
gives zero.
If the answer is yes,
everywhere is in the space,
for any vector,
then the space is flat.
If we discover
that there are places in the space
where the order of differentiation
gives different answers,
then we know the space has
some kind of
defect in it,
or it has curvature.
It has curvature,
analogous to the top of the mountain.
So,
all we have to do,
and it's a little bit complicated,
but it's not that complicated,
is compute the second derivative
of a vector,
the second covariant derivative of a vector,
in opposite order,
and compare them.
I'll tell you what to do.
You're going to do it.
I'm not going to do it on the blackboard.
It's too late.
It's easy.
It's really quite easy.
It's mechanical.
It's a little bit more complicated.
It's a mechanical operation.
I'll tell you what the steps are,
and I'll tell you the answer.
And it's entirely mechanical.
It's just pure plug-in.
It's too late to carry it out,
and,
uh...
Yeah.
What we're interested in is taking
a vector,
Vn,
the components,
covariant components of a vector,
computing the covariant derivative
in the r direction,
and then differentiating it
in the s direction.
Later on,
we will interchange s and r
and subtract.
All right?
But let's just do this.
This is equal to ds.
Now,
this object over here
is a tensor,
Trn.
It's a tensor,
and we have the rule
for calculating
the derivative of a tensor.
We have a contribution from each
index,
and I'm going to write it down.
I'm going to write down the answer.
I'll write down the...
Let's see.
It's ds of dr...
of ds of drv...
No.
Bop,
bop,
bop.
ds of drv...
drvn...
minus...
gamma rnt...
vt.
I've just stuck in here
the covariant derivative of vn.
So that's what's in this box here,
just this thing over here.
Now we have to differentiate it again
using this formula.
We have a two-indexed object,
and let's see if I can...
Let's see.
I'm going to leave it to you
to calculate.
Let's see.
All right,
I'll write down...
I'll write down one further equation.
It's ds of drvn...
minus gamma pn...
Oh,
brother.
No,
it's getting too late.
I don't want to try to write it down.
I'm going to leave it for you to do.
Just pure plug-in.
Pure plug-in.
You plug in for tmn
this object over here.
Put it right into there.
Or...
right.
Calculate the second derivative,
and then compute the following.
ds dr...
of vn...
minus...
dr ds...
dvn.
That corresponds to the difference
between the two ways
that you could get from here to here
by going through this direction
or that direction.
And I'll tell you what you get.
You get something called R.
It's a tensor.
With three covariant indexes,
one contravariant index,
and it multiplies vt.
Where...
This is pretty easy.
Except that R is a little bit complicated.
And I'll tell you what R is.
sRn t...
equals...
dr...
r...
gamma s...
n...
t...
minus...
ds...
gamma r...
n...
t...
plus...
gamma s...
n...
p...
gamma...
r...
t...
minus...
one more term...
gamma r...
n...
p...
gamma...
s...
t...
Two terms involving derivatives
of the Christoffel symbols
and two terms involving products
of Christoffel symbols.
There's a sum...
Let's see.
There's a sum over p here
and a sum over p here.
The indices...
Take a look at it.
The indices match.
It's a complicated expression
and it's even more complicated
when you remember what the gammas are.
The gammas themselves
are complicated derivatives of g's
and the curvature tensor...
This is the curvature tensor...
the Riemann curvature tensor...
This Riemann curvature tensor
is itself
another derivative
and also products of Christoffel symbols.
Let's see what it has in it.
When you differentiate...
The Christoffel symbol involves a derivative of g.
Differentiating again gives you
second derivatives of g.
Remember,
the second derivatives of g
are the things that you cannot
generally set equal to zero.
The first derivatives of g
you can find frame of reference
where they're equal to zero.
The second derivatives of g you can't.
So by the time you finish calculating
this thing here,
second derivatives of g have come into it
and it is testing out
and feeling out the geometry
a little more thoroughly
than the first derivatives would feel it out.
It's feeling out the second derivatives,
feeling out the coordinate systems
to quadratic order.
So it has second derivatives
of Christoffel symbols
and it has squares or quadratic things
involving first derivatives.
It's a complicated thing
and if I were to actually write it
in terms of the Christoffel symbols
or I were to try to calculate it
for a given metric,
it can fill up pages
and it will fill up pages.
But conceptually,
what it's doing is just
calculating the difference in a vector
if you transport it around here,
keeping it parallel to itself
until it comes around
all the ways around.
A little change in the vector
and going in a loop.
And this is the curvature tensor.
The curvature tensor,
as I said,
it's complicated to calculate.
But you can calculate it.
You can put it into a computer
and you can ask the computer,
is it zero?
In fact,
if the computer...
It's good if you have a computer
that can do algebra.
And if you have the metric
in some algebraic form
or you have the metric
in some mathematical form,
you can do these operations
and then test out whether this
curvature tensor is zero everywheres.
If the curvature tensor is zero everywheres,
all components of it,
the space is flat.
Now,
we'll study the curvature tensor
a little more.
But as I said,
it's a complicated thing.
But the main thing about it
is that it tells you whether the space is flat
and if not,
how unflat it is.
It is closely related to a quantity
in gravitational physics.
Can you guess what it is?
It's a local quantity which tells you
that the space is not flat.
So it must be something telling you
whether there's really a gravitational field
present or not.
Tidal forces.
It's exactly related to tidal forces.
Those things which in a gravitational field
squeeze one way,
stretch the other way.
That's what these things are.
And in fact,
they really are the tidal forces.
Tidal forces are represented
by the curvature tensor.
Now,
you can sort of see something like that
if you were to imagine...
Yeah.
Imagine...
Imagine you have,
again,
this kind of conical geometry.
It doesn't have to be conical geometry,
but something which is flat far away.
Yeah,
let's say it's flat far away.
Nice and flat far away.
And somewhere in the center,
it has a bulge so that it's curved.
Now you take some object out here.
It's a thing living in flat land.
It's two-dimensional.
You take some object that might be composed
of a bunch of links.
It might be a bunch of triangles
connected together,
links.
And then you start moving it.
As you move it in the flat region,
nothing happens to it.
It's perfectly happy.
It doesn't get stretched.
It doesn't get distorted.
It doesn't get deformed.
It doesn't get squeezed one way
and stretched the other way.
But now what happens when you try to move it
into the curved region?
When you try to move it into the curved region,
it simply can't follow the curvature
without having to stretch its length.
It has to follow the metric properties
of the curved space.
And in particular,
if you go around
a little closed loop in this space of links here,
what you're doing is sampling
this double covariant derivative here.
And what you're going to find out is that
when you go around a little closed loop,
some angle shifts from what it would have been
in the previous space.
So this is the flat space.
The angle shifts,
the length shifts
when you try to push this up into here.
It gets stressed.
It gets deformed,
it gets stressed,
it gets stretched and so forth.
And the measure of how much it gets stressed locally
is exactly this curvature tensor.
This curvature tensor is telling you
how the system gets deformed
as it moves up into the region of curvature.
That's why it's connected with tidal forces.
So it really is an important property.
If you're in a region where there's curvature,
you feel it.
You feel it as a distortion.
If you're in a region of a gravitational field,
let's say a uniform gravitational field,
uniform gravitational fields don't have curvature.
And that's why in free fall,
in a perfectly uniform gravitational field,
you simply feel nothing.
Okay,
so the next time we will
enter into gravity land,
we will talk about
what you have to do to change
from Riemannian geometry to Einstein geometry.
And then we will study a particular example.
The particular example is the Schwarzschild geometry.
The Schwarzschild geometry is the geometry
of a black hole or
a star or any gravitating mass.
And see what we learn.
We've left out one subject that was in my notes
for tonight.
And it has to do with geodesics.
But I guess we'll have to do that.
But we'll do that after we start thinking about gravity,
real gravity a little bit.
Okay,
I wish I had a way to make this
fewer indices,
but I don't.
Yeah?
In the first question,
she says that one of the differences between
an accelerating object
and a gravitational field is that
the gravity is privately in the form of a dot.
Yeah.
Do you apply that when you're,
you know,
trying to analyze a
so an object is not in a curved space
but a flat space?
And that's the fundamental difference
between accelerating objects
and not your gravitational field?
Please.
The difference between looking at an object
in free fall from
an accelerated coordinate system
or an accelerated frame of reference
and a non-accelerated frame of reference.
Or looking at a system
which has a genuine gravitational field on it.
In other words,
you can simulate
what looks like a gravitational field
for many purposes
by just an accelerated frame of reference.
But it won't cause tidal forces.
If you have a real gravitational field
made by real matter out there,
then it produces tidal forces.
And if there are tidal forces,
it means that there's something real going on.
It's not just a coordinate transformation.
So you can't tell the difference
between an accelerated reference frame
and a gravitational field?
Yeah.
Except for the uniform field.
Well,
there are no really,
there are no uniform gravitational fields.
The real gravitational field of the Earth
looks like this.
It's not uniform.
It produces tidal forces.
It varies from place to place.
There's no such thing as a
real uniform gravitational field.
There's an approximation.
An approximation near the surface
of a very big planet
over a relatively small solid angle.
The gravitational field looks approximately uniform.
Now,
there's another thing to say about it.
Tidal forces have much less effect
on small objects than on large objects.
You can see that also is true of curvature.
If I have a very,
very small object here,
and I move it around,
if it's much,
much smaller
than the scale on which things vary,
then it won't experience any great deformation.
If you have a large object
and you move it around,
it will experience deformation
because different parts of it
get stressed differently.
It's the same thing.
Tidal forces have very small effects
on very small objects.
A bacteria falling onto the surface of the Earth
would experience essentially no,
well,
free-falling,
would experience no tidal force
worth speaking about,
whereas the 2,000 mile man
would be crushed by the tidal force
as he falls toward the Earth.
So,
when you speak about
the strength of tidal forces,
you have to discuss how big an object
you're talking about.
And the same thing is true here.
When you speak about the effect of curvature
on an object moving around in this space,
again,
it depends on the size of the object
that you're talking about.
And this correspondence is not accidental.
It's literally the same thing.
You have to calculate the curvature temperature
at every point.
Is it technically still an infinite problem?
Yeah,
it is.
But,
you know,
very often,
very often you'll be presented
with the metric tensor in some analytic form.
There'd be even a formula for it.
And with a formula,
you can differentiate the formula
and everything becomes,
you know,
some analytic function
that you can calculate
when you look at it.
If it's zero,
it's zero.
You're right.
If you were just given numerically
the metric tensor,
you were just given a bunch of numbers
at every point,
you know,
a huge,
big
spreadsheet
filled with loads and loads of numbers,
you would have to check the curvature tensor
at every point.
And that is,
you know,
as complicated as anything else.
So,
where this is useful,
there's situations where you know the metric
in some analytic sense,
in which you can calculate the derivatives,
subtract them,
do all the things you have to do,
and then look at the analytic answer
and see if the analytic answer is zero.
Yeah.
Right.
So,
in that sense,
it's,
the problem is,
it's not as bad as having to look
at every possible metric
and see whether you can make it,
you have to look at every possible metric
at every possible point.
That's,
this is,
this is better.
This is not as hard as every possible metric.
Right.
Every possible coordinate system is what I meant.
Every possible coordinate system
at every possible point,
until you find one which expresses the metric
as being flat,
this is easier.
You calculate this one thing,
and you compare it from point to point.
Okay.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.