Stanford University
Okay.
All right,
let's talk about time-like,
space-like,
and light-like.
For that,
we just go back to special relativity.
Let's spell out what that means.
And special relativity is a metric.
We've discussed this metric many times.
We call it proper time.
d tau squared is the square of
the proper time of some little interval.
And as you remember,
it's dt squared minus dx squared
minus dy squared minus dz squared.
Okay.
And if we want to
put the speed of light in,
sometimes I'll put the speed of light in.
The reason I put the speed of light in sometimes is
to keep track of what's small and what's big under certain circumstances.
For example,
if you want to study,
if you want to go to the nonrelativistic limit,
the limit where everything is moving slowly,
then it's good to put back the speed of light because it keeps track in that case
of the fact that the speed of light is much bigger than any other velocities in the problem.
So let me put it back.
I'm going to put it in for the moment.
I'll put it in and
take it out under various circumstances.
It goes in like that,
1 over c squared.
And if d tau squared is greater than 0,
now,
of course,
the square of a real
number is always greater than 0,
but d tau squared is not defined
by being the square of a real number.
It's defined by this combination over here.
And it can be positive or negative,
depending on whether the x squared plus the y squared plus the
z squared is bigger than dt squared or smaller than dt squared.
I said the x squared plus
the y squared plus the z squared,
but I meant the x squared over c squared
plus the y squared over c squared and so forth.
But in any case,
if d tau squared is greater than 0,
then the little element here
is said to be t squared.
So it's got more time than it has space,
so to speak.
This part is bigger than this part.
And that can be described
in terms of a light cone.
Remember the light cone?
The light cone looks like that.
And the boundaries of the light cone,
the cone itself,
are the places where dt squared...
Let's,
for the moment,
I don't want the c squared there.
Are...
dt squared equals dx squared
plus dy squared plus dz squared.
That's called light-like.
If dt squared is bigger than dx
squared plus dy squared plus dz squared,
it means the little vector lies
in the interior of the cone,
like that.
It could also be lying in the backward direction.
In either case,
a little interval,
or a vector.
Let's speak about a vector in general.
A vector in general is time-like if its time component is
bigger than the sums of the squares of the space components.
Okay,
that's time-like.
Space-like is exactly the opposite.
It's dt squared,
d tau squared less than 0.
And in that case,
we usually define another quantity,
ds squared,
which is just a negative of d tau squared,
and it,
by definition,
is dx squared plus dy squared
plus dz squared minus dt squared.
It's the same object except for the relative,
or the different,
or the minus sign.
Space-like vectors are ones for which
ds squared is bigger than 0,
d tau squared is less than 0,
and space-like vectors lie outside the light cone.
Finally,
there are light-like vectors.
This is space-like.
And finally,
there are light-like vectors.
And light-like vectors are the ones for which ds
squared equals dx squared plus dy squared plus dz squared.
Those are the trajectories of light rays,
and they lie in the cone.
They lie in the surface of the cone itself.
Those are the three kinds
of vectors that you can have.
Um,
just for a moment,
consider what it would mean
if there were two negative,
sorry,
two positive signs and two negative signs
instead of one positive sign and three negative signs.
Somehow,
this would correspond to two time directions.
Uh,
that doesn't mean anything in physics.
In physics,
there are never two time directions.
There are always one time,
and three space.
Now,
can you imagine a world with two time...
I can't.
Frankly,
I can't imagine what it would
mean to have two different time directions.
And we will simply take the view that,
uh,
that that's not an option.
There is always one time-like direction in the metric here,
and three space-like.
But that doesn't mean that there's
a unique direction which is time-like.
There are many time-like directions,
pointing within this light cone here.
The invariant state of the light cone
is a statement about the metric tensor.
The metric tensor,
we can write this in the form
d tau squared is equal to
g mu nu with a minus sign
dx mu dx nu.
The minus sign is a convention.
It's always defined so that g
mu nu dx mu dx nu
goes with the space-like vectors
having a positive sign here.
Incidentally,
one other thing I'll just remind you.
Um,
the proper time along a trajectory like this
is a measure of what a
clock along a trajectory ticks off.
Proper time is a kind of time.
It's the time read off by a moving clock.
Proper distance,
the s squared,
proper distance along a space-like surface
is distance measured by a meter stick.
So proper distance,
the s squared,
or the square root of the s squared,
really is a distance,
and proper time really is a time.
Uh,
and keep that in mind.
Okay,
so,
uh,
this is our definition of the metric.
And for the case here that we've written,
the metric can be written in terms of a matrix.
And let's see,
the matrix is minus one,
zero,
one,
one.
It's called eta mu nu.
It's like the Kronecker delta,
except it has a minus sign.
Okay,
this thing has obvious,
obviously three positive eigenvalues.
It's a matrix.
It has three positive
eigenvalues and one negative eigenvalue.
And that's the invariant story.
That's the story,
not that there's only one time direction,
but that there is one negative eigenvalue here.
And a metric which would have two negative eigenvalues,
or three negative eigenvalues,
would have more than one time.
And we just don't even think about that.
That's something that physics does not
seem to have made use of,
two negative times.
Okay,
so that's space-like,
time-like,
light-like,
and so forth.
More generally,
it could be in flat space,
but certainly in curved space,
curved space-time,
the metric tensor G,
the metric tensor cannot be chosen
to be equal to this eta symbol here.
It's a general function,
G mu nu of X.
But G mu nu of X
cannot just be any old thing.
At every point,
at every X,
there's a matrix.
At every X,
there's a matrix,
every point.
And at every X,
there must be one negative eigenvalue
and three positive eigenvalues.
Wherever you are,
standing there,
you should experience a world with one time direction
and three space directions.
Or,
more exactly,
one negative eigenvalue and three positive.
Okay,
so what that means,
what that means is that every point in space
has a light cone associated with it.
Now,
I'm drawing it sort of tipped and tilted.
That reflects the fact that the coordinates themselves
might be wavy and curved and so forth.
So,
as you move around,
because the coordinates and also the metric tensor
might be varying from place to place,
the light cone might have an apparent tendency
to look different in different places.
But that is just because,
because,
because as you move around in space,
the metric tensor may change from place to place
and the coordinates change from place to place.
Alright,
so at every point,
there's a light cone.
There's a notion of light,
a space,
a time-like,
excuse me,
time-like vectors inside the light cone,
space-like vectors outside the light cone,
and light-like,
the motion of light rays
along the edge or the cone itself.
The cone is the surface.
When you have an ice cream cone,
the ice cream on the inside
is not part of the cone.
The cone is the surface itself,
the shell.
Okay.
So,
we have to make sure
that when we write a metric
that it does have this property
of the right number of positive and negative eigenvalues.
Incidentally,
it's called,
the property of having a certain number of eigenvalues,
positive and a certain number negative,
is called the signature of the metric.
One says the signature of the metric,
what is the signature of the metric
of ordinary flat space,
the blackboard,
not space-time?
The blackboard has two dimensions
and the signature of the blackboard would be plus plus,
the x squared plus the y squared.
The signature of Minkowski space,
special relativity,
is minus plus plus.
Minus plus plus.
Minus plus plus plus,
excuse me.
Minus plus plus plus.
Okay,
so we have to make sure
that if somebody gives us a metric,
wherever we got it from,
we might get it as a present in the mail,
we might calculate it
from some equations of motion,
some field equations,
always we should make sure
that that metric has signature minus plus plus plus.
And if it doesn't,
it means we did something wrong.
Not only should it have that signature
at every point,
not at some point,
it should have it at every point.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
So there's a single eigenvector
associated with negative eigenvalues?
There is a single eigenvector
associated with negative eigenvalues.
Is that the direction of the light?
No.
Is that related to the cut sheet of the...
No,
no,
no.
There's...
There...
No,
there is not.
there's not a single vector.
There's not a single eigenvector.
Anything...
Anything in this interior of this light cone
is equivalent to everything else
by Lorentz transformation.
You can Lorentz transform this vector
to any other vector.
No,
this...
no,
you see,
that's incorrect.
Supposing I gave you the metric
plus,
plus.
Does that look like it has only one
positive eigenvector?
Sorry,
does that look like it has three
positive eigenvectors and everything else
is not an eigenvector?
No.
Any vector,
if this is the unit matrix,
any vector is an eigenvector with plus one.
Here it's true that...
You'll work this out.
Any time-like vector is an eigenvector
of this matrix with eigenvalue
minus one.
Any space-like vector is an eigenvector
of this metric with plus one.
And any light-like vector is an eigenvector
with zero.
Okay,
you can check that.
That's something to check.
Okay.
This is sort of my question,
which is,
I'm trying to understand the shape
of each of those light cones.
This is the general relativity case.
How that relates to...
Why they get different shapes
and are totally different?
Well,
all right,
let's...
Let's take this...
Let's take the...
Good.
Let's take this light cone over here.
This light cone with x,
y,
z,
t coordinates
defined in this way,
the light cone is a 45-degree cone
with the generators of the cone,
the lines in the cone here,
at 45 degrees.
If I were to multiply,
let's say,
dt squared by some number,
let's...
Now,
let's divide this here.
it's the same space.
It's exactly the same space.
It just corresponds to changing the x coordinate
from x to x divided by c.
Okay?
All right.
But if I now drew the light cone
in the coordinates x and t,
it would look like this.
If c was large,
it would be squashed.
That's just reflecting the fact
that light moves with the speed of light,
and so if c is large,
light moves a long way in those coordinates.
Same space.
I have not changed the space,
just changed the coordinates,
but by changing the coordinates,
I can squash the light cone,
I can even tilt the light cone,
I can do all sorts
of things to those light cones.
It does not reflect a real change in the geometry.
All right.
Now,
since we have just arbitrary coordinates,
that we're dealing with here,
we could,
for example,
have this speed of light here
depend on position.
If it depended on position,
it wouldn't change.
We could have it depend on position.
Then the metric would have some funny position dependence,
and the metric,
as you moved from one place to another,
would go from looking this way to looking that way.
So it's a pure coordinate issue,
whether it looks one way or the other.
But the invariant statement
is that there are space-like vectors,
time-like vectors,
light-like vectors,
and the boundary between the space-like vectors
and the light-like vectors is a cone.
I have one comment.
I think the previous question actually was valid.
I think there is only
one direction of eigenvector for time,
and if the space-like eigenvector is a 3D space,
but time would be just one.
No.
The point here is that
that eigenvector is not a tensor.
It transforms under Lorentz transformation.
Let's see.
And for eta,
how about if the eigenvector would be 1,
0,
0?
Yeah.
I didn't want to get into it.
You're right.
But let's come back to it.
Let's come back to it.
I want to get through to
the metric of a black hole today,
and I didn't want to spend it all on this.
Let's come back to it.
One eigenvector,
three...
One positive eigenvalue...
Sorry.
One negative eigenvalue,
three positive eigenvalues.
This metric transforms under
Lorentz transformations into itself.
It transforms under Lorentz transformations into itself.
So if I do a Lorentz transformation,
we come back to exactly the same metric,
and that's the important issue here.
All right.
I told you what the rule for
a geodesic was last time or time before.
It's that the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector is 0.
As you move along,
it moves parallel to itself.
I'm going to give you a different definition tonight,
which in many ways is more useful.
But let me first write down the original definition.
d second x mu by d tau squared.
That's the tangent vector is dx mu d tau.
This is the derivative of
the tangent vector along some curve,
and...
Should be plus or minus.
I think plus mu sigma rho dx sigma...
d tau dx rho by d tau.
That's the definition of a geodesic.
But there's another definition which
is many times more useful.
It's the analog of the definition
of a geodesic in ordinary space.
In ordinary space,
it's the shortest distance between two points,
or better yet,
stationary distance between two points.
Stationary distance between two points defines...
defines a geodesic.
And so another way of writing
this is to say we extremalize
or we make minimum...
Let's take the case of ordinary space,
ordinary blackboard or a curved version of the blackboard.
We calculate the distance between two points.
We're interested in the
geodesic connecting those two points.
The geodesic connecting those two points.
Calculate a curve.
Take a curve and calculate its distance.
What is its distance?
Its distance in ordinary space would
be for each little element of it,
we have ds squared equals g,
let's say,
mn dxm dxn.
Now I'm talking about space and not space-time.
We'll come back to space-time in a moment.
That's ds squared or ds is
just the square root of that.
In other words,
Pythagoras'
theorem.
Okay,
that's the distance
along a little piece of geodesic here.
And then we just add,
not geodesic,
curve.
Then we add them all up.
And to add them all up,
we just do an integral.
That integral sign just means add them all up.
Or add them all up,
let the distances go to zero,
add them all up,
and that's equal to the
total distance between those two points.
The rule is to make that as small as possible,
to make it extremal.
We learned when we studied
classical mechanics how to do that.
We learned when we studied classical mechanics
that this is a problem in the calculus of variations.
It's a problem analogous to
minimizing the action for a particle.
In other words,
we could think of this
as the action for some kind
of particle moving between here and here,
and then extremalize this,
or make it stationary,
is the rule for calculating the geodesic.
What kind of equations do we use?
This,
Jim,
you know,
is a function of x here,
of course.
What is the equation called that tells
you how to minimize a thing like this?
It's called the Euler-Lagrange equations.
It's Lagrange's equations for a Lagrangian
which is derived from this action.
Think of this as an action for
a particle going from here to here.
Minimizing it is like minimizing
a principle of least action.
When you go from the principle of least action
to the Euler-Lagrange equations,
the principle of least
action turns into differential equations.
Typically,
it turns into F equals m a type of equations.
Going from here to here
is exactly that operation.
Here's an action.
Here's a thing to minimize.
Here's the solution to it in
the form of a differential equation.
In fact,
it sort of looks like acceleration is equal to something.
The something is kind of like a force.
Okay,
so let's come to the real problem
where we're not interested in distance but in proper time.
In proper time,
if I want to calculate the
proper time between the two points,
space-time points,
I do exactly the same thing.
Exactly the same thing.
Except there's a minus sign here.
And that's equal to the proper time
between point one and point two in space-time.
Point one,
point two in space-time,
and there it is.
That quantity is the thing...
Do you maximize it or do you minimize it?
Anybody know?
You minimize it.
Yeah,
you minimize it.
Uh...
Sorry.
You mind?
Let's see.
Um...
Do I have the sign right?
Let me get the sign right.
Yes.
Okay.
Now,
let's suppose this really corresponds
to the motion of a particle
that starts at the space-time point
and ends at the space-time point.
The action depends on one more quantity.
It depends on the mass.
And the actual action...
Let's,
uh...
The actual action...
is equal to minus the mass
times the proper time between points.
This is definition.
The mass...
Putting the mass in there,
we'll find out,
is important
for thinking about energy and so forth.
But the minus sign is strictly definition.
You'll see where it comes in as we go along.
Minus the mass times this thing here.
And,
in fact,
the action,
I think,
is typically...
Yeah,
it's minimized.
It's minimized.
Typically minimized
for a particle moving on a trajectory.
Okay,
what do we do with this thing?
This thing is a completely unrecognizable object.
You're probably saying to yourself,
first of all,
not only do I not know how to
calculate,
how to deal with it,
to do anything with it,
I don't even really understand what it means.
What does it mean to
have a square root of something
times dx dx an integral?
The kind of things we usually understand as integrals
have a d-something,
one d-something and a function,
right?
Some function and a d.
It could be a dt.
It could be a d-time.
But normally we don't see funny things like this
with square roots of dx dx.
All right,
so this is easy to explain.
Let's...
Let's break up the interval
into little time segments.
Little time segments.
Delta t.
Okay.
And let's divide here each one of the...
or dt.
Let's divide each one of these dx's by dt.
By dt.
Some of these dxm's might in fact be dt's.
dt is...
or t is one of the four coordinates.
What happens if we have a dt dx?
We just call it one.
What happens if we have a dx dt?
We call it the velocity.
Right?
We call it just the ordinary velocity.
Now I did something here.
I can't get away with just dividing things by dt,
but I've divided by dt squared.
So I take...
And on the outside I put dt.
Should your indices be Greek?
Hm?
The indices...
Yeah,
the indices can be Greek in space-time.
Now that we're in space-time,
we can put Greek in space-time.
We can put Greek indices in there.
Now that we're in space-time.
And you see what we have.
Each one of these components is equal to one
if it's dt dt,
or it's equal to a velocity along the trajectory.
In other words,
a thing like dx dt
along the trajectory.
These are components of the velocity of a particle,
or just one.
And so each one of
these things has a definite value
along the trajectory,
a certain function of the velocity,
it's a function of the velocity and the position.
So we have a square root of thing,
function of velocity and position,
times dt.
This now has the meaning of a conventional integral
along this trajectory here.
And the integrand...
The integrand here is the Lagrangian.
It is the thing which
plays the role of the Lagrangian.
Action by definition
is equal to the integral of the Lagrangian.
Which is a function of velocities
and positions.
Alright,
so we return to a
problem that we saw all quarter...
What was it,
last quarter?
Two quarters ago.
Two quarters ago,
the problem
of classical mechanics,
how to calculate an equation of motion
from an action.
Now I'm not going to do it here.
What I'm going to do is
tell you that if you work out
the Euler-Lagrange equations,
let me remind you what they are.
The Lagrangian is by definition now
minus m,
square root of minus g mu nu,
of x,
dx mu by d tau,
dt dx nu by dt.
Oh incidentally,
is this...
Is the thing inside the square root...
Is the thing inside the square root
positive so that you can take its square root?
It's got a minus sign here.
It's positive.
This is the proper time
and it's always positive
for a time-like trajectory.
Particles always move on time-like trajectories.
Real particles do not move
faster than the speed of light.
Incidentally,
in case you missed it,
a space-like trajectory is one which is going faster
than the speed of light.
Okay?
So this is always positive inside here
for a time-like trajectory.
This is the Lagrangian.
And what do you do with it?
Yeah?
Why is that item underneath the square root sign
equal to the Lagrangian?
Just because it's in the action equation?
Yeah.
Okay,
by definition.
By definition.
But it's more than definition.
If you now ask to minimize the action,
it is equivalent to applying
the Euler-Lagrange equations to this Lagrangian.
So let's write them down.
Let me remind you what they are.
They're the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to...
Let's call it
x mu dot.
That's the time derivative of x mu.
Oh,
incidentally,
again,
dt by dt is just 1.
Right?
So dt by dt,
just ignore that.
This is a function of the space components
of the velocity and x itself.
All right,
so what do we do?
We take the Lagrangian.
We differentiate it with respect to a velocity.
Then we take its time derivative
and set that equal to dl by dxm.
This is the Euler-Lagrange equations of motion
that we learned all about in classical mechanics.
All right,
so the point is,
if you know the metric,
you can work out an equation of motion
for a particle whose motion will be a geodesic.
Definition of a geodesic,
it minimizes the proper time between two points.
Now,
how does that relate to this definition over here?
Well,
if you work out exactly this equation
with a given metric here,
you will discover that it's exactly this.
It's exactly these equations here.
So there's a little exercise.
Work out the Euler-Lagrange equations
and show that they are the same
as requiring the trajectory
to satisfy this equation here.
It is generally true that this is
a much easier thing to work with
and we're going to do it tonight.
We're going to work out some equations of motion
for particles in a particular metric.
We'll work it out.
We'll work it out and see how it works.
And the metric will be everybody's favorite metric,
the Schwarzschild metric.
Okay,
let's now come to the problem
of studying the motion of a particle
or studying the metric and the motion of a particle
in a real gravitational field,
the gravitational field of the sun,
the earth,
or a black hole,
or whatever you have.
In other words,
a massive object,
a massive spherically symmetric object.
And we're outside the mass of the object.
We're far away from the mass of the object
and we're interested in the metric of space in there.
Okay,
so first I'm going to write a formula
and then we're going to check
and see that this formula
for a metric really does make sense
in the sense that it would give rise,
using these equations of motion,
it would give rise to something that looks very,
very familiar,
namely Newton's equations
for a particle moving in a gravitational field.
At least when you're far away from the gravitating object
where the gravitation is fairly weak.
All right,
so here's going to be the metric
we're going to write down.
Let's first start with flat spacetime.
That's just going to have dt squared.
Minus one over c squared dx squared.
And now dx squared stands for dx
squared plus dy squared plus dz squared.
So I won't write them all down.
Now,
that would be flat space
and we expect that as we go very,
very far
from the gravitating object
that the spacetime looks flat
if we go far away.
But now we know that
the gravitating object does something to spacetime.
And so this shouldn't be exactly right.
Let's put in here one.
That will be there when you're very far away.
And now let's put in something else
and we'll call it plus,
I think,
plus or minus?
Minus,
minus,
minus.
One plus,
yeah,
one plus.
Plus twice u of position.
u is a function of position
divided by c squared.
Times dt squared and leave
everything else alone for the moment.
Don't change anything else.
One plus two u,
and I'll tell you what u is right now.
It's the gravitational potential
due to this object.
Let's check
that
as long as our particles are moving slowly,
the geodesic equation here,
the Lagrangian equation of motion,
just becomes Newton's equation
for a particle
moving in a gravitational potential u of x.
Alright,
let's see what we get.
We have a Lagrangian.
And now we can write out what it is.
It's minus m
times the square root.
Okay.
Let's go back to this form over here.
Minus
one plus two u over c squared
dt squared.
And then I think plus
one over c squared
dx squared
plus dy squared plus dz squared and so forth.
Let's just put,
let's just call it x squared.
dx squared.
Okay.
That's,
no,
sorry.
The,
um,
the action,
the action
is,
the action is this thing,
right?
Square root of g mu nu dx mu
by dt,
by dt.
There we are.
Dt.
I simply wrote down what's here.
g mu nu dx mu dx nu.
That's one plus two u over c squared
dt squared
divided by dt squared
plus one over c squared dx squared by dt squared.
If you don't understand what I wrote,
tell me now.
Okay.
dt squared by dt squared,
that's just one.
So that's trivial.
And the x squared
by dt squared,
we can just call that x dot squared.
There are three of them,
and they,
and we have to add them.
x dot squared plus y
dot squared plus z dot squared
in there.
That's our action.
Now,
next step.
Let's work out,
now before we work it out,
let's approximate it.
Let's approximate it.
We can work this out as it is.
But what I'm interested in is very slow motion.
I'm interested in very slow motion.
And because I'm interested in slow motion,
I'm interested in slow motion because I want to
show that this really does give rise to Newton's equations
in the non-relativistic limit.
The non-relativistic limit is one in which
c is taken to be very large.
Now,
I could just erase anything with
a one over c squared in it.
But boy,
I would kill the,
I would kill everything then,
right?
I would kill everything.
I left something out here.
It's minus m c squared.
If I'm really putting c's in,
the action has an m c squared in it.
Okay.
An m c squared.
It's just dimensions.
Just multiply it by c squared.
All right,
there's our action.
And now let's expand it for small quantities.
What is it?
It's,
um,
I'm sorry,
I'm having,
I'm getting confused tonight.
This is bad.
Is this really minus here?
Um,
No,
it's plus.
And this is minus.
Now it's correct.
Okay,
how do you,
what do you do with a thing like this
if you want to approximate it when c is large?
Well,
you write the thing inside the square root
as one plus something small.
Something small has a one over c squared in it.
And then what is it?
It's two u
minus x dot squared
times minus m c squared.
Then you use the binomial expansion.
Use the binomial expansion,
square root of one plus a small quantity.
There's just one plus a half a small quantity.
Okay,
so this becomes minus m c squared
times one
plus one over two c squared
times two u minus x dot squared.
Equals.
Finally,
we look at this.
It has a constant
minus m c squared.
A constant in the Lagrangian makes no difference.
The only thing you do with the Lagrangian
is you differentiate it.
So when you differentiate this term,
it makes no difference.
The rest of it here has a term
minus c squared cancels,
we get,
and the two cancels,
and we get minus m times u.
Then the other half of it has m c squared
divided by two c squared.
That's plus m over two x dot squared.
That's the Lagrangian if you expand it out
to small quantities in the non-relativistic limit.
Notice what it has.
It has this constant,
which is irrelevant.
It has a conventional kinetic energy,
one half m v squared,
and then it has a potential energy.
It has a potential energy,
this is just a function of x.
It has a potential energy which
we get to choose.
We choose whatever we like for the potential energy there.
Incidentally,
for a gravitational problem,
the potential energy of a particle
is always proportional to its mass.
So here you see it,
the potential energy is proportional to its mass.
If you work out from this,
if you work out from this,
the equations of motion,
of course what you're going to get
is just Newton's equations
for a particle in a force,
in a gravitational field,
a gravitational field u.
What will the equations be?
They will be x double dot,
m x double dot is equal to
minus m d u by d x.
That's the force.
Here's the acceleration,
and the mass cancels.
Okay,
so the main point here was
that this action,
which is equivalent to the geodesic here,
is easily worked out
just by thinking of the Euler-Lagrange equations,
and it's even easier to work out
if you're in the non-relativistic limit
where you just say c is very,
very large,
one over c squared is very small,
and just expand the square root.
All right,
so that's a nice easy thing to see,
but the important point here
is that what we learned out of this
is that for some first approximation
in small quantities,
g naught naught minus g naught naught
is approximately,
perhaps exactly,
equal to one plus twice
the gravitational potential
divided by c squared.
So here's what we've learned.
We've learned that the metric,
now of course there may be additional things in here
which are even smaller than one over c squared.
If,
for example,
there were one over c fourth
or one over c sixth or anything like that
in any of these terms here,
they would not be important
in this non-relativistic limit.
So we can't say with complete confidence
that g naught naught is one plus,
twice the potential energy of a particle
divided by c squared,
but we can say that must be true
to the first order in small quantities.
Small quantities means one over c squared.
All right,
so let's write that down now.
Let's write down what we know.
Let me rewrite it again.
But what I want to do is for u,
we will put
the mass of the sun,
the sun is at the center,
the mass of the sun
divided by the distance to the sun
times Newton's constant
with a minus sign.
This is the standard gravitational potential energy,
the mass of the gravitating object,
g,
divided by the distance away,
u of x.
And now we can write down
our first guess
at the metric of space-time
surrounding a gravitational mass.
Here it is,
dT,
d tau squared,
the leading order is equal to
one minus two mg
over r c squared.
The c squared is from here.
There's a two mg over r c squared d tau,
d,
d t squared minus the x squared
minus the y squared minus the z squared.
That's d tau squared.
And of course plus,
oh,
over c squared,
plus smaller things.
Is that beginning to look familiar to anybody?
You recognize this piece?
Some of you?
Schwarzschild metric.
The Schwarzschild metric or the metric of a black hole.
But not quite.
Let's put c squared r here.
Now,
next,
let's take d x squared plus
d y squared plus d z squared.
That's this piece over here.
That's just the ordinary metric of three-dimensional space.
In this formula over here,
only the time component of
the metric has been fiddled with.
The space-space components of the metric and everything else
have not yet been fiddled with.
They will a little bit,
but not too much.
All right,
d x squared plus d
y squared plus d z squared
is just the usual metric of ordinary flat space.
Let's take flat space and polar coordinates.
Polar coordinates,
three-dimensional polar coordinates.
Three-dimensional polar coordinates are
characterized by a distance,
namely a distance from the center
of the sun in this case,
a distance,
and a pair of angles.
The pair of angles can be
a polar angle and a azimuthal angle.
So let's say,
so let's draw a sphere here.
This is a point on the surface of the sphere.
The sphere is at distance r.
There is an angle from the plane,
from the horizontal plane here.
We could take it to be
the angle from the North Pole,
but I think I'll take it
to be the angle from the equator.
The horizontal plane here is the equator.
The angle from the equator is called theta,
and then there's the azimuthal angle,
that can be measured from here.
That's phi.
Phi.
Okay,
now what is the length element on
the surface of a sphere like this?
Or on the surface of a sphere of radius r?
The length,
the,
or better yet,
what,
how is this metric expressed in polar coordinates?
I'm going to write it for you.
It first of all has a d.
It's d r squared.
Incidentally,
if this were two dimensions,
you would know what to write.
You'd write d r squared
plus r squared d theta squared,
right?
What you would write in two dimensions would be
d r squared plus r squared d theta squared.
And that's there.
That's correct.
It's still the same.
But there's another term.
And the other term is cosine
of theta squared d phi squared.
This is the metric of
ordinary three-dimensional space in polar coordinates.
Two angles and a radius.
d r squared plus r squared times this.
Why are we doing polar coordinates?
Because polar coordinates are the good
coordinates for studying the central force problem.
Polar coordinates are convenient.
You don't want to use x,
y,
and z to study the motion
of a particle in a gravitational field.
You want to use the polar coordinates.
And so we're going to write
this metric in terms of polar coordinates.
And we have it now.
All we're going to do is make one change.
We're going to give this a name.
d theta squared plus cosine theta squared d phi squared.
We're just going to give it a name so
we don't have to write it over and over.
We're going to call it d omega squared.
For no other reason than to not
have to write it over and over.
Okay,
so we now have the metric of ordinary space.
r squared d omega squared.
And that's what goes here.
That's exactly what goes here.
So let's now rewrite.
Question?
Is there a question?
No,
okay.
Let's rewrite this.
1 over c squared d r squared.
That's this.
Minus 1 over c squared r squared d omega squared.
And just keep in mind,
r is just radial distance.
Nothing special.
This complex thing here is just a
metric on the surface of the sphere.
If you keep r fixed
and you move around in angle,
this gives you the contribution to
the metric for moving in angle.
Okay.
Now.
Now there's something terribly wrong with this metric.
Something very,
very wrong with it.
It's fine when you're far away.
But there's something deeply wrong when
you get in close to the center.
What happens when r becomes r squared?
r becomes too small.
When r becomes too small,
not 0,
but when r is positive but too,
but,
but small.
When r becomes small,
this becomes large.
1 minus a large number becomes negative.
This coefficient becomes negative.
These coefficients are also negative.
What happens to the metric when you
move in too close to the center?
It has 4 positive eigenvalues,
or rather 4,
4 positive eigenvalues instead of
1 negative eigenvalue and 4,
and 3 positive eigenvalues.
When you move in too close,
this quantity changes sign.
Where does it change sign?
It changes sign when r is
equal to 2mg over c squared.
In fact,
there's a nicer way to write this.
Let's write it a different way.
Let's write it as r minus
2mg over c squared divided by r.
The thing in the bracket here.
r over r is 1.
2mg over c squared divided
by r is this thing here.
Notice what happens when r gets smaller than 0.
r over r is smaller than 2mg over c squared.
2mg over c squared is just some number,
positive number.
It's some particular characteristic
radius of the black hole.
It's the Schwarzschild radius.
At some point when r moves in toward the center,
this changes sign,
becomes negative.
What happens is the sign here becomes
exactly the same as the signs here,
all negative.
The meaning of that is
we somehow passed into a region
where there are four space directions and no time direction.
That's bad.
That's something we don't want.
That's not a good thing.
What really happens if you study
the field equations of general relativity,
which we're going to do,
we'll do this,
but for the time being let me
just tell you what the right answer is.
The right answer is at
the point where this changes sign,
this one also,
there's nothing here yet,
I haven't given you anything to put here,
just 1 over c squared,
but we're going to put something else here
that has the property that when this one changes sign,
this one also changes sign.
So what happens?
This one turns into a space direction,
but this one turns into a time direction.
The signature of the metric is maintained.
One time-like direction and three space-like directions.
So what can we put
here to make this flip sign
in the same way that this flip sign?
Well,
you could put in 1
minus 2mg over c squared r
in front of the r squared.
So when this one changed sign,
this one changed sign.
That turns out not quite to be the right thing
that Einstein's field equations tell you to do.
Einstein's field equations give a slightly different,
well,
it's a substantially different answer,
but let's see what it says.
It's 1 minus 2mg over c squared r.
So 1 minus 2mg over
c squared r dt squared minus,
now,
1 divided by 1 minus 2mg over c squared r,
the r squared,
minus 1 over c squared r squared,
the omega squared,
minus 1 over c squared r squared.
Alright,
so when we got to the point,
as you move in closer than the Schwarzschild radius,
this changes sign,
but so does this.
Because they both change sign,
the signature of the metric stays the same.
But something very odd has happened.
The thing that we're calling t here
becomes a space-like direction,
and the thing that we're calling r
becomes a time-like direction.
They flip.
Once you go inside that radius,
the coordinate r becomes a time,
and the coordinate t becomes a space direction.
This is not easy to visualize,
but I will give you the tools
to visualize it as we go along.
Something has happened as we
passed in through a certain surface,
the surface being r equals 2mg over c squared.
When you pass inside there,
there's a little bit of a gap,
there's a flip between time and radius.
Radius becomes time,
or becomes a time variable,
and time becomes a space variable.
This is completely mysterious for the moment,
but I assure you we
will explain in some geometric detail
what it is that's happening here.
Cross that line?
Yes.
How much time does it take to cross that line?
Say it again?
How much time?
How much time what?
To cross that line.
Right.
There's two things.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
That's what we're going to do.
We're going to do that.
We're going to do that problem.
We're going to see that to cross that line,
it takes an infinite amount of coordinate time,
but a finite amount of proper time.
So somebody falling with a particle
with a clock in their hand
will say it takes a finite amount
of time to cross that line there.
Okay?
Somebody watching from the outside,
watching that person fall through,
will say it takes an infinite amount of time.
That's a characteristic of this metric,
and that's one of the things
we want to work out tonight.
Question.
Yeah.
What was the motivation for
changing the coefficient on dr squared?
The motivation for changing the coefficient
is to make sure that the metric
stays with a signature plus minus my r,
minus plus plus plus.
Okay?
If this one changes signs,
something has to give.
With one of the other ones,
and the natural candidate is the r here,
that flips its sign.
Okay.
Now first of all,
think about where this is happening.
This is happening at a distance or
a coordinate r equals 2mg over c squared.
c is a huge number.
Right?
c is a huge number and it's in the denominator.
This is a small distance.
This is a small distance,
but it's a small distance that depends on the mass.
It's a small distance that depends on the mass.
For the Earth,
this distance would be about a centimeter.
Okay?
So we don't have to worry about it
in thinking about the gravitation of the Earth.
Question.
What happens to the clock?
It was ticking in a time direction.
Is it ticking in a space direction now?
No.
Is it not ticking?
No,
it's ticking in a time direction.
Clocks don't care about what coordinates you use.
It's ticking in a time direction.
We're going to discover that this
is an artifact of particular coordinates.
There's nothing going on special at this point.
We're going to discover that
this is just awkward coordinates
that make it look like
something as funny is happening here.
A switch of space and time.
There's nothing funny happening there.
And we're going to work out and see exactly why.
But for the moment,
it does look like there's something going on,
c squared,
all the time.
It does look like there's something
going on when this thing vanishes.
When this thing vanishes here,
this thing becomes infinite.
It looks like some terrible
thing is happening to the geometry.
In fact,
the geometry is completely smooth over here.
Nothing special happening.
The light cone is perfectly
healthy in all regions in here.
Nothing funny going on.
But we have to work harder to see it.
This was the form.
This is the form that Schwarzschild derived.
The Schwarzschild of history.
Einstein wrote down some field equations.
Schwarzschild.
And what Einstein knew about them
is he basically knew this piece here.
And he knew some...
Oh,
there's one thing that's important here.
One thing that's important.
Yeah.
Which I neglected to say.
How big is this correction here?
Well,
if I want to estimate how big this correction is,
in a non-relativistic limit,
I want c to be very,
very large.
If c is very large,
then I should expand this one over a small quantity.
This is a very small quantity,
2mg over c squared r.
All right.
And so this is approximately equal to
1 plus 2mg over c squared r
plus corrections.
If you take 1 over 1 minus x,
1 over 1 minus x is equal
to 1 plus x plus x squared.
That's the binomial expansion.
And so the first correction,
if I write 1 over 1 minus 2mg over r,
is 1 plus the small quantity.
The next contribution is 2mg over c squared r squared.
This is typically small.
If you're not too close
to the center of the thing,
if you're at a reasonable distance away,
so that 2mg over c
squared r is equal to 1,
then 2mg over r c squared is very small.
The next terms are even smaller and smaller and smaller.
Notice they're all 1 over c to the fourth,
1 over c to the sixth,
1 over c to the eighth.
So what we're doing here
is we're modifying this term here
also with corrections which are very small.
The next correction here does contribute to
the motion of particles and so forth,
but not in the non-relativistic limit.
The next correction here would be something
of order 1 over c to the fourth,
the x squared,
blah blah blah blah blah,
and 1 over c to
the fourth is very very small.
So as long as you don't get
too close where r is too small,
this correction is pretty negligible.
That's order 1 over c to the fourth.
There should be a c squared here,
I'm sorry.
There should be a c squared downstairs.
Yeah,
even this term,
even this term is small.
Even this term is small
because there are two c squares.
This gets multiplied by another c squared.
So even this is small,
too small to be important.
I don't think I've convinced you
that I can throw this term away,
have I?
Okay,
let's do it again.
This is 1 plus 2mg over c squared r.
Next term is 4m squared g squared over
r squared 1 over c to the fourth,
dot dot dot.
And it all gets multiplied by 1 over c squared.
All gets multiplied by 1 over c squared.
And notice that even the first
correction here is 1 over c squared.
So 1 over c squared is
1 over c to the fourth.
Much smaller than the original term dt squared.
Even these things are small,
but especially the correction to
a small thing is even smaller.
So this is negligible compared to this.
And we simply don't have to worry about it.
For slow particles.
For particles moving much slower than the speed of light.
Okay,
that's,
let's come back to this metric here.
Before we analyze it and see what's going on
at this point where you cross from space to time,
where you cross the horizon of the black hole,
let's use it.
Let's use it and see if
we can figure out how particles move.
Not in the non-relativistic limit,
but let's do better.
Let's see if we can answer how particles move
without taking any approximations.
If we're not going to do any approximations,
incidentally,
we might as well set c equal to 1.
Let's set c equal to 1.
Keep in mind that we set c equal to 1.
We can set c equal to 1.
It's just a choice of units.
And now see if we can see how particles move
in the presence of this metric.
And it's not so hard.
It's just a choice of units.
We can consider two kinds of orbits.
Two kinds of orbits that I
want to work out for you,
or at least I want
to show you how they work.
Circular orbits.
We'll find a little bit
of a surprise about circular orbits.
And then radial orbits.
Radial orbits,
maybe I'll do radial orbits.
I think we'll do radial orbits first.
I think we'll probably run out of time.
We're running out of time for circular orbits.
Which would you rather see,
circular orbits?
We're going to do both.
We'll do both.
One falling radially in.
It's not an orbit.
Just a crash.
A crash.
Here's our object.
Object.
A rocket crashes into it.
And the question is,
the question was already asked.
How long does it take for
that rocket to reach the horizon?
How long does it take
for it to reach the horizon?
Okay.
Is this lecture observer?
Hmm?
We're talking about lecture observer or a rocket that is?
No,
we're going to talk now about the external observer.
The external observer who uses t for time,
whereas somebody falling in in
the rocket uses tau for time.
Okay.
Proper time in the rocket
or coordinate time from the outside,
somebody watching with their clock.
Somebody on the outside watching
this thing with their clock,
uses time t.
Conventional time.
Somebody falling in uses proper time.
Okay.
So we can ask both questions.
And they have different answers,
very different answers.
Okay.
Now,
the main point of this is
to show you how the things work.
So let's go back to
the Lagrangian for the infalling particle,
for the particle.
Where is it?
Let's go back.
Incidentally,
where you start with any such calculation like this,
you start with the Lagrangian for the particle.
Then you work out the Euler-Lagrange equations
or whatever you need to do with it.
And you then solve the equations.
There are tricks.
There are tricks you can do,
and I'm going to show you tricks
that allow you to do the problem.
Okay.
The Lagrangian,
yeah,
the action is minus m.
I'm going to leave the c squared out.
We set c equal to 1 times
the square root of d tau squared.
And the square root of d tau squared,
let's write d tau squared over here,
is equal to,
here it is.
Oh,
here it is,
right here,
d tau squared.
I'm also going to assume that
the particle does not change its angle.
When it comes in,
it comes in along a particular angle.
And we will not have to worry
about the piece of this over here.
We're not moving around an angle.
And so if we're not moving around an angle,
as the particle falls in,
we can say that d tau is equal to
the square root of 1 minus 2mg over r,
dt squared minus 1 over 1 minus 2mg over r.
The r squared.
Let's put this into here.
This is the action in this integral here.
But now to make sense out of it,
I'm going to divide by
dt squared and multiply by dt.
1 minus this.
And now what is this quantity dr by dt squared?
That's just the velocity,
the radial velocity squared.
In other words,
r dot squared.
So this is r dot squared here.
And I have a Lagrangian.
Here's my Lagrangian.
l is equal to minus m square
root of 1 minus 2mg over r
minus 1 over 1 minus 2mg over r
times r dot squared.
The coordinate in this case is r.
And here we have a Lagrangian.
OK.
Fortunately,
this problem is easy.
Or at least it's easy to see what's happening.
Let's not worry about the exact solutions.
Exactly solving it is a little bit hard.
But seeing what happens is easy.
There's always a conserved quantity.
What's the conserved quantity that's always there?
Energy,
right?
Energy is always there.
What is energy in terms of the Lagrangian?
Energy in terms of the Lagrangian is the Hamiltonian.
So I'm going to remind you what the Hamiltonian is.
The Hamiltonian,
the first thing we do is
we calculate the momentum conjugate to r.
What's the momentum conjugate to r?
That's the momentum conjugate to r.
Partial of L with respect to r dot.
Do you remember that?
Partial of L with respect to the
velocity is the momentum conjugate to r.
And if we work that out,
let's see what we get.
That's not too hard.
The square roots are an annoyance.
They're a real annoyance,
but they're not so terrible.
You know,
I don't think I will work them out.
I'll let you work them out.
Partial of L with respect to r
dot is a straightforward thing to do.
You just differentiate with respect to r dot.
And you get p sub r.
What do you do with it?
You multiply it by r dot.
And then you subtract the Lagrangian.
Partial of L with respect to r dot.
You multiply it by r dot.
You subtract the Lagrangian.
And that's called the Hamiltonian.
Or the Engelmannian.
Or the Hamiltonian.
That's the energy of the system.
And you can work it out.
You work it out.
I'm not going to work it out.
Here it is.
H is equal to 1 minus 2mg over r
times the mass divided by square
root of 1 minus 2mg over r
in brackets
times r dot squared,
I believe.
Sorry.
Minus 1 over 1 minus 2mg over r.
r dot squared.
Complicated thing.
It's an ugly thing.
It's a complicated thing.
But it's a definite thing.
And what does it depend on?
It depends on the velocity.
And that's the energy.
What do we know about the energy?
We know that it's conserved.
And so we can write
that this is equal to E.
And that it doesn't change with time.
It does not change with time.
Okay.
Let's see what that says.
That tells us that we can solve for r dot.
We can find out what r dot
is as a function of the energy.
I'm going to write down what r
dot is as a function of the energy.
You just solve for r dot.
You solve this equation.
This is much easier than it looks.
You just square it.
You square it.
You get rid of the square root.
You get an e squared on the left-hand side.
You get the square of this here.
And you get the square of this here.
You turn it over and calculate r dot.
Okay,
let's see if I can find it.
Here it is.
Here's what you get.
It's not at all complicated.
r dot is approximately equal to...
I'll tell you when it's here.
r minus 2mg over...
Oh,
it's easy.
No,
it's not even approximate.
It's exact.
r dot is equal to...
Oh,
very easy.
Yep.
r dot squared is equal to the
energy squared times 1 minus 2mg over r.
r.
Oh,
where's that?
Squared.
Minus 1 minus...
2mg over r.
Cubed.
Divided by the square of the energy.
It doesn't really matter what it is.
It's a definite thing,
but what does matter is what
it does when r is near 2mg.
When r is near 2mg,
something bad happens to it.
r dot is approximately equal to
the square root of r minus 2mg.
r dot squared is equal to 2mg divided by 2mg.
r dot squared is equal to 2mg.
Remember what 2mg is?
mg is the radius of the horizon.
r equals 2mg.
And what this is telling us is
as the particle falls toward the horizon,
its velocity goes to zero as
it falls towards the Schwarzschild radius.
Its velocity gets smaller and smaller.
Instead of accelerating,
it gets smaller and smaller and smaller.
Can we see that from here,
I wonder?
The velocity will be smaller.
Yeah,
the velocity gets smaller and smaller.
So gravity is repulsed here.
No.
1 minus 2mg over r goes to zero.
Hm?
Mm-hm.
It's going to the bottom.
OK.
So let's see what's going on here.
This goes to zero.
This goes to zero as r goes to 2mg.
Ah.
This goes to zero.
So this is zero.
This will go to zero.
The first term here also goes to zero.
And then we'll have in the denominator r
dot squared times 1 over this thing here.
Square root.
So this goes to infinity.
It has to go to 0.
Because keep E constant.
Hm?
It has to go to zero.
Keep E constant.
R has to be.
It has to uptomate zero.
Because zero by zero is something like,
the numerator and denominator has to go to zero.
Yeah.
では、
終わりにして、
カバンの出来上がりを。
This goes to infinity,
right?
So if r dot did not go to zero,
this would be zero over infinity
which would be zero,
but it can't be zero,
it's supposed to be the energy which is conserved.
Alright,
the energy is conserved and so
r dot cannot,
sorry,
the only way to avoid,
to make this be zero
over zero and make any sense
which would be to have r dot go to zero.
But here,
this is,
you could solve the equation,
solve it.
Solve for r dot as a function of e and
m and everything else and this is what you get.
So as r goes to 2mg,
r dot goes to zero.
It's a surprise,
it's a surprise.
You might think the thing accelerates
but instead it slows down
and slows down and slows down.
Now,
can we see why this is?
It slows down,
gets asymptotic,
it's asymptotically slower and slower and
slower and never passes this point.
Never passes that point.
Just asymptotically approaching it.
Takes forever to get to here.
Can we see why this is?
I wonder,
I think we can.
Let's go back to the,
let's go back to the Schwarzschild metric.
Okay,
the Schwarzschild metric is
d tau squared is equal
to 1 minus 2mg over r
dt squared
minus 1 over 1 minus 2mg over r
dr squared.
And let's forget the other piece of it.
The other piece of it is not playing any role.
Now,
how does a radial light ray move?
A radial light ray moves
a radial light ray which is moving in,
let's say,
toward the,
or better yet,
moving away.
Moving away.
Let's think about a light
ray moving away from the object
at distance r.
Either moving away or falling in.
It doesn't matter.
Falling in or moving away.
Okay.
What is a light ray?
A light ray is a solution to the equation
that the interval here,
this little distance here,
is light-like.
Light-like means d tau squared equal to 0.
And our original,
where is it?
Our original light-like means
d tau squared is equal to 0.
So,
a light ray
satisfies,
let's solve this,
we're going to set this equal to 0,
and that will tell us
that dr
is equal to 0.
is equal to dt
times
1 minus
2mg over r.
Now let's do it.
We're going to set this equal to 0.
Now let's multiply
both sides by
1 minus 2mg over r.
That will give us
1 minus 2mg over r
squared.
dt squared
equals dr squared.
Take the square root.
And now divide by dt.
That's a light ray.
That's the fastest thing
that can ever be.
A light ray,
nothing can be faster
than a light ray falling in.
This could be falling in,
dr by dt,
either positive or negative.
This would be an infalling
of a light ray.
Now what do we find?
That as r goes to the
Schwarzschild radius,
what happens to this at the Schwarzschild radius?
This goes to 0.
This is equal to r minus 2mg over r.
And that's equal
to the radial velocity,
r dot,
the magnitude of the radial velocity.
Even a light ray
gets stuck
as it's moving toward the,
is it moving with the speed of light?
No.
Of course it's moving
with the speed of light.
What else could a light ray do?
But the speed of light
has this property
that in these coordinates,
in this particular set of coordinates,
the speed of light
goes to 0 as you get closer and closer.
So nothing,
even including a light ray,
can get past this surface here.
Or so it seems.
In fact,
this is a much easier way to think about it,
than to think about it
It starts going down the speed
right away.
Yeah.
What about when it's far away?
How about when it's far away?
When it's far away,
this 1 is the most important thing.
It's 1.
So when it's far away,
the r dt is 1.
1 here means
the speed of light.
As it starts moving in closer and closer,
it eventually gets to the point
where this goes to 0,
and then the r dt simply goes to 0.
Something odd happens beyond that point.
Something odd happens beyond that point,
and
we're going to work that out.
Okay,
this was...
The problem with general relativity
is the principles are pretty simple,
and the computations are always ugly.
They're always ugly.
They're almost always ugly.
There's nothing nice
about the actual computations.
The principles are simple,
and they give rise to complicated equations.
It's just the way it is.
But if you ask...
Let's have some questions now.
I have one up here.
I've read a thing
that when matter falls into a black hole,
some radiation is given off.
I guess,
at that boundary.
Is that correct?
Well,
I don't know.
Obviously,
if it was right at that boundary,
it wouldn't get anywhere.
Well,
that's what I was about to ask.
So,
I'm thinking,
well,
how can radiation be given off
because it would never reach
the boundary for something like that?
It would never escape from the boundary.
Yeah.
This fact that...
This is the magnitude of the velocity.
The magnitude of the velocity goes to 0
either for ingoing or outgoing radiation.
Let's see,
what do we do here?
We have
an equation that this is equal to this squared
before I took the square root.
Now,
there are two solutions
when I take the square root.
The two solutions when I take the square root
are plus and minus.
The plus solution,
the rdt,
is outgoing radiation.
All right?
Outgoing radiation or outgoing light
moving out,
the radial velocity is positive.
The negative solution here
is light falling in
but in either case
the magnitude of the velocity
goes to 0.
So,
you're right.
If you start a light ray
right at the Schwarzschild radius,
it won't get anywhere.
In fact,
a light ray will just sit
at the Schwarzschild radius.
A light ray
interior to the Schwarzschild
radius will fall in.
A light ray exterior
will go out
but the closer it starts
to the Schwarzschild radius,
the longer it will take to escape.
That's what this is saying.
So,
the so-called
Hawking radiation?
Well,
it materializes
outside the black hole.
It doesn't materialize...
It has to be a little bit outside.
But,
you know,
if it starts out very,
very close,
it will sit there for a very,
very
long time
and then after a very long time
it will be observed to be a little bit away
and then a little more away,
and then go off at the speed of light.
So...
It looks like a photon
with greater than zero
stationary mass.
Why?
The photon if it's falling,
since its velocity
is almost zero,
it looks like a photon
with non-zero stationary mass.
No,
no.
Why do you think it has
non-zero mass?
Oh,
sorry.
Non-zero stationary mass.
It has some mass,
but
it's apparently stationary.
It's apparently stationary.
We're going to find out that
from the point of view
of somebody falling with a photon,
the photon moves at the speed
of light and everybody,
including the photon,
just goes sailing right through.
This is an artifact of
peculiar coordinates at the horizon.
There's nothing really going on
that's showing
that's strange at the horizon.
The Schwarzschild radius is the horizon.
One other thing that I should emphasize
is that if we were really
talking about the Sun
or the Earth,
the Earth...
Well,
the Earth is how big?
The Earth is 12,000
kilometers,
6,000
kilometers in radius.
Yeah,
Earth is 6,000
kilometers in radius in Earth.
The Schwarzschild radius
for the Earth is about a centimeter.
So it's a little thing like that.
And this means that you
don't trust the solution
in the interior where there's
real stuff.
This solution is only
correct outside the region
where the stuff is,
where the matter
which creates the
gravitational field is.
So this is the solution of the equations
of motion for a lump of
material outside the lump.
Now,
it's only
if the lump shrinks and
becomes smaller than this radius here
that this radius means
anything particular.
It's only
if the whole thing were to collapse
down to a radius smaller than the
Schwarzschild radius that the
solution
is meaningful
and correct down to such small distances.
So,
nothing,
there's nothing funny going on near the
center of the Earth.
In particular,
even
this thing which I'm telling you is really
not so funny,
even this,
this does not happen near the center of the Earth.
The center of the Earth does not have
a horizon.
Rather,
the solution is different in the interior
than it is on the outside.
They have to be pieced together.
But,
if the Earth were to collapse
and shrink to smaller than the
Schwarzschild radius,
then this would be
the solution.
So,
from our point of view,
anything that falls
into the black hole doesn't really go into
the black hole.
All the matter
that falls in stays on the surface.
From us watching it,
in a sense,
that's true.
We will
not perceive it passing.
We will watch it and it will asymptotically
get slower and slower and slower
and slow down,
never passing it.
Whereas,
somebody riding
with the informing materials
will just sail right through the horizon.
Question.
If the outside observer is
nothing can ever get to
the event horizon of a black hole,
a black hole from the point of an outside observer
could never grow
and by extrapolating backwards
it would never form.
If you just accept
If what?
Correct?
No,
I didn't understand it.
From the perspective
of an outside observer,
if you accept
nothing but these equations,
a black hole would never get
larger because everything from
the perspective of an outside observer
would asymptotically approach the event horizon
but never cross it.
If that's true,
a black hole
could not grow and by extrapolating
backwards it couldn't even form.
Right,
this is
what you're saying
sounds right,
but it is wrong.
But to understand how
it's wrong,
you might say
that a black hole can never get started.
You say let's suppose
let's start with a little,
little tiny
black hole.
Yeah.
Let's start with a
tiny,
tiny black hole and now
let's throw stuff into it and try to
make it bigger.
That's what people tell us
can happen.
A tiny black hole can grow.
You throw more planets into a black hole
eventually it'll grow from being
a solar mass size to
being a million solar mass
size and so it grows.
But I've just told you also that nothing
ever gets to the horizon.
So there's
something not quite right.
Right.
We're going to work out some examples.
We're going to see exactly how a black hole
grows.
And the answer is it does grow.
Another question.
Suppose you're standing
you're outside a black hole.
You drop
a sports car
into the black hole.
And you track it with a radar gun.
Yeah.
How fast it's going.
What do you see?
At least at first it starts
going faster and faster,
right?
Yeah,
sure.
I'm sorry.
Yes,
that's right.
Certainly it starts going faster and faster.
But until it
starts to go slower and slower
there's a point,
there's a
specific point where
it sort of turns over and
starts to look slower and slower.
Can you see on the radar again?
Well,
let's see.
The radar gun
is out here,
right?
Yeah.
So as this thing
falls,
it falls,
it
flattens out.
It must flatten out
because the two edges of it,
the front of it and the back of it
never get past the horizon.
And at the front and the
back never get past the horizon.
And both asymptotically move toward it.
It gets
more and more squashed.
But now the radar gun
sends in its radar and its radar
does the same thing.
Its radar never catches it.
The radar will
never catch the in-falling thing.
It will also slow
down.
So after a long period
of time,
your car
will be squashed against the horizon
here and the radar
beam will also be squashed against
here.
They'll both be
inching slower and slower and slower
toward the horizon with the
radar beam
never quite catching the
horizon.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
It'll just take longer and longer.
That's right.
It'll take longer and longer.
When the radar beam bounces off,
it will be enormously redshifted.
So I don't have to ask the follow-up
question,
how do you talk yourself out of
the beam taking?
Yeah,
right.
Exactly.
No,
what I said about
the radar beam not catching up would be
true if this were falling in
if this were a light ray.
But
it just takes
an enormously long time for the radar
beam to catch up and when the radar beam
reflects,
it's enormously
redshifted.
Yeah,
you beat
that ticket because the radar gun's not good enough.
The radar gun is
not good enough for what reason?
To catch you speeding close to the horizon.
Question.
Yeah.
So the statement that,
the
statement,
I guess I would say,
that speed of light is constant no matter
what reference frame you're in,
is that
only true in special relativity
or what
is it we're saying here,
I guess,
about that?
No,
what is true,
alright,
let's
again,
we have a
somebody falling in who's in a car
and that car gets squashed
down and down and down.
It
is
so we could ask
the light ray which is crossing that car
as the car falls in
it gets more and more squashed
and at the same time
time slows down.
We
haven't talked about the slowing down of time.
It's in here.
Time
slows down,
meaning
to say
when this,
here's the way to think about it.
This quantity is going to zero.
When this quantity goes to zero,
a given amount of dt
corresponds to a smaller
and smaller and smaller proper time
in the car.
So we'll get to it,
we'll work all this
out,
but what does happen
is the light ray,
when you take into account how the
clocks behave and how the meter sticks
behave and everything,
the person in the car will
see light go from the back of the car to
the front of the car with the speed of light.
The time,
the clock
and the meter sticks and everything
will expand,
contract,
whatever they have to do
and in that car,
following with the car,
the light
will go from the back to the front in exactly
the amount of time that it's supposed to go.
So that's not going to change.
We'll work that out.
We'll work it out.
Yes,
Kevin.
If gravity is about the shape of space-time,
what does it mean to unify gravity
with the other forces?
Nothing right now.
What does the attempt even mean?
Well...
Is there some character
of the other forces that are
that are affecting the space of...
Most ideas about unifying
gravity together with the other forces
involves adding other dimensions
to space.
When you add other dimensions
to space,
the gravitational field becomes
more complicated.
It has more components.
And the additional components
of the gravitational field,
when viewed from three dimensions
or three space one-time dimensions,
the other components
become the fields
associated with electromagnetism,
associated with the standard model
and so forth.
So from the point of view of
three plus one,
ordinary three plus one dimensions,
three plus one dimensions means three dimensions
of space,
one dimension of time.
You have a bunch of fields
in addition to the gravitational field.
When they're put together
into a higher dimensional space,
all you have is the gravitational field.
So that...
That's most attempts
at unification work along lines like that.
That the
additional directions of space,
motion in the different directions
and the additional directions of space
are...
give rise to properties
of particles,
for example,
which are their charges,
which are their various properties.
And that's where most ideas
about unification go.
So in the end,
it's all gravity.
Like gravity in higher dimensions.
Yeah?
In those theories that end up
resulting in multiverse type ideas,
is the signature of the metric
always one plus three in all of those?
In any...
Well...
You can ask
in whether the current versions of the theory
or you can ask whether in reality.
Right.
In reality,
nobody has the vaguest idea.
Could there be regions of space
with odd properties of different signatures?
I have no idea.
So that sounds like the signature
then is mostly an empirical observation.
There aren't really...
No,
it's more than that.
It's a classical property of general relativity.
General relativity equations
of motion
will resist a change in signature.
As the signature tries to get to the point
where it's going to change,
the energies become explosive
and it's kind of like trying to exceed
the speed of light.
Energy blows up at the point
where the speed of light is approached.
Energy blows up
as the signature of space-time
starts to get close to the point
where it could shift.
So it's a very complex theory.
It's more than a statement of empirical fact.
It's a property of Einstein's general theory.
On the other hand,
you can ask,
well,
what happens if you add
to Einstein's general relativity
quantum corrections,
all sorts of things,
and then nobody knows.
Thus far,
nothing anybody has ever seen
in any version of quantum gravity,
string theory,
anything else,
has ever led to
a change in the signature.
Does that mean it doesn't happen somewhere?
I don't know.
I think that's way beyond us.
Really beyond us.
Certainly beyond me right now.
I'm about in the...
From a humanist
interest standpoint,
I read that Schwarzschild was on the front lines
in World War I when he worked out those equations.
Do you have any insight into,
I mean,
given that they're so complicated,
how did someone do that?
What kind of background did he have?
Your guess is as good as mine.
He was said to be an astronomer,
but he was obviously
a pretty sophisticated mathematician.
If he was in World War I,
I don't know.
It boggles the mind.
Sometimes when I want to go into
deep withdrawal,
I see the idea of,
let's sit down and solve equations.
It is one way of going into withdrawal,
I can tell you.
For more,
please visit us at
stanford.edu.