Stanford University.
Okay,
the last time I explained to
you Kruskal coordinates for a black hole.
Let's go over it.
And tonight,
I want to show you how
you can think about the formation
of a black hole,
a real black hole,
and how much of this Kruskal story,
the diagram we drew on the blackboard last time,
really is physically meaningful.
Not all of it is.
Okay,
so the last time I showed you that the geometry,
the metric of a black hole,
of a Schwarzschild black hole,
has the property that very near the horizon,
that's the horizon.
Over there,
it looks like flat space.
The horizon is a kind of polar coordinate,
a hyperbolic polar coordinate point,
similar to the behavior of accelerated coordinate frames.
Somebody's standing outside,
and this wedge over here,
this quadrant over here,
is outside.
The rule is,
first of all,
that 45-degree angles represent the motion
of light rays.
Either going in that direction or going in this direction.
Somebody outside the black hole means out here,
in this quadrant,
then quadrant,
let's label them,
quadrant one,
quadrant two,
quadrant three,
and quadrant four.
And as you're going to see,
quadrant three and quadrant four
really don't have any physical
significance for a real black hole.
It's quadrant one and quadrant two
which are the two black holes.
Which have real significance.
Outside the black hole,
somebody at rest,
outside the black hole,
of course,
is experiencing a sense of acceleration.
Just as I'm experiencing a sense of acceleration right here.
I've gotten used to it,
so I don't notice it,
the fact that I'm being accelerated.
But if somebody who had
been in outer space too long,
in free fall too long,
lost the
sense of what a gravitational field is,
then I'm not going to be able to see it.
I'm going to be able to
see what a gravitational field is like.
And you plunk them on the surface of the earth,
they would be experiencing a sense of upward
acceleration.
And in fact,
in this diagram,
somebody at rest does appear to be accelerating away
from the horizon.
Come in and go out,
and it's that acceleration which
is what we experience as gravitational
acceleration near the surface of the earth.
But in this case,
near the horizon of the black hole.
So this is a family of observers,
further and further out,
very far from the black hole,
way out here,
in close to the horizon,
here.
The closer you get to the horizon,
the more you have to accelerate.
That's the curvature of these lines here.
The more you have to accelerate
to keep out of the black hole,
and in any case,
this is
the exterior.
Okay.
So this is the
This is the interior.
This is the outside.
This is the inside.
This is the ground.
This is the floor.
The floating part,
with thisps in the right.
This is the boundary of the earth,
the top's in the upper boundary,
and this graduates
down to the variation.
And this flattest face is very pressing.
And this is another earlier example.
So basically,
it takes us from here to
the outside into this theええ coefficient or
we say point E of shadow.
So now you have the flat aspect.
But now comes the black surface.
looks like because I've never seen one but
it's a bad place with lots and lots
of tidal force and the problem with it
is once you find yourself in quadrant 2
there's no way out the only way to get
out even let's even if the left even if
quadrant 3 was meaningful which it is
not but even if it were meaningful you
can't escape from here to out here or
to out here without exceeding the speed of
light your trajectory somewheres has to
have an direction which is shallower
than 45 degrees and that means exceeding the
speed of light so that means if you
don't exceed the speed of light the only
place you can wind up and somewhere is
on the singularity so you're doomed if you're outside
and you make a bad mistake you could
fall in but if you don't make a mistake
you can jump back out and get out
so people on the outside or light sources
on the outside flashlights whatever you
like they can produce signals which go
in or they can produce signals which go
out and that's the character of a black
hole okay so that's that's
all there is to black holes
the geometry is somewhat warped it's not
just flat space it's somewhat warped and
curved but this is basically it
could you say what the axes of that diagram are?
time and space time and space
as seen by an infalling observer
and so the lines of constant position
that you drew are for what stationary observer
outside yeah that's correct so
for somebody falling in who doesn't
have a flat space in the sky and
they're not going to be able to accelerate the
coordinates that they see which are
not too different from ordinary flat space
and freefall at least until they get
near the singularity time and X those are
the coordinates that such a person will use
okay right so to them the space looks
flat pretty much pretty much especially near
the horizon over here to somebody on
the outside they experience this acceleration
which you can't quite capture off
camera she looks flat okay except for
Productors over here this one over here
it's not in space here it's in the午
now since they have combat operations
these light-like directions,
they are also infinite.
And so I can't draw
the entire spacetime on the blackboard.
For many purposes,
it is useful,
convenient,
provides some visual tools,
provides some intuition
to be able to draw the entire spacetime
on a finite piece of the blackboard.
Well,
you can imagine why.
You want to see everything that's going on,
you want to get a complete overview of spacetime,
you'd like to draw it on
the blackboard in some finite region.
Let's start doing that,
but let's start with flat space.
Let's start with good old ordinary flat space
and take all the flat spacetime.
When I say flat space,
I mean flat spacetime.
And let's redraw it,
or re-coordinatize it,
so that we do a coordinate.
So a coordinate transformation which pulls the whole thing
into some finite region on the blackboard.
I'll show you how to do that.
This is useful,
incidentally,
for geometries,
spacetimes,
which have rotational symmetry.
Rotational symmetry means they're
the same in every direction.
They mean the same thing,
rotational symmetry,
as when we say a
gravitational source has rotational symmetry.
It means the same in every direction.
And when a system is the same in every direction
and has rotational symmetry,
it's usually useful to describe it,
now I'm talking about ordinary polar coordinates.
When a system has rotation symmetry,
it's the same in every direction,
we don't care so much about the angle.
Everything is the same independent of angle.
What we care about is how things vary
as we move away from the center,
the radial direction.
And so...
for many,
many purposes,
we don't need to think
too much about the angular direction,
and we just think of spacetime,
flat spacetime,
ordinary flat spacetime,
as having a time axis.
That's the time axis.
It goes from minus infinity to plus infinity,
and it has a radial direction.
The radial direction is like that.
The radial direction never gets negative.
R is never negative.
In polar coordinates,
R is always positive.
And so the entire spacetime
is to the right of the time axis here.
Only because being to the left of the time axis
would mean negative R,
and R is always positive.
It's the distance from the origin.
So here's everything,
the entire spacetime.
And let's put some markers on it
to be able to visualize some landmarks.
First of all,
this horizontal axis
is T equals zero.
That is T equals zero,
right over there.
Let's put in T equals one.
T equals one looks like this.
T equals two looks like this.
T equals minus one is like this.
T equals minus two is like this.
And if I wanted to draw
the entire set of possible times,
it would take me up to heaven,
and down to hell.
Okay,
so this is all possible times.
And we could also plot all possible radial distances.
And the radial distances would just look like this.
This would be R equals one,
R equals two,
R equals three.
And in all cases,
I will imagine using units
so that the speed of light is one.
C equals one.
That simply means that I work in,
if I'm going to use seconds for time,
I use light seconds for distance.
And then light rays.
Light rays will move at 45 degree angle.
Well,
that's not quite right.
Let's think about the motion of light rays.
If a light ray,
let's draw another picture over here.
Here's R equals zero.
This is polar coordinates.
This is the radius here.
It's just one instant of time
looking and including the angle now.
If a light ray comes in
radially toward the origin,
it hits the origin,
and then what does it do?
It goes back out.
I meant to draw it straight.
But this is just saying that a light ray
in polar coordinates that happens to be aimed
directly at the origin from far away,
imagine it's coming in from very far away,
if it happens to be aimed right to the origin,
it will go to the
origin and then go back out.
On this diagram,
it will appear to bounce,
to reflect off the origin.
Here's R equals zero.
This is R equals zero over here.
And so a light ray coming
in from long in the past
would look like,
I think I'll use another color,
a light ray coming in from the past
will look like this.
Moving at 45 degree angle,
it will get to the origin at some time,
and when it gets to the origin,
it will simply start back out.
It hasn't really reflected off anything,
of course.
It has just gone through the origin,
came in and went back out.
So a light ray
starts out in the very remote past,
coming in at 45 degree angle from
a place that we call light like infinity,
past light like infinity.
But all it means
is the place where all light rays come from
in the infinite past.
And they go out to the infinite future.
Of course,
there are other light rays
that do the same thing.
This one comes in a little bit earlier
and goes out a little bit earlier.
Another one up here.
But they all look pretty much the same.
They come in at 45,
they bounce off the origin,
and they go out at 45 degrees.
Now,
just for fun,
let's think about a light ray
which doesn't pass through the origin.
A light ray which doesn't pass through the origin
will miss the origin.
It comes in and it misses the origin.
When it's very,
very far away,
you can't really tell that it isn't,
unless you have very good precision,
angular precision,
extremely fine angular precision.
Watching that light ray way,
way back there,
it's hard to tell whether it's
going to hit the origin or not.
So it starts out coming
in pretty much the same way.
But it never gets to the origin.
In fact,
it almost appears to be repelled away from the origin
and then goes back out.
That repulsion is not a real repulsion,
but it is what we call
centrifugal force.
It really is centrifugal force
that keeps the light ray from hitting the origin.
Or you can just say it doesn't hit the origin
because it wasn't aimed at the origin.
Same thing.
But what does it look like?
It comes in pretty much the same way at first.
And instead of going through the origin,
it gets a point of closest approach.
The closest approach is over here.
And at that point,
it starts going back out.
So a light ray which is perfectly radially tuned
to hit the origin
looks like a 45 degree
ingoing and outgoing line.
But a light ray which misses the origin
looks like,
in fact,
sort of like,
it looks like a hyperbola.
But whatever it looks like,
that's it.
I'm just telling you these things here,
to give you some landmarks
and to give you some perspective
on what we're going to do next.
Next thing,
we're going to take this diagram
and we're going to squeeze it
and stretch it in various ways
to get the whole thing on the blackboard.
That's going to deform it.
It's not going to look the same.
But we're going to keep one thing fixed.
The one thing fixed is that light rays
will always be assumed to move on 45 degrees.
In other words,
any squeezing and squashing
and stretching that we do
should preserve the fact that light rays
move in 45 degree angles.
That's a useful thing to do
because then we can see how light rays move.
And we can see what going
faster than the speed of light,
what going slower than the speed of light looks like.
So I'm going to show you how to do that,
mathematically.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
There's nothing special about the origin.
There's not a black hole there or anything?
No,
no,
no.
At the moment there's nothing special.
It's just a particular point that we may want
to focus on.
There may be something there,
but no need for it.
Okay.
So the light rays in this diagram are bent
just because of the particular way that we chose?
Yeah,
that's right.
It's just a choice of coordinates at the moment.
Now,
there may be good physical reasons
to want to use a particular choice of coordinates.
You know,
in studying the sun,
there is no black hole,
but the symmetry of the problem makes it convenient
to think about the sun as being the center
of the whole.
That's a good thing.
And,
uh,
right.
So that's all we're doing.
All right.
Next step.
Let's assign some coordinates.
I'm not going to call this T.
I'm going to give it another name.
I'm going to call the vertical axis capital T.
Capital T and the horizontal axis capital R.
I don't want to confuse
them with other T's and R's
that we're going to use
and that we have been using.
So we're going to call
it capital T and capital R.
But there is another way to calculate
the coordinates of this.
And that's to use coordinates at 45 degrees angle.
In other words,
to introduce axes
along 45 degree angles here and here.
Of course,
I don't mean to imply
that there's anything behind R equals zero.
Uh,
we're only interested in this region here.
But we're going to introduce new coordinates.
And this coordinate over here,
that's not going to be T or R.
It's going to be T plus R.
T plus R varies as you
go from here to here to here.
And if I were to plot constant T plus R,
constant T plus R would be these lines.
Whoops,
I didn't draw it well.
Let's draw another picture over here.
R,
T.
Constant T plus R
will look like this.
These will be the lines of constant T plus R.
Okay,
so there's T plus R
and of course there's also T minus R.
T minus R lines look this way.
But really we're only interested in this half over here.
So the lines of T minus R
and constant T minus R look like that.
These are useful coordinates,
as we'll see.
T plus R,
that's called T plus.
T minus R
is called T minus.
Just as you might expect.
Okay,
so we have a different way
of describing the same spacetime,
the same flat,
good old flat spacetime.
Instead of T plus R and T minus R,
we have T plus and T minus.
Now,
what about this line here?
This,
what was this line?
This line was just plain R equals zero.
R equals zero.
Okay,
so what is that?
What is R equals zero?
That's T plus equals T minus.
So let's write T plus equals T minus.
T plus equals T minus.
That's the same thing as T
plus R equals T minus R,
or R equals minus R.
The only solution to R equals
minus R is R equals zero.
So this line over here,
which was R equals zero,
is also just T plus equals T minus.
That's a way to describe it.
Okay,
now we're going to change coordinates.
And the way we're going to change coordinates
is to introduce two new coordinates.
These are called light-like coordinates.
T plus and T minus are called light-like coordinates.
We're going to change light-like coordinates.
We're going to introduce two new light-like coordinates.
One of them is called U plus,
and one of them is called U minus.
And U plus is a function of T plus.
So we're going to write U
plus is some function of T plus.
It's not going to involve T minus at all.
And U minus is going to be,
in fact,
I think the same function of T minus.
All right,
but this function is just a coordinate transformation
in which U plus and U minus independently,
sorry,
T plus and T minus just independently transform
to some new coordinate.
Okay?
Good.
What kind of function am I going to use?
I'm going to use a function of T plus.
This is F or U this way.
U equals F of T plus.
And the function is going to look like this.
When you go out to T plus,
it doesn't ever become absolutely flat.
It's always got a slight positive slope.
Also down here it also has a slight slope.
All right?
But it'll go to one over here,
U plus,
U plus.
This is U plus.
U plus of infinity is one and,
or just F.
Let's call it F.
F of infinity is one.
And F of minus infinity is minus one.
Now,
anybody know a function that does that?
There are many functions which do that.
Zeta plus,
I don't know,
but it's a function of T plus.
What's that?
Yeah.
A hyperbolic tangent is the one that's usually used.
Hyperbolic tangent goes to one asymptotically.
It's the usual one that's used,
but there's nothing special about it.
Hyperbolic tangent,
hyperbolic tangent F of T plus is,
and if you don't know what a hyperbolic tangent is,
don't worry about it.
It's just a function which looks like this.
Tanch of T plus.
Okay,
now think about what happens
as we start moving on this graph
further and further outward.
T plus is getting bigger and bigger and bigger.
What is U plus doing?
It's never going to get bigger than one.
Right?
So let's draw our same spacetime
with these new coordinates.
I think I erased them,
but let's put them back.
U plus equals hyperbolic tangent
of T plus and same thing for minus.
As we move out,
let's redraw our picture.
let's start over here and move out.
How big does U plus ever get?
U plus never gets bigger than one.
So this diagram,
if this is the U plane,
not the T plane,
but the U plane,
U plus never gets bigger than one.
Here it is,
right there.
It never gets bigger than one.
So that means all of the spacetime
has been mapped somehow down into here.
Okay.
What about U minus?
U minus is equal to hyperbolic tangent
of T minus.
What this says is as we move down
in this direction,
T minus never gets bigger
or less negative than minus one.
T minus is getting very,
very big
and negative as you go down here.
T minus is getting bigger and bigger
but negative as you go down here.
But U minus sort of minus
or maxes out again at minus one.
And here's T minus equals minus one.
T minus never gets too far.
T plus never gets too far.
This is...
No,
I'm sorry.
I said T plus and
T minus never get very far.
I meant U plus and U minus.
U plus equals one.
This is U minus equals minus one,
in fact.
And what about this vertical line here?
The original vertical line over here
was T plus equals T minus.
Right?
T plus equals T minus.
That's the same as R equals zero.
If T plus equals T minus,
then that says that U plus equals U minus.
So,
in fact,
this line happens to be
U plus equals U minus
and it looks like a vertical line.
All right.
So all we've done...
If you don't follow the details,
all we've done is squished the geometry this way,
squished the geometry that way,
and squished it onto a finite triangle.
You'll understand this better
when I draw in these coordinates.
Okay?
Now,
what is the trajectory
of a light ray,
an outgoing...
Let's say an outgoing light ray
in terms of the T pluses and the T minuses.
Well,
an outgoing light ray
is at a constant value of which...
T minus,
I guess.
T minus would be constant and fixed on here.
T plus would be constant and fixed
for an ingoing light ray.
But if T plus is constant and fixed
along some trajectory,
it means that U plus is constant.
U plus is constant and fixed along that trajectory.
Likewise for T minus and U minus.
The upshot is that
if you make a coordinate transformation like this,
it is still true that radial light rays
move on straight 45-degree angles.
Here's a...
These are light rays that come in
from the remote past,
bounce off the origin,
and go back out.
Again,
bouncing off the origin
is just a figure of speech.
You just pass through the origin.
So we've succeeded in taking all of spacetime
and mapping it to a triangle
that we can draw the whole thing on the blackboard.
Let's draw in some more coordinates.
Let's draw in more detail.
In particular,
let's take these horizontal slices
which correspond to different times.
Let's imagine starting at the origin.
Where's T equals zero?
Here's T equals zero.
And moving outward,
outward,
outward.
We'll allow ourselves even to exceed the speed of light
and just move outward in our imagination.
What does that look like?
That,
of course,
looks like starting
at a point over here
and just moving outward.
And where do you eventually get to?
You get to this point.
So,
this point must be spatial infinity,
r equals infinity.
It's where you get to if
you just walk along this line
till you get out to infinity.
But what about this line over here?
T equals one.
If you plot that in these coordinates,
it'll start about over here,
but it will go to that same point.
Likewise,
T equals minus one.
So,
what we've done is we've squished
all of spatial infinity.
We've squished it into a point.
Right over here.
And it's called space-like infinity.
Yeah?
Are those lines supposed to be straight?
No,
they're not exactly straight.
It depends,
of course,
on the particular choice of function,
but they won't be straight.
No,
let's draw them more carefully.
One of them will be straight.
The one that will be straight
will be the T equals zero.
This one will be straight.
And then the next one will look like this.
It'll have some curvature.
What about way,
way,
way up there?
T equals 100 billion.
T equals 100 billion is going
to be very close to this edge.
So,
as we keep putting in more of these,
they accumulate and get closer and
closer to this edge up there.
We've got to get an
infinite number of them in there.
Time really does go on and on forever,
at least in flat space.
And so,
this is what the series of timelines would look like.
Different times.
On the other hand,
now let's look at fixed spatial position.
Fixed spatial position,
we can mark off different locations.
Here's r equals 1,
here's r equals 2,
r equals 3,
r equals 4,
r equals 5,
dot dot dot,
and they again get all
squished up near r equals infinity.
Where do they all go?
They all go vertically upward,
and on this diagram,
they all go up right
up to this point up here.
You can check that by doing the transformation,
and that's what you would see.
More and more and more of them.
It's the same diagram,
just in different coordinates.
And this coordinates,
as I said,
everything gets mapped to a finite region of space-time.
Again,
I emphasize light rays move at 45,
radial light rays move at 45 degrees,
they come in and they go out,
and so forth.
Okay,
this is called,
this process of squeezing everything
onto a finite piece of the blackboard
without changing the speed of light.
It's called compactification.
You take everything and you compactify it.
But it's also called making a Penrose diagram.
This is a Penrose diagram of flat space-time.
Roger Penrose.
Sometimes it's called a Carter-Penrose diagram
because a physicist named Carter,
I think,
actually invented it first.
I don't know if you've
ever seen a pen in Carter,
but it's usually called a Penrose diagram.
Good.
So that's flat space-time laid out on the blackboard.
Now,
the question is,
supposing you took the black hole.
Here's the black hole geometry.
It also goes,
oh,
let's put,
there's some names of points.
This is called spatial infinity,
or r equals infinity.
This one up here,
what would you call that?
That's what you get when you just go vertically upward.
That's time equals infinity.
All right,
let's use green.
T equals infinity.
That's this point.
What about this one?
That's t equals minus infinity.
All right,
so this,
I'll give you the name.
This is called future time-like infinity.
This is called past time-like infinity.
This is called spatial infinity,
or space-like infinity.
And what about these lines here,
these 45-degree angles?
These 45-degree angles are where all light rays come from.
Light rays come in and go out.
They don't really go out,
because it takes an infinite amount
of time for them to get out.
But a light ray beginning in the infinite
remote past starts out its life coming in along,
one of these light-like trajectories here,
bounces off and goes back out.
The standard terminology is to call this script I minus,
sometimes called scri-minus,
script I.
Scri-minus,
and I don't know why,
I don't know where the I came from.
I know what the plus and minus means.
This is called I plus,
or script I plus.
And these are called past
light-like infinity and future light-like infinity.
The place where light rays begin
and the place where light rays end.
And that's the terminology.
And that's what flat space looks like when compactified.
Now,
what about the black hole?
The Schwarzschild black hole,
what does that look like?
We can do exactly the same thing.
Take this hole diagram.
Introduce again,
I guess we can call this R,
capital R,
the original Kruskal coordinates.
And we can again introduce light-like coordinates,
T plus R and T minus R,
do exactly the same operation.
And what will we get?
What it will look like,
I'm going to draw it over here,
and then I'll show you how it works.
What it looks like is a diagonal rectangle.
At the previous in the process of圖
and the size of the context of light,
You can see that this is the same Moment.
This is when the value
of the standard weak-and-vstellung area appears.
And the next thing we're going
to do is these galvanized legislatures here,
properly and we can again draw coordinates.
Here's t equals 0,
here's t equals 1,
here's
t equals 2,
here's t equals 3,
t equals 4.
That corresponds to these lines which all
pass through this point over here.
They also pass through this point over here.
The origin
over here,
which is the horizon,
is right over here.
Okay,
what about the vertical lines,
the red vertical lines?
Those are constant position.
Those are observers who are hovering
above the black hole at a constant radius.
They look like this.
Way out,
even further
out,
even further out,
in closer,
here's somebody hovering close to the horizon,
here's somebody
hovering very close to the horizon.
Okay,
so we're going to draw a line here,
and we're going to draw a line here,
and we're
going to draw a line here.
We're going to draw a line here,
and we're going to draw a line
here.
The closer you hover close to the horizon,
the more you have to accelerate to keep out.
So it's not a comfortable thing to be
hovering above the horizon because you're being pulled
or jerked or whatever,
you're being accelerated.
This is the exterior of the black hole.
What
about quadrant 2?
Quadrant 2 is over here.
Quadrant 2 is over here and it is the place
where you're doomed.
Here's the singularity.
Now the singularity is not off at infinity.
It takes a finite amount of proper time to
fall from the horizon to the singularity.
It is a finite excursion from here to here.
The singularity is a finite time away.
Somebody who falls through,
doesn't get to experience
an infinite time.
They will hit the singularity.
This is it.
Here it is.
It's the whole thing.
the whole black hole geometry.
Which is why I call it the singularity.
A singularity is
tree laid out in a Penrose diagram.
If you're over here,
you're doomed.
If you're out here,
you can escape,
or you may go in.
You should ask yourself now,
what is this other half?
If this is the outside of the
black hole,
what is this other half over here,
and what's down here?
What's down here in
particular,
what is this thing I drew down here?
That's quadrant three and quadrant four.
Quadrant three and quadrant four have no
real meaning for a real physical black hole.
As
we're going to see,
we're going to work out a real physical black hole,
but they really
have no meaning.
They're not really on the
diagram of a real black hole.
Nevertheless,
you can ask,
what kind of geometry
is
this?
The diagram is described by this full,
what's called the extended Kruskal diagram.
It seems
to have two exterior regions.
It seems to have two exterior regions,
a second exterior
region over here,
where you can escape outward in this direction,
or you can fall in from
this side.
It seems to have two exterior
regions connected together at the horizon.
That's
the horizon.
That's the place where r is equal to 2mg.
r equals 2mg,
Schwarzschild r.
Remember,
it's the place where 1
minus 2mg over r changed sign,
whereas you came in,
you suddenly changed
sign and went off in a light-like direction.
All right,
so that's what it looks like,
but
supposing now we take a
fixed slice here that looks like this,
go right through from here to here.
What does
that space look like?
It's space now.
It's not space-time,
space on this green slice
or this green sheet surface.
What does it look like?
I'm going to tell you what it looks
like.
You start out way out here,
and space is very big.
Namely,
the celestial sphere
is very,
very big.
Way,
way out here at large r.
So you see a very big region of space.
I'm just drawing it as a plane.
As you come in,
you're moving closer and closer to this
horizon.
What happens to the radius of the sphere?
It shrinks down to r equals 2mg.
So
you could draw that like this.
It's getting smaller and smaller.
That's not very good.
I don't like that.
I don't want
to.
Let's try to do better.
Let's look almost edge-on.
Then as we come in,
it shrinks down
these circles.
Okay,
let's go back a second.
Each point on this diagram represents a two-dimensional
sphere.
Do you understand why
it represents a two-dimensional sphere?
Remember,
we're
using polar coordinates.
Right.
So just as in polar coordinates on a plane,
each radial
distance represents a circle,
each radial distance in three-dimensional polar coordinates
represents a sphere.
At each point here,
there's a sphere that somebody could move around.
So you could draw
a two-dimensional sphere.
And the two-dimensional sphere is
a very big way out here.
As you
come in,
the two-dimensional sphere gets smaller and
smaller until it gets to some minimum
size over here.
And that's the horizon.
That's r equals 2mg.
Now,
what happens if you just
keep going on this diagram,
on this sort of fake diagram,
half of which has no real meaning?
That we'll see.
Well,
it starts expanding out again.
It starts expanding out again until it gets very big.
It looks like you can pass through from one
side to the other by going through what people
call a wormhole.
Okay.
It's also called an Einstein-Rosen bridge.
It connects to what appear to be atoms of
external regions to the black hole
which get bigger and bigger and
bigger as you move away from it
and it looks like
the black hole is connecting two universes,
two
asymptotic regions
you might think well you could pass through
going from here to here
you can't
let's think about somebody who
wants to start on this side
and wants to pass to this side
if they start out here
anywhere on this side
and they want to pass to this side
their trajectory has to exceed the speed of light
there's no way to get
from this quadrant to that quadrant
even if you start very very long in the past
and you're willing to go way up into the future here
you still have to exceed the speed of light
so in fact this diagram is a little bit misleading
it's everything at an instant of time
but there simply isn't really time
to go from one side to the other
you cannot go from one side to the other
and so the Einstein-Rosen bridge is not really a bridge
one way to think about it
is that it opens up and closes
again before anything can pass through it
but the best way to think about
it is just to look at this figure
and say yeah if you
could exceed the speed of light
and move horizontally
yes you would move from here to here
and going through the neck at the center there
but you're not allowed to do that
you can only move on 45 degree angles or less
and so you really can't get
from one side to the other
this has been a source
of all sorts of science fiction
passing from one universe to another
through the center of a black hole
but as you can see it doesn't happen
these kind of wormholes or
whatever you want to call them
which you cannot get through
they're called non-traversable wormholes
meaning to say you can't traverse them
you can't go from one side to the other
I'm sorry to disappoint you but
that is the way it is
but in fact as we're going
to see in a few minutes
the meaning of the left hand side
there's no real meaning to the left hand side anyway
there's no place to go
there is no real left hand side
the left hand side is really absent from here
so let's talk about now creating a black hole
creating a black hole not
in a laboratory that's too hard
but creating a black hole in infinite space
by having some infalling matter
we're going to take very special kind of infalling matter
what we're going to do
is imagine making a black hole
we start with no black hole
嗯
There's no black hole,
but what we have is a very,
very distant shell
It's not a shell made out
of iron or anything like that
It's a shell of incoming radiation
Somebody way,
way far away created an incoming shell of radiation
A thin shell of radiation
Radiation carries energy,
radiation carries momentum
And the shell is coming in
It's coming in with the speed of light
At some point,
as we will see,
this shell gets close enough together
That there's so much energy in a
small region that a black hole forms
Alright,
so this is the simplest version of black hole formation
A star
A star isn't really made up out of
things which fall in with the speed of light
This is the problem of a black hole being formed by
stuff coming in with the speed of light on a thin shell
It's the simplest of all relativity problems
So let's see if we
can figure out how it works
You need to know really only one important thing,
two important things
The shell moves in with the speed of light
And the other thing is a version of Newton's theorem
Anybody know what Newton's theorem is?
About gravity?
For a spherically symmetric gravitational region
In particular,
for a mass distribution which forms a shell
Supposing you have a mass distribution which forms a shell
It doesn't matter whether it's moving or doing anything
If you have a mass distribution which forms a shell
For which there's nothing on the interior
Then there's no gravitational field on the interior
The interior is completely without gravitational field
So if you have a shell of material
Spherically symmetric
With nothing on the interior
There's a gravitational field on the outside
This is Newtonian
Which is identical to a gravitational field
of a point mass at the center
Same amount of mass
But on the inside of the shell,
there is nothing
So outside,
it looks like a point mass
Inside,
it looks like there's nothing
on the inside of the material
nothing.
That's Newton's theorem,
or a special case of Newton's theorem,
that on the interior
of a distribution of mass which forms a shell,
you see no gravitational field.
On the outside
you see the gravitational field as it would
be if all of that mass was concentrated at
a point.
That's even true if the shell is moving.
As the shell moves in,
more and more
space will look like the field of the point mass,
and less and less will look like empty
space,
but interior to the shell
it always looks like nothing's there,
exterior to the
shell it looks like a point mass.
This theorem is also true in general relativity.
The statement
of the theorem is if you have a shell
of infalling or a shell of mass of any kind,
then the interior
region is just flat spacetime,
just as if there was no source.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community
The exterior region,
it doesn't look like the Newtonian point source.
What does it look like?
It looks like the Schwarzschild solution.
So if you have,
in general relativity,
on the inside of a shell of mass,
flat spacetime,
on the exterior of it,
it looks like the Schwarzschild black hole.
A C-H black hole.
So if you had a static,
non-moving shell,
what you would do to construct the actual solution
is you would sort of paste together an interior here,
which was flat,
with an exterior,
which is Schwarzschild.
You do the same thing in Newtonian physics.
Paste together,
no gravitational field on the outside,
and no gravitational field on the inside.
So you have a shell on the inside
with standard gravitational point source on the outside,
and that's the way you find solutions of Newtonian physics.
You do exactly the same thing in general relativity.
Okay,
so now we can,
let's redraw the rest of this
black hole here for a minute.
Let's put it back.
I erased part of it,
but I want to put it back.
Okay.
So,
let's go back up to here.
Flat spacetime.
In flat spacetime,
I'm going to redraw it.
I want to get rid of all
these decorations and just put in nothing.
Nothing in spacetime.
But now I want to add the
idea of an incoming shell of radiation.
You can think of the incoming shell of
radiation as a sort of pulse of incoming photons.
A pulse.
Distributed on a nice sphere of incoming photons.
In this picture here,
they come in from light like infinity.
So here's the pulse.
Let's draw the pulse of incoming photons.
Arranged around.
Let's put it a little bit later.
Let's make it a little bit later.
Put it up here.
There's the pulse of incoming radiation.
It forms a shell.
Where is the interior?
On this shell here has the line.
Where is hart the shell?
The shell is called the interior of the shell.
And that has for each
reasons a origin and its root.
At any given instant,
where is the interior and where
is the exterior of the shell.
So that's easy.
Here's a line of constant time,
space.
where is the interior of the shell
and where is the exterior of the shell,
there's the interior region,
interior to the shell,
That's the part of the space-time that's
inside the shell near R equals zero.
The part of the space-time that's
outside the shell is out below,
outside,
where the shell is.
the blue line here and it's out here.
Here's the incoming shell and what does
Newton's theorem or the general
relativity version of it say?
It says
that on the interior of the shell,
that's everything in here,
everything in there
is flat spacetime.
In other words,
it's correctly represented by the spacetime
that we drew here which was
just a representation of flat spacetime.
First of all,
on the interior of the shell,
which is the lower left here,
the
spacetime of just the flat Penrose
diagram is the correct representation of
everything that's going on.
Now what about out here?
Out here we're told that
there's a gravitational field.
The gravitational field does not look like
flat spacetime,
so this region out here is wrong.
This is not the correct
representation of
the
physics or the geometry of this
infalling shell out beyond the shell.
What is the correct representation?
The correct representation is
the Schwarzschild black hole.
So let's redraw the Schwarzschild black hole to
get rid of all the junk on it.
Just redraw it.
I lost my black pen.
Oh,
there it is.
So here it is.
And now somebody on the outside throws in
the shell.
Yes,
it does,
because left is the last아냅 Frico
and vents is the first one.
شكرا
riding in,
and what does it look like?
It looks like this.
Oh,
I used blue before.
Well,
alright,
let's use red.
Here's the incoming shell.
It comes in,
experiences nothing special at this point over here,
and just keeps going,
but eventually,
and it's a light ray,
it's a light ray,
a radially incoming light ray,
it must move on a 45 degree angle,
it moves in,
and just eventually hits the singularity.
Alright,
so that's what the light ray
would look like on the Schwarzschild geometry.
But now,
which part of the diagram is
correctly representing the physics that we're doing?
The interior of the shell is
not correctly represented by the black hole.
The interior of the shell
is correctly represented by flat spacetime.
It's the exterior which is correctly represented.
The exterior is out here.
We can make it a little bigger,
just to,
I didn't mean to slice it so thin.
Let's make it a little bit bigger.
That just means the shell starts in earlier.
The orange part here is the correct description.
Of the spacetime of the infalling shell.
And the interior in here is not correctly represented.
So how do we put these two together?
How do we put these two together
in order to make a single geometry?
And it's pretty easy.
You just take the wrong part
of this and throw it away.
And you take the wrong part
of this and you throw it away.
And you take the two
right parts and sew them together,
or glue them together,
along the joining line where the infalling shell is.
You take this,
you put it up there,
redraw it,
and it looks like this.
Let's see if we can see what's going on.
Alright,
you see I've taken this diagram over here.
And simply placed it on top of the flat
spacetime drawing so that the shell matches across them.
The shell is the thing they have in common.
The infalling shell is the region that
the two of them have in common.
And on one side you plaster the black hole geometry.
On the other side you
put in the flat space geometry.
That is the geometry of a black
hole that is formed by an infalling shell.
Now,
excuse me while I consult with Newton.
ありがとうございました
Any questions about this?
If you have a shell of batter like that collapsing,
is there any kind of discontinuity
when it crosses the sports channel gratings?
No,
no discontinuity.
But we're going to put that
in and see where it is.
以上です
No,
nothing special happens
Okay,
where is the horizon?
Where is the point of no return?
Where on this diagram is somebody doomed?
What you do is you
start up in that corner there,
that's the corner where the
singularity appears to meet scry plus
That's infinitely far away.
So don't worry about it.
Scry plus is very very
far away very very late time
But now run a 45 degree line from there down
It's not a place where anybody
gets hurt if they fall through it
It's just a place where
if you do fall through it
You cannot escape from the singularity
You will hit the singularity
If you're on the outside of it here,
you can get away you can
escape to scry plus for example
But notice something very very curious
Even over here you're doomed
You're still in flat space time
The shell hasn't even gotten in yet
You can't see the shell if
you look backward on your light cone
You'll not see the shell
The shell is coming in at
you at the speed of light
Light hasn't gotten to you yet
You don't know the shell is coming
And yet,
if you're still in flat space time
You're standing over here
In other words if you were
somebody who was just falling over here
Just in free fall over here
You're already behind the horizon
Even though
The shell hasn't even gotten in
In yet
You're still in flat space time
Not only don't you feel anything drastic
You don't feel anything
Nothing coming at you
But nevertheless you're doomed
You're doomed,
you cannot get out
So the horizon
Extends all the way back to here
Does that mean you can't cross the horizon
Or you can't cross the shell
No you can cross the shell
As long as you're outside the horizon
No
This is inside the horizon
What happens when the horizon is inside the shell
You know it hasn't collapsed down to the surface
When the horizon arrives to the source of the radius
When the shell hasn't collapsed
When it hasn't reached the
It's over here
Right over here
Is where the shell crosses the short-shield radius
Okay so let's go back and draw a picture
Here's the incoming shell
It has a certain amount of mass
Associated with that mass
Is the short-shield radius
Alright so there's some massive shell
Mass meaning energy
It's made of light but it still has energy
Therefore mass
And here
Is the short-shield radius
Of a black hole with that mass
If we had a black hole
Of that mass
It would have a short-shield radius that's that big
As long as you're outside the horizon
So if these masses on the outside
Um
Well we can say
That the mass is on the outside
That's all there is to say
But once the mass
Once the light
Crosses past the short-shield radius
It's trapped
It cannot get out
It has formed a black hole for sure
Where does that form on here
Okay right over here
Here's the in-falling shell
It crosses the horizon
Right over here
And then it's on the inside
And there's no way for that shell
To change its mind and get back out
Out here
The shell could change its mind
And accelerate back out
Well I suppose shells or photons don't have minds
But uh
If they had a mind
The photons could turn around over here
Once they get past here
They cannot turn around
They can try to turn around
But they won't get very far
So this is the point
At which the shell crosses its own
Short-shield radius
Is there a meaning of the word horizon
Until it gets past that point
Does it still mean something
The definition of the horizon
Is the place which separates
Those people who can get out
From those people who can't get out
But can't they get out
Before a collapsing shell crosses the distance
No
Look
Look at the picture
If you're over here
The shell hasn't crossed
What do you mean before
Pick a time coordinate
This diagram over here
If I'm inside the horizon
It's flat space
There's no gravitational field
Why can't I just walk across
Because by the time you get to here
The shell will have
Yeah
I think the only answer
is to look at this diagram
You look at this diagram
And you say I'm over here
But by the time you've gotten out
By the time
You can't get out
You simply can't get out
You have to exceed the speed of light
The diagram is the whole story
There's no more story than that
If you're here
You can't get out
So the horizon has materialized
Before the
Before the shell has actually gotten
Into the
Into its own short-shield radius
At least what I think is a paradox
Inside the shell
There's no gravitational field
There's flat space time
Why can't I just walk across the radius
What do you mean walk
Here's walking
You're walking with the speed of light
It's pretty fast walking
I mean the shell is
collapsing with the speed of light
If it's a lot farther away from the horizon
Than you are
You ought to be able to beat it
Here it is
What that's saying is
If we're sitting here
And a light shell is a million miles away
We are doomed
If the light shell is a million miles away
We are still doomed
It's coming this way
Because we cannot walk that little distance
That's right,
you can't walk fast enough
To get out of its way
If that light is coming in at you
You may be trapped
Even though you don't know that
there's a light ray coming in
So
The proof is
The diagram
Would this be analogous to
If you look at the
What do you call it
The radiation from the
Big bang
I forget what it's called
But it's radiation coming towards us
Yeah
But we can't get past it
Is that analogous to this
It's analogous but with a different analogy
But that's not a shell coming in
That's not a shell coming in
Right
Um
Okay
So the horizon is a funny thing
It actually forms
Before the material
Gets past the Schwarzschild radius
And its definition is
It's the point of no return
It is the point
Which if you're on this side of it
You can't get out
If you're on that side of it
It's not a point,
it's a sort of cone
Right at the other side of the
Schwarzschild radius
And the light comes in,
hits the mirror
And turns around and bounces back out
What would that diagram look like
Well
Not likely you can really do this
You're saying
Supposing there was a mirror
Right outside here
With no weight
Infinite reflection
Well I think the point is
You can't have a mirror that has no weight
If you could
Now
Surely you can do this to some extent
You can build a mirror around a region like this
And the light ray would reflect off
If you really succeeded in building a mirror
The light ray would reflect off
And it wouldn't
So it would turn 90 degrees
Right there
And hit the time like infinity
Yeah
You wouldn't have a black hole
So we can draw it on here
Here's the mirror
The mirror is at a certain distance
Away from the horizon
So away from the center
There's the mirror
The light comes in
And bounces off
And that's all that happens
So it's kind of not
until it actually crosses the horizon
That you're committed to being inside
Yeah
That's right
Question
Just to test my understanding
This light could decide to turn around
At this point
But there's no way that this gentleman over here
Could tell that light to turn around over there
But he could make a mirror really fast
Hm?
Not over here he can't
If he's over here he can't get
the material out for a mirror over here
He could have tried
He could have made a mirror in the past
And protected himself
Well let's see,
can he?
Yeah,
maybe so
If he was over here coming in
He could decide to shoot out a mirror
To reflect off the mirror over there
But once he gets past this point
Once he gets past that point
He cannot shoot out the mirror
Out to this point
He can't get it out there in time
To rescue himself
Of course in practice he wouldn't even know
That that light ray was coming in
Well he might know
He might know
He might have
Bob could be
Let's see,
let me get Alice
Alice is the one who
always goes in the black hole
It's just a convention
I didn't invent it
Alice
Alice goes in the black hole
But up to this point over here
She's together with Bob
And they're having a conversation
And she tells Bob
Look,
I got an idea
I want you to go out there
And then shoot out the mirror
Shoot in a shell
And this is going to be a lot of fun
I'm going to get trapped behind the horizon
And annihilated at the singularity
And in fact
I know that that's going to happen
Even before I can
See this shell coming at me
So isn't that interesting
So she could arrange
With Bob
To contrive to send in that shell
Know that it was going to come in
Be over here
But once she gets over there
She can't start to do anything about it
She can't get a mirror out there
She can get a mirror over to here
But getting it over to here
Is no good
Everything's behind the horizon already
Anything back here will hit the singularity
She's got to get the mirror out to here
She can't do it
So
I'm curious about what happens
If the mirror is inside
The horizon
What are you doing?
The mirror is inside
The mirror seems to
It has to get annihilated
The mirror will just hit the singularity
The mirror is just another thing
Which is doomed
Light will overwhelm any structure
That has been built there
When it was flat space time
You could build a structure
Over here
Well let's say a structure over here
Which reflected light
So that light coming in here
Would hit the structure
Reflect off
And go into the singularity
Mirror,
Alice,
light
All of it winds up on the singularity
So see there's actually a particular time
Or is it like infinitely far away?
No it's not infinitely
It's not infinitely far away
There's a finite amount of proper time
Between here and here
What about the corner there?
The corner there is infinitely far away
But only the corner
Only the corner
Right
But the implication is that somebody
Who's on the horizon
Has a finite amount of time to survive
Well
They could try to accelerate like mad
Once they pass the horizon over here
And try to save themselves by
By
Sticking to that corner
The problem with that is
That it would take an infinite amount of acceleration
And an infinite amount of energy
To make that much of an acceleration
You basically have to accelerate yourself
Up to the speed of light
So
Once you cross there
You're doomed
But you could last a long time
If you could accelerate hard enough
Actually that doesn't work
The more you accelerate
The less time you experience
That's a time dilation
Doesn't work
Your best strategy is to stand still
And just accept your fate
Question?
Just to make sure I understand
So if there's this shell
Let's say it's a
A man light years across
No matter what it's mass is
Or it's energy equivalent to mass
That thing
If it's going inward
It's going to form a black hole at some point
Correct?
And if I'm inside that thing
But I'm far enough away from it's eventual center
Then I can just hang out here
And there's not going to be a problem
Is that right?
Sir you're at the center of it?
No I'm not at the center
Inside the shell
I'm inside the shell far away from the center
The eventual center
Then there's no problem for me
Oh sorry
You're inside the shell before the shell crosses the
Then you
Then I can just hang out
Well yeah
You can just hang out
and let the shell cross you
Yeah absolutely
Yeah
Of course the shell might hit you
And make some damage
But that's a separate issue
So if you're in a plate transforming
Black coordinates
Would this be analogous here
In a particular point in time
Whatever that means
That's a point in time
This is a point of time
This picture
Some point of time
Would it relate that the distance from the shell
To the event horizon is greater than the event horizon
To the person in between
Is that a different way of looking at this picture
So no matter how fast he accelerates
To the event horizon
To the eventual event horizon
He can't get there in
time before the shell comes in
Right
Alright so let's ask about
What the relationship between these pictures are
Is
Or I don't know
Um
Maybe I should draw it bigger
Let's draw it bigger
Uh and um
Understand
No we can do it over here
Right over here
Alright so here's our Penrose diagram
For the formation of the black hole
Here's the horizon
Here's the infalling shell
The infalling shell hits right over here
Okay
Now
In order to speak of an instant of time
Which time do we use
Time is just a coordinate
We can make coordinate transformations
An instant of time really means
You pick a surface
Which is everywhere space like
Here's a surface
Here's another surface
But you could pick it in various kinds of ways
And these series of surfaces
Define a time variable
Time is one value on here
Another value on here
If you follow the time
At this time over here
The shell is far away
No horizon has formed yet
So this point has not been reached yet
A little bit later
The shell is still outside the horizon
You're inside
You're in here
This point over here
Corresponds to the position of the shell
And
So far nothing has formed
There's a horizon over here
There is a horizon
At this point right over here
At that time right over there
That's the time at which the shell passes
It's own Schwarzschild radius
It's the time that the shell
Passes into the interior of the horizon
Here's the horizon
Shell passes into the interior
And once that happens it can't get out
The Schwarzschild radius goes larger and larger
What's that?
It goes up that way
Oh yeah,
you're talking about this
Yeah
It's not the Schwarzschild radius
Schwarzschild radius is by definition always the same thing
But the size of the horizon
Right at this point here
The horizon starts
Okay
The horizon starts very small
Only if you're in
Right near the center here are you doomed
If you're out here
You'll get a chance to get away
That corresponds to being here or here
The little tiny horizon
Has formed,
the little tiny horizon
Has opened up
If you're in here you're dead
If you're out here you got a chance
Alright,
same thing here
If you're in here you're dead
If you're out here you got a chance
And then without the shell
Having even gotten to you yet
The horizon starts to expand
Until
It gets to this point over here
At that point the shell crosses it
At that point
The incoming shell
Crosses the growing horizon
And past that point
The shell is on the inside
The horizon is on the outside
And uh
Are these properties still growing?
Hmm?
I mean why is it still growing?
Why is what?
It stops growing
It should stop growing right?
It does stop growing
It stops growing right at that point
And above it is
Constant
Above it is a constant radius line
Yeah this is a constant radius line
That's correct
Doesn't look like it but it is
Could you draw an observer who's sitting at
Half of the square shut radius on that diamond
Yeah
Yeah well um
Alright
Yeah at some point
It just crosses the
The horizon
It's half the Schwarzschild radius
And uh
Crosses the horizon
But I thought he wouldn't experience any gravity
Until he passes through the shell
He doesn't experience any gravity
Until he crosses the shell
But nevertheless he's dead
I mean he's not dead yet
He's not dead yet
Nevertheless it's too late for him to escape
There's no gravity until that point
Right crossing the horizon
Does not mean that you sense any
Sudden gravity taking place
That only happens when you cross the shell
Right
But when you cross the horizon
You know what that means
That means you simply don't get away
You can't get away
So in that sense the
horizon is a little bit ghostly
That doesn't have a material significance
In the way the shell does
Uh
Somebody falling through it
Doesn't experience it
In fact down here somebody falling through it
There's nothing there but flat space
Nevertheless
From that point
Cannot travel fast enough to escape
The fact that that shell is coming in
Yeah
This says then that if you start out early enough
And you move
You move faster than the shell grows
Then the horizon
Then the horizon grows
Then you can escape
That's right
From here you can escape
From here you can't escape
Your velocity has to be greater
than the width of the horizon
Well
Yes yes yes yes
Yes
But that's correct
But you don't see any horizon opening up at you
Yes
That's right
You'll have to
That's a very good way of kind of envisioning it
You have two shells
If the distance between the observer to the inner shell
Is larger than the inner shell
Which is the horizon shell
To the radiation shell
No matter how fast he goes
He can't get to that point before they cross
So he's
He's doomed
That's a much simpler way of envisioning it
I think
That seems fair to me
This is a
A coordinate
You try to do a calculation with that
And find out where for example a horizon forms
Try to do that
You'll find
You'll find you can't do it
Then you wind up drawing the picture
Taking this line
Going backward to that point
And saying that's where it is
I mean
I assure you
If you want to get a good picture
Of what's going on
The way to do it
Is to become familiar with these diagrams
Um
If you try to reason it out
Without a good picture in front of you
That accurately represents
The relationships
Between the different parts here
And when the relationship
The important relationship incidentally
Is not the relative size of things
Here
There's a huge region of space and time
Up in this corner here
It's huge
Infinite
And this area here
Might be a tiny little region
So these diagrams are not correctly
Or you know faithfully representing size scales
What are they representing?
They're representing the motion of light rays
And in Mertman
In representing light rays
They're representing what things
Are in causal relationship to other things
What
What signals can propagate
Who can send a signal to whom
Can a signal from here
Get from Alice in here
It reflects
The technical language would be
That it reflects the causal structure
Cause and effect
Cause and effect mean
What can influence what
And the rule is
A thing can only influence
The things in front of it
Where light can get to
It cannot influence the things
Outside the light cone
Uh
So these diagrams
Were intended
They were built
First of all to be able to draw everything
On the blackboard
And second of all to reflect faithfully
The causal relations
What causes and effects
Who can send signals to whom
Who is trapped if they're stuck
Having to go slower than the speed of light
Those things are correctly reflected here
And so for that reason
These diagrams are very valuable
I can't think without them
I can't uh if I have to
answer a question of the kind you're asking
I can't draw the diagram
And the diagram uh
Says things much more clearly
Than trying to picture
I can't do it
I simply can't
I can't uh
I can't guess whether my guesses are right
I can't tell whether my guesses are right or wrong
Until I've drawn the diagram
Okay
How long did it take you
To be able to
Be comfortable and intuitive
With these diagrams
Well yeah
Not long
Not long just play with them for a while
Yeah
No not long yeah
So this is sort of
the opposite of what you said
In quantum mechanics
Instead of quantum mechanics
You can't think of it in terms of pictures
You have to go to the mathematics
To understand it
But yeah keep in mind
These are in a certain sense
These are abstract diagrams
But you're right
That's absolutely right
General relativity
Is classical physics
And it can be represented
It can be drawn
It can be even pictured to some extent
Alright it's not so easy to draw
To picture four dimensional curved space time
But that's hard
Yeah
But still
You can go a lot further
In visualizing it
Than you can quantum mechanics
I think that's right I think that's an interesting fact
Quantum mechanics is much more abstract in that sense
Okay
We're going to quit a little early tonight
For more
Please visit us at
Stanford.edu