Stanford University.
So the questions that were asked to
me tonight are more or less by accident.
They're exactly the ones that I want to address tonight.
Weak gravitational fields,
linearity versus non-linearity,
and gravitational waves.
Let's begin.
Working out the equations of
general relativity is always unpleasant.
And we're not going to do it on the blackboard.
They would fill the blackboard even for simple things,
and they probably would not be terribly illuminating.
So,
to learn this subject really how to compute
and how to solve its equations and so forth,
I think you just have
to sit down and do it.
On the other hand,
the principles are straightforward enough,
and it's easy enough to say what
you get when you do solve the equations.
So that's the way we'll talk about gravity waves,
by writing down the equations
and then writing down the solutions.
Now,
we're interested in what could
be called weak gravitational waves.
Weak gravitational waves means that
the amplitudes of the gravitational waves
are small enough that you can make approximations
such as the amplitude squared
of the gravitational field is zero.
When a quantity is small,
and you're expanding an equation
about the smallness of that quantity,
the usual rule is to
ignore things which are higher order,
and you're going to get a greater
amount of matter in that small quantity.
All right,
so we start with an equilibrium.
We're talking now about fluctuations
or perturbations about an equilibrium situation,
and the simplest equilibrium solution of...
Let's write Einstein's equations first.
Einstein's equations...
Let's take the case without any matter.
No energy momentum tensor.
Then the equations of motion are just
r mu nu minus one-half g mu nu.
r is equal to zero.
Let's call the Einstein tensor g mu nu equals zero.
And it can be simplified.
If you take the trace of both sides,
the r here is the trace of the Ricci tensor.
you will discover that r,
the scalar curvature r,
is equal to zero.
And once you know that,
you can ignore the second term in the equation.
The equation is simpler.
That doesn't really matter because we're not
going to write down the details anyway.
But this is the equation of Einstein
in a context in which there is
no energy momentum tensor on the right-hand side.
All right,
what's an equilibrium situation?
An equilibrium situation,
first of all,
means a solution
that has no time dependence.
There's really,
and which also doesn't have
any matter on the right-hand side.
Matter is another word for the
energy momentum tensor on the right-hand side.
No right-hand side.
There's really only one equilibrium situation.
The equilibrium situation is just empty space.
Empty space is time independent.
The,
uh,
empty space,
by empty space,
I mean empty flat space.
No curvature,
no interesting gravitational field.
And in that case,
the metric,
g mu nu,
now,
I'm not going to say the
metric is equal to such and such.
The metric depends on the coordinates you use.
If I wrote that the metric of a flat plane
is just the Kronecker delta symbol,
you would correct me and say,
no,
the metric of a flat
plane is not the Kronecker delta.
A possible metric expressing the flatness of space
would be the Kronecker delta.
But if I used other coordinates,
the metric would not be the Kronecker delta.
Use curved coordinates,
use polar coordinates,
use any other kind of coordinates.
What's special about flat space
is that you can find coordinates
in which the metric has a nice simple form.
The same is true in general relativity.
Flat space-time with no gravitational field,
there is a choice of coordinates
in which the metric has the simple form
of eta mu nu.
Let me just remind you what eta mu nu is.
Eta mu nu is a matrix.
Let's just write the matrix.
I think with the notations
we've been using in this class,
I think it's 1,
minus 1,
0,
0...
No,
sorry,
that's incorrect.
It's 1,
0,
1...
Ah,
minus 1.
Which row and column corresponds to time?
The first one
T,
x,
y,
z
This is,
and so forth
Okay,
so that's the metric of flat spacetime
1,
minus 1,
and 3 pluses
And it's an equilibrium solution
It is a solution of the Einstein field equations
The Einstein field equations say certain
components of curvature are equal to 0
This is a geometry,
or this is a metric
that has no curvature at all
And so it is a solution,
if you plugged it in
you would find it's a solution
In fact it would be trivial
One step
Now,
let's think about something which is close to empty space
Far away,
some complicated thing
Something is happening far away,
too far away to be interesting to us
Or at least to be close
enough for us to directly observe
There's something going on
A binary pulsar is rotating around
And doing some complicated emission of gravitational waves
Close by,
the gravitational field may be very strong
Even the gravitational waves might be rather strong
But it's not
So if you go far enough away
The gravitational radiation,
the gravitational waves that are produced by this thing
Are going to be very weak
What does weak mean?
Weak means that the true metric can be chosen
Again,
I emphasize,
can be chosen
To equal eta mu nu plus something small
Small means that its components are much
smaller than the ones which appear here
And that small thing is usually called h mu nu
As far as I know it's called
h because h is the letter after g
I don't know any other reason for h
h mu nu,
unlike eta mu nu,
is in general a function of position
It's also
When I say position,
I mean position and time
It's a function of the coordinates
It varies from place to place
And it might describe a wave
We'll come back to waves in a moment
But let's
What are we going to do with this?
We're going to take this metric
Calculate from it r mu nu
And set it equal to zero
And that's going to give us an equation for h
Now the equation that you
actually get from h for h
It's not big enough to fill the whole blackboard
But it's big enough to be quite unpleasant
And so I'm just going to be schematic
I'm going to show you what goes into it
First of all,
what is r?
r is a combination of components
Of the curvature tensor
I'm not going to write the curvature tensor
I'm just going to remind you what it contains
The curvature tensor itself
The thing with four indices
Contains one term which is
a derivative with respect to position
With respect to x
And I'm not even going to write which x
It contains lots of different derivatives
Depending on the index structure
Derivative of the Christoffel symbol
So it contains a first derivative of the Christoffel symbol
And secondly,
it contains the Christoffel symbol
Quadratically squared
Or Christoffel symbol times another Christoffel symbol
This is really all
This is as much detail as we're going to do
I could put the indices in here
And remind you where the indices go
And there are various terms which look like this
There are various terms which look like that
But this is good enough for us
What about gamma?
What about the Christoffel symbol?
If you remember,
that can
Well,
first of all,
it contains a factor of one half
It contains the metric tensor with components upstairs
The metric tensor with components upstairs
Is simply the inverse matrix
Of the metric tensor itself
It can also be expanded in powers of h
The first contribution to it
Is just the eta symbol itself
So the inverse eta is its own inverse matrix
And so it begins with
a g to the minus one
I'll be more specific in a minute
And then it has derivatives of g
It has various kinds of derivatives of g
Now come back to here
G inverse
That contains again things like eta
Probably minus h
But whatever it is,
it contains the eta symbol
Plus a small correction
The metric tensor with upper indices
If you only had eta
Would basically be the same eta
And then h would appear as a correction
Alright,
so g inverse here
This would contain things like
This is a wiggly equal sign
Which means not equal at all
It would contain things like
Eta minus a small correction
Or plus a small correction
That's not important for us
But then the derivative of g
That only contains h
Why?
Because the derivative of this metric tensor is just zero
All it contains is zeros and ones
The derivative of zeros and ones is zero
And so in the approximation that we're working in
The derivative of g just contains derivatives of h
Let's just call it derivative of h
Okay,
let's look at what we have here
This is the Christoffel symbol
It contains one term which has one power of h
Incidentally,
h is small
And we'll also assume that its derivative is also small
If you have a small number,
a small function
And you differentiate it
It's equally small in general
Unless it has very sharp points or something
Which we'll assume it doesn't
So the derivative of h is
also considered to be a small thing
Eta times h is once small
h times the derivative of h is twice small
It's quadratic in the fluctuation
Or in the small gravitational field
So we ignore it
Too small to be important
If h is 0.01
And derivative of h is 0.01
Then h times h is 0.0001
Whatever,
very small
Alright,
so we can ignore this
And eta times h we'll just call derivative of h
Just call it derivative of h
So the Christoffel symbol itself
Is just in the approximation of small gravity
Of weak gravitational radiation
The Christoffel symbol itself
Is just proportional to some derivative
Or some collection of derivatives of h
What about the Ricci tensor then?
The Ricci tensor will contain
Derivative of gamma
And that's going to be second derivative of h
It's going to contain various kinds of second derivatives
Of the gravitational field
Incidentally,
h is greater than 0.01
And that's going to be called the gravitational field
Or the field of the gravitational wave
And then over here
It's going to contain plus
Derivative of h times derivative of h
Gamma times gamma
Is quadratic in derivatives of h
So immediately we say
This is much smaller than this
And we ignore it
And we're going to go back to the last part
So whatever the devil
This Ricci tensor is
It's composed out of simple second derivatives
Of the metric tensor
From that we can conclude
That Einstein's equations have
A relatively simple form
There's still plenty of indices around
And the number of different terms
Involving second derivatives of h
Are significant
It's not a
It's complicated enough
I don't want to write it down on the blackboard
But it is basically built out of second derivatives
Second derivatives with respect to position
And second derivatives with respect to time
And maybe even some terms
Which have a derivative with respect to position
And a derivative with respect to time
And furthermore
There are several components of it
It's not just how many components of it
Well,
the Ricci tensor
Has a mu and a nu
So it has two components
What comes out has two components
But the whole works
Whatever it is
Is composed of second derivatives of h
Okay,
so
Our equation of motion is some kind of
Equation that looks like this
Equations of that form
Especially in relativity
Are usually wave equations
Just to remind you
What a wave equation
For an ordinary wave looks like
Let's say a wave
Moving down
The z-axis
A wave moving down the z-axis
Also satisfies an equation that looks like this
Let's say the wave field
Let's call it phi
The wave field phi
Will satisfy an equation like
d second phi by dt squared
Is equal
To d second phi
By dz squared
This is the simplest wave equation
That you can imagine
And the solution to it
Are waves
Which move either to the right
Or to the left
You can add waves
Which go to the right and the left
It's still a solution
So you can take a wave
Which looks like this
Add it to a wave
Moving to the left
The sum is still a solution
Because the equation is linear
Okay,
so
This is
Or we can
Let's write it this way
This minus this is equal to zero
If we had more directions of space
The structure of the equation
Would be a little more complicated
Instead of just derivative of phi
With respect to z
We would also have
We would have a sum of terms
Plus second derivative of phi
With respect to x squared
With respect to y squared
Equals zero
But it's evident that there's a
A family similarity
Between the kind of equation
Which occurs here
And the kind of equation
In fact
By clever manipulation
You can make these equations
This is not just one equation incidentally
There's an equation for each mu and nu
Let's put a bracket around here
And just remind ourselves
That there are
Four times four
Sixteen components
Of r mu nu
Now they're not all independent
And it's really quite a bit simpler than that
But still in principle
There are sixteen components
Sixteen equations
In that respect
It's somewhat similar to Maxwell's equations
Maxwell's equations
Have the form of wave equations
For example
For the electric field
For electric and magnetic field
But there are several components
There are three components of electric field
Three components of magnetic field
Sounds like there's only six equations
But in fact there are eight equations
Maxwell's equations
And
This is the same sort of thing
Several equations
But all of similar
Similar form
Any questions?
One question
Doesn't that derivative
Put two instances
Doesn't it actually have four indices?
Doesn't it have what?
Four indices
Yeah
Two go with the derivative
And two go with the age
Yeah,
yeah
But they were contracted in many ways
Remember
Yeah,
that's correct
But remember where r mu nu came from
It came from a thing
with r mu nu sigma tau
Or upstairs or downstairs indices
And then we contracted them
Put a nu upstairs here
So that
That nu disappeared as an index
And we just got the Ricci tensor
So yes
With four derivatives
Sorry,
with two derivatives
And two components to h
We certainly can make
How many?
Whatever,
whatever number
We can make a number of different combinations
Much more than just two indices
But
The combination that we're interested in
Is contracted in such a way
That there's only two indices
And only two equations left over
Excuse me
Yeah
On that contraction
When you have the index upstairs
Doesn't part of the contraction involve
Introducing the metric again or not?
Yes it does
Good
Right
So part of
Part of contracting
Involves introducing the metric again
But
Again the same thing is true
The metric is the same thing
The metric is eta plus h
R is composed out of derivatives
So it already is small
It already is small
And if you multiply it by another small number
It's doubly small
I think that's what you're asking
Well yeah but
But then you'll get
Won't you get terms of the form
H times the second derivative of h?
Yes
But they're counted as infinitely small
Okay so they're small
And then
Yes
Anything that involves
An h multiplied by another h
Or a derivative of h
Times another derivative of h
Or an h times a derivative of h
Is dropped in this approximation
This is an approximation
But it's a well defined approximation
In that it is the
Well technically it's the linearization
Of Einstein's equations
Which means
Which simply means
You throw away everything of higher power
Yeah
Okay
So
But it is a good approximation
When the gravitational radiation
Or gravitational wave is weak
Okay so we have equations of this form
Which we're not going to specifically write down
They're kind of messy
But before we discuss them
Well before we discuss the solutions
You might ask yourself
Well I originally told you
That
That it's not that the metric of flat space
Is equal to eta mu nu
It's that it can be chosen
To be equal to eta mu nu
That means
That there are other ways
To represent flat space
Make a coordinate transformation
On eta mu nu
And the metric changes
But it's still exactly the same
Exactly the same solution
And so what that means
Is that there must be solutions
Of these equations
Which look like they have
Which look like they're non-trivial
But really are just
That all they really represent
Is flat space
But in coordinates
Where the coordinates
Have little ripples in them
In other words
Supposing I
Take the flat blackboard
And I take the blackboard
I maintain that the flat blackboard
Is a solution of Einstein's equations
Well not really
Well it is yes
But not in the sense I mean here
It is a flat space
Okay
It can be represented by a metric delta m n
Let's say
M and n stand for x and y
On the other hand
There's nothing to prevent me
From introducing
Coordinates
With little wiggles in them
Well we could start with coordinates
Let's say we start with coordinates
Which are the good Cartesian coordinates
Let's call them
X
Standing for x and y
Yeah let's call them x
Uh
X and y
And then we can introduce
New coordinates
X prime and y prime
Where x prime
Is just x
Plus a small
Change
We could call that plus
F sub x of x and y
It's a coordinate change
A coordinate change
Is x prime
Is some function
Of x and y
And y prime
Is some other function
Of x and y
That's a coordinate change
Here the coordinate change
Is taken to be almost no coordinate change at all
Plus a small little correction
Same thing for y
Y prime is equal to y
Plus
Let's call it
F sub y
Of x and y
I have not changed the space in any way
All I've done
Is change coordinates
And perhaps put some little wiggles
If F has some wiggles in it
Then the new coordinate axes might have
The new coordinate lines might have
Some little wiggles in them
And now the metric
If I rewrite the metric
For the prime component
So let's say
Uh
Let's take the case
Let's assume the metric
In the primed coordinates
Is just
The x prime squared
Plus the y prime squared
I'm working backward
I'm supposing
That the primed coordinates
Are the nice coordinates
The nice Cartesian coordinates
And the x and y coordinates
Are the um
The slightly curved ones
Alright what is the metric
The metric
This is just a blackboard now
We're not doing space time
Just a blackboard
The metric of the blackboard
Is the x prime squared
Plus the y prime squared
Let's work it out for fun
In x and y
Okay so what is the x prime
We work out what the x prime is
The x prime comma
The x prime
Is equal to the x
Plus
The derivative of
F sub x
With respect to let's call it
X sub x m
M could be either x or y
Times dx m
And
Likewise for
Y
We figure out what dy prime is
That's dy plus a small correction
And you plug it into here
And what do you find out
You find out that the x prime squared
Plus dy prime squared is not
dx squared plus dy squared
It contains dx squared plus dy squared
But also contains
Other cross terms
dx times this
And dy times that
And if you work it out
What you find out is that this is equal to
dx dy
Sorry dx squared plus dy squared
Now I am assuming that f is small
I'm going to assume that f is small
And that means when I square dx prime squared
I can drop
The f dx squared
Likewise for y
So what I'm going to get is a correction
And the correction
Can be called h
Mn dxm dxn
And that's
h
Mn dxm dxn
In other words
Just by squaring out
The x prime squared and dy prime squared
Substituting in
You'll discover that there's a small correction
Now does a small correction to the metric tensor
Mean that the geometry of the blackboard
Has changed?
No,
it just means that the
That the
That the coordinates
That I've used
Have wiggles in them
You can work out
It's nice to work out
This is a little exercise
Work out what the correction in the metric is
Dropping anything which is quadratic in f
Dropping anything which is higher order
And I'll tell you what you get
That hmn
M and n now just run over x and y
Is equal
To dfm
By dxn
Plus
Dfn
By dxm
That will mean
Nothing to you until you
try to work out an example
Or until you try to prove it
This is
The correction to the metric
It's a correction to the metric
Which is small
Why?
Because I chose f to be small
It has the form
Of
A small
Perturbation
On the metric
But it doesn't represent anything
It represents just a trivial
Change
So there are some
Let's call them perturbations
Perturbations mean a small change
Perturbations
On the original form of the metric
Which are trivial
They don't represent anything
Likewise here
There are small fluctuations
That you can write down
Which just represent curvilinear
Coordinates in space time
How do you get rid of that?
How do you get rid of it and eliminate
The phony
Solutions which
Automatically solve the equation
Because they're just flat space
But which don't represent any real physics
And you do it
By imposing more equations
More equations
On the metric
That sort of cut away
And divide out and eliminate
The unwanted spurious solutions
I could write down the equations
It's not important
They're just equations
Which tell you
Get rid of the spurious
Coordinate
Coordinate ambiguities
And you can do that in a wide variety
Of ways
Wide variety of conditions
That will allow you to eliminate
The unphysical
Meaningless
Solutions of Einstein's equations
Once you've done that
And you've imposed
All of the Einstein equations
Here
Once you've done that incidentally
The equations become pretty simple
And in fact
All they become
Is wave equations
They become wave equations
They become several different equations
They become first of all
Ordinary,
just perfectly
Ordinary wave equations
For the components of H
Same kind of wave equations
That I wrote down
Where did I write them down
I guess I erased them
d second phi by dt squared
Minus d second phi
By dx squared
Blah blah blah
Y squared and z squared is equal to zero
Alright
So there's some
And let me write them now
In the correct form
Instead of phi
We have H here
H mu nu
Each component
Of the metric tensor
Or each component
Of the fluctuation
Satisfies a wave equation
That means that all the components
Of the wave equation
Sorry,
all the components
Of the metric
Just move down the axis
Like waves
And there are waves
On the other hand
There are also some constraints
The constraints come
There's a lot more equations
How many equations are there
Well
There are more equations
Than one for each mu and nu
The reason
That there are more equations
Is because you have to divide
Out this spurious
Fake solutions
That are there because of the coordinate ambiguity
Once you do that
You find out that the physical solutions
The ones that really have meaning
I'm going to classify them now for you
Supposing
We have a wave moving down the z axis
Let's suppose we have a wave
Moving down the z axis
What does a wave
Moving down the z axis look like
Wave moving down the z axis
If it were just a simple wave
Would just be phi
Is equal to something like
Some number
Times sine
Of k times
x minus z
Sorry,
times z minus t
Times t minus z
z minus t
t minus z,
doesn't matter
Same thing
This is a wave
That at a fixed
Instant of time is just a sine wave
And it moves down the axis
With unit velocity
Unit velocity here means the speed of light
Alright
Now,
each one of the components
Will have a
Solution like that
Each component
Will be proportional to sine k
Times,
what is k incidentally
It's the wave number
Right
It's the frequency of the wave
It's also the wave number
The number of oscillations per unit length
And of course it can be anything
It can be any number
Short wavelengths have large k
Long wavelengths have small k
Okay
So that's a typical solution
Of a wave equation
And the solutions to this equation here
Are all of the same type
H naught
Is equal to
Some function
Well there's a coefficient here
We call the coefficient phi naught
Phi naught is just a number
Alright,
each component
Is a function of
T and z
Which is proportional to the same thing
Sine k times t minus z
Times a number
Which we can call
H naught
Let's put mu and nu here
Mu and nu
And this is not a function of position
It's just a numerical coefficient
That multiplies
The sine of t minus z
And that's about all you can write down
This is the nature of a gravitational wave
Each component of the metric
Behaving like a wave
Moving down the axis
However,
as I said
There are more equations
The additional equations
There's a good number of equations here
And when you impose them all
You find out
Oh let's
Before we do this
Let's just remind ourselves
That we're going to do
Electromagnetism
In electromagnetism
We do the same thing
We solve Maxwell's field equations
We can solve Maxwell's field equations
Either for the vector potential
Or the electric and magnetic fields
But when we write down
All the equations
We find some constraints
The constraints are called
Transversality of the field
Does everybody know what
Transversality of an electromagnetic field means
It means that the electromagnetic field
The electric and magnetic fields
Always point in the directions
Perpendicular to the motion of the wave
Not only are the solutions waves
But they're transverse waves
Meaning to say that the electric field
And the magnetic field
The magnetic field points one way
The electric field points the other way
And the whole thing goes down the axis
Oscillating as it goes down the axis
Very similar thing to the
But the way things happen here
The waves have to be transverse
To say that the waves are transverse
Means that the time components
And the z components of h are zero
The only components of h
Which are allowed to be non-zero
Are the components in the plane
Perpendicular to the direction of the wave
So if you substitute this in
To all the equations
The full set of equations here
You get the following
Including the ones which
Remove the fake spurious
Fluctuations
You find
That
A gravitational wave has a very very
Simple form
Well it does have
This form
A set of
Numbers h nu
But the only components
That are allowed
It's a
This is z
X and y
I'll call
I and j
Represent
The directions in the plane
Perpendicular to the motion of the wave
Then the only components
Which are allowed
Are h i j
Times sine
K z
K z minus
K times k
Z minus t
So if you're looking down the z-axis
If you're looking down the z-axis
You see in front of you
The xy plane
You see in front of you the xy plane
There's the xy plane
And the xy plane
At each
Z and t
I slice
Here's my slice
I slice it at a given location
At a given time
At a given location and a given time
The metric
Of the two dimensional plane
I slice the wave
Into two dimensional planes
As I go down the axis here
At a fixed instant of time
And what I have here
Is a metric
For each z
Which
Looks like
Where is it?
Right over here
With only two
With only components
With the components only in the plane
Perpendicular to the motion of the
Of the
Of the wave
And the components are simply numbers
At each z and t
The metric is simply
A set of numbers
There's one more equation
One more equation that I
I'm going to show you
It comes from Einstein's field equations
And it says
That the trace of hij is equal to zero
In other words
Hxx
Plus hyy
Is equal to zero
That's it
That's the whole set of equations
And what it tells you is that the metric
The metric
Of a gravitational wave is
H00 equals zero
Hzz
Is equal to zero
In fact,
h anything
With either a time component
Or a space or a z component
Are equal to zero
The only components
Which are not zero
Are
Hxx
Hyy
And hxy
Hyx
The metric tensor is symmetric
And so hxy
And hyx
Are the same
And finally
Hxx plus hyy
Is equal to zero
Which means that hyy
Is minus hxx
So the metric tensor
Is equal to zero
Well,
hyy is equal to minus hxx
That's pretty simple
But what does it mean
First of all,
all of these
Vary
With z and t
They vary only with z and t
going down the z-axis.
Then by definition,
the variation is along the z-axis,
and so
hxx is some number to begin with
times sine kx times sine kz minus t.
This one
is h naught yy sine k times z minus t,
and likewise this one is
h naught xy sine kx times,
yeah,
okay.
Okay,
so think of a series of layers.
Let's look at it at a fixed instant of time.
At a fixed
instant of time,
for example,
time t equals zero,
as we move down the z-axis,
there's a perturbation on the metric.
The metric tensor is a little bit
different from just a flat space metric.
It oscillates as you go down the z-axis,
and the components that oscillate are the components that have to
do with the metric of the plane perpendicular to the wave.
What does it mean to have an hxx?
Well,
let's just take the case of hxx.
If there's
an hxx,
that means that the x-x component
of the metric is a little bit
different than 1.
The x-x component of the metric was originally 1,
that's a ,
and it's 1.
plus this little bit,
blah blah blah,
plus this little bit.
That means that proper distances along the x-axis
are a little bit different than actual distances,
let's say between x equals 0 and 1,
or let's say between x equals minus 1 and 1.
But the actual distance,
the actual distance,
remember the metric tensor is the thing
which tells you the actual distance between points.
The coordinates are just labels.
The actual distance between point minus 1 and point plus 1 is
a little bit different than it would be if this perturbation weren't here.
Either a little bit larger separation
or a little bit smaller separation,
depending on the sign of hxx.
For example,
if hxx is positive,
then the actual physical distance between here and here
would be a little bit larger than 1 meter,
supposing we're working in meters.
That would mean that a meter stick
doesn't quite extend from minus 1 to 1.
What about gyy?
What about gx?
Well,
we'll take hxx to be positive.
If hxx is positive,
did I say that?
Yeah,
I did get that right.
The distance between minus 1 and 1
is a little bit bigger than a meter,
and therefore a real meter stick would look,
would not look,
it would be a little bit shorter
than the interval between minus 1 and 1.
Not because the meter stick is necessarily shorter,
but because the coordinates are such that at that,
on that surface,
the distance between the meter stick and
the meter stick is a little bit shorter.
And if it were just a
white bit of glass right there,
the distance between minus 1 and plus 1
would be a little bit bigger than a meter.
Alright,
what about gyy?
Gyy is equal to 1 minus hxx.
Minus hxx,
because Einstein's equations tell us that the
sum of these two are equal to zero.
That,
in turn,
tells us that a meter stick oriented along
the 1- coexistencealter's term will not make much difference.
y-axis,
let's say from y equals 1 to minus 1,
here's again 1 minus 1,
a meter stick would
look a little longer.
The distance between plus 1 and minus
1 would be a little bit less
than if you only had the 1 here,
and so our meter stick
over here would look a little
bit longer.
Now,
this would just be,
this would be nothing but a squeezing of the coordinates
so that you would be choosing coordinates
along the x-axis where the meter stick was
a little bit less than 1 unit and the
meter stick along the y-axis was a little bit greater
than 1.
It would be nothing at all,
it would be nothing significant except for the fact
that it would be a little bit longer.
So,
what happens is that it changes
as you go down the axis.
As you go down the axis,
from one point to another,
or if the wave were passing you,
imagine better even yet,
the wave was passing you,
the wave is passing these meter sticks.
After a brief amount of
time,
the h's will change sign,
not the sign but S-I-G-N,
the sine wave oscillates,
so
after a brief interval of time,
one half-cycle of the wave,
hxx has changed sign,
hyy has
changed sign and the result is
after a brief interval of time,
the meter stick will look
a little bit short in these coordinates along the y-axis,
and the meter stick will look
a little bit long along the x-axis.
Yeah.
The meter stick will look a
little bit short along the y-axis.
The meter stick is held together electromagnetically,
it's not changing length,
so you're talking about two little test masses?
In fact,
two little test masses would move back and forth,
but not because...
The meter stick is one meter long.
It's always one meter long.
But an oscillating wave is going back and forth,
perturbing it.
A real wave,
a real wave of curvature.
This is real curvature.
And if you like,
I think one way to imagine it...
Well,
the time dependence of this
wave really does exert tidal forces.
They're not just tidal forces.
They're tidal forces.
The wave has curvature.
The wave is moving past here.
It's a kind of tidal force.
And the nature of the tidal force is
to actually cause the meter stick to be compressed,
stretched,
compressed,
stretched.
And the way that it's compressed and
stretched is that when it's compressed horizontally,
it's stretched vertically.
When it's compressed vertically,
it's stretched horizontally.
So,
if you like,
this wave going by a meter stick,
or for that matter,
if it were just two test masses,
if it really were just two test masses,
the two test masses would oscillate back and forth.
If instead of taking a meter stick,
you took a square piece of plywood,
the square piece of plywood would be deformed this way,
and then reverse.
This way,
Now,
it's interesting.
There is another solution.
There is another solution in which
not HX and HY are non-zero,
but in which HXY is non-zero.
That would be a metric
which would look like a Kronecker delta,
delta mn,
or delta ij,
plus a little matrix which had an
HXY over here and an HXY over here.
That still has HXX plus HYY equal to zero.
There is no HXX,
HYY.
If you think about it a little bit,
and just spend a little bit
of time figuring out what this means,
it's also exactly the same kind of thing,
except that the squeezing and stretching
are along the 45 degree axes.
Stretch this way,
squeeze this way.
Oscillating.
It's not a new thing.
It's not a new solution,
except that it's the original solution turned by an angle.
In fact,
any solution that you write down,
which is a superposition of these two kinds of solutions,
any solution is a linear superposition of the two solutions,
and they correspond to some orientation of axes,
where along those axes the compression
and expansion are along those tilted axes.
That's all there is.
That's all the kind of gravitational waves there are.
You pick a set of axes perpendicular.
First of all,
you pick the direction that the
gravitational waves are going to go.
The direction that the gravitational wave is moving.
What do you use to measure
this compression that does not change?
A strain gauge.
This will create honest,
real stresses in the piece of plywood.
A strain gauge will register them.
When this wave is going past,
if the wave was static,
if the wave was static and not moving,
then this piece of plywood would really be unaffected.
Everything would be simultaneously squeezed
or stretched the same way.
The rulers which measure the plywood,
the strain gauges which measure,
but it's the oscillating character of the solution
which really does create real
honest stresses and strains in it.
It does have real curvature.
And this is what it does.
What triggers the gravitational waves?
An electromagnetic wave is triggered by currents.
Or by a moving charge.
Or by a charge.
For example,
one charge of an electron going around a proton
will create electromagnetic waves.
The same thing,
a star or a black hole
or a pulsar or whatever it is,
in orbit around another one,
a binary pulsar for example,
the famous binary pulsar,
two very,
very concentrated masses,
which happen to be rotating around
each other at a rather small distance.
Neither one is a black hole.
The whole thing is not a black hole.
But it is a very,
very strong gravitational field.
They're going around each other.
And in going around each other,
the accelerating masses create the gravitational waves.
So,
now near the binary pulsar,
this is a bad approximation.
The gravitational field is too strong
to linearize the equation this way.
But if you get back,
you know,
a few radii,
a few distances away,
then the wave spreads out,
dilutes itself,
and gets weak enough that this becomes a good approximation.
So,
if you had the binary pulsars over there,
and you're standing back,
the wave is coming at you,
let's say the axis between you
and the binary pulsar is the z-axis,
then what you'll see coming
past you will look like this.
And what it will do is
it will cause stresses and strains
along perpendicular to the line of sight to the pulsar.
Yeah?
To clarify,
that red meter stick you have,
is it the red one?
Yeah.
The red meter stick is an abstract meter stick,
not a real physical meter stick?
Well,
it could be a real physical meter stick.
But it changes,
right?
It has stresses in it.
Other than the stresses and strains,
how do you measure it with a variable meter stick?
Well,
I think the way you measure it is by
the stresses and strains that are induced in it.
You know,
it's hard to say that it's not a meter,
because it's by definition a meter stick.
But it's a variable,
in essence,
it's variable.
Yeah,
in fact,
if you had a steel meter
stick and a wood meter stick,
they would probably react differently.
They would probably react differently.
So,
once these stresses are applied,
once the stress due to the curvature tensor here,
and it's a real thing,
the curvature tensor,
it is a kind of tidal force.
Once these tidal forces are applied,
the meter sticks,
the two meter sticks,
the steel one and the wood one,
will stress by different amounts in general.
So,
if you measured the wooden meter
stick with the steel meter stick,
I'm not sure which one would be
bigger and which one would be smaller,
but they wouldn't match up precisely.
Yeah.
Would this be how you
would build a gravity wave detector?
That's kind of the point I was making before.
A steel meter stick has got a big elastic modulus.
It's not going to shrink very
much when the wave goes past.
But if you have two test masses that are
floating right at the ends of the meter stick,
they have no elastic modulus.
They'll move right with the space time.
That's right.
Well,
no.
No,
they won't move quite with the space time.
They'll be accelerated.
Yeah.
So,
they'll start ringing.
Now,
if you want to detect a gravitational wave,
what you want to do is
create some system which has a resonance
at the frequency of the gravitational wave.
You know what a resonance is.
A resonance means that the
system has its own natural frequency,
frequency of oscillation,
which is the same as
the oscillation frequency of the wave.
Then you would have a driven system
being driven at its own natural frequency,
and under those circumstances,
the response will be particularly big.
So,
if you wanted to detect a gravitational wave,
oh,
let me say that the gravitational
waves that we expect to detect
in astronomy from different sources,
I'm not,
believe me,
I'm not an expert at this,
but I know enough about it
to know that the H mu nu,
which are produced by a distant gravitational source,
are very,
very small.
They're so small that the
dimensionless strain on a steel rod
or something like that would be
something like 10 to the minus 21.
Really,
really small effects.
The fact that people even
contemplate measuring them is quite astonishing,
but it seems they can be measured.
And...
No,
no.
There is a system that measures the legal system.
There is a system that is built in two places,
I think one in Louisiana and some other place,
which is measuring the interference of...
Laser waves,
I believe.
I'm not sure what you're asking.
LIGO or...
LIGO.
Yeah.
But they have...
LIGO is a gravitational detector.
It's not sensitive enough.
It's not a steel rod.
It's a pair of mirrors,
which are monitored by laser beams,
interference effects due to the
relative motion and so forth.
But basically,
a gravitational detector
is a system which is
allowed to be set into oscillation
either this way or that way.
And...
Yeah.
Is there a velocity that comes out of those solutions?
Oh,
yeah.
The speed of light.
Okay.
It's not been artificially in advance by...
No,
no.
It's the speed of light.
So if you were...
If you saw a gravitational collapse,
a gravitational collapse
or the collision of two black holes
would make...
And that happens from time to time.
When I say it happens,
I mean to say that you can estimate
roughly from observed facts
how many black holes are out there,
and you can guess how many black hole collisions
take place every year.
And if I remember,
I think within range of such...
of the best imagined detectors...
If I remember,
I think it's about one black hole per year.
So it's a lot.
When...
Right.
So...
In principle,
if it was possible to detect a black hole collision
through other means other than gravitational radiation,
you ought to see the signal
at the same time as the gravitational radiation.
Gravitational radiation
is a pretty weak effect when you're far back.
But it's not...
But from the collision of two black holes,
it's an enormous effect when you're...
It's much bigger than any
other kind of radiation that's emitted.
So if the collision is taking place
at large cosmological distances,
it can be the case that
the only way to detect it
would be through gravitational radiation,
gravitational waves like this.
That's why it's interesting,
because it's a new window
on...
for astronomy.
Okay,
that's what gravitational radiation is,
or that's what gravitational waves are.
They're real.
I mean...
You asked me if gravitational
radiation has ever been detected.
Yes and no.
It's never been detected by direct detectors.
But...
Just like electromagnetic radiation,
for example,
from an orbiting system,
radiation carries off energy.
Carrying off energy means that as
two systems are rotating about each other,
they will lose energy,
and in losing energy,
they may speed up a little bit.
They will speed up a little bit
due to the loss of energy.
And so the study of
this binary pulsar that's out there,
which is...
has all the properties necessary for gravitational radiation
to be emitted from it,
when the timing of the...
procession...
not the procession,
the rotation of the two systems about each other,
they are...
the frequency is changing a little bit in time,
exactly as would be expected,
quantitatively exactly as would be expected from the system
if it were emitting gravitational radiation.
Gravitational radiation is the main thing
which would cause its energy to change,
and it works out exactly right.
So...
What sorts of frequencies are we talking about?
Milliseconds?
I think milliseconds.
Yeah.
I think.
But,
um...
You look it up,
I'm not sure.
It might be a little slower than milliseconds.
Milliseconds is what a pulsar does
when it rotates around its own axis.
It might be a little slower than that.
If I remember correctly,
it's days.
Oh,
days.
Okay,
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
This is two stars going around each other.
What am I saying?
Milliseconds?
No.
Milliseconds is for the rotation of the pulsar.
These are two stars going around each other.
It's not the...
Take back what I said.
Okay,
yeah.
We arbitrarily took x and y as two coordinates
that we decided to put them on a flat line.
What about if we took x and t?
In other words,
how would it affect space-time
rather than just the space?
This is the time direction.
The wave has a directionality along which it's moving.
The wave is transverse,
which means the only
components that have physical significance
are the ones in the plane perpendicular
to the direction of motion of the wave.
The other components are either not there
or they correspond to a wiggle in the coordinates.
The other components are either wiggles in the coordinates
or they're not there.
Yeah?
I looked it up.
For the original binary pulsar,
where the detection is done,
it's 7.75 hours.
Okay.
Geometric mean of a day and a million...
Right.
How much has it changed over
the period that it's been observed,
though?
A very small number.
About 30 seconds.
Really?
That much?
Yeah,
but it's been looked at for...
Decades.
Yeah.
So,
time is actually oscillating as well,
like you just said?
It's not time is not oscillating.
The wave is oscillating with time.
If you stood in one place,
the wave would oscillate with time.
Yes,
but you were going to ask.
Well,
but time is one of these coordinates,
right?
Yeah.
In fourth dimensional space.
Time is a coordinate.
And it is orthogonal to z.
No,
no,
no.
When I said orthogonal to z,
I meant the space directions orthogonal to z.
But there is time.
There is time.
And the components of the metric
which have a time component in them
all are equal to zero.
It's very much like an electromagnetic wave.
The electromagnetic wave also has space and time,
or electromagnetic field also has space and time components.
The vector potential has space and time components.
In a wave moving down the z-axis,
only the transverse space components
of the vector potential are there.
So it's very much like that.
You said before that H
zero zero and H zero x,
H zero y,
H zero z,
are all zero.
Yep.
So there's no curvature in the time direction.
Well,
no,
there is curvature in the time direction.
Remember,
some things,
yeah,
the H's in those directions are non-zero,
but when you differentiate,
you can differentiate with respect to time,
and get the time into it,
right.
So,
derivative of H,
let's say,
x,
y,
with respect to t,
is not equal to zero.
And remember,
the curvature tensor has two derivatives on H,
so you can get a whole
collection of different kind of components.
Yeah.
But still,
it's a very special kind of curvature
that's not generic.
Okay,
that's gravitational waves.
You can,
you can,
learn more about them by
any good book on general relativity,
which will assault,
work,
write down the details of these equations.
You know they will,
and we'll fill about one blackboard,
but it won't be terribly illuminating.
But uh...
the basic principle I've told you.
Any other questions?
Yeah?
So we start out with detto-
Einstein's equations,
equations which are non-linear,
we wind up with a wave
equation which I believe is linear.
Only because we made the
approximation of a very small h.
Okay,
so it's got nothing to do
with getting rid of the non-physical solutions?
No,
no,
no.
The linearity is because the wave is weak.
Generally speaking,
I tried to explain before,
small oscillations about an equilibrium
and the approximation that the
oscillation is very small are linear.
This is linear because of an approximation that h
is so small that the square of it is zero.
Any other questions?
Yes?
If you do this approximation like we did and then you go back
at the end and see how far off it was from an accurate solution,
how much error is there?
Depends how big h is.
If h is .001,
the corrections will be .00...
If h is 1 tenth,
the corrections will be 1%.
Whatever h is,
the corrections will be of order the square of it.
Yeah.
So right,
so that's something you always do.
When you make a linearized approximation,
you always check at the end that
the corrections to it would be small.
But they will be if h is small enough.
Yes?
If you make h much larger so
there is a component of a higher order,
would that affect the fact that i
and j are perpendicular to the z-axis?
Would that...
No.
But what it will affect is
whether waves will pass through each other.
They won't.
They will scatter off each other.
Right.
No,
the wave will maintain...that's a good question,
but the wave will maintain its transverse character.
Yeah.
In the mechanical wave,
the magnitude of the mechanical wave is related
to the energy and the stiffness of the material.
The energy and the stiffness of the material,
yeah.
Is there any sense in talking
about the stiffness of the material?
Yeah,
yeah.
The stiffness of a material determines
the velocity of propagation through the material.
So you can substitute for stiffness.
You can substitute velocity of propagation.
Electromagnetic and gravitational waves are extremely stiff.
They are the stiffest things possible
in that the speed of light...
And that they are both
governed by the speed of light.
So the...you know,
in the old days when people thought about the
ether and things and the mechanical properties of the ether,
they attributed a stiffness...what is it called?
A Young's modulus or whatever it's called to...
To the ether.
And it was a very,
very big Young...a very,
very big coefficient of whatever it's called
because the speed of light is so
much larger than the speed of propagation,
for example,
through a metal beam.
So...
We no longer really think of it as a stiffness,
but if you did think about it as a stiffness,
you would say that the...
the space on which these waves move is very stiff.
Well,
it's really the stiffness divided by the density,
isn't it?
Mm-hmm.
So either it's very stiff or there's not much density.
Yeah.
And only the combination of them appears in
the...in the propagation of...in the propagation of light.
Right.
That's true.
It's just one combination,
namely the velocity which appears.
Right.
True enough.
Okay.
Let's...
In the little bit of time that we have,
I just wanted to tell you about another
way of thinking about the equations of general relativity.
Again...
The complexity of actually carrying
out the equations is too complicated,
but nevertheless,
the basic idea is there.
One of the things I've
told you and emphasized to you,
particularly in classical mechanics,
is that the principle of least action is the
most central principle of classical physics that we have.
All systems that we know about...
Mechanical systems,
electromagnetic radiation,
quantum field theory,
all of these things,
the standard model of particle physics,
they're all governed by an action principle.
And the action is something which in field theory,
in...for ordinary particle mechanics,
the action is an integral
along the trajectory of the particle,
so it's an integral over time.
The action of a field...
is an integral over space and time.
A field configuration is a value of the
field at every point of space and time.
So,
we draw.
Here's space-time.
All of it.
I've gotten it all down onto the blackboard.
Time goes this way.
Space goes this way.
Here's everything.
A field configuration,
or a field history,
even better,
a field history,
is just labeled by...is basically a value of the field,
or...
fields,
at every point on here.
So,
it's some field,
let's call it generically phi,
and it's a function of x and t,
and that's a field configuration.
Not every configuration is a solution
of the equations of a theory.
Just like not every trajectory...
is a solution of the equations of motion,
every trajectory is a thinkable trajectory,
but not every trajectory satisfies the equations of motion.
In the same way,
every phi of x and t is a thinkable
possible value of a field in space and time,
but they're not all solutions.
And,
in general,
to the best of our knowledge,
every such field is governed
by a principle of least action.
The principle of least action involves some action,
which is composed out of the fields.
This is just a generic...
term for field.
It's an integral...
it's an integral over space and time,
dx,
dt,
and x now means x,
y,
and z,
so it's a four-dimensional integral,
of some thing,
usually called the Lagrange density,
which is a function of the fields,
and their derivatives.
Let's call them phi sub mu,
derivatives of the field with respect to x mu.
And what do you do with this?
You minimize it,
or you make it stationary.
You find the field configurations,
let's use shorthand,
which minimize the action,
subject to a constraint.
You go out to a large space,
some large distance,
and some large times.
You take some region of space-time,
and you say what the values are on the boundary.
It's the same deal as when
you look at a particle motion,
and you say I'm interested in the solution,
given that the particle goes through two points.
Given that the particle starts someplace,
and ends someplace,
then what's the trajectory in between?
In the same way,
you say,
supposing you know that the field,
at some late time,
has some value,
let's say final,
phi initial,
and you ask,
what is the solution which interpolates between these two?
The answer will be the field that,
or the solutions that make the action stationary.
Okay,
so the point here is that the field equations,
the Einstein field equations,
can be derived from an action principle.
It's a long computation,
but the action is simple.
I'm just going to tell you what the action is,
and then you can go home,
and try to take that action,
and apply the Euler Lagrange equations to it,
and see if you can derive Einstein's field equations.
I guarantee you it can be done.
I also can tell you I never finished it.
I started it several times,
and never quite got to the end of it.
Uh,
but it is,
it's just tedious.
It's straightforward,
but tedious.
Alright,
so you go back,
and you look at Euler Lagrange equations,
I'll tell you what the action is.
It has some interesting pieces in it.
First of all,
let's do a simpler thing first.
Let's just calculate the space-time volume.
I will tell you what I mean,
but,
well,
let's actually even think about ordinary space for a minute.
Let's suppose we have ordinary space,
and it has a metric,
g m n.
When I'm thinking about space,
I use m n.
g m n dx m dx n.
That's the metric,
ds squared.
The distance between two neighboring
points is given by this formula.
Now supposing I'm interested in the
volume of a small region of space,
let's say dx dy.
Let me begin by supposing the metric has two components,
g x x and g y y.
And I have a small interval
dx and a small interval dy.
I want to know the area,
and we'll call it the volume.
Volume means three dimensions,
area means two dimensions,
but they're the same concept.
Okay,
what's the area of this,
little square?
The area of the little square,
I would know it
if I knew the distance,
the actual proper distance associated with dx,
and the actual proper distance associated with dy.
Alright,
what's the proper distance associated
with a little x dx here?
Square root of g x x,
square root of g x x,
dx.
Can you read that?
Let's make it bigger.
This distance is square root of g x x,
dx,
and this distance is square root of g y y,
dy.
So,
what's the area of the rectangle?
It's square root of g x x,
square root of g y y,
dx,
dy.
It's not just the x,
The important thing is it's not
just the x or the y.
No more so than the distance between two
points is just the x or the y.
The actual physical area is the
square root of g x x,
dy.
The actual physical area in this case
is the square root of g x x,
g y y.
Now,
I've used a case here where there was
only g x x and g y y.
There could be other components of the metric.
If you work it out,
this is a special case.
This is a special case where
there's no off-diagonal g x y term.
Here,
let's think of it this way.
You have a metric,
you have a matrix,
g x x,
g y y.
Now,
there may be some other components here,
g x y and g x y.
But what I tell you is that when
there's no g x x and g y y,
sorry,
when there's no off-diagonal components,
the volume element involves the product of g x x,
g y y.
Can you guess what the general formula is?
What replaces that product?
The determinant.
The determinant is g x x,
g y y minus g x y squared.
The determinant is exactly right.
So,
if you actually work out the volume
element of a little square like this,
or a little rectangle,
v x d y,
the actual answer is not g x x,
g y y.
It's g x x,
g y y minus g x y squared,
which is the term as
the determinant of the tensor g.
It's usually just written with two
bars to represent determinant and g.
That's the formula for the volume element,
or for the volume of a small differential,
d x and d y.
What would be the,
and this can be in curved space,
this is in curved space or any space,
whatever.
So,
given a little rectangle,
d x d y,
in coordinate space,
the area,
or in higher dimensions it would be the volume,
would just be the square root of g,
square root of the determinant of
g times d x d y.
If I have some large region,
and I want the total volume of it,
I integrate this.
The integral of square root of the determinant
of the metric times d x d y,
that is equal to the area,
of the entire region enclosed within some boundary.
What about the volume of space?
If we're talking about volume,
in other words,
three-dimensional space.
Well,
it's exactly the same,
except you have d z here.
Exactly the same.
Square root of the determinant of
the metric is called the volume element.
It's usually called the volume element.
And if you have four-dimensional space times,
it's useful to define a similar concept,
which would just involve the fourth component.
We call it the space-time volume.
It's an interesting quantity.
It's invariant.
It's the same in every coordinate system.
That's the important thing about it.
If you re-coordinatize the region,
change coordinates,
this quantity stays the same.
The volume,
in some sense,
the physical volume of a region of space time,
or the physical four-dimensional volume
of a region of space time.
And this integral is an invariant quantity.
Other invariants,
other quantities,
which are invariant and which will not change
when you change coordinates,
are based on this quantity.
If you take the volume element,
and you integrate it with any scalar,
let's call the scalar S of X,
S of X and T,
the X,
D,
T,
this also is an invariant quantity
which doesn't depend on the coordinates.
It's just the sum.
You take each little volume element,
you take its volume,
and you multiply it by the square root,
sorry,
by the scalar field.
You take the volume of each little element,
multiply it by the scalar quantity in there,
and add them all up.
That's a quantity which is really not dependent
in any way on the coordinates you use,
even though writing it down
may use a certain set of coordinates.
Action is a thing
which is supposed to be invariant.
Action in relativity theory
is always supposed to be the same
in every coordinate frame.
Otherwise,
the laws of physics
which came out of it
would depend on the coordinate system.
If the laws of physics are supposed to be
the same in every coordinate frame,
one way of ensuring that
is to make the action an invariant,
a quantity which doesn't change
from coordinate to coordinate,
from coordinate system to coordinate system.
So it's natural then
to take the action to be,
I'll call it D4X,
meaning
DX,
DY,
DC,
DT,
some kind,
well,
the square root of G,
the square root of the determinant of the metric,
times some scalar.
Now let's just take the Einstein theory
without any energy momentum tensor
on the right hand side.
Just pure gravitational field,
nothing else.
What kind of scalar could I put there?
How many scalars are there
that I can make up only out of the metric?
Well,
Indeed.
So,
that's called R.
It's the thing on the right,
let's see,
it's the,
that's a scalar.
Anything else you can think of?
I'll tell you there's one more thing.
The other thing is any number,
7 or 4 or 16,
or whatever number you like.
So you can add to this
a numerical number.
Numerical numbers are always regarded as invariants.
Everybody who sees 7 sees the same number.
And the number that you put here,
depends on the laws of physics.
It is a law of physics.
It itself is a law of physics.
It has a name,
what's it called?
Alright,
I'll tell you what it's,
I'll tell you what its symbol is.
Its symbol is lambda.
Now what's it called?
The cosmological constant.
It's a term in the action
which is just proportional to the space-time volume itself.
The term in the action,
lambda times this integral
is just the space-time action itself.
The cosmological constant
has not been,
I have not included it
in these equations here.
These are the solutions,
these are the equations without cosmological constants.
So without cosmological constant,
this is the action.
And Einstein's equations
are completely equivalent
to saying minimize this,
or make it stationary,
make its variation equal to zero,
away from a solution.
That's minimizing something,
is making it stationary.
Yeah?
What does the stress-energy tensor come into it?
The stress-energy tensor would come in
as additional terms in the action
which would depend on the material
and the other fields.
For example,
there could be electromagnetic energy,
there could be other kinds of energy,
they would come in as additional terms here.
This is the vacuum?
Yeah,
this is the vacuum theory.
This is the vacuum theory,
for example,
the theory which would govern gravitational waves.
Other things could be in here,
but those other things would be made up
out of different fields.
They always have a square root of g,
they always have a scalar.
If you remember your electromagnetism,
the electromagnetic field is described
by an anti-symmetric tensor,
F mu nu.
One of the things that you would put here
would be F mu nu,
F mu nu.
That would govern the electromagnetic field.
But let's leave that out.
Let's leave that out.
Here's the Einstein,
the Hilbert-Einstein action,
discovered,
I think,
just about simultaneously by Einstein and Hilbert.
Of course,
Einstein already had that.
He already had the whole works,
knew how it all worked,
but they independently sat down and said,
can these equations be derived from an action principle?
And both of them,
Hilbert and Einstein,
both came up with the same answer.
This is it.
So this is a shorthand,
but not just a shorthand,
a physical principle
that contains all the Einstein field.
Incidentally,
what replaces this field?
I said a field in space.
What do you put in there?
The metric.
This is an action that's
made up out of the metric,
and you vary the metric a little bit,
you vary the metric a little bit,
and you look for places
where you found a minimum of value.
What's the negative quality of that?
A solution.
You have a single solution.
Why would you consider Sirius
not going to support this applies to the底 Superior
audiobook.
Today's lecture on Ninguidal basketball
is entirely specific to this problem,
the metric.
You do that by first calculating the Christoffel symbols,
then differentiating
the Christoffel symbols,
multiplying them together,
sticking them all together,
multiply
it by the square,
do whatever contractions are necessary
to produce the curvature scalar,
multiply it by the square root
of the determinant of the metric,
it's a four by four metric,
four rows,
four columns,
the determinant is a great big
thing made up out of lots of
components,
calculate the determinant,
and then apply the Euler-Lagrange variational
equations to that action,
and it takes about five minutes,
the whole operation,
and out
of it you will get Einstein's field equations.
If you can't do it in five minutes,
you fail
the course.
As I said,
I've been trying to do it for
fifty years and I've failed.
I've never quite succeeded.
A lot of my friends have,
but...
There's a whole chapter in Tute's General Relativity Notes,
and it's very involved,
because it does all the things you talked about,
and he plucks certain things out of
the air because he knows the
answer and then just verifies it,
so it's really not easy.
No,
no,
no.
As I've told you repeatedly,
the principles
are not terribly hard.
For whatever reason,
somehow in the...
You know,
there are people who have such a
good visual feel for curvature and differential
geometry that they can more or less see through it.
You have your choice.
Either you're a person with a
great deal of visual ability to be
able to see through the complexity of a...
You know,
you have curvature,
tensors,
and so forth,
and figure out how to do these processes
by almost visualization,
or you work them out by the algebra.
So if you're good at algebra,
you do it one way.
If you're good at visualizing geometry and
you have a great command of differential geometry,
you probably can short-circuit a lot of that.
I,
frankly,
have neither.
I am not very good
at algebra.
And I certainly don't have the visual
ability to be able to visualize four-dimensional curvature
tensors.
So repeatedly,
I have sat down and tried to do this calculation,
usually in the process
of teaching the subject,
and give up after about two hours.
If I had to do it,
I could,
but since I don't have to,
I don't.
All right.
I don't ever tell any of
my friends that I don't know.
I can't do it.
Okay.
They'll see something.
Hmm?
They'll see.
Yeah,
I know.
They know I can't do it.
So this is not standardly written
down in a text on relativity?
It probably is,
but it fills pages.
I'm sure it is filled,
written down somewheres.
It doesn't help,
because when you have a thing of that complexity,
it really doesn't help
to follow the steps from one step to another.
Either you do them yourself and you figure
out what the relation between the steps is,
or you don't.
A very long calculation really is not very
illuminating unless you try to do it yourself,
and then when you run into trouble,
you peek.
Oh,
that's the next step.
And then you understand why it's the next step.
But I've never learned anything
by looking at these long steps.
These days,
people don't do them.
People throw them on a computer,
either numerically or analytically,
and let the computer grind
out because it's just too nasty and complicated.
Yeah?
In hindsight,
this seems more motivated than
the way Einstein did it originally.
But I'm wondering,
I think it went from 1905 to 1916.
Yeah.
And then it went from 1916 to 1916,
before he published General Relativity.
What do you think?
Is it apparent from his papers what was
taking so long to put it all together?
The only papers I read were the early
ones around 1907 and then the 1916 paper.
And I read them 50 years ago.
So I really don't know what the...
But part of it is that very,
very few people knew very much about Riemannian geometry.
Einstein didn't know.
He basically had to invent all of Riemannian geometry.
I think one of his friends helped him with it,
who knew some mathematics,
was it Marcel
Grossman?
I don't know.
But 10 years to put all of
this together doesn't sound like a lot.
I think it's a lot to me.
And he literally had to build
all of the ideas of curvature.
So it took a long time.
Was he aiming for that from pretty early on?
Yeah.
I think he knew what he was doing pretty well.
But you can go back and look yourself.
The papers are in English.
They were translated into English.
You can find them.
I think they're all in English.
I think we're finished for the quarter.
Yeah.
Anyway,
I could use a rest.
I'm going to take a rest.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.