Stanford University
Let's spend a few minutes talking about units.
In particular,
the Boltzmann constant.
What is the Boltzmann constant?
The Boltzmann constant,
like many constants in physics,
are conversion factors.
The speed of light is a conversion factor,
you know that.
And the conversion factor from distances to times.
And of course,
if you judiciously choose your units,
you can set the speed of light equal to one.
The Boltzmann constant is also a conversion factor.
And the Boltzmann constant is also a conversion factor.
And typically these things are conversion factors
from what I tend to call human units
to units which are,
in some sense,
more fundamental.
Human units are units which are
convenient for scales and magnitudes of quantities
which people can access reasonably easily.
Okay,
so we haven't talked about temperature.
We're going to talk about temperature,
but I thought I would
just say something about units first.
The units of temperature,
as invented by,
I guess,
19th century physicists and chemists,
I'm not sure when Fahrenheit was.
I know Kelvin,
of course,
was late 19th century.
I'm not sure who or what Fahrenheit was.
About 17th century.
Fahrenheit was 17th century?
No,
very early.
Wow,
okay.
But in any case,
the units that we tend to use
these days are Kelvin units or centigrade.
It's the same kind of unit.
Kelvin,
temperatures Kelvin are relative to absolute zero.
Temperatures centigrade are relative to what,
the freezing point of water?
Which is a totally arbitrary thing.
And the centigrade scale,
the unit of one degree,
as you well know,
was simply set by the arbitrary choice
to divide the temperature scale
between freezing and boiling of water,
freezing and boiling of water
at atmospheric pressure into 100 units.
Highly arbitrary.
Didn't have to be water.
I mean,
it was water.
It was not water that was used.
If we would have used alcohol,
it would have been a different unit.
If we would have used,
and so forth and so on.
But it was a unit which people could manipulate.
People could manipulate temperatures.
They could measure temperatures.
It's not too hard to measure
a change in temperature of a degree
with a human scale thermometer.
By human scale,
I mean,
you know,
it's made out of a lot of atoms.
It's a thing that you can make in your shell.
And so the degree Kelvin,
the one unit degree of temperature change,
is a human construct that was invented for convenience,
if you like.
Now,
it was,
at the time,
it was not fully understood,
although Kelvin may have understood it,
but it was not fully understood
that the natural units,
the real physical units,
that temperature has to do with,
is energy.
That a temperature is really an energy.
For example,
an example is that
the temperature of a gas,
for example,
determines the kinetic energy of the molecules.
And,
you know,
one measure of the temperature of the gas
is just the kinetic energy of the molecules.
Well,
you might say,
wait a minute,
that's not so good,
because if the gas is
a composite of helium and oxygen,
I don't know if it's a composite of helium and...
I choose helium because I don't want it to explode.
But helium and oxygen,
then do I mean the
helium atoms or the oxygen atoms?
Surely they have different kinetic energy,
but they don't.
The thermal equilibrium at a fixed temperature,
and we will prove this,
eventually we will prove this,
all of the atoms have basically the same kinetic energy,
and in fact,
if you put a bowling ball,
suspended a bowling ball at finite temperature
into a gas or even a liquid,
the kinetic energy of the bowling ball
would be exactly the same as the kinetic energy
of an oxygen atom.
Now,
that seems a little bit odd,
but when you think about it,
it's not that odd.
If the bowling ball has the
same energy as a single molecule,
it will surely move a
lot slower than a single molecule,
for the reason is that its mass is much larger.
So if mv squared for the bowling ball
is the same as mv squared for the oxygen molecule,
the bowling ball will be moving a lot slower.
But the main point is that temperature
is really a measure of an amount of energy.
So the natural units for temperature
are really energy,
but at the time that
temperature first started to be measured,
nobody could measure a molecule.
Nobody had the vaguest idea how big molecules,
how massive molecules were,
how much energy a typical molecule had
at a given temperature.
In fact,
probably in the beginning,
nobody had the idea that temperature had to do anything
to do with the energy of a basic constituent.
So the scale of temperatures was defined
before there was a notion that temperature,
so to speak,
equals energy.
Okay,
so the natural unit for temperature
could be joules,
for example.
A joule is a good unit of temperature.
It's a rather large unit of temperature.
To see that,
the typical energy of a single molecule
in thermal equilibrium
at a temperature of room temperature
for one molecule is a tiny,
tiny,
tiny number in joules.
And so the conversion factor
between human units
and,
let's say,
the basic units of energy
is going to be a very
large or a very small number.
So let's just define it.
I can define it by giving you the relationship
between the energy of a molecule in a dilute gas,
energy of a single molecule in a dilute gas,
dilute because we don't want to worry too much
about the energies of interaction between the molecules,
and the energy of kinetic energy.
The kinetic energy is the energy
of a molecule in a dilute gas
is equal to three halves.
Now,
the three is easy to understand.
What does it have to do with?
The dimension of space.
The dimension of space,
right.
It has a kinetic energy for moving along the x-axis.
It has a kinetic energy for moving along the y-axis.
It has a kinetic energy for moving along the z-axis.
So there's a factor of three.
And the half,
well,
that's just a glitch of definition.
All right.
So three halves,
the Boltzmann constant times the temperature,
but this is the human scale of temperature,
so it could be Kelvin.
Temperature measured in Kelvin units.
In that case,
the Boltzmann constant here
has units of energy divided by degrees Kelvin.
Energy divided by degrees Kelvin.
And it's a rather small number,
as you might expect.
If the temperature is 300 degrees,
that's room temperature.
Temperature Kelvin is 300 room temperature.
The energy of a single molecule is clearly very,
very,
very small.
And so 300 is pretty big.
E is terribly small.
K Boltzmann is very small.
And this number in human units,
human units now means standard units,
meters and so forth.
K Boltzmann is about 1.4
times 10 to the minus 23rd.
It's no accident that Avogadro's number
is also roughly 10 to the 23rd.
Not an accident,
but...
And the units are joules divided by degrees Kelvin.
The unit of a joule is a unit of energy,
and so it's a unit
of mass times a velocity squared.
We could reduce it to the standard units,
get rid of the joules if we like,
but this is what it is.
Main point is that the really interesting quantity here,
temperature in fundamental physics always
comes in multiplying K Boltzmann.
It's in all fundamental formulas of physics.
K Boltzmann times temperature comes in,
and that's just because the
fundamental quantity is really energy.
And so we redefine...
K Boltzmann times temperature has units of energy.
We redefine a new unit of temperature,
let's call it capital T,
which is just K Boltzmann
times the human unit of temperature.
And once we do that,
we will get rid of degrees...
We will get rid of K Boltzmann in all equations.
We'll never see it again.
But you do have to
remember that what I call temperature
differs from thermometer temperature by a very small factor.
Okay,
that same factor actually is there in units of entropy.
Remember what entropy is?
It's a unit of information.
It's measured in bits.
It's measured in fundamental little bits of information.
At the time that entropy
was discovered as an interesting quantity,
which always increases,
it was discovered by a steam
engineer by the name of Carnot.
And he was a steam engineer.
That's what he did for a living.
He built...
He designed steam engines.
He didn't know anything about the microscopic energy.
He didn't know anything about
the microscopic underlying principle of entropy.
He had a quantity.
The quantity wasn't so easily measured,
but he had a quantity defined in
terms of temperatures and energies and so forth.
And he called it entropy,
or somebody called it entropy.
And it got the letter S.
And I'm going to call
it little s for a minute.
And I'm going to put a sub-Carnot here.
So,
Sadi Carnot had a quantity,
which he called entropy.
It has units.
Let's see,
what are its units?
Let me cheat over here for a minute.
It's energy divided by temperature.
But if temperature measured in Kelvin,
then it's joules per Kelvin.
Joules per Kelvin was Carnot's unit of entropy.
But in modern physics,
we think of entropy as being measured in bits.
A fundamental unit of entropy is logarithm of two,
for example.
And that's dimensionless.
So there's some other notion of...
Not some other notion.
It's just a conversion factor again.
Carnot's unit of entropy differs by what
I have called entropy up till now.
I have to get the...yeah.
Okay.
Do you remember what entropy is
from a statistical point of view?
If you have a probability distribution,
if you have some probability distribution
over some discrete set of states,
then we define the entropy,
S,
capital S now,
to be minus the sum over all the states
of P sub i logarithm of P sub i.
We did that last week.
And it's a rough measure of
the logarithm of the number of states
which are important under a statistical distribution here.
That's what we called entropy.
What's the connection between Carnot's entropy
and this is Boltzmann's entropy?
Boltzmann's entropy here...
What's the connection?
The connection is simply a factor of K Boltzmann.
And it is such that this is equal
to one over K Boltzmann
times Carnot's quantity.
In other words,
when Carnot's entropy is a normal number like six
in a steam engine,
Boltzmann's entropy is enormous.
Boltzmann's entropy is roughly proportional
to the number of molecules in the system
or something like that.
But once we know this now,
once we know how to go back and forth
between human units of temperature
and human units of entropy
and the more fundamental units
for temperature,
it's energy,
for entropy,
it's a dimensionless quantity,
then from now on,
I will not introduce K Boltzmann.
The Boltzmann factor
effectively is gone out of all of our equations.
But you can put it back.
And the way of putting it back
is always,
whenever you see capital T,
and you want to get it into human units,
think of it as K Boltzmann times temperature in Kelvin,
and whenever you see an entropy S,
which has a huge,
huge value typically,
and you want to get it into steam engine units,
divide it by K Boltzmann.
Question?
Yes.
So your new units for temperature
called capital T,
other than that vector 3 halves,
isn't it just joules?
It depends on,
of course,
now it depends on what unit of energy you're using.
So if you're using the energy unit joules,
then it would be joules.
And the point is,
it's not a new unit.
What is a joule?
A joule is the energy in MKS units,
MKS meters,
kilograms,
seconds units.
So what is it?
It's the energy of a
one kilogram object,
moving at a velocity of one meter per second.
I think there's a factor of two,
one half MV squared in there,
so it's twice the energy
of a one kilo object
moving at one meter per second.
But as you had that written up there,
you got very specific that the temperature is in Kelvin,
that's a very well-specified thing.
You have a very definite constant there.
No,
it's not a very definite constant.
If you change units,
K Boltzmann will change.
If you change units instead of using for,
instead of using Kelvin units,
we use Fahrenheit units,
then K Boltzmann will change.
But I'm just looking at your equations up there,
and you've got the temperature in Kelvin.
Yeah,
yeah,
I was doing that as an illustration.
Right,
that's right.
All right.
So energy is,
energy itself is a quantity with units.
And so you have to
specify what units you're talking about.
When I say temperature has units of energy,
yes,
it does,
but you have to pick your units of energy.
So if you're working in the meter,
kilogram,
second set of units,
then your natural unit or your unit of energy
is called a joule,
but it's not a new unit.
It's the unit of energy,
and that's the unit that you would use for temperature
if you want to keep your formula simple.
On the other hand,
you could use,
I don't know,
kilotons of TNT.
That's a bad thing to talk about today.
Some other unit,
electron volts or Planck masses or whatever.
You change your units of temperature,
sorry,
you change your units of energy,
the temperature will also change.
But your units of temperature and
energy should be kept the same.
Entropy,
on the other hand,
is dimensionless.
This entropy is dimensionless
and doesn't have units.
Yeah.
Another question.
Is the constant itself,
is that essentially determined experimentally?
Yes.
Boltzmann himself,
like Newton,
never knew the value of his own constant.
I don't mean the usefulness,
I mean the actual numerical value.
And that's because nobody had measured
the properties of atoms,
the masses of atoms,
to any,
to,
at all,
until Einstein came along and
figured out how to do it.
So,
Kelvin died just before the value
of his constant was really paid.
I'm quite sure that they had a rough idea.
They had a rough idea.
And he certainly knew that it was Kelvin,
connected to Avogadro's number.
But he probably never knew with any detail
what the value of his number was.
The same was true of Newton.
Newton had a rough idea of what his constant was,
but no precision.
Okay,
so,
but,
but Boltzmann did understand,
he did understand that if only
he could measure the properties of atoms,
that energy would be related to temperature
through his constant.
That he did understand.
Okay.
Alright,
but thus far,
I have not told you what temperature is.
You have an intuitive sense of temperature,
that's because when you touch a hot thing,
it does something to your nerve cells,
and so forth and so on,
and you have a natural intuition about hot and cold.
But,
temperature is a rather derived quantity.
It's a derived mathematical quantity
that begins with a notion of entropy,
sorry,
begins with a notion of energy and notions,
twin notions of energy and entropy.
And so let's,
let me tell you what temperature is.
When a system is in thermal equilibrium,
and we haven't defined that yet,
if we get to it tonight,
we'll do it,
but it just means that,
a closed system has been allowed to evolve
for a long enough time that it just settles down
to some equilibrium configuration.
And it may be that that system,
it doesn't have to be a closed system,
let's take back closed system,
and a system in contact
with a lot of other environment.
If it,
if the environment is not changing with time,
the system under consideration
will equilibrate in a certain sense,
it will become clear,
with its environment.
Energy may flow from the system to the environment,
in that case,
we say the system is hotter than the environment,
or the energy may flow
the other way on the average.
And in equilibrium,
on the average,
energy is flowing neither way.
Okay?
In thermal equilibrium,
what characterizes the thermal equilibrium of a system,
so here we have a system,
that's our system,
consists of a lot of degrees of freedom in there,
it may be interacting with an environment out here,
and exchanging energy with it,
until it comes to equilibrium.
It has a collection of states,
let's label them by I,
and each state I,
has an energy E sub I.
E sub I,
I,
and so forth.
Okay,
now,
when a system comes to equilibrium,
it doesn't come to a particular state I,
it's interacting with its environment,
energy is going back and forth,
complicated things are happening,
but on the average,
in equilibrium,
there are some probabilistic ideas,
some probability,
just probability,
that the system is in the I-th state,
with energy E sub I.
That becomes probabilistic now,
because when it's interacting with an environment,
well,
you get the point,
there's some P sub I,
and,
that P sub I satisfies some rules,
the first one,
is that the sum of all probabilities is one,
another rule,
it's not even a rule,
it's a definition,
is that if I take P of I,
multiply it by the energy of the I-th state,
and sum over I,
that's the average energy,
I guess we can call it,
E,
that's the average energy of the system,
when you say average,
what I really have in mind,
is that the energy is constantly changing,
it fluctuates,
some extra energy goes out into the environment,
and then it comes back in,
and so forth,
and it's constantly fluctuating,
but over short times,
it averages,
and this is the equation for the average energy,
we have that,
and finally,
we have a notion of entropy,
and the entropy is just this notion up here,
okay,
now,
what is the probability distribution P of I,
what does it depend on,
well,
first of all,
among other things,
mostly,
what it depends on,
is the average energy,
in the system,
now the average energy,
may depend on the nature of the environment,
if the environment is very hot,
the average energy in here,
may be high,
if the environment is cold,
the average energy in here,
may be cold,
but there's some average energy,
here it is,
average energy,
and it can be different,
depending on the precise nature of what's going on,
the average energy,
can be thought of as a parameter,
you can change it,
you know,
you can change the average
energy of a pot of water,
by putting it on a stove,
or you can cool it down,
by putting it out in the snow,
so you can change the average energy,
and in that sense,
in that sense,
the probability I,
depends on the average energy,
now the way to think about this is,
for every value of the average,
I'm not going to put the complicated bars around here,
this now stands for average energy,
the,
for every given average energy,
in thermal equilibrium,
there's a probability P sub I,
of course if you increase the average energy,
then you tilt the probability distribution,
toward larger energy values of E sub I,
alright,
so that means,
that there's not a single probability distribution,
that you call equilibrium,
there's a family of them,
for each value of E,
for,
this horizontal axis could either plot,
the I-th state of the system,
or it could plot the energy of the I-th state,
but for each value of the average energy,
there's some probability distribution,
for every value of the E,
for every energy,
we can now put in here,
let's put in here E,
let's put a comma in there,
for every energy,
the total probabilities have to add up to one,
and what about this equation here,
on the right hand side,
this E here is just the average energy,
it is just the average energy,
so that defines the average energy,
if you change the average energy,
to,
if you change the energy of the,
what's in the box,
then the probability distribution shifts,
oh,
I should draw it so that
the area under it is always one,
the area under it,
or the total probability should always stay to be one,
so,
maybe like this,
which one corresponds to more average energy,
the one which is peaked further out,
and imagine the energy increases
as we go in this direction,
E of I,
as we move to the right,
energy increases,
and so the probability distribution,
which is peaked further to the right,
I'm not doing this well,
the area under each one
of these should be the same,
but there's a one parameter family,
of equilibrium distributions like this,
which we haven't calculated yet,
we don't know what they are,
but,
as a matter of experience,
for each value of the average energy,
there's a probability distribution,
and that's called P I of E,
every single one of them satisfies,
the sum rule here,
and,
the average energy is equal to this quantity here,
yeah.
Things seem circular to me,
the average energy depends on the probability distribution,
but the probability distribution depends,
on the average energy,
I mean,
you didn't really put the E in that second equation,
with the I,
Which equation here?
Down,
the last equation,
down there,
put in P I E,
like you did upstairs there,
you put an E in there,
right?
Ah,
yes,
thank you,
good.
So,
but that E is really,
bracket E,
so it's like,
you have to use bracket E to define bracket E.
Let's for the moment,
just say,
from experience,
there are,
a sequence,
or a one parameter family of probability distributions,
okay?
So here's a one parameter family,
the parameter is called E for the moment,
but it doesn't have to be called E,
call anything you want,
a family of different probability distributions,
each one of them has an average energy,
alright?
So once I know the average energy of it,
I can think of it as the probability distribution
for that given average energy.
Right.
Do you have a question?
Yeah.
So,
is there a reason,
we assume a closed system,
is there a reason that you say,
average energy instead of total energy?
Yes,
because I'm imagining,
that the system,
the system,
we're talking now about,
as opposed to the environment,
that it's in,
and there's a constant,
interchange of energy back and forth,
between the system and the,
and the,
the system,
we'll call the system,
the rest of it,
we'll just call the heat bath,
right?
So it could be the atmosphere,
it could be a box of gas,
with permeable walls,
that heat can leak through,
sitting in room temperature,
in this room,
then it's constantly exchanging,
energy back and forth,
the energy fluctuates,
so the energy isn't definite,
it has a probability distribution,
if you go into the system,
at one instant,
and you measure the energy,
you get one value,
if you go in at another instant,
you'll get another value,
and if you do many,
many,
many measurements,
you'll get a probability distribution.
Okay.
Okay,
is that clear?
Yeah.
Okay,
good.
All right.
And the clarification,
the,
you have these states I,
and you have P of I,
and E sub I,
it's true then that every,
that there could be many,
many states that have the same energy?
There could be,
right,
that's why I said,
let's assume,
let's assume for the moment,
that there's a one parameter family,
that's correct,
yeah,
of course that's true.
There are many probability distributions
that you could write down
that have the same average energy.
Where we're getting this one parameter family,
from will come later.
We'll just say,
as a matter of experience,
if you know the average energy of the system,
then there's some probability distribution
associated with it.
To give it a name,
it's the Boltzmann distribution.
また
or the Maxwell-Boltzmann,
well it's the Boltzmann distribution
Alright,
but for now we're just doing a mathematical exercise,
a one parameter family
of
probability distributions
parameterized by the average energy
no two of them have
the same average energy by assumption
and the higher the energy is
of course the broader this probability
the broader the probability distribution is likely to be
and we'll take that as a given
but there's an implicit assumption that each of
the states are independent of the other ones
each of which states?
the i state
oh,
the i,
they're different,
yeah
but suppose the i state
is correlated with the j state,
then you have a
what does it mean that the i
state is correlated with the j state?
the energy of the i state
is the same as the j state
is that what you're saying?
oh you're asking what happens if there's more
than one state with exactly the same energy
no,
that the correlated,
that probability
what does correlated mean?
correlated is a very technical term
and if you're going to try to
transmit information back and forth between us
we have to do it with precision
so what does it mean to say that the
correlation is a very definite meaning
and it doesn't apply to this
but it means that the
probability of the
now that I think about it,
it's hard to describe
that would be
let me let it go
okay
I have a question
you could ask what if there's more
than one state with exactly the same energy
not average energy,
but that there isn't
that the e sub i's,
e sub 7 and e
sub 6 are exactly the same
that's my question,
yeah
that's,
first of all it never happens
and it's not particularly important
degeneracy,
that means equal energies for different states
is a very rare and unusual thing
we don't have to worry about it
every state has its own energy
every energy has its own state
let's take that as a working assumption
yes,
question up there
the thing that's confusing me here is that
i is the possible states of energy,
right?
the microscopic description of the states
the precise exact microscope
every molecule
position and velocity or whatever it takes to
describe the exact microscopic state of the system
right,
so if it's an arbitrary
choice of what like i means
then it's hard to
it's not arbitrary
so state one,
we can label this state as
oh,
how we label them?
yeah,
okay,
so let's,
good,
good
so let's agree to label them
in ascending order of the energy
good,
right,
good
and let's take it as given that
no two states have exactly the same energy
which is typically true except in very unusual situations
okay,
so then we have a clear
notion of what we mean by i
we have a notion of what
we mean by p of i
and p of i for
different values of the average energy
the nature of this thing will become clear,
not tonight
we don't have enough time tonight
to work out the Boltzmann distribution
but we do have enough time
to define the concept of temperature
alright
so,
consider the following
oh,
one more thing
each one of these probability distributions
for each value of e
has its own entropy
let's write it out
the entropy s
becomes now a function of e
now it's not a universal function of e
it depends on these probability distributions
but given this one
parameter family of probability distributions
s of e is equal to minus the sum
over i
of p of i comma e log
of
I don't need a bracket there
log of p
and so,
for this reason
s becomes a function of energy
average energy in this case
the entropy
which is a feature of a given probability distribution
now becomes a function of the energy
because for each energy we
have a different probability distribution
alright,
so that tells us that there's a notion,
there's a connection
between entropy and energy
if we know this one parameter family
and as I said,
we'll discuss later where that comes from
now let's look at the other one
now let's ask a very funny question,
an interesting question
how much energy does it take
each one of these probability distributions
parameterized by a given average energy
the higher the average energy,
the more they'll spread out to the right here
in particular to the right
we could ask how much energy does it
how much do you have to change the average energy
in order to change the entropy
by one bit
one bit means log two
how much do you have to shift
the energy here
in order that the entropy
changes by
one bit's worth
and the answer's gonna be disappointing
because I'm just gonna write a formula in the blackboard
which is totally obvious
the answer is
that
the change
in the entropy
let's
how did I write it,
let me see how I wrote it
yeah
sorry
the change in the energy
is going to be equal
to the derivative of the entropy
with respect to the energy
sorry,
derivative
the change in the energy
when I go from one probability distribution to the next
will be equal to the derivative of the energy
with respect to the entropy
times the change in the entropy
this is an identity,
right?
I mean this is only making
this is assuming nothing more
than
that things are smooth functions
that can be differentiated
the change in the energy
in going from one probability distribution to the next
is the derivative of the energy
with respect to the entropy
times the change in the entropy
it might have made a little more sense to you
if I would have written it the
the alternate way
than in going from one distribution to the next
the change in the entropy
is equal
to the change in the energy
divided by
dE by dS
incidentally,
there's no difference now between
partial derivatives and total derivatives
just the derivative of E with respect to S
in some problems there may be more variables
and we might have to keep track of more variables
here it's just derivatives of E with respect to S
times delta S
or we can write it in this fashion here
this is trivial
there's nothing insightful here
it's just the definition
of what I mean by differential changes
question
it seems that you're talking about
the variation of the entropy with respect to energy
so energy would be
the variable that has the function
would it be not more
more of a function
or would it be more logical to
do dS dE instead of dE dS
either way
dE dS is the inverse of dS dE
yeah
this is also equal to dS by dE
times delta E
all the same thing
okay
if for example I want to know
how much do I have to shift the probability distribution
how much do I have to shift the energy
in order to change the entropy
by one bit
then I would just stick in for delta S
one bit
namely log two
so that would tell me how much energy
it takes to change the entropy
by one bit
the main point here
is this object over here
this object is called temperature
that's what temperature is
it's a derived quantity
and it tells you how much
you have to change the entropy
or either way
either way you say it
how much you have to change the energy
in order to change the entropy
by a certain amount
I sort of fixated on one bit
but it doesn't matter if it's one bit
as long as it's small
or using differential formulas
I don't know why I write delta
just d
and then I would say
the definition of temperature
is such
that dE
equals
T temperature
times dS
and that's the only definition
of temperature that's universal
general and
dE equals T dS
sometimes written
dS equals one over T
times the E
okay
one point that's interesting
well it's a little bit interesting
if I change my units
if I change my units from these
physical units
to human units
then this formula doesn't change
and the reason is
it does change of course
but it changes to become
equals
T measured in Kelvin
times
dS
of the Carnot
you know
and why?
because the Boltzmann constant cancels
capital T
is K Boltzmann times
little t
and capital
S where is it
I seem to have lost it
no here it is
capital S is one over K Boltzmann
times S Carnot
so they cancel and
this is why Carnot
who wrote this formula here
he wrote
the energy equals little t dS
the K Boltzmann
the Boltzmann factors
cancel out of that
one gets a K in the numerator
one gets a K in the denominator
I'm just
telling you this because
you may wonder what happened to the K Boltzmann
if you go read
a book on standard thermodynamics
and you say wait a minute
what happened to the K Boltzmann?
they cancel out
in the definitions
so here we are
definition of temperature
it's an odd and an abstract
definition of temperature and it's not in the least bit
clear from this what it has
to do with temperature
as you
experience it
so I'm going to tell you what
it has to do with temperature now
so we have the
entropy is a function of
energy
and what you're saying is
it's invertible so
is that obvious that it's invertible?
it's not obvious but it's usually true
ok
there are
counterexamples
there are counterexamples
and I would also say
it is typical of normal
physical systems
that the entropy and the energy
are monotonic
so when you increase the energy
you usually increase
the width of the probability distribution
and in so doing
increase the entropy
we will take that as a given for now
that
energy and entropy
are monotonically increasing functions
of each other
single valued
and we can come later
and ask is that always true
the answer is no
but when it's not true
unusual
situations
ok so we're going to assume then
that the energy is a
monotonically increasing function
of entropy or
entropy is a monotonically increasing
function of energy and that
means the temperature is positive
dE by dS
or dS by dE
are positive
assumption
for the moment
and as I said
what it means
is that when you increase the parameter
E you spread
the distribution over a larger
number of states
we're going
as I said we're going to
prove some of these things most of them
but let's take it as given for now
ok so then the question
is in what way
is this definition of temperature
in any way
related to the familiar
concept of temperature
now what is
the familiar concept
sure ouch I burned myself
but can we do something
that's a little bit more physics oriented
basic fact
yes
well ok
but that depends on the properties
of light and so forth
that's true
but it's not really a statistical mechanical
concept I mean we can have a box of gas
without having light
so there's a
statistical mechanics notion
but I'll tell you what
you can think of a thousand things
that temperature has to do with
but
the really useful
definition the definition
that's closest to
to being general
is
that
temperature is a measure
or differences of
temperature if you have two systems
now let's take two systems
and let's
for simplicity now suppose the two systems
are isolated
this is system A
and system B
and they're connected
by a thin pipe
a thin pipe
simply means
that they can exchange energy
in the same way
with each other
but weakly
that little bits of energy
can go back and forth between them
and cause
the energies to fluctuate
but on the average each one has
an energy now let's start them out
without having
been in contact
they start out
not being in contact
they're each in equilibrium
but at a different
temperature
let's call this one
T A and T B
we know what temperature means
temperature is the rate of change
of energy with respect to entropy
an abstract definition
to be sure
but each one of these boxes
has been prepared
with a given temperature
by whatever it takes
to make them have
whatever temperature they have
and now connect them
and connecting them simply means allowing them
to interact with each other
and exchange energy back and forth
ok
which way does the energy flow
that's the most basic concept
of temperature or
the most basic concept of temperature
is that heat
or energy
energy will flow
from the hotter
in other words
the system of higher temperature
will be the same
to the system of lower temperature
and we can prove that
arbitrarily
let's say that
T B is bigger than T A
if it's the other way
then we just interchange A and B
of course it's possible
that T A exactly equals T B
and we will see in that case
that heat doesn't flow either way
ok on the average
heat meaning energy now
ok
so what we need to do
we need to write down a couple of simple
oh oh oh
I left out one step
I left out again
something which will not become
completely clear till later
it's the second law of thermodynamics
the second law of thermodynamics
which I have given you
no reason to believe at the moment
you can take it as a postulate
for the moment
but we will do a lot better
because we are going to do a lot better
the second law of thermodynamics
says that
when you allow the system to come to
thermal equilibrium
when you allow A and B to equilibrate
heat will flow one way or the other way
we don't know which
energy will flow
but eventually
it will come to some sort of
compromise equilibrium
the second law of thermodynamics
says that the entropy increases
ok
so let's look at
let's try to follow the line of reasoning now
the total entropy
of the system
S
is equal to the entropy of A
plus the entropy of B
why
why is entropy additive
does anybody know
from the mathematics
because it's the logarithm
yeah
because it's the logarithm of something
and the entropy of B
the entropy of B
just now
particularly
I don't think
this is his
he doesn't exist
so
my
Another useful fact.
We're going to write down some useful facts.
The second useful fact is that when the system
equilibrates by exchanging energy,
the total energy is conserved.
All right,
here's the first law of thermodynamics.
First law.
If the energy of A
increases,
then the energy of B decreases by the same amount.
So that says that DEA is equal to minus DEB.
Or the change in energy
of A and B has
to add up altogether to zero.
I'm not sure we're going to make it through this.
What time is it?
Yeah,
maybe we will.
Okay.
Next,
the second law of thermodynamics.
The change in SA
plus the change in SB
is greater than zero.
Entropy increases.
Again,
something we will need to justify.
Finally,
for each one of these,
the change in energy A
is equal to the temperature of A
times the change in the entropy of A.
Right?
That's DE equals TDS.
Definition of temperature.
Likewise,
DEB is equal to TB times DSB.
All right,
hold on to these equations.
Lock them in your head.
And remember,
we're going to have to move across the hall.
Because I think we are going
to have to move across the hall.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.