Stanford University
No physical device ever measures what it's intended,
the mathematical thing that it's
intended to measure.
At best,
what's usually true is a thing measures what it's supposed
to measure over a limited range
of whatever it happens to be.
A spring,
what do you call
those,
a spring balance.
You know,
just a spring with a calibrated measure along it.
You use it to measure force.
You want to pull on something,
and so you connect your spring
balance to it and you pull on it,
and you look at the calibration,
and you say,
okay,
the number of ticks,
or not the number of ticks,
but the length of the stretch of the
spring is a measure of the force.
Well,
that's not really true.
If you pull too hard,
you
break the spring,
and so forth.
So over some limited range of force,
the spring,
the length
of the spring constant,
the length of the spring displacement measures the force.
So
normally,
what the situation is,
is you have some quantity which
you can measure in the laboratory easily.
It could be the length of a stretched spring,
or it could be the height of the mercury in
a thermometer.
And you ask yourself,
what could the quantity in question,
what could it depend
on?
All right.
The length of the spring displacement
clearly depends...it depends on doesn't mean
it's equal to.
It depends on the force that's being applied.
But it could depend on other
things.
It could depend on temperature.
It could depend on rain.
It could depend on the
on the air pressure,
but gee,
that's not terribly important.
Those variations are pretty small,
so you ignore them.
And you say,
what could it depend on?
It can depend on the force that's pulling the spring.
There's going to be some relationship between them.
I don't know,
it might look like that.
Who knows?
Some crazy curve.
And then over some limited range,
over some limited range
where the function is linear,
and if the function is smooth,
any function that's smooth,
that doesn't vary in some crazy way,
over a limited range will be linear.
If it's linear,
then you can say over that limited range,
variations in the quantity
that you're measuring are proportional
to variations in the,
in whatever you're measuring.
Whatever the independent variable happens to be.
In the case of the spring balance,
it's just force.
Same thing with the mercury in a column here.
What can the height of the column depend on?
Well,
yeah,
it can depend on temperature.
What else can it depend on?
Can it depend on the air pressure in the room?
Not much.
Not much because the air pressure in the room is,
it's isolated by the closed,
right,
by the glass that holds the mercury in.
What else can it depend on?
I can't think of anything.
Can you think of anything it might
depend on besides the temperature in there?
Local gravity field.
Oh,
yeah,
maybe,
sure,
the local gravity field.
Yes,
right.
Okay.
So let me say it a different way.
It could depend on the
direction that you hold the thermometer.
Now,
the local gravity field is pretty
constant over the surface of the Earth.
The only,
you could have a funny thermometer,
a bad,
not necessarily a bad thermometer,
but a thermometer which behaved
differently if you held it horizontally
than if you held it vertically.
And then you would just say,
okay,
my rule is going to be hold the thermometer vertically.
If it depends very much,
then you just say,
okay,
let's fix the direction of the thermometer,
make it part of the definition of the thermometer.
And we'll hold the thermometer vertically.
Anything else anybody can think of that,
that...
Over time,
it could change the calibration because of maybe chemical...
Mmm.
Mercury and glass are pretty inert.
So we're in pretty good shape for that.
What else might it...
Of course,
over very long times,
you're right.
I mean,
the protons that make up the...
The mercury could decay over long enough times,
10 to the 34th,
10 to the 35 years.
All right,
but you think about it for a while,
and you say,
gee,
to a very,
very high approximation,
the only thing that the height of the column is
going to depend on is going to be the temperature,
or equivalently,
the energy that the mercury has absorbed
from the thermal environment that it's in.
But that's equivalent.
Okay?
If that...
Assuming.
Assuming that the thermometer is
in equilibrium with the environment.
Of course,
if the thermometer is not
in equilibrium with the environment,
it is not measuring the temperature of the environment.
It's only if there's been time established for
the environment to come to equilibrium with the mercury.
And then the only thing around is the temperature.
Okay?
Well,
the height of the column depends
on the temperature in some way.
Let's suppose...
This point over here,
we've measured it.
We find out over some range,
over some range that it looks pretty linear.
A small range,
not a big range.
Big range,
it's going to go through the...
It's going to do also...
If you make the temperature very hot,
the column gets bigger if you make it hot,
right?
Yeah.
It's not going to go through the ceiling here.
So over some range,
it looks pretty linear.
Let's say you measure it
at the freezing point of water.
And the freezing point of water,
this is temperature.
This is the height of the column.
And you find it's over here.
Then you measure it at boiling water.
Find it's over here.
If you are lucky,
over that particular range,
this function will look pretty linear.
And so you divide it into a hundred little segments.
And you say each segment constitutes a...
You arbitrarily say this point you call zero.
That's on the centigrade scale.
This point you call a hundred.
And you divide it into a hundred steps.
Is it a thermometer measuring temperature?
Yeah.
The thermometer is measuring temperature to a high accuracy.
But first of all,
it's not measuring temperature in the absolute sense.
We've called this temperature zero.
So it's not measuring absolute temperature,
the thermometer.
When you go out in the winter time
and it says zero degrees on your Fahrenheit thermometer,
it doesn't mean you're going out into absolute zero.
So there's a convention about where you put the zero.
But small incremental changes in the temperature
will be proportional to small incremental
changes in the height of the column.
What about equilibrium?
That's kind of what I was wondering.
The time scale over which you can achieve equilibrium.
Are we really talking about sort of a
boundary layer around the bulb of the thermometer?
Are you asking how long
it takes to establish thermal equilibrium?
Hmm.
Depends on the thermal conductivity of the glass here.
If it's too good an insulator,
it will take too much
time for the heat to pass,
for the energy to pass
between the mercury and the environment.
But the answer is pretty simple,
experimentally.
When the thermometer stops changing,
that's when it's in equilibrium.
So it's not measuring temperature.
It's measuring the temperature of the temperature.
So how long does it take if you change the
temperature from zero to 100 degrees or something like that,
how long does it take the thermometer to equilibrate?
The answer is half a minute.
Depends on the thermometer.
But experimentally,
the answer is when the thermometer stops changing,
it's in equilibrium.
With the environment.
So technically you're taking the temperature of the medium
immediately surrounding the thermometer,
assuming it's in equilibrium and uniform.
That's your assumption.
You know,
it also depends on the environment.
You can have a high temperature and have very,
very few molecules
if the density is very low,
but the temperature is high,
and there's no reason why that can't happen.
It just means the kinetic
energy of the molecules is high.
Kinetic energy of the molecules is
high means the temperature is high,
but there may be very few molecules in the room.
You bring the thermometer into the room,
it's not going to equilibrate very rapidly because very,
very few molecules are going to hit it.
So depending on the density of the material,
the equilibration time could be very long
or it could be a lot shorter.
If you were to thin
out the air in the room
so that the air density was,
let's say,
1,100th or 1,1000th
of the air density in the room here today,
but you would keep the temperature the same,
the thermometer would take a longer time to equilibrate.
But nevertheless,
experimentally,
the rule would be
it's equilibrated when it stops changing.
You could also have a difference
between the radiation temperature and the temperature.
Yes,
but that means the air temperature,
the air and the radiation are not in equilibrium.
Right.
It's rather hard to bring radiation in a room
into thermal equilibrium with the air.
The air molecules are neutral,
they don't radiate much.
I assure you,
in this room here,
the radiation in the room,
optical radiation is nowhere near
being in equilibrium with the air.
On the other hand,
there's very,
very few photons in this room
compared with the air molecules,
and so they really don't count very much.
When does the ideal gas breakdown,
under what conditions,
can you show mathematically?
Well,
since you happen to ask,
why don't I just off the top of my head
do a calculation of how
the ideal gas law breaks down
when there are forces behind it?
Well,
there's a few things I can say.
there's a question about the interaction between molecules.
Just purely off the top of my head,
I'm going to throw away my lecture notes.
Just because I'm looking at them and staring at them,
don't get the wrong idea.
I'm not using them.
Okay.
A gas of weakly interacting particles.
Now,
why weakly interacting?
Well,
we've done the problem
of the non-interacting gas molecules.
Okay.
Well,
it's easy to make a little step.
Little steps are usually easy.
Where you change problems,
known solved problems,
it's often easy to change the problem a little bit,
numerically,
to change some parameters just a little bit,
and then try to expand in the small changes.
That's the usual trick.
You have some problem that you solve
for some quantity epsilon equal to zero,
epsilon being some small number.
Then you reformulate the problem
with epsilon not being zero,
and it's too hard to solve.
But if you're lucky,
you might be able to expand
in a power series in epsilon,
and then check whether the succeeding orders
are as big as the thing you started with.
How do you tell when a,
when a series like that breaks down?
You tell when it breaks down
when the second term is
as big as the first term.
So we're going to do that problem today.
We're going to do the problem
of a weakly interacting gas.
And of course,
it's weakly interacting because it's dilute.
Because the molecules are on the average
rather far from each other,
and the energy is not
as big as the first term.
We'll assume the range of the forces
is small by comparison with
the distance between the particles.
We'll assume that the potential energy between particles,
or the forces,
are small.
We'll do our calculation,
and then we'll look at the result and we'll say,
where does this break down?
Where does the correction term become as large
as the first term?
It's going to depend on the density.
The bigger the density,
the more likely molecules are
going to crash into each other,
and if they crash into each other,
they're going to experience
the fact that they're interacting.
If you make the density too high,
they're all jumbled in,
squeezed on top of each other,
and the ideal gas is a very bad approximation.
On the other hand,
you could keep the density low,
but if the range of the force is long,
if particles were to interact with each other,
strongly,
when they were six feet apart,
the molecules in this room,
even if the interaction was pretty weak,
that would still be a very,
very serious modification
of the ideal gas law.
And so,
we want to,
we start by assuming
that we can make an expansion in a small parameter.
We make the expansion,
mathematically expand,
and then check whether the corrections to the first term
are big enough,
or small,
as big or smaller,
big or smaller,
than the term that they're correcting.
Okay,
so let's set up that problem.
What we're going to do is we're going to calculate
the partition function
for a system of molecules
for which the energy
is not just the sum
of the kinetic energies.
Where there are forces.
Forces means a potential energy.
So let's start with a formula.
The formula is that the
energy of a set of molecules
is the sum of all the molecules,
sum of all of them,
n stands for which molecule we're talking about,
p squared,
now p stands for the sums of the squares
of the components of the momentum,
p squared over twice the mass,
that's the usual kinetic energy,
of a molecule,
plus,
now we're going to assume that every molecule
experiences a force
from every other molecule.
That means that there's a potential energy
for each pair of molecules.
And the total potential energy
is the sum over all the pairs of molecules.
Sums over pairs.
Not sums over pairs,
like apples and pears,
but sums over pairs of molecules.
Okay,
so how do we write a sum over pairs?
We say a sum over n and m,
but n and m label two particles,
the fifth particle and the 192nd,
but we don't want to count twice.
We don't want to count n equals 3
and m equals 7,
and also n equals 7
and m equals 3.
That's the same pair.
We also don't want to count as a pair
n and m.
We don't want to think that the first molecule
and the first molecule forms a pair.
So we can do this by saying
we only sum for n bigger than m.
Do you want to have something other than m,
since we've already got an m one?
All right,
sum n greater than m,
that means you count 3 and 2,
but you don't count 2 and 3.
You know what I mean.
All right,
and what is it going to be?
It's going to be some potential energy u.
Now I'm not going to use v for potential energy
because v we're saving for volume.
v is the value of the
distance between molecule n and molecule m.
So let's write that as
the distance between xn and xm.
And this means xn minus xm means the vector separating
the nth position from the mth position.
The absolute value means that the
absolute value of the absolute value
is the distance itself,
and the potential energy is a function of the distance
between these two molecules.
When we sum it over n greater than m,
we add up all of the potential energy.
So we can just call this thing here,
let's just call it u,
u of x.
But here's what it is.
All right,
now,
u is,
what is going to be the small quantity?
The small quantity is going to be u.
The potential energy is going to be assumed
to be a good deal smaller
than the kinetic energy between molecules.
In other words,
we start with the ideal gas,
and then we simply turn a knob
that turns on the potential,
but we keep that knob very small
so that at least at first,
the potential energy stored by these pairs of molecules
is much smaller than the kinetic energy
of either of them.
That's our approximation.
That's where we're going to begin.
All right,
there's actually only one number
regarding this potential which is important.
I'm going to define it now.
Question?
We're going to encounter the following integral.
It's going to be,
let's take particle one and particle two.
Doesn't matter which pair,
just two particles,
one and two.
dx1,
dx2.
Now,
what do I mean by dx1 first of all?
Particle one has three coordinates,
right?
x,
y,
and z.
When I write dx,
I mean
the integral over the volume element for particle one,
the three-dimensional volume,
and I mean the same thing here.
If I just write dx,
it means this kind of symbol here.
And now I want to write the potential energy
as a function of the distance between them.
What I'm doing is I'm taking the two particles
and I'm integrating over all possible positions
of the two particles
the potential energy between them.
Let's look at this.
Let's suppose for a moment
that I hold the relative position,
the relative position,
x1 minus x2 fixed,
and I integrate over the position of x1.
That's moving x1 around,
dragging x2 with it.
How can I do the integral over two coordinates?
One way is to integrate over one of the coordinates,
keeping the separation to the other one fixed,
and then afterwards integrate over the separation
between them.
Two separate steps.
And what do I get if I hold the distance
between the two of these fixed,
but integrate the position of the pair of them
all over space?
I'm going to get a factor of the volume.
Just holding the two of them fixed
and thinking of them as a unit
and integrating them all over space,
I will get a factor of the volume of space.
All right.
I've taken care of that integral.
Let's hold this point fixed.
I could have said it the other way.
I could have said,
let's hold this point fixed
and integrate over the position of the second one.
Yeah,
let's think of it that way.
Let's do it in the opposite order.
Let's think of it by first holding particle one fixed
and integrating over the position of the other particle.
What does that give me?
That gives me the integral d,
let's call it x,
any x,
u of x.
All it's doing is holding one particle fixed
and moving the other particle around
and adding up or integrating
the total potential energy
times the volume element
of the particle it's moving around.
Yeah,
what are the units of this quantity?
What's the units of u?
Energy.
What's the units of dx?
Length,
right?
But this is really d3x.
It's a volume integral.
So what are the units of d3x?
Volume.
The units of this thing are volume times energy.
This quantity is telling us how important the energy is
because it's both telling us
how strong the potential energy is
and over how big a volume does u act.
How spread out is it?
And let's give this thing a name.
This thing is going to be our important numerical quantity
that determines the strength of the potential.
It's a combination of how strong the potential is
and how widespread it's distributed.
Let's just call this u0.
It's the only parameter that will come into our calculation.
And you don't know if it's big or small.
If it's big,
you don't know offhand whether it's big
because it's distributed over a large volume,
but u is small,
or whether it's distributed over a
small volume and u is big.
One way or another,
u0 is the thing which will determine everything else.
All right,
so now supposing we held this particle fixed
and integrated over the other one,
that would give us this integral
here and it would be u0.
Now having done that,
let's integrate the position of this molecule,
which means move the pair around.
That's going to give us another factor of volume,
of the total volume of the gas times u0.
Can everybody see that?
Make sure I understand.
That u0 integral,
is that referring to...
A single pair of particles?
Yeah,
we pick out any pair of particles.
Any pair.
Are you keeping the other one at a constant distance
or are you removing it all over?
No,
we first hold this one fixed
and integrate the other one everywheres.
Yeah,
but of course we're not going to get much
except when this is in the field of the potential.
You might ask,
why doesn't holding this one fixed
and integrating the other one,
why don't we get a factor of volume for that?
Because...
We're assuming,
I should have said,
we're assuming that whatever the function u is,
that it's a function which goes to zero
when the particles get far apart.
So whatever u is,
it's a function
which is only significant
when the two particles are within a certain distance,
let's say.
Beyond that distance it goes to zero.
So if we hold one particle fixed
and integrate the other one,
well if it were a one-dimensional problem,
we would just say the integral
would be the area under this curve.
Well,
it's not quite the area under the curve
because it's a three-dimensional integral.
It has units of energy times volume,
not energy times length,
energy times volume,
but it is just the integral that you get
if you held one of them fixed
and integrated the other one all around it,
so to speak.
Having done that,
we can now integrate the second particle.
The one that we held fixed.
And when we do that,
it will just give us another factor
of the overall volume of a system.
It's not the same volume,
right?
Not the same volume as what?
In the u0 you only had
the volume in the vicinity of...
That's right.
This u0 is equal,
let's say it's qualitatively equal,
to the height of the function,
I don't know what to call it,
I'll just call it u,
times the volume over which
the function is significant.
This volume is roughly the volume of a,
a couple of times the volume of a molecule,
basically.
All right?
The forces between molecules,
the potential energy between molecules
is only significant when the two molecules
are within a couple of molecular dimensions.
Diameters of each other.
So this volume is roughly the volume
of a couple of molecules.
The other volume
is the volume of the whole sample,
of the whole box of gas.
The small volume here is absorbed into u0.
We don't have to worry about it anymore.
It's absorbed into u0.
u0 is a combination of the small molecular size volume
times the strength of the potential energy
between the molecules.
And then we have to take into account
the other integral.
The other integral
is the total volume of the system.
Yes?
Just to make sure I understand,
u0 at least a priori is,
it depends on the particle that's fixed.
But what you're saying is because of our...
Depends on the distance between particles.
We're assuming it depends on the distance
between particles.
If we move to...
One of them fixed,
and then you do this integral,
and so that result depends upon
the point that you kept fixed.
If you move to another fixed point,
it might be different.
No,
no,
no.
You're saying it's not.
No,
right.
I am saying it's not because
it only depends on the distance between them.
That's right.
So if we hold the molecule fixed over here
and take the other one
and integrate it all around it,
we get a u0.
If we put the first molecule over here
and we integrate around it,
we get the u0.
We get the same number.
But if you don't make this assumption
about the nearness,
it would seem to me if you took a particle
that was very near the boundary,
you might get a different integral
than one in the center.
So it's that assumption that you've got there
that makes...
Yeah.
There are always,
in all of this,
there are always boundary effects.
Boundary effects.
And what we're always using is the fact
that for a large volume,
the volume is much bigger than the area.
It's a...
You know,
it's a surface-to-volume ratio story.
But you're perfectly right.
This is not exactly true
just because when you take the molecule
and you move it near the walls of the box,
you've made a little bit of a mistake
by assuming that the other molecule
can be anywheres around it.
It can only be anywheres around it
but not banging into the wall.
So there's a little mistake there.
The mistake is not important
as long as the box is much bigger
than volume...
than the volume here.
In other words,
if the box is much bigger than a...
than a molecule,
then the error made is very small,
negligible.
All right.
So here we are.
We have this integral,
and we're going to save it
because we're going to use it.
But I just wanted to get it up there
for your comments.
Question.
Yes.
So the end...
the end result of this integral
is the sum of the potential energies
of all possible configurations
of two particles?
Is that basically the answer?
That's correct.
Okay.
That's exactly what it is,
but it's only proportional to one volume
and not two volumes
for the reasons we said.
Its units are the units of volume squared
times energy,
but it's only proportional to one volume
as a...
You know what I mean.
Yeah.
Question.
You said that the surface-to-volume ratio
has to be such that we can ignore boundary effect.
Is it reasonable to say
that it's similar to a sphere?
Because,
you know,
as you grow the volume,
grow the surface,
so the shape is what really matters.
The sphere has the smallest surface-to-volume.
Is that...?
It does,
but if the sphere is big,
it's still true that the surface-to-volume
is very small.
So...
Um...
The answer is...
doesn't depend on the shape of the object,
except for these small surface-area effects.
Mmm.
In thermodynamics in general and in statistical mechanics,
we often ignore surface things.
Surface things are sort of the exception.
Molecule at the surface is the,
let's just put it this way,
the number of molecules which
are within a molecular diameter of the surface is much,
much smaller than the number of molecules
which are further than a
molecular diameter from the surface.
So there's a small fraction,
fractionally speaking,
the number of molecules for which
we're making a mistake by saying the
potential energy only depends on the distance between
them and ignoring the boundaries.
The percentage of the system is...
It's very,
very small.
We could estimate it for a box,
but we don't have to.
We know that surface to volume is very small.
Of course,
if we take the box small,
at some point,
we're going to start to experience
the importance of the surface.
But that's pretty small.
Yeah?
No,
we're still not bringing in collisions yet.
Not yet.
Well,
no,
of course we are.
The existence of a potential energy...
The derivative of a potential energy is a force,
and a force creates collisions.
We're not going to ever have to think about collisions.
We're never going to have
to think about following the particles.
We don't have to think about it,
you see.
This is the beauty of statistical mechanics.
You lose all intuition about what's really going on.
But you have a set of mechanics.
You have the mechanical rules.
You go onto autopilot.
You follow the rules,
and you get the answers in a completely rigorous way.
And you don't have to worry about
whether some assumptions that you may have made,
such
as whether the particles have the same average
velocity if they're near the walls or not
near the walls,
or if they're near each
other and not near each other.
You don't have to worry about that.
So it's always good to go back and say,
you know what?
Really?
Really,
are we doing?
And are we getting an answer that
we would have expected from naive thinking?
But if we want to really
know whether we have the right answer,
best to set out the rules,
get onto autopilot,
follow the equations,
and at the end,
look at it and say,
does this
make sense?
So we're basing this on looking at pairs of particles.
Are we losing anything by not looking at triplet?
And higher combinations?
First of all,
there could be terms in the
energy which depend on three particles at
a time.
The energy between two particles conceivably could
depend on the presence of a nearby third
particle.
So we have made an assumption when we've written
that the energy can be written on the energy
of a particle.
And that's the same thing as a sum of pairs.
Now,
the point is,
why is it a good approximation,
first of all,
to use the ideal gas?
And the answer is,
it's a good approximation when
the probability of the particles being
close enough together to feel each other is small.
So when the gas is dilute.
The particles spend most of their time being
far enough away that they simply don't feel
each other.
Some fraction of the time,
two particles will get close enough together to feel,
to be within
this little volume distance.
And that's when the forces
between those two molecules become important.
Now what's the fraction of the time that
three given molecules will be within the molecular
distance of each other?
Much,
much smaller.
The probability that three,
take three and ask what's the probability that all three
of them will be within a molecular
diameter of each other is vastly smaller,
depending
on the volume of the gas,
of course,
is much smaller than the probability that two of them
will be near each other.
So if there were three body forces,
the three body forces would be less important,
not because
they're weaker,
but because just on the average,
the probability of four particles being close
to each other,
that's even smaller.
So the probability of finding three particles in
the neighborhood of each other for a dilute
gas is even smaller.
Alright,
three body forces.
There are also,
we're going to do an expansion.
And the expansion,
there are three body effects,
even if the forces are only two body effects.
But the answer to your question is we're going
to follow the expansion and see what we find.
There are other terms.
They won't be important as
long as the particles are dilute.
Dilute.
Okay,
so where do we go?
Now we get on autopilot.
What do we want to calculate?
We want to calculate the partition function.
Z.
An integral.
Remember,
you integrate over the momentums,
the momenta.
You integrate over the position.
Now dp and dx really stand
for a very high dimensional multiple integral.
How high is the dimension of the integral?
Each one of them,
three times the number of particles.
You have the three components
of momentum for the first particle,
the three components
for the second particle,
and so forth.
So,
that's three n,
and I'm not going to bother
writing it that this is a multiple
integral of power three n.
Likewise,
dx is a big multiple integral.
We'll just write it this way.
There's this factor of n factorial
that makes no difference at all,
that we sometimes put
in,
makes no difference at all.
And then we have e to the minus,
e to the minus what?
e to the minus beta.
Beta is the inverse temperature.
I just wrote that.
times the energy of the whole system.
And the energy of the whole system
is a term which is kinetic energy.
I'm just going to write
it as P squared over 2M.
Capital M.
It stands for this sum here.
I could put the summation sign in,
but this is close enough.
That's one term.
And then the other term is the potential energy.
So it's going to be an exponential
of the sum of two things.
And the exponential of the sum of two things
is just the product of two exponentials.
E to the minus beta
times,
let's just call it U of X.
And this stands,
U of X here stands
for the total potential energy
as a function of all of the positions.
And this is our...
our job to try to compute.
Now,
the glorious and simplifying feature of this
is that it factorizes.
It factorizes into a momentum integral
and a position integral
with the integrand itself being a product.
So in fact,
we can write it as the product of two integrals.
The first integral we've in fact seen before.
I won't bother to remind...
I will actually tell you what it is,
just to remind you.
We're not going to need it,
but the first integral,
the momentum integral,
was...
Now I've forgotten what it was.
Square root...
of...
There's a two in there,
there's a pi,
and there's an m over beta.
Is that right?
Do you remember that?
Raised to the power...
3n over...
No,
3...
Yeah,
3n.
Do you remember that?
It was this Gaussian integral for each momentum,
and it's what we used.
It's exactly the integral that we did
for the case of the ideal gas.
If U was zero,
we would be doing the ideal gas.
But we'd have exactly the same integral here.
We're not going to need it.
Fortunately,
we're not going to need it,
but one of the integrals is exactly
the one that we did the last time.
Now,
the previous time,
when we did the integral over position,
before we had any potential energy,
do you remember what this integral over position gave us?
It gave us the volume raised to the nth power.
That's when...
This was just when U was zero.
If U was zero,
it's just the integral dx,
just the volume to the nth power.
Everybody remember that?
Okay?
So let's actually multiply and divide
by the volume to the nth power.
Let's put in here
volume to the nth power,
and then divide by volume to the nth power.
And the reason for doing that
is because then we immediately recognize this integral
as the old partition function
for the ideal gas.
This integral here is just the partition function
So we can call it
Z zero.
Zero now stands
for the calculation
when U is equal to zero,
when there are no forces between them.
The ideal gas.
That's the partition function
as a function of beta,
it depends on beta,
of the ideal gas.
The other factor is the new thing here.
So this is the factor we have to work on.
Let's take it over to
this blackboard and work on it.
And of course I'm not telling you anything
you wouldn't have done yourself
if you would have spent 15 minutes with it.
You would have realized very quickly
that the integral factorizes.
One of the factors,
if we put in the V to the n,
would have been just the partition function
of the ideal gas.
And the other factor is the new thing
that we want to calculate.
So here it is.
Integral
dx
over volume to the n,
e to the minus beta of the potential energy.
Now what's the small question?
What's the quantity in our calculation
that we're going to expand in terms of?
U.
The potential energy is the thing
which is being assumed to be small.
We're starting with an ideal gas
and then we turn our little knob
that turns on the potential energy
and we turn it on very,
very weakly.
If we turn it on very weakly,
we can expand this exponential
in a different way.
We can tail a series in the strength of U.
But it's very easy.
It's just equal to
1 minus beta U of x.
Those are the first two terms
what I'm using
is that e to the minus something,
let's call this s,
is equal to 1 minus s plus s squared
over 2 factorial,
blah,
blah.
But when s is very small,
when s is sufficiently small,
we ignore everything but the 1.
But we're interested in keeping track
of the correction.
The s squared will be much smaller than s
if s is small.
So let's keep the first correction.
That's 1 minus beta U of x.
All right,
so let's plug that in.
Let's get rid of the exponential
and replace it by
1 minus beta U of x.
What does the integral over 1 give us?
Can anybody guess what the integral of the first,
the first integral is?
V to the n,
right?
V to the n divided by V to the n?
That's 1.
I've got a question.
By that 1 there,
it means that you assume
the potential at 0 is 0,
right?
No.
No,
I have not.
I've just said the first term here is just 1,
and the integral over dx
is just V to the n.
Right.
So the first integral is just the number 1,
V to the n over V to the n.
Then minus beta times the integral
dx over V to the n,
or minus beta times delta,
so V to the n over V to the n,
plus beta times lata,
Now they're just points of an equation.
Just to think about that.
This is one thing you can write to your paper,
and it has to do with
being calculative,
is just the sum of the integrals.
And it's just the integrals,
the sum of integrals
for pairs of particles.
Every pair of particles gives exactly the same answer
as every other pair of particles.
So up in here,
we have the sum for n greater than m.
Doesn't matter.
n greater than m or m greater than n.
U of the distance between them.
Of.
OK.
This is the sum of integrals.
Let's focus on one.
And every one of them gives exactly the same answer
as every other one,
because every pair of particles
is,
there's nothing distinguished about particle
2 and particle 7 relative
for particle 50 and particle 494.
You have the same answer.
And in fact,
they will give exactly the same answer
as particle 1 and particle 2.
Just no sum.
Just n.
Just particle 2 and particle 1.
But how many such terms do I have?
How many such pairs are there?
n choose 2.
Which is what?
n times n minus 1 over 2.
Over 2.
So we can just do this as dx1,
dx2,
and then dx,
all the other dx's,
all the other ones,
and then we can just do
this as n minus 1 over 2.
How many of them are there?
How many x's here?
3 and n.
No,
we've already got two of them here.
So it's n minus 2.
Well,
yeah,
3 times n minus 2,
but n minus 2.
All right.
Good.
What's the next step?
The next step is exactly that,
to say,
ah.
What's the next step?
There's a factor of n
times n minus 1 over 2.
It was just explained to us.
That's n choose 2 minus beta
times n times n minus 1
divided by 2.
Once we put that factor there,
we
don't have to sum any more over the various particles.
We just take particle 1 and particle 2.
Nothing special about 1 and 2.
Is it n minus 1 or n plus 1?
n times n minus 1.
n minus 1.
Yeah.
I'm a little confused about
why u of x2 minus x1
has the same value for every pair of particles.
No.
No,
no,
no.
It doesn't.
There are many integrals here.
It's a sum of integrals,
but every integral
has exactly the same form.
Right.
Has exactly the same form.
Each integral is an integral
where two of the x's are
in some form.
Each integral has a form inside of u.
And all the other ones are not inside of u.
You want me to write the whole thing out?
I will write it.
OK.
So we're not assuming that that is usual?
Dot,
dot,
dot.
That's the first term.
The second term is exactly the same,
except wherever
I see 1 and 2,
I put 2 and 3.
Or 2 and 7.
Exactly the same here.
And?
Still not right.
Each one of these integrals is the same,
and there are n times n
minus 1 over 2 of them.
And so I just leave it that way.
OK.
What about these integrals over here?
What do they give me?
The ones that aren't in u here?
Each one gives me a volume.
So there's a factor of volume to how many powers?
x.
n minus 2,
right?
n minus 2.
Now,
what about this integral over u?
We erased it.
Integral dx1 dx2 of u of x1 minus
x2 is equal to the volume times u0.
That was the definition of u0.
So,
when I do that integral,
I wish I was taller,
but I'm not.
Can you remember this?
Never mind.
That's exactly the integral that we have here.
So let's replace it by that.
It's 1 minus beta.
Now,
n times n minus 1 over 2,
we can approximate that by n squared.
Are we making a mistake?
Yes,
we are,
but we're making a mistake very
small compared to the piece we keep.
We could
keep the n times n minus 1,
but let's just approximate it by n squared.
We've done worse
things than that when we did the Sterling's formula.
n times n minus 1,
you know,
1,000
times 1,000 is a million minus 1,000.
Well,
you know,
that's close enough to a million.
Divide it by a 2.
That's good.
Now we have v to the n
minus 2 over v to the n.
That's
1 over v squared.
Sorry.
Yeah,
1 over v squared,
right?
And then we have this integral.
This
integral gives us another power of volume upstairs,
so it becomes a volume times u0.
So now we have the partition function.
The partition function is equal to the partition
function of the free gas.
So we have the partition function of the free gas.
.
So the I should've been able to get the
the corrections,
plus logarithm of 1 minus beta
n squared over 2v times u0.
What are we expanding in?
We're expanding in the magnitude of u,
of u0 to be precise.
u0 is our expansion parameter.
We're trying to make a Taylor series expansion,
or an expansion
in powers of u0.
Well here we have the logarithm
of 1 minus a constant times u0.
What is our
goal?
Our goal is to expand it in powers of u0.
So what is the Taylor series expansion
of log of 1 minus,
let's call it 1 minus x.
Log of 1 minus x.
For small x.
Anybody know what that is?
Minus x.
Log of 1 is 0,
right?
So that doesn't give us anything.
And if we Taylor series
expand log of 1 minus x,
this is an exercise,
you know how to do a Taylor series expansion,
you differentiate.
It's already on the upper board,
e to the minus s.
Okay.
What's that?
The Taylor expansion is already on the upper board,
e to the minus s.
It is.
Yeah,
it is.
So this is just equal to minus x.
Log of 1 minus x is equal to minus
x,
if I wanted to write it all out,
I could write the whole thing out.
Minus x,
I think
it's plus x squared over 2 minus,
I think,
x cubed over 3 plus
x to the 4 over 4.
That's
not factorial,
just 1,
2,
3,
4.
But we're not interested in things which are quadratic
when u is small.
So it's just 1 minus,
it's just minus x.
So what does that do?
When Taylor
series expanded,
we don't even have to write the log anymore,
and we don't have to have
the 1 here.
It's just log of z 0 minus,
I think it's minus,
I hope it's minus.
So it's
plus.
Is it plus?
It's minus.
It's minus,
I think.
Minus beta n squared over twice
the volume times the u 0.
Now,
is this what we want?
No.
We're never really interested in
the log of the partition function.
We're interested in what you can get from it.
So pick something interesting to get that
you can get from the log of the partition function.
Energy.
Let's calculate the energy of the gas.
That's equal to minus the derivative
of the partition function,
or minus the derivative of
the log of the partition function,
with
respect to what?
Remember?
Beta.
We're going to get the first two things.
We're going to get the first term over here.
That's just going to be the original expression
that we had for the ideal gas.
I don't have to calculate it again.
I know what happens
if I differentiate log z 0 with respect to beta.
I get the energy of the ideal gas at
temperature beta.
So what's the first term?
The number of molecules times 3 halves times
the temperature.
3 halves n times T.
That's the first term from here.
That's just the good old Boltzmann,
Maxwell Boltzmann,
whoever it was,
who realized that in thermal equilibrium at temperature T,
each particle
has energy 3 halves T.
So that's the first term.
The second term,
we want to differentiate with respect to beta.
We have to change.
There's a minus sign.
That'll kill this minus sign here.
And we'll get a plus.
Differentiating this with respect
to beta just gives us n
squared over 2v times u 0.
Now,
of course,
we always expect in a situation like
this that the total energy should be
proportional to the number of particles.
This term here is proportional to the number
of particles.
This term here is weird.
It's quadratic in the number of particles,
proportional
to the square of the number of particles.
That's crazy.
If I have 10 to the 23rd particles,
I get an energy of 10 to the 46th.
I don't care what units you use.
10 to the 46th is
too big.
But that's all right,
because the volume is also big.
So let's factor out an
n.
Let's factor out an n.
And now what is n over v?
The density.
And the density is whatever it is.
It's neither big nor small.
Well,
it may
be small,
because we're talking about a dilute gas.
But here's our formula for the energy.
A term which doesn't depend on the density at all.
Of course,
it does depend on the density.
It depends on the number of particles.
Depends on the number of particles,
but only the number
of particles.
And it's proportional to the number of particles.
And here's another term
that's proportional to the number of particles.
It depends on the potential energy between
particles.
But it also depends explicitly on the density.
Why does it depend on a factor
of the density?
Yeah,
because it's an energy per particle,
but there shouldn't really be an energy per particle.
There should be an energy per
particle only if there's another particle nearby.
So if we focused on one particle and we said,
what's the probability that there's another particle nearby,
it would be proportional to the density.
The higher the density,
the more probable it is that there's a neighboring particle.
So the correction term here,
it's also contained in the fact
that there's an n squared here.
n squared is the number of pairs of particles,
roughly.
So it's n,
for each particle,
there's an energy,
but the energy is proportional to the density of particles.
And as I said,
that's because each particle,
if the density was very small,
you might have a particle okay,
but the chances that there was another particle,
nearby would be negligible.
As the density increases,
the chances that that particle is
near a second one start to increase,
and so there's a factor of the density here.
Okay,
so we could express this in terms
of an of a energy per particle.
The energy per particle
has a first term,
which is just proportional to the density.
It doesn't have to be proportional to the temperature.
It doesn't have,
it doesn't care how many other particles are nearby.
And the second term is proportional to
the potential energy between pairs of particles,
times another factor of the density.
And that,
of course,
this can be confirmed for a,
this,
one doesn't easily measure the energy of a gas.
So this is not the way to confirm it.
What's an interesting thing that you
can measure that is easy to measure?
Well,
the temperature is an input.
The temperature is input here.
Oh,
notice this term doesn't depend on the temperature.
Interesting fact,
doesn't depend on temperature.
Okay,
what's another thing that you can measure about a gas?
The pressure.
Easy to measure pressure.
So,
the question is,
what does this say about the pressure?
So,
let's calculate the pressure.
We have everything we need.
This is log z.
And let me remind you what
the formula for the pressure is.
We wrote it in terms of the Helmholtz free energy,
but that's a funny way to write it.
We can,
sorry,
we can write it that way.
There was this quantity,
which was a,
which was minus t.
And this is t log z.
And the formula,
I'll just remind you,
the formula for the pressure was the derivative of
a with respect to volume minus sign at fixed temperature.
That was the formula we worked out last time.
The pressure is the derivative of a.
Or just minus,
or it would become plus,
temperature times the derivative of the log of
z with respect to volume at fixed temperature.
This was the formula we worked
out last time for the pressure.
So now all we have to do is apply it.
There are two terms.
When we differentiate log z,
we're going to get a term from here.
What's that going to be?
That's the pressure of the ideal gas.
Alright,
so we first get the pressure of the ideal gas.
PV equals NT.
Remember that.
So,
P equals PV.
PV equals NT.
P equals NT.
NT divided by V,
right?
That's the pressure of the ideal gas.
N over V is rho.
So the first term is the
density of particles times the temperature.
That's exactly what we had
last time from differentiating log z0.
Now,
what about this term here?
Let's differentiate that.
But first we have to multiply it by temperature.
Alright?
So let's multiply this by temperature.
If we multiply this by temperature,
then the correction term,
let's go to the correction term here,
multiply by temperature by T.
And what is T times beta?
So by the time we have finished multiplying by temperature,
this just becomes minus N squared over
2V times U0 with a minus sign.
But we actually want...
We actually want...
Minus T times log z.
Oh,
the minus signs are flying all over the place.
And it's only a question of whether there's
an odd or an even number of them.
Right?
I will tell you that there's...
The number is such that the answer is...
We want to differentiate...
Let's see what we do.
We want to differentiate this with...
There's minus signs all over the place.
The number of them add up to an even number.
Okay.
But what happens when we differentiate
this with respect to the volume?
It's going to be a plus sign.
What happens when we differentiate
this with respect to the volume?
We get volume squared in the denominator.
So we're going to get N squared over 2...
Volume squared...
And U naught.
Isn't it minus instead of plus?
No,
it is not.
Isn't it minus instead of plus?
No,
it is not.
It's not.
And,
uh...
Right,
it's not.
You go through it and just check it out.
All right,
what's N squared over V squared?
Rho squared.
1 half rho squared times u0.
So you see,
among other things,
we're
expanding in powers of the density.
When the density is low,
when the density is very low,
it's linear in the density,
the pressure.
If the density is 0,
there's no pressure.
It doesn't matter what the temperature is.
If there's no particles there,
there's no pressure.
So it's proportional to the density.
And it's also proportional to the temperature,
because if the temperature is 0,
the molecules
aren't moving at all,
and they don't bounce off the walls
at all.
So this term is sensible.
This term is proportional to rho squared.
So when rho is small,
this is a lot smaller than this.
For small rho.
If you make rho small enough,
this is going
to be much smaller than this.
And that's good,
because we're trying
to expand in this variable.
And we expect.
What we expect is when the density is low,
this is less than this.
And it's true.
As the density gets smaller and smaller,
rho squared over rho goes to 0.
It's proportional to rho.
It's proportional to u0.
It doesn't seem to care about the temperature,
incidentally.
It's a term in the pressure that does not
depend on the temperature.
But it does depend on the energy,
on this one parameter
which governs the strength of the interaction.
And it's got a rho squared.
So that,
of course,
can be measured.
That can be measured.
You take the gas.
And you simply start.
You measure its temperature.
You measure its pressure.
You measure its density.
And you change the density.
You can keep the temperature fixed
by keeping it in equilibrium.
You can change the density by changing the volume.
So you just start changing the volume.
Forget the volume.
Just keep track of the density.
And you calculate the pressure
as a function of the density.
And in fact,
you see that it's not just a linear function,
but it starts to increase with a quantity
of the quadratic term.
Quick question.
Initially,
you ignored three body problems
by saying that the density is not big enough.
But there is no numerical indication.
How big may it be before
you have to take into account
three body problems?
OK,
so that's good.
If I assume that the
energy scale for the three body
interactions is about the same
as for the two body interactions,
then the next term would
be of order rho cubed here.
To find three bodies at the same place
will have a probability proportional to rho cubed.
Two bodies at the same place,
rho squared.
So the next term in the expansion,
whether it's coming from three body forces
or from anything else which involves three bodies,
which will be of order rho cubed u0 typically squared
divided by the temperature.
That's what the next term in this expansion would be.
There can be other kinds of,
there are other kinds of terms also.
Let's see.
Sorry,
I made a mistake.
If there are three body forces,
and the three body forces have
the same order of magnitude as u0,
and this is not u0 here,
not u0 squared,
it's just u0,
and then,
do I have the time?
I don't think I have
the temperature in the right place.
This doesn't look right.
Temperature,
u0,
temperature,
there's something wrong with it.
I have to think about it.
I'm not sure what the next corrections are.
We'll figure them out later.
In any case,
this is a good approximation
for a dilute gas.
The first correction,
dilute gas.
Because we say that this is the approximation
where rho cube is much smaller than rho squared.
That's it?
Yeah.
But you really should calculate the next term
and ask when it's bigger or smaller.
Okay,
so when is it a good approximation
to just keep this term?
It's a good approximation,
the ideal gas,
when,
rho squared u0
is much less than rho times the temperature.
Let's divide by rho.
In other words,
when the temperature
is bigger than rho times u0.
Temperature is a measure of
the kinetic energy of a particle.
u0 times rho.
What are the units of rho,
of u0,
remember?
Energy times rho.
And what's the units of rho?
So what's the units of u0 times rho?
Energy.
So we're comparing energy on the left
with energy on the right.
Let's see.
Look over here.
Rho times u0
is basically the potential energy per particle.
That's what it is.
Rho times u0
is the potential energy per particle.
When the potential energy per particle
is much less than the kinetic energy,
then it's a good approximation.
Okay,
that's what we're doing.
We're really
studying the gas
in the range
where the potential energy is much smaller
than the kinetic energy.
Okay.
So I did this mostly to show you
how the rules work,
to show you that you're not limited
to the ideal gas,
and to show you
could you have guessed this formula?
Well,
you might have guessed that it's proportional to rho squared
because it involves pairs of particles.
You might have guessed that it involves
the potential energy.
It would not have been so obvious
that it involves exactly that integral.
But it's plausible that a
u times a volume is there.
Would you have guessed the one-half?
Maybe if you were really,
really smart,
you might have guessed the one-half.
Would you have been sure you were right?
Probably not.
The mechanical calculation
of calculating the partition function
by tropic nature
You know how to use a electron
is the question.
Well,
this purplish right here
In the real world you're not interested
in the physicality ofом
think
about
these
quella
more or less like you know
row versus user compared to temperature.
You mean like for the air in the room?
Yeah.
Oh boy.
The temperature is much,
much bigger,
very,
very much bigger.
Look,
it's a little exercise to work out.
The potential energy between a pair of molecules is roughly,
oh,
let's say electron volts or something like that.
So you can convert that to whatever units you like.
U is of order electron volts.
The density of particles is just the number of particles
in the room divided by the volume of the room.
Oh,
you need something else.
You need the volume of a molecule.
U naught is the energy scale,
which is a couple of electron volts times the
volume of a molecule or a couple of molecules,
couple of molecular volumes.
How big is a molecule?
10 to the minus 7 centimeters,
something like that.
An atom is 10 to the minus 8 centimeters.
A molecule is 10 to the minus 7 centimeters.
So you can take the density,
the volume of a molecule times the electron volt unit,
convert everything to meters and everything else,
or whatever unit you like.
Electron volts is fine.
And compare that with the
temperature measured in units of energy.
You would find that in this room,
you would find that in this room,
this is vastly smaller than this.
You have to start getting into the range where the
molecules are sort of almost butting up against each other.
It's when they start to,
you know,
have appreciable probability of being on top
of each other that this becomes violated.
So how much would you have to shrink the room?
I don't know.
I have to think about it.
But you'd have to shrink it down
quite a lot before that became important.
The U0 term,
is it possible for that to
have either a positive or negative sign?
Yes.
I was just about to talk about that.
All right.
Okay.
So U0 is the potential
energy between the pair of molecules.
It could look like this.
Conceivably,
it could look like this.
Now,
normally it wouldn't,
but it could.
What does this represent?
Which represents attraction and which represents repulsion?
This represents repulsion.
The energy goes up as you bring the molecules together.
This represents attraction.
What would you think offhand would be
the effect of repulsive forces on the pressure?
Yeah.
Repulsion between the molecules.
Clearly,
that if the repulsion is really,
really strong,
and you try to squeeze the
molecules to the way they are,
where they're really saying,
I don't want to get close to you,
buddy.
The pressure is going to go up.
So,
when the pressure,
when the U0 is positive,
that's the repulsive situation,
it corresponds to an extra bit of pressure.
So the pressure is stronger if the molecules repel.
If the molecules attract,
that means that you just choose U0.
It's going to be negative.
Okay,
that's the near ideal gas,
or the almost ideal gas,
or the weakly interacting gas.
The other limit,
yes?
Can you consider actual forces
like electrostatic repulsion and gravitational attraction?
Forget gravitation.
Yeah.
I mean,
to know what the force is,
what the pressure is between two molecules are,
you have to know something about molecular physics.
Okay,
molecular and atomic physics.
They're repulsive on the average.
They are,
on the average,
they're repulsive.
They have a,
they tend to look like this.
They're repulsive at short distances,
and then there's an attractive tail.
An attractive tail,
and the attractive tail leaks off slowly.
But the average tends to be repulsive.
The average is repulsive,
and so for most molecular situations,
this is positive.
But we're not doing molecular physics,
so I'm not going to
tell you how to calculate this.
You need a handbook of physics and chemistry or something.
You look it up,
and somewhere in there,
they would tell you what the potential energy is
between a pair of hydrogen molecules,
or hydrogen atoms,
or a pair of helium.
Helium is always a clean thing.
Not reactive.
Because it's a dipole.
Water is a good example because you get dipole forces.
Van der Waals forces are the
one over r to the sixth.
There's something called the 6-12 potential.
One is the one over r to the twelfth,
one is the one over r to the sixth.
They compete,
and they leave something which looks like this.
This is not the point,
though.
The point is,
given the dynamics,
given the formula for the energy,
how do you proceed?
Getting the formula for the energy
is not a problem in statistical mechanics.
Getting the formula for the potential
energy is not a problem in statistical mechanics.
It's a problem in quantum mechanics.
It's a problem in molecular structure.
It's a problem in atomic physics.
Whatever it happens to be,
that's your starting point
for thinking about statistical mechanics.
Okay.
That's not subtle.
This is very straightforward.
As I said,
it's blind navigation.
Just write down the energy formula.
Start doing the integrals.
Here and there,
of course,
there are tricks,
but the tricks are tricks of experience.
Knowing that I should multiply and divide
by the volume to the nth power,
that's just a matter of experience.
It doesn't take a hell of a lot of insight.
It's blind manipulation of the symbols.
In that sense,
it's...
Now,
at the end of the calculation,
it takes some insight to say,
look,
am I getting a sensible kind of answer?
What does this answer mean?
Is it of the right sign?
Does it make sense to say
that if the forces are repulsive,
that it increases the pressure between things?
Is it reasonable that it's proportional to rho squared?
The factor of a half,
well,
we know where that came from.
It came from the n
times n plus 1 over 2.
So you might,
in hindsight,
say,
yeah,
there should be a one-half there.
You'd overcount if you counted every pair of particles.
If you counted 1 and 2,
it was different than 2 and 1,
and so that's the half.
Okay.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
Why is intuitively rho squared
the right factor of rho to come in there?
You expect one more power of rho
because this term has to do
with the probability that two particles come together.
The other term only required one particle.
A particle is either there or it's not there.
It doesn't matter whether another particle is nearby.
So the probability for finding,
the probability to find a particle in a little volume
is proportional to rho.
The higher the density,
the more likely it is to
find a particle in a volume.
What's the probability for finding two particles
in a small volume
that's proportional to rho squared?
That's the probability to find one part.
If you only had two particles,
if you only had two particles,
let's start with one particle.
If you only had one particle
and the density is rho,
what's the probability of finding the particle
in a unit volume?
It's rho.
Right?
I mean,
uh,
it's proportional to rho.
What if there are two particles
and you want them both
to be in the same volume?
It's proportional to rho squared.
So,
that's all that's going on.
It's straightforward.
Okay,
now something that's much less straightforward.
And
I remember it really confusing me
when I learned thermodynamics.
Unfortunately,
the professor was more confused than I was
and couldn't straighten me out.
It had to do with heat and work
and something called exact differentials.
How many people have,
uh,
have heard of such things
and have been frustrated
and,
uh,
found themselves,
wanting to kill,
uh,
the textbook
because of,
uh,
exactly that?
Only two people.
Three.
Okay.
Four.
You may want to kill me,
too.
Let's take a little mathematical,
uh,
interlude
to talk about
exact
and inexact.
Now,
exact and inexact in this context
has nothing to do with precise versus imprecise.
Exact is a
technical mathematical term
which probably predates,
um,
homology theory
and other fancy things like that.
It does.
But,
uh,
it may have first turned up
in thermodynamics.
So,
let's talk about
the notion
of exact differentials
and non-exact differentials
and that sort of thing.
Take a function
of two variables.
So,
here's the two variables.
That's the xy plane,
x and y.
And the function is some,
think of it as the altitude.
Just the altitude
as a function of,
uh,
record,
f altitude,
faltitude.
f is the altitude
and it's a function of x and y.
Okay.
Now,
let's talk about what happens
when you move
from one point to another.
You're taking a little walk
in this altitude,
uh,
terrain,
in this altitude landscape.
And you're taking a little walk
and you take a step
and it corresponds
to a dx
and a dy.
Oh,
we,
we assume we know
the function f of x and y.
How much does our altitude change?
All right.
So,
our altitude,
altitude changes,
df
equals partial of f
with respect to x.
That's the rate of change
of f
if you moved along
the x-axis
times the x-axis.
Times the amount
that you move in x
plus
the rate of change
of f
if you move along
the y-axis
times dy.
You don't have to be moving
along the x-axis
or the y-axis.
You can be moving
at an angle.
This,
nevertheless,
is the formula.
Okay.
And let's write this
in the form
f sub x dx
plus f sub y dy.
This is called
a differential df.
Okay.
Is there any restrictions
on what f of x
and f of y
can be
in order
that this really be
the small change
in some genuine function?
And yes,
there are.
Basically,
one restriction.
Take the following quantity,
d second f
by dx
by dy.
This is the second derivative
of f
where you first differentiate
with respect to y
and then you differentiate
the result
with respect to x.
It's a theorem of calculus
that,
and it's an easy
theorem to prove.
We won't do it tonight.
I'm sure most of you
know it.
But it's a theorem
that it doesn't matter
in which order
you do the derivatives.
So that translates
into the statement,
let's put it over here,
df by dy,
that's fy.
And now we're differentiating
it with respect to x.
So that's d derivative
with respect to x,
of fy.
That's this term.
And on the right hand side,
we have exactly the opposite.
We have derivative of fx
with respect to y.
If I give you
an fx and an fy,
and I don't tell you anything else
except fx and fy,
this clearly
no guarantee
that this is true.
Given any old two functions
of x and y,
it will not be true
that,
I'll give you some examples later,
and the condition,
the condition that fx and fy
are really the derivatives
of a unique function
are exactly this over here.
Now,
take fx and fy.
They form the components
of a vector.
What is a vector called,
incidentally?
The gradient.
The gradient of f.
They are the gradient of f.
And if these two things
are the components of a vector,
of a gradient,
what is the statement over here?
Let's write it this way.
This minus this is equal to zero.
What's the left hand side?
The left hand side of the equation.
dy,
dfy by dx minus dfx by dy.
It's a curl.
It's the curl of f.
In this case,
it's only two-dimensional.
If it were three-dimensional,
there would be other components
of the curl.
This is the curl,
and given an object,
a set of components,
two components of a vector,
you can ask,
are those two components of a vector
really the gradient
of some function?
Is there really a function
of which fx and fy
are the components of the gradient?
And the test is this,
that the curl should be equal to zero.
There's another implication
of the curl being equal to zero.
I'll tell you what it is.
It's intuitively obvious that the
following.
Thinking this is principle 2.
The firstwelt output is one scale.
The sum of bothamental output
Oh,
But another answer is to add up all of the little
incremental changes in f as you move from one point to another
And that is,
we'll call that delta f
in moving from 1 to 2
Is just the integral,
just the sum of all the little incremental changes
Of df,
the little change in f,
which is f dx plus fy dy
That integral along this curve
here is the change in f
Now what would happen if you chose another
curve and you went from 1 to 2?
Would you get the same
answer for the change of f?
Yeah,
because f is just the altitude
And if you go from 1 to
2 on one path or another path,
the change in the altitude is the same
Okay?
So that says that this line integral
doesn't depend on what path you take
Is that true in general for any fx and fy?
That a path of an integral
like this doesn't depend on the path
So let me give you an
example of just an intuitive example
A silly example,
but it's a real example
Okay?
So you do this operation by driving your car
from one point to another along two different trajectories
Okay?
And what I'm interested in is
not the change in the altitude
I'm interested in the change in
the reading of my gas meter
I want to know how much gas I used
So does the change in the gas meter,
does the amount of gas that you use,
what is it?
All right?
It's just the change in the altitude,
right?
And then you'll be interested in what?
the quantity of gas that's left in the car,
that's left in the gas tank,
does that depend on the
on the route that you take?
Yeah.
Of course it does.
For example,
if I take a route from one point
to another that keeps you at the same
altitude at all times,
you'll use a different amount of gas
than if you go from one point
to another
over a hill.
The
change in going over the hill
will be a larger change in the gas tank.
Another way to say this incidentally
is that if you go around in a closed loop,
starting one place,
coming back to the same place,
how much does the altitude change?
Zero.
How about the change in your
gas tank
not only does it depend on how you go,
but it certainly won't come
back to the same value afterwards.
Nevertheless,
nevertheless,
the change in your fuel,
now F stands for fuel,
the change in the fuel
can be written in this form.
How much fuel you use
to go a little X distance,
and then how much fuel you use to
go a little Y distance on this terrain.
The change in the fuel can
also be written as a differential.
But it's not the differential,
it's the differential of some function.
If it was the differential of a well-defined function,
if you go around in a loop,
the change has to be zero.
It's quite clear that if we're talking about the,
another example could be how
tired are you after going around.
Let's make the approximation for simplicity
that you don't get tired at
all if you don't change altitude.
Walking,
sliding along a frictionless surface or something,
no effort.
What about climbing over a hill
and coming back to the same place?
Well,
if you got untired by going down the hill,
then maybe you could say
that your tiredness ratio wouldn't change.
But that's not true.
You get plenty tired going downhill.
So,
whatever these F's are,
they are such that if you
go around in a closed loop,
you do get a change.
There is a complete mathematical equivalence
to the question of whether line
integrals around closed paths give zero
and whether the curl of
the function is equal to zero.
They're the same mathematical statement.
The curl has to do
with going around a little loop.
Going around a little loop and asking
how much things change is the curl itself.
Going around a big loop is the line integral.
So,
the main point is not every pair of functions,
Fx and Fy,
define in this way,
they can always,
they define a differential,
but that differential is not
necessarily the differential of a function.
So,
let me give you some examples,
two examples specifically.
Two very simple examples.
Oh,
incidentally,
when this is true,
the vector field F or the
Fx and Fy are called exact.
When it's not true,
they're called inexact.
Exact here does not refer to accuracy.
It refers to whether the curl
of the vector field is zero.
The problem I had was that
I was told on the one hand
that it applied the exactness condition applied to a system
when it was a conservative system,
but no mathematical statement was given
for what a conservative system was.
Conservative systems have to do with forces.
If Fx and Fy correspond to the force field,
then exactness corresponds to conservation of energy.
But that's not what we're talking about here.
We're just talking about mathematical properties.
I'm just saying that when I raised my hand,
I didn't have any trouble with the math part here.
I know.
I understand.
Right.
But not everybody is familiar with the concept,
so I want to go through it,
the mathematics of it.
Yeah.
Is this somehow related to the curvature?
Again,
if you look at x as
a vector and y as a vector,
the cross product is a tensor and the
dot product has to be zero or something.
It has a great deal to do with curvature.
For example,
on a curvature of a surface,
going around the curve may change angles.
But I don't want to go there now.
It has a great deal to do with curvature.
But it is what it is.
It is what it is.
Some Df's are differentials of functions.
Others are just random expressions involving small
changes of things that you carry with you.
You know,
how about the gas?
The gas in the car is a well-defined quantity.
It just doesn't depend on x and y.
You can go from one point
to another in two different routes
and change the amount of gas in two different ways.
So the gas in the car is a
thing you carry with you along a path,
and it definitely has a definite meaning along the path.
It's just not a function of where you are.
It's a function of the whole
path of how you got there.
In exact differentials usually have to do with things,
changes that depend not only
on the endpoints of a trajectory,
but depend on the whole trajectory,
like getting tired,
or the entire trajectory.
So you can't just change the
amount of fuel in your gas tank.
Okay.
So...
We now know what exact and inexact means.
Let's give some examples.
How about trying f sub x is equal to y,
and f sub y is equal to x.
The test for exactness is this.
All right.
So let's calculate dfx by dy.
What is that?
One.
How about dfy by dx?
Is this exact?
Yes.
This is exact,
and it must mean that fx
and fy are derivatives of some function.
Can you guess what function
fx and fy are the greatest?
What are the gradients of?
xy.
Take the function f equals xy.
Its derivative with respect to x is y.
Its derivative with respect to y is x.
Okay.
So this is really the gradient of some function.
What about this one here?
fx is equal to y.
fy is equal to minus x.
This is a possible rule for how
the change in your gas tank might work.
If you take a little,
this is a perfectly good rule about small
differentials of the amount of gas in your car,
but it does not define a function.
All right.
How do I know that?
Because in this case,
dfx by dy is one,
but dfy by dx is equal,
what did I write here?
One.
Minus one now.
Okay.
When I wrote zero here,
I meant that the difference between them was zero.
Excuse me.
The derivatives were the same the first time.
Now they're not the same.
These are simply not the derivatives of a real function,
of any function.
And if I were to take a little excursion,
calculating the change of f as I
move around according to that df there,
as I move from one point to another,
and I came back to the same point,
I would find that f didn't come
back to the same value in this case.
Now let's talk about heat and work.
Heat and work have to do with energy,
and they have to do with the changes in energy.
So let's define them.
We've...
We're thinking about a gas now.
It doesn't have to be a gas.
It could be a liquid.
It could be anything.
But we're thinking about energy,
volume,
and those kinds of things.
Let's imagine...
All right.
So let's take our independent variables.
Independent variables.
The system is a box of gas.
And it has a,
you know,
a plunger that allows us to...
A piston which allows us to
change the volume of the gas.
We can push it in.
We can push it out.
What are the independent variables?
There are two independent variables.
One can take them to
be the temperature and the volume,
or you could take them to be
the energy of the box and the volume.
We'll take them to be the energy and the volume.
Energy and volume are our independent variables.
Energy and volume.
And let's think about the...
Energy and volume?
No,
I'm sorry.
I'm wrong.
What do I want to do?
Sorry.
Entropy and volume.
If you know the entropy,
any two things will do.
Any two things will do.
It only depends on two things.
It depends,
if you like,
on the temperature and the volume.
But you can substitute,
if you like,
the entropy and the volume.
That's enough to determine the state of the gas,
the thermodynamic state of the gas.
How much entropy and how
much volume completely determines it.
Let's think about the energy.
Let's take the change in the energy,
if we change the volume a little bit,
without changing the entropy.
What's a process called if you don't change the entropy?
Adiabatic,
right?
Alright,
so for an adiabatic process,
what's the change in the energy?
We're changing the volume a little bit.
The term is reversible,
and the adiabatic is repeatable.
There seems to be a disagreement about the terminology.
Quantum physicists mean by adiabatic slow.
And what I will mean by adiabatic
is both slow and no heat exchange.
Both.
In that case,
you're right,
it's also called reversible.
Reversible is another word for no change of entropy.
But in any case,
bottom line,
if the entropy doesn't change,
how does the energy change?
Minus pressure times the volume.
That's the change in the energy of
the gas if you don't change the entropy.
That's what we went through last time.
Definition of pressure.
It's essentially the definition of pressure.
How does the energy change if you change the
volume slowly and without allowing any heat to flow in,
reversibly if you like,
with no change of entropy?
Okay.
This is the formula.
Now,
what about the change in energy
if you keep the volume fixed,
but you add a little bit of heat?
I don't know where you got it.
You got some energy you took from somewheres,
and you dump it into the system,
however you did it.
You could do it by putting a flame
under here and heating it a little bit.
Then what is the change in energy?
In that case,
without changing the volume,
it's equal to the temperature
times the change in the entropy.
That is basically a definition of entropy.
Or temperature,
I'm sorry.
That's the definition of temperature.
The change of energy is by definition
the temperature times the change in entropy.
Entropy we defined independently.
We defined it probabilistically.
All right.
So these are two statements.
Now,
supposing you change both the volume and the entropy.
This means you do a process.
You could think of it as little incremental processes.
First you do a change of volume,
keeping the entropy fixed.
Then you change the entropy a little bit,
keeping the volume fixed.
But at the end of the day,
you make a small change of both volume and entropy.
And how do you do it?
You change the volume a little bit,
and you put in a little bit of heat.
You do a general process involving both kinds of things.
In that case,
dE is equal to minus pdV plus TdS.
That's called the first law of thermodynamics.
And it just expresses energy conservation.
Incidentally,
who's doing work?
This is work.
It's called dW,
dWork.
And this is called dQ.
Q stands for heat.
Isn't it obvious that Q stands for heat?
Don't ask me where the Q came from.
I don't know.
Qualories or something.
I don't know where it came from.
The Q stands for heat.
And this is the definition of heat.
This is the definition of the
heat that you put in TdS.
You change the energy by changing the entropy.
That's an irreversible change.
It could correspond to just dumping some heat in.
This corresponds to changing the energy.
Who's doing work on whom,
incidentally?
Is this the work done on the gas?
Or is this the work done
by the gas on the piston?
They're equal and opposite,
of course.
The work done...
Hm?
This is the change in the energy of the gas.
So this should be thought of as the
work done by the piston on the gas.
If the pressure is positive and you change the volume,
you lower the energy of the gas.
Why?
Because you do work on the piston.
If the pressure is positive
and you push against the piston,
you do work on the piston,
and therefore you lower the energy of the gas
and raise the energy of the piston.
All right.
So this d-work here is
the work done on the gas.
And this says that the change in energy...
This is just definition.
This is definition.
This is work.
And this is heat.
The question is whether Q is really a function.
Is dQ really an exact differential?
Is there such a thing
as the heat of a system?
Now,
the problem is you could go from...
What is it?
All right.
If you know the volume and the entropy,
you know everything about the system.
Volume and entropy is
thermodynamically enough to know everything.
It tells you the temperature.
It tells you the energy.
It tells you everything.
Okay.
So you would think of going from
one value of volume and entropy to another,
taking a walk in a volume-entropy space.
The question is whether the heat
that you have to put in
to go from one point
to another depends on the path
or does it depend on the energy?
It doesn't depend on the path.
Or another way of saying it is
if you go around a closed loop,
you put little bits of heat in,
you put little bits of work in,
you take little bits of work out,
you take little bits of heat out.
At the end of the day,
if you come back to the same point,
is the total amount of
heat that you've put in zero
as it would be if
the heat were a real function?
You came back to the same point.
Or does it depend on the path,
the path that you took?
And the answer is it depends on the path,
but we're going to prove that.
We're going to prove that
dq is not an exact differential.
Neither is dw.
What is true is if you
take a system through a cycle
or a series of steps and
come back to the same state,
that the total energy that
you put into it is zero.
You bring it around and
come back to the same state,
you're going to have the same point,
the energy will be the same,
but the heat that you put in
or the work that you take out
or whatever will depend on the route that you took.
Are we assuming that all
these paths are on an equilibrium?
Yes,
we do them slowly so that they stay in equilibrium.
Does this have a curl-type formulation?
That's what we'll do.
We'll use a curl-type formulation to check
and we'll see what the...
It's not too hard.
It's actually just one or two steps.
Okay,
so let's just write this.
leave it as it is.
TDS.
Let's write...
Remember,
our independent variables are entropy and volume.
So let's write now that...
What do we want to write?
Let me get my notes.
Yeah.
Here it is.
dq,
that's this term over here,
is equal to dE minus or plus pdV.
Okay.
I'm going to change the
independent variables from S and V
to energy and volume.
Energy and volume.
Do I have this right?
Yeah.
Energy and volume.
However I move from one point to another,
dq will be equal to the change in energy
plus the pressure times the change in volume.
Okay,
so now let's write.
Let's assume that q is a real function,
that it's an exact differential.
First of all,
this would say that dq
by dE is equal to one.
You would read off here that dq by dE,
the change in q,
if you change the energy keeping the volume fixed,
is equal to one.
That's one thing that this tells you.
Another thing that it tells you
is that the change in q,
when you change the volume keeping the energy fixed,
is the pressure.
That's what it would say if
there really was a function q
that this was the derivative of.
Is it true?
How can we test out whether
there really is a function q?
Well,
there is a function that satisfies this.
We test the curl.
This is dq by dE.
Let's differentiate it with respect to volume.
What do we get?
So we get on the left-hand side,
d second q by dE by
d volume is equal to zero.
Now let's differentiate the right-hand
side with respect to energy.
What do we get?
We get the derivative of the
pressure with respect to the energy.
If there really was a function q,
in other words,
a function that didn't depend on how
you move from one path to another,
it would have to say that dp
by d energy would be equal to zero.
That's the curl test.
Differentiate this one with respect to volume.
That gives you zero.
Differentiate this one with respect to energy.
This would give you d pressure by d energy.
Will you believe that if
you have a box of gas
and you change the energy in the box of gas,
that the pressure doesn't change?
No.
Of course it does.
But let's check it for an ideal gas.
Let's check it for an ideal gas.
We've done the calculation for an ideal gas.
The pressure of an ideal gas,
PV,
uh,
yes,
is equal to,
PV equals NT.
So,
P equals P over V,
right?
Okay,
leave it that way.
That's one equation.
Good.
And another equation I want is that
the energy is equal to three halves NT.
NT is equal to two-thirds E.
This says that NT is equal to two-thirds E.
So,
we can write that this is
equal to two-thirds E over volume.
Do I have that right?
E over volume.
Pressure is two-thirds E over volume.
Okay.
Now we come back to this side over here.
And we ask,
when you change the energy,
does the pressure change?
At fixed volume.
And the answer is yes.
At fixed volume,
if you change the energy,
the pressure changes.
So,
it is simply not true that the P
by DE is simply not equal to zero.
Not equal to zero.
The curl test has failed.
I'm getting tired.
But the curl test has failed.
I'm going to give you an example of this.
indicating that there's no such thing as
Q being a function of where you are,
of what the state of the system is,
it depends on how you
move from one place to another.
In other words,
the amount of heat that you
have to put into a system
in order to change it
from one state to another state
description,
how much heat you put into the system is
not a good description of the state of the system
It's as good as asking how tired
you are and whether that determines your altitude
Right.
No,
how tired you are depends on how
you went from one point to another and
not just a change in altitude
so
Heat is like that.
Heat is like that and work is like that.
Only the combination of the two of them
Is really a function of the state of the system
Function of the state of the system means a
function of the temperature and volume or energy and volume
Okay,
I'm getting a little tired.
Is there any questions left?
This is very subtle stuff.
It's very tricky
I know everybody has or many people
have seen it and been confused by it
You're probably still a little bit confused by it
but
Why should you be why
should it be the case that?
The that the heat that you have to put in
versus the work
To get from one place to another
Should not depend on how you
get there how you go there.
Okay,
I'm tired.
We've had enough
It's related to the efficiency of an engine yes,
right
right,
so right exactly so
What's that
It's connected with all of these things.
It's connected with things like hysteresis
Memory and systems,
but here it's just a statement
that the heat is not a
Function of the properties of there's
not a property of a system
Heat is not a property of a system now
You know your state of
tiredness is a property of you,
but it's not a property of the landscape
Not a property of where you are in the exercise
You're not a property of the landscape
Your state of tiredness depends on how
you went from one X to another X
Same with heat same with all right enough of that
Enough of that we're finished with it.
We won't have to do no more heat
For more please visit us at Stanford edu