Stanford University
Alright,
let's,
what I want to do tonight is just begin,
well what we're going to do
is eventually get to the second law,
what the second law means,
how it's consistent.
I will try to explain the second
law to the best of my ability.
There should be lots of
questions which I will try to answer.
I know a little bit about the second law.
There may
be two or three people
in the world who know more,
but I've never met any.
we'll talk a little about the second law,
what it means.
But before we do that,
I want to just think
about some physical examples that we've
learned some information about by doing
statistical mechanics.
First,
I just want to illustrate
some of the just numerical facts
about gases and so forth
by contemplating the speed of sound.
Speed of sound in a gas,
and in particular in a fairly dilute gas.
What is the speed of sound?
There are two formulas for the speed of sound,
but if you think about it for a moment,
and you start with a very dilute gas,
what would you expect the speed of sound to be?
Let's say you make a little bit of overdrive
in a very dense region.
How fast does that overdensity spread?
That's the speed of sound.
What would you guess?
Well,
I know what I would guess.
I would guess that it
sure isn't going to be faster
than the time that it
takes for a molecule to travel
out to a certain distance.
And in fact,
for a very dilute gas,
you might expect that that little overdense region
just spreads out,
with a velocity that's not too different
than the average velocity of the molecules.
How does it spread out?
It spreads out by the molecules moving out.
How fast do the molecules move out?
They move out with their velocity.
What is their velocity?
Ah,
now,
then we have to work a little bit
to find out what the velocity is.
So let's write down a formula.
In thermal equilibrium at a temperature T,
in a dilute gas,
every molecule has a energy equal to 3 halves kT.
Now,
I'm going to put the k in now,
because we want to do some laboratory numerology.
3 halves k Boltzmann times the temperature,
where the temperature is measured in Kelvin.
Kelvin means relative to absolute zero,
but the difference between,
you know,
one degree corresponds to one centigrade degree.
Nine,
what is it,
nine-fifths of a Fahrenheit degree.
Okay,
so it's three halves,
and you can see from this formula
that the temperature goes to zero
when the energy goes to zero.
You see it right here.
Okay,
so temperature zero,
energy zero.
And what is that energy?
That energy must be the kinetic energy
of the molecule.
It's the only energy that it has
for an ideal gas in a big box.
So it's got to be one-half
the mass of the molecule times the velocity squared.
And now that tells us what the average velocity is.
Multiply by two.
I didn't mean to throw away the three.
And now divide by m.
And take the square root,
but I'll leave it as velocity squared for the moment,
just the velocity squared.
And you might expect that that's more or less
the speed of sound in a gas.
And that's pretty close.
There is a more exact,
let's see,
there is a more exact formula.
The more exact formula comes by actually studying
the mechanics of lumps of gas
and the forces on them.
The forces,
I'm not going to work it out.
We're not going to do this tonight.
We could do it another night.
It's not hard.
It's easy to do.
Newton was able to do it.
Well,
I mean,
you know.
Newton did it.
It's not too hard.
You know,
you take a box of gas,
you take a region in the gas,
and you first say what forces are on it,
the forces have to do
with the pressure from the outside,
and there's a net force
if there's a gradient of pressure.
If the pressure on this wall
is the same as the pressure
on that wall,
there's no net force.
So there's some force due to the gradient of pressure.
You take that into account.
What is the response to the variation in pressure?
It's F equals m a.
It's acceleration.
So the box starts to move.
The acceleration depends on the mass in the box,
so the density,
the mass density,
comes into it.
But in the end,
you find a formula.
And the formula,
I'm just going to write the formula down.
The formula is that the speed of sound squared,
this is the velocity of a molecule,
the speed of sound squared is equal,
and this is a fairly general formula.
This formula is more general than just the ideal gas
or an approximately ideal gas.
It's E squared is equal to,
the derivative of the pressure
with respect to the mass density.
Now I'm going to write the mass density
as the product of the density of particles,
the thing we've already called rho,
the density of particles,
times the mass of an individual particle.
Mass of the individual particle
times the density,
of particles,
is the mass density.
So the standard formula
for the square of the speed of sound
is the derivative of the pressure
with respect to the mass density,
which is the same as the derivative of the pressure
with respect to the particle density
divided by the mass.
Let's see what the ideal gas formula
has to say about this.
The ideal gas formula that we derived
is pressure times volume equals
n times,
let's put the k Boltzmann in,
times the temperature,
or dividing by the volume,
n over the volume.
Now n over the volume
is the particle density.
So here we have the particle density.
This is rho.
But it's not the mass density.
If,
well alright,
here it is.
We have it here.
Derivative of p with respect to rho
times one over mass.
So this is the formula.
Here we have p as a function of rho.
What is the derivative of p with respect to rho?
Derivative of p with respect to rho
is equal to k Boltzmann t.
Just differentiating.
And then we divide by one more mass.
And we get k Boltzmann t over m.
Not quite the same formula.
But for the velocity itself,
this is the square of the velocity.
This simplistic formula
is wrong by a factor of square root of three.
Square root of three is 1.7,
so it's not so bad.
But order of magnitude,
it's essentially correct.
We could,
let's work it out.
Let's work it out for a,
for the air.
I have some numbers written down.
Let's use this formula.
You just stick in some numbers,
either formula,
they'll be,
the velocity will be the same
to within a factor of 1.7
or whatever it is.
Alright,
so if you stick in,
k Boltzmann equals 1.3
times 10 to the minus 23rd.
The mass,
what about the mass of an air molecule?
Air molecules are mostly made out of nitrogen.
And nitrogen is one of these
di-molecular,
what do you call it,
a two atoms,
a diatomic molecule.
Alright.
Nitrogen is,
nitrogen has atomic weight 14,
if I remember.
And so the mass of a,
the mass of a nitrogen,
or the mass of an air molecule,
is about 30,
28,
30,
times the mass of a proton.
And you look that up,
that winds up being about
4 times 10 to the minus 26th,
kilograms.
What else do we need to know?
Oh,
and we need to know room temperature.
We're working at room temperature.
Room temperature is 300,
300 degrees
in the same units where k Boltzmann
is equal to this number here.
So stick it in,
what do you get?
I get about,
when I stuck it in,
I got about
the velocity itself,
was about
I think 500,
yeah,
500 meters per second.
That's what you get out of,
out of this formula.
It's a little on the high side.
The right answer is about
300 meters per second.
Yeah.
If you,
if you add the neutrons in there,
you'll get a smaller number of...
No,
no,
the neutrons are in there.
14 means 14 protons plus neutrons.
Oh,
you did that.
Mm-hmm,
that's in there.
Quick question.
Yeah,
atomic weight is 14,
not the atomic number.
The number three
in the initial derivation
had to do with the three dimensions.
Yes,
it did.
And the speed of sound
is meant to be in one direction.
Doesn't that make the three go away?
Well,
no.
Maybe.
Thanks.
Okay.
All right,
good.
Good point,
maybe.
I'll have to think about it.
But the point,
yeah,
you may be right.
You may well be right.
So,
but in any case,
the orders of magnitude are correct.
And,
I suppose this,
I wonder,
I don't know who the first one
to actually do this calculation was.
I don't know.
Actually,
sit down and say,
what is the speed of light
given the atomic weight of nitrogen,
given Boltzmann's constant,
and,
of course,
they didn't,
in order to use,
where's the other equation?
dp by d rho,
all I had to do
was to measure the pressure result.
And,
I think,
that was a function of density.
So,
they didn't have to do anything fancy.
But I'm not sure who
was the first one to realize
that it was basically the velocity of a molecule.
Question?
All right,
now,
I want to come to a puzzle.
Well,
let's see,
are we ready for the puzzle?
No,
we're not ready for the puzzle.
We're going,
yeah.
So,
what we just did assumes that it's constant,
but it's not really constant.
Which is constant?
The temperature.
Yeah,
I think it's a fairly good assumption.
The,
of course,
yes,
we did assume the temperature was constant.
I think that's probably very good
for small amplitude sound waves.
Imagine for small amplitude sound waves,
the temperature doesn't vary very much
as it vibrates.
Now,
again,
I'm not absolutely sure about that.
I would guess that the temperature
has very,
very little variation
in a near ideal gas
for very,
very low amplitude sound waves.
So,
I think that's probably okay.
The variation of pressure is also small.
What's that?
The variation of pressure would also be small.
The derivative of that,
I've heard.
The variation of pressure is also small,
yeah.
Yeah,
the variation of pressure is small.
The variation of density is small.
But the variation of pressure with respect to density
is not necessarily small.
Yeah.
I mean,
usually,
I expect that when something is,
if you increase the pressure of it,
you'd think that the speed of sound would go faster
because it's sort of like a
solid is faster speed of sound
than a liquid is in the gas.
Well,
this dpd rho is calculated
at the pressure that you're working at.
dpd rho is not necessarily a constant.
The pressure depends on the density
in a complicated way.
In particular,
as the molecules get really squeezed together,
the derivative of pressure with respect to rho
gets very,
very large.
So,
you're right,
but it's because this changes.
Yeah.
You'd expect V0 to be a constant,
but something related to...
You'd expect what?
I mean,
the speed of sound,
you'd expect it to be related to pressure somehow.
Yeah,
sure it is.
Sure it is.
This quantity depends on pressure.
So you can't say V equals 500?
No,
no,
no.
This is at...
I'm sorry.
Okay.
That's right.
This is at low pressure,
or better yet,
low density,
where the gas can be approximated as an ideal gas.
It doesn't...
In the ideal gas range,
it doesn't depend on pressure.
But,
as you...
You know,
the reason it doesn't is because,
if you go to the formula,
that pressure is equal to rho times the temperature,
at fixed temperature,
pressure is just proportional to rho.
But as the pressure gets larger and larger,
this formula is going to break down.
For example,
it might start varying like rho squared.
In which case,
as you say,
the speed of sound will depend on
the pressure.
Right.
Just sort of to come back
to the idea that you started with,
where the velocity of sound is about
equal to the velocity of a monofuel.
Yeah.
I imagine that idea would break
down also as the density gets larger.
Probably.
Yeah,
I think it probably does.
You know,
I never thought about it very much.
This is as much...
This is the depth that I've gone into it.
Yeah.
I have a question.
Sorry I missed out.
Why is the mass 32?
30 times the mass of the proton?
Well,
I've made an approximation.
30 is equal to 28.
Oh,
okay.
Right.
So as far as an approximation,
if you divide 500 by 1.7,
you get about 300.
And just divide it by square root of 3.
Could be.
Let's move on.
Let's move on to the harmonic oscillator.
Now we have not a free particle in a gas,
but I'm going to put into
the gas or into the system,
whatever it happens to be,
whatever the heat bath is,
I'm going to put in a single harmonic oscillator.
It's part of the...
It's part of the system.
And I'm going to treat the rest
of the system as a heat bath
and ask about the property of the harmonic oscillator.
Now the harmonic oscillator could be a spring
with a mass on it
or anything else which naturally oscillates.
It could be an electromagnetic wave in a cavity.
What else oscillates?
What's another example of an oscillator?
Sorry?
Crystal with a...
Crystal.
Right.
All sorts of oscillations take place in crystals.
That's right.
So there's lots and lots and
lots of oscillating systems in nature.
Almost anything will oscillate if you
just disturb it a little bit.
So when we say the harmonic oscillator,
we're studying an extremely wide class of systems.
Anything will oscillate.
Which when disturbed a little bit away from equilibrium,
away from its ground state,
will oscillate and that covers
almost anything you can think about.
So let's do the statistical
mechanics of the harmonic oscillator.
Interesting question.
What is the average energy of the oscillator?
How does it depend on its mass?
How does it depend on the spring constant?
And so forth.
Uh...
And see if we can work
out the answer to that question.
So what do we do?
We begin with a Hamilton...
With an energy,
with an expression for the energy.
We're going to put it into the Boltzmann distribution
and then we're going to
calculate average quantities for the oscillator.
Okay,
what is the energy?
The energy is one half mass times x dot squared,
where x is the coordinate of
the oscillator away from its equilibrium position.
Mass is the mass plus the
spring constant times x squared over two.
This is not the Boltzmann constant.
Now we are finished with Boltzmann.
Boltzmann will fade into the background now.
We no longer will keep track of the Boltzmann constant.
K here is the spring constant.
The Hooke's law spring constant.
Or equivalently,
if we go to momentum instead of velocity,
it becomes p squared divided by two m.
Momentum squared divided by two m
plus the same kx squared over two.
So that's our expression for energy.
This is our expression for energy.
And now we want to write
the Boltzmann distribution for this system here.
And that's e to the minus...
beta.
Beta is the inverse temperature.
Now what determines the temperature?
The heat bath that it's immersed in.
So if the oscillator was in this room,
it would be 300 degrees.
If it was in liquid helium,
it would be three degrees,
four degrees,
whatever.
If it was in the middle of the sun,
it would evaporate and it wouldn't be there.
But it's not there.
You know what I mean.
Okay,
e to the minus beta,
p squared over two m.
I'm going to factorize it.
e to the minus beta,
kx squared over two.
I've simply used the fact
that the exponential of a sum
is just a product of exponentials.
So I've factorized it like this.
That's the expression for e to
the minus beta times the energy.
What do we do with it?
We calculate our friend,
the partition function.
And the partition function is our best friend
in statistical mechanics.
So we calculate it,
and that's equal to the sum of all configurations,
which in this case means dp,
dx.
Now in previous situations,
the x integration just gave
us the volume of the container
that the box was in.
Now that's not true,
because we're doing an integration of the integrals factor.
dp,
dx.
Two separate integrals.
It's just a product of two integrals.
We can write it.
Let's call it the p integral and the x integral.
I put the p downstairs here because
I didn't have room to write dp.
But that's what I mean.
Integral dp,
integral dx.
Okay,
so all we have to do
now is to do these two integrals.
Remember that numerical constants in the partition function,
multiplicative constants,
don't make any difference.
Why not?
Because when you take the
logarithm of the partition function,
they correspond to additive constants.
And since we're always going
to be differentiating the partition function,
we don't care about numerical constants.
Okay,
so let's,
forgetting the numerical constants,
we want to do these integrals.
The p integral is the number of integrals.
So we're going to do the integration.
We do the same way that we did.
I'll just remind you how we did it.
We said that p squared over 2m beta,
the thing occurring here,
we changed variables and we called that q squared.
And obviously that means that p is equal to
the square root of 2m over beta times q.
Once we do that,
this integral here becomes integral.
Now,
dp,
we have dp here.
I took it away.
dp,
let me put it back.
What is dp?
dp is the square root
of 2m over beta times dq.
So,
the first thing we do is we
pull out a factor of square root,
p equals square root of 2m over beta.
All right,
so first of all,
we have the factor of
square root of 2m over beta.
That's coming from dp.
Then we can write dq,
and this thing just becomes
e to the minus q squared.
This is a definite integral.
What are the ends of the integration?
Minus infinity.
Minus infinity to infinity to infinity.
The momentum can be anything.
Minus infinity to infinity.
And this is a number.
If you happen to remember,
the number happens to be the square root of 2pi.
But who cares?
It's a numerical constant that we don't care about.
It happens to be,
it is a pi.
Let's put it in there,
pi.
That's this integral,
and we're finished with it.
We've seen it before.
It's the same one that occurred in the ideal gas.
The new integration that occurs,
so this,
this integral has been replaced by this.
What about this one over here?
We play exactly the same game.
Let's make it,
this is dx.
Change of variables.
X squared beta spring constant over 2,
we will call y squared.
That means that x is equal to square
root of 2 over beta kappa times y.
Alright,
we have dx here.
So the dx is going to become a dy.
It will give us an additional factor
of square root of 2pi over beta kappa.
And then we have this integral,
k,
spring constant.
That's the dx.
Forget the 2pi,
just square root of 2.
Comes from here.
And then the integral just
becomes e to the minus beta,
e to the minus y squared dy.
By changing variables,
we turn the integral into just a simple integral,
e to the minus y squared.
And that again is equal
to the square root of pi.
So that's our whole answer,
very simple.
That's the whole partition function.
Z.
Let's write it in Z.
And it's equal,
first of all it has a 2pi.
The 2pi is of no particular interest to us.
It contains also a,
a square root of m over kappa.
Square root of m over kappa.
m from here,
kappa from here.
Anybody know what the square
root of m over kappa is?
What about the,
what about the frequency of the oscillator?
Do you remember the frequency of a harmonic oscillator
in terms of its mass and its spring constant?
What's that?
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
So we could just write this as
1 over the frequency,
and I'll do so.
But of course the frequency is a constant.
But nevertheless,
I want to keep it for now.
2pi over omega times 1 divided by beta.
That's Z.
Now let's calculate the energy of the oscillator.
How do we do that?
We calculate the logarithm of Z
and differentiate it with respect to beta.
That's the formula that we've
learned to use and to trust.
So log Z
is equal
to the log of 2pi over omega.
That's a constant.
So let's write it as a constant.
And then minus log beta.
Minus log beta.
That's equal to log Z.
And now what we want to do is,
we want to calculate minus the derivative of log Z
with respect to beta.
What is that equal to?
Remember?
The energy.
The average energy.
That's the energy.
Minus the log Z by d beta.
You know,
we're cruising now.
We're not thinking.
We're just chasing symbols.
The constant gives us nothing.
The minus sign takes away the minus sign from here.
And the derivative of log beta with respect to beta
is just 1 over beta.
1 over beta,
yeah.
Which also is better known as the temperature.
Okay.
Not so different than the 3 halves kT.
Well,
let's just write 3 halves T
for the particle and the gas.
Now,
the first thing is,
where's,
why no 3?
Well,
because this is just a one-dimensional oscillator
oscillating along an axis.
So there's no 3.
But what happened to the 2 down here?
Why wasn't it 1 half?
And the reason is because there were two integrals,
each of which gave us a 1 half log beta.
The first integral here gave us
a 1 over square root of beta.
The second one also gave us
If there would have been more integrals of this type,
for whatever reason,
more dimensions,
more degrees of freedom,
whatever,
we would have gotten a 1
half log beta for each of them.
1 half log beta means 1
half T for each of them.
So for each integration that we have to do,
which has this form of
e to the minus x squared,
they're called Gaussian integrals,
for each integration like that that we have to do,
there is basically a 1
half the temperature in the energy.
Okay.
What are the two kinds of energies,
incidentally,
that we're talking about?
We're talking about the energy of the atom,
the energy of an oscillator,
this kinetic energy and potential energy.
In fact,
the kinetic energy and potential energy,
the average kinetic energy and potential energy,
are in fact equal,
and each one equal to 1 half beta,
1 half temperature.
So the kinetic energy is 1 half temperature,
the potential energy is 1 half temperature,
together they give you the temperature.
Now there's a couple of
interesting things to notice about this,
two interesting things to notice about it.
They're both very similar.
First is that the answer doesn't
depend on the mass of the oscillator.
That was also true of the particle in the gas.
At a given temperature,
the energy,
the kinetic energy of the particle,
did not depend on the mass of the particle.
The velocity did.
The velocity does because the velocity,
1 half mv squared is the energy,
1 half mv squared is the same
for all of the different mass particles,
v squared of course will be smaller for heavy particles.
Same is true here.
The average kinetic energy is the temperature,
and it's independent of the mass of the oscillator.
It's also independent of the spring constant.
That's a little surprising.
It's surprising if you think about it,
because imagine making the spring constant huge.
Imagine making the spring constant so large
that no known force on earth can,
or elsewhere,
can stretch this spring away from its equilibrium point.
One would think under such circumstances,
that it's not a spring,
it's just a constrained thing,
which has a fixed length,
perhaps the length being zero,
which cannot be changed.
Under those circumstances,
any sensible person would say,
you can't excite it.
You can't give it any energy.
There's no way to start it vibrating.
There's no way to give it any structure at all.
You can't give it any kinetic energy,
because it's absolutely locked in place.
You can't give it any potential energy,
because you can't pull it away from that point,
no matter how much force you exert on it.
Yet,
the formula doesn't seem to care.
The formula doesn't seem to care.
There always seems to be energy kT for every oscillator,
no matter how unphysical,
no matter how hard it
is to get that oscillator going.
There's something wrong.
Question?
If k goes to infinity,
z goes to zero.
k doesn't appear...
k appears here,
but it doesn't appear here.
Once you take the logarithm,
the k appears as an additive constant.
You can't take the logarithm if z is zero.
Let's let k be 10 to the 500.
There's something wrong about the limits here.
There's something wrong,
but the something that's wrong is
that we've ignored one very crucial feature of nature.
We have not ignored anything about classical mechanics.
This is a correct classical mechanical conclusion.
On the other hand,
it's crazy.
Let me give you an
example of the kind of craziness
that would be involved.
We talked about a particle...
Excuse me.
Yeah.
Before we move on,
I just had a question about the partition function.
When we did the analogous computation previously
and there was no dependence on the position,
we then got the volume to the nth power.
But divide by an n factorial
to take out some repetition of stuff.
Yeah,
yeah,
but it didn't make any difference.
All it did was add a multiplicative constant
in the partition function.
So is there an appropriate n factorial
that's needed here?
No,
it's only one particle.
It's only one oscillator.
Yeah.
Yeah,
well,
one oscillator.
That's all.
This is the world's simplest system,
an oscillating system in a heat bath.
Okay?
And what we find is the odd conclusion
that the energy stored in that oscillator
is independent of the spring constant and the mass.
Let's say especially the spring constant.
Let's take the mass to be fixed.
But now we just jack up the spring constant,
not 10 to the 500,
10 to the 10 to the 500.
All right?
For all practical purposes,
it must be that it's infinite,
and yet the formula takes that infinity
or that large number,
puts it here,
and still the derivative of
log z with respect to beta
is equal to the temperature.
Okay,
so there's something funny going on.
This occupied people around the turn of the 19th century.
They were very confused by it.
And the reason they were confused by it
is because the ideal gas law
and the energy per particle
seemed to work pretty well
where the particle was treated as a point particle.
But supposedly,
using that point particle,
that molecule was actually not a single point particle,
which molecules are not.
They might be a diatomic molecule.
Diatomic molecules can vibrate.
They're little oscillators.
They are little oscillators.
And so one might have expected that...
And of course,
they're rather stiff oscillators.
They are rather stiff.
They have a good solid spring constant.
So it's...
You have to give them
quite a bit of energy to...
Well,
you have to give them quite a knock,
I should say.
Quite a knock to start them vibrating.
But the formula seems to say
that for a diatomic molecule,
you ought to have not 3 halves kT,
but maybe 5 halves kT.
And so you have to give
them a little bit of energy
to account for an extra harmonic oscillator
that could start to vibrate.
Well,
it was known that that energy wasn't there.
So you could think of two conclusions.
One conclusion is that the diatomic molecule
is not really a diatomic molecule at all.
It's a point particle.
But that's ridiculous.
The other conclusion is that you're doing something wrong
or you're missing some ingredient to physics here,
which tends to keep that oscillator
from having this much energy.
You,
of course,
all know what the ingredient is,
right?
Good.
Then I won't tell you.
It is,
of course,
quantum mechanics.
Right.
So what we want to do
and to compare with this calculation
is the quantum mechanical calculation,
the corresponding quantum mechanical calculation
of,
again,
a quantum mechanical oscillator
in equilibrium.
How much do we have to know about quantum mechanics?
Very little.
We need the expression
for the energy of a harmonic oscillator.
And most of you,
I'm sure,
know
that harmonic oscillator energies are quantized.
They come in discrete multiples,
and the discrete multiples are discrete multiples
of plus or minus.
So the energy of an oscillator is
the Planck's constant times what?
Planck's constant times the frequency.
So the energy of an oscillator is
n units of energy
where each unit of energy costs h-bar omega.
The set of energy levels,
the set of states of a quantum harmonic oscillator
is just this discrete set of states,
all equally spaced.
And that's all that we have to know
about the quantum harmonic oscillator.
It's the only quantum mechanics we need to know
is that the energy of a single harmonic oscillator
comes in discrete integer multiples of h-bar omega.
Now we can calculate the
energy of a single harmonic oscillator.
Let's look at the partition function
for the quantum mechanical oscillator.
Remember what the answer is?
The answer is always z
is the sum of all states.
For the classical oscillator,
we replace that by an integral.
For the quantum mechanical oscillator,
it's truly a sum.
It's a sum over n
of e to the minus beta
times the energy of the nth state.
And the energy of the nth state
is n h-bar omega.
I'm keeping h-bar,
but throwing away the Boltzmann constant.
I refuse to keep track of both of them.
It's too much.
Okay,
so this is the formula for the partition function.
It looks like a complicated mess of exponentials.
How do you sum that up?
Oh boy,
it looks hard.
Not hard,
it's very easy.
e to the minus beta n h-bar omega,
is e to the minus beta h-bar omega,
to the nth power.
So this is a series.
The first term is just one.
That's when n is equal to zero.
So this is a series that has the form.
One plus a number,
let's call it x,
namely this number in here,
plus x squared,
plus x cubed,
plus dot dot dot.
And that's a geometric series.
That's a geometric series which
is very easy to sum up.
The answer is that this is equal to
one divided by one minus x.
That's the geometric series where x,
where this thing in here is just x.
So now we can sum it up.
We'll calculate the partition function at z
is equal to one divided by one minus,
e to the minus beta h-bar omega.
And that's it.
That's the whole calculation of the partition function.
It's fairly simple.
You can write it in a number of ways.
But I think this is probably
the best way to write it.
Just leave it in this form.
There's other ways to write it,
but this is fine.
What do we want to do?
We want to calculate the energy.
The energy is the derivative of log z.
But it's also equal,
in this case it's a little easier
just to take it to be one over z
times the derivative of z with respect to beta.
This is equal to the,
or minus this,
this is equal to minus the derivative of log z
with respect to beta.
Just using the property of logarithm.
That the derivative of logarithm
gives you a one over z.
In this case I think it's a little easier
just to calculate the nut bar taking the logarithm.
Okay,
so what is dz by d beta?
Well,
there's some ugly expression in the denominator.
When you differentiate the thing
with the thing in the denominator
you get the denominator squared.
So we get dz by d beta,
let's just work it out,
dz by d beta will contain a one divided by one
minus e to the minus beta h bar omega all squared.
That's just coming from differentiating a denominator.
One over x,
one over x squared.
Yeah,
minus.
Okay,
next we have to differentiate
the argument,
we have to differentiate what's in the denominator,
with respect to beta.
That's going to give us another minus sign from here
and another two minus signs,
I think the whole thing will
have one minus sign in it.
Yeah,
there will be one minus sign left over.
You get a minus sign from here
and you get another minus sign from here.
But basically it's just the derivative in the numerator here
of the exponential.
Well,
what's the derivative of the
exponential with respect to beta?
It's h bar omega times e
to the minus beta h bar omega,
right?
That's it.
Minus h bar omega.
Minus here.
Yeah.
Okay.
Now we have to divide by z.
That means multiply by one
minus e to the minus beta,
a blob.
Okay?
Multiply by that and that
gets rid of one factor here.
And what is that?
That's minus the energy.
We want plus the energy.
So let's put a minus sign here.
And by sheer luck,
we wound up with a positive quantity.
Okay.
This is the answer.
What is this compared with?
This is compared with one over beta.
So what's the relationship between them?
Well,
let's first go to high temperature.
Let's first ask what this is like at high temperature.
High temperature is a situation
where the classical theory is good.
Why is the classical theory good?
Well,
each one of these little quanta of
energy here are thought of as very small.
A classical spring has a great many units of energy.
So in that sense,
the classical system in quantum
units has a lot of energy.
That must mean that it has
very high temperature in some quantum sense.
Classical systems are...
Quantum systems become classical when
the temperature is very high.
Okay.
When the temperature is high,
they have a lot of energy.
And the quantization of energy becomes unimportant.
So let's go to high
temperature and see what we have.
This is...
where did I...
Ah,
here it is.
This is the energy.
Let's erase everything else and just call this the energy.
Okay.
High temperature means beta big.
No,
no,
sorry.
High temperature means beta very small.
Beta is one over the temperature.
So high temperature,
beta...
What did I say?
Beta small.
Beta small,
if we take the limit that beta gets very,
very near zero,
this is perfectly...
This is just approximately one.
And gets closer and closer to zero.
And closer to one as beta gets smaller and smaller.
So,
here's the answer.
H bar omega.
This factor here just goes to one.
We could do the same thing with this factor here,
but then we get in trouble.
One minus one,
bad thing to do.
So,
what we do is we expand this.
That's one minus...
And now,
e to the minus beta omega is one.
Plus,
I think,
beta h bar omega.
I'm using the expansion that e to the x is
one plus x plus x squared over two and so forth.
And only keeping track of the first term.
I have to keep track of the first...
Actually,
it's the second term.
The first term is...
The second term cancels out.
Okay?
So,
not good to just take the first approximation one.
The second term is to
approximate the exponential by just x,
which is minus beta h bar omega,
which just gives us beta
h bar omega in the denominator.
And the next terms after
that are proportional to beta squared,
beta cubed,
beta fourth,
and so on.
And so forth.
And they're much smaller than this.
They can be ignored when beta gets very small.
What do we get?
We get one over beta.
One over beta.
So,
you see,
in the high temperature situation,
it just reproduces the classical physics.
Okay?
But let's ask about the low temperatures.
What happens at low temperatures?
At low temperatures,
that means large beta.
Where's the energy?
All right.
Small beta...
Sorry.
Large...
Low temperatures.
Large beta.
Large beta,
this exponential is small.
E to the minus a large number is small.
So now we're going to low temperature,
large beta.
This is negligible.
If beta is 100 million or something,
very,
very low temperature,
then this is negligible.
We just get one in the denominator.
So the answer is h bar omega times
e to the minus beta h bar omega.
But again,
this exponential is extremely small.
So we see far from getting just the temperature,
we get something that's exponentially small
when the temperature goes to zero.
When the temperature goes to zero,
which means beta gets large,
this becomes enormously small
because it's exponentially small.
E to the minus beta,
where beta is large,
is very,
very small.
Okay?
So what do we find?
We find that quantum mechanics,
tends to suppress the energy of an oscillator
when the temperature is low enough.
Very low temperatures,
it doesn't behave like the classical oscillator at all.
It has much less energy than
the corresponding classical oscillator would have had.
The question is where is the crossover?
Where does it go from being quantum to classical?
And if you look at a formula like this,
you would know that the crossover is where
the exponential goes from being small to being large.
The biggest the exponential ever gets is one,
e to the minus,
but it goes where it goes.
And when does that happen?
That happens when beta h bar
omega is about equal to one.
The crossover between high temperature,
or between the high temperature
behavior and the low temperature behavior,
is when what's in the exponential here is about one.
For very low temperatures,
this quantity here is large.
For very high temperatures,
this quantity is small.
And it's this exponential which controls
whether the discreteness of the
energy levels is important or not.
So,
let's write where the crossover is.
The crossover happens,
when beta,
crossover means,
the transition from quantum behavior to classical behavior.
It happens when beta h bar
omega is about equal to one.
Now let's see,
which way does it go?
If beta h bar omega is bigger than one,
is that quantum or classical?
That's quantum because it's low temperature.
If beta h bar omega is bigger than one,
quantum.
Beta h bar omega,
less than one,
it starts to behave classically.
Let's just write one other equation.
Beta is one over the temperature,
and so that says,
h bar omega is equal to the temperature.
That's where it crosses over.
If you look at it,
it makes a lot of sense.
It says,
the crossover is when the
energy of the oscillator classically
is equal to one quantum's
worth of quantum mechanical energy.
If you try to make the temperature lower than that,
the oscillator has less than one quantum's worth of energy.
The temperature is so low that it
has less than one quantum's worth of energy.
It doesn't want to do that.
It doesn't want to have less
than one quantum's worth of energy.
And so,
the partition function or the expression
for the energy is almost zero,
exponentially small.
Here's the crossover point.
Or,
let's write it,
greater than temperature,
less than temperature.
Okay,
so now we actually know the answer
to the puzzle about the diatomic molecule.
When the temperature is too low,
that's when,
when the temperature is too low,
we're deep in the quantum regime.
And when you're in the quantum regime,
the oscillator has exponentially small energy
compared to what it would be classically.
On the other hand,
when the temperature goes up,
at some point,
the temperature will get larger than h bar omega.
At that point,
you begin to activate the oscillator.
You can't activate the quantum oscillator
unless the temperature is such
that it corresponds to more
than one quantum's worth of energy.
That's what this says.
So where are we?
At very low temp- at low temperatures,
up to some temperature,
the diatomic molecule behaves like a monatomic molecule.
You do not stop the vibrations going.
But at some temperature,
at some temperature,
if you raise the temperature enough,
so that the temperature becomes
bigger than the quantum of energy,
the diatomic molecule starts to
behave like a diatomic molecule.
Now,
that temperature's pretty high.
For a good stiff molecule,
oh,
this,
here's another point.
The stiffness determines omega.
The stiffness,
the stiffness of the oscillator,
what is it,
the square root of k over m?
The stiffer the oscillator,
the larger the frequency.
So the crossover point,
the stiffer the oscillator,
the higher the temperature of the crossover point.
Well,
you know,
molecules are pretty stiff on the scale of rubber bands.
And the temperature at which the monatomic molecule,
where the molecule goes from
looking like a monatomic molecule
to being a diatomic molecule,
is fairly high.
But what happens if you raise
the temperature even a little more?
Oh,
incidentally,
before,
often before this happens,
something else starts to happen.
The molecule starts to rotate,
other things start to happen.
This is just one example.
What happens if you heat it even more?
You activate even worse things.
The atoms themselves start to vibrate,
and eventually they'll get ionized.
So when they become ionized,
it doesn't behave like an atom at all.
It behaves like an electron and a proton.
So this is an example of quantum mechanics
solving a deep problem that physicists have been very,
very confused about.
In particular,
I'll tell you where this came up.
Solids are simply systems of molecules
where the molecules are arranged in a lattice.
They vibrate around the lattice centers.
So each atom is sort of a,
a kind of oscillator.
The energy of the oscillators,
as a function of the temperature,
the amount of energy as a function of the temperature,
determines the specific heat of the crystal.
The specific heat of a crystal
with a very,
very large number of oscillators,
or the heat capacity,
was estimated by classical physics
to be much,
much larger than the actual answer.
It was Einstein who basically figured out
that what was going on is
that the quantum statistical mechanics of oscillators
suppressed the,
suppressed the oscillators until
the temperature got high enough.
So this is another Einstein,
one of his minor,
one of his small minor,
contributions.
Did he get the Nobel Prize for it?
I thought he got the
Nobel Prize for the photoelectric effect.
I think so.
Okay,
but this is neither of them.
So when was this done?
When did he do this?
I mean,
when quantum mechanics had already come in?
Right,
but remember that
Einstein invented quantum mechanics in 1905,
so I'm not sure exactly,
somebody look it up,
specific heat of solids.
No.
It was early.
It was long before people
understood the foundations of quantum mechanics.
He just knew that the,
that the quantum energy levels
had to be proportional to frequency,
and to n.
So he wasn't opposed to all aspects of quantum mechanics?
No.
Question?
Yeah?
When we first derived the Boltzmann distribution,
we were,
it was based on discrete states and the position function
by summing that possible state.
And then when we looked at the gas,
we went from the sum to the integral,
and in that condition,
we're inherently assuming that the possible states for,
say,
the position of momentum are uniform.
Uniformly available.
Now,
is this a reasonable assumption?
Like,
from the results of what that was,
I don't think that,
I don't think that's considered a concept.
I think that,
I would think that for the momentum,
Yeah.
the way that some improvements of H bar,
so maybe that would be uniform based on that,
and the position might be,
your project to that momentum,
but is there any?
I,
I would say the ultimate
justification was the quantum mechanics,
the quantum derivation of the,
for example,
ideal gas.
But here's an example of what we're going to do,
of where the quantum derivation reproduces,
in the high temperatures,
the classical,
the classical answer.
So really the right logic,
the real serious logic,
is to start with quantum mechanics,
and show that the quantum mechanical counting of states
corresponds to the integral over phase space.
And that's true.
I'll just give you an example here.
Do the calculation as classical
physicists would ordinarily do it.
Here it is.
So,
So you've got this,
and we got,
what do we get?
Let's go back,
actually,
to the partition function itself.
Yeah,
let's just look at the partition function itself,
not even take the energy,
let's just see how close we get.
Okay,
this partition function at high temperatures,
means that,
small beta is 1 divided by
1 minus beta H bar omega,
right?
H bar is a constant,
incidentally so is omega,
but H bar is a numerical
constant that sits in front of all partition functions.
Let's not
worry about it.
1 over beta omega.
Now what was the partition function that we
said for the classical case?
Here it is.
1 over beta omega.
The 2 pi is again a
constant,
not particularly interesting,
but its dependence on beta and omega is
1 over beta omega here,
1 over beta omega here.
The quantum mechanics only comes in
in this multiplicative constant 1 over H bar,
which doesn't matter when you
differentiate it.
So here's an example of the derivation of the
classical statistical mechanics from the quantum mechanics,
and that's really the
right way to go.
But let me tell you,
this formula was known long before quantum
mechanics,
so they were doing something right.
They intuited that phase space was
the right space.
x is the right space.
xp space,
momentum position space,
was the right way to think about classical
systems.
OK.
Yeah?
Einstein figured that out in 1907.
1907,
yeah.
I figured it was very early.
Right.
This is a naive question,
but does that mean that
if you heat up a harmonic
oscillator,
it's going to go faster,
or the spring's going to tighten up,
or what's going to
Well.
Excuse me.
Classically or quantum mechanically?
Classically,
when you're at already a
high temperature high enough classical approximation,
when we heat it up further,
does that mean the energy .
Well,
the energy stays equal to the temperature.
Once it's above the quantum
threshold,
the energy is just equal to the temperature,
and it does not matter at all.
what the spring constant is.
It speeds up and makes larger oscillations
when you apply temperature.
The point is
that as you heat it from low temperature
to high temperature,
it's
the paradox
of saying that the oscillator always has that energy
independently of how stiff it is.
What's true
is the place where it begins to have that energy,
in other words
the temperature at which the classical behavior sets in
gets to be a higher and higher
temperature as a function of the spring constant.
So if you took a very,
you know,
this 10 to the
10 to the 10 to the 10th spring constant,
yes,
at sufficiently high temperature,
it would have an energy equal
to its temperature.
But at any kind of ordinary
temperature,
it would essentially have no sort of threshold for it
to start behaving classically.
It would get higher and higher
and higher as the spring constant
got stiffer and stiffer.
Now that's kind of interesting because what it means
is that as you heat a system,
you start to
discover that it has more and more degrees of freedom.
Let's
make a crazy molecule now.
A crazy molecule consists of a
spring with two atoms connected to it,
and then each one of these
atoms,
and a very stiff spring at that,
and then connected,
this atom over here
turns out to be two particles
with a really stiff spring,
a much,
much stiffer
spring.
Alright,
so how does it look at low temperatures?
At low temperatures,
there's not enough temperature
to overcome the quantum threshold
for this oscillator to start
oscillating.
So it behaves like a point.
Behaves with 3 halves
kT.
You heat it up to the point where
this oscillator here,
the frequency of this oscillator is such
that the temperature is such that you activate
the oscillations,
but still not enough
temperature to activate this super duper strong spring here.
It behaves like a diatomic molecule.
You heat it more,
it
starts to behave as if it had 3 molecules
connected by springs.
Instead of
5 halves kT,
I don't know,
maybe 7 halves kT,
whatever the right number is.
So,
the lesson is,
as you heat the system,
more and more degrees of freedom become activated,
and you
start to discover the complexity of things.
You don't discover
the complexity of things at low temperature.
You
discover the quantum behavior of things.
As you heat it,
you start to discover complexity,
and you start to discover
degree of freedom by degree of freedom.
They unfreeze themselves
from the quantum constraint and start behaving classically.
Now,
some of you may realize this has
to do a lot with black body
radiation,
but we'll come to that.
Well,
let me,
to relate it,
I won't relate it right now to black body radiation,
but let's relate it to something else.
A violin string.
Take a violin string.
A violin string consists mathematically of
a large number of oscillators.
The oscillators
are the violin string,
or the guitar string,
oscillating in its lowest harmonic.
Plus,
on top of that,
you can superpose
the first harmonic,
second harmonic,
or I think I just
put,
I don't know,
however many harmonics.
And fundamentally,
the mathematics of it is that a string,
a vibrating string,
is basically an infinite
number of harmonic oscillators.
The infinite number become the
shorter and shorter wavelengths.
If each one of these oscillators
had
energy equal to the temperature,
and there are an infinite
number of them,
that string would have an infinite
amount of energy when it was
when it came to thermal equilibrium.
Something's wrong.
Now the answer is that most of these oscillations
have very high frequency.
The shorter the wavelength,
the higher the frequency of the
oscillator.
And therefore,
most of these oscillators at any given
temperature are frozen out by quantum mechanics.
Not free to oscillate.
As the temperature goes up and
up,
more of these oscillations begin to oscillate,
begin to
have energy.
But,
so that's another
similar paradox.
Question?
Yeah.
I was just wondering about the relative
sizes of these numbers,
whether this transition can be observed
experimentally,
somewhere,
somehow?
Absolutely.
Is that a sun or something?
Just studying the specific heat of crystals.
It's very obvious.
In fact,
I mean,
it was obvious to the experimental physicists around
1900 that there was something wrong,
because their crystals
did not behave according to classical mechanics.
So yes,
it's extremely,
extremely easy to
see this.
And if you heat the crystal,
can you make it
behave the other way?
Yep.
As you heat the crystal,
the specific heat starts to behave
as if there was a certain number of kT,
a certain number of,
you know,
T per
oscillator.
Yeah.
This is really easy to see.
So,
for the flat end strain,
if we wanted to calculate the
partition function,
we would take the sum we had,
what we have
left here,
and just do it for multiple oscillators?
Right.
The partition function would be
the product of all the partition
functions.
The logarithm would be the sum.
Absolutely.
Yes.
Right.
The logarithm
being the sum would mean that the
energy is the sum of all the oscillators.
Right.
But those whose,
those whose,
where's our
transition point?
Those whose
frequency is too high,
above the temperature,
Those are in the quantum regime,
and they're not appreciably excited.
Okay.
That was fun.
It is.
You ignore the zero point
one half h-bar.
Yeah,
okay,
good,
good.
Good.
The reason that doesn't matter,
you're right,
we did ignore it,
it makes
it multiplicative.
Adding a constant to the energy,
adding a constant to
every energy level,
is equivalent to multiplying the partition
function by a constant,
and the result
is no change in anything of interest.
Alright.
Um,
so we
start to talk about the second law.
Why is the second law a puzzle?
The second law is a puzzle
because it,
it says
that the world is irreversible,
and that something
called entropy always increases.
Or
it stays the same.
And in fact,
you'd have to be infinitely
careful with a big system
to keep it from increasing and
make it be the same.
On the other hand,
Newton's
equations of motion are completely reversible,
so anything that can happen in one
direction can happen in the opposite direction.
So there's a tension there.
There's a tension between reversibility on the
one hand of the fundamental equations,
and
irreversibility of the observational
properties of,
um,
of complicated systems.
Um,
and
that took some time to sort out,
and people are still
confused about it.
So,
let's talk about it.
嗯
Let's imagine some phase space.
The phase space is the space
of states of some classical system,
and it's got a lot
of dimensions.
It's got a lot of particles or a
lot of whatever it is that it has,
but we're going to just
draw it.
We're going to represent it simply as two-dimensional.
One dimension will be the coordinates,
and the other direction will be the momenta.
And as I said,
there are a lot of them.
This is a high-dimensional space.
We start out with some probability distribution.
Let's say,
for example,
let's start out with a
probability distribution which looks like
that.
Meaning to say,
there's 0.5.
There's no probability on the outside.
Constant probability on the inside of this blob.
What it means to say is we know nothing
except that the system starts out inside that blob.
We don't know anything more about it,
so the probability density is constant within that
blob.
What is the entropy of that system?
Anybody remember?
Max.
At the maximum.
No,
no,
no.
It's not all in maximum.
The maximum would be if the probability
distribution was uniformly spread over the phase space.
In other words,
if you knew nothing.
The entropy is the logarithm
of the volume of the blob.
Now that's...
Yeah?
Are you talking about a
system that's constrained to that blob?
It's not constrained.
We just happen to know that it's in that blob.
We did our best possible measurements.
And we discovered that the system is in that blob.
Whatever measurements it took.
So it may not be in equilibrium?
Oh,
no.
It's not in...
No,
no,
no.
It's not in equilibrium.
No.
And so we're not talking about the entropy of equilibrium.
We're talking about the entropy
of a certain probability distribution.
And the probability distribution is handed to us.
Somebody tells you,
somebody upstairs tells you the momenta
of 10 to the 23rd particles,
and the positions of 10 to the
23rd particles are all within this blob.
For example,
I mean,
you know,
this is not that unrealistic.
You might start with all
the air molecules in some tank,
you know,
a tank,
an air tank.
And they're up in the corner of the room.
And then you open up the air
tank and the air tank goes out.
Well,
originally,
the molecules were in that corner,
in that tank.
So they were confined in a small space.
And moreover,
you had a pretty good idea of
what their energy was because you knew the
temperature of what's in there.
So you had a pretty good idea of
what the momenta of all the particles were.
That might not quite correspond to
a uniform probability distribution in a blob,
but it
would certainly correspond to some blob-like configuration.
The more you know,
it corresponds to the smaller the volume of this region.
Oh,
did I say the entropy
was the logarithm of the volume?
Minus the logarithm of the volume.
As the volume gets smaller and smaller...
No.
Yeah.
As the volume gets smaller and smaller,
the entropy goes down.
Which way is that?
That's...
Yeah.
Okay.
It's minus the volume.
All right.
But in any case,
in any case,
there's an entropy,
which is a little bit more than
the entropy,
which has to do with the size
of this blob in the phase space.
All right.
Now,
what happens to the blob as time goes on?
Do you remember a theorem called Leoville's theorem?
Leoville's theorem says what?
Volume stays the same.
Therefore,
the entropy stays the same.
This is just another way of
saying that if you follow the states,
each state goes into
a unique state.
It has its analog in the discreet little
games we played in classical mechanics of coins
or whatever,
where we talked about how states evolve one
to the next to the next to the
next.
Any given state goes to a
unique state in the next instant,
another unique state in
the next instant.
And so if you have some probability distribution,
the probability distribution just translates
if there are six states.
A die.
If there are six states and you know
that one of two of them is occupied,
in other words,
that the die is in one of two states,
and you also know the rule for going from one
state to the next state,
after the next step,
you'll also know that it's in one of two states.
Not the same two states,
but you also know that
it's in one of two states.
So the entropy,
in that sense,
stays the same.
The probability distribution may change.
It may change because the
states which are occupied become different,
but the fact that
there are two of them
and that they have equal probability,
that stays the same.
So,
on the one hand,
that seems to say that entropy doesn't change.
And this is true.
This is a correct view of
what is called microscopic entropy or...
I don't know what it's called.
It's called microentropy.
But there's another concept of entropy which does increase.
And the other concept of entropy
has to do with something called coarse-graining.
Typically,
your experiments are such that you
cannot resolve points in the phase space.
You don't have...
Even if your experiments were ideal,
perfectly precise experiments,
you still could not tell
one state from another state if it was too close.
There's some resolution.
Some resolution of states.
Now,
in quantum mechanics,
it turns out that that resolution is naturally built in.
The smallest uncertainty is given by Planck's constant.
But in other situations,
it may just be that your
resolving powers are not good enough.
So instead of talking about points of phase space,
you talk about resolved or...
What should we call them?
Coarse-grained points in phase space.
Now,
let's make an example.
Supposing we started with this blob in
phase space and it has a certain volume.
Let's follow it.
And I'm going to tell you what it does,
not because I've solved any mathematics problem,
but I'm just going to make
up a dynamics which preserves the volume,
preserves the area on the plane here,
but takes this phase volume here and turns
it into a long snake which looks like this.
It's the same total volume.
The snake is extremely thin.
And it looks like that.
But unfortunately,
because of our limited resolution powers,
we cannot tell a phase
point from a neighboring phase point.
So what we do when this happens is
we take these phase points and we blobify them.
We think of them instead of
as being points in the phase space,
blobs.
And now we start going through it.
And guess what?
The blobs cover...
Are these overlapping or are they...
They're overlapping,
whatever,
yep,
they're overlapping.
Doesn't it violate Liouville?
No,
it doesn't violate Liouville.
We're just losing information because we
can't keep track of this volume.
So we're going to do this fine structure.
The actual true dynamics is such that the snake here
has exactly the same volume as the blob over here.
But because we have fuzzy resolution,
we're looking at these
things with somebody else's eyeglasses.
What do we see?
We see a blob.
And if we were to be asked,
what is the volume of this blob?
In other words,
where...
Where is the point in
phase space where this thing exists?
We'll come to the conclusion
that it's uniformly distributed over here
because we couldn't follow the system carefully enough.
If we could follow it with infinite precision,
if we could follow it with infinite precision
and define the probability density of the blob,
by defining it with infinite precision,
the volume would not change.
But in every real situation,
in every real situation,
we can't distinguish one state from a nearby state.
So we do this process of coarse graining.
Coarse graining is replacing points of
phase space by blobs of phase space.
Once we do that,
guess what?
The volume increases.
I always imagine a big,
you know,
piece of cotton.
What is the volume of
a piece of cotton this big?
Well,
if you mean the volume of
the cotton fibers all added up,
you can squeeze them down to something small.
If you let that cotton fiber go,
the volume of the cotton fibers doesn't change very much,
incidentally.
They're pretty rigid.
They don't...
But the cotton sort of grows out,
and now you look at it,
and it has this big a volume.
If you look at it through somebody else's graph,
through the glasses,
and you can't see the cotton fibers,
you will say that the volume of
that piece of fiber stuff has increased.
And that's what happens.
That is what happens.
So,
yeah?
Are you saying then that
classically entropy only appears to increase,
but quantum mechanically it does,
because of the limit of the fiber?
Is there any limit of resolution in any of these?
Let's forget the quantum mechanics.
Just limits of resolution.
Yes,
limits of resolution.
No,
remember that entropy is not
really a property of a system.
It's a property of the system
and what you know about the system.
So,
if you could follow in infinite
detail every point in the phase space,
all you knew in the beginning
was that it was inside some here,
but not exactly where.
Then you would say afterwards
it's inside the snake somewhere,
but you don't know exactly where it's in the snake.
Then entropy would be conserved.
But if you take into account that
you can't tell one point from another
because of limits of resolution,
then you wind up saying,
look,
I know much less about where it
is than I did to begin with.
Right.
So classically you can imagine
that you might be able to,
entropy would remain the same because
you can imagine that you could.
Yeah.
Yes,
that's right.
But the problem is given any resolution,
given any degree of resolution,
whatever your resolution is,
let's suppose it was good enough
to resolve the snake after 10 seconds.
So it's good enough to resolve the snake.
But then the way systems evolve in physics,
in the phase space,
is they start to grow even littler snakes.
And littler snakes and littler snakes.
Whatever your degree of resolution,
this snakiness,
we'll give it its right name,
chaos is what its name is.
The way systems evolve in phase space
is they start to spread
and they start to spread out tentacles
and they start to spread out tentacles.
So,
without changing the volume,
they grow fibers,
and the fibers grow smaller fibers,
and the smaller fibers grow smaller fibers.
And eventually,
no matter how good your resolution is,
you'll eventually start seeing that the entropy increases.
And that's the second law.
That's what the second law says.
Now,
let's imagine some phase space.
We started out knowing a great deal.
Let's talk about how big the available
region of phase space is for a minute.
Let's think of it as a gas of
a large number of particles in a box.
If it's in a box,
that means the X's are bounded.
So,
in a one-dimensional analog,
it would say that the phase
space is bounded between here and here.
There's the phase space.
Can the momentum be anything?
No,
usually the energy constrains how
much the maximum momentum can be.
So,
even if all of the energy of the system
went into one particle,
that one particle would still itself have a finite energy.
And so,
the effective region of phase
space which is available to you
is some big box.
Maybe it's not a box.
It's got some shape.
But it's finite.
It's finite.
It doesn't extend to infinity in any direction.
Okay,
now the phase point starts someplace.
The exact precise phase point.
What tends to happen
is the subsequent motion
is extremely sensitive to where you started with.
So,
if you started over here,
the system would evolve for a time.
If you started very close to it,
the system would evolve in a very similar way
for a while,
but then it would start to depart.
It would go off in some different directions.
An example would be billiard balls,
an idealized billiard table with no friction.
How many people play billiards here?
Okay.
Pocket pool?
Chicago?
No.
Straight pool?
What do you play?
Okay.
Three cushion is too hard.
Too much chaos.
Yeah.
So,
you know that if you arrange
the balls in a certain fashion,
and start with a cue ball,
and you are extremely accurate,
you start with the cue
of the balls exactly the same
on two different occasions.
If they're exactly the same,
and you shoot exactly the same,
exactly the same things will happen.
Now,
what if you're a tiny,
tiny,
tiny bit off
in your aim,
everything else being kept perfectly fixed?
Well,
if you're really just off by a truly,
truly tiny amount,
the difference in the trajectory will be,
the whole system will be small for a while,
but sooner or later,
it's going to start exponentially,
errors compound,
and sooner or later,
that trajectory,
that nearby trajectory is going to deviate.
That's the character of what is called chaotic systems,
and most systems in nature are chaotic.
And so that means that no
matter how close you start together,
you'll eventually depart and fill up a lot of faces,
jakğimizmesiέ
bands
regions of phase space beginning to depart from
each other because errors compound and then two
points over here which are close
together nevertheless eventually will depart from each
other and the phase space gets very
the phase space volume gets extremely complicated and
eventually if you wait long enough
till the system gets to thermal equilibrium
this cottony stuff basically fills up the whole
phase space fills it up as as cotton
would fill up the volume the actual volume
of these fibers stays equal to whatever the
initial volume of the face of the the phase blob
was but it spreads out in a way that if
you do any coarse graining of it at
all it basically fills the thing with uniform probability
you
all right so now we watch a particular
phase point a particular phase point start here
that means we start with a particular configuration of
the of the cue ball and one two three through
fifteen we stack them up and we let it
run it starts to go somewhere and then it goes
somewhere else then it goes somewhere else
and then it goes somewhere else and eventually
if there's no friction on that
billiard table eventually you'll sample something
close to every possible configuration if you
wait long enough you will see every possible
configuration in the phase space visited
not exactly but very close you'll pass
to just about every point in the
phase space very very close to it when
And so what will happen is on the one hand
if you know something in the beginning like for example
You might know
That the initial phase point is something very special
It's down here in the corner all
the molecules in the corner of the room
With a certain definite velocity going off in some direction
Alright,
they start to bump into each other the phase point begins
to separate and the phase points begin to separate and eventually
It fills up the whole thing here
And so
So I don't know anything anymore
It's reached its maximum entropy.
There can't be any more entropy
than saying I don't know anything
But
Nevertheless in a completely unpredictable and
random way that you can't foresee
Because you don't have enough detail
this phase
point will eventually
Come back to this point here
In other words in the cue ball
Billiard ball analogy
You start your cue you start your rack racked
up in a certain very very special the triangle
The cue ball down,
you know definite the shoot
And you're very precise,
but after a certain amount of time
they begin to go off in funny directions.
They begin to fill the
They begin to fill not
that they fill the pool table,
but they fill the space of possibilities
But if you wait long
enough if you wait long enough
We can talk about how long it takes those
balls will come back and and form the triangle again
How long
Well,
it's not infinite.
It's not infinite.
It does depend on
how precise
you require
To reproduce the the original configuration if you
allow even a very small tolerance and you say
This is the original configuration
X to within a certain tolerance
Then depending on that tolerance it will take a finite time
for the phase point to come back to that original configuration
If you require infinite precision
it will never come back.
But if you require precision to within some epsilon,
then the time that it takes to pass
back through that phase point to within tolerance epsilon
is finite.
Yeah?
In the case of a billiard table,
right,
you actually are imparting energy by hitting the cue ball,
right?
Mm-hmm.
Well,
no,
that's the starting point with the energy.
Oh,
okay.
So the starting point is
already the cue ball hitting it.
So the system will replicate with
the cue ball coming at it,
then?
Right.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
So,
on the one hand,
the entropy increases.
It increases in this cross-grain
sense because you lose track.
On the other hand,
that does not say that you
can't return to the original configuration.
You can try to estimate how long it'll take.
And
maybe we'll do that next time.
We'll make it.
We'll make an estimate of how long it
takes for a system of many degrees of freedom.
Let's say the air will try out this problem.
Take the air in the room,
put it all up in the corner with its energy.
It has its energy.
It has its kinetic energy.
All the molecules are going in the same direction.
Very,
very special state.
They shoot off to the other wall.
They bounce off the walls.
They start hitting each other.
They go crazy and they begin...
The system is running.
It's very chaotic.
And after a while,
they fill the room in
a normal pattern of thermal equilibrium.
And we sit and we wait
and we wait and we wait.
How long does it take?
We can be certain.
We can be certain that
if the room lasts long enough,
and it's a really truly closed system,
how long...
Well,
there doesn't have to be a closed system.
We just don't want to leak molecules out.
But it's kept at constant temperature.
How long will it take on the
average before all the molecules will be up?
In the corner again.
Or in that corner.
And that question can be answered.
The answer is a long time.
Don't you lose information if,
in this case...
It's not a reversible system,
right?
It is.
Because after some time it goes back into the corner?
Completely reversible.
Anything that can happen,
the opposite can happen.
But...
No.
Alright,
we'll talk about it more.
We'll talk about the second law more.
We'll talk about reversibility.
And how this paradox gets resolved.
How this paradox of
reversibility and irreversibility gets resolved.
And,
you know,
it was one of the great classic...
paradoxes of physics.
That puzzled a lot of people.
As you undoubtedly know,
in the history of physics,
it drove Boltzmann to distraction.
I don't know if it drove him to suicide,
but it certainly depressed him.
And eventually he came up with the right answer.
The right answer being that,
not that entropy always increases,
but given any configuration,
it's most probable that the
next configuration will have more entropy.
Entropy probably increases.
And the probability of the configuration
aiming itself back into some unusual configuration,
unexpected,
that's always small.
Well,
I'll give you some more examples.
I'll try to make this
a little more intuitive next time.
But we do owe the second
law at least some kind of explanation.
Yeah?
You said earlier most systems in nature are chaotic.
It sounds like an empirical fact.
Or is there a principle behind that?
Well...
There's an infinite number of chaotic systems,
and there's an infinite number of non-chaotic systems.
And now we have to start talking about measures on...
Measures on what?
Measures on Hamiltonians and things.
It's a good question.
I'm sure that the mathematical people could probably answer,
what is the right measure of
the chaotic systems versus the non-chaotic systems?
But...
That's a good question.
I mean,
not all systems are chaotic.
That's for sure.
And in many cases,
you can perturb them a little bit.
You can change them a little bit,
and they will still remain non-chaotic.
It's not the sort of situation
where if you have a chaotic system
and you change the rules,
meaning the Hamiltonian,
a tiny,
tiny bit,
it will become chaotic.
No,
there's usually some...
Oh,
chaotic.
What does chaotic mean?
Chaotic means that the phase
trajectories tend to separate like this
after a long enough time that...
I didn't want to define it
with any infinite precision right now,
but it is this phenomenon
of close-by points in phase space
following each other for a
while and then exponentially departing
so that the system becomes a phase.
It's effectively unpredictable.
It's a situation in
which predictability effectively breaks down
because in order to predict a
system for a length of time t,
your precision with the initial conditions
and your precision and knowledge
of the evolution of the system
has to get better and better and better
as the time over which
you want predictability to be predictability.
So you take the weather.
Just define it as a collection of molecules
doing whatever they're doing instantaneously.
And you ask,
how long can I predict the weather?
How long can you predict
the weather depends on how precisely
you know the initial conditions.
And if you want to
predict it for a long time,
for a longer period of time,
you have to have more precise initial data.
Even longer,
more precise.
Now that's quite different than the harmonic oscillator.
The harmonic oscillator in phase space
just moves around in a circle with constant frequency.
If you start a phase point over here,
it travels around over here.
Start a phase point over here,
they just go together.
And they go together forever and ever.
Close by phase points never get far from each other.
That's a very non-chaotic system.
A particle in an orbit around the sun
in a true inverse square law
where we do exact Newtonian physics
is not chaotic.
The two close by trajectories,
two close by orbits
will remain close by
basically forever.
The three body problem is chaotic in general.
That neighboring orbits
eventually tend to depart from each other.
So that means predictability
is a function of how accurately
you know the initial conditions.
To predict for a length of time t,
you must know the initial conditions
to within epsilon of t.
As t gets longer,
you need to know the initial conditions better.
That's what it means to be chaotic.
Not also the laws of motion,
you need to know also with a very high precision?
Yes,
you also need to know the laws of motion
with a very high precision.
Both the laws and the initial conditions.
What's the kind of moment
between the two bodies
that are in another direction?
One is chaotic and one is not.
It's mathematical problem.
It's a matter of property.
You've seen chaotic pendulums.
The double pendulum is chaotic.
You know,
double pendulum is...
The ordinary pendulum is not chaotic.
It's very,
very predictable.
Now you add a second pendulum like that
that swings around this one.
And you start it going.
Have you ever seen the double pendulum in action?
It's quite fascinating.
You can follow it a little bit,
but then after a little bit of time
it does something really weird.
All the energy will go into one of the modes.
Very chaotic things happen.
Why is it a model though,
mathematically?
Why is it a model?
Because the phase space spreads.
You know,
you're asking...
You're asking a very hard question.
Why some systems are chaotic
and other systems aren't chaotic.
I would say the state of the art
is almost...
It's very,
very hard
to look at a Hamiltonian
and know whether it's chaotic or not.
Except for the fact
that if it's complicated
it's usually chaotic.
But that's a...
You know,
there are complicated ones
which are not chaotic.
So this is not an easy question.
And it's something that mathematicians
and mathematical physicists study.
And they don't have answers
that are very general.
You mean even a theoretical double pendulum
is chaotic with no friction?
With no friction.
Right.
The precision with which you know
the initial conditions,
the relationship between that
and the precision,
you can predict the ultimate conditions.
That relationship blows up.
If you don't have...
No.
So precision gets so bad in the future
you don't have a clue where it's going to be.
Right.
But if you really did know
the initial conditions
to infinite precision,
perfect.
If you know the initial conditions
to infinite precision,
whatever that means,
you could predict for infinite time.
Right.
Now,
I think that's probably
a meaningless statement.
But the right statement is
some connection between
given the time that you want to predict
and how precise you have to know
the initial conditions.
Yeah,
that's what I was trying to say.
Yeah.
So that has to do with how fast
these trajectories depart from each other.
If the trajectories tend to stay close
to each other for a long period of time,
the system is rather predictable
for a long period of time,
but eventually they will separate.
So...
And...
Right.
So most systems are unpredictable
in that sense.
But you're right.
I mean,
given...
Another way to say it is
given any length of...
Yeah,
given any length of time
that you want to predict,
there exists a tolerance
or a precision,
an epsilon
that would allow you,
if you knew the phase point
within that precision epsilon,
would allow you to predict
for that length of time.
So,
you know,
it's given T,
there exists an epsilon,
such that,
and so forth.
It's usually called the Yapanov...
Yeah,
the Yapanov co-exponents,
right.
That's exactly what they are,
Yapanov.
What's the term?
L-Y-A-P-A-N-O-V.
A-P-O-N-A-V?
No,
A-N-O-V?
Yapanov.
Lapanov.
L-Y-A-P-A-N-O-V.
L-Y...
A-N-O-V.
L-Y-A-P-A-N-O-V.
Is it the same as saying,
for example...
That tells you how far...
The Yapanov coefficient
is the exponential growth
of the separation
between trajectories.
Is it the same as saying,
for example,
with the delt pendulum,
that it doesn't have
a closed solution?
That you can't...
Right,
the equation is
the position and speed...
Oh,
sorry,
to you.
Oh,
Yapanov.
Yapanov,
yeah.
Chaotic systems certainly
don't have closed solutions
as a rule.
The thing with the delt
pendulum is,
at some point,
the second pendulum starts,
will be on a path
going to the right,
straight up,
ending up here.
And then,
depending on
exactly where it is,
it'll go here or here.
And now we run
completely different
trajectories.
It's unstable.
Yes.
The orbits are unstable.
Well,
the simplest
kind of instability
is just the top of a hill,
as you were saying.
So,
what's the difference
between the two?
If you go over here,
you go this way.
you go that way.
All right.
But that's just one point
of instability
at the very top of the hill.
If you start anywhere else,
nearby,
let's say with zero velocity,
the phase trajectories
don't separate that much
and that quickly.
At the top of the hill here
is a point of instability.
In these chaotic systems,
basically every point
is a point of instability.
Every point in the phase space
is unstable like that.
You...
Yeah.
All right.
Okay.
For more,
please visit us
at stanford.edu.