Stanford University.
You all know about boiling water,
water to steam.
And it has been understood qualitatively for
more than 100 years,
VanderWals.
When was VanderWals?
VanderWals must have been at
the end of the 19th century.
Somebody look up VanderWals.
Mike Hewitt is usually the
one to go to for that.
Okay,
it doesn't matter.
It's been understood qualitatively from
both mining and statistical mechanics
for well over a century,
I think.
And we like to work with it a little bit.
I'm going to show you how
the liquid gas phase transition works,
not in the standard way that VanderWals approached it.
The way that VanderWals approached it is very elegant,
very nice,
and
is equivalent to what I'm going to show you.
What I'm going to show you is
based on a system that we've already studied,
magnets,
so the Ising magnet.
What I'm going to show you
is in what way the Ising magnet
is a model for the liquid gas phase transition.
But before we do,
let me just remind you
what we learned last time by
studying the mean field approximation to the,
not the liquid gas,
but
to the Ising model.
We also know that it doesn't
work very well in one dimension.
In fact,
it gives the wrong answer in one dimension.
Mean field approximation.
Mean field approximation always tells
you that it's a phase transition,
and this happens not to be true in one dimension.
But it is true in two dimensions and higher,
and by the time you get to three dimensions,
every particle in a lattice has enough nearest neighbors,
basically six of them,
that the mean field approximation becomes very good.
Not accurate in the sense of 1%,
but probably accurate in the sense of 1%.
And so mean field approximation is a good
way to qualitatively understand how phase transitions take place.
Now,
it has to do with these little magnets,
which can either be up or down.
They were described by placing at each point
on a lattice a variable that we call sigma.
And sigma could even be one.
In which case,
it's a point.
we thought of it as pointing up or minus 1.
In which case,
we thought of it as pointing down.
And we talked about several,
well,
at least two different kinds of models for magnets.
The Ising model was the more difficult of the models.
It said there's an energy not for every particle,
every site,
not for every site,
but for every pair of neighboring sites.
That the energy was stored
in the relationship between neighboring sites.
And in particular,
energy was lower if the sites
are parallel and higher if they're anti-parallel.
You can think of the energy as being located
in some sense in the links between the sites.
If two neighbors are parallel,
we'll call that an unbroken bond.
If they're parallel,
then the energy is low.
If they're anti-parallel,
we'll call that a broken bond.
If the bond is broken,
then the energy is higher.
And so we wrote an expression to represent that.
And the representation was that the energy is the sum.
Not over the energy.
over the sides of the lattice,
but the bonds,
the links.
They're usually called links.
Links of the product of sigma
at one end of the link,
let's call it sigma i and sigma j.
Let's not try to make a fancy notation.
i and j just mean the
two opposite ends of a link.
We put in here a minus sign,
w y in a minute,
and a constant j.
The constant j is just associated with how tightly bound,
how tightly,
how hard it is to break a bond.
How much energy does it cost to break a bond?
Well,
if we start with two spins,
two sigmas aligned,
then sigma dot sigma is plus one.
If they're anti-aligned,
it's minus one.
So the difference,
in this expression here,
is two units.
Not one unit,
but two units to go
from minus one to plus one.
And so that means every broken bond
costs you an energy plus j,
two j.
Two j.
Every broken bond costs an energy.
That's how much energy it takes to flip it.
Okay,
that was the first thing we introduced.
And the second thing was
another possible term in the energy
that would correspond to a uniform magnetic field,
which is just a term
which acts not on the neighbor,
not on the links,
but acts on the individual sites.
It's an extra energy if
a site is up or down.
It doesn't depend on what its neighbors are doing.
And so let's put that in there
as something proportional to a magnetic field.
That just means a number here.
I think I probably called it capital H last time.
I'm going to use standard notation,
and I'm going to use a notation
that's in the statistical mechanics notes.
I'm going to call it little h.
You called it B last time.
I called it B,
you're right.
You're right,
I called it B.
But I'm not going to now because...
I'm going to call it H.
Because in the notes,
it's called H.
But H looks a lot like B.
It just looks like a badly drawn slide.
So that's not the labor of the difference.
Yeah,
okay,
so let's see.
If H is positive,
then this term is lower
if sigma is negative.
So if this was all there was,
which was incidentally,
the first model that we studied,
only H,
then this would favor spin,
spin.
This would favor sigma being negative or being down.
That would lower the energy,
lower the energy by this being
a down configuration,
in other words,
the minus one.
But of course,
thermal fluctuations would cause it
to fluctuate up sometimes,
and at very,
very high energy,
it would be at a very,
very low energy.
At very high temperature,
it would be up as much as down.
And so there's a pattern according to energy.
So this term here tends
to want to make things lie
in the same direction,
and this one wants
to make them lie down.
Since you're summing over length,
shouldn't there be a H sigma J as well?
No,
that coefficient is called J.
Here,
this one?
No,
no,
no.
You're summing over length.
Yeah.
So shouldn't there be an H sigma J as well?
Okay,
so I assume that was science.
An H sigma J.
Sorry.
I'm missing your point.
Yes,
sir.
If you're summing over the legs.
Here,
we're summing over length.
Right,
and there you're summing over.
Here,
we're summing over science.
Okay.
All right,
sure.
Quick question,
please.
It seems that the larger J,
when sigma is one,
I mean the product,
it's the lower energy.
When they're parallel,
Not only when they're parallel,
but also when J is large.
Yes,
J will.
So.
Yes,
but J is not variable in the problem.
J is just a number.
I understand.
Right.
But it's a number that
varies from one substance to another.
Yes,
yes.
It's a number that varies.
So.
So does that mean that it is harder
to break a bond when the energy is lower?
Is there a physical meaning to that?
Do you mean when J is lower?
When J is bigger,
it's a lower energy.
And at the same time,
when J is bigger,
it's harder to break.
Both are consequence of larger J.
I don't think the zero energy matters.
It's the energy difference between
the broken and the unbroken.
unbroken bond,
we are perfectly free to
add any constant that we want.
And in fact,
the
material may tell us what constant to add.
For example,
there's energy stored in mass,
you know,
little e equals mc squared.
A lump of uranium would have a bigger number here
than a lump of frozen hydrogen.
So,
but the point is this is just a numerical constant
that added a constant to the energy,
that doesn't matter.
ありがとうございました
And also,
the ground state energy here,
how much energy you have,
let's calculate how much energy you have.
Let's forget this for the moment.
Ask how much energy you have
if all the spins are aligned.
That's the lowest possible energy.
If they're all aligned,
then it's just the number of links times minus j.
Minus j times the number of links.
Incidentally,
how many links are there in a,
let's take a three-dimensional lattice.
If the number of sites is n,
how many links are there?
Anybody know?
Six links.
Six n?
Six n.
How many people say six?
How many people say three?
Three is n.
I'll show you why for two,
because I can't draw three so well.
Is that assuming it's infinite?
Yeah,
yeah,
assuming it's infinite.
Assuming it's infinite.
I mean,
if it were infinite,
then.
Assuming it's infinite.
Oh,
assuming it's infinite.
Yeah.
That's fine.
All right.
So each site is connected to four links.
So you might think the answer
is four times the number of sites.
But that's not the way it works.
So the way it works,
the way to draw it,
is to draw,
for each site,
draw two links.
Now,
for the next site here,
also draw two links.
For the site over here,
draw two links.
Notice we'll fill up all the links.
So all you have to do is put two links.
At each site.
And that fills up everything.
Three dimensions,
it's three links at each site.
And that covers everything.
The reason,
of course,
is that the link connects two sites.
So it's only half the half
of what you might have thought.
Okay.
But in any case,
you have in here.
In here.
in energy that's associated with the ground state,
which means when everybody is aligned.
Well,
that's a constant.
We could subtract it out.
We could add it or
subtract it in such a way
that the ground state is zero energy,
and group it together with this constant here.
It wouldn't make any difference.
Only energy differences are important
in statistical mechanics,
or in almost everything.
Energy differences.
So the ground state energy is not so important.
What is important is the energy difference
between an up spin and a down spin,
or a bond and a broken bond.
All right,
let's just remember what we found out
from the mean field theory.
Excuse me,
does there need to be a j
by the sum over the sides?
No,
no j there.
No j there.
All right.
It's reminding now that we calculate the partition function,
e to the minus beta times e.
That means every time you see a j,
it'll come together with a beta.
And also every time you see an h,
it will come together with a beta.
It'll always be there.
All right,
we calculate the partition function.
We go through the manipulations that we went through.
And if you remember,
we calculated
in the mean field approximately,
we calculated the mean field approximation.
Just to remind you,
for anybody who wasn't here,
just what the mean field approximation was.
So here's a sign.
It's surrounded by a bunch of neighbors.
Let's draw the neighbors as crosses.
The neighbors have an average sigma.
That average sigma might be zero,
or it might have a net average value
when averaged over the neighboring sites.
The more neighboring sites that you have,
the better approximation it is to just say
each spin here,
each neighbor,
has a spin which is equal to the value,
equal to the average.
So in a high enough dimension,
which turns out to only mean two,
you can make a reasonable approximation
by saying each spin here sees around it
a collection of spins,
each one of which has the average spin.
All right,
then we say,
all right.
Good.
Then what is the energy
of the spin on the average?
It is minus j times
the average spin of the neighbors
times the spin itself of that particular particle.
Sigma bar means the average.
Minus j,
sigma bar,
sigma.
And then what about this term over here?
Well,
this term doesn't care about the neighbors.
And so it's just,
oh,
I missed something here.
What did I miss?
The number of neighbors.
That's where twice the dimension came from.
Twice the dimension,
whatever the dimension is,
minus twice the dimension of space,
the dimension of the lattice,
j,
times the spin of the neighbor.
Well,
this is the average of the spins,
whatever happens to be,
times the spin itself.
And then another term from here,
which is just h times the spin itself.
ありがとうございました
And we pretended that the
average u was just a number
and did the statistical mechanical problem of one spin
with an energy given by this expression.
And of course,
this is just a number.
うん
times the spin.
Okay,
so that's a calculation that we did
when we first looked at these magnets,
and we found out that the average spin,
the average spin that you would get,
I'm gonna call it for the moment sigma double bar.
It's the average of the spin that you would get
if all of the neighbors happened to be frozen
and had the value sigma bar.
Then,
if you remember,
that's equal
to the hyperbolic tangent of the coefficient,
the thing in the bracket,
minus two VJ sigma bar plus H times beta,
that is the inverse temperature,
and that was it.
Okay,
that's it.
Now,
it's a complicated expression.
We studied it a little bit,
but the important thing was
we now make the mean field assumption
that sigma bar,
the average of this spin,
is just equal to the
average of all of its neighbors.
This,
of course,
would be true if we had a big enough sample
and we were deep in the interior of it.
It wouldn't matter which one
of the spins we look at.
They all have the same average,
so we now,
we now do the self-consistency trick of saying
that's our equation that determines sigma bar.
Two,
D,
J,
and H are all just numbers,
so this is now an equation for sigma bar.
Let's just remind ourselves what the solution looked like.
What we did,
we did a trick.
We defined a new variable by redefining this thing
and calling it Y.
We wound up with an equation that looked like Y
divided by two,
D,
J,
of course,
that's it,
Y,
or,
that's beta,
equals tanh of Y.
That was our equation.
Let's forget the rest of it.
Let's just start over.
Start right there and remind ourselves what we learned.
Oh.
And Y plus H?
Yes,
Y plus beta H,
I think.
And aren't you missing a minus sign also?
Yeah.
Y minus beta H,
I think.
Y minus beta H.
Which was by,
what was Y,
is that equal to two,
D,
J,
beta,
or minus two,
D,
J,
beta?
Plus.
And you had a minus sign.
The thing you originally had was tan minus two,
D,
J.
See what I'm saying?
That's why the minus sign is here,
I think.
No.
Oh,
okay.
No.
There's a relative minus sign between them.
Okay,
all right.
Yeah.
Okay,
so this was our equation,
our mean field equation,
our consistency equation,
which tells us what Y is.
Y is just the average spin divided by two,
D,
J,
beta,
or beta.
All right,
one more element,
one more thing.
Let's just remember that beta is one over the temperature,
so let's put the temperature
over here,
the temperature of here.
All right,
first exercise.
What happens if H is equal to zero?
Then it's just Y times T over two,
D,
J is equal to tan of Y,
and we can get this.
And now we can just,
by inspection,
get a quiz.
pretty good idea of what things look like.
Hatch function looks like this.
Hatch of y.
y on this axis,
and on the vertical axis,
the hyperbolic tangent.
On the left side,
you have a linear function of y,
and the linear function of y
passes through the origin,
and it has a slope.
It has a slope,
which is the temperature
divided by 2dj.
So in particular,
when the temperature is very high,
the slope is steep.
And the only place where these curves intersect
is right at the origin,
and therefore,
for large temperature,
there is no magnetization.
y is equal to zero.
y is proportional to sigma bar,
and therefore,
sigma bar is equal to zero
when the temperature is high.
As expected.
Now we start lowering the temperature.
The slope of this curve decreases,
and at some point,
it becomes exactly tangent
to the hyperbolic tangent.
Tangent,
two different uses of the term tangent.
Tangent meaning
hugs it closely.
Hyperbolic tangent
means,
yes.
What is the slope
of the hyperbolic tangent function?
At the origin.
Anybody know?
It's exactly one.
Easy to differentiate.
You differentiate the hyperbolic tangent,
you can do it yourself,
and you discover that the slope
of the hyperbolic tangent
at the origin is exactly equal to one.
That means,
when the slope of the left-hand side
is adjusted to one,
that's the magic point.
It's a magic point.
Where the two curves
lie on top of each other.
Go past that,
decrease the temperature even more,
you decrease the slope of this line even more,
and all of a sudden,
you have a solution over here,
and a solution over here.
Those solutions are magnetized.
Those solutions
have non-zero y,
and therefore non-zero
sigma bar.
Sigma bar over two d j,
I believe.
That's a phase transition.
At that point,
the system
doesn't quite know what to do.
Should it go here?
It doesn't go there.
Should it go here,
or should it go here?
In other words,
there's an ambiguity.
It seems like the spins
want to have
an average value.
But is that average value up,
or is it down?
That's the question.
Here the average value is up,
sigma bar is positive,
here it's down.
And the problem is,
there's a complete symmetry in the problem.
If you take all the spins and turn them over,
whatever they are,
turn every one over,
it's the same problem back again.
So,
there's no way to decide
whether it does this or it does that.
To decide,
we add a tiny,
tiny,
tiny little bit of
h.
And the effect of adding
a tiny little bit of h is to
shift this curve,
either to the left
or the right.
But once you shift it,
that point of the solution
is no longer there.
And only
one of these two
will remain.
In that case,
that's what happens,
that's magnetization.
One of them wins,
and the one that wins,
of course,
is if you put a little
magnetic field which is trying to push
the spins to be up,
then up will win.
If you put the
magnetic field such that they want to be down,
then down will win.
So,
we can now
draw a graph
of what
the system looks like as a function
of two variables.
The two variables are the temperature
and the external magnetic field.
Those are the two things
we can vary in the problem.
We can
turn up the temperature or down the temperature.
We do that by turning up the
heat bath or turning it down.
Putting a little fire under it.
Or,
we can change the magnetic field
by
turning on the current through
a coil and making
the magnetic field
a little larger or smaller.
Those are the two things at our disposal.
What about J?
J is also something
we can change,
but in order to change it,
what we usually have to do is change the material.
Now,
in fact,
you can also
change it by changing the pressure
and other things,
but we're going to take J
to be a fixed number.
Fixed chemical composition,
fixed pressure,
fixed distance between the atoms,
J is a well-defined number.
You can look up in the
handbook of physics and chemistry or whatever.
But,
beta and J
are the things that you,
sorry,
beta and H
are the things that are easily under your disposal.
So,
you might
want to ask,
as an experimental fact,
what does the
magnetization look like
as a function of
temperature
and magnetic field?
So,
first of all,
let's turn
off H altogether.
No H.
No H,
and go to large temperature.
Oh,
oh,
let me come back a second,
one second.
Let's go back to this formula.
The question is,
at what temperature does the transition
happen?
The transition
from having a solution like this
to not having a solution like that.
So,
the transition happens
when the slope of the left
side is equal to one.
When the slope
of the left side is equal to one,
that's where you're hugging
the curve's hub.
Okay,
so the slope of the left side is one
when the temperature
is equal to 2 d
J.
That's called the critical temperature.
It's not exact.
This is a mean field approximation.
It becomes exact when d becomes large.
And
I'm sorry,
I forgot to look up
what the correct answer is for
d equals 2 and 3.
But for d equals 2,
it's off by a significant amount.
For d equals 3,
it's fairly good.
But it captures
qualitatively
what it is that does really happen.
Okay,
so a temperature
2 d J,
that's called the critical temperature,
and let's write it C R I T.
The critical temperature
below which
the system is spontaneously
magnetized.
Everybody wants to line up
and the lining up tendency
wins and everybody lines up.
Not absolutely.
They're not 100%
lined up.
They fluctuate,
but there's
a net tendency for everybody to line up.
Above that temperature,
thermal fluctuations win
and it doesn't magnetize.
Okay,
so now
let's draw a picture here.
Is that the Curie temperature?
What's that?
The Curie temperature?
きゅうり
Yeah,
yeah,
same thing.
Curie temperature is a term that's used for magnets,
but it's strictly.
If we're talking about the general phenomena
of phase transitions,
this would just be called critical temperature.
So Curie temperature is a
special case of a critical point.
A lambda point in liquid helium is another one,
and they're very similar to each other.
In fact,
they fall into a class of phase transitions
which are almost identical in many ways.
I'm going to show you why that,
or at least how this is related
to another interesting transition.
Okay,
so there's some critical temperature over here.
T critical.
Now,
what is the magnetization?
All right,
let's think about the value
of the magnetization on this plane.
First of all,
if you're at higher temperatures
than T critical,
and there is no magnetic field,
then magnetization is just zero.
There's no bias due to the magnetic field,
but at higher temperatures,
the statistics of ups
and downs being equal will win.
And so over here,
let's call it average
of sigma bar is equal to zero.
Along this line,
along the line,
the average of sigma bar is equal to zero.
Now you start lowering the temperature,
and you come to this critical point.
When you get to the critical point,
it just doesn't know what to do.
Should it go up or should it go down?
But the tiniest little bit
of straight magnetic field H will
tell you which way to go.
If H is positive,
the magnetization will be positive.
And right above this line,
it won't be zero.
And right below the line,
Spontaneous magnetization has happened.
And so all along here,
sigma is positive.
Plus,
plus,
plus.
On the average,
the average is positive.
And down below,
it's negative.
Corresponds to the two possible roots
where the red line either intersected on the right side,
or on the left side.
And physically,
it's just the extra little bit
of magnetic field.
It's broken the symmetry between ups and downs,
and it's biased it.
And that little bit of biasing is enough
that just the tiniest little bit of H goes plus.
Tiniest little bit of H down goes minus.
Now,
you can ask what the jump
is in the magnetization going on.
We'll do it across here.
Remember,
this is the average magnetization.
It's not zero or one.
It's not one or minus one.
It can be zero,
or it can be two-thirds,
or it could be one-quarter.
It can be any number between zero,
sorry,
between minus one and one.
Well,
at zero temperature,
way down here,
it doesn't matter what the magnetic field is.
It's zero temperature.
All these guys line up,
and they line up
in the down direction down here.
So all along here,
sigma bar is equal to minus one,
and all along here,
it's equal to plus one.
That's just the fact that at zero temperature,
even,
they just line up.
Choose the lowest energy.
Now,
what about right at the critical point,
and that's the point where you're
going to have to go down.
Imagine going up and down from negative temperature
to positive temperature just at the critical point.
Well,
just at the critical point,
that's this place where the red line is just barely
at 45 degrees,
just barely,
critical barely.
So.
At the critical point,
the magnetization is clearly zero.
If you increase the temperature,
sorry,
decrease the temperature just a tiny bit,
the magnetization changes a tiny bit.
If you decrease the temperature just a tiny bit,
that means lowering the slope here.
Don't turn on the magnetic field,
but there are two branches,
one just to the right,
one just to the left,
and the magnetization is tiny if the temperature is tiny.
So,
as we move vertically here at the critical temperature,
the magnetization increases,
but continuously.
Just above here,
it's very small,
but positive.
Just below here,
it's very small,
but negative.
So,
as you come into this critical point,
the magnetization tends to zero from every direction,
no matter how direction,
including this one,
the magnetization tends to zero
at the critical point,
but once you pass the critical point,
there's a jump in the magnetization.
So,
for example,
if you had your magnet turned on,
and you slowly vary the magnetic field,
if you slowly vary the magnetic field,
above the critical temperature,
then the magnetization gets smaller and smaller
and smaller and smaller,
goes to zero continuously,
and then gets bigger and bigger and bigger,
completely smoothly,
just as you might expect.
With the magnet is pointing down,
it makes everything tilt down,
with the magnet is pointing up,
it tilts stuff up,
but completely continuously,
as you turn off the magnetic field,
it goes to zero,
and as you turn it back on,
it becomes positive.
We could draw a curve for that,
I don't mind.
Question?
Yeah.
I'm still not clear what's happening
on a horizontal axis.
It jumps.
Pardon?
But what do you see,
what's it doing?
It jumps.
It jumps when you go across it?
Yeah.
But what's it doing on it?
Oh,
on it,
doesn't know what to do.
Okay.
It can't decide what's the minus.
Now,
it does one thing or the other,
but of course the answer is you could never really
turn off all the magnetic field.
Something is gonna bias it a little bit.
In particular,
it's not continuous there.
It's not continuous.
That's the key to what a phase transition is.
So,
or this is technically called
the second order phase transition.
We don't need to distinguish them
because I'm not gonna get a chance
to talk about first order phase transition.
So,
what is it?
It's a series of changes.
Okay.
So,
as the experimental physicist manipulates
his magnetic field at fixed temperature,
the magnetic field varies at first
the magnetization is nice and smooth
until it gets to this point.
When it gets over to here,
it's not zero.
It's negative.
And then a little tiny change in the magnetic field,
whoop,
flips it over.
flips it over and the
magnetization changes discontinuously across there.
That discontinuous change is a,
well,
it's a symptom that in a sense there are two
phases.
Supposing you didn't know anything about this up here,
let's suppose T
critical is too high a temperature
for our experimental physicists to ever
study,
they would say there are two phases.
There's a phase of negative
magnetization,
there's a phase of positive magnetization,
and as you vary the
parameters,
it jumps.
It's not all down to all up.
It's an average down to average up.
Because it would be the hysteresis
if it was all to all up.
No.
We're not going to have
time to talk about the hysteresis.
All right,
but there's another way you can move around in space.
You can say,
can I go from here to
here without having a sharp change?
And of course you can.
You can go from here to
here going around the critical point.
If you go around the critical point,
you experience no jump.
But you do get from negative to positive.
So on the one hand,
experimentalists down here who never got up to
T critical would say there are two phases.
And they're distinct.
And not only are there two phases,
but there's a sudden jump
as you vary the magnetic field.
On the other hand,
somebody who had more experience with this system would say,
oh,
well,
no,
there's really not a sharp difference between here and here.
Let me show you how to go
from one to the other without jumping.
And both would be right.
Both are correct statements.
Does it jump if you stay at fixed temperature?
Have you allowed yourself to adjust?
If you explore the whole region here,
you'll discover there are ways to get from
here to here which don't involve a jump.
Smooth.
Another question?
Yeah.
On the part below the critical where you're
going from negative to positive and there's that jump.
Yeah.
As you're getting closer and closer to the horizontal axis,
say from below,
are you getting closer and closer to zero?
Is the average getting closer and closer to zero?
No.
No,
I know it's not zero.
It's a relative thing.
Is it?
The actual value is getting less and less or not?
Here?
Yeah.
No.
No?
The average is staying negative.
I know it's negative,
but is it very near zero?
No,
it's not near zero over here.
Oh.
No,
no,
no.
Over here,
look.
Go back to this curve.
And now draw.
Now we're essentially at zero magnetic field.
Right.
So I don't need to shift the curve.
Yeah.
Okay.
We still have these two solutions.
Yeah.
And the two solutions don't have y near zero.
Well,
as you get it closer and closer to one,
to the critical,
that's here.
That's here.
Oh,
yeah.
Okay.
That's here.
I see.
So as you approach from here,
it goes to zero.
Yeah.
Okay.
Right.
But over here,
that's when the temperature is.
Yeah.
Okay.
Got it.
Good.
Thank you.
Excellent.
Okay.
So now we have everything
we need to know about magnets.
But I'm interested in the liquid-gas phase transition.
What does that have to do with this?
There's a way of thinking about exactly
the same system as being the transition between
liquid and gas.
It's not good for liquid to solid.
That is not good.
Liquid solid.
But liquid solid phase transition is very different.
So let's talk about what this possibly could
have to do with a bunch of particles.
Okay.
Let's talk about a box of particles.
There are a box of particles,
a box of liquid.
And the fluid is in,
I'll tell you what this drawing means in a minute.
It's a potential energy block.
So it's a potential energy block.
The edges here are the edges
of the walls of a box.
Here we're inside the box.
Here we're outside the box.
As it turns out,
the box really corresponds to some,
it might correspond to a material
or whatever it happens to correspond to,
the energy of the particle when it's inside the
box is lower than the energy of
the particle when it's outside the box.
Now we could manufacture this just by having
the inside of the box and the outside of
the box being inside one another.
slightly different elevations,
right?
We could have a flat box and a drop box.
But for whatever reason,
we're going to imagine
that a particle at rest inside the box
has less energy,
negative energy,
relative to what it has outside the box.
That difference in energy has a name,
it's called the chemical potential.
And it's usually written mu.
It's the amount of energy difference,
it's actually the amount of energy that it takes
to remove the particle from the box.
How much energy does it take
to remove the particle from the box?
Now we're not going to ask what is it,
in this particular case it's not important
what makes the difference,
why there's a different energy.
We'll just take it that the
energy is lower inside the box.
But furthermore,
there are particles
outside the box and inside the box.
Lots of them all over the place.
And we can ask what
the density is inside the box
and outside the box.
Oh,
one more thing.
The walls of the box are permeable.
Particles can come in and go out.
So they can cross the boundaries of the box.
So this could just be,
you know this could be,
this could be a bunch of molecules,
you dig a hole in the ground.
And the ground,
and now you just deposit some particles.
If the particles are in the hole,
they have less potential energy
than if they're out of the hole.
Where do you think the density of particles
is likely to be larger?
In the hole or out of the hole?
We're thinking thermal equilibrium now.
We're thinking thermal equilibrium.
That's right.
Anyhow
The energy is less in the home,
and so it's natural that the
Boltzmann distribution always favors lower energy.
Always favors lower energy.
Remember,
the Boltzmann distribution is e to
the minus beta times the energy,
so it's always a function which decreases energy.
It always prefers lower energy.
So the answer will be that this system will adjust itself so
that the density in here is in a certain kind of equilibrium.
And the equilibrium will depend on the energy
cost of taking the particle outside the box.
Now we can set this
up in a very definite way.
We can say we can do ordinary statistical mechanics.
And we can just say there's
a potential energy which depends on position,
but it depends on position in a very special way.
It's flat completely over the box of interest,
and maybe jumps when you go outside the box.
But we can focus on inside the box,
and we can ask what
is the density of the fluid
as a function of the energy cost
of taking the particle outside the box.
And that's kind of the depth of this potential.
Question.
Yeah?
Is the depth mu?
The depth is mu.
Chemical potential.
It's called the chemical potential because…
In general,
it can be different for different chemical molecules.
So you could imagine a situation where one
kind of molecule prefers to be in the box
and the other kind of molecule
doesn't prefer to be in the box.
And then turning on chemical potentials
can change chemical compositions in various ways.
But we're not interested in the chemistry here.
We're interested just in this idea
that you can tune the
density by changing the chemical potential.
By changing the chemical potential,
you can change the density.
And all the chemical potential is
is a term in the energy
which depends on the number of particles in the box.
Mu for each particle.
If there are n particles in the box,
then n mu.
If there are n minus 1 particles in the box,
n minus 1 mu.
Now in this problem,
the number of particles is a variable.
It's a variable because particles can come into the box
and out of the box.
That means a configuration
involves not only the positions
and momentum of every particle,
but also the number of particles.
Now the number of particles is free to change
because they can come into the
system and out of the system.
And part of determining thermal equilibrium
is determining how many particles on
the average are inside the box.
So I'm not going to go through this in detail.
But I'm going to tell you what to do.
You write the usual formula for the partition plus.
E to the minus beta times the energy.
You sum over all the configurations.
That means the momentum and the
position of all of the particles.
But you add another term here.
Plus the number of particles
times the chemical potential times beta.
Why is that there?
Well,
this is just the potential energy
of the particles inside the box.
If there are n of them,
this is the energy stored inside,
just in the particles of being there.
And you also sum over the number of particles.
We're not going to do that.
We don't have time.
But I'm just going to
show you how to do it.
And I'm going to indicate to you
what the meaning of the chemical potential is.
It's the thing that you adjust if you
want to adjust the density of the fluid.
You could do another thing.
You can seal the box and
not let particles go in and out.
And then just put in the
number of particles that you want.
But you may be interested in the problem of particles
that can come into the
box and out of the box.
And then you change the density
by changing the chemical potential.
By changing the chemical potential,
you can change the average
number of particles in the box.
What,
in this language,
what is a liquid gas transition?
And I will tell you.
What happens in a liquid gas transition is
you take your box,
you keep it at a fixed temperature,
and you start varying the chemical potential.
The more you vary the chemical potential,
the more it wants to pull back,
depending on the science,
of course,
lowering its energy here,
the more it wants to suck particles into the box.
And so there's a density,
which is a natural function of the chemical potential.
And what is it that happens in a transition?
What happens in a transition is
as you vary the chemical potential,
all of a sudden,
you hit a point
where the density of the fluid suddenly drops.
It suddenly changes.
It changes from being a gas to being a liquid.
So if you were to fill up this,
a box,
of course,
here,
might mean a region of three-dimensional space.
I'd imagine it was a,
when I imagine a hole in the ground,
it was in two-dimensional space.
But imagine,
you know,
a box,
a real box of three dimensions.
Particles go in,
you get some extra energy out of it,
because there's a chemical potential.
Particles go out and cost energy.
The extra energy that you save
by bringing particles into the box
will tend to increase the density inside the box.
You keep lowering the energy inside the box,
it keeps wanting to suck particles in,
and then all of a sudden,
even though the atmosphere around the box
might be at a temperature,
and whatever else,
temperature and density
that corresponds to vapor,
all of a sudden you hit a transition point
where it becomes liquid.
The difference between liquid and vapor
is a sudden discontinuity in the density,
liquid being denser than vapor.
So if you could do this experiment with a box
and vary the potential energy
of a particle inside the box,
lower the potential energy,
outside conditions are such that you have steam,
or vapor,
water vapor,
and you lower the energy,
particles will congregate inside the box
as you lower their energy,
and then all of a sudden at some point
it will jump to the fluid phase,
to the liquid phase.
That transition is very much like this transition,
I'm going to spell it out,
I'm going to spell out exactly what the relationship is.
Well,
first of all,
what are the conditions that you need
to have a liquid-gas phase transition?
You need two things.
You need to have a hard core repulsion between molecules.
Well,
molecules always have hard core repulsions.
You cannot stick two molecules onto the same cycle,
they repel,
for a number of reasons.
So,
it's natural to have hard,
that molecules behave like little billiard balls.
Little billiard balls,
they don't want to interpenetrate,
so roughly speaking you can't put
two of them on the same cycle.
The next thing that's important is
that there be a little bit of,
and that's a form of really hard core repulsion.
Just like two billiard balls really repel
when you try to push them together.
You need something else though.
You need a little bit of attraction
when they're not quite together.
You need a little bit of
attraction when they're not quite touching.
So you need a potential energy
which is big and repulsive and positive
when they're trying to get into each other,
and then when you separate them out a little bit,
all of a sudden they
want to attract a little bit.
That's an extremely common
feature of molecular interactions.
Hard core repulsions and very short range attractions.
And that's what you need in order to have
the standard liquid gas transition.
Alright,
so I'm going to show you how the magnet
produces exactly that situation.
Let's start with the magnet with
all of its little elementary magnets down.
When they're all down,
that's the ground state,
and let's call that empty space.
When all the magnets are down,
in fact what we're going
to say is something like this.
We're going to say on each side of the lattice,
each side of the lattice,
you can have a particle or not have a particle.
This is our game.
We're going to make out of the liquid gas problem,
we're going to make a lattice version of it.
The particles,
the molecules,
live on a lattice.
You can have no particles at a site.
Let's call that down.
Let's call that sigma equals down.
Sigma equals minus one means no particle on that site.
What about sigma equals plus one?
We're going to take that to the next slide.
Model.
Yes particle on site.
What about two particles on site?
Well,
the magnet doesn't allow that.
Sigma can't be two.
It can only be minus one or one.
It can't be four.
It can't be anything else.
So immediately from the start,
it forbids the possibility of
two particles on a site.
But then again,
that's exactly what we're trying to do.
We're trying to model a gas
where you can't put two particles on the same site
because they have a hard core.
So it's built in to this system of particles.
If they're really described by the same kind of variable,
sigma equals plus one and minus one,
it's automatically built in
that they have an infinite hard core repulsive barrier
when they try to get out to the same site.
So we satisfied condition number one.
What about condition number two?
Do they attract?
Now here we're going to use for the energy
exactly the Ising model energy
plus a little magnetic field.
And I'm going to show you what that does
in the language of these fake particles.
Well,
I'm not sure which are fake.
Are the particles fake or is the magnet flat fake?
The point is it's the same mathematical system.
The particles or the magnet.
Let's start with this term here.
Minus J times sigma I times sigma J
where these are neighboring sites on the lattice.
Sung over all the links.
How much energy is there
if there are no particles whatever?
Well,
that's the situation where all sigmas are down.
When all sigmas are down,
then there is an energy minus J for each link.
So there's total ground state energy
which is minus J times the number of links.
What do we do with that?
Don't do anything with it.
That's just the energy of the system
when there's no particles at all.
Does it matter for anything?
No,
it doesn't.
It's always there.
It's the ground state energy.
We can throw it away.
And we can throw it away just by subtracting
minus the number of links
and the number of links.
I think it's times 2 J.
Now that I've thrown it away,
let's really throw it away and ignore it
because it plays no role in anything.
It's just a number.
And energy differences are the important things.
Alright,
so we have this term in the energy.
No particles.
That gives us a certain energy.
Let's call it zero.
Let's make the zero of energy
when there are no particles.
Now what happens if I put in one particle?
That means flip one of the spins over.
It means all the spins went down.
Every one of them goes down.
はい
We take one and we flip it up.
That's mathematically equivalent
to putting one particle in some place.
How much energy do we get?
Let's calculate.
The energy that we get,
how many bonds have we broken?
Depends on the dimensionality.
Let's do two dimensions,
because it's easy to visualize.
We flip this spin over,
then we break four bonds.
We get a total amount
of energy equal to two j
for each bond,
eight j I believe.
Eight j,
eight?
Yes,
eight j.
One particle has energy eight j.
Later on,
we're going to put in a little bit
of magnetic field.
When we put in a magnetic field,
that's going to add another twice h,
but we'll do that later.
So one particle has eight j.
That's how much energy it costs
to create a particle at that point.
What about two particles if one particle is over here
and one particle is over here?
16 j.
Two particles,
But,
incidentally,
the same is true
if the two particles are over here.
Let's just check that.
Let's see how many bonds we have to break
if they're on the corners of the bag.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six,
seven,
eight.
Yes.
So even if they're on diagonals,
you still pay a price of 16 j.
But what if they're neighbors?
What if they're even closer?
What if they're even closer like that?
Then how many bonds do you break?
One less.
Two less.
This bond is not broken.
Same.
Why not?
Because they're both plus.
Right.
That bond is not broken.
So we've broken six bonds.
So two particles close together.
Two close particles.
And close now means within one bond length away.
What do they have?
They have 12 j.
So let me suppose I plotted the energy
as a function of difference.
I would find,
yes,
just the mere act of putting particles in
cost me 16 j.
But that's all right.
That energy is always there no matter where
I move the particles around.
But if I move them within a bond length,
the energy decreases.
The energy decreases.
That's like a potential energy which decreases
when they get very close together.
So there's a point.
There's a potential energy,
an energy which depends
on the position of the particles.
And when the particles get within one bond length
of each other,
the energy decreases by two j.
Two j or four j?
Four.
Four j.
Or the energy decreases by four j.
So that's like having a short range attractive energy
where when the particles are close together,
the energy is negative relative to what it would be
in their far apart.
Negative relative to what they would be
when they're far apart.
So the particles attract.
They like to be close together.
How close together?
One bond length away.
But it's not an overwhelming attraction.
It doesn't say the energy is infinitely negative
if you put them next to each other.
It's just a modest amount of attraction.
A modest saving of energy of putting them close together.
and it's very much like the molecular attraction of
a pair of molecules when they get close together.
Okay,
so we
have a system now
which is mathematically isomorphic
to a system of particles on a lattice
which have
an attractive force between them where
you can have any number of particles.
The particle number is something that can change.
So it's like the system of molecules where
molecules can come into and out of the system.
Doesn't have a definite number of molecules.
The number of molecules itself is a variable.
Short range potential,
short range attraction,
excuse me,
very short range infinite repulsion.
You cannot put two of them on the same side.
But
when they get a little bit apart,
they're slightly attractive.
Exactly what you need for a liquid gas phase transition.
Now,
let's add something else.
Does this system have a chemical potential incidentally?
A chemical potential
is the energy stored in just having one particle.
That's what it is.
The chemical potential is just the energy
in having a particle present.
Just by virtue of having the particle,
if there's an energy which wouldn't
be there if the particle weren't there,
that is called the chemical potential.
Well,
yes,
just having the particle with no other particles around
gives you an energy 8 Gen.
So yes,
give me some chemical potential.
But I want to be
able to vary that chemical potential.
I would like to be able to vary that.
And without varying J incidentally.
I'd like to hold J fixed.
I want to be able to
vary the chemical potential separately from J.
That's easy to do.
Put a magnetic field in.
Now this is sum over the sites.
Sum over the sites of sigma I.
How much does this give me
when I add a particle to the,
to the brew?
Sigma starts down when there's no particle.
When I put a particle in,
sigma becomes plus.
So it jumps two units.
It gives me two units worth of
energy for every spin which is flipped up.
For every particle that you put in,
it gives you twice H.
So you can add,
for each particle,
for each isolated particle,
you can add plus two H.
So now we have everything we need.
We have a system that is equivalent
to a collection of particles on a lattice.
It has a variable chemical potential which,
notice how we vary it.
We vary it by varying the magnetic field.
Magnetic field gave us an energy per particle.
And we have a short range of traction.
The short range of traction,
of course the hardcore,
the hardcore billiard ball potential.
But then a short range of traction,
the coefficient of which is 2J.
4J.
All right.
So I can,
I want to give you an example.
I want to keep the molecular properties fixed.
So I'm not going to play with J.
That has to do with the molecular properties that design
to tell you what the potential energy between them is.
What I can vary is the chemical potential.
And mathematically that seems to be
the same thing as varying H.
Varying H.
So this problem is exactly the same as the average.
I've already said,
I've already said.
No,
there it is.
It is exactly this problem here.
Precisely.
There's a temperature that we can vary.
Particles are at some temperature.
There is a chemical potential we can vary.
Now H is not exactly the chemical potential.
There's an offset by an amount AJ.
What about the particle density?
Let's talk about the particle density.
We haven't discussed the particle density.
Okay.
How many particles are there
on the average at a point?
At a particular point?
Well,
I say the answer is somewhere,
first of all,
between 0 and 1.
I say the number of particles on the average,
the number of particles at a point,
of course it's either 0 or 1.
But we're talking about the average.
The average number of particles.
The average number of particles is 0.
It's 1 plus sigma divided by 2.
Let's see why that's true.
If there is a particle there,
that means sigma is 1,
right?
So 1 plus 1 is 2,
divided by 2 is 1.
What if there's no particle there?
That's a good candidate for the
number of particles at a point.
And it's the average.
It is truly the average
number of particles at a point
is equal to 1 half plus the average of sigma.
The average number of particles at a
point is 1 plus the average of sigma.
That tells us that the density of particles,
let's call it rho,
is proportional to 1 plus sigma divided by 2.
That's the density of particles.
In other words,
the number of particles per lattice cell,
the average number of particles per lattice cell,
is 1 plus sigma bar divided by 2.
That's the average number of particles.
It's not sigma divided by 2.
It's not sigma bar.
It's 1 plus sigma bar divided by 2.
And that's because of this offset that
sigma bar being down means no particles.
Not minus 1.
It's 0.16 is minus 1 particle.
So we offset it by this half here.
Excuse me.
Didn't you say sigma bar could be
a value between minus 1 and minus 1?
Yes.
Which?
It says rho goes between 0 and 1.
Right?
You can't have more than one particle in a cell
because they have sharp elbows and they
push each other out of the way.
You can't have less than one
particle because that doesn't mean anything.
So it goes between 0 and 1.
And so the density is just 1 half.
So it's 1 half plus the average magnetization.
For rho2?
For rho2.
Plus half the average magnetization.
What did I say?
Half plus half the average magnetization.
Right.
Half plus half the average magnetization
is the density of this fluid.
So now we're all set to say what
happens if we were to vary the chemical potential,
varying H,
keeping the temperature fixed.
If we're above the critical temperature,
the magnetization varies uniformly and continuously.
No joke.
That says the density doesn't jump.
The density of particles.
So above the critical temperature,
as we vary the chemical
potential in a box of gas,
lower the energy,
pull it down,
nothing very exciting happens when
we pass this horizontal axis.
In other words,
the horizontal axis is when the chemical potential
plus the clever H plus this is equal.
好
The horizontal axis is when h is equal to zero,
corresponds to the chemical potential of aj plus 2h,
whatever.
No sudden jump in anything above the critical point.
Below the critical point,
by contrast,
as you vary the chemical potential,
h,
all of a sudden at this point here,
the magnetization jumps.
It jumps from negative.
When it's negative,
that means the density is low.
The density is low when this is negative,
so it jumps,
and it jumps from low density to high density.
The experimentalists didn't have temperatures
available as big as t critical,
which was t critical for water.
No.
どうもどうも
That's a,
I shouldn't have asked that question.
That's pressure dependent,
which means chemical,
chemical potential dependent.
No,
the critical is a good deal higher than that.
And it's a good deal higher than that.
You see,
going across here is the phenomenon of boiling.
Or going down this way is the phenomenon of boiling.
Here's where boiling happens.
Boiling doesn't happen out here.
It's just a smooth,
continuous transition of the density
when you're at high temperature,
high enough temperature above the critical point.
Below the critical point,
you're here.
Are you referring to superheated steam above that?
You could,
yeah.
The density changes.
Question please,
how do you vary the chemical potential?
We understand magnetic,
but in the other case,
how do you do it?
Really by varying the density.
You can do it even,
you can either vary the density,
you see the density jumps across here,
but how do you vary the chemical potential?
Pressure?
Yeah.
Pressure is one way,
but...
ああああああ
chemical potential for water molecules.
A little tricky.
Whatever it takes to vary the density.
So I like to think about it by,
in a thought experiment,
by doing what I said,
which is to create a box.
And then literally pull the molecules into the box.
Literally pull the molecules into the box,
and pull the molecules into the box
by creating a potential energy inside the box.
I have to think about how
you would do that in practice.
It's not actually what you do.
What you do instead is raise the pressure.
But varying the chemical potential
is the simplest thing to do.
When you do it,
you suddenly find a sudden jump
in the density of the fluid.
And that is the way to do it.
That is what happens.
We're gonna do gas-based transition.
Down here is gas,
low density.
Up here is liquid.
But notice that you can go from gas to liquid
without any jump by going around the critical point,
way up above the critical temperature.
And varying whatever you have
to vary to vary the density.
You can vary the density by varying the pressure.
That's actually the easiest way.
You vary the pressure.
You increase the temperature,
vary the pressure,
increase the temperature and the pressure,
making sure you go above the critical point,
the critical temperature,
and then lower the temperature back,
and you'll go from gas to liquid without any jump.
Question?
Yeah.
When you say you're changing the chemical potential,
by changing the density,
you're basically changing your effective distance
for a van der Waals potential?
No,
no,
no.
You're keeping the,
the property of the molecule is fixed.
But the density says,
the van der Waals potential is not constant.
Oh,
it's function of position,
yeah.
So when you change the density,
you're changing the distance between molecules.
Certainly.
In that sense,
you're changing the potential energy.
Right,
right.
So when you change,
that's right.
So when you change the density enough,
it suddenly makes a transition,
realizes that the potential,
that the negative potential energy is there,
and tries to put all the molecules together.
Right.
What's the relationship between,
in this case of the gas-liquid transition,
between the critical temperature and the boiling point?
Well,
boiling point depends,
Yeah.
The boiling point depends on the pressure,
which in turn means it depends on the density.
Let's see,
so how would we say this?
The problem with this is
I haven't worked out the pressure.
What we could do,
the pressure is a function
of temperature and chemical potential.
And if I were to have worked out the pressure,
we could have varied the pressure
instead of the chemical potential.
That's why I'm hemming and hawing,
because I don't want to go through the effort now
of calculating the pressure.
But just in a simple-minded way,
when I'm boiling water,
what's my path along there from?
From liquid to gas or gas to liquids?
Go on,
say it over here.
go on.
Yeah.
Okay.
Where you going,
from liquid to gas or gas to liquid?
Doesn't matter,
just keep it where you are.
I'm going across here,
but the point at which
you go across there depends on,
depends on the pressure.
Sure,
I understand.
Depends on the pressure.
So,
right,
so the point at which you cross
does depend on the pressure.
So there's another variable in here,
it's not independent.
And,
okay.
One of the very fascinating things is the properties
of the system near the critical point there.
There's a whole theory of the behavior,
there's a whole theory of lots of experiments
that have been,
that has been felt.
And,
what happens as you approach the critical temperature?
As you approach the critical temperature,
the critical point,
as you approach the critical point,
a number of fascinating things happen,
but they're all characterized
what are called critical exponents.
Every quantity that you can think of that's interesting,
in its dependence on temperature,
will generally go as P minus T critical,
to some power.
And that power,
those powers,
they're not ones and twos,
they're various kinds of irrational numbers of things,
transcendental numbers.
They're called the critical exponents.
And,
of course,
they vary from one kind of phase transition
to another,
but they're exactly the same
for the magnetic transitions and the liquid gas transitions.
They fall into exactly the same class.
The behaviors,
the,
these critical points are,
are rather insensitive to the details.
And,
they depend on features
that don't care whether you put them on a lattice,
they don't care whether it's nearest neighbor
or second nearest neighbor,
they all behave the same way.
And,
the magnets and the fluid transitions
are in the same class.
Okay,
I think we're finished.
I'm sorry,
do they,
Is it a form of continuum or
is it a discrete countable even finite?
Oh,
the set of possible critical points?
Yeah.
Because they're discrete.
Finite?
No,
they're probably not finite.
I don't think they're finite.
The number of critical points is not finite,
but they are discrete.
さあ、
始める
How do you define a gas
and gas
So they coexist.
Liquid and gas coexist if you go around.
Well,
they're not distinguishable.
They're continuously,
you know,
they have a continuous transition from one to the other.
What do you need to put into
the theory to get a gas liquid interface?
A gas,
oh,
to have a gas liquid interface,
you have some gravitational potential
energy or something to be separated.
It's not surface tension?
It's not surface tension.
Oh,
it could be surface tension.
It could be surface tension.
If you are,
look,
most of this kind of analysis is what
you think about for an infinite volume of fluid.
So surface tension is not really the thing here.
But you could have an infinite volume of fluid
laid out on an infinite plane in a gravitational field,
and then you would create a
liquid gas transition at some point.
And that could be worked out.
That's a full-blown tool.
Basically,
the altitude is related to the chemical potential.
So varying the altitude varies the chemical potential.
And,
you know,
a sudden transition at some height,
which is connected to this transition.
In this model,
do you get a heat of
vaporization as you go across that transition?
In general,
yes.
No doubt.
I would have to think about
what that means in this model.
The thing is,
the energy down here is exactly
the same as the energy down here.
The energy up here is exactly
the same as the energy just above.
I would have to think about that.
So this...
Isn't there a heat release at that point?
Total energy is conserved,
of course,
but...
Yeah,
but there's a certain...
In a magnetic problem,
the energy above and the energy
below is just exactly the same.
That's a good question.
I don't know if the answer is offhand.
I have to think about it.
It's getting late.
Okay.
Does this have implications for superconductor magnets?
I suppose it does,
but I'm not sure what.
What's the question?
Well,
you talked back about the Germanium detectors at the...
At Sudren Mine for the dark matter detectors.
And how the...
The...
The physical interaction creates a point where the...
It kicks over.
Where the transition happens
between superconductor and ordinary.
Right.
Yes.
Oh,
you're asking...
Yeah.
Is that a phase transition like this?
It's a phase transition.
It has similarities.
And the point there is if
you can adjust your superconductor to the...
To be very near the transition
or very near the phase transition,
let's say across here,
by a tiny change in some parameter,
you can have it to
jump from superconducting to non-superconducting.
And that gives you the possibility...
You know,
some energy is deposited in the detector
and even a small amount of energy
can create a little local pocket of a changed phase.
So it can be useful as
a very sensitive kind of detector.
But I don't know a lot about superconductor detectors.
They are...
If you're very close to the
phase transition and something really jumps,
then the presence
of a phase transition can be a very,
very good detector of very small changes in things.
Any phase transition?
Any phase transition.
Yeah.
And it can be very,
very sensitive.
Thank you.
Okay.
We have finished with statistical mechanics.
We've done our duty to...
Bulk money.
I think.
I keep making the same mistakes about Isaac.
I went back and looked at my notes,
and I realized that in
my notes I had an apology
to the students.
I'm doing the wrong thing.
I'm realizing exactly the same thing.
I'll probably do it again.
Okay.
I said I would talk about the anthropic principle.
What do you do with this question and answer?
That's sort of...
If you want to ask me questions
about the anthropic principle,
perhaps you will get me going
and I will answer them.
But I've sort of run out of steam.
No cookies.
It's not my fault.
There's no coffee.
But who asked me about the anthropic principle again?
Go ahead.
Shoot your question.
I wish I'd turned out the email now.
It was just basically about the generalities
of the applications,
the misapplications,
the implications.
Well,
all right.
I asked you a preceding question if I could.
Could you give a clear,
if there is such a thing,
a crisp statement of the anthropic principle?
Exactly what does it say?
Can I give a crisp?
No,
because it means many things to many people.
But I can tell you how I
think a rational use of it looks.
I don't say it's right,
but I think it can,
in some circumstances,
be a rational explanation of something.
First,
you have to understand what fine-tuning means.
OK,
let's talk about fine-tuning.
There's a small number of physics.
The classic case of an extreme fine-tuning
is,
of course,
the cosmological constant.
The cosmological constant is very small.
In natural units,
in Planck units,
it's 123 decimal places small.
What's the difference between being small
and being fine-tuned?
They sound like the same thing,
but they're not the same thing.
So I'll give you an example.
It's an example that I
cooked up to explain this once
to a bunch of people.
I had a bunch of condensed matter physicists
who didn't know what fine-tuning meant.
As soon as I told them what it meant,
they said,
oh,
we know that.
But let me explain it in terms of an example.
It's a silly example.
This is the only example
I've ever made up like this.
It doesn't have fish in it.
But it does have submersible submarines.
And also balloons.
OK.
Here's the difference.
Let's suppose that you were a certain kind of creature
that could only exist at a certain altitude
where the air was at just the right temperature,
not just temperature,
density,
and so forth.
OK.
So you find yourself at that temperature,
density,
and so forth,
in a balloon.
Not in a balloon,
in a gondola,
in a dirigible.
And a Zeppelin.
What's a good Zeppelin?
A dirigible.
Just get next to that.
What's a good Zeppelin?
Branding.
Yeah.
A Zeppelin,
I think,
is a big bag of gas.
A dirigible,
I think,
has some support.
Some supporting structure.
A Zeppelin.
A Zeppelin and a balloon,
but a dirigible.
A Zeppelin is a brand name.
Oh,
a Zeppelin is a brand name.
OK.
All right.
Anyway.
So there you are.
You're floating above the earth.
In your...
Blimp.
And you notice you're neither rising nor falling.
Isn't that wonderful?
You're neither rising nor falling.
Isn't that lucky?
You're at some stationary height.
And at stationary height,
you've been there for several billion years.
Long enough to have evolved.
And you've evolved in just the right way
to be able to live at that temperature
and at that behavior and so forth.
Let's see.
Isn't it very lucky that this blimp
happens to be exceptionally light?
Light enough that it floats.
OK.
Yes,
you're lucky.
The blimp happened to be light enough that it floats.
And it was a small number.
The small number was the density
of the material inside the blimp.
And that number is small.
In this case,
it's not horribly small,
but it's small.
It might be the density of hydrogen.
It might be the density of helium.
But notice there's a factor of,
what,
four difference
in the mass of helium and the mass of...
So the density could be quite different.
But still,
you'll float somewheres.
Your helium will support you.
Your hydrogen will support you.
You're OK.
And you'll come to equilibrium at some position.
The density of the air varies.
And you'll find some equilibrium.
And you'll just hover at that equilibrium.
And you stay there forever and ever,
long enough to evolve your species.
And that's an example of a small number.
The small number in this case being the luck
that your system happens to have a low density.
In fact,
lower than air.
Small number.
No fine tuning.
It didn't matter if it was helium or hydrogen.
And it wouldn't matter if it was
an equal mixture of helium or hydrogen.
You could have changed the parameters
of the gas quite a lot.
By several hundred percent,
you could have changed the...
As long as it stays lighter than air.
So there you're in luck
that there was a small number.
But there was no exceptional fine tuning of anything.
You didn't have to fine tune in any detail.
A percentage of hydrogen and helium.
So that's a small number.
Now let's talk about another situation.
This object is now not a blimp.
It is a submarine.
Yellow submarine.
We all live in a yellow submarine.
Submarine has no motor.
It just floats.
Down here,
the pressure is much too great for us to survive.
As it happens,
the atmosphere is highly poisonous.
And if we float to the top,
we're dead.
We have to stay in the water.
Maybe it doesn't matter so much
how high we are in the water.
But we've got to stay there.
Our submarine has existed in that
configuration long enough for us to evolve.
In other words,
for a billion years,
it has been hovering in the water.
Without falling or without rising.
We know that.
Because we're here.
All these people who live in a submarine are here.
And they know that if there
was any significant tendency to fall,
they'd be dead.
If there was any significant tendency to rise,
Let's assume for simplicity that the water has the same density
from the bottom of the sea to the top of the sea.
Which is very proximately true.
Very close to being true.
What do these people in the yellow submarine conclude?
They conclude that whatever the submarine is made out of,
the density of that submarine is finely tuned.
It's made out of some iron,
together with some brass,
and maybe a little bit of concrete,
and a few other things.
Plus,
it's hollowed out in the interior.
Its average density is such that...
Its average density is very,
very close to that of water.
If it was any denser than water,
it would sink.
If it was any lighter than water,
it would flow.
And what's more,
it's been sitting there at that
compromised position for a billion years.
From that,
you can conclude that whatever the chemical composition is,
it is very,
very finely tuned.
If you would change the ratio of iron to concrete,
by one part in a thousand,
or probably one part in a million...
Remember,
this thing has been sitting there for a billion years.
Or,
let's say,
four billion years,
or ten billion years.
It's been sitting there for ten billion years,
and it's right somewhere in the middle of the zone.
That's extraordinary.
That's extraordinary because there's no feedback mechanism
whereby it could start to sink.
It would rise.
If it started to rise,
it would sink.
No feedback mechanism.
If it's just a little bit too heavy,
it would just slowly sink to the bottom.
If it's a little too light,
it would slowly rise.
And so somebody,
very,
very fortunately,
has tuned the chemical composition
and the amount of hollowing out
and the weight of everything that's inside it
to one part in I don't know how much.
We can try to work it out,
but it's not important.
But it's important to take it to one part
in a fairly large number
to make sure that that submarine hovers.
Now,
the submariners are curious about this.
They want to know why is this true.
They have no explanation for it at all.
Their first reaction is,
this must be something like the dirigible,
the Zeppelin.
The Zeppelin had a feedback.
If the Zeppelin goes too high,
the air density goes down and it sinks back.
It goes too low,
it rises up again.
But they do a few calculations
and they realize there's no question
of that kind of feedback mechanism.
The density of water is too constant over this range
and there's no possibility of using that
to get a stability mechanism.
They try all kinds of mathematical tricks,
symmetry principles,
whatever you have.
Nothing works.
And the reason nothing works
is because this is one of these very fine-tuned things.
If you just change the chemical composition
a tiny bit this way
or a tiny bit that way,
the whole thing breaks down.
What kind of conclusion could they come to?
They do a little more calculation
using whatever laws they know
and they discover something very interesting
about the nature of the fluid that they're in.
The nature of the fluid that they're in
is that it has a instability.
It makes bubbles.
And the form of these bubbles is somewhat similar.
It's like a submarine.
Somewhere in the fluid,
bubbles nucleate.
And when the bubbles nucleate,
they morph into submarines.
But the trouble is the submarines
that they can nucleate into
are generally not of the right type.
In fact,
as it turns out,
the submarines can nucleate
with different chemical compositions.
Some of them have a little more brass.
Some of them have a little more iron.
A few of them have more hollowed out.
And there's a whole huge variety
of different species of submarine
that can nucleate.
They do.
They make these calculations.
And they discover this is a property
of the fluid that they live in.
You say,
ah,
I think I know the answer.
The answer must be that there must be
zillions of different kinds of submarines,
huge,
huge numbers of different kinds,
and moreover,
they keep nucleating and nucleating
and nucleating this fluid.
And so the fluid just keeps
producing more and more and more of them
of every conceivable type.
10% iron,
90% brass,
and all possible things in between.
And most of them either sink to the bottom,
they lie dead at the bottom,
or they rise to the top
and they poison the proto-inhabitants
that have time to...
And some tiny fraction of them,
some incredibly tiny fraction of them,
were nucleated with the right properties.
They were nucleated with the right properties
just because everything that could happen happened.
And so they are not particularly lucky.
They are just the ones that were in
the kind of submarines that...
that nucleated with exactly the right density to hover.
If all of that really happened,
and these people really had a genuine scientific reason
to believe in submarine nucleation in their city,
and they could see that the submarines could nucleate
with a vast variety of different types,
they would have what I would say
was a reasonable explanation of what's going on.
It's just a lot of stuff.
The sea is very big.
A long time has passed.
Every conceivable kind of thing is nucleated.
It's been nucleated many,
many times,
and they are just in
the kind where survival is possible.
That is the logic that I think the anthropic principle,
when it's rational,
is making use of.
That fine-tuning is a consequence
of many,
many,
many possibilities
and many actual events taking place,
creating the submarine that we live in,
so many so that some
fraction of them will be livable.
Then it becomes a non-mystery
about why we live in a fine-tuning universe.
That's a logic that I find,
personally,
I find acceptable.
If...
You know,
there are other possible answers.
The other possible answer is always the benevolence
that created the submarine
with exactly the right properties.
Uh...
There are some people who would like to believe that.
Most of my scientific friends don't think that
is an acceptable solution.
Um...
So,
what are the other possibilities?
And at this time,
right now,
here and now,
there are no other plausible possibilities
for why certain things are fine-tuned.
Okay,
now,
what is it that's playing the role
of this,
um...
uh...
the density of the submarine?
What's playing the role of the density of the submarine
is the cosmological constant.
If the cosmological constant is slightly negative,
the universe would re-collapse.
Now,
if it's sufficiently small,
that's like...
that's like the density of the submarine
being only a tiny bit different
than water.
If the cosmological constant is very small,
then it will take a
long time for it to re-collapse
in the same sense...
in a very,
very similar way to the way
it would take a long time for the submarine
to fall to the bottom of the sea
if the difference between water density
and,
um...
and submarine density were small.
Okay,
so,
um...
If the cosmological constant is small enough,
the universe lasts long enough...
assuming it's negative,
it lasts long enough without re-collapsing
for us to be here and to survive and,
uh...
and so forth.
On the other hand,
a cosmological constant could be positive,
in which case the universe doesn't crunch.
It expands,
and it expands in an exponential way.
But if it expands too fast,
if it expands,
uh...
too rapidly,
then it prevents structure.
It prevents structures from forming.
If the universe was accelerating very rapidly,
um...
an accelerated expansion,
then the material that's in it
would get carried along with the acceleration
and,
uh...
would simply be,
um...
incapable of contracting into galaxies,
stars,
and so forth.
So the sun window...
the sun window,
uh...
which is analogous to the window of densities.
So submarine densities,
where either positive or negative,
some new window,
where the submarine could last for a billion years.
Here,
it's a window between,
um...
collapse and destruction
on a time scale that
would not allow our own existence,
on the one hand,
and in the other direction,
uh...
lack of galaxies,
stars,
planets,
structures would form.
And that window is very,
very small.
The window is small because,
uh...
because time scales are so long.
The same reason the window is small for the,
uh...
for the submarine.
We have to be able to survive in this universe
for a period of time
which is very long,
uh...
and,
um...
that means
that the imbalances in the cosmological constant
have to be very,
very small.
Now,
there's another sense in which the cosmological constant
is like the,
uh...
the density of the submarine.
The density of the submarine
is made up out of some composite
of the densities of the
different materials that make it up
in various proportions.
It's not just that some number is small.
It's that some number is very,
very finely adjusted.
The same is true of the cosmological constant
in quantum field theory.
It gets contributions from many,
many different sources.
Basically,
it gets a contribution from every quantum field that exists.
Bosons give positive.
Fermions give negative.
The mass of the particles that
are associated with those quantum fields
shift them a little bit.
The cosmological constant that results from it
shifts a little bit.
And the whole thing,
all of the constants,
all of the particles,
all of the contributions,
all of the contributions to the cosmological constant
have to balance very finely
exactly the same way as the
density of the submarine has to balance.
If there's a little too much iron,
you're dead.
If there's a little too much brass,
you go up.
Same thing with the cosmological constant.
Put in an extra fermion species into the theory
and the cosmological constant gets too negative
and you implode.
Put in an extra boson,
the cosmological constant gets too big,
and you're out of luck at
a tiny fraction of a second.
So...
Question,
please.
What is the meaning of
making a change but that compensates?
Meaning it doesn't...
It's just a different submarine,
but still floating.
Yeah.
There are parameters in physics,
such as various masses and coupling constants.
You could change one thing
one way a little bit,
which might increase the cosmological constant,
and change something else another way a little bit,
which might decrease the cosmological constant,
and you might be able to...
It's not just that there's only one
chemical composition of the submarine that can survive.
There's just a very thin surface
in some space of different configurations.
That's the same thing here.
You can change things.
But you have to change them
in a very,
very fine-tuned way.
If you change one thing by this amount,
you have to change the other thing by that amount,
and it has to be adjusted to 123 decimal places.
So that's the...
So will this water that produces every kind of submarine
will make various submarines that have the same density
but look different than this?
So these are alternate universes?
Yeah.
Well,
they're all alternate universes,
but some of them are capable of sustaining themselves
for a long enough time.
Yeah.
You have people,
others are not.
Yeah.
You know,
we know very little about this.
I mean,
our knowledge of space of possibilities
is extremely limited.
We don't know very much about it.
String theory seems to say
that there are endless huge numbers of possibilities.
Analogous to every possible chemical composition.
So that's a plus.
I don't know whether to regard
that as a plus for string theory
or a plus for the entropic principle
or a plus for cosmology.
But it does seem to fit together with the idea.
And the fact is there is no other known explanation.
There's just nothing out there.
It's been many years now
that people have looked for explanations.
Oh,
there's one more thing.
Just a moment.
There's one more thing about the submarine.
Yeah.
These submariners might,
as I said,
they might start looking for mathematical explanations,
some symmetry of nature,
some symmetry of their equations,
which makes the submarine density exactly equal
to the surrounding water.
They think they have this
theory called rope theory or something.
I don't know.
Rope theory seems that they can't quite prove it.
But they have some idea,
they only have the right idea,
that rope theory would say that the submarines
always come out with exactly the right density of water.
Some symmetry between water and other things.
We've got it.
We don't quite understand it,
but we've got it.
We know there's some theory there.
If we could only understand that theory better,
it would tell us why the cosmological constant
or the density of submarines is exactly the right thing.
But then,
with their horror and dismay,
they discover that in their own submarine,
it's not exactly the right thing.
In fact,
the submarine is slowly sinking.
Oh,
my God.
It really is slowly sinking.
How long does it take for it to sink?
More than 10 billion years.
But their finest measurements tell them,
no,
it's not that things are perfectly adjusted.
We'll have to explain why they're perfectly adjusted.
They're not perfectly adjusted.
They're just adjusted to 123 decimal places.
And at the 124th decimal place,
they're sinking.
Excuse me.
Isn't this precision violating the uncertainty principle?
No.
Any one thing can be as accurate as your life.
Oh,
yes.
Question?
Yes.
When you gave this explanation,
you said,
this is an explanation of the anthropic principle
that I'm comfortable with.
Are there?
No,
I wouldn't say it's an explanation.
I would say it's a use of the anthropic principle
that I'm comfortable with,
say.
Right,
but what are some other uses
that you are not comfortable with?
Look,
I have no idea if there was an intelligence,
benevolent or not,
that created the universe.
I do not know and I don't pretend to know.
So are you saying that
others sort of give that spin
on things a little bit?
I suppose.
Not many scientists do.
Yeah.
At least at one time.
OK,
there are other uses of it
which I find much less compelling.
There are all sorts of models,
but there are also modest coincidences.
If any of them were not satisfied,
they might be enough to destroy life on Earth.
If we were to make
a list of the elementary particles,
we would find that almost all of the known ones,
almost all of them are necessary for our own existence.
On the other hand,
our understanding of particle physics
would allow just about any one of them
to not be there or other ones to be there.
For example,
I mean,
stop thinking about the particles
you know about.
A photon is the lightest.
Where would we be without a photon?
There would be no light,
no heat from the sun.
Worse than that,
there would be no photons jumping back and forth
between the atomic nucleus and
the electron to hold it together.
No chemistry,
we wouldn't be here.
What about no neutrinos?
No neutrinos,
there would be no nuclear reactions
of the kind which created the elements
from the time of the Big Bang.
So the existence of carbon and all these other elements
that make us up wouldn't be here without neutrinos.
What about no electrons?
Well,
no electrons is a clear disaster,
there's no question of that.
What about no quarks?
No quarks,
no protons,
neutrons.
What if you change the parameters a little bit?
What if you...
It was a puzzle for many
years and still is a puzzle.
Why the proton is lighter than the neutron?
In the early days of nuclear physics,
this was a great puzzle because the electron is charged.
You would have thought its electrostatic energy
would make it a little bit heavier than the neutron.
Neutrons and protons are twins.
They are almost exactly the same
with the exception that the proton
has a little bit of positive electric charge.
Ordinarily,
you would say that,
hey,
that increases its energy.
It takes energy to pull together a charge.
So that increases its energy.
Protons would be a little bit heavier than the neutron.
It would have been a disaster because if the proton
was heavier than the neutron,
the proton would decay into neutrons
instead of the neutron decaying into protons.
If the proton decayed into neutrons,
there would be no hydrogen.
There would be nothing.
We wouldn't be here.
So the little tiny difference between proton and neutron
is small,
which happens to go the wrong way
from expectations is absolutely essential
to our own existence.
All sorts of other...
フェインを見せる
What would happen if the electromagnetic coupling constant,
the fine structure constant,
which is one over 137,
what would happen if it was one over 10
instead of one over 137?
Well,
then the atom would be very,
very tightly bound,
and ordinary chemistry would probably go awry.
And what would happen if the electron
were heavier than the proton?
It would be buried deep
inside the center of the atom
instead of having a valence structure.
So you can look at physics as we know it,
which means largely particle physics,
and you can say,
you know,
there's so many different things
that you could have changed by 10,
20%,
or even 1% here and there,
and any one of them would have destroyed our existence.
I can easily imagine 1% accidents.
I can even imagine 10 1% accidents,
although it gets a little harder.
Are those accidents sufficient to really push us
in the anthropic direction?
I'm not gonna answer that.
I don't have an answer to that.
That's a matter of taste,
but the accidents of one
part of 10 to the 123,
or in some other case,
one part of 10 to the 60,
or something else having to do with the Higgs boson,
or one part of 10 to the 30,
I'm sorry,
one part of 10 to the 30,
those are not the kind of accidents
that you can imagine are accidental,
one part of 10 to the 60,
or 10 to the 120.
So I think if it wasn't for the cosmological constant
and the other fine-tuning,
comparable fine-tuning,
I think we would not be,
most serious physicists would be rejecting
the anthropic explanation.
Maybe not completely,
but not with the same support.
That doesn't mean that every physicist approves of it.
They just don't have another explanation.
Spinehart and some other guys in April
had a set of inflationary paradigm
and trouble after 2013.
Have you seen what they said?
They say basically most of the inflationary models
don't work.
Who said that?
Paul J.
Spinehart,
Abraham Lube.
Who said that?
Abraham Lube and Eloy B and Adam.
Okay,
these are contrarians.
The vast,
vast,
overwhelming majority
of cosmologists and physicists believe in inflation.
Now they said that plot 2013 results are in
and that they knock out most of the,
Well,
they didn't model the world.
Sure.
People make up a lot of wild models.
And then when good data comes in,
it knocks out most of the wild models
and leaves the sensible ones.
Nothing is done.
You have 500 models.
One of them is the gold standard model.
And the data comes in and knocks out 499.
Good.
Unfortunately,
it's not that good.
Sure.
Yeah,
no.
This bit,
no,
no.
There are people with axes
that could fit with the grind.
Physics is not a highly politicized subject.
It's not.
But here and there,
it does have people in it
who get very highly politicized about their own ideas.
And going around saying things like that,
I think,
is irresponsible,
frankly.
I would consider that.
I would consider that irresponsible.
I do consider it irresponsible.
Paul J.
Steinhardt is not the most responsible cosmologist.
Sorry,
Paul.
It's true.
Yes.
Would it also be possible for the cosmological concept
to vary in some sense,
perhaps,
over time?
So instead of having like a ..
There's no good theory in which it varies gradually.
It can vary in a jump.
It can vary in a jump if one of these,
if one of these submarines nucleates
with a different value of it.
Yes,
it can jump.
There's no good theory in which it varies smoothly
over such a long time scale,
slow enough to be consistent
with the data.
That was another theory,
a very,
very slowly varying
cosmological constant.
But it doesn't seem to fit with anything we know.
In any case,
it would require,
it turns out,
you know,
that they have a slowly varying version of it,
which
seconds down to zero,
requires a fine tuning
of several parameters,
not just one,
not just the vacuum
potential energy,
but several of its derivatives
have to be fine tuned.
So it's not a better explanation.
Look,
we don't know where this is going to go.
Nobody knows at present where it's going to go.
There are contrarians.
There are people.
There are people who have political agendas.
I don't.
I don't really.
I'm not the inventor of inflation.
I don't have a big stake in it.
I will not win a Nobel Prize if it's confirmed.
It is confirmed.
It's highly confirmed.
Somebody's going to win a Nobel Prize for it.
But it ain't going to be me.
The logic of it,
to me,
is extremely
compelling.
And I honestly cannot understand these people who
say that Planck data is ruling out inflation.
I think they are off base.
But why trust me?
Who am I?
Does that apply?
Does the anthropophic principle imply nucleation?
It fits together with it very well.
Now,
you could go back to the submarines.
You could.
that you could say,
well,
the anthropic principle itself,
all that says is we live in a submarine
which is of the right
type for us to live in.
And which is cause and which is effect.
Now,
what's cause and effect?
Do we explain the fact that we live
in the right kind of submarine
by the fact that we're here,
or do we explain the fact that we're here
by the fact that we live
in the right kind of submarine?
I prefer the latter.
That we can understand why we're here
as a consequence of there being enough
right kinds of submarines,
rather than to say the opposite,
that we can explain the properties of submarines
by the fact that we are here.
That seems backward.
Seems scientifically backward to put us
at the center of the
laws of nature to that extent.
Yeah,
I guess I think a misuse of it
is going to be a misuse
of the fact that we're here.
We've tried to start explaining why the laws of nature
have to be the way
they are because we are here.
It seems to me much less egregious to say
that the laws of nature are highly variable,
which theories tend to suggest anyway.
Highly variable,
environments are highly variable,
and that we live in a temperate zone
for the same reason that we all live in Antarctica.
It's just too damn cold there.
It's too cold.
The real question,
look,
the real question is,
apart from the fact that it's nine o'clock,
the real question is how are we gonna find out?
The agenda of those who hate the idea
and who love the idea should be exactly the same.
Take it seriously enough to either kill it
or make it into science.
The fact is that it looks very,
very hard to do either.
It looks extremely hard to find signatures
of this kind of thing in data
which would either kill it or confirm it.
That's the real problem.
The problem is not that it's bad philosophy
or that it's religious or that it,
one of my friends seems
to think it's a terrible thing
to propose because young people will,
you know,
their minds will be deformed by it
and they will stop thinking about other explanations.
Okay,
these are political reasons.
These are,
oh,
other people think it's a bad idea
because it enables the religious right to say,
ah,
the world was created,
though,
just the right properties.
None of these are science.
That's not science.
The scientific question is,
is it true or is it not true?
And if it is true or not true,
how do you find out?
How do you find confirming evidence?
It's hard.
In other words,
you want to try to observe
other submarines nucleating.
Right,
right.
So if you're very lucky or unlucky,
as the case may be,
you might bump into another submarine
that could be either lucky or not lucky.
I mean,
it's lucky if it doesn't kill you
and you find out that
there are other submarines out there
and you confirm and you win a Nobel Prize.
Or it could be bad.
The submarine could make a hole in your submarine
and then you sink to the bottom.
Right.
Still a good one.
In principle,
there could be collisions
between regions of space with different properties.
It's expected to be extremely rare.
Computation seems to say that it's extremely rare.
Basically,
computation seems to say that the ocean is
exceedingly big,
but the nucleation of submarines
is very rare.
It doesn't happen very often.
It doesn't happen very often and very frequently.
And so most submarines will last a long time
without bending into a middle one.
So we found no evidence in the cosmic microwave background
for a collision like this.
None.
There's no evidence.
It's probably not going to be there.
So the only question is then,
what other possible kinds
of signatures could there be for the physics that
goes into this kind of theory?
It's hard.
Nobody has a really good idea.
That's the worst thing about this kind of idea,
that it just looks overwhelmingly hard to find
the convincing data for.
OK.
We are finished.
Thank you.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.