Stanford University.
Let's start with some philosophy. Let's start with some general philosophical principle. It's
a principle that philosophers call reductionism. Reductionism is the principle or the philosophy
that big things are made out of little things and little things are made out of littler things.
That's one element of reductionism. How many people would agree with reductionism here? Yeah,
I mean, you know, molecules are made out of atoms, atoms are made out of electrons and nuclei,
nuclei are made out of protons and neutrons, protons and neutrons are made out of quarks
and gluons and so forth.
I call that the building block theory that houses are made out of brick,
bricks are made out of molecules, and nobody in their right mind mistakes a house for a brick,
right, we all know the bricks from the houses, the bricks are smaller than the houses,
they're also simpler than the houses. So that's another element of reductionism. As you go deeper
and deeper into the legal scene, you'll see that the effects of reductionism is very much similar to
the effects of reductionism. You can see how the prices are different in a few of the questions
layers of reductionism, things get simpler, or at least we hope they do.
That's a pious hope of reductionism. I think from what we've learned both
from string theory, from the quantum mechanics of gravity, and so forth, that
modern theories really do spell the end of reductionism. But before you end
reductionism, it's interesting to ask how well it does as a philosophy and as a
as a theory of elementary particles. If reductionism is right, particularly in
that aspect which has to do with simplicity as you go deeper and deeper,
you might have expected that by now elementary particle physics would be
pretty simple. We've gone several several layers and
is it's simple? The answer is no. It is very very complicated, and to measure
how complicated it is, you can simply ask how many different kinds of particles
are there, and in particular, particles which are unexplained. Well there's
something like about 75 different particles, all of which, in the
standard model of particle physics, and the standard model
of particle physics, maybe only about 20 or maybe even a little bit less than
that independent particles that don't have tight relationships between each
other. So it's maybe 10 to 15 or 20 distinct different particles depending
on how you count. How many parameters? Parameters again mean unexplained
constants that have to go into the theory to make sense out of it. Well,
about 20, 20 distinct parameters, but the theory is definitely incomplete. We know
that it's incomplete. It doesn't have gravity, it doesn't have dark matter, it
doesn't have the particles that are necessary for inflation, the theory of
cosmic inflation to make sense, and it has a terrible fine-tuning problem. We've
talked about that fine-tuning problem.
That in order to overcome this fine-tuning problem, people introduced
things like supersymmetry. My guess is that supersymmetry will really be
discovered at the LHC. But if it does, it adds about 100 new parameters ...
Well, I take that back. It's a hundred plus n, where n is an unknown number, but
...
That n is now zero because it's necessary for understanding the breaking of supersymmetry,
why supersymmetry is not a real...
Another hundred parameters, a doubling of the number of all of the particles,
plus a whole bunch of stuff that's necessary for inflation and other things.
By the time you're finished, the standard model of particle physics,
together with all of the bells and whistles that have to be added to understand everything, let's say,
is a theory with about 200 parameters, huge number of particles, and totally unexplained connections.
So it's not simple. It's very, very complicated.
And complicated... either you have to say,
well, we haven't gotten anywhere near the bottom yet,
or we just have to...
admit that maybe reductionism isn't working.
But the fact, the idea that reductionism isn't working,
that's not what I meant when I said modern theories sort of spell the end of reductionism.
What I meant was a more theoretical fact.
A more theoretical fact based on both quantum field theory and string theory.
So I'll tell you a little bit about what is known.
In particular, about the idea...
that endlessly... well, not necessarily endlessly,
but that we can always tell the bricks from the houses.
Is it really always true that we can tell which thing is more fundamental than which thing?
I'm going to give you a couple of examples of places where in quantum field theory
that idea has broken down, broken down badly.
The first example was an example of a very simple kind.
I'm not going to explain this. I'm just going to tell you about it.
It was studying the quantum field theory of one-dimensional systems.
Models. Models in which there was time and only one dimension of space.
Very easy to draw. A dimension of space and a dimension of time.
And that's all there is.
And particles.
What was discovered is that there's a very simple kind of theory.
It's just simple. There are a number.
Just, in fact, almost every theory of this type
can be described in terms of particles which are fermions.
Remember what fermions are?
Fermions are particles that satisfy the Pauli exclusion principle.
They're the particles which have this odd behavior that they can't go into the state.
You can't put two of them into the same state.
Electrons are fermions. Quarks are fermions.
Photons are not fermions. They're bosons.
The opposite of a fermion is a boson.
And all particles are either fermions or bosons.
So in this mathematical theory,
you start with some particles which are fermions.
The fermion field, the object which describes the fermions,
which creates and annihilates the fermions,
we call psi.
The mathematical terminology is not important.
But it's important.
The mathematical terminology is not important here.
What is important is that the basic starting point
is a field theory of fermions.
Now, what happens if you put two fermions together?
What do you make?
Zero.
The bosons.
If you put two of them, identical ones together, you make zero.
But supposing two not quite identical ones,
one sort of right next to the other but not right on top of it,
then you make a boson.
Okay?
For example, protons are fermions,
electrons are fermions,
hydrogen atoms are bosons.
Okay?
So you take a fermion and a boson,
two fermions, and you put them together,
almost together.
Maybe there's some attractive force between them
which holds them together.
And these particles, which are now composites,
they're clearly composites,
they can move up and down.
They're also particles, but they're composites.
They're composite particles.
Those composite particles are bosons,
and bosons are also described by fields.
You would think that it's not really a fundamental field.
You would think that it's a field
that is some effective description
of the two particles stuck together.
And you call it phi.
Phi creates bosons.
It creates pairs of these fermions.
That sounds very straightforward.
But what was then discovered in these field theories
is that you could rewrite exactly the same field theory
in terms of an underlying starting point
which started with the bosons.
Let's draw that field theory over here.
Now you start with the bosons.
The fermions cannot be composites of the bosons
because any number of bosons put together
make another boson.
But these fermions can be described in a totally new way.
They're described if we plot,
this is not plotting time anymore,
this is plotting the field phi
as what's called a kink in the field phi.
A place where the field phi jumps,
smoothly jumps,
doesn't jump suddenly.
It smoothly jumps over a distance,
some distance,
jumps from one value to another.
It's called a kink.
If you want a picture of it,
I should have taken off my belt.
Well, I won't take off my belt.
But imagine my belt.
Here it is.
And here I've laid it out on the blackboard
so that it's not twisted.
That's got no kink.
Now take the belt and twist it.
Rotate this end around by two pi
so it's twisted once.
It comes back to its original configuration over here,
its original configuration over here,
but in between it's twisted.
That's a kink.
That's a kink in my belt.
I often do that when I put my belt on
and then discover two hours later
when I'm talking to somebody
that my belt is on wrong.
That's called a kink.
The bizarre thing is that these fermions
that we thought we started with,
the bricks which built the houses,
the fermion bricks which built the boson houses,
can now be re-represented as kinks
in the boson field.
Kinks which are extended, thick, and massive,
much heavier than the bosons.
Which are the houses?
Which are the bricks?
Nobody can say.
It's entirely equivalent.
There are parameters in such a theory.
Field theories have parameters.
It turns out that for some values of the,
some ranges of the parameters,
it's much more convenient
to think of the fermions
as the fundamental building blocks.
And for another range of the parameters,
the bosons are much more efficient
at studying the theory,
and they are the more useful building blocks.
It simply becomes a matter of which is more useful.
Is it more useful to think of psi,
the fermions,
or phi, the bosons,
as the fundamental objects of the theory?
And that depends on the parameters.
That depends on a coupling constant.
A coupling constant that's usually called G.
It doesn't matter what it's called.
So,
starting with very small G,
you discover that it's much more useful
to think of the fermions as the starting point.
Easy to deal with.
Easy to study.
These things are composites
that are held together by complicated forces.
Now you start changing this coupling constant,
and increasing it and increasing it.
Oh, incidentally,
when that G is very small,
uh,
let's see,
that kink is,
um,
very tight.
Very small like that.
Now you start changing the cou-
and that's why the fermion is a small object.
The fermion is a small object because it's a small kink.
Now you start tuning the coupling constant,
making it stronger and stronger.
What happens is the kink starts to spread out,
it gets less and less point-like,
but the boson starts to behave more and more
like a simple elementary object.
So the question of which is fundamental
and which is composite
doesn't have a unique answer.
By varying the constants,
you can make,
you can morph,
you can make one thing go into the other.
The houses go into the bricks, so to speak.
Um,
that was a case that was known,
oh gee,
since I was a very young physicist,
um,
the key word is called bosonization.
It's making a fermion out of bosons,
or form bosons out of fermions.
Are there any things like this in elementary particle physics?
It is believed that there are.
And the belief centers around
electric and magnetic monopoles.
Let me tell you what an electric and magnetic monopole is.
An electric monopole,
could be an electron,
could be any charged particle,
ordinary charged particle,
surrounded by an electric field,
usual electric field.
And let's take these,
let's take the particle to be,
let's say an electron.
The electric charge of an electron
is very weak as a matter of fact.
It's a very weak electric charge.
The amount of charge,
and not just because the electron is small,
that's actually not the issue.
There's a dimensionless quantity.
What's a dimensionless quantity called?
Anybody know?
The fine structure constant?
The fine, yeah.
The fine structure constant is a measure
of how much an electron would radiate
if you, you know, if you accelerated it suddenly.
Or if you plowed it into a,
an anode.
If you plowed it into a stop,
into a, you know,
a field,
how much would it radiate?
How many photons would it radiate?
The answer is that an electron
will radiate on the average
about 1 over 100 photons.
Another way of saying it
is that the electron will only radiate
about 1 out of 100 times
when it's stopped,
radiate a photon.
So the electron charge is very weak.
And the electron is very simple.
The electric field around it is rather,
is rather weak,
because the electric charge is weak.
And it doesn't do very much
to the neighboring space around it.
It doesn't polarize the vacuum.
It doesn't create electron positron pairs
to any appreciable amount.
Electron is simple.
It is also believed that in nature
there do exist magnetic monopoles.
Most physicists like myself believe
in the existence of magnetic monopoles.
They,
they come up in so many theories
that by now,
they,
but they've never been discovered.
They've never been discovered
in the laboratory.
A magnetic monopole
is like the end of a bar magnet.
North,
south.
If you just imagine the end
of the bar magnet
with the bar magnet itself being so thin
that you couldn't see it,
then waving around the bar magnet
would look like waving around
a magnetic monopole
where the magnetic field comes out
of the magnetic monopole
exactly the same way the electric field
comes out of the electric monopole.
The amount of the monopoles
that theoretical physics seems to produce
have a magnetic charge
which is huge,
very large.
The force between two magnetic monopoles
would be 10,000 times larger
than the force between two electrons
at the same distance.
That means that the magnetic monopoles
make large fields around them
and do very, very complicated things,
make a very complicated mess around them.
That complicated mess is extended,
it's broad,
the same way that the kink was broad,
and it's massive.
It's very, very heavy
because there's so much going on
in the vicinity of the monopole.
I'm not really talking about
the end of a bar magnet.
I'm talking about the end of the bar magnet
without the bar magnet,
magnetic monopoles.
They haven't been discovered in the laboratory
because they're too heavy to make.
Will they ever be discovered?
Perhaps.
But most theorists believe in them.
But the point is,
the more important point is,
the mathematics of quantum electro-economy
is that the mathematical definition
of quantum electrodynamics,
which contains monopoles and electrons,
is totally unclear about which of them
is the elementary particle.
It depends on the fine structure constant.
It depends on alpha,
the fine structure constant.
If the fine structure constant,
which is basically the square
of the electric charge of the electron,
if that's much, much less than one,
then the electron is the simple one.
It's simple.
It's almost point-like.
It has very little structure.
The charge is very weak.
The monopole has a very, very complicated
structure in that limit.
The magnetic field is very powerful
and does very complicated things
to space around it.
And that's why it's heavy.
What happens if you could imagine now
that you had a dial,
that you could start dialing,
redialing the fine structure.
What happens if you could imagine now
that you had a dial,
that you could start dialing,
redialing the fine structure constant?
Start increasing it.
What happens as you start to increase it?
The field surrounding the electron
becomes stronger.
Effectively, the electric charge
is getting larger.
The field is getting stronger.
It starts to do more complicated things
in the vicinity of the electron.
What happens to the magnetic monopole?
Well, I can explain easily.
But the fact is,
it starts to shrink.
It gets smaller and smaller.
It gets lighter and lighter.
The electron gets heavier and heavier
as alpha gets large.
When alpha gets bigger than one,
they simply interchange.
The magnetic monopole
becomes light and small
and fundamental.
The electron would become heavy,
complicated,
and hard to understand.
And full of all kinds of structure.
And basically, they would just
interchange themselves.
So again,
which is the building block?
Is it the electron,
whose
complicated structure here
is making up the monopole?
Or is it the monopole,
which is simple, and whose complicated structure
is making up the electron?
Modern quantum field theories
say they're equivalent.
You can't tell the difference.
You may want to choose one of them
as the starting point,
depending on the fine structure constant.
It may be more convenient
to think of the electron as fundamental,
and less convenient to think about the monopole.
And that, of course, is true.
And that's why we use electrons
as starting points for quantum electrodynamics
and not monopoles.
Yeah?
Going back to your philosophical point,
if,
if there's a belief that reductionism
is not the
correct view of things,
why do physicists use calculus,
which is the most reductionist
of mathematical tools,
to constantly...
Calculus is not necessarily reductionist.
It just says everything is smooth,
smoothly varying.
But it doesn't in any way
tell you what the fundamental objects
are of theory.
But with, like, a derivative,
you chop it up into teeny,
weeny little points,
and then you...
Right.
You chop up the things into little distances,
and you ask, what's in those little distances?
And that tells you what
the fundamental things are.
Okay?
In quantum field theory,
it's just an endless hierarchy
of distance scales.
And so, you never get
to the point where you can decide
which one is fundamental.
Hmm?
Like a fractal?
Yeah, pretty much like a fractal.
For example, describing a curve,
you can use it using a derivative,
or one of the few non-reductionist
models is
general relativity, where you describe it
as a geodesic on your...
Quantum fields fluctuate,
and they fluctuate on every scale.
So they're never smooth.
They're never smooth.
Never smooth.
And in some sense,
some of the great difficulties of
understanding quantum field theory,
the reasons that mathematicians
have so much trouble with it,
is sort of because in a certain sense,
calculus does break down.
In studying the fields,
they fluctuate too much, they vary too much.
But, uh,
let's not get into that now.
Alright, now what does string theory say?
Does string theory have an answer
to what are the fundamental
building blocks?
Well, obviously string theory has an answer
for what the fundamental building blocks is.
It must be strings, right?
Okay, so let me tell you a little bit about...
We talked about D-brains, yes?
Alright, so I will just very quickly
just remind you
what a D-brain is.
We don't need to know a lot about the mathematics.
Pictures are good enough.
D-brains are objects that were
discovered through a fairly
indirect mathematical route.
They are part of the theory.
You can't get rid of them.
You're stuck with it.
They're objects which are, first of all,
very heavy.
They could be...
They come in different dimensionality.
The simplest one is called
the D-zero brain.
And zero stands for the dimension...
What's the dimension of a point?
The dimensionality of a point?
First of all, what's the dimensionality of a line?
One dimension.
The dimensionality of a
membrane or a two-dimensional surface?
Two.
What's the dimensionality of a point?
Zero.
So in that sense,
particles...
point particles are called
zero-dimensional objects.
Even if they're not absolute points,
they're still regarded as
zero-dimensional.
They are not extended
in higher dimensions.
So a particle is
a D-zero brain.
The word brain, incidentally,
B-R-A-N-E,
brain comes from membrane.
A membrane, a surface, is a two-brain.
Or a two-brain.
A two-dimensional brain.
What's a string?
A one-brain.
What's a three-dimensional block of
solid stuff?
What's a three-dimensional block of solid stuff?
It's a three-brain.
And can you picture a four-brain?
No, we don't have enough directions to put it into.
But if we had more directions,
we could make four-brains.
Alright, so a D-zero brain is a kind of
particle.
The D stands for the mathematician
Dirichlet, and it's not important.
But the property of these D-brains
in string theory is that they are
places where strings can end.
Fundamental strings.
Let's call them F-strings.
This is an F-string, F standing
for fundamental.
The building blocks, the things that gravitons
are made out of.
All the good stuff that we've talked about up till now.
The fundamental strings.
And D-zero brains are just sites
on which a fundamental string can end.
In fact, any number of fundamental
strings can end on a D-zero brain.
And that means
that these zero brains can have
strings attached to them.
And they typically do.
If you were to probe a D-zero brain,
by scattering something
off it, you would find out
that it has a collection of strings
attached to it like that.
In fact, the harder you probed it, the more string
you would find closer and closer in,
and you would eventually come to the conclusion
that the D-brain is in some sense
made up out of strings.
But it's got a lot of strings.
And it's heavy.
It's much, much heavier
than the ordinary
strings themselves. It's a little core
that's very massive,
and that core is a place where strings
can end.
The mathematics that went into this,
through its discovery and so forth, is less interesting
than the fact that these things are necessarily
forced to exist. They're massive,
they're complicated,
and they
are there.
They're in the theory.
Now, that's a D-zero brain.
There are also D-one brains.
A D-one brain
is like a string.
I just want to thicken
it out, because it's
much heavier than an ordinary string,
much more mass per unit length,
but it also has the property
that it's a place where ordinary strings,
fundamental strings, can end.
And so again,
it's kind of a
an object which is
made up out of these strings,
a sort of cable,
a cable, a thick cable,
a thick cable,
much thicker than the ordinary strings,
and much heavier,
heavier in the sense that per unit length,
its mass is much larger.
Very much
in a sense, well, let's draw two strings
next to each other. Here's a D-string,
and here's
an F-string. A D-zero, a D-zero,
a D-one brain
can also be called
a D-string.
Here's an F-string,
a fundamental string. It's thin,
it's narrow, it's light.
These two objects are related
in very much the same way
that
this one and this one
are related in very much the same way as
can you guess what I'm going to say next?
Monopoles and a light.
Electrons.
The fundamental strings are like the electrons,
the building blocks, the starting point
for string theory. These objects
are big, heavy, composite
structures which are made out of
cables of lots of string.
They're heavy, and they're obviously
composite.
String theory has,
I said it has no parameters.
Now we're going to come back to whether,
we're going to come back in a minute to the question
of whether it has parameters or not.
For practical purposes
for the moment, it does have a parameter.
The parameter is a coupling constant.
Let's call it G.
G is a coupling constant,
a parameter of the theory,
which basically tells you the probability
that if a string is wiggling around
it might split in half.
It's very
similar in many ways to the probability
that an electron, when accelerated,
will emit a photon.
String wiggling around
if you grab a piece of it
and pull it, it might,
it can break. The probability
for that is called the coupling constant.
If the coupling
constant is very small,
then the F strings are light,
they're thin, and they look
very fundamental, point-like.
Well, not point-like, but line-like.
When G is
very small, the D string is very
heavy, very complicated,
and full
of F strings.
Guess what happens
as you start increasing G?
As you start increasing G,
the fundamental string here
tends to break off little pieces.
Those little pieces don't
disappear and fly off, they hang
around, and they form a kind of
I don't know what to call it, an atmosphere
around the fundamental
string.
And the fundamental string gets
more and more complicated.
In the same way that the electron
got complicated when you started to
increase the fine structure constant,
the fundamental string starts
to develop structures.
At the same
time, well,
at the same time, the D string
starts to get simpler.
The fundamental string gets heavier.
Because it gets heavier, it gets harder
and harder for the D string to produce
fundamental string, and so
these structures get
thinned out. As they get
thinned out, the D string gets thinner
and thinner. Eventually
at some point, when G
is about one, they
start to look exactly like each other.
And then if you
go to even larger coupling constant,
the D string gets very
simple, turns into a
thin, line-like object,
and the fundamental string just gets
as complicated as the D string
was originally.
Which one describes,
or which one of these strings
when they form little loops
create particles,
create gravitons,
create photons, and so forth?
Well, if G is
much less than one, then
the fundamental strings
when they
close back on themselves
form the particles,
the ordinary particles of
string theory.
But as G gets larger and larger,
these things get more and more massive,
in fact eventually
they turn into black holes,
and what's left over
is the D strings, which
get lighter and lighter, and the graviton
is made up out of the D strings.
This is called
D string
fundamental string duality.
It's not the usual name for it.
It's usually called S-duality. I do not know what S stands for.
I didn't make up the term.
I don't know why it's called.
Oh, strength duality.
Strength.
Yeah, strength of the coupling constant.
So, again,
we find this pattern
that you can't say
once and for all which thing is more
fundamental than which. You just find
them morphing into each other.
Now they morph into each other as the
coupling constant varies.
But at least you could say, well,
at least you can say that if the coupling constant
is small, then it's
profitable to think of the fundamental
strings as fundamental.
If the coupling constant is very
large, switch them.
The problem with that is the coupling
constant is something that can vary in space.
It's a field.
G
in string theory is not a constant.
It's a
thing which can vary from place to place.
It satisfies
field equations
just like the gravitational
field.
And so
you can easily have a situation
in the
mathematically idealized string theory
where the coupling constant
goes from very strong to very weak
as you move across the universe.
And in one place,
the D strings are fundamental,
in the other place, the F strings are fundamental.
And in between, nothing is simple.
That's the character of string theory.
Question?
On a cosmological scale,
I mean, if it varied
or became
less massive than F, wouldn't that have
an effect on spectra and such?
Yeah. Absolutely.
That's how we know, that's one of the ways
we know that string theory, the
mathematically precise version of string
theory is not our world.
Another question?
So is there a dual for like the
E2 brain?
We'll talk about the E2 brain.
And there's a dual, like a
fundamental dual for that.
Yeah.
Just trying to get it straight in my mind,
the greater likelihood of splitting
makes complexity in the upstream?
Is that what?
Yeah.
Let's go back to quantum
electrodynamics for a minute.
Now my vertical axis is time,
and here's an electron
world line.
And I'm going to do
a little bit of a
little bit of a
it's a point.
That means it's a very thin world line.
It's not a string.
Vertical, remember, vertical for a physicist
always means time.
Horizontal means space.
So here's a point electron
moving
through time, so to speak.
That point electron
emits
and absorbs photons.
Now, when the fine
structure constant is very small,
the emission
and absorption of photons
is very intermittent, meaning
to say
that there aren't very many of these
photons being emitted.
What about the photons
themselves? Well,
a photon
can create and annihilate
an electron positron pair.
So that means
that the photons
can create electron
positron pairs.
But now each one of these
little electrons here
can also emit photons.
There's a sort of
unending hierarchy at
smaller and smaller distance scale
of structure
within the electron.
As long as
the coupling constant is weak,
this is a relatively small
effect. In fact, it's a small effect
and the electron
in the laboratory looks pretty darn
point-like.
You have to work very hard
to scatter things off it
and see that the electron has this
composite structure there.
Where does the energy come from?
It's, uh,
it's, um, where does the energy
come from?
Uh, the energy
the energy
the energy needed for this
process is part of
the mass of the proton, or
the mass of the electron.
It's part of the mass
of the electron.
It is the mass of the electron.
Where did the energy come from
to create the Coulomb field around the electron?
Well, the point is
you don't start without the Coulomb field.
The Coulomb field was always there.
Yes.
But, uh,
I don't
I see things much
simp-
not accurately enough.
I see two electron
pair being produced.
Uh, and I don't see the mass
of the electron enough to produce an electron pair.
Would it help if I said that virtual pairs?
Well,
I mean, obviously
you know, you skin by
the skin of your teeth, virtual.
No, but mass and energy are the same thing
and so when you say the mass of the electron
you're basically including the energy
needed to do this kind of stuff.
Alright, but what is that energy?
That energy is a kind of potential energy.
Uh,
that's connected with the
interactions between the electrons
and the photons.
The energy of a system
in quantum electrodynamics is not
just the energy of the electrons
plus the energy of the photons.
There's also an interaction energy between them.
And that's the, that interaction
energy is the source of this.
But, uh,
alright, but it's, you know,
it's an empirical fact
that if you scatter things off an electron,
at high enough energy,
you will see
this structure around the electron.
Yes, but see if you scatter it with enough energy
then I can see that the energy
of your experiment
will produce what you see.
Well, okay, we can debate
whether the
energy of the experiment is producing
what you see or whether it's seeing
what you see.
Um,
we can debate that, but the fact of the
matter is that when you scatter things
off the electron, what happens
is complicated.
What happens is, well, it's not so complicated.
Most of the times you don't see anything.
About 1%
of the time you see, uh, some stuff.
On the,
on d-brains,
uh, you said that, uh,
for a couple of constants small, you said
the, uh, the mass of the
d-1 brain is
more than the mass of the f-string.
Yeah.
And would the tension also be more
or do you still... Yeah, yeah, the tension, the mass means
the tension, uh, the tension means the mass per
unit length. Okay. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
So mass per unit length is called the tension.
Right, exactly.
Energy per unit length. Alright, now,
um,
as I said,
as the, as the fine structure
constant starts to get bigger and bigger,
this structure starts to
proliferate, and the result
is that the electron develops
this very complicated
structure.
It's no longer something which is
very rare or very, uh, dilute.
The electron gets
big, gets heavy, gets all the structure
there. Very, very
similar thing happens to a string.
What, uh,
what is this coupling constant g?
This coupling constant is the
probability that if the
string fluctuates,
if it undergoes a
quantum fluctuation,
let's say
into a configuration like that,
then it's basically the probability
that the string splits off
and forms a little,
uh, sort of satellite string
around the original string.
As
the coupling constant gets larger and larger,
a very similar thing
happens. The satellite
strings start to proliferate,
and they form
a structure surrounding
the string the same way that the electron-positron
pairs and the photons surrounded
the electron. They make it heavier,
they give it a structure,
uh, and, uh, the result
is that the f-string
starts to look more and more like the d-string.
In the meantime,
the d-string has
more and more trouble
emitting or
producing
f-strings. Why?
Because those f-strings are getting heavier and heavier.
And the result is
that the d-string gets less
and less structure.
And becomes more like the f-string.
So that's
another example
of a duality.
These things are called dualities.
Uh, this one's called s-duality.
The name is not important.
Um,
and it interchanges
fundamental strings with d-strings.
The mathematics of this by now
is very tight,
even though, uh, I'm not trying
at all to give you the mathematics.
Now,
um,
there are different versions
of string theory.
The mathematics of them is
not so important, but there are different versions.
In one version,
all of the d-brains
are odd-dimensional.
So, that means that there are
d-1-brains, d-3-brains,
d-5-brains. How do you stick a d-5
brain into space? We don't have enough
dimensions of space.
Well,
remember that string theory is fundamentally
a 10-dimensional theory.
You've got a lot of extra dimensions.
String theory has enough
dimensions that you can put in things
up to about 8 brains.
Uh, and then you run out of
directions to put the brains in.
So,
one version of string theory,
the mathematics tells you that they're
must be d-1,
d-3, d-5, d-7 brains.
In another
version of string theory, which is
closely related, but different,
there are even-dimensional
brains.
No string theory has both
odd-dimensional d-brains and
even-dimensional. It's just a fact.
That no version of it has both.
Not, this is by no means
transparent. I'm telling you facts
more than I'm telling you explanations.
Uh,
it would take many hours of mathematics
to explain why that's true,
but nevertheless, this is a fact.
So let's go to the version of
string theory which has
even-dimensional brains instead of
odd-dimensional.
It doesn't have d-strings.
It has d-0 brains.
It has point-like particles,
which are not quite point-like,
but which are very complicated
and full of string theory
that are very complex.
And, uh,
it has a string,
and it also has fundamental strings
that make gravitons and so forth.
That's the description
when the coupling constant g
is much, much less than one.
This theory does something
very different
as g starts to get large.
It was a great puzzle that nobody knew the answer to.
What happens
to these objects
as g starts to get large?
This can't become this.
This is a point-like thing.
This is a string which could be spread out all over the place.
There are different kinds of creatures.
It's not the case that one will go
back and forth into the other.
That's not the way it works.
Something much more bizarre happens.
So I will tell you.
Let's see.
Before I tell you, I have to...
Um...
All right, I'm going to tell you what happens.
And perhaps, uh,
in the second hour
I can tell you why,
or what it means for it to happen.
What happens
is that a new dimension,
as g gets large,
a new dimension of space materializes.
Now that's crazy.
That's the silliest thing I ever heard.
A new dimension of space materializes.
How can a dimension of space materialize?
Well, it can't.
But what can happen
is a very small, compact direction
can start to expand.
I'm going to show you how it works
to some extent,
but let's just begin with that.
Let's take ordinary space
to start with
to be two-dimensional.
Just for pictures.
Really, we're talking about
ten-dimensional space.
Ten-dimensional string theory.
Let's take ordinary space...
How many directions of space
does ten-dimensional string theory have?
No. Nine.
The tenth dimension is time.
Right. Okay.
So when somebody tells you
ten-dimensional string theory,
they're talking about a theory with nine dimensions of space.
Okay.
So let's take a theory with two dimensions of space,
just because I can draw it on the blackboard.
It's not the right theory,
but let's just draw it on the blackboard.
Here's two dimensions of space.
Now, maybe secretly,
that two-dimensional space
is really three-dimensional.
How could it really be three-dimensional?
It could be three-dimensional
because this...
because there could be a thickness to it.
We could imagine a world
sort of a peanut butter sandwich.
With a piece of bread on this side,
a piece of bread on this side,
the bread being infinitely thin,
and the peanut butter being real space in between.
But with a special rule.
The special rule is
that when
an object goes out here,
it reappears at the bottom.
That's the idea of compactification,
of periodicity.
That there really isn't an edge to it.
But when you go out one end,
when you go out on the top piece of bread,
you reappear on the bottom piece of bread.
Then there's no real edge.
Somebody moving vertically
would not notice the edge
because when he got to the top piece of bread
he would just reappear at the bottom piece of bread.
All right.
That's the idea of
one compact dimension.
Now, if the compact dimension
was small enough,
it might not be a problem.
It might not be noticeable to the physicists
that live in this world
that the direction has a little,
that there's this extra dimension.
That this direction has some,
that there's some thickness to the world
along a direction that they didn't notice.
So they would call this world
two-dimensional.
What happens
as G starts to increase
is that
the peanut butter sandwich gets thicker
and thicker and thicker.
And eventually,
when G gets very large,
a whole new dimension
of space materializes
which the physicists
who lived in here
would not be able to ignore anymore.
They would have discovered
that they really live in a world
with an extra dimension.
That is what happens to this theory.
This theory that has D0 brains
and strings.
Now you say, well,
what happens to the D0 brains?
The D0 brains
start getting lighter
and lighter.
Just the same way that the D1 brains did
when G gets large.
They start getting lighter and lighter and lighter.
More and more
simple. But what do they turn into?
They turn
into the gravitons
in this extra dimensional theory.
Just the ordinary gravitons.
The ordinary gravitons
are ordinary elementary particles
that live in this extra dimensional theory.
This new theory
is now 11 dimensional.
We thought it was string theory
with only 10 dimensions.
And when we started increasing this coupling constant
we discovered another dimension of space.
And these D0 brains
just turned into the gravitons
that exist in here.
In other words,
again, very, very complicated
objects turn into
very simple light objects.
Let me tell you what happens to the strings.
To understand the strings,
go back to the thin sandwich.
Go back to the very thin sandwich.
Now remember,
I told you that this theory has even
dimensional brains.
Zero is even.
So it has D0 brains.
But it also has D2 brains,
D4 brains, D6 brains.
But concentrate in particular on D2 brains.
What does a D2 brain mean?
It means a membrane.
You could have two kinds
of membranes
stuck into this sandwich.
A membrane
simply means
a surface. A surface of energy.
You could stick in a membrane
in between
the floor and the ceiling.
In between the two pieces of bread.
Sort of embedded in the peanut butter.
Or if you liked,
you could think of the top piece of bread
as the ceiling,
the bottom piece of bread as the floor,
and then the two brains stuck in between
would be a floating magic carpet
that just hovered
halfway in between.
That's one kind of D2 brain
you could have.
There's another kind that you could have.
It's a kind of ribbon.
Let's see if I can draw it.
It goes from the floor
to the ceiling.
But it's a ribbon
sort of stretched between
the floor and the ceiling vertically,
which is extended
in the other direction.
So it's a string.
What happens
when the floor and the ceiling
get closer and closer?
What happens to this ribbon?
It starts to look
more and more like a string.
It starts to look more
and more like a point-like string.
And so when G
is very small,
not a point-like string,
but a line-like string,
the line-like strings
are the membranes
which are oriented vertically
in this direction here.
As and
there are also
D0 brains.
D0 brains being very heavy.
Now you start to increase
the coupling constant.
The floor and the ceiling
start to separate.
The D0 brains
just turn into gravitons.
They turn into just gravitons
moving in the extra dimension.
And they're very simple.
They're just simple elementary particles
in the higher dimensional theory.
What about
the membranes, or what about the strings?
The strings
now become
very, very unstring-like.
Very, very
unstring-like.
They have a lot of membrane
in them. They're stretched a long
ways. They're very heavy.
Why are they so heavy?
Because there's so much
material there, vertically
here. They turn into something
very heavy.
The D0 brains
turned into something very light.
This is an extremely bizarre
story. It is one which is
the mathematics
was discovered by a bunch of people
and
the consistency
of it, the requirement
for it, the need of it
was
it was
a lot of heavy mathematics which went into it.
The need for it to be
consistent involved conjectures,
mathematical conjectures,
which the physicists didn't know how to prove.
They were conjectures about
mathematical structures which mathematicians
knew about. The mathematicians
had no idea about
these conjectures. They'd never heard of these conjectures.
But when the physicists
told them, look,
for these ideas to make any sense,
such and such a mathematical theorem has to
be true, the mathematicians went back and said,
ooh, yeah, those
theorems turned out to be true.
So there's really very
little doubt that all of this holds together,
as bizarre as it sounds.
But it's just a whole
collection of examples
of the breakdown of what I call
reductionism in the beginning.
Now the other ingredient
that makes it
especially bizarre
is that all these things like coupling constants
can vary in space.
So you can have a variation
from place to place where in
some places the world looks very, very
close to ten-dimensional
with very light strings,
heavy D0 brains, and if
you move over a couple of
meters or whatever,
the theory will change its character,
develop a large direction
in this direction,
strings will turn into very heavy membranes,
and D0 brains will turn
into gravitons.
These things are called
inequalities, these relationships
between what happens at one end
of a parameter space and the other end of a
parameter space.
And in many ways they're very magical
and surprising.
They're nothing
like
what was originally expected
from this theory.
It was a simple theory, strings make
up particles, end of story.
What turned out was
much, much more complex,
and much more
elusive in a certain sense.
Elusive in the sense that it
just
became totally unclear
what the starting
objects of the theory are.
What the starting objects,
what the things which,
what the bricks are,
and what the houses are.
And to this day we really simply don't
know what, if anything,
the fundamental
objects that the theory is built out of are.
If there are such objects.
Perhaps it's just this way.
Perhaps there is no set of objects
which are more fundamental than
the strings and the brains and so forth,
and they just transform into each other.
Perhaps there's something
underlying the whole thing
that's more fundamental than
any of them, and can rearrange
itself, can rearrange itself
into different, these different patterns,
and form different kinds of structures.
So we don't know.
We don't know the answer to those questions.
Alright, let's take a
break for ten minutes.
Let me just tell you a few more
interesting connections I was talking about
a few minutes ago with Michael and a couple of other people.
There's an enormous web
of interconnected ideas
and interconnected theories
that string theory brings together
so let me show you
two more interesting ideas
that
take a
D3 brain. Remember, now
there are those theories that have odd brains
and those theories that have even brains.
Let's take the case
of the odd-brained
theories, which have
D1 brains,
fundamental strings, and also
D3 brains. Now a
D3 brain is like
ordinary space. It has three dimensions,
in which you can move around in.
If you are stuck on this brain and you couldn't get off
it, perhaps because you were attracted to it,
you might
think you're living
in a world of three dimensions.
Just as
if there was a two-dimensional membrane
and you were a little creature that moved around
on the membrane, you would think you live in two dimensions.
You might not, you know,
under certain circumstances,
you might really
describe your world as being pretty
similar to a quantum
theory or to a theory in two dimensions,
two space dimensions.
Same thing
on three brains. Three brains
in many ways just
behave as if they were just ordinary
space.
Now, the three brain
itself can have all sorts of
wiggles on it, all
sorts of motions,
and
it also has, well, it has
among other things, here's
a picture of a three brain. No, I think I
should draw it the other way.
Let's draw it this way.
You say,
that's not a three brain, it's a two brain.
Too bad, I can't draw,
I'm not good at drawing three-dimensional
figures.
Imagine that
it's three-dimensional, not two-dimensional.
We're going to need the other dimension
for
additional dimensions, so
I don't want to use full three-dimensionals.
You know what I mean.
Okay, so that's a D3 brain,
and it can do things. It can have
wiggles on it and so forth. It can also have
strings attached to it,
like that.
Here's two strings
attached to the D3
brain, ordinary strings.
Those two strings can come along,
here they are, one is over here, one is over
here. They can come along,
they can join and form
a single string.
Okay, so here is the
picture. They come along,
they join, and they form
a single string, and then they go
back out and they do something else.
They scatter.
They scatter, they interact,
they do all the things that
particles do.
And so on this
world of three dimensions, which
is not really the full space
time, but just a
brain, all sorts of things go
on, which are in many
ways similar to the things
which happen in
ordinary quantum field
theory in three dimensions.
Well,
let me give you
one interesting thought.
Supposing from
outside the D3 brain
a fundamental string comes
and ends on the D3 brain.
How about the people
who live on this D3 brain,
who are made up out of the strings
wiggling up and down the string.
What do they call this object
over here? They call it a
particle, right? It looks like a particle
to them. It's a little point over here.
Somebody over here sees a little
particle over here.
Somehow, they've come in from
some other direction. He doesn't see the other directions.
He only sees the directions
he lives in and
sees a particle over here.
What kind of particle?
This is now a fundamental string.
What kind
of particle? An electrically
charged particle.
Well, if we
can have fundamental strings
and in a theory with
odd brains,
we also have D-strings.
So here's a D-string,
and a D-string can also end
on a
three brain. That's part of the
mathematical story of D-brains.
Fundamental strings
and D-strings can
end on the three brain.
That's a D-string.
What does that D-string look like
to somebody living in here?
It also looks like a particle.
It's kind of a
fatter particle. Why is it
fatter? Because the D-string
is fatter than the fundamental string.
Unless the coupling constant is very large,
of course. If the coupling constant
is very large, they might get interchanged.
But I'm in a world now
where the coupling constant is small.
The fundamental strings are skinny
and thread-like.
The D-strings are fat
and rope-like.
And a D-string ending
on here
would look like a bigger,
heavier particle.
This one
looks like an electric charge.
Can you guess what this one looks like?
A magnetic monopole.
So,
the duality
that connects
the fundamental strings with the D-strings
is nothing
but the duality
which connected the electric charges
with the magnetic charges
of ordinary field theory.
That's a
kind of spectacular
connection that
something we already knew for a long
time has
a new interpretation in terms
of D-strings
and fundamental strings, the duality between
D-strings and fundamental strings.
I'll give you
one more example.
One more example which also
involves D-strings and F-strings.
And
I want you to go back to this
11-dimensional theory that we had over here.
It's 11 dimensions.
The horizontal axis
is
9 dimensions of space,
one extra dimension of space
plus time.
Let's go back to this theory over here.
But unfortunately
I can't draw enough dimensions
to do this satisfactorily.
In this picture
over here, only one dimension
of space is compact.
The sandwich has only
one direction
along which it's sandwich-like.
I want
to imagine taking two dimensions
of space
and compactifying them.
How can I draw that?
Well, the maximum number of
dimensions I can draw on the blackboard
is three. I can't draw more than
three dimensions on the blackboard.
If I compactify
two of them, that only gives me
one more left to
think of as all the other dimensions.
So I'm
just going to have to make do with a world
which
has only one large dimension
or at least one visible large dimension
and two small ones.
What does that look like? It looks like this.
Here's the two small dimensions
and here's the one
big dimension which is a stand-in
for how many?
Seven.
Right.
Okay, now imagine
this is the same
theory that had
D2 brains.
Oh, let's
just for fun, let's draw this
as rather asymmetric.
I'm going to draw it asymmetrically
so that
one of the axes
is shorter than the other
to make a point.
Now this theory also
has
D2 brains.
The D2 brains were these
things which formed strings
when the sandwich
was small.
Those strings
sort of stretched
from the ceiling to the floor.
Here's the ceiling, here's the floor.
And we can draw
those strings. Let me take another color.
This happens to be a string
which is stretched out
along the one
visible direction that I can draw here.
If I could draw more directions
I could make the string wiggle and wave
and so forth.
But let's just stretch it out
along this direction.
It's a string.
Well, it's not quite a string. It's sort of a ribbon.
But
if these directions are very small
then it looks like a string, right?
Looks like a string.
And what happens
as the sandwich
in this direction
gets thinner and thinner?
It gets more and more string-like, of course.
But in fact it also gets
lighter and lighter because there's less
material in the vertical direction here.
But we can also
put
a string in
in the other
oriented the other way.
How about this string?
That's also, from the point of view
of the large dimensions of space
it also looks like a
one-dimensional object
as long as both axes are small.
What does this one look like?
This one is called
It's not the same thing.
In fact, which one of these two
strings would you think is heavier?
The bottom one, because it's more
material that way, right?
This one's heavy.
This one's light.
They're both strings.
Can you guess what they are?
F strings
and D strings.
So this is
another way to think about
the relation between
F strings and D strings.
They're membranes
which are wrapped around
two different directions,
two different small directions.
One of the directions being
larger than the other.
Now, what happens
if we imagine taking the space
and distorting it
so that we start squeezing
this direction this way and stretching
this one that way?
What happens to the two kinds of strings?
The F strings get
heavier and heavier,
thicker and thicker, more and more material.
The D strings get lighter
and lighter.
So we see, again,
this is another way to think
about D strings and F strings.
They're all mathematically
equivalent.
And it's just a small part
of an enormous network of
ideas
that emerge out of string theory.
Sometimes connecting one string
theory with another string theory.
Sometimes connecting
string theory with quantum field theory.
Connecting ideas like
monopoles and charges
with strings and other things.
Most of it
having very little to do with what we see
in the laboratory.
In that picture,
can't you view alpha as the ratio
of the...
In that picture, can you view
alpha as the ratio
of the two dimensions?
Yes.
That's exactly what it is.
When the ratio,
when this direction is small,
we would normally call it
a small coupling constant
and, yeah,
that's right.
These things do not have
a finite width because
of the cyclical nature.
Well, they're finite
in extent, but they're cyclic.
Right.
So the bottom here is
the same point as the top.
So if you walked along the ribbon
and you came to here,
you would reappear over here.
Likewise over here,
if you went out over here,
you'd reappear over here.
That gives you
a kind of infinity.
Well, you can go...
It's the same kind of infinity
as the Earth, okay?
as this circle.
You can go around it
and around it and around it
but never come to the end.
But nevertheless,
you wouldn't say the distance
around you was infinite.
No, but in this case,
you start out,
you go this direction.
And you go up another step.
In other words,
if you add up all the steps...
All that is is going around
and
around and around and around.
It's just, look, it's taking a circle.
This idea of going out the top
and reappearing at the bottom
is nothing but taking a circle
where you just go around
and in order to mathematically
exhibit it,
you cut it, open it up,
draw it on the blackboard,
and the blackboard is a line.
But remember that this point
and this point are really the same point
so that when you go from here
across, you jump across to here.
When you go out here, you come here.
Why isn't this a helix
rather than just a circle?
At each point, this is a circle.
Yes, but we're going
along in this way
and therefore it's kind of a helix.
Well, if
you go around
as you go forward,
then you get a helix.
Is there any...
This is, of course, a geometrical picture.
Is there any useful
story about how the geometry
here connects to the
earlier point you made
that the D-Brain can look like
a collection of F-Brain, so where you look very closely
and scatter the D-Brain, you see a lot of F-Brain.
From this picture,
it's a little bit hard to see.
It is useful,
but you need a little bit more
geometric imagination to see
how a D-Brain
can be connected up with an F-Brain.
I'm reaching a saturation
point of complexity
where I...
If you put the two in the same picture
and then you
oscillate it,
between the thin and the narrow,
then you get those flip-flopping
perpendicular...
You mean oscillating in space?
As you move along...
Well, let's say if you oscillate the long dimension
and the short dimension...
Oscillate in time or space or what?
Either.
Just the shape.
But when you say oscillates,
it's just space, numbers.
You're just going to squish one this way
and the other one pops out.
Yeah, exactly.
If you have the same diagram,
then you've got them changing places.
That's right, exactly.
You can imagine that as you move along space
in this direction,
it squishes horizontally
and broadens vertically.
Right.
So then you would say,
over here, the fundamental
strings are light,
over here, the fundamental strings are heavy.
Now, fundamental is just a name.
It's quite clear that which is fundamental
and which is...
There's no preference for which one is fundamental.
It's just a word.
We call the ones which are arranged vertically here
fundamental.
We call the ones which are arranged horizontal, D.
And that's right.
As you move along here,
you can imagine going back and forth.
Or with time.
You could also imagine that with time,
these...
And that can also happen.
And so you could go back and forth
between the two of them. Absolutely.
Now,
let me just sort of
finish up
these thoughts
by saying these precise
features are features of
an
idealization.
The idealization is the
idealized supersymmetric
string theory.
Supersymmetric means that it has
bosons and fermions of exactly the same
mass, and
it's an
idealization in the sense that
it's not really nature.
In some sense, it's like the
idealization of studying perfectly
circular orbits.
Why do you study circular orbits?
Because they're easy to study.
Undoubtedly the first kind of orbit
that Newton studied.
Circular orbits. They had an extra symmetry,
they were highly symmetric,
and easy to study.
The mathematics was easy.
They weren't the real planetary
orbits, but of course
many of the features of real planetary
orbits
in simplified form
were there
for circular orbits.
Again, the kinds
of string theories that we really know
how to deal with, mathematically,
string theory is infinitely more
complex than the theory
of orbits.
The kind of theories that we know
how to deal with are also especially
symmetric.
Symmetric meaning to say that they
have some mathematical properties
which are idealizations,
makes them easy to understand,
easier to understand,
and
but is
not real nature.
What they show us is the kind
of things that can happen.
The kind of things, all of
these things which happen here
are expected to have a reflection of
one kind or another in a more realistic
theory, but it will be more
complicated and it will be less
tractable and
not so easy to
visualize and certainly not
so easy to prove anything about.
But it does show us the kind of things
that can happen
in a string
theory and very likely the kinds of things
that can happen more generally than just
string theory.
So, as I said, string theory
as we understand it now, the
things that we really understand
mathematically are
over-idealizations.
And so when people
argue in the press and
books and silly books for the
most part about whether string
theory is the right theory of the world
or not,
the answer is it's not.
It's just not.
On the other hand, does it have an enormous amount
to teach us about the way that quantum
mechanics, gravity, microstructure
fits together? Probably
yes. That's my
opinion in any case.
Many of the things
really don't depend on the
details of string theory.
But, okay, enough
of that sermon.
There are other objects besides
D-brains.
I don't
I think I probably saturated you
with ideas for tonight.
There are other objects in the theory.
There are things called fluxes.
There are things called
orbifolds, things called orientafolds,
things, all kinds of structures
which add to the
elements that you can
put together to create a
world.
You can take
a geometry. For example,
this room
with the
floor and the ceiling
being thought of as the
top and bottom of the peanut butter
sandwich, maybe even
periodically identified.
We take that wall,
we can take that, this room,
think of it
really as one compact
direction and two
non-compact directions.
And then we can put a D-2 brain
into it, a D-brain into it
that fills up like a flying carpet
halfway between the floor and the ceiling.
And that's a new structure
that could be there in space
and we shrink
the size from the wall of the floor
to the ceiling, but with that
flying carpet always stuck in between
it changes the character
of physics
in that two-dimensional world.
We can put
one flying carpet in,
we can put two flying carpets in,
we can put three flying carpets in,
and we can make a whole variety
of different worlds
by changing the D-brain
content that we put into the world.
As I said, there are other objects,
there are fluxes, we can change
the nature of
the microscopic world
by adding those things
or subtracting those things.
What string theory
gives us is a
bunch of tinker toy
parts, a lot of
tinker toy parts, that we
can play with, arrange,
rearrange, do complicated things
with, and in the process
change what the
microscopic physics is like, change what
particle physics is like, change
what the parameters of
nature are like.
It gives rise to huge numbers
of possibilities,
permutations and combinations
of how you put these tinker toy pieces
together.
How many possibilities?
Huge number.
Ten to the five hundred is a number
that's often thrown around.
It's not very hard to get to
ten to the five hundred.
Supposing
Yeah.
Really all you need is five hundred.
You don't really need anything.
Five hundred is not such a big
number, right?
Supposing you have a
space
which is like a donut
except it has five hundred holes
and handles in it. Now five hundred holes
and handles is not a large
number for the kind of spaces
that
string theory uses,
Calabi-Yau spaces.
The six dimensional spaces, they're complicated.
Five hundred holes and
handles attached to them is not very
complicated. Now
we can, around each
one of what are called
cycles, we can wrap
brains, we can wrap fluxes.
If around each
one of five hundred cycles
we can wrap a few brains,
three or four brains
more or less, or
we can put in a few fluxes or whatever
a flux is and modify
the geometry for each handle
if we could modify the
structure in ten different
ways, then we would have
ten to the five hundred possibilities.
You know, it's kind of like DNA.
You take a DNA chain.
If the DNA chain
was five hundred units long
how many different creatures,
how many different possibilities are there for a creature?
Four to the five hundred.
Not five hundred, but four to the five hundred.
So
with the permutations and
combinations of
five hundred objects being
rearranged in maybe four,
five, ten ways, you can make
huge numbers of possibilities.
And that's what happens.
How many tinker toy, given
a tinker toy set, how many different
constructions can you make?
Well, you have
how many of those little wheels?
And in each wheel you can
put, you know,
numbers get very, very large.
So
the same is true with string theory.
And
the numbers are large
and any given construction
is likely to be
rather complicated. The generic
construction that you make is likely
to be rather complicated.
Just like the generic construction
you can make with a DNA chain,
well, DNA chains are more than
five hundred units long.
What, a hundred million units long?
A hundred million base pairs long?
Still only about twenty thousand
genes.
How many
kinds of creatures can you make?
A huge number. Are any of them simple?
Well, some of them are simple, but the
generic creature that you make
is very complicated. It has trunks and ears
and all sorts of
appendages.
It could very well be
that that's the reason that particle
physics is so complicated.
Because a lot of moving parts
go into constructing
particular string theory
construction.
I think most string theorists believe
this by now, that the world
is complicated because there's a lot of moving
parts, but not because the rules are
complicated. The rules of DNA are not complicated.
You have a long chain,
and you either put in a T, a G, an A,
a C, whatever the
base pairs are,
and you put them in an arbitrary
sequence of
base pairs, and then
What's that?
Four of them. What did I say?
T, G, C, and A.
They come in pairs
though, you realize.
On the other hand, it is, yeah, yeah, but there's two
strands
so if you focus on one strand and you move
along it, any point along it
could be one of four, so it's four to the five hundred
or whatever, four to the thirty thousand, whatever.
And
none of them are particularly simple,
but the rules, the basic underlying
rules for putting things together
are simple. The same is true of string theory
in very much the same way
that the basic rules for
what you're allowed to do
are pretty simple. The number of
arrangements that you can make
for a particular
setup is very large.
And most of them
will lead to fairly
complicated particle physics.
That's the situation
we're facing, and
string theory, if string theory is
correct, I think
we should expect that
particle physics will be more
complicated, probably
than we'll ever be able to
unravel completely.
Question. Is it thought that
of the four to the, ten to the five hundred
that there are really only a few
that describe this? Ten to the five hundred
incidentally is an underestimate.
That was a, yeah, but go ahead.
But is it thought that
if we had all the information that we would
find that only one or a couple of
I know about the duality that you've
talked about. Yeah, yeah, there are the dualities
but when you sort of
when you divide out the dualities
the ten to the five hundred
is the number that's left over.
And it's not ten to the five hundred,
that's an old number.
But I mean, is it only a few
that would, if we knew
what it was, it would only be one of those
choices? Well, okay.
Presumably so.
But there may be many which look
very similar. There may be
many, many which look very, very similar.
You know, there may be a lot of junk DNA
in it.
There's a lot of junk DNA in it.
But there's some where, for example
in this picture, the aspect ratio
were one, and therefore
the F and the D's were kind of
the same thing. Right.
Like, are there some
of those ten to the power of five hundred
where the whole thing becomes a lot similar?
There are, I think you're asking
whether there are specially symmetric
points. And there are specially symmetric
points, yeah.
There are specially symmetric points.
Our world does not seem to be one of those
specially symmetric points.
A specially symmetric
point would be one in which
the monopole mass and the electron
mass were the same.
Apparently we don't live in that world.
We live in a lopsided world
more like this.
Do we know why? No.
Long, long ago
I studied communications
engineering here at Stanford, and
at that time, what they
taught us about coding theory
and communication
and direction codes was that,
and this is always hit with a sense of
dire humor, that almost all
the codes you can find are really
very, very good. But
because the only ones you can decode
have mathematical structure, the ones
you can actually decode are universally
bad. Bad in what sense?
In bad in that they don't give you
the, they give you just a fraction
of the performance that you get to.
Now it's turned out
that
in the many years since I've studied this
that they have in fact found codes that are
unbelievably good compared to what we had
back in the 70s.
But it reminds me of this, that
it's the mathematical structure
when, that
if the mathematical structure is
understandable, the complexity is too low
to explain. Yeah, almost
anything you can name is too simple to be
interesting. Like
almost every number is
small, because any number you name
almost all of them are much bigger.
Any
thing you can describe is probably too,
you know, it's described in a
small number of
bits. Yeah,
this is probably true. And
I think
what it means, if true,
if these things are true, is
we've got to learn to ask a new class
of questions. The question is not
exactly what is the set up
which, what
are the common features, what are the
generic features, what the, and
you know, we're
people are wrestling with those questions.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Now, will it turn out that way?
We don't know.
This is, this is, this is,
but it doesn't do anybody any
good to have
ideological warfare
in the press over these things.
Okay.
Yes, sir. It seems
that there wouldn't be a big difference
between... Do I have to answer? Yeah, yeah.
Hmm? You want Leonard?
No. No. He's Leonard.
Right. I wasn't.
I wasn't.
It seems that there wouldn't be
a big difference between a
compact
direction that has a very large
size and an
infinite. Well...
And, and so
do we know that we've, that our
three ordinary dimensions
really are infinite? Nope.
We do not.
As a matter of fact, I mean, you know,
standard old-fashioned cosmological
theory said the three dimensions form
a sphere, a growing sphere
to be sure, but
a three sphere, and so they were all compact.
All compact, but
growing. So, no, we don't.
And there's no way to
actually tell.
We can only say that they're bigger than this or that.
The, the
measured flatness of the
universe, you know, if you wanted to know how big the Earth
was around,
you, going out
in the farmer's field, which is, you know,
a, a
kilometer by a kilometer, and looking around,
all you could do is put a bound
on how big the Earth is. From
looking at triangles and things
and over small distances,
you could say, well,
the Earth is so flat
that I suspect it must be at least
60 miles big.
Does a little bit better,
measures a little more accurately, triangles
at the surface of the Earth,
assuming the surface of the Earth was nice
and flat and didn't have hills in it,
he might be able to say it's 500 miles
big or bigger.
And that's all he can do until
he starts to detect the
curvature of the Earth, and when he detects
the curvature of the Earth, then
he can say, aha, the Earth looks like a
24,000 miles in circumference.
Same thing, when we look out
cosmologically,
space looks very flat
on very large scales, so
all we can say is it's at least
this big. It's at least
40 billion light years on a side,
well, it's bigger than that,
no, no, it's much bigger than that, 400
light years on a side at least, at
minimum, and
but we can't say one way or another
whether it's infinite or not.
If G can vary over space,
how would you be able to detect
whether you are...
In the real world, it can't.
In the real world, which is not as
symmetric and as simple as this,
it can't.
No.
It may be able to vary,
but it'll vary in steps.
We're going to talk about
the whole thing, but
we're going to talk about the whole thing.
We're going to talk about this when we talk about cosmology.
What are the kinds of variations
that the laws of physics
can have from place to place?
Consistent with both theory
and with what we know experimentally.
And from what we know experimentally,
is that these changes
have to take place
in discrete jumps,
more or less in jumps.
Okay, because if it was continuous,
it would seem that you can move along a linear dimension
and then end up in one of the curved dimensions
that's become big.
I think we know
with pretty much certainty
that it can't continuously
smoothly vary.
What we don't know is whether it can vary in jumps.
And there are good reasons to think that it varies in jumps.
Some kinds of black holes, yes.
Other kinds, no.
Ordinary Schwarzschild black hole, no.
Not in the
horizon of a Schwarzschild black hole, no.
The horizon of a Schwarzschild black hole
is a very ordinary place
where nothing special like that happens.
I'm losing my voice.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu