Stanford University.
Okay, let's go back to, I'm going to try to, we've done this before,
incidentally, but there's only so much physics out there and
I can't keep making it up fast enough to, I wish I could, but I can't.
When I was younger, I could.
So we're going to do things that we've done before.
Alright, let's go back to what we learned about the geometry of
a black hole near the horizon.
Near the horizon, we found out that it was just pretty much good old flat space-time,
approximately, very, very close to the horizon.
And we described it by a particular metric.
For this purpose, we started, of course, with the good old Schwarzschild metric,
but we made a bunch of changes of variables.
In particular, instead of the Schwarzschild coordinate r,
there's never enough ink here, instead of the Schwarzschild coordinate r
that goes into the Schwarzschild metric in the usual way,
we replaced it with a new one.
We replaced it...
Oh, good.
We replaced it by another variable, which was actually the proper distance from the horizon.
r is not the proper distance from the horizon, but rho is.
That's its definition. That's the definition of rho, proper distance from the horizon.
And I won't bother writing down the relationship between them.
Not terribly important to know.
But rho, one thing is important, when...
At the point when r is equal to 2mg,
that's the Schwarzschild radius, that's the point where the horizon is,
at that point, rho is equal to 0, proper distance from the horizon.
We also made another change of variables.
Omega, which is a time variable,
was equal, and it's a dimensionless time variable,
is equal to the Schwarzschild time divided by 4mg.
So roughly speaking, in every place here, c is equal to 1.
c is equal to 1.
Roughly what omega is, time and length are measured in the same units, when c is equal to 1.
2mg is the Schwarzschild radius of the black hole.
So apart from a factor of 2,
omega is time measured in units of the Schwarzschild radius.
So that's what omega is.
And that's why it's dimensionless, because it's a ratio of things.
Time divided by the Schwarzschild radius.
And when we did that, we went through the little exercise,
it was a number of steps, more steps than I really like to do, but nevertheless, we did it.
And we found out that near the horizon of the black hole,
we call it the near horizon geometry,
that the proper distance was equal to minus rho squared,
d omega squared, I can write this in terms of proper time,
the difference between proper distance squared and proper time squared is just you change the sign.
You can write d tau squared and put a plus sign here.
d omega squared plus d rho squared.
And then there was another piece coming from angles on the horizon,
but I'm not terribly interested in that.
I'm interested in distance from the horizon and time.
A two-dimensional picture of the black hole.
Just time and distance from the black hole.
This is what the metric is like.
And then I pointed out to you,
that this metric is very, very similar to the metric of ordinary flat space,
conventional flat space, the surface of this table here,
in polar coordinates.
In polar coordinates, we would ordinarily write,
I don't want to write it here because I don't want to confuse it with this,
ordinarily in polar coordinates,
theta, rho,
we would write that ds squared
is equal to rho squared d theta squared
plus d rho squared.
So they look very similar to each other.
The only difference is this minus sign.
And omega is analogous to theta.
It's a hyperbolic angle.
Just to finish, yeah, alright, that's good.
That's, that's,
this is flat space, ordinary flat space.
This happens to be nothing but ordinary flat space time
in a kind of polar coordinate reference frame.
Everybody remember this?
And omega is t over 4mg.
Now, this is the metric close to the black hole horizon.
We draw a picture of this.
This is just flat space in polar coordinates.
So it looks something like this.
Omega is a kind of hyperbolic angle variable,
which way down the remote past,
omega is equal to minus infinity.
Way up here, omega is equal to plus infinity.
And rho, lines of constant rho,
are just hyperbolas which look like this.
The firth- and here's the horizon.
Right over here is the horizon.
Or right over there,
if we come in along a line of constant omega,
fixed time,
that point right over there,
is r equals 2mg.
It's rho equals zero,
but it's r equals 2mg.
So that's what we set up last time.
We also said that the horizon of the black hole,
well, the general horizon,
there's two notions of horizon incidentally.
One is called bifurcate horizon.
I'll tell you the words.
The bifurcate horizon is simply this point over here.
And the bi, I don't know what furcate means,
but bi means two.
And the two-ness are the intersection
of these two light cones here.
That's called the bifurcate horizon.
But there's another notion of horizon.
The other notion of horizon
is a more physically interesting one.
It's this whole light-like surface here.
Why is that interesting?
Well, if somebody gets stuck behind that light-like surface,
they cannot send a message to the other person.
They cannot send a message to the outside.
They cannot send a message out beyond that light-like surface.
So this is a kind of horizon.
And once you're behind it,
you can't get any information out
to distances beyond the r equals 2m,
or rho equal, r equals 2m,
or rho greater than zero.
Okay, so that's the geometry of the near horizon.
What about when we go very, very far from the black hole?
When we go very far from the black hole,
we see also it looks like flat spacetime.
But here's the metric that we would see.
We take the Schwarzschild metric,
the good old Schwarzschild metric.
Let's write it down.
ds squared is equal to 1 minus 2mg over r,
dt squared plus 1 over 1 minus 2mg
over r, dr squared.
And now we go far from the black hole,
which means r very large.
What happens to this when r is very large?
This is dt squared, excuse me.
It just becomes dt squared plus or minus dt squared
plus dr squared.
Okay.
r and rho, far from the black hole,
r and rho are the same thing.
Once you're way far away from the black hole,
the proper distance to the black hole
is approximately just r.
It's only near the black hole that r and rho
are very different from each other.
But when you're far from the black hole,
radius is just radius.
Distance from the horizon is basically the same
as it would be in flat space.
So far from the black hole,
rho and r are basically the same thing.
This factor here is not interesting.
It goes to 1.
This factor down here also goes to 1,
and we just get minus dt squared plus dr squared.
All right, so far from the black hole then,
the s squared is minus rho squared.
But let's write,
sorry, not minus rho squared, excuse me.
I just want to write dt squared.
I just want to write dt squared
because there is no interesting factor.
So what is dt squared?
dt squared is 16 m squared g squared d omega squared.
What I've done here is just multiply by 4mg
so that omega,
so that t is equal to 4mg times omega.
That's this piece here.
And then the other piece is just plus dr squared.
So I've got this d rho squared.
The d rho squared is just this over here,
making use of the fact that rho and r
are the same thing far from the black hole.
So look what's happening.
That near the black hole,
the only different,
the only interesting difference between these two
is not in the d rho squared term,
but it's in the time term.
Omega is a kind of time.
It's related to time
through this equation over here.
And on the one hand,
near the black hole,
there's a factor rho squared.
When rho is very, very small,
it means that time runs very, very slowly.
Very far, near the horizon of the black hole,
there is very little proper time
in any appreciable d omega.
But far from the black hole,
this is what the formula says.
Okay, this is curious.
What's going on?
How do we think about this?
What kind of geometry?
It's a little hard to envision.
In fact, it's quite hard to envision.
But as you move away from the horizon of the black hole,
this here thing goes to this thing.
Let me give you,
I'll try to give you the best picture I can
of what this geometry is like.
Minus 60?
Yeah, minus.
All right.
Let's come over to here.
To this picture over here.
It's much easier to understand space
than it is space-time.
So let's come back to this picture.
And now imagine a geometry
which has the following property.
Near the origin, it looks like
rho squared d theta squared plus d rho squared.
But far from the origin,
it looks like instead of rho squared,
let's just say 60.
So here we have 16 m squared g squared
d theta squared plus d rho squared.
Very similar to what's going on over here,
except we're not dealing with space-time,
we're dealing with just ordinary space.
What kind of geometry is this?
So let me show you what it looks like.
Can you guess what it looks like?
This is, I'll show you.
Near the origin,
it looks like polar coordinates.
Let me draw this plane on its edge,
like this.
Here's this plane drawn edge-on.
As I go around theta,
I just go around here.
Near the origin, it looks like the plane.
But now as I move away from the origin,
what happens, look at it,
instead of having this rho squared here,
we just get a constant squared.
The meaning of that is that the distance around theta,
between two neighboring values of theta,
instead of depending on rho,
just becomes constant.
It becomes 16 m squared g squared.
I'll show you what it looks like.
It looks like a cigar.
It looks like a geometry that looks like this.
Where the distance around the cigar at this end here,
is, well, theta goes from 0 to 2 pi.
So the distance around the whole cigar,
in this direction, the cigar band,
is 4 m g times 2 pi.
Theta goes from 0 to 2 pi as you go around.
So that's what's at this end.
On the other hand,
very near the origin over here,
it really just does look like polar coordinates.
Theta goes around, looks like polar coordinates,
very close to the tip of the cigar,
the cigar looks flat.
Any geometry in the vicinity of a point
looks pretty flat.
But as you go out, and as you move around
this point here,
close to the tip of the cigar,
this is the metric.
Far from the tip of the cigar,
the distance around the theta axis
does not depend on how far away you are.
Same here.
The distance in omega,
when you're far away,
doesn't depend on rho.
When you're close in,
the distance for a given omega
does depend on rho.
The main message here is that this is a curved space.
It's a curved space,
with a curvature near the horizon.
And how does that curvature depend on m and g?
Well, the distance around this cigar
gets very, very big when m and g get big.
So when the mass,
well, sorry, when the mass gets big,
the distance around the cigar gets big,
and that means that the curvature
at the tip of the cigar gets less.
The bigger the mass is,
the less curvature that you have
at the tip of the cigar,
the less curved it is.
A small mass
would look like this.
Highly curved at this end.
This is also true
of the Schwarzschild black hole.
Highly curved when the mass is small
near the black hole tip,
near the horizon.
This point is the horizon.
It becomes, it maps,
or becomes this point over here.
So you can get some feel
for what this geometry is like
by looking at its ordinary space version.
But still, I think that's not completely satisfying.
It just is what it is.
It is what it is.
Here's the geometry.
The coefficient of the omega squared varies
from near the horizon,
where it's rho squared,
to far from the horizon,
where it just becomes a number.
The number being 16 m squared g squared.
That's,
and that's really all you really need to know
about the black hole.
What is this,
this factor here?
We look at,
given angular separations,
the factor in front of the omega squared
tells us how much proper time there is
from one omega,
let's call this omega equals zero,
and let's call this omega equals one.
Near the horizon,
very close to the horizon,
where rho is very small,
the proper time distance
between omega equals zero
and omega equals one is very small.
Okay?
So near the horizon,
as time flows,
as omega flows,
very, very little proper time
between neighboring values of time.
Far from the black hole,
neighboring values simply
have
times,
time differences,
which are just
this number here,
which is nothing but
dt squared.
Okay, so clocks,
this is a statement about clocks.
Clocks far away from the black hole
behave exactly as you would expect.
They read this time here.
Clocks very close to the black hole
read rho times omega.
Rho times omega.
Omega is a kind of time variable,
but it scales differently close to the black hole.
All right, that's what a black hole is like.
Now,
again,
outside the black hole,
corresponds to rho greater than zero.
Rho greater than zero
is all of these curves here.
It's rho equals one,
rho equals two,
rho equals three,
rho equals four.
That's outside the black hole.
Anybody who's stationed at rest
outside the black hole,
if you could,
if you were at rest outside a black hole
and just let go,
you'll slowly fall toward the black hole
if you're far away.
If you're very, very far away,
it'll take a long time,
but it doesn't take much effort
to stay out of the black hole.
You can orbit around the black hole.
You can just have a little jet propulsion device
that can keep you out of the black hole,
and that's moving along one of these trajectories here,
just staying a certain distance away from the black hole.
All right?
On the other hand,
once somebody passes through,
we'll now call this the horizon,
the event horizon.
This is the bifurcate horizon.
This is the event horizon.
Once you pass past the event horizon,
you cannot send a message to the outside world.
That's the character of the black hole.
That's what makes it a black hole.
Good.
On that diagram,
speed of light is a straight line?
Oh, speed of light,
radial speed of light,
radial light waves always move
on 45-degree axes.
In any drawing I ever draw,
unless I tell you otherwise,
and I may tell you otherwise sometimes,
but the speed of light is a 45-degree line.
Right.
So a light ray falling in that way,
a light ray trying to get out that way,
but it won't get out.
So light rays can fall in,
but they can't fall out.
All right, what about the singularity?
Let's go back to the Schwarzschild theory.
I'm going to use the Schwarzschild metric,
which I've erased off the blackboard someplace,
and write it down again
and see if we can trace.
Well, first of all,
let's redraw this diagram.
Just a question about the terminology you're using.
You're saying when the light ray falls in.
Light ray shines into the black hole.
Go ahead.
What are you going to ask?
Does the light ray stay at the horizon?
Right across the horizon of the black hole.
We'll see.
Okay.
Well, we can answer that right now.
Here's Bob.
Bob is riding on his trajectory.
He's riding on his world line.
Let's move him out a little bit.
Okay.
Bob is quite far from the black hole.
Here are
the two points.
Omega equals zero.
Omega equals one.
Omega equals two.
What about the Schwarzschild time?
You know, the usual time
that Bob measures on his wristwatch.
He measures Schwarzschild time, the t.
Well, t and omega are basically the same thing,
except for a factor of 4 mg.
So this would be his time equals zero.
This would be his time equals 4 mg.
This would be his time equals 8 mg, and so forth.
So riding along here,
Bob is looking at his wristwatch,
and time is ticking off.
There's an infinite number of ticks along his trajectory.
He never falls into the black hole.
Why not?
Because I tell you, he doesn't fall into the black hole.
He stays outside.
He's orbiting it.
So he stays at a fixed proper distance.
That means on a fixed hyperboloid here.
And he looks back.
Let's draw in Alice.
Now Alice doesn't have to be Alice.
Alice could be a proton.
It could be a photon.
It could be anything falling or moving in this direction.
Let's say a photon.
You asked me about a photon.
Here's a photon.
That photon moves 45 degrees,
and it sure looks to me like it passes the horizon.
What about Bob?
What does Bob say?
So Bob's wristwatch reads off time.
Time infinity is way, way out there.
So he looks back from wherever he is.
Let's get another color onto this problem.
Red.
Bob looks back, and he sees the photon over here.
Why do I say he looks back?
He looks back, and he sees the light coming to him from...
Light doesn't usually come from...
Yeah.
Strictly speaking, Bob can't see this photon.
The photon's going the other way.
So let's not make it a photon.
Let's make it Alice.
Okay?
Alice is falling through.
She's waving her hand as she falls through.
And Bob looks at her.
Let's say here's her waves.
Let's make them closer together.
She's waving pretty rapidly.
Along her world line, she's waving.
Hi, Bob.
Bob is looking back, and from this point, he sees Alice over here.
We all see each other slightly in the picture.
Slightly in the past.
Takes time, light time to get to us.
So Bob sees Alice over here.
Next, after another interval of time, he sees Alice over here.
She's waved a certain number of times.
Bob sees Alice wave a few more times.
Bob keeps looking back.
He keeps looking back.
And according to him, each one of these measurements,
each one of these observations is separated, let's say, by one second.
Each one is separated by one second along this trajectory here.
But look what happens.
He sees fewer and fewer of Alice's waves per unit time.
Eventually, as he gets way out there, a huge amount of time, of his time, transpires.
But he only sees one wave.
And then as he goes further and further,
into the distant future, along his accelerated trajectory,
he sees the last wave right over here,
but he never sees Alice cross the horizon.
He cannot see Alice cross the horizon.
So, from his point of view, Alice waves slower and slower and slower,
and eventually just comes to a frozen halt,
where she appears to be frozen on just,
just outside the horizon.
How close to the horizon?
Well, let's say, let's take that point over here.
That corresponds to some hyperbola,
and that hyperbola tells you how far she is from the horizon at that point.
So, that's Alice.
From Bob's perspective, he's going to see Alice in the exact same place, right?
He sees Alice...
She's frozen in the exact same place.
Yeah. Right.
So, that means there's some information that's being obtained.
This is a classical picture of the black hole.
There's none accounting for the quantum mechanics of the black hole.
So, from a completely...
Look, what would Bob actually see?
Imagine Alice, you see her wavings getting slower and slower.
She's sending out light waves.
It's the light waves that Bob sees.
How does she send out light waves?
She sends out light waves by taking electric charges and wiggling them, right?
It's our atoms that do the wiggling, of course.
Bob sees Alice's wiggles of her charges slow down.
What does that say about the light that Bob sees?
At first, it's optical waves.
Then it becomes infrared.
Eventually, it becomes long wavelength radio waves.
Bob doesn't see Alice anymore.
But maybe his long wavelength radio can pick up a few of her waves.
But then her wavelengths get so long, or the frequency gets so low,
that Bob just doesn't see anything.
So, really, strictly speaking, Alice just fades away.
She just fades away from Bob's point of view.
Her radiation goes from being optical radiation to being thousands of miles long,
not infrared, but radio waves, and even longer.
So Alice fades away.
How about Alice? What does she see?
You might think maybe that means that Alice sees Bob speed up.
So let's look at what Alice sees.
One quick question before you get to...
Yeah.
But as Alice is fading away, she's also getting smaller, right?
More squashed.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
If I'm falling onto the horizon, I slow down from your point of view.
I don't get squashed this way.
I get squashed this way.
Right.
It's a form of Lorentz contraction.
But, yes, that's what it sees.
How about Alice?
What does Alice see?
Alice looks back.
Let's draw...
Let me draw a little cleaner Alice here, now in green.
This is Alice's clock.
Alice's clock doesn't do anything very special.
She looks back and sees Bob.
And she sees Bob.
Even after she passes the horizon, she sees Bob.
What she sees is Bob accelerate away from her.
Bob doesn't disappear from her horizon.
Bob doesn't disappear from her perspective when she crosses the horizon.
Not at all.
What does happen is she sees him accelerating away from her.
Okay.
So that's what happens to...
That's Alice's view of things.
She doesn't see Bob speed up.
Bob sees her slow down.
But she doesn't see Bob do anything special when she passes the horizon.
Bob looks perfectly normal.
She can send him...
Oh, no, sorry.
He can send her signals.
He can send her signals from...
Yeah.
But she can't send...
He can send her signals.
That goes this way.
He's sending her signals.
But she cannot send him signals.
So it's a kind of one-way barrier.
The horizon is a one-way barrier.
Is his light blue shifted?
No, actually not.
Well, it means as seen by her?
As seen by her.
No.
As a matter of fact, since he's accelerating away from her, her light is red shifted.
His light is red shifted.
He's more and more Doppler shifted toward the red.
So, no.
His light is red shifted.
He sees...
She sees him red shifted.
He sees her red shifted until she just fades away.
Okay.
So, it's totally asymmetric.
All right.
That's the picture of Alice and Bob falling into the black hole.
Yeah, question.
Yeah.
Does this apply to gravitons?
So, Alice's gravitons are never seen by Bob.
Right.
And her colleagues.
And all the infinite number of colleagues.
Yep.
Gravitons are just particles like photons.
But maybe...
Maybe.
Much harder to see, but...
Much harder to detect, but still, conceptually, they're just photons.
All right.
We'll see more from photons.
But once Alice falls in, the mass increases, so the radius increases.
Once Alice falls in, what?
Once Alice falls into the black hole?
Yes.
Like, we've increased the mass of the black hole, so theND so the radius does increase
a bit.
We'll come to that.
We'll come to the increase of the mass of the black hole, yeah.
If...
the rest of the black hole.
Yeah.
We'll talk about that.
If the gravitons can't escape, I would think that just
like the black hole not only dark,
it would be gravitation free.
But that's not .
No.
You don't feel gravitational fields
because there are really genuine gravitons coming at you
from the Earth.
I thought that was the force.
The field that carried the gravitational forces.
Virtual gravitons, which have no trouble
exceeding the speed of light.
Sorry?
Virtual gravitons have no trouble
exceeding the speed of light.
Oh.
What's true is I've been standing here a long time.
You can feel my gravitational field.
What in a sense you're feeling is
the gravitational force.
It was the gravitational field that was created
some time in the past, relative to you.
Now I move suddenly.
The constraints on the speed of light of gravitons
tell you that you can not see me move
or you won't feel me move.
Your gravitational field that I exert on you
will not change until light gets
a chance to get to you.
That's all it says.
Doesn't that save that light and that gravitational field
moves at the same speed?
No.
Everything I just said is also true of
electromagnetic
Fields if I were highly charged and you were also highly charged
We might either repel each other or attract each other. He's supposed to laugh at that but
All right, and that would be a sort of steady-state situation, but if I suddenly moved
You would only detect my field changing by
I have to like that view at light speed and light speed
I mean, but but right but you just said virtual gravitons go at infinite speed
I don't know the distinction between virtual gravitons and what you've just described I guess
If it's perfect you're not your main then that's fine
Virtual gravitons you can just think of as the
Units of gravitational field which make up the static gravitational field of a stationary object, right?
They don't have to escape from the black hole. They're there. They're there. They're there these
Okay
Let's talk about this puzzle of what you see when you watch your feet fall through the black hole as you're falling
Everybody always gets confused about that what happens when I see my do I see my feet pass through the black hole horizon
How can I see my feet pass through the black hole horizon?
So let's let's set up that problem
Alice is falling into the black hole
Here's a feet her feet fall through first, okay, she's falling feet for feet first
Right
Here's Alice's feet. I'm not gonna try to draw feet. Yes. I will. Here's her feet. I
Can't draw feet. Okay. Here's a feet
That's the world line of her left foot
The world line of her head is over here. It follows her in falls in later. So here's Alice's feet. Here's Alice's head
Alice is looking at her feet
Okay, so at this point over here
She certainly sees her feet, but she sees her feet over here
She doesn't see her feet at the instant when she looks at them. She sees her feet slightly in the past
Alice sees her feet from here. There's Alice's foot
Alice sees her feet from here
Alice sees her feet from here and she sees him from here
Yeah
right, she looks back and sees the
Light coming to her from her feet
Here's the light coming to her from her feet along a 45 my 45 degree angles are not
Particularly accurate, but they're supposed to be all right. So light comes from here Alice sees it
She's wiggling her toes and their toes are electrically charged. So the sending light
She's light here. She's light here. She's like, you know, there's no point that which she doesn't see her
At which she doesn't see her feet
of course
She doesn't see her feet from this point at the same time
From this point over here, she doesn't see her foot at that same instant of time. She sees her feet from slightly in the past
So there's nothing special happens when she passes through the horizon
Okay
now suppose
That her head stays out of the black hole and her feet
Which have already passed through too late a foot has passed through
But she decides at the last minute. No, I don't want to go there
Then what happens? Well, that's that's bad
That's not good. Let's see what happens
Alice's head
now whoops now takes off and
Separates from her feet
Okay
There's no way that she can avoid her feet being torn off by by the acceleration
So to keep out of the black hole, she has to accelerate away from her feet now her feet might get pulled
Okay, her feet might get pulled
But they can't get pulled fast enough to keep up with her
It looks like they're keeping up with her but they're not and the reason is the following as Bob moves faster and faster
in
Bob is accelerating away from the black hole
He's not really accelerating. He's standing still but when you stand still in a gravitational field, it's the same as accelerating
So Bob is accelerating away
think about this now think Bob accelerating away and
the distance to Alice or Alice
Bob and Alice this is now Bob and Alice Alice is dragging behind Bob at a
Fixed distance in your reference frame
What is it like in Bob's reference frame?
if
the distance
to Alice in your reference frame at rest is
Fixed and Bob is going faster and faster. What does Bob say about Alice?
Well, she's not so much going the opposite way is she's just getting lost she's getting separated farther and farther
because of
Lorentz
contraction
So Bob says oh
My goodness Alice is getting farther and farther away from me even though the observers at rest
Say that that Alice is a fixed distance away
She can't get closer because she can't get past this light cone she can't get up to the speed
She can't go faster than the speed of light
right, so
eventually from Bob's point of view here Alice just drags further and further and further behind and
If it happens not to be Alice and Bob, but happens to be Alice's head and Alice's feet
Then Alice's feet are just stretched stretched stretched away from her until
Bad things happen until they break
So once Alice's feet are behind the horizon she has two alternatives
four
Fall in with them no problem. Nothing unusual or stay out of the black hole and
she will be
Defeated
Defeated well, it's good
Now so far
We haven't discussed anything about the singularity of the black hole
So let's start to talk about the singularity of the black hole. Where is it on this chart here?
Where is it on this diagram? Let's clean up the diagram again
Let's get rid of the head and the foot
And let's come back to the Schwarzschild metric let's rewrite the Schwarzschild metric
Dt squared times 1 minus 2 n
mg over R
With a minus sign and with a plus sign 1 over 1 minus 2 mg
over R
The R squared and then there's another term R for the for the angular coordinates. Let's suppress that not worry about
The
Term which has the negative sign is always time you always recognize time
Or the time like variables
By a minus sign in front of their metric
You recognize the space like variables
ordinary space by a positive sign in the metric
But something happens when R crosses
2mg when R is greater than 2mg this is positive 2mg over R is small 1 minus a small number is positive
But when R gets smaller than 2mg
Suddenly the sign changes here
The sign also changes here
it means that somehow R is becoming a time like variable and
T is becoming a space like variable that this does not mean that anything dramatic something space turns into time behind the black hole horizon
This is a feature of a peculiar set of coordinates
When you go past the horizon the coordinates interchange?
What's happening?
Here is something like this if you were to move in
Along a surface of constant time toward the horizon
You would get to the horizon
You would R would be decreasing are
decreasing decreasing decreasing until it gets to 2mg and
Then where does it go from there?
Then suddenly when R gets past the horizon it becomes a time like variable
a time like coordinate
R goes up that way
What about if Omega is a little bigger or T is a little bigger?
So we come in also to the horizon this is Omega equals zero
This is Omega equals one one unit of time later
We also come in and we hit this point here
And then these coordinates these Schwarzschild coordinates which are peculiar coordinates suddenly make another turn and go off here
So they're funny coordinates, there's nothing special happening over here
It's just a choice of coordinates that you've used
Where on one side of the horizon R is a time like a space like variable on the other side of the horizon?
It's a time like variable and vice versa
Time turns into space space turns into time, but nothing really is happening at this point. It's just an ordinary
generic point of space-time
Okay, now let's go to where the singularity lies
The singularity is that R equals zero. That's a nasty place. There's something very dramatic happening there tidal forces become infinite
curvature becomes infinite
All hell breaks loose at the singularity
That's R equals zero
Well as we start coming in we go to R equals 2mg. That's not zero
Then we continue along
The R axis think of it as the R axis
But the R axis makes a right angle turn until we get to R equals zero and that's over here
This is R equals zero
We do the same thing on another curve
And we come to R equals zero over here
If we connect all the points that correspond to R equals zero together, it looks like this
It looks like a hyperbola. It is a hyperbola
That hyperbola is the singularity
Let's draw it having our nasty wicked points because it's highly curved and very unpleasant
You sort of thought originally that the singularity was a place
A place means a place is a vertical world line
But it's not a place. It's a time
Moving along here the singularity occurs after a certain amount of time
Not really a place. It's a kind of time. There's the singularity
That's the nasty place, okay, let's um, let's think about now poor Alice who
Has
Fallen behind the horizon here. She's over here
Where does she go next?
She wants to escape the terrible fate of falling into the singularity
She can try to get out
Or she can try to go that way either way
She cannot escape. There's no way that she can without a seat and without exceeding the speed of light
She cannot escape the fate of falling into the singularity
So that's another property once you pass the horizon
That's it. You have no chance but to fall into the singularity
Not only can't you communicate to the outside but you're doomed you're doomed by the singularity and
That there's one more feature of the black hole
Now the mathematics of this metric
It's now we come to a real curiosity
but it's a
mathematical artifact
Which we're going to find doesn't really mean anything physical, but still is a mathematical artifact
This geometry here is the same if you turn time to minus time in
fact these coefficients here don't depend on time altogether and
What happens to DT squared if we take time to minus time?
It stays the same
This metric here is what a physicist would call time reversal invariant
It looks the same going forward as going backward
Well, that's a little bit peculiar because you can see over here
That sort of forward in time. There's a singularity
What it implies is that there must be a singularity also in the past and if you study this metric and
It's mathematical detail you'll find out that what it really represents is a time symmetric situation
with a singularity in the past and
a singularity in the future
Now Alice doesn't have to worry about the singularity in the past
There's no way she can get back to the past you can't get back to the past
She has to worry about the singularity in the future
Okay, she's gonna fall into the into the singularity over here
But let's just think of Alice's history for a moment
incidentally the meaning of saying that something is time reversal invariant is
the same as saying that a
particular history if you were to run it backward if
You are watching watching the events taking place and you were to run them backward
Meaning to say you would take a film of them and run the film backward that the backward film would also be a plus
You're looking at a possible
History which makes sense as a solution of the equations of the theory that's what it means for something to be time reversible
The equations of general relativity are completely time reversible
So anything that can happen forward can also happen backward. So let's think about what that means
Here's a history
Alice jumps into the black hole and winds up on the singularity there as she passes the horizon
Bob loses track of her can't see her
Well, if that's a possible history, then we should be able to fold it over
And say there's another possible
solution of the equations in which Alice is
created at the singularity and
jumps out of the black hole
Well, there's Bob looking back at the black hole
Oh, she has no trouble going this way
No trouble at all
She can't cross out from here well
The the time reverse of that has nothing to do with her ability to get out of this this is called a past horizon
Alice has no trouble at all getting out of the past horizon
it's
simply the time reversal of the statement that Alice had no trouble falling into the horizon the
time reverse of
Passing out here's the horizon time reverse of passing in is
Passing out so if she can pass into the horizon in the future she can pass out of the past horizon in the past
What does Bob see?
Bob looks back and sees something silly
He sees a Alice
ejected out of this black hole
That's silly of course right I mean that that's that's nonsense
So there's something wrong with this picture. We're gonna find out what it is
Hmm
No, no, no, no, no, no, here's
Here's Bob over here. He looks back. He actually seems to be able to see the singularity
That's in itself a little bit annoying
I mean, I mean, I don't know
I mean, I don't know
I don't know
Probably not
He looks back and he sees the singularity. Oh boy, and then he suddenly sees
Alice jump out from the singularity
What does that call anybody know what that's called this nonsensical configuration
Fiction. Yes it is
Well, the first thing is yes, it is possible is it likely no it's unlikely. This is called a white hole
White hole this is what a white hole is now white holes don't exist. They don't really really make sense
Isn't Bob also have a history going in Reverse at this point?
No, Bob is Bob is out here. He's just doing what he ordinarily does. This is not this is this is fictional
This is not something that makes a lot of sense
it's about as likely as
You well, what's a good example
You evaporate water from a puddle into a
Into space
Instead you see water
Materializing from space. Well, this this can happen candid. It's called just a condensation. I bet I better be I better be careful. All right
Obama explodes
Obama explodes and sends guns
And then he's going to throw garbage all over the place. All right, that's a possible history of
Let's say Newton's equations for a bunch of particles where
You start with a bomb
You know one of these old-fashioned bombs that Bolsheviks carried around
With a fuse
My grandfather would have had I'm sure and
You wait a little while boom
And stuff gets scattered all over the place. You'd be pretty damn surprised to see a bunch of stuff
flying inward
reassembling the bomb and doing it very delicately so that eventually it just had a little bit of a
Flame at the end of it that doesn't happen right? I'm not gonna happen
But wait a minute. It's a possible solution of the equations of theory of Newton's theory Newton's theory is completely time reversible
So what's wrong?
both are possible and
But we know very well that one of them is not possible
Okay, what the just throw words doesn't help
Yeah, it's entropy and it's a
One of them is clearly extremely unlikely the other is rather likely they're both possible
With the inverse process
Yes, but what these Comedy 120s do is their
optical
sampai
and Cyberinvesting in terrible worldsjukup
that comes to a point. It's very easy to roll a ball off the top, starting at rest,
just give it the tiniest little kick, where will it go? It'll fall down the
mountain. The probability that it will fall down the mountain is extremely high.
The reverse trajectory is possible, throwing the ball up to and just getting
up to the top, but extremely unlikely, the tiniest little bit of error and you'll
wind up missing the top. Another example, everybody here play pool when they were
kids? Billiards? You know, yeah, of course you did. You start with all the billiard
balls, all the balls racked up in a triangle, perfect triangle.
How many of them are there? 15. Right.
And,
you take a cue ball, you give it a good hard shot, and it goes scattering all over the
place. High probability that they'll just scatter all over the place. It would be
rather amazing to see 15 billiard balls, even if we didn't worry about friction
on the table, it would be rather amazing to see 15 billiard balls come together
and form a perfect triangle, with the cue ball going out that way. Pretty unlikely,
right? But both of them are solutions of the same equation, so both are possible
from the point of view of the ball, and the ball is going to fall down the mountain.
But the difference is that if you started those 15, 16 balls in a configuration which
was just perfect so that they reassembled into the triangle, and then the tiniest little
error, you would miss the triangle completely and all you would make would be a table full
of billiard balls going in random directions.
Yes, but also isn't it just as unlikely that you would have precisely the same thing
going the other way?
Every time you did it.
Yes.
In other words, each of these is equally unlikely.
Yes, yes, that is correct. But, you know, if you were just to say, I'm not, I'm
watching this thing and what I see is billiard balls scattered all over the place, yeah,
if you did it over and over and over again, you would get more or less the same pattern
every time of billiard balls scattered all over the place, and unless you were following
the billiard balls carefully, you wouldn't notice there was a difference.
Yeah, I think that's a good point. I think that's a good point. I think that's a good
point.
You wouldn't notice there was particular differences, but you would notice if the billiard
balls came together and formed a triangle. So, yes, you're right. I mean, any given,
I think your point is any given configuration is very unlikely.
Right.
All right, that's where entropy comes in, and, but what Bob is seeing here, and we're
ultimately going to understand this in terms of the entropy of the black hole, but what
Bob is seeing here, what we now understand is that the black hole is a black hole.
Yes.
What we now understand is he's seeing one of these very, very unlikely processes, not
an impossible process, but unlikely, where a black hole just sitting there suddenly spurts
out a full-fledged version of Alice, very unlikely, but not unlikely that Alice falls
into the black hole. So it really is very, very much the same thing. We're going to find
out that this is one of the aspects of black holes that has to do with their entropy.
Yes.
So, what we're going to do is we're going to go back to the black hole, and we're
going to go back to the black hole.
So, how do we know if an animal is in a black hole or not?
We're going to go back to green, but when I send the Sophie way, seeing Genesis
and African hermaphrodites, and if the shape of the colocaal equation is the same?
.
What's the likelihood that that person is
happened?
Wow
This action with black holes, but also has to do with their entropy. We've already
discovered. Black holes have entropy. They're in thermal equilibrium. They have thermal
properties. You could say the same thing about a pot of hot water. What's the likelihood
that if you drop an ice cube into a part of hot water that it will form a melted configuration,
very high right what's the probability to sit and wait and watch that pot that
an ice cube will get ejected out of it but both of them satisfy the same
equations both of quantum mechanics and classical mechanics so in that sense
they are both they are both possible the same thing going on here the horizon of
the black hole has entropy just like the pot of water hidden information very
rarely very rarely will the entropy of the black hole of the pot of water
assemble itself into an ice cube same thing here very rarely will the garbage
on the horizon of the black hole assemble itself into ejecting Alice
is that probability all quantum mechanical probability or is it the it could be both it's a
combination of quantum mechanical and thermal thermal fluctuations and
quantum mechanical fluctuations both are there but in the case of the hot water
of course it's mostly thermal great
ok let's take a five-minute break and then we're going to talk about Penrose
diagrams and we're going to talk about actually making black holes how you
actually make a black hole and why half of this diagram
namely the bottom half is completely on physical it's not something you ever
really have to worry about the bottom half which is the peculiar half of the
white hole yeah michael asked me a question and I realized in when he asked
the question that I was using a bit of jargon so let me just clarify the jargon
I used I told you that row was proper distance from
the horizon. The jargon there was proper distance. Let me just remind you what proper distance
means. It is a piece of jargon. It's similar to proper time. What is proper time along
an observer's trajectory measure? It measures wristwatch time. Right. But it's wristwatch
time along a curve. Right.
Alright, now we have over here Bob, and let's take Bob right at time equals zero.
He draws the straightest path he can to the horizon. In this case, a straight line. What
does it mean to say that this is a given proper distance away from the horizon?
Yeah, yeah. It's the distance measured by real yardsticks, or meter sticks in this room.
We don't allow yardsticks in this room. We allow meter sticks. Distance measured with
honest meter sticks. That's all it means. Now, little r, where is it? Little r up there,
I think I've erased it, little r over here, does not measure distance away from the horizon.
So, it's a distance measured by real yardsticks. That's what it means. Now, let's take Bob,
and let's take Bob. I think I've erased it. Little r over here does not measure distance away from the horizon.
There is a parallel goes to the horizon.
That's our value.
It's a después.
Right?
For general condition, we draw a slope at the horizon from the horizon by adding shared
land only, square root, and one-third plus.
Okay.
So, just once more, you.
Also draw problems.
So, just a second, wonderful.
administrative function just for fine sense of timeframe and so on.
Okay.
So, you'll remember that because this is a real gravity degree, this is a better
vacuum.
I see you're getting a little nervous.
Go ahead and show me.
great, they really are the way to understand all kinds of things in general relativity
and they're easy
they're easy to think about, easy to draw
a little bit difficult to actually work out in detail
but we don't need to work them out in detail
let's draw spacetime on the blackboard
in particular
let's draw just ordinary flat spacetime on the blackboard
well we don't have enough dimensions on the blackboard to draw four dimensional spacetime
so let's pick out two coordinates
one will be time and the other will be distance from the origin
now this is ordinary flat spacetime, so it could be t in rho
time runs vertically upward
t
and rho
is just distance from the origin
so it runs this way, here's the rho axis
we can make a grid out of this
by chopping up the time axis into intervals and extrapolating them horizontally
and we can make a vertical grid
so the first point here is rho equals zero incidentally, nothing to the left
because by definition rho and z are nothing to the left
definition, rho is always positive. It's the proper distance from the, it's a sort of polar
coordinate kind of coordinate. So it's always positive. And here it is. Here's all of spacetime.
This is rho equals zero along here. Rho equals one. Rho equals two. Rho equals three. Here's
t equals zero. t equals one. t equals minus one. Time can get negative in this picture.
And this is the history of the whole universe. How about light waves? Let's take a light
wave that comes in from the remote past, comes in, hits the origin. What happens after it
hits the origin? It just goes back out. It's not really bouncing off anything. It's just
here's the origin. My fist is the origin. It just goes right through the origin. But
in polar coordinates.
It comes in and goes out. So there's a light wave that comes in and goes out. A later light
wave might come in later and bounce out and so forth. Again, that's the history of the
world on a small blackboard. But it's not the history of the whole world. The blackboard
isn't big enough to describe the whole world. The whole world meaning all infinite distances
out to infinity and all infinite times from minus infinity to plus infinity.
So what relativists do is they make coordinate transformations. That's what relativity is
all about. It's about coordinate transformations. But in particular, coordinate transformations
which take the whole expanse of space and time and simply squash it by coordinate transformation
onto a finite region of the blackboard. What you get is called a Penrose diagram. And it's
a formula. There's a rule. And the rule is that however you draw the Penrose diagram,
basically only two rules. The first thing is use coordinates that gets the whole thing
onto the finite blackboard. Squash it and squish it until you get the whole thing on
the blackboard. But subject to the rule that light rays radially going, light rays always
move at forty five degree angles, this can be done for a very large varietale use for
characters. That can't just melt into plastic. Can't take free material from a manufactured
animal like metal. They might stop at only a very gas佐 relating these objects to the
region posea and cold air over the finishingudo and another way someone's going to lambda place
знает thatرة it's not going to the center, so whatever that race will not settle here.
drawing theelnorr drama as we start to Assessment, when do the problems on this here is that for ول centres,
of geometries that you can squish it down, squish it down, in such a way that the light
rays continue to move at 45 degrees. The result is called a Penrose diagram, and don't worry
about the mathematics of how you derive the particular Penrose diagram, just learn to
read them, because they're easy to read. Here's what it looks like. Here's what the Penrose
diagram of flat space looks like. There's the time axis, but it doesn't go from minus
infinity to plus infinity. Well, it does, but we draw the whole thing between some point
in the past and some point in the future, and that's the whole time axis. The space
axis also goes out to some point. That's really r equals infinity, or rho equals infinity,
but we squash it in. And the rest of it is just a triangle in here. There it is.
Alright, let's see if we can take this grid and re-plot it on here. Start over here and
work your way outward. That's t equals 0. And work your way outward. Here's rho equals
1, here's rho equals 2, rho equals 3, but we've got to crowd an infinite number of them
into here. So, they're going to crowd up like that. Likewise, let's take times. So, I'll
roll 5 times over this, times 2, 4, I'm just going to keep this in so I don't put it in
onder, but I get that it's always afforded in equation 1. Ah, it's a plus. And this way
I wrote the Since Assumption was the most Restaurant I've ever did. So, here's the defragmentation
here. And then it moves. Because we've got an infinite number of them in to here. So, they're
let's take time. Time 1, and they're going to crowd up as we go up here and likewise
down here. Let's try drawing this grid. Time-like lines, vertical time-like lines,
all go up to time infinity. That's up here. That's time infinity up here. So all
these vertical lines look like this.
More and more and more of them out here. What about the horizontal lines? They all go out
to rho equals infinity. That's all over here. It's all been squished or smushed into
a point over there. It looks like this.
Curved.
Curved. Okay, what about light rays?
In particular, light rays that are aimed from far away toward the origin. Light rays come
in from, first of all, they move on 45 degree lines. An incoming light ray would look like
that. That would be the image in this diagram of the light ray which came in like this.
It bounces off the origin and goes back out. You could have
earlier light rays that came in earlier and bounced back earlier. All light rays, all
incoming light rays, originate on this side of the triangle. Now that's really way, way
out at infinity, way down here. All outgoing light rays pass out of the diagram up here.
That's just asymptotically far away in that direction.
What about all time like lines? Time like lines are these observers? For example, these
people who are standing still. They might be moving a little bit. They all wind up here.
Where do they come from??? They come from here. If you walk out – you can't walk out
but if you imagine moving outward along one of these time lines here to a larger and larger
route…
you would eventually get over to here
this diagram and that diagram are the same diagram
this one has just been smushed or squished or whatever your favorite word is
so that it can all be drawn on the blackboard
but subject to the constraint that the speed of light stays
that light rays move at forty five degree angles
this is called a Penrose diagram this is the simplest Penrose diagram
and that's all it is
what else is there to say about this particular Penrose
are those light lines squished to meet the corners of each of those squares
as it goes through is that light line curved or is it always
as it passes through each of those squares
is it supposed to be passing through the corners of each one as it goes through
so it would slightly curve as it goes through the graph
I suppose it would be if we drew it accurately
if we drew it accurately it would be
yeah
I suppose this is true
since it's passing through the corners here
they all end up at ninety degrees to that
outside boundary
what about a light ray that was pointed not right at the origin but missed the origin
how would you draw that
we could come back here first and draw it here
well you still have to be forty five degrees so it would just intersect the higher lower point
no
teraz
it misses the origin never gets to the origin
so it comes in when it's very very far away
it looks like it's aimed straight toward the origin so it looks it follows this
route here
but
it doesn't quite get the origin it comes into a distance of closest approach
and then goes back out
so in fact it would look like this
it gets to a distance of closest approach and then goes back out
but of course there's angles involved that's an come out in same in the same direction than it can be
tried to perfect something like aisan here since we got it right
out in the same direction that it came in in, but on this diagram, alright, so same
thing here. A light ray that misses the origin just simply misses it. It never quite gets
to it. It gets to a distance of closest approach over here and then goes back out.
But then it's not going at 45 degrees.
Yeah, I said radial light rays are drawn at 45 degrees. Radial light rays, ones which
are aimed radially, right. Ones which are not radial, you have to worry about especially.
You have to take that into account. Okay, these different places, these different extreme
limits of the Penrose diagrams have names. Of course, this is just a time axis. This
one up here is called future time-like infinity. And it's usually just called t plus.
Or t equals infinity. Yeah, how about just t equals infinity. This one down here is called
t equals minus infinity. Time-like past infinity, time-like future infinity. What would you
call this one? Space-like infinity. So this is rho equals infinity over here. What about
these? Got a name for those?
These are the places where light rays come in from. They're called light-like infinity.
This one's called past light-like infinity. This one's called future light-like infinity.
And for reasons that I have no idea, this was originally labeled I minus, minus for
past and I for the future. It was always labeled with a script I and known as scry. Scry minus
and scry plus. Not my notation, so I don't have to apologize for it. Good. So that's
the Penrose diagram of flat spacetime. What about a black hole? What does a black hole
look like? So to get to a black hole, let's redraw the diagram that we had earlier. And
then try to see what it would look like if we did some smooshing and squishing.
Mm-hmm.
To squeeze it onto the blackboard. Okay. Here's what we saw. We saw way out here,
a space-like infinity. That's way out large distances from the black hole. Here are our
time coordinates like that.
Here was the singularity over here. There was also a past singularity over here. And
we never discussed what was on this side. We never discussed what was on this side.
I hesitated to tell you what was down here, but I eventually did. What's on this side?
Nothing of physical interest, but nevertheless, the mathematics of the Schwarzschild metric
contains all of this.
It contains an outside world over here and another outside world over here. This outside
world is not the same as this outside world over here. You can't get a message from here
to here, but the mathematics of Schwarzschild has both of these. We're going to find that
half of this is really quite meaningless, but for the moment, this is what we found
the metric looked like.
This is what the geometry looked like.
So let's ask what happens if we squish this. We're going to do the same kind of squeezing
to get everything onto the finite plane. And I'm just going to draw it for you. I'll show
you what it looks like.
You'll recognize, or I think you'll recognize it pretty fast. Let's see. I need some guidelines
to do it with. And I'll show you how to read it in a minute.
Okay.
So what happens if we start out here with this?
Let's start out here at r equals infinity. That's like r equals infinity or rho equals
infinity. That's like way out here. Where do you think it ought to go? Way out here.
This horizon over here, the bifurcate horizon, is right at the center over here.
Okay.
If I start at the horizon and go out to infinity, I can go this way, but I can also go along this line.
This is omega equals zero. This is omega equals one.
Where is that on here? And notice, in either case, you wind up sort of in the same place.
Same place, sort of. You wind up going out to r equals infinity.
r equals infinity has all been smushed down to here.
So where do you go? You go out to here.
Likewise from here.
That's the sequence of different time.
Now let's look at different radial distances from the black hole.
Different radial distances, I'm going to change color.
Different radial distances.
These are observers, if you like, who are stationary outside the black hole.
They go up to time infinity over here, and they look like this.
So this guy is 200 miles from the black hole. I don't know.
This one's 500 miles from the black hole. That's 1,000 miles from the black hole.
That's 10,000 miles from the black hole, and so forth.
This one over here is hovering right above the horizon.
And in fact, because he's trying to hover above the horizon, he must be accelerated.
To hover above the horizon takes some rockets that are going to keep him from falling through.
So that's him over here.
The other side is a perfect reflection of this side.
And this diamond here, that's the outside of the black hole.
That's the outside of the black hole. That's where Bob lives.
He lives out here, and if he doesn't want to cross the horizon, where's the horizon?
That's this.
Well, this is the bifurcate horizon. This is sort of the point of no return over here.
What is this?
That's the singularity.
That's the image of the singularity over here.
So here we go. Here's the singularity.
What's this one?
That's the past singularity.
The one that was down there.
Past singularity.
Future singularity, past singularity.
This is either r or rho equals infinity.
Either way.
How about light rays which come in?
They come in from here.
But now they don't bounce off the origin.
What happens to them if they're radially inward?
They're straight lines.
What happens?
Do they bounce off and go back out?
No. They fall into the black hole.
They pass through here.
And where do they wind up?
On the singularity.
There are light rays which go out to infinity.
Of course, they could have been created by somebody here.
One of these people here could have been created by somebody here.
But they're not.
They're not.
Maybe it was a liber Martha distant哇
or someone else talking about these
inge
datasets
In fact,
Some of the most transcendental podéis
WHO
into U.S.
The only way that the masked person could 저기
The only way his eyes can be the most
benefited.
You came to something.
Well, he saw it because the light was not coming out of the
east.
More Sagittarius electricity.
The people here could have had a flashlight and
past light like infinity this is called future light like infinity
okay and that's it that's the black hole that's the Schwarzschild black hole in a nutshell
drawn all of space-time drawn on a finite piece of a plane
radially moving light rays always 45 degrees
from this picture you can see a lot of what of the properties of black holes
well we've talked about them already we've talked about what happens when Alice falls in
when Bob stays outside here's Bob here's Alice except here Alice is a photon
but if Alice was moving more slowly but same thing would happen
and once you cross into this triangle here you're doomed
you have no choice but to go to the singularity now what is this region out here
that seems like a second world it looks like the black hole
this is the source of a black hole this is the source of a black hole
a lot of science fiction it looks like there are two worlds connected together by a black hole
hmm a wormhole right a wormhole however it's not possible to go from this world to this world
because even a light ray once it passed this horizon would wind up over here
so they're completely out of communication with each other
nobody on this side can signal anybody on this side
so from the point of view of anybody in this diamond here this doesn't exist
well that's a little bit glib isn't it to say it just doesn't exist
in fact the real story is a little bit different
the real story has to do with the way black holes are made in nature
this diagram doesn't tell you how this black hole was made
this black hole was sort of always there
from the remote past to the remote future
the schwarzschild metric was there
so it's a black hole which is eternal
black holes are not eternal they're made they're made by collapsing stars
so the next question that we want to understand is how is a black hole made
now a black hole before there's a black hole it's not completely empty space
stuff was coming in we can imagine let's let's take a look at this black hole
let's take an imaginary scenario
some particles come in from very far away
they might even be photons
when enough photons come in to a region of space
photons have energy therefore they have mass
enough photons and mass and therefore they gravitate
if you can get enough photon energy into a region of space you can make a black hole
so...
we can start with not with nothing
but with just a very diffuse cloud of photons coming in from far away
that's practically empty space
looks a lot like empty space
where's the diagram that represents empty space
that's here
that's empty space
no black hole just plain empty space
maybe with some photons coming in
after the photons come in if they make a black hole
then later what we should see is the black hole
the question is how do you put these together
how do you put this together in the past
with this in the future to represent the assembling of a black hole
so we want to go through that
we want to spend a little bit of time assembling a black hole
to do so I have to tell you a theorem
I think the theorem will do for tonight
and we'll go through the construction next time
but
it's called in Newtonian physics it's called Newton's theorem
in general relativity it's called Burkhoff's theorem
and it's a very simple fact about Newtonian gravity or about general relativity
it's easy to understand
hard to prove
let's begin with Newton's theorem
Newton proved this
it's a theorem about 1 over r squared forces
1 over r squared forces
can such as the Coulomb force in electromagnetism or the Newtonian force of gravity
1 over r squared forces can be described by lines of force
I'll just remind you about lines of force
here's your mass let's say it's a point mass
and imagine lines of force that are in the center of gravity
and you can see the lines of force coming out of it
the lines of force could also be flow lines of a fluid
coming out of a source at the origin
it could be two-dimensional with fluid spreading out over two dimensions
or it could be a three-dimensional source over here where fluid flows away from the source
and you draw lines of force
the lines of force begin on the charged particles
the circle or the massive object
and just go out and they don't end
they don't end of course unless there's another mass someplace or another charge someplace
but let's say there's just one mass
that's the
and what's the rule for the either electric field or the gravitational field
the rule is at any point the gravitational field
oh I think I will draw the gravitational lines pointing inward
why is that?
yeah because gravity attracts
so it's pulling on things
so the rule is at any point
the force on a test object
points along the direction of the line of force
that passes through that point
and what about the magnitude of the force the magnitude of the gravitational field
it's proportional to the density of the lines
if you think of if space is being filled up with a network of lines
the closer they are together the stronger the force
so lines of force it's an imaginary mathematical construction
you fill up space with these lines of force or lines of flow of a fluid
that is everything that you can say about the Newtonian field gravitational field of a point object
if you put two point objects together
then you just add the fields
which is exactly the same as saying I have two sources of fluid
in this case I guess this would be a sink of fluid because the fluid is flowing in
you have two sinks of fluid
the fluid is being pulled in
and so you have two sources
and you simply sum the field of both of them
which means you study the fluid flow of the two sources
juxtaposed
alright if you work out that
you figure out the field of arbitrary distribution of masses
now the Newton theorem is the following
it says if I take a spherically symmetric distribution of mass
and I'm going to take a very simple case
I'm going to take a shell
the theorem is more general than what I'm going to say
but I'm going to take a shell
a shell a thin shell
spherically symmetric of mass
here it is
you can think of every point on that shell
as producing fluid
if you look on the inside of the shell
there is no flow
how could there be
which way would the flow flow if you were inside the shell
well you might say
it flows radially
by symmetry it would flow radially
but if there was flow inside the shell
where would it go?
there's no mass at the center
I'm assuming all of the mass is on the shell
there's no place for the fluid to go
so if there's no mass at the center
there can't be any radial flow
there can't be any flow at all
so the interior of a shell of sources of fluid
has no flow at all in it
which is another way of saying there's no gravitational field at all
inside a spherical shell like this
what about the outside?
the outside
has a flow which is radially outward
the lines of force look exactly as if they had emanated from the point at the center
and the total amount of flow
is whatever the total amount of flow coming out of the shell is
in the language of gravitation
what it says is the gravitational field
of a shell of mass and
outside the shell
is absolutely identical to a gravitational field of a point mass at the center
but inside the shell is no gravitational field at all
so inside the shell
exactly the same as empty space
outside the shell
exactly the same as the point mass
there's a general relativity version of this
incidentally, let me say something else
this is true even if the shell is time dependent
for example, as long as the total amount of fluid coming out of it is conserved
if the shell were to change size
in a way that did not change the total amount of fluid coming out of it with time
it would still be true at any given instant
the gravitational field inside the shell
would be that of empty space
and the gravitational field outside
would look exactly like the point mass
it would just be the place where you go from outside to inside
which would change with time
so in particular if you had a time dependent shell of mass
which was contracting
with the mass staying fixed
then outside it
you would see the point mass gravitational field
inside you would see nothing
only the boundary between the two regions would change with time
the same exact thing is true in general relativity
almost the same thing
close, not quite, but close
so let me tell you what is called Berkhoff's theorem
and then the next time we will combine Berkhoff's theorem
with these two diagrams
and put together the theory of how a black hole is formed
so get Berkhoff's theorem, remember it
what does it say?
it says if you have a spherically symmetric distribution of mass
what do you see inside the spherically symmetric distribution of mass?
exactly what you would see if there was no mass at all
flat spacetime
empty space
flat
Minkowski, whatever you want to call it
just the solution of Einstein's theory with absolutely nothing there
just good old empty space
inside
what about on the outside, what do you see?
do you see a Newtonian gravitational field?
no, not quite
what do you think you see on the outside?
it's spherical mass, but what's the gravitational field on the outside?
Schwarzschild
in other words, the metric on the inside is exactly that of flat space
and the metric on the outside is exactly that of flat space
and the metric on the outside is exactly that of the Schwarzschild black hole
we can write it
on the inside we have good old the t squared minus the x squared, the y squared, the z squared
and on the outside we have Schwarzschild
I'm not going to write it
I think I could have written the metric faster than I could have written Schwarzschild
right
in other words, we piece together two things
both of which we know very well
connected together by a shell
how about the mass of the Schwarzschild solution?
Schwarzschild solution has a mass associated with it
it's just the mass of the total shell
does the mass of the shell change with time?
even if it moves, even if the shell contracts?
does the total mass of the shell change with time?
why not?
well supposing I tell you, supposing I just mutter the words E equals mc squared
conservation of energy
right
the mass, the total mass of that shell
even if the shell, and can the shell change?
of course the shell can change
you build yourself a shell
but the shell isn't strong enough to maintain itself against the gravitational force
if it's in the field, what happens?
it starts to collapse
as it collapses, the mass doesn't change
but the radius of it changes
what was inside was just good old flat space
what was outside was Schwarzschild
and the boundary between the two behaviors might change with time
so what we're going to do next time is we're going to take the flat space solution
that's the inside
and patch it together with the outside
which is the Schwarzschild solution
I'll show you how to do that
and in that way we will learn
in a very simple example how a black hole is formed
we'll find that half of this diagram doesn't mean anything
but we'll come to it next time
so, formation of a black hole next time
okay
for more, please visit us at
stanford.edu