Stanford University.
One thing that I'm confused about is vacuum energy.
I know you said when you
get the Planck scale it explodes.
My question in particular, does electron positron pair
production annihilation actually occur or is that excluded by?
Actually occur means what? That you can actually see
out of the vacuum electrons and positrons coming out?
Let's say measured vacuum density, if
that would be a fair measurement.
Electron, positron, virtual pair production. Virtual
pairs do contribute to the vacuum energy.
That doesn't mean
that you should see electron
positron pairs popping out of nowhere.
It does not mean that.
It means they pop out and go back in
a very short time subject to the uncertainty principle.
So it's quantum fluctuation and
not real genuine particles being produced.
It's much like the zero
point energy of a harmonic oscillator.
Classically the harmonic oscillator just sits still
at the bottom of its potential well.
Quantum mechanically it cannot both sit still
and be at the bottom of the potential.
There's competition and it's resolved by
a little bit of quantum fluctuation.
That quantum fluctuation has energy. How much is it?
Half h bar omega.
Okay.
It's always there.
You can't get rid of it.
It's the least energy that the oscillator can have.
Of course that doesn't mean looking at the oscillator.
Most quantum oscillators are too small to see.
It is the ground state.
And as the ground state it means it's the state in
which nothing is happening to the extent that nothing can happen.
Same is true with electron positron pairs.
Same is true with virtual photons.
And in fact,
it's a closely related phenomenon.
The electromagnetic field, for example, in a cavity, electromagnetic field
in a cavity is just a collection of harmonic oscillators.
Each oscillator has a little bit of zero point energy.
Add them all up, you call that the vacuum energy.
Well, I was saving that for a little bit later,
but, you know, because it plays an important role in cosmology.
Are you also going to talk
again about the 120 orders of magnitude?
No, I think I won't spend
a lot of time on that.
I didn't mention it.
But, no, I thought tonight in any
case we'd mainly concentrate on cosmic horizons.
What a horizon is, why there are horizons.
And, um...
And a little bit about cosmology, the equations of
cosmology, how they lead to an accelerated expanding universe,
and why the accelerated
expanding universe has event horizons.
I thought that would be a good thing to do tonight, since
we've spent a lot of time learning about what a horizon is.
We're not quite finished learning what a horizon is.
We've got four minutes.
I was going to say, you mentioned last
week, I guess it was, the ultraviolet, infrared relationship.
And you said you were going to
be getting to that. Is that tonight?
Well, we can talk about it. All right.
That's a good... Maybe we'll start with that.
Um...
Maybe.
It's not really on my
list of things to do tonight.
Maybe we'll get to it, though,
if I run out of things.
Okay.
Let's wait three minutes and sit and think.
I have a question related to
the question back there about vacuum energy.
If in a vacuum there is a positive energy density,
why would that have some kind of refractive effect on it?
Refractive?
Optically refractive effect.
What is refractive? Remind me,
which is refraction, reflection, and...
Is that the speed of light?
Speed of light.
Speed of light, for example, would be ever so slightly
less than the quantum vacuum as it goes through space.
Yeah.
The vacuum energy...
It's a good question. It's a good question.
Most energy that you think about, if you have that energy
present, it creates a situation where the world is not Lorentz invariant.
I don't mean that the theory is not Lorentz invariant.
I mean that...
The configuration of the world is not Lorentz invariant.
What does it mean? What exactly does that mean?
Let's first talk about something simpler.
Translation invariance.
Every place is like every other place, right?
No, it's not true. Stanford University is not like Berkeley.
The Earth is not like the Sun,
and it's certainly not like interstellar space.
So what do we mean when
we say the world has translation invariance?
We don't mean that the configuration of
the world, every place looks the same.
We mean if we took the whole thing
and moved it, it would look the same.
But moving it means moving
us, moving Berkeley, moving everything else.
Now, in the same way, you talk about Lorentz invariance.
Is the world Lorentz invariant?
No. I'll tell you why in a minute.
Are the equations of physics Lorentz invariant?
Yes.
So what does it mean for
the world not to be Lorentz invariant?
Well, it means that for whatever reason, the stuff in the
universe does not look the same from every frame of reference.
If I were to whiz by you at a thousand miles a
second, you would look different to me than if I were standing still.
So stuff in the world breaks
the symmetries that we talk about.
They create special locations.
They create special directions.
The equations of physics are
supposed to be rotationally invariant.
That means the same no matter how we rotate.
True enough, the equations
of physics are rotationally invariant.
But is this room rotationally invariant?
Certainly not.
If I look that way, I see you.
If I look that way, I see something else.
So the presence of stuff breaks symmetries.
And the presence of stuff breaks Lorentz invariance.
The world is not Lorentz invariant by virtue
of the fact that there's stuff in it.
Now, most of the times, the stuff, energy and
so forth, as I said, is not Lorentz invariant.
And the result of that is, in particular, a
result of the fact that there's no Lorentz invariant.
And in particular, a result
on the motion of light waves.
Light waves moving through materials have different
velocity than they have moving through empty space.
The rule about the speed of light is that
light always travels with the same velocity in empty space.
But that's another way of saying
that empty space is Lorentz invariant.
Empty space is Lorentz invariant.
Empty space is translation invariant.
It's rotation invariant.
Empty space has no preferred frames of reference.
And the statement that light always travels with the same velocity is a
statement about a Lorentz invariant world where there is no preferred frame of reference.
When there's a preferred frame of reference due to the presence of
material, light can travel at any velocity lower than the speed of light.
On the other hand, there are often2000 electricinking
forces that walk below the speed of light.
Vacuum energy is the one fortunate thing in the world.
But still, zumatiz
The vacuum energy has a certain
value, whatever its numerical value is,
a certain number of joules
per cubic meter, very, very tiny,
but nevertheless finite.
And so you might think, well,
that's like a material being here,
that's like a stuff being here,
and a stuff being here
would define a frame of reference
where the stuff would be at rest.
Vacuum energy is very special that way.
It does not define a frame of reference.
I could detect the vacuum
energy with a vacuum energy detector.
I won't tell you how to build one.
I'll tell you how to
build one in a little while.
We'll talk about how you build a vacuum energy detector.
I could detect the vacuum energy
and see how much is here,
or we get some number.
I would then go whizzing by
as fast as I can go
and do the same experiment.
If it was ordinary material,
I would discover that the energy changes,
the energy of that material,
changes with my velocity.
In particular, if I whizz past a gas,
then, of course, the gas looks higher energy.
Why?
Because all the molecules appear to be moving past me.
Vacuum energy is the one special case
where my vacuum energy detector will give the same answer
no matter how I'm moving.
So vacuum energy is the special case
where its presence does not change.
It does not change.
It does not pick out a special frame of reference,
does not violate Lorentz invariance,
and it's a special case where light will move
with the speed of light independently of the observer.
Now, moving with the speed of light means something.
It means when the light ray passes you,
passes right in front of your nose,
and you have your clocks and your detectors
locally right near you,
you measure the same velocity of light.
Because of the speed of light,
the expansion of the universe and so forth,
it becomes a more problematic question
of whether light moves relative to us far, far away.
When the light is far away from us,
does it move with the speed of light?
And we're going to talk about that.
The answer is no, not in general.
It moves relative to local observers
where that light is passing by them
with the same speed of light,
but it doesn't necessarily move
relative to us with the speed of light.
Faster, slower.
In this discussion,
is vacuum energy synonymous with cosmological...
Yes, absolutely.
All right, so let's begin there.
Why don't we begin there?
If we take the universe and
fill it with full of particles,
then, let's say ordinary particles,
protons,
fill it up, I don't mean fill it up
so that every particle is full,
fill it up so that every particle is full,
every proton is against every other proton.
I just mean create some uniform density of protons.
And, of course, the universe is something like that.
It's not so different.
There's a more or less uniform energy density
throughout all of space.
It tends to be clustered
into stars and stuff like that,
but on scales bigger than superclusters of galaxies,
it's homogeneously distributed,
rather diffuse.
Something, if I remember,
something like about 50 protons,
it's about 50 protons per cubic meter on the average.
And there's some energy density.
Let's give that energy density a name.
The standard terminology for density is rho.
And now that could stand for the mass density,
mass and energy being the same thing.
So that's the mass density.
That consists of a bunch of particles.
Now what happens,
and it's the number of particles per unit volume,
or the number of particles per unit volume,
is the mass of each particle divided
by a volume of space.
Take a volume of space.
The density of energy is the mass of each particle.
Let's suppose there's only one kind of particle.
The particles are standing still.
They're not photons.
Let's not get involved with photons right now.
They're just protons standing still.
Protons, neutrons, electrons, atoms.
Mass of an individual particle times the number of particles
en a volume divided by a mass of individual particles.
And that's what the mass of an individual particle is.
by the volume, that's the density. Now
what happens to that density as the
universe begins to expand? Well, the
number of particles doesn't change, at
least not if they're ordinary particles.
The number of particles doesn't change,
their mass doesn't change. What does change
is the volume of the region of
space occupied by those particles. So we
take some particles that started out in
a region of space a square on a side,
a hundred light years on a side, a hundred
light years, a hundred light years the other
way too. It has a volume of a
million cubic light years, which is
some number in cubic meters. That's
the volume that goes in here. The number
of particles stays the same, and now the
universe expands. Everything expands with it,
but only when you have a light years
of space on the other side. And then you
on sufficiently big scales, the volume of
space, let's say over some period of time,
doubles. When the volume of space doubles, what...
I'm sorry, I meant the radius of the...
I didn't mean the volume. When the radius
of this cube, the linear dimension of the
cube doubles, what happens to the density?
Well, when the radius doubles, the volume
gets multiplied by eight, and the density
becomes one-eighth of what it started. So,
ordinary material has the behavior, and this
is true for photons, for anything, not this
exact formula is a little bit different for
photons, but the general rule is that as the
universe expands, the energy density dilutes.
It decreases. The density of energy decreases
just because...
Yes, everything separates. Again, vacuum energy is
the exception. Vacuum energy is the exception.
Vacuum energy has the property, vacuum energy
density, vacuum energy density has the property
that as the universe expands, as the volume
of space expands, the amount of... the density
of energy does not change. The density. Not the
amount in the box, but the amount of energy.
All the energy stays the same. The density
of vacuum energy in this room stays the same
number of pac implementation, most of it.
victims
We can useан
a
It doesn't change as the observer moves
past it. It doesn't affect the wall覾
Exactly.
But whatever the density is, it endureado
it is power equivalent instead of age. If the universe were to expand by a factor of a hundred in every direction, the volume
of a region of space would go up by a million. Nevertheless the density of vacuum energy in this room would stay exactly the
doesn't change when the observer rotates, it's
not clustered, it's just uniformly filling space,
picks out no direction, picks out no
Lorentz frame, and picks out no special time,
in the sense that as
the universe expands, it doesn't change.
That's, energy of that type is called vacuum energy, if
it exists at all, and it does seem to exist.
What do we care? Why should we care if the
universe were filled with something that we call vacuum energy?
We do experiments, and the only thing we're interested
in this room, if we're doing experiments in this room,
is differences of energy. The zero point
of energy really usually doesn't matter for anything.
The thing which usually counts is differences of energy.
What's the energy difference between an
excited atom and an unexcited atom?
What's the difference of having, of
the energy with or without the atom?
The energy of an atom counts, but that's because we can
compare it to the energy of a configuration without the atom.
But just empty space, who cares? We could call, we could
just put as much energy into an empty space as we like,
as long as that energy cannot
turn into any other kind of energy.
As long as it doesn't come into the question zone.
Okay.
So, we've got a lot of differences of energy.
Why should we care if there's
something called vacuum energy in the room?
Well, the answer is, what I said is, we don't
care about the zero of energy until gravity becomes important.
Once gravity becomes important, what's
the source of the gravitational field?
The source of the gravitational field is mass.
Mass is energy.
Vacuum energy gravitates.
It has a gravitational effect.
It has an effect on space-time.
And it has an effect on space-time
which is different than if it weren't there.
So, let's talk about, well, the first
question is, what's the origin of vacuum energy?
And as I said, or somebody asked me earlier, vacuum
energy is, it wasn't quite asked me in these terms,
but vacuum energy is a feature.
A feature of quantum field theory.
Quantum field theory, quantum electrodynamics, quantum,
the standard model of particle physics,
all quantum field theories have vacuum energy.
It's just the zero point energy
of the oscillating fields, if you like.
There's a contribution to it from the electromagnetic field.
There's a contribution to it
from the electron positron field.
There's a contribution to it from quark
fields, even if there are no quarks present.
The point is, you don't need to
have anything really present to have that energy.
What does it do to?
It's due to virtual creation and annihilation.
Virtual, if you remember, means that it happens so fast that the
little bit of energy that is created and annihilated satisfies the uncertainty principle.
If you create some particles out of nothing, then
they can only last for a very short time,
because of the energy time uncertainty principle.
Let's leave it at that.
But the net result is that
there is energy density called rho.
And it fills up space.
It's everywhere.
It's Lorentz invariant.
It doesn't matter how you're moving and so forth.
Vacuum energy.
Let's call it rho vacuum.
Now what does it do?
It has an effect on the
right hand side of Einstein's equations.
Let me remind you what Einstein's equations are.
The details of them we don't need to know.
I will write down as much detail as
you need to know, which is very little.
But let me just remind you what Einstein's equations say.
On the left hand side of Einstein's
equations is a tensor called G mu.
G stands for gravity, I think.
It's a tensor.
And it's made up out
of the metric components of space.
The metric of space.
It's made up out of the metric tensor.
The metric tensor is little g mu nu of x.
It's on the left hand side.
It's got to do with curvature.
It's got to do with derivatives of the metric.
Christoffel symbols.
All sorts of awful stuff.
And by the time you write it down,
it takes up what g mu nu is.
It takes up a fair piece of space.
But it's got to do with...
Oh, I said it has to do with gravity.
I'm not sure it has to do with gravity.
I think maybe it has to do with geometry.
The g.
It's the geometric side of Einstein's equations.
It says some property of the geometry of space-time
This is space-time geometry, not
the geometry of space alone.
And on the right hand side...
In other words, it's the gravitational field.
Gravitational field, geometric field, however
you want to think about it.
And Einstein's field equations are that
this on the left hand side
is equal to something...
A numerical constant, but I'm not interested in...
A numerical constant is 8
pi over 3, but not important.
On the right hand side is...
The source of the gravitational field.
And the source of the
gravitational field is energy and momentum.
Energy, also known as mass.
And the motion of masses,
which is also known as momentum.
So on the right hand side, there's another tensor.
It's called t mu nu.
I don't know why it's called t.
But it's a thing which is made
up out of particles, out of ordinary fields.
Not the gravitational field.
The gravitational field, the
electric field, the magnetic field.
And...
If you know what this is, you
know what the ordinary energy density is.
The density of particles and so forth.
That's Einstein's field equation.
And...
On the right hand side is
all the various kinds of energy,
both those which dilute...
Particles, ordinary stuff, light.
The stuff which dilutes when the universe expands.
But also the stuff which doesn't dilute.
The vacuum energy.
So...
That's the reason we have to know about vacuum energy.
To know how the geometry of space-time behaves.
If there's only vacuum energy here...
I'll tell you what, I'm going to write these equations...
I'm going to write them out in full.
But for one very, very special case.
I told you that the left hand side
is made up out of the metric tensor.
And let's take a very,
very special case for what geometry,
for what space-time geometry is like.
In some sense, it's the simplest geometry
that's not just static space just sitting there.
I think we actually wrote it out last time.
It was the expanding...
Uniformly expanding space.
That I told you to think
of as an infinite rubber sheet.
Where the infinite rubber sheet is being stretched.
So that the coordinate marks on it...
We take a rubber sheet,
we mark it with coordinate marks.
X equals 1, X equals 2,
X equals 3, X equals 4.
And then we start to stretch it.
Okay.
The actual distance between
neighboring points increases with time.
And that's represented by writing a metric.
The metric...
Ds squared.
That's the space-time distance between pairs of points.
Neighboring pairs of points.
Just as it would be in ordinary Minkowski space.
We start with a minus...
This pen seems weak.
Minus Dt squared.
That's how we would have an ordinary Minkowski space.
Meaning flat space-time.
And then what we would
have in Minkowski space would be...
Dx squared.
Now, Dx squared here stands for the x
squared plus the y squared plus the z squared.
Which I won't bother writing.
It stands for the ordinary
Euclidean metric of ordinary space.
There would be some speeds of light in
here if I kept the speed of light around.
But I'm not.
But that's not the expanding space-time.
The expanding space-time...
You introduce one more thing.
A thing called a scale factor.
A of t.
A of t is a function of time.
It is not a function of space.
And it tells you...
Oops, I'm sorry.
This should be a squared of t.
A squared of t.
What it says is that if you take two points...
Let's say x equals 0 and x equals 1.
What's the difference?
What's the distance between them?
Well, it's one unit.
No, it's not one unit because
x doesn't actually measure physical distance.
It's this which measures physical distance.
The actual distance between them at
any instant of time is a.
And as a changes with time, the distance
between these marked points on the rubber sheet world...
The rubber sheet world, x equals 0, x equals 1.
The marked points...
The marked points separate, so a grows with time.
It doesn't matter if they're
separated by one unit, two units.
If we want to separate them by...
Let's say this is x equals 7, x equals 13.
Then the distance between them is delta x.
That's 13 minus 7, which is 4.
13 minus 7 times a.
a of t.
13 minus 7 is a?
Is it 4?
No, 13 minus 7 is 6.
Thank you.
Right.
Okay, that's the meaning of this metric.
They don't have to be on the x-axis.
They can be off the
x-axis, but you get the idea.
Okay.
This is a non-trivial geometry.
It has space-time curvature.
Unless a is constant, it has...
If a is constant, then it's
just flat space, good old flat space.
If a is varying with time doing things, maybe
just expanding, that's enough to make the space-time not flat.
Space may be flat, but space-time is a different story.
Expanding space-time is a new kind of geometry that's...
Good.
Okay, now let's write down Einstein's equations.
What do Einstein's equations have to do with?
They have to do with how a varies with time.
a is the only thing
in this geometry that's not known.
It's the only degree of
freedom for this kind of geometry.
For a geometry of this type,
all of the geometry is coded
in the properties of a ,
which means a is a function of time.
So Einstein's field equations must be simply
equations for how a varies with time,
and they are, and here's what they say.
They say that dA by dt squared is equal...
I'm going to put in all the factors now.
8 pi over 3 times Newton's
constant times the energy density of matter.
The assumption here is that the energy
density of matter is completely uniform in space.
You could have such a thing if space was filled
up with a uniform radiation bath all at the same temperature.
You could have such a thing if the universe
were filled up with atoms at a uniform density.
So we don't have to write
rho as a function of x,
because rho is not a function of x.
But of course we do have to
write rho as a function of time.
So rho is some function of time.
But what is rho as a function of time?
Oh, I'm sorry.
There's a 1 over a squared here.
Whoops.
1 over a squared.
It's a dot over a squared.
Do you remember from last time
what a dot over a is?
It's the Hubble constant.
But let's leave it there.
a dot over a squared.
That's it.
Okay, now this equation also
has another significance in general relativity.
It's one which confuses people.
I get zillions of emails.
I get so many emails about this particular point that I
can't keep up with them and I don't even try anymore.
This equation is also an equation for energy conservation.
It expresses energy conservation in general relativity.
The right-hand side is all
of the energy of ordinary stuff.
But it does not include
the energy of the gravitational field.
The gravitational field, because it's varying with
time, A of t, also has energy.
And that energy is a kind of kinetic energy.
It's a kinetic energy of motion or a kinetic
energy of the time dependence of the metric of space-time.
What is that energy?
That energy is simply the
energy of the varying gravitational force.
The energy of the varying gravitational
force is called the varying scale factor.
The energy of the varying scale
factor, A is called the scale factor.
One odd thing about it is
that it's negative in general relativity.
Minus a dot over a squared is probably
a factor of 3 over 8 pi g.
3 over 8 pi g, I think.
It's not the number that's important.
It's important that in the formal structure,
in the mathematical structure of general relativity,
gravity has energy and some piece
of the gravitational energy is negative.
And it corresponds to a negative kind
of kinetic energy of the gravitational field.
So what this equation can be
written as, it can be written as
minus this
plus this
is equal to zero.
Minus this plus this is equal to zero.
Well, zero is conserved.
Zero doesn't change with time.
Zero is zero.
It doesn't change with time.
So among other things, among
the many things that this says,
is it says that energy doesn't change with time.
It also says the total
energy of the world is zero.
But it includes this piece coming from expanding space-time,
which you're not used to counting.
So if we count the energy of this room,
we don't normally think about the
fact that the universe is expanding.
We just ignore it and we say
the energy in the room is positive.
OK.
Good.
Let's put it back the way that it was.
This equals this.
Let's go a little further now.
Let's look at what the time dependence of
the energy density in the world is like.
So let's come back to this box.
It's not a real box.
I've taken a region of space
and just drawn a mathematical box.
The mathematical box has a side
delta x equals one on each side.
How much energy is in it?
Well, it's the number of particles inside it,
number of particles inside it,
which is not going to change.
As the box expands, the particles move with it,
so that if this room
was part of the expanding universe
and you were a bunch of protons,
you would expand.
The protons wouldn't expand,
but the distance between them would expand
so as to keep the proton density uniform.
So there's n protons in there.
Each one has mass m.
That's how much total mass is in there.
And what's the volume of space?
The volume of space is delta
x times delta x times delta x.
That's one.
But times a cubed.
Why a cubed?
Because the actual length here is delta x times a.
So the side of the box here,
I've chosen a box whose side at
any given time is a of t.
And so to find the density,
I have to divide it by a of t cubed.
The only important thing here is that at any time,
if I know the energy,
this is the energy density,
if I know the energy at any given time,
then I know it at all times,
not because it stays the same,
but because it always scales like
one over a of t cubed.
So we can say that rho
of t then is some number,
we could call it rho zero,
rho is some particular instant of time
divided by a of t cubed.
So now we can come
back to this formula over here.
We can say, aha, I
now have an equation for a.
It's Einstein's equation for an expanding universe,
and what goes over here is
some constant rho naught over a cubed.
One can solve this equation.
Maybe we should solve it.
It's not a difficult equation.
It's much easier to solve
if we take all the constants,
eight pi g over three times rho naught,
and absorb them into another constant.
Let's just call that other constant,
let's just call it rho naught,
and thereby erase this.
Good.
Okay, how do we solve this equation here?
Let's write out what it is.
I bet you can solve it.
I'll have you solve it,
but first I'll manipulate it a little bit.
This is a dot over,
this is the a dt
squared.
There's an a squared in the denominator,
but I'm going to multiply through
and put it on the other side.
So we multiply by a squared,
and we get rho naught divided by a.
Is that right?
Right.
And now I take the square root of both sides,
rho naught divided by a.
I take the square root of both sides,
square root of rho naught,
a to the one half,
multiply so that it reads
a to the one half times dA
equals square root of rho naught times dt.
a to the one half on this side times dA,
or just the square root of rho naught,
we could write it this way.
Can you solve that?
Yep, say it again.
Right.
What we're doing is integrating both sides of this equation.
What Michael suggested is to
integrate both sides of this equation.
On the right-hand side,
we get square root of rho naught times time.
The integral of dt is just t.
And this one is what?
Three halves?
a to the one half, so that's integrated.
That's three halves.
No, two thirds.
Two thirds.
a to the three halves.
Is that correct?
And now we know a is a function of time.
Forgetting all the numerical constants,
two, three, rho naught,
what it says is that a grows
like t to the two thirds power.
The scale factor grows like
t to the two thirds power
because the energy density has a particular behavior.
That's cosmology.
That's standard,
absolutely standard.
Absolutely standard cosmological expansion.
a growing like t to the two thirds.
Let's just draw it.
a growing,
let's first draw a growing like t.
There's a growing like t.
a, t.
t to the two thirds is smaller.
It grows less rapidly than t itself.
This is, this large t is smaller.
And it looks like this.
Not quite a parabola,
but it looks like that.
It slows down.
A uniform line like this would be
an a which grows linearly with time.
It would be like a coordinate of
a particle moving off with linear motion.
That's not what happens.
What happens is it turns over,
and it appears to go slower and slower.
The universe decelerates in this kind of cosmology.
This is a decelerating cosmology.
What is it that causes the universe to decelerate?
Gravity is pulling everything.
Yeah.
Another way to think about it is
stuff started out moving away from each other,
and gravity just grabbed the whole
of it and slowed it down.
And eventually,
it'll get slower and slower.
Okay, now let's ask what happens
if we have a different kind
of energy on the right hand side.
We could put in, if we want,
just for fun, I'm not going to do it tonight,
we could put in radiation energy.
Energy solely due to radiation
as if there were no particles,
only photons in the universe.
That would correspond, you can work it out yourself,
that would correspond to the energy
that's going to be in the universe.
So, what happens if we're
putting A to the fourth here?
I won't, we don't have to go into that now,
it's just a fact.
You can solve the equations and
find out how the universe would expand
if it were radiation dominated.
The particular version that I
gave you is particle dominated.
It's usually called matter dominated.
Matter as opposed to radiation,
where the energy density decreases like one over A cubed.
Okay, but what happens now
is that it really is vacuum energy.
Vacuum energy has the property that it never changes
under any circumstances, the density itself.
The density itself does not change under any circumstances.
We need to give it a name.
Let's...
We'll put back, for the moment,
we'll put back the eight pi G's and so forth.
The theory tells us that it doesn't change.
Quantum field theory tells us it doesn't change.
It tells us that it's a sort of universal constant
that can be calculated.
Now, does that mean that the
universe that we know with certainty
that the universe is filled
up with a kind of energy
which doesn't dilute as the universe expands?
Theory doesn't tell us that.
What tells us that is experiment,
and we'll talk about the experiment in a minute.
Theory tells us only what
to put on the right-hand side
for various different hypotheses
about what the energy density is.
If the energy density is vacuum energy
in the sense of quantum field theory,
then it really is just constant.
Okay?
So that means what goes
on on the right-hand side here
does not vary with A,
does not vary as the universe expands,
and let's just call it rho vacuum.
Okay?
So rho vacuum.
Let's call it the vacuum energy density.
Rho vacuum is 8 pi g over 3.
Sorry.
A dot over A squared
is 8 pi g over 3
times this constant value of the energy density.
Now, first of all,
if this is correct,
then one thing it says is that
the Hubble constant,
A dot over A is the Hubble constant.
It says also H squared.
It tells us that H squared,
or H also,
8 pi g over 3
times the vacuum energy,
that this doesn't change with time.
Remember what the Hubble constant is.
The Hubble constant is the relationship
between distance and velocity.
Velocity is Hubble constant,
and distance is Hubble constant.
It's Hubble constant times distance.
So it says for all
time in this kind of world,
in this kind of world for all time,
the relationship between velocity and distance
is unchanged and always the same numerical value.
That incidentally would not be true
in the other solution we wrote down.
Normally, for other kinds of cosmology,
the distance between the two of them
decreases with time.
Here, it just stays constant.
An implication is that the distance out
to which you have to go
in order to get to the speed of light,
where stuff is moving away from you
with the speed of light,
that distance is always the same.
It's given by C equals H times D,
or equivalently, C over H is equal to D.
H is a constant.
The distance out to the place where things are receding
with the speed of light from us is fixed.
It doesn't change with time.
So that's one implication of what this means
to say that there's a constant value here.
But let's see now if we can now solve
Einstein's equations for an expanding universe.
Under the assumption that the only energy density now,
the only energy density is vacuum energy density.
All right.
So what do we have?
We have A dot over A squared
is equal to 8 pi G over 3 times rho,
but that's just the number H squared.
Let's just call it H squared.
Now, I'm using H now not to mean definition.
This is not definition now.
Previously, A dot over A was the definition
of the Hubble constant.
Now, it's the numerical value of 8
pi G over 3 times rho V.
It's a number.
It's a number that we
don't know how to calculate it.
We don't know the theory
of it, but it's a number.
H squared is now a number.
Everybody understand the difference between saying
H squared is A dot over A
is a definition,
and H squared is A dot over A
as a numerical relationship.
Here, H is not defined this way.
It just is a number.
It's measured?
It is measured.
It's a measured number,
and it's not expected to be,
and there's evidence that it is not changing with time.
All right.
So it's a number.
How do we solve this equation?
Well, first of all, we take its square root.
A dot.
We multiply it by A,
and it reads A dot
is equal to H times A.
I think some fraction of you can solve this equation.
Nobody can solve it?
All right.
A dot A is equal to E to the HT.
This is the equation that tells
us that the growth rate of A
is proportional to A itself,
exponential growth with time.
The thing which changes by an
amount proportional to its own value
exponentially grows,
and the growth factor, the time factor,
the time constant for this is H.
E to the HT is
the way this universe is growing.
Exponentially.
You can put a constant in front of it.
The constant doesn't matter much.
So this is an exponentially growing universe.
That's the result of vacuum energy.
Vacuum energy really is important,
and the way to detect it,
well, I'll give you two ways to detect it.
One is astronomical.
Measure the Hubble constant,
and measure the Hubble constant over a period of time
and see whether it's staying constant.
The other way is to measure the scale factor A
over a period of time
and see whether it's expanding exponentially.
There's another way that you
could measure it in the laboratory.
There's no way you're actually going to do this,
but if you have,
the laboratory now means way out in outer space.
Take two objects which are very light,
and therefore their gravitational between
them is not very important.
Start them out at rest,
and if they're light enough,
so the gravity between them is unimportant,
they will just expand with the expansion,
and you can measure the rate
at which the distance between them expands with time.
Make sure there's nothing else present,
complete vacuum.
So the only possibility is vacuum energy distorting space,
and you would discover that these begin to accelerate
and begin to expand,
separate from each other exponentially.
So that's how you would build a vacuum energy detector.
Now of course the effect in the real world
is so minuscule that you couldn't
even begin to hope to detect this
in the laboratory,
but you can detect it cosmologically.
How do you detect it cosmologically?
A number of ways, but...
You say, well we have to
check that H is constant with time.
That's going to take a long, long time.
But no, not really.
When we look out at the distant universe,
we see it at different times.
And we can actually measure the Hubble constant
at different times by looking
at it at different length scales.
Or we can look, what comes to the same thing,
is we can measure the expansion rate,
or we can measure how A varies with time.
All right, so I'll tell you
now how it varies with time.
Oh, wait, let's point something else out.
The real world doesn't just have an H squared.
It also has some other energy density.
Let's add in the other energy density.
It was called rho naught
divided by A cubed, for example.
When A is small, when the universe is small,
when the scale factor is small,
this term is going to be much bigger than this.
Why is that?
Because A is in the denominator.
That's why.
So early on in the real world,
this is not very important.
And this may be very important when A is small.
In that case, we worked
it out a few minutes ago,
and we found out that A
goes like T to the 2 thirds.
It goes like this.
But now as A grows,
eventually this term will get small,
whereas this one is not getting small.
This one's not diluting.
This one is diluting.
So eventually the diluting term
gets smaller than the non-diluting term.
And then after that, you can basically forget it.
Once this term gets smaller than
this term, you can forget it.
And how does A behave?
A behaves like E to the HT.
So what you expect in a
world that has both kinds of energy
is that early on, the scale factor
or the radius of the universe,
or the radius, the distance between distant galaxies
grows this way.
But then at some time,
when the vacuum energy becomes more important
than the other forms of energy, it takes off.
Exponentially.
Exponentially something like that.
When you solve that differential equation,
you end up with a C in front of the...
With a what?
With an integration constant in front of the...
Yeah, there's an integration constant here.
How do you know that
that integration constant isn't really small?
Well, you measure it.
You measure it.
And...
Here's T.
Here's A.
And of course, when you measure A,
you don't just measure A now, as I said.
You measure A by looking out
deeper and deeper into distant galaxies.
You can measure the
distance between different distant galaxies
at earlier times.
And so at one time,
you can measure this whole curve up to some point.
You can't measure what it's
going to be in the future.
But you can measure what it was in the past.
So if this is now,
we get to measure all of this curve.
And it looks something like that.
It looks something like
that, approximately something like this.
With this branch of it here
being fit rather accurately to an exponential.
I won't try to tell you how accurately.
It's about a 5%...
The proper figure of merit is about a 5%...
It's not a deviation.
It's exponential plus or minus 5%.
Okay, so that looks, to most cosmologists,
that looks fairly convincing
that we live in a world with vacuum energy.
Certainly, we don't know anything else
that would have much chance of doing precisely this.
And it's a...
It's...
It's not a fact in the same sense
that we know that the electron exists
so that the fine structure constant is
1 over 137 point blah, blah, blah, blah.
But by now, it's pretty
much considered a fact of cosmology
that we live in a world with vacuum energy
and that we live in an exponentially expanding world.
That's pretty remarkable in a way.
Good question.
I have a quick question.
I...
In some books, I've seen if
you take our position right now
and draw the slope down,
now we can...
If that slope intersects to the left of the origin,
you can see back to the Big Bang.
As it exponentially goes up,
there'll be a time where you
can't see past the Big Bang.
Is that...
In other words, we'll expand it away so far
that we can see it?
I don't quite understand that point, or is it important?
Well...
Um...
I'm not sure it's an issue of expanding back to...
of tracing back to the Big Bang.
Or to the cosmic background radiation emission and stuff?
Well, in the sense that the Hubble distance
is related to the age of the universe.
In the sense that the Hubble... Yeah.
Um...
Right.
The Hubble...
In this exponentially increasing world here,
the Hubble scale is not related
to the age of the universe.
It's just a constant.
Right.
But at some point, you...
Uh...
Oh, I don't know.
The...
There's a horizon...
There's a horizon.
We're gonna talk about horizons.
We're gonna talk about event horizons.
There's a lot of different
kinds of horizons on the market.
But the only ones which
are of deep and fundamental interest
are event horizons.
So we're gonna talk about event horizons.
So let's, uh...
Let's now just...
put in our back pocket this piece of knowledge
that the world is exponentially expanding,
that...
We can summarize everything that was on the blackboard.
Oh, there is an interesting fact.
If the world continues to exponentially expand like this,
then all of the dilutable matter,
the kind, the energy that dilutes with expansion,
is just gonna get more and more and more diluted.
Right?
So in some number of, um...
billions of years,
the material in the universe will stretch out so much
that it's gonna be more and more diluted.
And that's what we're gonna do.
So much that it will become of negligible density.
And the only energy left
over will be the vacuum energy.
It'll become a very dull world.
Uh...
But so be it.
Does that mean that, um...
the galaxies which aren't expanding today because gravity...
No, they won't. No, they won't expand.
They won't expand.
Uh, what will happen is
the few galaxies which are close enough to us,
which...
and which happen just by accident, more or less,
to be falling toward us.
There's one or two galaxies
which are actually falling toward us.
Uh...
That's a sort of...
When we say that everything uniformly expands,
of course, it uniformly expands
plus or minus little bits of fluctuation.
It happens that there's a little
bit of fluctuation in our neighborhood
which happened to cause the Andromeda galaxy
to be somewhat moving toward us.
So...
Us and the Andromeda are
not gonna separate from each other,
but, uh...
But, you know, if you
go out a few more galaxies,
they're certainly moving with the flow.
Anything which is moving with the flow
will eventually depart.
It will just grow and separate and separate and separate.
And after a few hundred billion years,
all that will be left for us to see
is us, our galaxy, and that's it.
We will be living in a world
where...
We'll be able to see out to enormously large distances,
but you won't see anything.
Well, astronomers who were born at that time
and don't have a good record of history
will come to the amazing conclusion
that they are alone in the universe.
Uh... Yeah.
Does that say that you eventually exceed
the gravitational attraction?
Because our galaxy is gravitationally bound to a group.
Well, that's a good question.
It's gravitationally bound to a group.
Yeah.
And if the group expands, then...
No, no, no.
If the group expands,
then we're not gravitationally bound.
Right.
So when you said all
we can see is our galaxy...
And the Andromeda,
which by that time probably will have crashed into us
and formed some sort of single structure.
But aren't each of the clusters
gravitationally bound to each other also?
Correct.
So...
Not... No, no, no, no.
It depends on what you mean by a cluster.
If you look at a few galaxies out,
not very many, just a few, one or two more,
they're moving away from us,
even though they form what's called a cluster.
Well, if they're gravitationally bound,
but they attract...
No, they're not gravitationally bound.
Gravitationally bound means that they won't,
that they...
that they won't separate.
So the measure of gravitationally bound
depends on this expansion rate.
Yeah, but not very much.
But not very... Hardly at all.
Hardly at all.
For nearby things,
if they're gravitationally bound,
can just mean whether...
Just forget...
Forget this expansion
and just ask whether they're moving relative to each other
with less than or greater than the escape velocity.
That's what gravity...
All right.
Now, it happens,
it's a more or less accidental fact
that the Andromeda happens to be moving toward us.
A few galaxies out,
they're moving away from us,
and they will continue to move away from us.
They're moving away from us
with greater than the escape velocity,
and they'll continue.
Yeah, it's like a galaxy.
The gravitational constant is a constant,
it never changes in time.
But the outward force
due to the vacuum energy
is a function of time.
It grows...
It grows with distance.
It grows linearly with distance.
It grows with...
Distance.
But not with time.
No, not with time,
except insofar as things separate with time.
Two objects will separate with time,
their distance will become larger,
and for that reason,
the repulsive force will increase.
But the repulsive force does not increase...
Okay, you have a small repulsive...
Very small repulsive force now,
and over a period of billions of years,
the repulsive force...
See from the equation,
that is sort of cumulative.
There's a bigger amount of repulsive force.
That's only because things get further away from each other.
But a galaxy won't get farther away from each other.
If the galaxy...
If two galaxies are at the same distance
at a later time,
as they are now,
the component of the little repulsion
from the vacuum energy will be the same.
What I was asking is that the net gravitational force
is G minus the expansion force.
And if the expansion...
If the force...
The tendency towards expand increases,
wouldn't the net effect be that G very gradually decreases?
That...
That doesn't make sense.
No, what he's saying is that
the force is a function of distance,
not a function of...
It's a function of distance,
not a function of time.
If you have two objects,
if you have two objects
at distance r between them,
at any time,
doesn't matter what time,
there are two components to the force.
One of them is G times m1, m2
divided by r squared.
And then there's another force,
which is proportional to...
on each of them,
or there's another force,
which is proportional to...
It has a G in it,
but mainly it's proportional to and repulsive.
This is minus meaning attractive,
plus a repulsive force,
proportional to r itself,
to the distance between them.
So the order of the change doesn't change?
Coefficients don't change.
What does change
is the distance between things.
Okay?
So as the distance grows,
this will become less important,
this will become more important.
But you're gonna ask,
where does this become important relative to this?
The answer is when the distance scales
are pretty cosmological.
You know, five billion light years
or something like that.
The crossover,
the coefficient of this piece is so small
that the crossover between
the normal gravitational attraction
and the bit of repulsion
is on the billions of light years scale.
So that's why you can't make
or measure it in a laboratory.
So it's not just a function
of expanding space
that is represented as a repulsive force.
It is the expanding space,
but you can fake it by a force
which is pushing everything else apart from each other.
It's a slight fake,
but it sort of works the right way.
Yeah.
Okay.
We've now...
Now, does that kind of,
I think, satisfies my curiosity here.
In the early universe,
these galaxies were gravitationally bound,
and the expansion has now taken them
to where the vacuum expansion,
this other factor, are.
In the early universe,
they were not gravitationally bound.
It's crossed over.
So the gravitational attraction field
is falling below.
When they get far enough apart,
then the repulsion becomes more important
than the attraction.
Right.
So in the early universe,
they were gravitationally bound.
Well, yeah.
This was not important in the early universe.
Right.
That's another statement.
It's two different statements
to say that they're gravitationally bound
and that the important force
was the ordinary gravitational force.
If we shoot a rocket
off the surface of the Earth
at one and a half times the escape velocity,
it is not gravitationally bound.
But still, the most important force on it
is the ordinary gravitational force.
These are two different statements.
One statement, gravitational bound,
means it's going to come back.
The other statement is,
this may be more important than this
in the early universe, and it was,
but it doesn't mean that the gravitational force
is going to come back.
So, in the early universe,
it was gravitationally bound.
But it doesn't mean that the galaxies
were gravitationally bound.
They were still moving apart from each other
with greater than the escape velocity.
For the most part.
I mean, pretty much.
Galaxies were sort of shot out
at pretty much greater than the escape velocity
between them.
Roughly.
At very close to the escape velocity.
Very, very close to the escape velocity.
Extremely close.
But it's not.
Extremely close to the escape velocity.
And then,
they either turn around
and fall back in,
or they accelerate away from each other,
depending on whether there's this
kind of new energy.
Okay.
Let's take a little break.
And when we come back,
I will tell you more about
the geometry of
this kind of space,
and why it has horizons.
What it means for it to have horizons.
So now that we know
that in a couple of hundred billion years,
the universe is going to be described,
and it's getting that way pretty quickly, actually.
On the scale of
tens of billions of years,
we're getting there pretty fast.
We're getting to a condition
where the geometry of space-time
is described
by a metric,
and the metric is
the energy of the universe.
And the metric is
e to the 2 h t,
that's a squared,
times dx squared.
And again, dx squared stands for
dx squared plus dy squared
plus dz squared,
and this is the scale factor.
This space-time,
it's a space-time,
it has a geometric property,
it has a name.
Anybody know what the name is?
The Sitter space.
It's the Sitter space.
It should be called
the Sitter space-time, obviously,
but it's called the Sitter space.
And
we'd like to examine
its properties a little bit.
Not because,
not because
uh
we're going to be sending
rocket ships out there to explore it,
that's going to take a while,
but just for the intellectual value of understanding
the space-time that we live in.
And it's pretty weird.
It's pretty weird, of course it looks weird,
but it's weirder than it looks.
Um,
it's weird in that it has horizons.
Before we get into horizons
of the Sitter space,
let's just talk for a moment
about what horizons are in general.
And
I'll give as the illustration
the horizon of a black hole.
Remember we
worked out what a black hole
formation, a black hole
which is created by an
infalling collection of
material, what it looks like.
And we drew a pen, remember the
Penrose diagram?
Penrose diagram looked like that.
Before we do that, we're going to use
Penrose diagrams, so,
because it's helpful.
But let's first draw the Penrose diagram of ordinary
flat space.
There's ordinary flat space, there's
points far away,
it's spatial infinity,
here's time infinity, light rays
come in from here and they go out from here
and all that sort of
stuff. And that's just empty space.
Okay?
A black hole space-time looks like this.
Oh, one other point.
Imagine
an object, a massive
object, not a photon, a massive
object in this
space. How does a massive object
move through space-time?
Well,
all massive objects
wind up at the same
place. They were massless
objects. Photons go out
the sides here,
moving with the speed of light. Massive
objects, they all
go to this point up here.
Now that's
not really a point.
It's not really a point. It's a whole
big space-time that's been smushed
onto the diagram.
To look small.
Obviously, if we wanted to take all of
space-time and squeeze
it onto the blackboard, we're going to have to
distort it pretty badly.
And it's very distorted up here in that there's
an infinite amount of space and time
up in this corner. Likewise here.
Likewise here. In fact, on all of the
edges. And all
of the massive
objects eventually
wind up at this corner. That's
not to say that they get close together.
It's just to say that
this is a very big place up here.
Okay.
Now let's
think of the massive
objects in the black
hole space.
In the black hole space, you can have one of
two things happening.
The massive object can fall into the
horizon and hit
the singularity.
Let's avoid that.
Let's avoid that. Let's talk about the objects
which don't fall into the
singularity.
Where do they go?
They go to here.
They all do.
Again, that doesn't
mean that they literally get close together.
It just means there's a lot of space time
out there.
All of
these people wind up.
Let's draw the horizon. The horizon's over here.
Okay. Now
let's ask what these
people here can see as
they look back into the past.
They can see
only those things which are
inside their backward
light cone. Backward
light cone means take all the
light rays which can get
to this point over here.
All the light rays
come in from here and
take that region.
That's the region
that he over here can be aware
of. When he looks back,
he can only see the things inside his light cone.
Same for this guy over
here.
Same for this observer.
They can see
things in their backward light cone.
Now, how much can they
see given arbitrary
amounts of time?
Given arbitrary amounts of
time, they can look back
from later and later times
and eventually they can
see all
of this blue region here.
What they cannot see is what's in
here.
A horizon
is by definition
the place which separates
the region that these observers
can see from where they can't see.
Given enough time,
you draw
the backward light cone of a very
future point along that observer's
trajectory, and that
is the region he can see.
Everything on the other side is behind
the horizon, and the horizon is the
separation between them.
Here, there's no horizon.
An observer way up
here gets back,
looks back, and sees everything.
Sees the entire space-time.
No horizon. Here there's a horizon.
So I just remind you
of that to
tell you what a horizon is.
We're now going to take this
metric, and we're
going to do a little bit of mathematics on it.
It's not hard mathematics. It's pretty easy
mathematics.
It's not particularly abstract,
but it
helps us visualize
the space-time.
What we're going to do with it is we're going
I'm not going to try to take all of
space and squeeze it onto
the blackboard. I'm going to leave space
infinite, but what I'm going to do is
take the time axis,
and I'm going to schmush it.
I'm going to make a coordinate
transformation of time
so that I can put the entire time
from minus infinitum, well not from minus infinitum,
minus infinitum will be deep down
in the floor, but
plus infinitum will be in some
finite place here.
Because we're going to want to
study
what this world is like at
late times. And I'd like to get the
whole infinite future
onto the blackboard.
Not the whole infinite future
of space, but the whole infinite
future of time. So we're going to
make a coordinate transformation,
and we're going to do this in a way
that makes light rays
move on 45 degree angles
in this space.
It's always good to do
that. Always get the light rays
moving at 45 degree angles, and it's
easy to see what can communicate
with what.
Alright, so here's the trick.
We're going to change
coordinates. We're going to introduce
a new coordinate, I'm going to call it
capital T, and it's
a function of the old
T. And it's
going to have the property, here's the property
it's going to have.
It's going to be such that
dt squared
what appears here
is going to be equal to
e to the
2ht, exactly
what appears here, times
d capital T
squared.
This is the definition of capital T.
It's a new time
coordinate, and it's really
related to the old time coordinate
by a pretty simple equation.
We're going to solve it.
And then we're
going to rewrite the metric
with the new time
in place of the old time, and the
metric will have a nice appearance
that will allow us to explore it
very nicely.
Okay, how do I solve for
big T as a function of little t?
The first thing I do is take the square
root of both sides of the equation.
dt
is equal to e to the
ht d capital
T.
And now divide
by e to the ht.
What do I get on the
left hand side if I divide by
e to the ht?
e to the minus ht, right?
So we'll put an e to the minus
ht here.
And now we have
dt.
Well all we have to do to find the
relationship between big T and little
T is to integrate.
The integral on the right hand
side just gives us T.
What about the
left hand side? Anybody can do that integral?
Dime for anybody?
1 over h.
Minus sign.
e to the minus ht.
e to the minus ht, right?
Plus a constant, but we
can fix the constant
by just shifting
T here.
There's a constant, but I can shift the
constant. Suppose I put a constant.
Now I just redefine T so that it's
T plus C. That doesn't make any difference.
Right. Okay, now
notice first of all capital T
is negative.
Let's just think about what happens to it.
This 1 over h here is not so important.
Let's see what happens to it. What is it
like at very remote
past times?
Let's say when little T here
is extremely negative,
what happens to e to the minus ht?
It becomes very big.
If T is negative
and we have e to the minus,
this becomes e to a positive
number, a big positive
number. This gets very big,
but there's a negative sign out here.
So that means the remote
past, where
little t is very, very negative,
is also the remote
past from the point of view of big T.
When little t gets very,
very negative,
so does big T.
So in both variables,
the remote past
is way down through the floor in the basement
and even deeper.
What about the remote
future?
What happens in the remote future
to capital T?
The remote future is when little t is
very, very big.
What happens to this when little t is very big?
It goes to zero.
So big T goes to zero
in the remote future.
Now we can draw it.
The time axis,
let's draw the time,
the big T axis.
The big T axis
goes into the very
remote past
in the negative region,
deep past,
and
then
the remote future.
But where is the infinite future?
The infinite future is
right at capital T equals zero.
Capital T equals zero.
That also is
little t equals infinity.
So
big T
runs from minus infinity
up to zero.
That's one way of getting
not the whole geometry on the blackboard,
but getting the remote future
onto the blackboard.
That was the goal.
Okay, let's see if we can
rewrite the metric.
Let's see if we can rewrite the metric
in terms of big T instead of little t.
So here we have
little t squared. What's the relation between
little dt here?
Little dt,
here it is,
little dt
is equal
to
e to the big
ht
times big T,
right?
Good?
I just
multiplied by e to the ht
to get it over on this side
over here.
And now we come to this metric over here.
We have minus dt squared.
So this is equal then to minus
dt squared,
plus e to the 2 ht
the big T squared.
And then we have
plus e to the 2 ht
the x squared.
In other words,
I've engineered it
so that the e to the 2 ht
would come on the outside
would be equal to
e to the 2 ht
times
the
t squared.
So this is
the common
Minkowski space metric.
This would be the metric of
ordinary flat space time
minus dt squared plus
the x squared plus the
y squared plus the z squared
but it has this factor in front of it.
How about this factor that's in front of it?
What can we do with it?
I want to re-express it
in terms of capital T.
So let's do that.
Let's first multiply by h.
e to the minus
ht
equals h times
big T. All I did was
multiply by h.
And now let's square it.
If I square it, the minus sign
goes away and I get
e to the minus 2 ht
and this side I get
h squared t squared.
And finally,
I take
1 over it.
So that e to the 2 ht
is equal to
1 over h squared
t squared.
Go through it,
check the arithmetic,
you'll find it works
that way.
And now we can write this metric
just by substituting
for e to the 2 ht
1 over h squared t squared.
So let's put that there.
In fact, let's write it over here.
ds squared
is equal
to 1 over h squared t squared
times
minus dt squared
plus dx squared.
Okay, now this is a long story.
Nice simple result.
But the main point of it,
the main point of it
is that we've written the metric
as an ordinary Minkowski space
metric times a function
with the same function
appearing multiplying all of this.
How do light rays move in this geometry?
What's
the rule for light ray?
ds is 0.
Right. Light rays move on
paths of
proper time.
Okay. What does that say?
That says
that you can forget this factor
altogether when you're thinking about a light ray.
If you want to know how a light
ray moves, you don't
need to know about this factor.
All you need is this factor.
Alright?
Everybody see that?
If you want to know how
a light ray moves, it moves exactly
as it would if this were
just ordinary flat space time.
How do light rays move in flat space time?
On straight lines tilted at a
45 degree axis to the vertical.
Okay.
So we now know
in this geometry how light rays move.
Let's draw the geometry.
Here it goes. It starts out
deep in the past.
We can't go down that deep into the basement.
But it ends.
This is space. Space
now goes this way.
And this way.
It ends at capital T
equals 0.
How can it end at capital T
equals 0? Little t went on and on
forever. Well, it's
just that the metric
when big t gets small,
the metric
here blows up. It gets big.
So that means there's a lot of
time in here.
The metrical distance between
neighboring points gets very large
when t goes to 0.
So it's highly
distorted. I mean it's a highly
distorted geometry.
The one advantage of it
is that light rays move on
45 degree axes.
So we now know how light rays
move. They move
like that.
If they're moving out of the blackboard,
they also move on 45 degrees, but I'm not
going to try to draw it. I can't draw it.
All right.
Good.
Now let's ask what an
observer can see. Imagine
an observer in this world.
I'll make
him blue.
Here she is.
She's standing
still in her own reference frame.
Time is going on
more and more and more
time is unfolding.
And eventually
she gets up to the top.
Now how long does that take according to her watch?
Forever.
Right? Takes forever for that to happen.
But on this diagram,
on this formal mathematical
abstract
description of the Sitter space,
the terminal
point is over there.
That's the end of her existence.
Doesn't bother her at all because her clock
has gone off to infinity.
Let's ask what she can see.
What she can see is
she looks back.
All right. Let's draw that in red.
Here she is right over here.
That's Alice.
And Alice looks back
and sees everything that she can see
within her light cone.
Remember, the whole purpose of this
coordinate transformation was to make it easy
to follow light rays.
45 degrees.
If we want more dimensions, we'll have to
extend this out to make a cone
out of it. But you can
see all the main features from here.
She can see everything behind her
here. But if she
waits a little while, she sees more.
And if she waits a little longer,
she sees more.
But no matter how
long she waits, the
most that she can ever see
is this.
What about things out here?
Nothing.
If there's somebody out here,
she can never know about it,
in principle.
She has a horizon.
The red line out here
is her event horizon.
It is her private event horizon.
Other people have different
event horizons.
But this is her private event horizon.
And this is her
private event horizon.
She cannot see anything out beyond it.
In principle, as a matter of
real principle,
she cannot, at least
by classical relativistic reasoning,
by classical light reasoning
and so forth, she cannot
see anything out. All kinds of things
could be going on there.
Her friend Bob
might have originated over here,
and she might have been able to
see Bob in the past.
From here, she could even
see Alice. Bob is moving.
There's Bob. Alice.
Bob.
In the past, Alice was able to send
messages to Bob. Bob was able to
send messages to Alice.
And now Bob passes Alice's
horizon.
From there on in, Bob
cannot send a message to Alice.
Bob may be able to see Alice,
but Alice cannot see Bob.
There's Bob.
So from this point on, Bob
has passed out of her horizon. He's gone.
That's what's going
to happen, unless
of course, if she's holding hands. What does it look
like if she's holding hands with Bob and she doesn't
want to let him go?
Yeah. Then
it looks like this.
Now does this mean they really get closer and closer
together? No, it doesn't.
It doesn't because the metric is
getting bigger and bigger out here.
So the actual metrical distance
between them, the actual proper distance
between them can stay constant.
And if it does stay constant,
they would appear
to join up here.
But they're not really getting any closer together.
So if they're bound together, if they're holding
hands, this is what it looks like.
And they can continuously forever and ever
send messages back and forth.
No limits.
But if Bob lets go
of Alice and goes with the flow,
if he's, let's go
implies among other things that
he gets far enough away that the gravitational
pull between them doesn't hold them together.
If he lets go
and passes outside her horizon,
they simply fall out
of causal contact. That's the
expression for it. They've fallen out of
causal contact. In this particular
instance, Bob can send
a message, sorry, can receive a message
from Alice, but he can never send
a message to Alice.
Alice up here
cannot send a
message to Bob either, because Bob also
has his own private event horizon.
Let's make Bob's
event horizon in green.
Here's Bob's event horizon.
Bob cannot see anything
outside of his event horizon.
So he can see Alice
early on,
but he can't see Alice after she passes
out of her horizon.
So he won't be actually able to see Alice
at his time.
Bob won't be able to see Alice
in his time. That's right. Bob
Well, you can never see anything at the same
time, period. Right.
You can never see. The only thing you can ever
see is those things which are
back inside your past light cone.
So you never can see anybody at the same time.
But once Bob
has passed through here, Alice
can never see him.
If this really was flat space, if it
really wasn't this peculiar De Sitter space
with this factor here which terminates it,
then Alice could keep going
and look back at Bob.
But Alice comes to the end of her
world line over here and simply
cannot look back.
So this is the character of
De Sitter space.
It has horizons.
In fact, every single observer
has his own private event horizon.
In this case, Alice
and Bob constitute one observer.
And
maybe we'll talk a little bit more
about these event horizons
next time.
I'm getting a little tired,
so I think I'll quit soon.
But we apparently
live in such a world.
And in such a world,
it's not Alice and Bob,
but it's galaxies.
Lots of galaxies.
Here we are now.
We can see about
10 to the 22 galaxies
around us.
As time goes on, they will pass
through the horizon and pass out
of, let's say we're Alice.
They will pass out of Alice's horizon
and Alice will not be able
to see them anymore.
They will be gone.
So, as I said,
Alice will be alone in the world
for all practical purposes.
So,
ありがとうございました
Is there this is data theory that in the
far distance we would not be able to see
Any galaxies at all? That's right
That's right. They will have
Galaxy Alice
You might you might okay, let's let's ask
whether Alice at a very very late time here
Can see Bob back here
And a very in a sense. No, it looks like
he can but in the sense no and I'll explain why
This is Alice, yeah Alice's time steps look like this
Many many time steps here now
imagine that Bob sends her a signal
And that signal is gonna come up to here
Bar Alice is gonna look back and look for
Bob back here. Well, you say she can see him
But in fact because her time
clocks are so bunched up over here
It means the radiation that she
sees from Bob is incredibly redshifted
that
How many beats of Bob's clock?
gets squeezed into Alice's
time scale here
One beat of her clock
Says stretched out over an enormous time scale from
Alice's world. So when Alice looks back and sees Bob
From way way up here. He's
Enormously redshifted you can't see very
very redshifted things his his wavelength
Wavelength of his light and the energy
of his light will be so stretched out
So in fact really Alice has no
chance of really seeing Bob over here
he's just been redshifted to Hell and
Except like on whole
That's right as in the horizon of a black hole
nd so will Bob
all other Galaxy up here
galaxies having passed out of their horizon.
Is it the same with the black
hole, it takes forever to reach the horizon?
Yeah, yeah, but okay. It is the same. It
is the same. Well, it is the same. Alice
looks back. Has Bob crossed her? Where is
Bob? Here's Bob over here. Has Bob crossed
the horizon? No. Alice looks back. Has
Bob crossed the horizon? No. Alice looks back.
Has Bob crossed the horizon? No.
She never sees him cross the horizon.
But do objects falling into a
black hole become infinitely redshifted as well?
Yes, yes. It's exactly the same thing.
It's exactly the same thing. Here's the black
hole. Here's who stays outside. Let's put
Alice outside. Yeah, let's put Alice outside.
Okay.
Let's keep the color coding. Blue? Blue for Alice?
Red.
Alice is red. Bob is green.
No, here's Alice. Alice is blue.
Bob is green.
I don't know. Here's Alice. I usually
send Alice into the black hole, but this
time Alice gets to stay outside. Here's
her clock. Her clock is going faster and
faster.
Okay.
It's going faster and faster and faster
and faster. It's not going faster and faster,
but on this diagram, all her time intervals
are bunched up, same as they are over here.
And Bob, who is now green, is falling
through the horizon. Alice looks back. Does she ever
get to see Bob fall through? No. Bob's signals,
his light waves or his waves of his hand that
he sends out, are not going to be the same
as they were when Alice was in the black hole.
They're not going to be the same as
they were when Alice was in the black hole.
These time intervals appear to get slower
and slower to her, because they're drawn
out over longer and longer time scales, which
is another way of saying Alice becomes infinitely
redshifted. The light from Alice becomes
infinitely redshifted from Bob's perspective. It's exactly
the same thing.
Yeah.
In Alice's real time, in her proper
time, she's slowing down. I mean, she's going
at her proper time, but on
the scale, it's getting compressed, right?
Well, on the scale, not on her
scale, well, she's just ticking along happily.
No, that's Bob.
That's Bob, you're right. That's Bob, yes. That's Bob, yes.
So how is the scale time, right? Her
proper time is still her proper time, right?
So she looks back and
she sees Bob slowing down, right?
But she not only sees him slowing
down, she sees his atoms slowing down,
she sees the radiation that's coming out.
She sees not only Bob slowing down,
but she sees the atoms slowing down,
she sees the emission of photons getting slower and slower,
the photons getting longer and
longer wavelength, smaller and smaller frequency,
and eventually his photons
become so monumentally long wavelength
that they can't be seen at all.
The energy of them gets diminished to negligible.
Yeah?
How would she measure the temperature
of the surface right above the horizon?
Well, to do that, she has to send down a thermometer
and make sure the thermometer doesn't fall into the black hole.
So to keep it from falling through
the black hole, she'd send down a thermometer,
measure the temperature, pull it back
up and see what it recorded.
But that's not what she's doing with Bob.
Bob is...
And the same incidentally, same thing here.
If Alice...
So here would be the experiment.
Alice has a very long rope, a long cable.
On the end of the cable is a thermometer.
She throws it out hard enough that it's beyond
the escape velocity from a local cluster of galaxies,
and waits a long time for it
to migrate out toward the horizon, her horizon.
But she doesn't let it go through the horizon.
Right?
She doesn't let it go through the horizon.
She then pulls it back in.
And after she's pulled it back in, she
sees what the temperature that it recorded was.
She will also see a high
temperature, but we'll come to that.
Horizons are always hot in a
sense, but we'll come to that.
This is so far the
classical description of the Sitter space.
Full of horizons.
There's horizons everywhere.
No matter where Alice is,
there's somebody...
She's passing through somebody's horizon.
So wherever you are,
you're passing through somebody's horizon.
Say goodbye because you won't see them again.
I'm trying to understand what it looks
like in the untransformed, in the little team.
And they're at the same distance.
I'll leave that for you to do an exercise.
It's an exercise to see what it looks like.
No, no, it's a good exercise.
Just undo what I did.
Just say that my assumption is they're not moving apart.
The X is not expanding here.
No, no, no, no, no.
The whole metric is blowing up,
including the X parts of it.
So the distance between points, if you
keep the points at fixed coordinate separation,
here Bob and Alice are at fixed Xs.
The distance between them is getting bigger and bigger.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
It goes to E to the infinity there.
That's right.
The distance between them blows
up when they get up to...
That's another fact of the Sitter space.
Now, something you can work out is you can compare
the distances between these two points
with the distance between these two points
with the distance between these
two points between the distance...
Comparing.
How far apart are these two?
What do you think the answer is?
Hmm?
Are they growing?
Shrinking?
No, staying the same.
Staying the same.
Yeah.
If you draw a horizontal line, work it out.
Here's the metric.
Draw a horizontal line.
Draw a horizontal line here and ask for
the distance, let's say, from the center to the
horizon over here.
And compare it with the distance from
the center to the horizon over here.
Compare it with the distance from
You'll find they're all the same.
The coordinate distance is shrinking,
but the metric is increasing.
And the distance to the horizon is always the same.
That is connected with the fact
that the Hubble constant is constant.
And so the distance to where the speed
of light is, where the things are moving away
with the speed of light is constant.
So Alice doesn't see things changing with time.
Everything stays the same.
She just sees a horizon around her, and
that horizon stays at a fixed distance from her.
So would she be seeing the projection of
all things in the past be projected onto that
horizon space?
Because they'll never go away, right?
Right.
They'll never go away, but she sees it harder
and harder to see them because they get redshifted.
Now that doesn't take into account the
Hawking radiation coming from the horizon, but what
you say is right.
Yeah.
All right.
Okay.
So assuming that we don't pass through
each other's horizons, we'll meet here next week.
For more, please visit us at www.nasa.gov.
And if you have any questions or
other questions, please visit us at stanford.edu.