This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Gravity.
Gravity is a rather special force.
It's unusual.
It has different than electrical forces,
magnetic forces.
And it's connected in some
way with geometric properties of space,
space and
time.
And that connection is of
course the general theory of relativity.
Before we start,
tonight for the most part,
we will not be dealing
with the general theory of relativity.
We will be dealing with gravity
in its oldest and simplest mathematical form.
Well,
perhaps not the oldest and simplest,
but Newtonian gravity.
And going a little beyond what Newton,
certainly nothing that Newton would not
have recognized or couldn't have grasped,
Newton could grasp anything.
But some ways of thinking about it which
will not be found in Newton's actual work.
But still,
Newtonian gravity.
Newtonian gravity set up in a way that,
that is useful for
going on to the general theory.
Okay,
let's.
Let's go.
begin with Newton's equations.
The first equation,
of course,
is F equals mA.
Force is equal to mass times acceleration.
Let's assume that we have a frame of reference,
a frame of reference that means a set of coordinates
and it's a collection of clocks,
and that frame of reference is what is called
an inertial frame of reference.
An inertial frame of reference simply means
one which,
if there are no objects around
to exert forces on a particular,
let's call it a test object,
a test object is just some object,
a small particle or anything else
that we use to test out the various fields,
force fields that might be acting on it.
An inertial frame is one which,
when there are no objects around to exert forces,
that object will move,
with uniform motion,
with no acceleration.
That's the idea of an inertial frame of reference.
And so if you're an inertial frame of reference
and you have a pin
and you just let it go,
it stays there.
It doesn't move.
If you give it a push,
it will move off with uniform velocity.
That's the idea of an inertial frame of reference.
And in an inertial frame of reference,
the basic Newtonian equation,
equation number one,
I always forget which law is which.
There's Newton's first law,
second law,
and third law.
I never can remember which is which.
But they're all pretty much summarized by
F equals mass times acceleration.
This is a vector equation.
I expect people know what a vector is.
A three vector equation.
We'll come later to four vectors,
where when space and time are united into space,
space time,
but for the moment space
is space and time is time,
and a vector means a thing,
which is a pointer,
and a direction in space,
it has a magnitude,
and it has components.
So component by component,
the x component of the force
is equal to the mass of the object
times the x component of acceleration,
y component,
z component,
and so forth.
And in order to indicate
that something is a vector equation,
I'll try to,
I'll try to remember to put an arrow over vectors.
The mass is not a vector.
The mass is simply a number.
Every particle has a mass.
Every object has a mass.
And in Newtonian physics,
the mass is conserved.
It does not change.
Now of course,
the mass of this cup of coffee here can change.
It's lighter now.
But it only changes because mass has been transported
from one place to another
so you can change the mass of an object
by whacking off a piece of it.
But if you don't change the number of particles,
change the number of molecules,
and so forth,
then the mass is a conserved,
unchanging quantity.
So that's the first equation.
Now let me write that in another form.
The other form,
we imagine we have a coordinate system,
an x,
a y,
and a z.
I don't have enough directions on the blackboard
to draw a z.
I won't bother.
There's x,
y,
and z.
Sometimes we just call them x1,
x2,
and x3.
I guess I can draw it in.
x3 is over here someplace.
x,
y,
and z.
And a particle has a position,
which means it has a set of three coordinates.
Sometimes we will summarize
the collection of the three coordinates,
x1,
x2,
and x3.
Incidentally,
x1 and x2 and x3 are components of a vector.
The components,
they are components
of the position vector of the particle.
The position vector of the particle
I will often call either small r or large r,
depending on the particular context.
r stands for radius.
But the radius simply means the distance
between a point and the origin vector.
So,
for example,
we're really talking now about a thing
with three components,
x,
y,
and z,
and it's the radial vector.
The radial vector,
this is the same thing as
the components of the vector r.
All right.
The acceleration is a vector
that's made up out of the time derivatives
of x,
y,
and z,
or x1,
x2,
and x3.
So,
for each component,
the,
one,
two,
or three,
the acceleration,
which let me indicate,
well,
let's just call it a,
the acceleration is just equal,
the components of it,
are equal to the second derivatives
of the coordinates with respect to time.
That's what acceleration is.
The first derivative
of position is called velocity.
We can take this to be component by component,
x1,
x2,
and x3.
The first derivative is velocity.
The second derivative is acceleration.
We can write this in vector notation.
I won't bother.
But we all know what we mean.
I hope we all know what we mean
by these,
by acceleration and velocity.
And so,
Newton's equations are then summarized
not summarized,
but rewritten
as the force on an object,
whatever it is,
component by component
is equal to the mass
times the second derivative
of the component of position.
So that's the summary of,
I think it's Newton's first and second law.
I can never remember which they are.
Newton's first law,
of course,
is simply the statement that if there are no forces,
then there's no acceleration.
That's Newton's first law.
That's the second law.
Third law is equal and opposite.
Equal and opposite,
right.
So this summarizes both the first and second law.
I never understood why there
was a first and second law.
It seemed to me there was just one,
F equals m a.
All right,
now,
let's begin even previous to Newton
with Galilean gravity.
Gravity as Galileo understood it.
Actually,
I'm not sure how much of this mathematics
Galileo did or didn't understand.
He certainly knew what acceleration was.
He measured it.
I don't know that he had the...
He certainly didn't have calculus,
but he knew what acceleration was.
So what Galileo studied was the motion of objects
in the gravitational field of the Earth
in the approximation that the Earth is moving.
The Earth is flat.
Now,
Galileo knew the Earth wasn't flat.
But he studied gravity in the approximation
where you never moved very far
from the surface of the Earth.
And if you don't move very
far from the surface of the Earth,
you might as well take the
surface of the Earth to be flat.
And the significance of that is twofold.
First of all,
the direction of gravitational forces
is the same everywheres.
This is not true,
of course,
if the Earth is curved.
Then gravity will point to the Earth.
Toward the center.
But in the flat space approximation,
gravity points down.
Down everywhere is always in the same direction.
And second of all,
perhaps a little bit less obvious,
but nevertheless true,
in the approximation where the Earth is infinite and flat,
goes on and on forever,
infinite and flat,
the gravitational force doesn't depend on how high you are.
Same gravitational force here as here.
The implication of that
is that the acceleration of gravity,
since force,
apart from the mass of an object,
the acceleration on an object,
is independent of where you put it.
And so,
Galileo
either did or didn't realize,
well,
he,
again,
I don't know exactly what Galileo did or didn't know,
but what he said was equivalent to saying
that the force on an object
in the flat space approximation
is very simple.
It's first of all has only one component pointing downward.
If we take the upward
sense of things to be positive,
then we would say that the force is,
let's just say the component of the force
in the x2 direction,
the vertical direction,
is equal to minus,
the minus simply means that the force is downward,
and it's proportional to the mass of the object
times a constant called the gravitational acceleration.
Now,
the fact
that it's constant everywhere is,
in other words,
mass times g doesn't vary from place to place,
that's this fact
that gravity doesn't depend on where you are.
You can't tell where you
are in the flat space approximation.
But the fact that the force is
proportional to the mass of an object,
that is not obvious.
In fact,
for most forces,
it's not true.
For electric forces,
the force is proportional to the electric charge,
not to the mass.
And so gravitational forces are rather special.
The strength of the gravitational force on an object
is proportional to its mass.
That characterizes gravity almost completely.
That's the special thing about gravity,
the force is proportional itself to the mass.
Well,
if we combine F equals mA
with the force law,
this is the law of force,
then what we find
is that mass times acceleration,
d second x,
now this is the vertical component,
by dt squared,
is equal to minus,
that's the minus,
mg,
period.
That's it.
Now the interesting thing that happens in gravity
is that the mass cancels out from both sides.
That is what's special about gravity,
the mass cancels out from both sides.
And the consequence of that
is that the motion of an object,
its acceleration,
doesn't depend on the mass,
it doesn't depend on anything about the particle.
Particle,
object,
I'll use the word particle,
I don't necessarily mean a point,
a small particle,
a baseball is a particle,
an eraser is a particle,
a piece of chalk is a particle,
that the motion of the object
doesn't depend on the mass of the object
or anything else.
The result of that
is that if you take two objects
of quite different mass,
and you drop them,
they fall exactly the same way.
Galileo did that experiment,
I don't know whether he really
threw something off the leaning tower
of Pisa or not,
it's not important.
Yeah,
he did balls down an inclined plane,
I don't know whether he actually did or didn't,
I know,
the myth is that he didn't.
I find it very difficult to believe that he didn't.
I've been in Pisa,
last week I was in Pisa,
and I took a look
at the leaning tower of Pisa.
Galileo was born and lived in Pisa.
He was interested in gravity,
how it would be possible that he wouldn't think
of dropping something off the leaning tower
is beyond my comprehension.
You look at that tower and you say,
that tower is good for one thing,
dropping things off.
Now,
I don't know,
maybe the Doge or whoever they
called the guy at the time
said,
no,
Galileo,
you can't drop things from the tower,
you'll kill somebody,
so maybe he didn't,
but he must have surely thought of it.
All right,
so,
the result,
had he done it,
and had he not had
to worry about such spurious effects
as air resistance,
would be that a cannonball and a feather
would fall in exactly the same way,
independent of the mass,
and the equation would just say,
the acceleration would first of all be downward,
that's the minus sign,
and equal to this constant G.
Excuse me,
let me,
now,
G is a number,
it's 10 meters per second per second,
at the surface of the Earth,
at the surface of the Moon,
it's something smaller,
on the surface of Jupiter,
it's something larger,
so it does depend on the mass of the planet,
but the acceleration doesn't depend
on the mass of the object you're dropping,
it depends on the mass of
the object you're dropping it onto,
but not the mass of the object that's dropping.
That fact,
that gravitational motion
is completely independent of mass,
is called,
or it's the simplest version
of something that's called the equivalence principle.
Why it's called the equivalence principle,
we'll come to later,
what's equivalent to what?
At this stage,
we could just say,
gravity is equivalent between all different objects,
independent of their mass,
but that is not exactly what the equivalence,
an equivalence principle was about.
That has a consequence,
an interesting consequence.
Supposing I take some object,
which is made up out of something
which is very unrigid,
just a collection of point masses,
maybe,
let's even say they're not even exerting
any forces on each other.
It's a cloud,
a very diffuse
cloud of particles,
and we watch it fall.
Let's suppose we start each particle from rest,
not all at the same height,
and we let them all fall.
Some particles are heavy,
some particles are light,
some of them may be big,
some of them may be small.
How does the whole thing fall?
The answer is,
all of the particles fall at exactly the same rate.
The consequence of it is
that the shape of this object
doesn't deform as it falls.
It stays absolutely unchanged.
The relationship between the neighboring parts
are unchanged.
There are no stresses or strains
which tend to deform the object.
So even if the object were held together
by some sort of struts or whatever,
there would be no forces on those struts
because everything falls together.
The consequence of that
is that falling in a gravitational field
is undetectable.
You can't tell that you're falling
in a gravitational field by...
When I say you can't tell,
certainly you can tell the difference between
free fall and standing on the Earth.
That's not the point.
The point is that you can't
tell by looking at your neighbors
or anything else that there's
a force being exerted on you
and that that force that's being exerted on you
is pulling you downward.
You might as well,
for all practical purposes,
be infinitely far from the Earth
with no gravity at all
and just sitting there
because as far as you can tell,
there's no tendency
for the gravitational field to deform this object
or anything else.
You cannot tell the difference
between being in free space
infinitely far from anything with no forces
and falling freely in a gravitational field.
That's another statement of the equivalence principle.
Would you say not mechanically detectable?
Well,
in fact,
not detectable,
period,
but so far not mechanically detectable.
Well,
would it be optically detectable?
No.
For example,
these particles could be
equipped with lasers.
Lasers and optical detectors of some sort.
I was just looking at the view.
What's that?
Oh,
you could certainly tell
if you were standing on the floor here,
you could tell that something was falling toward you.
But the question is,
from within this object by itself,
without looking at the floor,
without knowing the floor was...
Something that wasn't moving is still moving.
Well,
you can't tell whether you're falling in its...
Yeah.
If there was something that was not falling,
it would only be because there
was some other force on it,
like a beam or a tower
of some sort holding it up.
Why?
Because this object,
if there are no other forces on it,
only the gravitational forces,
it will fall at the same rate as this.
All right.
So that's another expression of the equivalence principle
that you cannot tell the difference
between being in free space,
far from any gravitating object,
versus being in a gravitational field.
Now,
we're going to modify this.
This,
of course,
is not quite true
in a real gravitational field.
But in this flat space approximation,
where everything moves together,
you cannot tell that there's a gravitational field,
or at least you cannot tell the difference,
not without seeing the floor in any case,
the self-contained object here
does not experience anything different
than it would experience far from any gravitating object
standing still,
or in uniform motion.
Another question.
What's up,
yeah?
Um.
Well,
we can tell when we're accelerating.
No,
you can't tell when you're accelerating.
Well,
you can't feel that you're accelerating.
Isn't that because there's a
connection between the different objects?
Okay,
here's what you can't tell.
If you go up to
the top of a high building,
and you close your eyes,
and you step off,
and go into free fall,
you will feel exactly the same.
You'll feel weird.
I mean,
that's not the way you usually feel,
because your stomach will come
up and do some funny things.
You might lose it.
But the point is,
you would feel exactly the same discomfort
in outer space,
far from any gravitating object,
just standing still.
You feel exactly the same peculiar feelings.
What are those peculiar feelings due to?
They're not due to falling.
They're due to not fall.
Well...
They're due to the fact that
when you stand on the Earth here,
there are forces on the bottoms of your feet
which keep you from falling.
And if the Earth suddenly disappeared from under my feet,
sure enough,
my feet would feel funny,
because they're used to having those forces
exerted on their bottoms.
You get it.
I hope.
So the fact that you feel funny in free fall
is because you're not used to free fall.
It doesn't matter whether you're
infinitely far from the Earth,
far from any gravitating object standing still,
or freely falling in the presence of a gravitational field.
Now,
as I said,
this will have to be modified in a little bit.
There are such things as tidal forces.
Those tidal forces are due to
the fact that the Earth is curved,
and that the gravitational field
is not the same in every...
same direction in every point,
and that it varies with height.
That's due...
to the finiteness of the Earth.
But in the flat space...
in the flat Earth approximation,
where the Earth is infinitely big,
pulling uniformly,
there is no other effect of gravity
that is any different than being in free space.
Okay,
again,
that's known as the equivalent principle.
Now,
let's go on beyond the flat space
or the flat Earth approximation
and move on
to Newton's theory of gravity.
Newton's theory of gravity
says every object in the universe
exerts a gravitational force on
every other object in the universe.
Let's start with just two of them.
Equal and opposite,
attractive,
attractive means that the direction
of the force on one object
is toward the other one.
Equal and opposite forces,
and the magnitude of the force,
the magnitude of the force of one object on another,
let's characterize them by a mass.
Let's call this one little m.
Think of it as a lighter mass,
and this one,
which we can imagine is a heavier object,
we'll call it big M.
All right,
Newton's law of force
is that the force
is proportional to the product of the masses,
making either mass heavier
will increase the force.
The product of the masses,
big M times little m,
inversely proportional to the square
of the distance between them,
let's call that r squared.
Let's call the distance between them r,
and there's a numerical constant.
This law by itself could not possibly be right.
It's not dimensionally consistent.
If you work out the dimensions of force,
mass,
and r,
it's not dimensionally consistent.
There has to be a numerical constant in there.
So,
and that numerical constant is called capital G,
Newton's constant,
and it's very small.
It's a very small constant.
I'll write down what it is.
G is equal to six,
or 6.7 roughly,
times 10 to the minus 11th,
which is a small number.
So on the face of it,
it seems that gravity is a very weak force.
You might not think that
gravity is such a weak force,
but to convince yourself it's a weak force,
there's a simple experiment that you can do,
weak by comparison with other forces.
I've done this for classes,
and you can do it yourself.
Just take an object hanging by a string,
and two experiments.
The first experiment,
take a little object here,
and electrically charge it.
You electrically charge it by rubbing it on your sweater.
That doesn't put very much electric charge on it,
but it charges it up
enough to feel some electrostatic force.
And then take another object of exactly the same kind,
rub it on your shirt,
and put it over here.
What happens?
They repel.
And the fact that they repel means that
this string will shift,
and you'll see it shift.
Take another example.
Take your little ball there to be iron,
and put a magnet next to it.
Again,
you'll see quite an easily detectable deflection
of the string holding it.
Next.
Take a 10,000 pound weight and put it over here.
Guess what happens?
Undetectable.
You cannot see anything happen.
The gravitational force is much,
much weaker
than most other kinds of forces.
And that's due to the,
or not due to,
but the,
not due to that,
the fact that it's so weak
is encapsulated in this small number here.
Another way to say it
is if you take two masses,
each of one kilo,
not one kilometer,
one kilogram,
a kilogram is a good healthy mass,
right?
A nice chunk of iron.
M,
and you separate them by one meter,
then the force between them is just G,
and it's 6.7 times 10 to the minus 11,
the units being Newtons.
So it's a very weak force.
But,
weak as it is,
we feel it rather strenuously,
we feel it strongly,
because the Earth is so darn heavy.
So the heaviness of the Earth makes up,
the smallness of G.
And,
um,
so we wake up in the morning
feeling like we don't want to get out of bed,
because gravity is holding us down.
Question.
Yeah.
Um,
so that force is measuring the force between,
from the larger to the smaller,
or both?
Both,
both.
They're equal and opposite.
Equal and opposite.
That's the,
that's the rule.
That's Newton's third law.
The forces are equal and opposite.
So the force on the large
one due to the small one
is the same as the force of
the small one on the large one.
And,
uh,
but it is proportional to the product of the masses.
So,
the meaning of that is,
I'm not,
well,
I'm heavier than I like to be,
but,
uh,
but I'm not very heavy.
I'm certainly not heavy enough to deflect the hanging,
uh,
weight significantly.
Right?
But I do exert a force on the Earth
which is exactly equal and opposite to the force
that the very heavy Earth exerts on me.
Okay.
Why does the Earth accel-
When I,
if I drop from a certain height,
I accelerate down,
the Earth hardly accelerates at all,
even though the forces are equal.
Why is it that the Earth,
if the forces are equal,
my force on the Earth and
the Earth's force on me are equal,
why is it that the Earth,
accelerates so little and I accelerate so much?
Why is that a big mass?
Yeah.
Because the acceleration involves two things.
It involves the force and the mass.
The bigger the mass,
the less the acceleration for a given force.
So,
the Earth doesn't excel-
Yeah,
question?
Uh,
how did Newton arrive at that equation
for the gravitational force?
I think it was largely a guess,
but there was,
so it was an educated guess.
And,
um,
what was the key,
uh,
it was largely,
ah,
no,
it was from Kepler's,
it was from Kepler's laws.
It was from Kepler's laws.
He worked out,
roughly speaking,
I don't know exactly what he did.
He was rather secretive and he
didn't really tell people what he did.
But,
um,
the piece of knowledge that he had
was Kepler's laws of motion,
planetary motion.
And my guess is that he just wrote down
a general force
and realized that he would get
Kepler's laws of motion for the inverse square law.
Um,
I don't believe he had any underlying theoretical reason
to believe in the inverse square law.
Yeah,
Edmund Halley actually asked him,
um,
you know,
what kind of force law do you need
for,
uh,
tonic section coordinates?
And he had already performed the calculations years before.
Yeah.
So,
yeah.
Actually,
I don't think that,
yeah,
I think the question,
that's correct.
He asked the question for inverse square laws
and I think that,
uh,
that Newton already knew the solution was an ellipse.
Well,
the key,
no,
it wasn't the ellipse which was the,
the,
the orbits might have been circular.
It was the fact that the period varies
as the three-halves power of the radius.
All right?
The period of motion is,
uh,
the circular motion has an acceleration toward the center.
Any motion in the circle is accelerated toward the center.
If you know the period and the radius,
then you know the acceleration toward the center.
Okay?
Uh,
we could write,
well,
let's,
let's do it.
Uh,
anybody,
uh,
know what,
if I know the angular frequency,
the angular frequency of going around in an orbit,
uh,
that's called omega,
do you know what the,
and it's basically just the inverse function,
the inverse period.
Okay?
Omega is roughly the inverse period,
number of,
uh,
cycles per second.
What's the,
what is the acceleration of a
thing moving in a circular orbit?
Anybody remember?
Omega squared r.
Omega squared r,
that's the acceleration.
Now,
supposing he sets that equal to some unknown force law,
f of r,
and then divides by r.
Then he finds omega as a
function of the radius of the orbit.
Okay?
Well,
let's do it for the real case.
For the real case,
inverse square law,
f of r is one over r squared,
so this would be one over r cubed,
and in that form,
it is Kepler's second law?
I don't remember which one it is.
It's the law that says that the frequency,
or the period,
the square of the period,
is proportional to the cube of the radius.
That was the law of Kepler.
So from Kepler's laws,
he easily could,
or that one law,
he could easily deduce,
uh,
that the force was proportional to one over r squared.
I think that's probably historically what,
uh,
what he did.
Then,
on top of that,
he realized if you didn't have a perfectly circular orbit,
then the inverse square law was the unique law,
which would give,
um,
uh,
elliptical orbits.
So it was a two-step thing.
What happens when the two objects are touching?
Well,
then,
of course,
there are other forces on them.
If the two objects are actually touching each other,
there are all sorts of forces between them
that are not just gravitational.
Electrostatic forces,
atomic forces,
nuclear forces,
so you have to modify the whole story.
As the distance approaches zero...
Yeah.
Then it breaks down.
Then it breaks down,
yeah.
Then it breaks down when they get so close
that other important forces come into play.
The other important forces,
for example,
are the forces that are holding this object
and preventing it from falling.
These,
we usually call them contact forces,
but in fact what they really are
is various kinds of electrostatic forces
between the atoms and molecules in the table
and the atoms and molecules in here.
So other kinds of forces.
All right.
Incidentally,
let me just point out,
uh...
If we're talking about other kinds of force laws,
for example,
electrostatic force laws,
then the force...
We still have F equals mA,
but the force law...
is the force that's going to be
in the center of the object.
The force law will not be
that the force is somehow proportional to the mass
times something else,
but it could be the electric charge.
If it's the electric charge,
then electrically uncharged objects
will have no forces on them,
and they won't accelerate.
Electrically charged objects will accelerate
in an electric field.
So electrical forces don't have this universal property
that everything falls
or everything moves in the same way.
Uncharged particles move differently
than charged particles
with respect to electrostatic forces.
They move the same way
with respect to gravitational forces.
And there's repulsion and attraction,
whereas gravitational forces are always attractive.
Where's my gravitational force?
I lost it.
Yeah,
here it is.
All right,
so that's...
that's Newtonian gravity between two objects.
Um...
For simplicity,
let's just put one of them,
the heavy one,
at the origin of coordinates
and study the motion of the light one.
Then...
Oh,
incidentally,
one usually puts...
Let me...
let me refine this a little bit.
As I've written it here,
I haven't really expressed it as a vector equation.
This is the magnitude of the force
between two objects.
Thought of as a vector equation,
we have to provide a direction for the force.
Vectors have directions.
What direction is the force
on this particle?
Well,
the answer is
it's along the radial direction itself.
So let's call
the radial distance r,
or the radial vector r,
then the force on little m here
is along the direction r,
but it's also opposite to the direction of r.
The radial vector relative to the origin over here
points this way.
On the other hand,
the force points in the opposite direction.
If we want to make a
real vector equation out of this,
we first of all have to put a minus sign.
That indicates that the force is opposite
to the direction of the radial distance here.
But we have to also put something in
which tells us what direction the force is in.
It's along the radial direction.
But wait a minute.
If I multiply it by r up here,
I had better divide it
by another factor of r downstairs.
To keep the magnitude unchanged.
The magnitude of the force is 1 over r squared.
If I were to just randomly come
and multiply it by r,
that would make the magnitude bigger
by a factor of r,
so I have to divide
it by the magnitude of r.
This is Newton's force law
expressed in vector form.
Now let's imagine
that we have a whole assembly of particles.
A whole bunch of them.
They're all exerting forces on one another.
In pairs,
they exert exactly the force that Newton wrote down.
But what's the total force on a particle?
Let's label these particles.
This is the first one,
the second one,
the third one,
the fourth one,
dot dot dot dot dot.
This is the ith one over here.
So i is a running index
which labels which particle we're talking about.
The force on the ith particle,
let's call it f sub i,
and let's remember that it's a vector.
It's equal to the sum.
Now this is not an obvious fact
that when you have two objects
exerting a force on the third,
that the force is necessarily equal
to the sum of the two forces,
of the two objects,
you know what I mean.
But it is a fact anyway.
Obvious or not obvious,
it is a fact.
Gravity does work that way,
at least in the Newtonian approximation.
With Einstein,
it breaks down a little bit.
But in Newtonian physics,
the force is the sum,
and so it's a sum over all the other particles.
Let's write that j not equal to i.
That means it's a sum
over all not equal to i.
So the force on the first particle
doesn't come from the first particle,
it comes from the second particle,
third particle,
fourth particle,
and so forth.
Each individual force involves m sub i,
the force of the i-th particle,
times the mass of the j-th particle.
Product of the masses
divided by the square of the distance between them,
let's call that r i j,
squared.
The distance between the i-th particle is i and j,
the distance between the i-th particle
and the j-th particle is r i j.
But then,
just as we did before,
we have to give it a direction.
Put a minus sign here,
that indicates that it's attractive.
Another r i j upstairs,
but that's a vector r i j,
and make this cube downstairs.
Alright,
so that says
that the force on the i-th particle
is the sum of all the forces
due to all the other ones
of the product of their masses,
inverse square in the distance,
and the denominator,
and the direction of each individual force
on this particle,
is toward the other.
Alright,
this is a vector sum.
Yeah?
The minus indicates that it's attractive.
Oh,
excellent.
But you've got the vector going from i to j.
Oh.
Uh...
Let's see.
That's a vector going from r to i to j.
Yes,
there is a question of the sign
of this vector over here.
So,
yeah,
you're absolutely...
Let's see.
Blah,
blah,
blah.
Um...
Yeah.
I actually think it's...
Yeah,
you're right.
You're absolutely right.
The way I've written it,
there should not be a minus sign here.
Alright?
But if I put r j i there,
then there would be a minus sign.
Alright?
So you're right.
Uh...
But in any case,
every one of the forces is attractive.
Alright?
And what we have to
do is to add them up.
We have to add them up as vectors.
And so there's some resulting vector,
some resultant vector,
which doesn't point toward any one of them in particular,
but points in some direction,
which is determined by the
vector sum of all the others.
Alright?
But the interesting fact is,
if we combine this...
This is the force on the i-th particle.
If we combine it with Newton's equations...
Let's combine it with Newton's...
with Newton's f equals m a equations,
then...
Well,
this is f.
This...
On the i-th particle,
this is equal to the mass of the i-th particle
times the acceleration of the i-th particle.
Again,
vector equations.
Now,
the sum here is over all the other particles.
We're focusing on number i.
i,
the mass of the i-th particle,
will cancel out of this equation.
I don't want to throw it away,
but let's just circle it
and now put it over on the side.
We notice that the acceleration
of the i-th particle
does not depend on its mass again.
Once again,
because the mass occurs
in both sides of the equation,
it can be canceled out,
and the motion of the i-th particle
does not depend on the mass of the i-th particle.
It depends on the masses of all the other ones.
All the other ones come in,
but the mass of the i-th particle
cancels out of the equation.
So what that means
is if we had a whole bunch of particles,
here,
and we added one more over here,
its motion would not depend
on the mass of that particle.
It depends on the mass of all the other ones,
but it doesn't depend on the mass
of the i-th particle here.
That's,
again,
the equivalence principle,
that the motion of a particle
doesn't depend on its mass.
And again,
if we had a whole bunch of particles here,
if they were close enough together,
they would all move in the same way.
Before I discuss a little more mathematics,
let's just discuss tidal forces,
what tidal forces are.
Can I ask one question?
Yeah.
Once you set this whole thing into motion,
dynamically,
we have all different masses,
and each particle is going to be affected
by each one differently.
Yes,
yes,
yes.
I think I know what you're going to ask,
but I'm just...
Every particle in there is going to experience
a uniform acceleration?
No,
no,
no.
The acceleration is not uniform.
The acceleration will get larger
when it gets closer to one of the particles.
It won't be uniform anymore.
It won't be uniform now because the force
is not independent of where you are.
Now the force depends on where you are
relative to the objects that are exerting the force.
It was only in the flat Earth approximation
where the force didn't depend on where you were.
Okay?
Now the force varies,
so it's larger when you're far away,
it's...sorry,
it's smaller when you're far away,
it's larger when you're in close.
Okay?
But is it going to be changing in a...
It changes in a vector form
with each individual particle.
Each one of them is changing position.
Yeah.
And so is the dynamics that every one of them
is going towards the center of gravity
of the entire...
Not necessarily.
I mean,
they could be flying apart from each other,
but they will be accelerating toward each other.
Okay?
If I throw this eraser into the air
with greater than the escape velocity,
it's not going to turn around and fall back down.
No,
the question is,
is the acceleration a uniform acceleration
or is it a changing dynamic acceleration?
Changing with what?
With respect to what?
Time?
Oh,
it changes with respect to time
because the object moves further and further away.
In the two-mass system,
I call that a uniform acceleration.
Uniform with respect to what?
It's not uniform.
The radius is...
The radius is changing
and it's inverse cubed with the radius.
Inverse squared.
One of these can't...
Yeah.
Let's take the Earth.
Here's the Earth
and we drop a small mass from far away.
As that mass moves in,
its acceleration increases.
Why does its acceleration increase?
Its acceleration increases
because the radial distance gets smaller.
So in that sense,
it's not the...
All right.
Now,
once the gravitational force depends on distance,
then it's not really quite true
that you don't feel anything in a gravitational field.
You feel something which is to some extent different
than you would feel in free space
without any gravitational field.
The reason is more or less obvious.
Here you are.
Here's...
Here's the Earth.
Now,
you or me or whoever it is
happens to be extremely tall.
A couple of thousand miles tall.
Well,
this person's feet are being pulled
by the gravitational field more than his head.
Or another way of saying the same thing is...
Let's imagine that the person is...
This person is very loosely held together.
He's just more or less a gas of a...
We are pretty loosely held together.
At least I am.
Right.
All right.
The acceleration on the lower portions of his body
are larger than the accelerations
on the upper portions of his body.
So it's quite clear what happens to him.
He gets stretched.
He doesn't get a sense of falling as such.
He gets a sense of stretching,
being stretched.
Feet being pulled away from his head.
At the same time,
let's...
All right.
So...
Let's change his shape a little bit.
I just spent a week,
two weeks in Italy,
and my shape changes whenever I go to Italy,
and it tends to get more horizontal.
My head is here.
My feet are here.
And now I'm this way.
Still loosely put together.
All right.
Now what?
Well,
not only does the force depend on the distance,
but it also depends on the direction.
The force on my left
end over here is this way.
The force on my right
The force on the top of my head is down,
but it's weaker than the force on my feet.
So there are two effects.
One effect is to stretch me vertically.
It's because my head is not
being pulled as hard as my feet.
But the other effect is to be squished horizontally
by the fact that the forces
on the left end of me
are pointing slightly to the right,
and the forces on the right end of me
are pointing slightly to the left.
So a loosely knit person like this,
falling in free fall near the ground,
a real planet or a real gravitational object
which has a real Newtonian gravitational field around it,
will experience a distortion,
will experience a degree of distortion
and a degree of being stretched vertically,
being compressed horizontally.
But if the object is small enough,
what does small enough mean?
Let's suppose the object that's falling
is small enough.
If it's small enough,
then the gradient of the gravitational field
across the size of the object
will be negligible,
and so all parts of it will experience
the same gravitational acceleration.
All right,
so tidal forces,
these are tidal forces,
these forces which tend to tear things apart vertically
and squish them this way,
tidal forces.
Tidal forces are forces which are real,
you feel them.
Do you recall if Newton calculated lunar tides?
Oh,
I think he did.
He certainly knew the cause of the tides,
yeah.
I don't know to what extent he calculated,
what do you mean calculated the...
As in this kind of a
system with the moon and the sun.
Well,
I doubt that he was capable,
I'm not sure whether he estimated the height
of the deformation of the oceans or not,
but I think he did understand this much about tides.
Okay,
so that's what's called tidal force,
and remember the tidal force
has this effect of stretching,
and in particular,
if we take the Earth,
just to tell you why it's called tidal forces,
of course it's because it has to do with tides,
I'm sure you all know the story,
but if this is the moon down here,
then the moon exerting forces on the Earth
exerts tidal forces on the Earth,
which means to some extent it
tends to stretch it this way
and squash it this way.
Well,
the Earth is pretty rigid,
so it doesn't deform very much due to the moon,
but what's not rigid is
the layer of water around it,
and so the layer of water
tends to get stretched and squeezed,
and so it gets deformed
into a deformed shell of water,
with a bump on this side
and a bump on that side.
Alright,
I'm not going to go any more deeply into that,
that I'm sure you've all seen.
Okay,
but let's define now what
we mean by the gravitational field.
The gravitational field is abstracted from this formula.
We have a bunch of particles.
Question?
Yeah.
Don't you have,
need some sort of a coordinate geometry
so that when you have
the poor guy in the middle
is being pulled by all
the other guys on the side?
I'm not explaining it right,
but it's always negative,
is that what you're saying?
No,
I'm saying it's always attractive.
Alright,
so you have,
but what about the other
guys that are pulling upon him,
from different directions?
Well,
let's suppose there's somebody over here,
and we're talking about the
force on this person over here.
Alright,
obviously there's one force pushing this way
and another force pushing that way.
They're all negative.
No,
they're all opposite to the direction of
the object which is pulling on them.
Alright?
That's what this minus sign says.
Well,
you kind of retracted the minus sign at the front
and reversed the J-I.
Yeah.
So it's the direction.
We can get rid of the minus sign
at the front there by making this I-J.
R-I-J and R-J-I are opposite to each other.
One of them is the vector between I and J,
I and J,
and the other one is
the vector from J to I,
so they're equal and opposite to each other.
The minus sign there,
look,
as far as the minus sign goes,
all it means is that every one of
these particles is pulling on this particle toward it,
as opposed to pushing away from it.
It's just a convention which keeps
track of attraction instead of repulsion.
Yeah,
for the ice mass,
if that's the right word,
that makes sense,
but if you look at it
as a kind of an ensemble,
wouldn't there be a nonlinear component to it?
Because the I-th guy affects the J-th guy,
and then when you compute the J-th guy,
you know what I mean?
When you take into account the motion.
Now what this formula is for is supposing
you know the positions of all the others.
You know that.
Then what is the force on one additional one?
But you're perfectly right.
Once you let the system evolve,
then each one will cause a
change in motion in the other one,
and so it becomes a complicated,
as you say,
nonlinear mess.
But this formula is a formula for if
you knew the position and location of every particle,
this would be the force.
Okay?
Something you need to solve some
equations to know how the particles move.
But if you know where they are,
then this is the force on the I-th particle.
Alright,
let's come to the idea of the gravitational field.
The gravitational field is in some
ways similar to the electric field,
of an electric charge.
It's the combined effect of all the masses...
...everywhere's.
And the way you define it is as follows.
You imagine one more particle.
One more particle.
You can take it to be a very light
particle so it doesn't influence the motion of the others.
Add one more particle in your imagination.
You don't really have to add it in your imagination.
And ask what the force on it is.
The force is the sum of
the force due to all the others.
It is proportional.
Each term is proportional to
the mass of this extra particle.
This extra particle,
which may be imaginary,
is called a test particle.
It's a thing that you're imagining
testing out the gravitational field with.
You take a light little particle and you
put it here and you see how it accelerates.
Knowing how it accelerates tells you
how much force is on it.
Alright?
In fact,
it just tells you how it accelerates.
And you can go around and imagine things like this.
You're putting it in different places and mapping
out the force field that's on that particle.
Or the acceleration field.
Since we already know that the
force is proportional to the mass,
then we can just concentrate on the acceleration.
The acceleration,
all particles will have the
same acceleration independent of their mass.
So we don't even have to know
what the mass of the particle is.
We put something over there,
a little bit of dust,
and we see how it accelerates.
Acceleration is a vector.
And so we map out in space the
acceleration of a particle at every point in space.
Either imaginary or real particle.
And that gives us a vector
field at every point in space.
Every point in space there
is a gravitational field of acceleration.
It can be thought of as the acceleration.
You don't have to think of it as force.
Acceleration.
The acceleration of a point mass located at that position.
It's a vector.
It has a direction.
It has a magnitude.
And it's a function of position.
So we just give it a name.
The acceleration due to all the gravitating objects.
It's a vector.
And it depends on position.
Here,
x means location.
It means all of the components of position.
x,
y,
and z.
And it depends on all
the other masses in the problem.
That is what's called a gravitational field.
It's very similar to the electric field,
except the electric field is force per unit charge.
It's the force on an object
divided by the charge of the object.
The gravitational field is the force on the
object divided by the mass on the object.
Since the force is proportional to the mass,
the acceleration field doesn't depend on
which kind of particle we're talking about.
So that's the idea of a gravitational field.
It's a vector field.
And it varies from place to place.
And of course if the particles are moving,
it also varies in time.
If everything is in motion,
the gravitational field will also depend on time.
We can even work out what it is.
We know what the force on the i-th particle is.
The force on a particle
is the mass times the acceleration.
So if we want to find the acceleration,
let's take the i-th particle to be the test particle.
The little i represents the test particle over here.
Let's erase the intermediate step over here.
And write that this is m i times a i,
but let me call it now capital A.
The acceleration of a particle at position x
is given by the right-hand side.
And we can cross out the m i,
because it cancels from both sides.
So here's a formula
for the gravitational field,
at an arbitrary point,
due to a whole bunch of massive objects.
A whole bunch of massive objects,
an arbitrary particle put over here,
will accelerate in some direction
that's determined by all the others,
and that acceleration is the definition
of the gravitational field.
Okay,
let's take a look at this.
I'll take a little break.
I usually take a break at about this time.
And I recover my breath.
To go on,
we need a little bit of fancy mathematics.
We need a piece of mathematics
called Gauss's theorem.
And Gauss's theorem involves
integrals,
derivatives,
divergences,
and we need to spell those things out.
They're a central part of the theory of gravity,
and much of these things we've done
in the context of electrical forces,
in particular the concept of divergence,
the divergence of a vector field.
So I'm not going to spend
a lot of time on it.
If you need to fill in,
then I suggest you just find any little book
on vector calculus
and find out what a divergence and a gradient
and a curl,
we won't do curl today,
what those concepts are,
and look up Gauss's theorem.
And they're not terribly hard,
but we're going to go through them fairly quickly here
since we've done them several times in the past.
All right.
Imagine that we have a vector field.
Let's call that vector field A.
It could be the field of acceleration,
and that's the way I'm going to use it,
but for the moment it's just an arbitrary vector field,
A.
It depends on position.
When I say it's a field,
the implication is that it depends on position.
That better?
Now I probably made it completely unreadable.
A of X varies from point to point,
and I want to define a
concept called the divergence of the field.
Now,
it's called the divergence
because what it has to
do is the way the field
is spreading out away from a point.
For example,
a characteristic situation
where we would have a strong divergence for a field
is if the field was spreading out
from a point like that.
The field is diverging away from the point.
Incidentally,
if the field is pointing inward,
then one might say the field has a convergence,
but we simply say it has a negative divergence.
All right.
So divergence can be positive or negative,
and there's a mathematical expression
which represents the degree to which the field
is spreading out like that.
So that's what we call the divergence.
I'm going to write it down,
and it's a good thing to get familiar with.
Certainly,
if you're going to follow this course,
it's a good thing to get familiar with.
But if you're going to follow any kind of
physics course past freshman physics,
the idea of divergence is very important.
All right.
Supposing the field A has a set of components,
the 1,
2,
and 3 component,
or we could call them the x,
y,
and z component.
Now I'll use x,
y,
and z.
I have x,
y,
and z,
which I previously called x1,
x2,
and x3.
It has components AX,
AY,
and AZ.
Those are the three components.
Those are the three components of the field.
Well,
the divergence has to do,
among other things,
with the way the field varies in space.
If the field is the same everywhere it's in space,
what does that mean?
That would mean the field has both not only
the same magnitude,
but the same direction
everywhere it's in space.
Then it just points in the same direction
everywhere it's with the same magnitude.
It certainly has no tendency to spread out.
When does a field have a tendency to spread out?
When the field varies.
For example,
it could be small over here,
growing bigger,
and we might even go in the opposite direction
and discover that it's in the opposite direction
and getting bigger in that direction.
Then clearly there's a tendency for the field
to spread out away from the center here.
The same thing could be true if it were varying
in the vertical direction,
or if it were varying in the other horizontal direction.
And so the divergence,
whatever it is,
has to do with derivatives
of the components of the field.
I'll just tell you exactly what it is.
It is equal to the divergence of the field,
it's written this way,
upside down triangle.
And the meaning of this symbol,
the meaning of an upside down triangle
is always that it has to do with the derivatives,
the three derivatives,
derivative with the three partial derivatives
derivative with respect to x,
y,
and z.
And this is by definition
the derivative with respect to x
of the x component of A
plus the derivative with respect to y
of the y component of A
plus the derivative with respect to z
of the z component of A.
That's definition.
What's not a definition is a theorem.
It's called Gauss's theorem.
No,
that's a scalar quantity.
That's a scalar quantity.
Yeah,
it's a scalar quantity.
So it's,
let me write it.
It's the derivative of A sub x
with respect to x,
that's what this means,
plus the derivative of A sub y
with respect to y,
plus the derivative of A sub z
with respect to z.
Yeah,
so the arrows you were drawing over there,
those were just A
on the other board.
You drew some arrows on the other board
that are now hidden.
Yeah.
Those were just A.
Not the divergence components.
Right.
Those were A.
And A has a divergence
when it's spreading out away from a point,
but the divergence is itself a scalar quantity.
Okay?
I'll,
let me try to give you some idea
of what divergence means
in a context where you can visualize it.
Imagine that we have a flat lake.
All right?
Just a water-thin,
a shallow lake.
And water is coming up from underneath.
It's being pumped in from somewhere underneath.
What happens if the water's being pumped in?
Of course,
it tends to spread out.
Let's assume that the high,
let's assume the depth can't change.
We put a lid over the whole thing
so it can't change its depth.
We pump some water in from underneath,
and it spreads out.
Okay?
We suck some water out from underneath,
and it spreads in.
It anti-spreads.
It has a,
all right.
So the spreading water has a divergence.
Water coming in towards the,
towards the place where it's being sucked out,
it has a convergence or a negative divergence.
Now,
we can be more precise about that.
We look down at the lake from above,
and we see all the water is moving,
of course.
It's moving.
If it's being pumped in,
it's moving.
And there is a velocity vector.
At every point,
there is a velocity vector.
So at every point in this lake,
there's a velocity vector.
And in particular,
if there's water being pumped in from the center here,
right,
underneath the bottom of the lake,
there's some water being pumped in,
the water will spread out away from that point.
Okay?
And there'll be a divergence
where the water is being pumped in.
Okay?
If the water is being pumped out,
then exactly the opposite.
The arrows point inward,
and there's a negative divergence.
The,
if there's no divergence,
then,
for example,
a simple situation with no divergence,
that doesn't mean the water is not moving.
But a simple example with no divergence
is the water is all moving together.
You know,
the river is simultaneously,
or the lake is all simultaneously moving
in the same direction with the same velocity.
It can do that without any water being pumped in.
But if you found that the water was moving
to the right on this side
and the left on that side,
you'd be pretty sure that somewhere in between,
water had to be pumped in.
Right?
If you found the water was spreading out
away from a line,
this way here,
and this way here,
then you'd be pretty sure that some water
was being pumped in from underneath
along this line here.
Well,
you would see it another way.
You would discover that the x component
of the velocity has a derivative.
It's different over here than it is over here.
The x component of the velocity
varies along the x direction.
So the fact that the x component of the velocity
is varying along the x direction
is an indication that there's some water
being pumped in here.
Likewise,
if you discovered that the water
was flowing up over here and down over here,
you would expect that in here somewhere
some water was being pumped in.
So derivatives of the velocity
are often an indication that there's some water
being pumped in from underneath.
That pumping in of the water
is the divergence of the velocity vector.
Now,
the water,
of course,
is being pumped in from underneath.
So there's a direction of flow,
but it's coming from underneath.
There's no sense of direction...
Well,
okay,
that's what divergence is.
The diagrams you already have
on the other board behind there
with the arrows,
I think,
is...
Yeah,
I think that's what I'll do.
Okay,
you take...
You take,
say,
the rightmost arrow,
and you draw a circle between the head and tail
in between,
then you can see the in and the out.
The in arrow and the out arrow
of a circle right in between those two.
And let's say that the bigger arrow
is created by a steeper slope of the stream.
Oh,
it's just faster.
It's going faster.
Okay,
and because of that,
there's a divergence there
that's basically...
Mm-hmm.
It's sort of the difference
between the in and the out.
Right,
that's right.
That's right.
If we draw a circle around here,
we would see that more...
Since the water is moving faster over here
than it is over here,
more water is flowing out over here
than is coming in over here.
Where's it coming from?
It must be pumped in.
The fact that there's more water
flowing out on one side
than is coming in from the other side
must indicate that
there's a net inflow from somewhere else,
and the somewhere else would be
from the pumping water from underneath.
So that's the idea of divergence.
Could it also be because it's thinning out?
Would that be a crazy example,
like the lake got shallower?
Yeah,
well,
okay.
I took a...
All right,
so let's be very specific now.
I kept the lake having an absolutely uniform height,
and let's also suppose that the density
of water...
Water is an incompressible fluid.
It can't be squeezed.
It can't be stretched.
Then the velocity vector
would be the right thing to think about then.
But the density would...
Yeah,
but you could have...
No,
you're right.
You could have a velocity vector
having a divergence
because the water is...
Not because water is flowing in,
but because it's thinning out.
Yeah,
that's also possible.
Okay,
but let's keep it simple.
All right,
and you can have...
The idea of a divergence makes sense
in three dimensions just as well as two dimensions.
You simply have to imagine
that all of space is filled with water,
and there are some hidden pipes coming in,
depositing water in different places
so that it's spreading out away from points
in three-dimensional space.
In three-dimensional space,
this is the expression
for the divergence.
If this were the velocity vector at every point,
you would calculate this quantity,
and that would tell you how much new water
is coming in at each point of space.
So that's the divergence.
Now,
there's a theorem which...
The hint of the theorem
was just given by Michael there.
It's called Gauss's theorem,
and it says something intuitive,
very intuitively obvious.
You take a surface,
any surface,
take any surface
or any curve in two dimensions,
and now suppose there's a vector field.
Vector field,
points.
Think of it as the flow of water.
And now let's take the total amount
of water that's flowing out of the surface.
Obviously,
there's some water
flowing out over here,
and of course,
we want to subtract
the water that's flowing in.
Let's calculate the total amount
of water that's flowing out of the surface.
That's an integral over the surface.
Why is it an integral?
Because we have to add up
the flows of water outward.
Where the water is coming inward,
that's just negative flow.
Negative outward flow.
We add up the total outward flow
by breaking up the surface
into little pieces and asking
how much flow is coming out
from each little piece here.
How much water is passing out
through the surface.
If the water is incompressible,
incompressible means its density is fixed,
and furthermore,
the depth of the water
is being kept fixed.
There's only one way that water
can come out of the surface,
and that's if it's being pumped in,
if there's a divergence.
The divergence could be over here,
it could be over here,
it could be over here.
In fact,
anywhere where there's a divergence
will cause an effect in which water
will flow out of this region here.
So there's a connection.
There's a connection between
what's going on on the boundary
of this region,
how much water is flowing through the boundary
on the one hand,
and what the divergence is
in the interior.
There's a connection between the two,
and that connection is called
Gauss's theorem.
What it says is that the integral
of the divergence in the interior,
that's the total amount of flow
coming in from outside,
from underneath the bottom of the lake,
the total integrated,
and now by integrated I mean
in the sense of an integral,
the integrated amount of flow in,
that's the integral of the divergence,
the integral over the interior,
in the three-dimensional case,
it would be integral dxdy dz,
over the interior of this region
of the divergence of A,
if you like to think of A
as the velocity field,
that's fine,
is equal to the total amount of flow
that's going out through the interior
through the boundary.
And how do we write that?
The total amount of flow that's flowing
outward through the boundary,
we break up,
let's take the three-dimensional case,
we break up the boundary into little cells.
Each little cell is a little area.
Let's call each one of those little areas
d sigma.
d sigma,
sigma stands for surface area,
sigma is the Greek letter sigma,
it stands for surface area.
This three-dimensional integral
over the interior here
is equal to a two-dimensional integral
d sigma over the surface,
and it is just the component
of A perpendicular to the surface.
Let's call it A perpendicular to the surface d sigma.
A perpendicular to the surface
is the amount of flow that's coming out
of each one of these little boxes.
Notice,
incidentally,
that if there's a flow along the surface,
it doesn't give rise to any fluid coming out.
It's only the flow perpendicular to the surface,
the component of the flow perpendicular to the surface,
which carries fluid from the inside to the outside.
So we integrate the perpendicular component
of the flow
over the surface,
that's the little d sigma here,
that gives us the total amount of fluid
coming out per unit time,
for example,
and that has to be equal
to the amount of fluid that's being generated
in the interior by the divergence.
This is Gauss's theorem,
the relationship between
the integral of the divergence
on the interior of some region
and the integral over the boundary
where it's measuring the flux,
the amount of stuff that's coming out
through the boundary.
Fundamental theorem.
Let's see what it says now.
Any questions about Gauss's theorem here?
You'll see how it works.
I'll show you how it works in a minute.
You mentioned that for water,
as in compressible,
does that mean that we're,
that we were dealing with a compressible fluid?
Well,
yeah,
you could have,
sure,
if you had a compressible fluid,
you could discover that all the fluid
out in the boundary here is all moving inwards
in every direction
without any new fluid being formed.
In fact,
what's happening is just
the fluid is getting squeezed.
But if the fluid can't squeeze,
if you cannot compress it,
the only way that fluid could be flowing in
is if it's being removed somehow from the center,
if it's being removed by invisible pipes
that are carrying it off.
So that means the divergence in the case of water
would be zero,
would be integrated over a volume?
If there was no water coming in,
it wouldn't be zero.
If there was a source of the water,
divergence is the same as source.
Source of water is,
source of new water coming in from elsewhere is,
right,
so in the example with the two-dimensional lake,
the source is water flowing in from underneath.
The sink,
which is the negative of a source,
is the water flowing out.
And in the two-dimensional example,
this wouldn't be a two-dimensional surface integral.
It would be the integral in here equal to
a one-dimensional surface integral coming out.
Okay.
All right,
let me show you how you use this.
Let me show you how you use this
and what it has to do
with what we've said up till now
about gravity.
I think,
I hope we'll have time.
Let's imagine that we have a source,
it could be water,
but let's take three-dimensional case.
There's a divergence of
a vector field,
let's say A.
There's a divergence of a vector field,
del dot A,
and it's concentrated
in some region of space
that's a little sphere.
In some region of space that has spherical symmetry,
in other words,
it doesn't mean that the divergence is uniform over here,
but it means that it
has the symmetry of a sphere.
Everything is symmetrical with respect to rotation.
Let's suppose that there's a divergence of the fluid.
Okay.
Now let's take,
and it's restricted completely to be within here.
It could be strong near the
center and weak near the outside,
or it could be weak near
the center and strong near the outside,
but a certain total amount of fluid
or a certain total divergence,
an integrated divergence,
is occurring with nice spherical shape.
Okay.
Let's see if we can use that
to figure out what the field,
what the A field is.
There's a del dot A in here.
And now let's see,
can we figure out what the field is elsewhere,
outside of here?
So what we do is
we draw a surface around there.
We draw a surface around there.
And now we're going to use Gauss's theorem.
First of all,
let's look at the left side.
The left side has the integral
of the divergence of the vector field.
Alright.
The vector field,
or the divergence,
is completely restricted to some finite sphere in here.
What is,
incidentally,
for the flow case,
for the fluid flow case,
what would be the integral of the divergence?
Does anybody know?
If it really was a flow of a fluid.
It would be the total amount of fluid
that was flowing in,
per unit time.
It would be the flow per unit time
that's coming into the system.
But whatever it is,
this integral doesn't depend on the radius of the sphere
as long as the sphere,
this outer sphere here,
is bigger than this region.
Why?
Because the integral over the divergence
of A is entirely concentrated in this region here,
and there's zero divergence on the outside.
So first of all,
the left-hand side
is independent of the radius of this outer sphere
as long as the radius of the outer sphere
is bigger than this concentration of divergence here.
So it's a number.
Altogether it's a number.
Let's call that number M.
No,
not M.
Let's just,
Q.
That's the left-hand side,
and it doesn't depend on the radius.
On the other hand,
what is the right-hand side?
Well,
there's a flow going out,
and if everything is nice and spherically symmetric,
then the flow is going to go radially outward.
It's going to be a pure,
radially outward directed flow,
if the flow is spherically symmetric.
Radially outward directed flow means
that the flow is perpendicular
to the surface of the sphere.
So the perpendicular component of A
is just the magnitude of A.
That's it.
It's just the magnitude of A,
and it's the same everywhere as on the sphere.
Why is it the same?
Because everything has spherical symmetry.
Now spherical symmetry,
the A that appears here,
is constant over this whole sphere.
So,
this integral is nothing but the magnitude of A
times the area of the total sphere.
If I take an integral over a surface,
a spherical surface like this,
of something which doesn't depend on
where I am on the sphere,
then it's just,
you can take this on the outside,
the magnitude of the field,
and the integral d sigma
is just the total surface area of the sphere.
What's the total surface area of the sphere?
Four-thirds pi r squared.
No third,
just four pi r squared.
Oh,
yeah.
Four pi r squared times the magnitude
of the field is equal to q.
So look what we have.
We have that the magnitude of the field
is equal to the total integrated divergence
divided by four pi,
four pi is just a number,
times r squared.
Does that look familiar?
It's a vector field.
It's pointed radially outward,
well,
it's pointed radially outward
if the divergence is positive.
If the divergence is positive,
it's pointed radially outward,
and its magnitude is one over r squared.
It's exactly the gravitational field
of a point particle at the center here.
That doesn't look like magnitude of A.
Hmm?
Doesn't look like you've got a scalar.
It's the magnitude of A.
Yeah.
That's why we have to put a direction in here.
You know what this r hat,
this r over r is?
It's a unit vector
pointing in the radial direction.
It's a vector of unit length
Right.
So it's quite clear from the picture
that the A field is pointing radially outward.
That's what this says over here.
All right.
In any case,
the magnitude of the field,
it points radially outward,
it has magnitude q,
and it falls off like one over r squared,
exactly like the Newtonian field
of a point mass.
Okay?
So a point mass can be thought of
as a concentrated divergence
of the gravitational field right at the center,
a point mass,
a literal point mass,
can be thought of as a concentrated
divergence of the gravitational field,
concentrated in some very,
very small little volume.
Think of it,
if you like,
you can think of the gravitational field
as the flow field or the velocity field
of a fluid that's spreading out.
Oh,
incidentally,
of course,
I've got the sign wrong here.
The real gravitational acceleration points inward,
which is an indication that this divergence is negative.
The divergence is more like a convergence
sucking fluid in.
So the Newtonian gravitational field is isomorphic,
is mathematically equivalent
or mathematically similar
to a flow field to a flow of water
or whatever other fluid
where it's all being sucked out
from a single point.
And as you can see,
the velocity field itself,
or in this case the field,
the gravitational field,
but the velocity field would go like
one over r squared.
That's a useful analogy.
That is not to say that
space is a flow of anything.
It's a mathematical analogy that's useful
to understand the one over r squared force law,
that it is mathematically similar
to a field of velocity flow
from a flow that's being generated
right at the center at a point.
Okay,
that's a useful observation.
But notice something else.
Supposing now,
instead of having
the flow concentrated at the center here,
supposing the flow was concentrated
over a sphere which was bigger,
but the same total amount of flow.
It would not change the answer.
As long as the total amount of flow is fixed,
the way that it flows out through here
is also fixed.
This is Newton's theorem.
Newton's theorem in the gravitational context
says that the gravitational field of an object,
outside the object,
is independent of whether the object
is a point mass at the center,
or whether it's a spread out mass,
or whether it's a spread out mass this big.
As long as you're outside the object,
and as long as the object is spherically symmetric,
in other words,
as long as the object
is shaped like a sphere,
and you're outside of it,
on the outside of it,
outside of where the mass distribution is,
then the gravitational field of it
doesn't depend on the mass
it depends on whether it's a point,
it's a spread out object,
whether it's denser at the center
and less dense at the outside,
less dense in the inside,
more dense in the outside.
All it depends on is the total amount of mass.
The total amount of mass is like
the total amount of flow through,
coming into the...
That theorem is very fundamental and important
to thinking about gravity.
For example,
supposing we are interested
in the motion of an object
near the surface of the Earth,
but not so near that we can make
the flat space approximation.
Let's say at a distance two or three
or one and a half
times the radius of the Earth.
Well,
that object is attracted by this point,
it's attracted by this point,
it's attracted by that point,
it's close to this point,
it's far from this point,
it's a point that seems like a hellish problem
to figure out what the gravitational effect
on this point is,
but no.
This tells you the gravitational field
is exactly the same as if the same total mass
was concentrated right at the center.
That's Newton's theorem,
and it's a marvelous theorem,
and it's a great piece of luck for him
because without it he couldn't have
solved his equations.
He knew,
he had an argument,
it may have been essentially this argument,
I'm not sure exactly what argument he made,
but he knew that with the
one over r squared force law,
and only the one over r squared force law,
wouldn't have been true if
it was one over r cubed,
one over r to the fourth,
one over r to the seventh.
With the one over r squared force law,
a spherical distribution of mass behaves exactly
as if all the mass
was concentrated right at the center
as long as you're outside the mass.
So that's what made it possible for Newton
to easily solve his own equations,
that every object,
as long as it's spherical in shape,
behaves as if it were a point mass.
So if you're down in
a mine shaft that doesn't hold?
That's right.
If you're down in a mine shaft that doesn't hold,
but that doesn't mean you
can't figure out what's going on.
You can figure out what's going on.
I don't think we'll do it tonight,
it's a little too late.
But yes,
we can work out what
would happen in a mine shaft,
but that's right,
it doesn't hold in a mine shaft.
For example,
supposing you dig a mine shaft
right down through the center of the earth,
and now you get very close
to the center of the earth,
how much force do you expect
to be pulling you toward the center?
Not much.
Certainly much less than if you were,
than if all the mass
were concentrated right at the center.
You've got,
it's not even obvious which way the force is,
but it is toward the center,
but it's very small.
You displace away from the center
of the earth a little bit,
there's a tiny,
tiny little force.
Much,
much less than as if all
the mass was squashed toward the center.
So,
right,
it doesn't work for that case.
Another interesting case is supposing
you have a shell of material,
to have a shell of material,
think about a shell of source,
fluid flowing in.
Fluid is flowing in from the outside onto this blackboard,
and all the little pipes are
arranged on a circle like this.
What does the fluid flow look like in different places?
Well,
the answer is on the outside,
in the middle,
it looks exactly the same as
if everything were concentrated on a point.
But what about in the interior?
What would you guess?
Nothing.
Everything is just flowing out away from here.
And there's no flow in here at all.
How could there be?
Which direction would it be in?
And,
uh,
so there's no flow in here.
Wouldn't you have the distance argument?
Like,
if you're closer to the surface of the inner shell,
Yeah.
wouldn't that be more force towards that?
No.
You see,
you use Gauss's theorem.
Let's do Gauss's theorem.
Gauss's theorem says,
okay,
let's take a shell.
The field,
the integrated field coming out of that shell
is equal to the integrated divergence in here.
But there is no divergence in here.
So the net integrated field coming out is zero.
No field on the interior of the shell,
field on the exterior of the shell.
So the consequence is that if
you made a spherical shell of material,
like that,
the interior would be absolutely
identical to what it would be
if there was no gravitating material there at all.
On the other hand,
on the outside,
you would have a field which would be absolutely identical
to what happens at the center.
Now,
there is an analog of this
in the general theory of relativity.
We'll get to it.
Uh,
basically what it says is the field of anything,
as long as it's spherically symmetric on the outside,
looks identical to the field of a black hole.
Uh,
but,
uh,
I think we're finished for tonight.
Go over divergence and all those,
uh,
Gauss's theorem.
Gauss's theorem is central.
There would be no gravity without Gauss's theorem.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.