This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Let's very quickly review and
then I want to move on to some,
I think,
somewhat difficult concepts.
My purpose in teaching these courses was to
try to teach what I called the theoretical
minimum.
The minimum amount of stuff that you really
need if you truly want to technically be able
to go on to the next step.
The next step in this case
after general relativity might be cosmology.
And you really want to do it right,
but you don't want to do everything.
You don't want to do all the applications.
You don't want to learn everything.
You want to learn just enough,
the bare minimum,
to be able to go to the next step.
Tonight I think we're going to face the
fact that the bare minimum is already a little
bit complicated and requires some mathematical effort.
It doesn't require advanced mathematics.
It just requires patience to go through
the calculations and to do them right.
If I just told you
in words what the answers are.
I think I would not be giving you the minimum.
I think I would be
giving you less than the minimum.
So
Today today may be a little
bit trying but bear with it
What you get out of it if
you follow it will be worth the effort
Okay,
let's just go through the definitions of
the transformation properties of the two
kinds of components covariant and contravariant
if I have a
Covariant set of components
Covariant means lower
And they're now referring to a coordinate system Y
Not only do I think
of them as functions of Y
But I also think of them
as the components the covariant components
relative to the coordinate axes of Y
defined by the Y coordinates
Okay,
so this is V sub M in the Y
coordinate system both with respect to its components and
With respect to what it depends on Y
Those components can be expressed in terms of
the components in terms of some other coordinate system
You know some other coordinate system X Y and X
Given the components the covariant
components in one coordinate system
You can translate them to
the components in another coordinate system,
and here's the formula that we worked out last time
that
Vm is related to Vn of X
By multiplying it by dx n by dy M
We worked that out last time
These are the set of objects that you use and
Keep in mind that the
summation convention is in force here
So summing over n the open
index on this side is M
So this side here is the Mth component of V
The n index here is summed
over so it's just a dummy index
But on both sides you have an open index M and
notice that that open index M has to do with Y
It's the Mth Y coordinate here and on the
left hand side this also has to do with Y
Because we're talking about the components of
the vector in the Y coordinate system
the X coordinate system that's been summed over and
It appears only as a dummy index here.
This is the transformation property of
A vector if it doesn't transform this way,
it's not called a vector
Even if it has components even if you
might try building up an arrow to represent it
You know,
there's no question you can take
Let's take the temperature the pressure and
The humidity there are three numbers and
I could now build myself a arrow
Which along that axis has a length equal to the
temperature along that axis has a length equal to the humidity?
And so forth and so on
that object is not a tensor.
It is not a vector
It's just a thing you
made up out of three scalars
It's not a tensor because
The its components when you go to a different
reference frame don't transform right the temperature is the temperature
It's the same in all coordinate systems,
and it doesn't change from one coordinate system
to another so the temperature does not transform
like one of the components of a vector
In fact,
it transforms as a scalar
All right,
so any set of three numbers or four numbers depending on the dimensionality of the space is not
does not constitute a vector a vector is characterized by its transformation properties given it in one coordinate system.
How do you get it in the other?
likewise
I'm using V now is the generic term for a vector
not necessarily the same vector if I have a vector with
Total vector higher or lower you can stored element together
which is the set of confirming
the segment in a set of signs
What I see is that the set of superintendent you
have inside yourла set has an Hotel have aual name
Well now my test is to remove the constraint
or the solution on x from the hits vector.
I'm not going to leave it 영상
I see this something trained to
break mine and sort my equations
Let's say I have as one gradient vector
With a very long now I can't find it unless you have
a Russia counter-variant variant but you know what we addressed this idea?
mistake about whether it's dxdy or dy dx,
if you're talking about a thing
with a covariant index here,
it's got to match with a contravariant index here.
On the left-hand side you have a covariant M,
on the right-hand side you
have a covariant M,
and what's more the covariant M
on this side has to do with
Y,
so the covariant M on this
side has to do with Y,
so you can bet your boots that
that this one is going
to be X in the upstairs.
Same here,
on the left-hand side
you have a contravariant index M,
an upstairs index M,
associated with the Y
coordinates and that's why you have
an upstairs index here also associated with
the Y coordinates.
So there's a pattern,
that's the pattern of transformation
properties of a vector.
I won't bother writing down the transformation
properties of a scalar,
they don't transform,
they're the same in every
coordinates as a vector.
I think I'm a little confused about,
you said if it's a vector
it has to satisfy that top equation.
Does it have to satisfy the second equation?
Don't identify this set of objects
with this set of objects yet.
This is just some covariant vector.
Remember I gave you some example of a
covariant vector.
The gradient,
the derivative of a scalar with respect to
a coordinate is a covariant vector.
Don't try to think of now of the connection
between covariant and contra,
they're different objects for the moment.
So I
shouldn't have called them by the same letter,
I just don't want to
run out of letters,
so I'll call them both V.
Wait,
let's not,
let's call it W.
Okay,
this is,
let's call it W.
Okay.
So here is the transformation
property of a covariant object,
this is the transformation
property of a contravariant object.
And they're not the same thing.
Here's a covariant vector.
An example of a contravariant vector
would just be a small displacement,
dx,
m.
dx and dy representing a small little displacement.
Well,
the x,
sorry,
dx1 and dx2.
Let's see,
here's the x coordinates.
Let's say this one is x1,
let's say this one is x2.
You build yourself a vector by going off and
making an excursion along the x1 axis by dx1,
and then along the x2 axis by x2.
And the resultant is the vector that
we can use to find the vector.
So we can just call dx.
The vector that we call
dx has components which are contravariant.
They're contravariant indices.
The components of a gradient are covariant.
And you can't go wrong.
If you remember,
the only rule you have to remember
is that coordinates carry their indices upstairs.
That's an arbitrary rule.
It could have been the other way.
But it's an arbitrary rule.
I'm not sure whom it's due to.
But you label the coordinates,
x1,
x2,
x3,
with superscripts.
And once you do that,
it's hard to go wrong.
Here's a superscript on an m,
but it's downstairs in the denominator of something.
It just looks like it has
to do with something with lower indices.
And in fact,
it is true that this can
be thought of as the gradient vector.
Let me call it v again.
v sub m.
It's a covariant vector.
dx has its indices upstairs.
It's a contravariant vector.
Now the transformation properties came from
the transformation properties of this object.
Right?
Let's just see.
If the vector we're talking about is a gradient,
then this equation just says that
partial of phi with respect to ym,
that's the left-hand side here,
because v is a gradient,
that's equal,
on the right-hand side,
we have partial of phi with respect to x,
whoops,
x,
y,
m,
n.
That's this object times dxn.
By dyn.
And dym.
Is this a correct equation?
Yeah.
That's a correct equation.
d phi by dy is d
phi by dx times dx by dy.
This equation didn't come from the
definition of any vector or covariant-contravariant.
It just came from element of calculus
that the gradient with respect to y
is just equal to the gradient with respect
to x times the set of components dxdy.
That's elementary calculus.
Elementary multivariable calculus.
But it's the place that we abstracted this rule.
If I now call this vm,
sorry,
vm,
and this one vn,
then that's my rule.
Likewise,
the transformation property of the complex,
the quanta-variant vectors,
came from the statement that dym
is equal to the partial of ym
with respect to xn times dxn.
Again,
this here had,
did not come from somebody's preconceived notion
about how tensors should transform.
It's just a calculus fact.
Or some sort of chain rule.
They're both some sort of chain rules,
I guess.
And now if I replace dym
by wm and dxn by wn here,
that defines,
or this defines,
the transformation property
of a covariant-contravariant vector.
That's where they came from.
So covariant and contravariant mean things that transform
the same way as gradients on the one hand
and differentials,
differential displacements.
Differential displacements,
and gradients.
Those are the sort of
archetypes of covariant and contravariant objects.
We can have more complicated
objects with any number of indices.
The transformation properties of objects
with more indices are similar.
Let me just give you an example.
Let's say that we have a complex object.
Here's the transformation property
of a covariant expression.
Supposing I have a tensor with two indices.
Let's say m and r.
Then the rule is for each index,
for each index,
there's a factor of a dx by dy.
And here's the way it works.
This is t in the y coordinate.
We're going to relate it
to t in the x coordinate.
Not mr,
but we better choose some new,
let's call it ns.
And now,
just as over here,
to relate the m index to the n index,
we need dx.
This is a sort of operation which takes
us from an n index to an m index.
We do exactly that.
dxn by dym.
But that works on the first index here.
We also need to work on the second index,
and that's dxs by dyr.
Now look at it.
On the right-hand side,
we have the components of the tensor,
the rank two tensor,
two indices,
in the x coordinates.
All right.
Two lower indices.
Those lower indices have to do with x.
So on the right-hand side,
sorry,
it must multiply something with
contravariant indices,
again,
referring to x.
But on the left-hand side,
we have covariant indices referring to y,
likewise on this side over here.
That's the pattern.
Indices are the things which transform.
Yeah?
Could you mix them or make any sense,
sir?
How would you want to mix them?
Some upper and some lower.
Yes.
Certainly.
For example,
you could have a,
all right,
let's do another example.
Supposing we had a tensor
which had one lower index and one upper index.
Perfectly good object.
How does it transform?
Well,
we should have,
I should not have erased the transformation properties
of the things with upper indices here.
Let me write them down over here.
So,
yeah,
here's for the lower index m,
and let me change variable here.
Let's call it rr.
And now let's write the transformation property
of an upper index,
and that's going to be dyn by dxs vs.
All right,
so here's the thing with the lower index.
Here's the thing with an upper index.
Here's an object,
a tensor with a lower index
and an upper index.
How does it transform?
Well,
just,
first of all,
we have to work on the m index.
That's going to give us a dxr by dyn.
And then we have to work on the upper index.
That will give us a dyn by dxs
times t.
Now,
let's see,
what is it?
T,
the upper index is s,
and the lower index is r.
All right,
so,
that's the transformation properties of a thing
with an upper and lower index.
And it's just borrowed,
it's just exactly the same as
if you just stuck this thing
next to this thing,
and thought of the tensor as just a product,
vm,
vn.
On the left-hand side,
vm,
vn,
referred to the y coordinates.
On the right-hand side,
vr,
vs,
related to the y coordinates.
All right?
So that's the transformation property of a mixed tensor
with some upper and some lower indices.
And the general rule for
any number of indices is similar.
Okay,
that's,
that,
without this set of rules,
it would be hopeless to try to explain
the geometry of even a simple thing like a sphere
in any great detail.
But certainly,
a general geometry
of arbitrary curvature,
wiggles,
and so forth,
hopeless,
without tensors.
So tensors are the key
to understanding the geometry of curved spaces.
Okay,
let me point,
let's do something else.
Let's take a tensor
which happens to have,
yes,
let's take this tensor,
which happens to have an upper and lower index.
And now,
let's identify and sum
the upper index with the lower index.
In other words,
let's take tmm.
That means
t11 plus t22 plus t33,
however many dimensions of space I have.
t,
one lower and one upper index.
This is a legal operation to combine
or to identify an upper index with a lower index
and sum over them.
I don't need to write the summation sign.
I claim that this object
with the indices identified
and then summed,
how many indices,
what indices does this whole object have?
Does it have any indices?
No,
it has no indices left over.
They've been summed over.
It doesn't have a t1.
It doesn't have a,
it's just a pure thing.
It's a sum
and it doesn't have any leftover indices.
What kind of thing is it likely to be?
A scalar.
Alright,
let's check that it really is a scalar.
All we have to do
is identify m with n.
Let's do it over here.
Set m equal to n
or n equal to m.
We better do it over here also.
I've set n equal to m.
And sum.
Now,
what do we have here?
We have the change in xr
when we vary y
times the change in y
when we vary xs.
What is this whole object here?
Anybody know?
That's the Kronecker delta.
It's the Kronecker delta.
It's really just the derivative of xr
with respect to xs.
The derivative of xr
with respect to ym
times the derivative of ym
with respect to xs.
Summed over m
is the same as
the derivative of xr
with respect to xs.
Just cancel out the ym.
Well,
what's the derivative of xr
with respect to xs?
It's like having three coordinates,
x,
y,
and z.
The derivative of x with respect to x is 1.
The derivative of x with respect to y is 0.
So this is a number
which is 1
when r is the same as s
and 0 otherwise.
In other words,
it's just the Kronecker delta.
We could replace this
and replace it by the Kronecker delta,
delta rs.
1 when r is equal to s,
0 when r is not equal to s.
But now we're supposed to sum over r and s.
What will that give us?
It'll just give us the sums
of t11 plus t22 plus t33 again.
Whenever you see a Kronecker delta,
it's really just a shorthand
or it's just an instruction
to set r equal to s.
Why?
Because it's 1 if r equals s
and it's 0 otherwise.
So it's just an instruction.
You can throw it away
and the rest of the expression
set r equal to s.
So look what we have.
We have tmm of y
equals trr of x.
In other words,
this particular combination
doesn't depend on which coordinate system you use.
The dependence of the components
on coordinate system
cancel out
when you identify the upper index
and the lower index and sum.
That's a general pattern.
If I have some tensor,
let's call it w,
with a whole bunch of indices,
mnrpq,
I don't know,
what's another letter?
Z.
That's a terrible notation.
You're not supposed to do that.
Mnr.
And now that's a tensor
with six indices,
a six-rank tensor
with three covariant
and three contravariant indices.
Let me make it a little general.
Let's make a different number
of upper indices and lower indices.
So a,
four upper indices
and three lower indices.
Now,
if I identify an upper index
with a lower index,
for example,
replace z by m and sum,
the result is a tensor
with three upper indices
and two lower indices.
That's a pattern.
You prove it the same way
as I proved this,
that when you identify
upper and lower indices
and sum over them,
what's left over,
the index structure that's left over
after you've summed over m,
the components still transform
as a tensor,
in this case with three upper indices
and two lower indices.
So that's a process
that you can do on a tensor,
that creates another tensor
of lower rank,
smaller number of indices.
For example,
if you construct a tensor
out of two vectors,
let's construct,
let's take two vectors,
v and w.
Let's suppose v has upper indices
and w has lower indices.
That's a tensor,
just a product.
In other words,
the components
are simply the products
of components.
We call that T m n.
If I then identify m with n
and sum,
that defines a scalar.
What is that scalar called?
That's the dot product
of two vectors.
It's the inner product,
sometimes called the inner product
between two vectors.
So,
the inner product,
and even better,
supposing they're the same vector,
well,
we haven't defined what it means
for them to be the same vector.
So far,
things with upper components
are simply different
than things with lower components.
Yeah?
Can we therefore say
that w,
you've expressed there,
with seven indices
is equal to a scalar times w n r a?
No,
no,
it's not a scale,
it's not a scale of times.
It could be,
depending on the character
of this tensor.
It could be that,
but it's not typically a product,
no.
But when you do contract,
this is called contracting the indices.
This process is called
contracting the indices m.
When you contract the index m,
it simply lowers the rank
of the tensor,
and the remaining objects
do form a tensor.
It doesn't mean
that this w here
is some scalar times w n r a,
or you know,
n r a p q.
It does not mean that.
In general,
that won't be true.
What's that?
In general,
no,
it's not equal to that.
It may be equal to that
in a special case.
That's a special case,
but in general,
it's not true.
So,
yeah.
When you have one vector,
when you have one index,
you have vectors.
When you have two indexes,
does that correspond
to planes or anything?
Yeah,
it corresponds
to planes.
Yeah.
But,
sometimes it corresponds
to planes.
The tensor that we,
got a little bit familiar with
last time,
the rank two tensor,
was the metric tensor.
The metric tensor has
a geometric meaning.
It's simply related
to the distance between
neighboring points.
Neighboring points mean points
which are separated
by differential distances.
All right,
so if I have
a,
a set of differentials,
dxm,
and that corresponds
to two neighboring points,
and we can ask,
what's the difference,
what's the distance,
what's the distance between them?
The actual distance.
The distance between them,
squared,
it's called ds squared,
and it's given by
dxm,
dxn,
times the metric tensor,
gmn of x.
Now notice,
this is a special case
of the rule of contracting indices.
We've contracted m with m
and n with n.
There are no leftover indices.
This is a scalar.
Two contravariant indices,
two covariant indices,
and the metric tensor
is the object
which allows you to compute,
if you know it,
you know,
it allows you to compute
the,
the distance between neighboring points.
Now,
is g really a tensor?
Let's check.
To check,
we have to see how it transforms.
All right,
to see how it transforms,
we need to write the distance
between the same two points,
but instead of in x notation,
in y notation.
So,
all we need to do is write
that dxm
is equal to the derivative
of xm with respect to
yr,
dyr.
Right?
The change in xm
is just,
or the differential displacement in xm
is the derivative of xm
with respect to yr
times the differential displacement in y.
If I plug that in
for both x,
dxm and dxn,
what will I find?
I'll find that this is the derivative of xm
with respect to yr,
that's for this one,
and this one,
dxn
by dys
times gmn
times
dyr
dys
All right,
I've just
got
the derivative of xm
Here's gmn,
that's still there,
gmn of x,
that's still there.
dxm and dxn,
I've each replaced by
dx by dy
times the corresponding dy.
Each one of them,
dxm and dxn.
And now,
if I take this whole thing here,
and call it
grs of y,
then my formula reads,
that ds squared
is equal to
grs of y
dyr
dys
In other words,
we've discovered
that
g
in the y-coordinate system
is g
in the x-coordinate system
times these familiar factors,
which are the standard factors
for the transformation of
covariant indices.
So this is the simple illustration
that the metric tensor
is indeed a tensor.
If you express the distance
in either the x-coordinates
or the y-coordinates,
you'll wind up
with a grs of y
or a grs,
or a gmn of x,
and they are related
by this transformation property.
So,
that's the notion
of the metric tensor.
Now there's another important
thing that goes with
the metric tensor.
Second-rank tensors like this
are matrices.
They have two indices.
They are matrices.
g
Think of gmn
at an arbitrary point,
and I won't label the point.
It's a matrix.
I can put g11,
g12,
g13,
g21,
g22,
g23,
g31,
dot,
and so forth.
It's a matrix.
It's symmetric.
g12 is equal to g21.
And it has an inverse.
This is something you can prove.
Matrices have inverses.
What does it mean
that a matrix has inverses?
A matrix has an inverse.
It means there's another matrix
that you can multiply it by
to get the unit matrix.
What is the unit matrix
in this notation,
incidentally?
The unit matrix in this notation
is,
of course,
the matrix 1111
with all zeros.
That's the matrix,
which is...
It's what?
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Well,
however many components there are.
Yeah.
The unit matrix is the matrix
which every component is either zero
if m is not equal to n
or one if m is equal to n.
In other words,
it's the matrix
representing
the Kronecker delta symbol.
دلتا
أمان
Should both be lower m and n though?
That's not right,
equals,
that's right.
Say it again?
Should the m and n
and the delta both be lower?
No.
The Kronecker delta in relativity theory always
has one index upper and one index lower.
If ever you have a formula with two
lower indices and it says delta m n,
either you're
doing something special and unusual
and not following the usual conventions,
which is
okay,
you're allowed to,
you're allowed to break conventions if you need to,
but it means
it's not associated with a tensor,
it's not a tensor operation.
So delta n m,
its components are also a tensor.
Now,
to say that there's another matrix,
let's call this matrix,
let's just call it g,
let's
not indicate any indices at all and
let's just think of it as a matrix.
There's another matrix,
which is the inverse matrix,
and the product of the two matrices
are the unit matrix.
In index notation,
to write that in index notation,
it's g,
let's call it,
let's call it r n,
g inverse,
and now m r.
Here's the matrix.
Here's the rule,
the standard rule for contracting indices.
Take a upper index here.
Now so far I haven't told you that the,
I'm telling you now,
the thing,
the inverse matrix
defines a tensor.
The components of the inverse matrix
define a tensor with upper indices,
with contravariant
indices.
This is not obvious.
It's a theorem.
I would look it up.
If you want,
look up the theorem that the inverse of the metric,
thought of as a matrix,
is itself also a tensor,
or also defines a set
of components which are tensor components.
Now this operation here of contracting r
and summing over r is matrix multiplication.
This is the process of matrix multiplication.
It gives another matrix.
It's a matrix with an
index m and an index n.
I've summed over r.
The right hand side here is the identity matrix,
which is the Kronecker delta,
m n.
That's the definition of the inverse matrix here.
It's the thing which when you multiply it
by g with lower indices and then contract
one index,
you get the Kronecker delta.
Let's see if we can find it.
Okay.
First of all,
yeah,
let's take the polar coordinates.
Polar coordinates,
we have the metric ds squared is equal
to the r squared plus r squared sine
squared theta.
No,
sorry,
r squared d theta squared.
All right,
what's g11 in this case?
Let's say r corresponds to the first coordinate,
theta corresponds to the second coordinate.
Just one.
What about g22?
r squared.
No off-diagonal elements at all.
This is gmn.
What about its inverse?
Its inverse in this case is very simple.
When you have a diagonal matrix,
if you have a diagonal matrix,
its inverse...
Say it again?
I was wondering if it was r squared or r.
r squared.
Yep,
it's r squared.
You don't square d.
You don't square g.
Yeah,
the components of the metric are already squared lengths.
They already correspond to squared lengths.
The inverse matrix,
the matrix that's inverse to that
is just 1 over r squared.
So,
what's g?
If you multiply the two matrices together,
you'll get the unit matrix.
If you think of them as objects
with indices and contract the r index,
you'll get the Karmica
delta.
Try it out.
Check it out.
This inverse of the metric...
I don't know that it has the next...
I don't think it has
a special name of its own.
It's just called the metric with contravariant components.
It's called the collection of
contravariant components of the metric.
If you know one of them,
you know the other.
If you know a matrix,
you know its inverse.
The inverse of the inverse is the original matrix.
So knowledge of g with lower indices is
equivalent to knowledge of g with upper indices.
The theorem...
And this is not a trivial theorem.
The theorem is...
And I'm not going to do it on the blackboard.
The theorem is that the set of components
of the inverse matrix are themselves a tensor.
They're a tensor with contravariant components.
So if you take the metric
and you invert it as a matrix,
it's a collection of components.
Those components form a contravariant tensor.
It's another representation of the metric.
Since it has the same information in it,
but it's just presented in a different way.
Those two objects are fundamental.
G with lower indices and g with upper indices.
And we don't bother writing the inverse there.
We just remember that when
g is written with upper indices,
it's the inverse matrix to
the ones with lower indices.
And so the identity...
The...
Identity in the sense of a...
A...
This is...
This is the definition of the equation.
GMRGRN is delta MN.
This is,
if you like,
the definition of the object with contravariant components.
It's a...
Now its geometric meaning is a little more obscure.
The geometric meaning of this object is clear.
It has to do with the separation between points.
This object you'll just get familiar with.
You'll get to use it and
you'll see it does some useful things.
Alright,
that's the idea of the metric tensor
and its inverse or the metric tensor with
covariant indices and the
metric tensor with contravariant indices.
Now once you have this
metric in covariant and contravariant form,
you can start playing
games and write mappings that
relate covariant and contravariant vectors.
In fact,
you can define for every covariant vector
or for every set of covariant components,
you can define a set of contravariant components
and think of it as contravariant and covariant
components of the same vector.
Here's the rule.
If I give a set of
contravariant components of the same vector,
I can define a set of
covariant components of the same vector.
If I give a set of
contravariant components of the same vector,
I can define a set of
covariant components of the same vector.
I can construct from it,
from it together with the metric tensor.
Well,
let's start with contravariant.
Let's start with contravariant.
I can construct from it and the
metric an object with a lower index.
By multiplying it by GMN and summing over M,
I can get a set of covariant components
of the same vector.
That gives me a new thing,
which I'll call V sub N.
If I know V with
superscript and I know the metric,
let's say the metric is given.
The metric is given knowledge.
It's a piece of the geometry of space.
If I know V and I know G,
then I can reconstruct a
corresponding set of components with lower
indices.
You can just think of this as the representation
of the same vector except with a lower index.
Now,
what is the connection between them really?
I'll tell you now.
The connection between them is what
I told you in the first place.
The connection between these two things is if
VM are the set of coefficients that you
multiply by unit vectors and sum them up.
Think about it.
I'm going to do a little bit of math here.
If you get the vector V,
if you think of these Vs here
as defining a vector by adding up
the Vs times unit vectors,
then the Vs with lower components are,
as I told you in the
beginning,
the covariant components of the same vector.
In other words,
the projections onto the axes.
These are the set of coefficients
that you use to expand the vector.
These are the set of orthogonal projections onto the axes.
So they're really representations of the same object,
two different representations,
and
they're related in this form.
Question?
Yeah.
Going back to the other blackboard,
can't there be tensors that don't have inverses?
There are,
but the metric tensor is never one of them.
Oh,
okay.
Yeah.
Okay.
Let's not prove that now.
It follows from the fact that G is
symmetric and that there are no directions in which
the vector has no length at all,
or no zero eigenvalues of the metric.
Right.
But that's a good question.
It's a fair question.
Let's just take it as a rule
that the metric tensor always has an inverse.
And we'll see.
I'll come back to it.
I'll prove it for you another day.
I hadn't thought about it,
but it's an easy thing to prove.
Yeah.
Is that also true in the
bubble statistic where you have minus?
Yeah,
it is.
It is.
It's still true.
Yeah.
On the upper board there,
it can be shown.
On the left.
The upper board on the left.
It can be shown,
right?
Yeah.
The ds squares are the same regardless of the coordinates.
The distance is in fact the same.
Wait,
say that again.
The distance,
the ds would be the same regardless of the coordinates.
Yeah.
It's not obvious in the expression,
but I assume it can be shown.
Wait.
That the ds squares are the same?
The ds squared is the same whether you
compute it with the gmn or the gr.
No,
that's...
That is where we got the...
We assumed that to find the...
We assumed that to find the relationship
between gmn of x and grs of y.
In other words,
I simply took this and rewrote it in this way.
It's really the same equation.
Yeah.
Given that the g's are related as they
have to be related by tensor transformation properties.
Yeah.
All right,
so let's see what it would mean for
them to not be symmetric and then see
why.
The answer is it doesn't matter whether
you're choosing to be symmetric or not,
but let's
see why.
All right.
What does g12 multiply?
G12 multiplies dx1 dx2,
right?
What does g21 number?
multiply,
multiplies dx2 dx1.
But really what that means is that the only thing
that comes in when you calculate ds
squared is g12 plus g21 dx1 dx2.
Only the combination g12 plus g21 enters into anything.
That means you can
take g21 and g12 to be equal
to each other and sort of divide it
symmetrically between the x1.
There's a piece in the metric which has dx1
multiplying dx2.
You could call it all coming
from g12 if you like or you
could all call it all coming from
g21 but the convention is to split it
equally between g12 and g21
and therefore make the g symmetric.
So it's
partly a convention but it's not a convention.
It's a useful convention.
And,
right.
So the general rule would be that
g12 is not the same thing as g21?
You could imagine generalizing things
that way but then the difference,
the non-symmetric piece would never come into anything.
Right?
Supposing g12 and g21 were the negative of each other.
Then this would just cancel out.
You'd say you just wrote
something redundant that you didn't need.
So there's no loss of generality in taking it to be
symmetric but you don't have to take it to be symmetric.
If you don't take it to be
symmetric it's not clear there's always an inverse.
Matrices with,
well I'll come back to the
question of the inverse next time.
I don't want to interrupt.
I don't want to interrupt it right now.
Okay,
so the metric allows you to play new games where
you take tensors and shift the index from upstairs to downstairs.
And think of them as the same
object except covariant components and contravariant components.
It allows you to find a one
to one correspondence between a set of
contravariant components and contravariant components.
And a set of covariant components.
And you're free to think of them as
the same thing since they have the same information.
Incidentally,
you can solve this equation for the upper components.
This is the lower components written
in terms of the upper components.
See if you can prove using the property,
where is it?
Using only the property that g,
what is it?
m r g r n equals delta r n.
Oh,
sorry.
M and n.
See if you can prove,
it's very straight forward,
that you can solve this as
v m equals g m n.
And you can solve this as v
n with upper index times v n.
Really all it is,
is another way of writing in matrix language,
it would be g times,
ah,
do it,
do it.
It follows immediately from this equation over here.
Okay.
Right.
Yeah.
All you have to do is
take v n from this equation,
plug it into here,
and you'll get an identity
that v m equals v m.
You do it.
Okay.
So you can go back and forth symmetrically
between things with upper indices and lower indices.
And the process is called
raising and lowering indices of tensors.
So every tensor has multiple tensors.
And there are multiple identities in which you can
raise and lower any of the indices at will.
Keep track of them.
Keep track of which ones you've
lowered and which ones you've raised.
For example,
if I have a general tensor t m n,
I can raise the index m.
How would I do that?
I would multiply it by g m r n.
I would multiply it by
g m r t r n.
I've taken the first index,
the first index on the left here,
and I've applied the trick to
the first index to raise it.
And what does this give me?
This gives me an object that
I can call t m n.
So I can raise and lower the indices.
And of course,
the objects that you get are
different when you raise and lower them,
but they're collections of objects which have
the same content as the original starting ones,
since you can go back and forth freely between them.
All right.
That's the sense in which vectors have an identity.
That's the sense in which a
vector has both covariant and contravariant indices.
All right.
That's basic tensor arithmetic.
Tensor algebra,
I guess one would say.
Upper indices,
lower indices,
transformation properties of the indices,
and the metric tensor that allows you to do this.
And that allows you to raise and lower indices.
Let's,
yeah.
In particular,
take the object dx m.
That stands for a little interval dx.
A little vector.
I can assign it,
and it's natural to think of
the little interval as having contravariant components.
But,
you could also define an object dx sub m,
the same vector,
by writing it as g m n dx n.
The natural thing to define to
start with is the contravariant components.
Those are just the little intervals dx.
But then nothing prevents you from constructing
the covariant version of the same object.
And this is the way you would do it.
Now,
before I told you earlier that if you have
an upper index and a lower index in a tensor,
you can contract them.
So let's take a new tensor.
Let's take a tensor which
has an upper and lower index.
And it's made just by
multiplying dx m by dx n.
That is now an object
with indices of x and y.
It's a tensor.
And now I want to
contract the index m with n.
And get dx m dx m.
What happens when you take a tensor with two indices,
one upper and one lower,
and you contract them?
What do you get?
A scalar.
So this object is a scalar.
But now let's rewrite it.
Let's rewrite it by using the tensor.
So we're saying that dx with the
lower m is g m n dx n.
That means that this object here is dx m.
Well,
let's change.
Yeah,
let's write it this way.
n.
Yeah,
no,
it was right.
dx m.
It's clearly dx m dx n g m n.
This object is just a dx with the lower index.
I lowered the index of dx n.
That's here.
And I multiply it by another dx.
So what is this object with one
dx m upper and one dx lower contracted?
It's g m n dx m dx n.
What is that?
It's the s squared.
It's the distance between them.
So by using the metric tensor to lower the index,
you can write the distance formula in two distinct ways.
You can write it g
m n dx m dx n.
Or you can just write it dx m dx m.
One lower and one upper.
Same thing.
This is a little more condensed.
This is a little more explicit.
Would you go back over that first equation you wrote,
dx m superscript and then subscript?
Here?
Yes.
And you ended up making those equal.
Sorry.
I didn't mean to write equals.
I just meant it goes to by contracting the indices.
I did not mean to write an equation.
I simply meant that you could
contract the index m and n
and construct the x with superscript,
the x with a subscript,
and this is a scalar.
This doesn't transform.
It's an invariant quantity.
Whereas the things that it was built out of transformed,
but then you contracted the index and got a scalar.
So there's two distinct ways.
In fact,
there's another way that you could write the metric.
Another way you could write it.
A third way is to write two lower indices,
dx m,
dx n,
and then what would I have to multiply it by?
G with upper indices.
Indeed.
That's also equal to the same thing.
They're all equal to each other,
and they're all equal to the distance between the points.
Okay.
The points which are
separated by the differential displacements,
the x.
All right.
That's the basic idea of the metric and simple.
What's the significance of the Gs in that relationship?
Where?
Say it again.
That you could do the orthogonal projections now.
Is there PC in those terms?
The GMN in the top equation and the bottom equation.
Lower board.
Yeah.
GMN.
Is there any correlation between those?
The upper and the lower.
Here?
The G,
GMN.
Yeah.
And then the GMN in the third equation.
Oh,
they're all summation indices,
so it doesn't matter what you call them.
Yeah.
As long as they're summed over,
it doesn't matter what you call them.
But is there a relationship in the values of them?
Like are they like inverses or ?
Well,
this is the inverse matrix to this.
So you have to know
how to construct inverses of matrices.
All right?
For simple diagonal matrices,
the inverses are easy.
You just turn the entries upside down.
For things of off-diagonal elements,
it's more complicated,
and you have to consult the book
or use a computer program or whatever.
And in particular,
for 4x4 matrices,
it's no picnic.
For 2x2 matrices,
It's always easy.
But...
Good.
All right.
So that takes us through tensor arithmetic,
tensor algebra.
Incidentally,
there are some other operations you can do with tensors
that may give you tensors.
I haven't exhausted all the operations that
you can do that give you tensors.
You can add tensors.
Add two tensors.
But when you do,
you had better make sure
they're tensors of the same type.
In other words,
you would not want to add...
Tmn plus Wmn.
That's a nonsense expression.
It has no distinct transformation properties.
This transforms one way.
This transforms the other way.
For example,
if this happened to be
zero in one set of coordinates,
it might not be zero in another set of coordinates
because the t's with the lower
indices don't transform the same way.
If a tensor is zero,
if its components are all zero in one coordinate system,
there's zero in all coordinate systems.
Why is that?
Let's just look at the sorts of things...
Well,
that's because if we have a
tensor with any number of indices
upstairs and downstairs in the y coordinates,
it is equal to a bunch of dx's
times dy's and dy's times dx's of various kinds
times the corresponding tensor in the x coordinates.
If it's zero on one side,
it's zero on the other side.
So if a tensor is zero,
in other words,
a tensor being zero means all of its components,
if all of its components are zero,
then it follows they are zero in every coordinate system.
So a tensor being zero is
an invariant statement about that tensor.
Another way to say the same thing...
perhaps it's saying something a little different,
but almost the same thing,
is that if two tensors
are equal in one coordinate system,
let's say t equals w,
m,
n in the x coordinates.
That also says,
of course,
that the difference between them is equal to zero.
Then the difference is going to
be zero in every coordinate system,
which means that the tensors
are equal in every coordinate system.
So once you prove a tensor relationship,
namely that the left-hand side of an equation
is equal to the right-hand side of an equation
in one set of coordinates,
it's true in every set of coordinates.
That's one of the powerful things about tensors,
that it allows you to make statements such as
one thing is equal to another,
although each...
side of the equation
may have complicated transformation properties,
you can be assured that
both before and after the transformation,
they will remain equal.
That may not have come out right.
You can be sure that if
they are equal in one coordinate system,
they will be equal in the other coordinate system.
That's part of the power of...
The equality of tensors
is a geometric fact which
doesn't depend on the coordinate system.
The components of the tensors
are things which do depend on the coordinate system.
Okay,
now let's take a little bit of a break
and then come to tensor calculus,
which is harder than tensor arithmetic and tensor algebra.
I was going to start
the subject that I call tensor calculus,
which means the study of how you differentiate tensors.
Of course,
you can just differentiate them,
but then it's not clear that you get tensors
when you differentiate the components of a tensor,
and in fact you don't.
You have to do something smarter than just differentiate
the components of the tensor to get the component.
The derivatives of the components of tensors
are not ordinarily components of tensors.
Does that make sense?
The derivatives of components
are not themselves components of tensors.
Hmm?
Position.
Xs.
But I think I won't do that now.
I think instead we'll do that next time,
and I think I would like to get to space-time.
We've been talking about space,
space,
and we have not been talking about relatives.
We've been talking about relativity.
We've been talking about space.
So I think we're all set up in a way
that allows us to jump straight into space-time.
And then somebody asked me what the meaning of saying
that the universe is expanding,
what does that mean,
and I think we can probably do that yet tonight,
once we introduce the idea of space-time.
Now,
to introduce the idea of space-time,
we have to go back to special relativity.
Special relativity is a subject that you can learn,
and you can learn in three days.
I assume that we all know it,
and if not,
we can all learn it quickly.
I think we...
If you've been in my class,
you've taken special relativity a couple of times already,
at least two times,
maybe more,
and I'm going to assume
that you have a basic understanding
of Lorentz transformations.
But even if not,
I think we're set up in a
manner that allows us to sort of
make quick work of it.
First,
let me just make some remarks about ordinary space.
Even if I am only going
to use the term ordinary space,
even if I am not interested in curvilinear coordinates,
or curved space,
all I'm interested in now is Cartesian coordinates,
there are still more than one Cartesian coordinate system
that we can use to describe space.
Even if I don't even...
Even if I place the origin of coordinates,
nail it to the center of someplace,
there's my origin of coordinates,
I still have not fully specified
a set of coordinates by saying they're Cartesian.
Here's a set of Cartesian coordinates.
Here's another set.
Well,
I meant to place the origin
at the intersection of the axes.
Here's another set.
Can that be seen?
Let me...
And they're just related by rotation of the coordinates,
of course.
Rotation of Cartesian coordinates is a special case
of transformations between x coordinates and y coordinates.
Another thing you can do
is translate the coordinate systems,
keep them parallel,
but translate their locations.
Those are also coordinate transformations.
In neither case do they correspond to curved coordinates,
curvilinear coordinates,
but they are coordinate transformations.
And...
All of the rules we've
set up up till now hold.
The only thing is that
in all of these coordinate systems,
the metric tensor has the same form.
The metric tensor is just the Kronecker delta.
In other words,
ds squared...
Let's talk about two dimensions for a moment.
It's just equal to dx1 squared
plus dx2 squared.
That's the same as saying that the metric tensor gmn
is equal to the Kronecker delta,
delta mn.
Now,
I said that,
strictly speaking,
delta mn with both of its indices lower
is not a good tensor object.
It is a good tensor if only...
If all we're doing is translating
between one set of Cartesian coordinates
and another.
For curvilinear coordinates,
this equation would be nonsense,
but if we're just
translating between Cartesian coordinate systems,
just rotating them or translating them,
then in every such coordinate system,
the metric is just dx1 squared plus dx2 squared,
which I can also write as delta mn dxm dxn.
In Cartesian coordinates,
there's no difference between
upper indices and lower indices.
They're the same things.
So there's a lot of simplification.
But there's another way to do it.
There's another way to say this,
that the transformations,
the class of transformations that takes you
from one coordinate system to another
are the transformations which preserve the form
of the interval,
preserve the form of the length,
preserve the form of Pythagoras'
theorem.
That the s squared,
the length of an interval is dx squared.
And what happens if I have more components,
more than mn,
dx3 squared and so forth?
So the ordinary transformations that you can do
on Cartesian coordinates are the transformations
which preserve the form of the simple
sums of dx squared as the length interval.
Now let me come to space-time.
As you know,
and if you don't,
you better find out quickly,
space-time has four coordinates.
It's a four-dimensional space.
One of the coordinates is time.
Incidentally,
we are always going to work
in units in which the speed
of light is equal to one.
Now,
there's a notion in special relativity
of the proper time,
or of the interval separating two points.
Space and time will work
with speed of light equal one,
except when I say that we won't.
And we can consider two points.
For example,
these could be two points
on the trajectory of a particle.
There's a notion that we've discussed
in previous quarters of the idea of the proper time,
the proper time interval between two points,
which is very similar,
but not,
a little different,
but very similar to the distance between two points.
But you might expect,
if you were naive,
that,
let's say there's only two dimensions,
one coordinate,
one space coordinate,
one time coordinate.
You might write ds squared is equal to dt squared
plus dx squared.
And you could write that.
That's a possible definition of something.
But it's not the right thing for relativity theory.
In particular,
the Lorentz transformations,
the things which transform you
from one frame of reference to another,
are not the things,
are not the transformations
which keep this invariant,
but keep something else invariant.
What is it?
dt squared minus dx squared.
And that's called the proper time,
often labeled by d tau squared.
If we insist on taking the speed of light
not to be one,
then the speed of light goes into this equation,
in the denominator over here.
But in special relativity,
not using c equals one
is as stupid
as using meters for x components of vectors
and inches for y components.
If you did so,
think about what your equations would look like.
You would have some crazy factors,
appearing all over the place.
First of all,
your equations would not look rotation invariant.
And they would have all over the place
peculiar numbers,
which was simply the conversion factor
for the units that you use for x dimensions
and for y dimensions and z dimensions.
The speed of light is very much like that.
It's a conversion factor
from units of length to units of time.
Choosing c equals to one
is the natural analog
of using the same units
for x measurements as y measurements.
Notice,
incidentally,
if I talked about the distance between two points,
and I measured x in different units than y,
would the distance be dx squared plus dy squared?
Let's suppose I measured x in different units than y.
Suppose I measure y in inches
and x in,
let's say,
feet.
And now I want the distance
between those two points in feet.
What would I have to put there?
If I want the distance in dx squared,
if I want it in feet,
and x is measured in feet,
then I'll have dx squared.
But what about dy squared?
y is measured in inches.
Yeah.
Divided by 12 squared.
Right.
Plus dy squared divided by 144.
You have a stupid factor of 1 over 144
multiplying the dy squared term.
Basically the same silly factor that's here.
If you use units in which the
speed of light is equal to one,
it's the same thing as using meters or inches for...
Yeah.
I think I've read somewhere that
particle physicists use units
in which electron volts is everything.
Are they measured in electron volts?
Yes.
Well,
you can.
How does that work?
If it's in a plasma?
You get length and time.
You need the Planck's constant,
which isn't in here yet.
The speed of light relates...
Look,
normally you say there are
three distinct units that you need.
Length,
time,
and mass.
Okay.
Now,
given that the speed of light is equal to one,
or assuming the speed of light is equal to one,
it eliminates one of these.
Setting Planck's constant equal to one
will allow you to write masses
in the same units as you use length and time.
But we're not going there today.
We're not going to quantum mechanics today.
Today,
we're just going to set c equal to one.
So...
And now,
Lorentz transformations
and the special theory of relativity
is simply the theory of transformations
or coordinate systems which preserve this form,
dt squared minus dx squared.
Coordinate transformations,
space-time coordinate transformations,
which preserve the form of the metric.
This metric now represents proper time,
not the...
uh...
not the spatial distance,
necessarily.
It can also represent spatial distance,
but it represents what it represents.
And the Lorentz transformations
are transformations from one set of coordinates
to another set of coordinates
in which,
in both sets of coordinates,
the form of d tau squared
is equal to dt squared minus dx squared.
Now,
I've written it for two dimensions.
What if there are more dimensions of space
as there really are in the real world?
Then it will be d tau squared
is equal to dt squared
minus dx squared
minus dy squared
minus dz squared,
or whatever...
if there are three coordinates of space.
Okay.
So...
That's it.
That's all you have to know about special relativity.
It's the theory of transformations
which preserve a length element
which is a funny thing
with a minus sign in it.
Now,
we're going to assume that everybody knows that,
and we're going to move on.
What we're going to say is,
supposing I introduce curved coordinates into space-time.
Have we ever seen any examples of curved coordinates
in space-time in this quarter so far?
Yeah.
Accelerated coordinates were examples
of curved coordinates in space-time.
Remember,
I gave you...
like,
coordinates which look like this,
and we also talked about coordinates
which were accelerated.
There's an example of the...
of the introduction of curved coordinates
into space-time for a particular purpose
in order to study accelerated coordinate systems.
So,
it's not insane,
not silly,
to introduce curved coordinates into space-time.
And if you do,
what's going to happen to this formula?
What's going to happen to this formula
is the same thing that happens to the formula
for distance between points
when you introduce curved coordinates into space.
Namely,
you're going to get some new coefficient functions,
and the formula is going to look like...
Well,
first of all,
notation.
There are four coordinates of space-time,
t,
x,
y,
and z.
We're going to label them x,
mu.
Whenever you see a Greek index
as a coordinate index,
it always means that you're talking about space-time.
And how many...
what does mu run over?
Mu runs over four possibilities,
one of time and three directions.
Three directions of space.
The usual convention
is not to call it x1 through x4,
but to call it x0...
I don't know how that got started.
Why x0 through x3,
rather than x1 through x4,
I don't know.
With x0 being the time coordinate.
Time versus...
Time first.
Before you start with space,
you got one,
two,
three.
What are you going to do,
add four?
Eh,
why not add zero?
Yeah.
If you decide you want
to make higher dimensional space times,
you add more space components,
you never add more time components.
That's...
I mean,
you can play with that if you like,
but...
Uh...
It's a thing,
though.
Oh,
yeah,
sure.
Anyway.
So,
what's the natural generalization
of this formula
when you introduce new sets of coordinates,
let's call them y mu now,
which also has a time component
and three space components,
and assume that the y coordinates
and the x coordinates are related to each other
by coordinate transformation.
Then what's the natural analog,
or the generalization,
I should say,
of the simple special relativity formula?
That's exactly what you might expect.
d tau squared is equal to g mu nu of...
Now,
when I write just of x,
it means of space and time.
A general function of position in space-time
is just written as a function of x
without specifying whether we're talking about
x zero,
x one,
x two,
x three,
and so forth,
times dx mu dx nu.
We don't need to have real genuine curvature
and gravity and so forth to do this.
We could just do this by introducing
curvy linear coordinates for x and t.
So at the moment,
we haven't introduced
the theory of gravity when we say
we can write this down.
We're just generalizing the allowable coordinates
that we can play with.
So that's the general form
of the proper time element between two points
in space-time,
where space-time has a number,
and space-time has a number.
So we're just going to use a metric tensor.
Now,
what is the metric tensor?
Let's call these simple coordinates like this.
Let's call these...
Should we call them Cartesian?
What's the right term for...
Hmm?
You have a name for them?
Minkowski.
Good,
good.
Minkowski coordinates.
Yeah.
Ordinary Minkowski coordinates.
And Minkowski coordinates are not unique.
Just like Cartesian coordinates are not unique,
you can rotate them,
you can translate them,
you can Lorentz transform Minkowski coordinates.
What's the Minkowski form for the metric tensor?
Well,
it's clear.
It's of the form 1 for the dt squared
and minus 1,
minus 1,
minus 1 for the dx squared.
In other words,
it's a matrix
just like G was a matrix before.
The,
uh,
in flat coordinates,
originally the metric was 1,
1,
whatever.
What is it now?
It's a 1 and 3 minus 1s
with all 0s elsewhere.
All right.
So a special case of a metric,
of a formula like this
would be where G mu nu
was simply 1,
minus 1,
in which case you would reproduce
the usual Minkowski
proper time.
Okay.
This symbol has a name.
It's the analog of delta Mn.
But it's not delta Mn.
It's not 1,
1,
1.
It's 1,
minus 1,
minus 1.
It has a name.
It's called eta.
Eta Mn.
Greek letter eta.
So eta is the metric of space-time
in Minkowski coordinates.
So we could write in Minkowski-type coordinates,
the analog of Cartesian coordinates,
that tau squared is equal to eta mu nu
dx mu dx nu.
Okay.
That's space-time in a nutshell.
Almost everything we said about tensors,
their transformation properties,
is still correct.
of tensors are identical to what they were before.
I'll write them again.
You have things like dx mu
which have a contravariant structure.
They're related to dy mu by partial of
y mu with respect to x nu dx nu.
So this defines the
transformation properties of contravariant indices.
It's exactly the same as it was before.
The transformation properties of tensors are exactly
what they were in the pure space case.
You don't have to change it,
not at all,
for both contravariant and covariant indices.
The only thing is that the metric tensor
typically has minuses as well as pluses in it.
Now,
what kind,
what kind of tensor is this?
What are the special rules about how many
minuses and how many pluses will come to that?
But this,
for example,
is a special case,
three minuses and one plus.
I'll be more precise about what's an allowable tensor,
an allowable metric tensor.
But for now,
the rules are almost exactly the same
with the Kronecker delta being replaced by eta.
What do you do with the transformation of
x and y instead of y and super?
What do you mean by that?
Just a definition of a,
just a notation.
x super zero equals,
is t.
So I mean,
you could,
one transformation could be,
you could just reverse,
let's say,
x and t,
and then you could say the
new x would be the time dimension.
Yeah,
you could do that.
You can do it if you like.
It even happens in some
situations that you might want to.
Now,
there is a rule.
I'll tell you,
I'll tell you what the rule is.
The rule is now,
and we'll go through it another time,
but we need to,
we do need to go through it.
The rule is that g mu nu,
g mu nu is again a symmetric,
is a symmetric tensor.
Symmetric tensors have eigenvalues.
They have a complete set of eigenvalues.
They will always have four eigenvalues.
For an ordinary space,
those eigenvalues are all positive.
And it corresponds to the fact
that spatial distances are always positive.
In relativity,
there is always three negative.
And one positive eigenvalue.
If you're writing something down which has not
the right number of positive and negative eigenvalues,
you have some sort of pathological space.
But we'll come to that.
We'll come to that.
For now,
the rules are really unchanged.
The rules are really unchanged,
apart from the fact that a typical metric
will have some minus signs and some plus signs.
And in terms of eigenvalues,
there are always three.
Three negative ones and one positive one.
Which means,
yeah?
It is its own inverse,
yeah.
Just like the Kronecker delta is.
Right.
So,
the eta with the upper indices is the
same as the eta with the lower indices.
Right.
Uh,
I'll go through this,
I will go through this again.
But I just wanted to,
since I was asked the question about,
how to think about the geometry of an expanding space-time,
let me answer it right now.
We have everything we need now to write,
to express it.
In a general space-time,
these metric components are functions
of all of the coordinates.
A particularly simple kind of
space-time is one where the coordinates,
where the metric only depends on time,
and doesn't depend on space.
That's the sort of situation
you have when space is homogeneous.
If space is homogeneous,
everywhere the same,
that's a typical cosmological setup,
where space is everywhere is the same,
apart,
of course,
when I say it's everywhere is the same,
I mean on very large scales,
on scales much bigger than galaxies and so forth.
Space is the same one place as another.
The metric doesn't depend on space,
but it does depend on time,
and that time dependence is the expansion of the universe.
So let me write down for you a particular metric,
and then just look at it a little bit.
It corresponds to G mu nu is equal,
instead of,
instead of 1,
minus 1,
let's write 1,
0,
0.
now instead of minus 1,
let's write minus A of t,
where A of t is time dependent.
0,
minus A of t,
minus A of t.
One function A of t,
just one function,
and that function is called the scale factor.
What this means is that the proper time or the line
interval is the t squared minus A of t squared dx squared.
dx squared plus dy squared plus dz squared.
It may not be obvious to you,
but this space-time with a time dependence,
here,
is very different than flat space-time.
To show you the kind of difference,
supposing we did something similar with space.
Incidentally,
this is the characteristic metric.
If A of t is an expanding function of time,
if it's an increasing function of time,
then that's called an expanding universe.
I'll come back to this,
but let me just show you qualitatively what this means
by giving you the analog for ordinary space.
Let's just think about two dimensions of space,
and let me imagine one of
the directions is an angular direction.
We've already done things like that.
We considered dr squared plus r squared d theta squared.
dr squared plus r squared d theta squared.
That's somewhat similar to this.
The r squared is like dt squared,
and r squared itself is like A squared.
It's a function of t.
A is a function of t.
Here,
r is a function of r,
or r squared is a function of r.
So there's a similarity between this formula here,
dt squared minus A of t squared dx squared,
and the r squared plus r squared d theta squared.
Now what is this space here?
It's a plane.
It's just polar coordinates.
It's flat spacetime,
and it's just looking at
that spacetime and polar coordinates.
But now,
supposing instead of just r squared,
I put some general function of r in.
First,
before putting a general function in,
let's put in another specific function,
sine of r squared.
What is this space now?
Square.
That's a sphere.
And the way to think about it
now is that the distance around the,
well,
the distance around the theta axis
depends on r in a characteristic way.
Here's the sphere.
Let's think of r as,
r is now like the polar angle.
And as you go around the sphere,
or as you go around the theta direction,
theta I'm having go this way now.
I think I've turned the sphere
on its side for some odd reason.
Why did I do that?
It was stupid.
Let's put it,
let's stand it up again.
Theta goes around this way.
And r is just replacing what I called phi before.
Right?
What's happening is instead of sine
of r just increasing like r,
it increases and then it decreases.
Sine is a function which increases and then decreases.
Right?
It increases from zero to
pi over two and then decreases.
That's why the sphere increases and then decreases.
Right?
It starts growing as you
move away from the south pole.
It starts growing but then shrinks again.
That sphere,
of course,
is not a flat spacetime.
If I only had r squared here,
it would be like looking at just a plane.
With sine squared here,
it's more complicated and it's curved.
Okay?
Supposing I put an arbitrary function,
some kind of function which,
um,
I don't know,
let's put an exponential function here,
e to the two r.
What kind of space would that look like?
It would look like a horn.
Yeah.
It would look like a,
by a horn I mean,
you know,
toot toot.
The distance around the theta axis would grow exponentially.
And it would look like that.
Now it's not growing exponentially.
It's not growing with time.
It's growing with r.
So this would be some kind of space which had
the property that as you move away from r equals zero,
r equals zero is over here,
it grows.
It grows rapidly.
It grows exponentially.
Supposing I put in,
I don't know,
you could put in all kinds of things.
Uh,
I don't know,
e to the two r times,
uh,
times,
oh,
I don't know.
Some arbitrary function which grows
and at the same time oscillates.
It grows and oscillates at the same time.
Well,
you could make very complicated kinds
of spaces which look like that.
They're just surfaces,
but the character of the surface and the way that
it grows as you move away from r equals zero
depends on the space.
So what is function f of r?
Most of these spaces are not flat.
They have curvature of all kinds
that we'll talk about next time.
But that's exactly what this a of t does here.
It creates a space-time which as a function of time,
the space-time grows.
Grows,
shrinks,
does whatever it does.
It can do all kinds of wiggles.
And instead of r,
this would be t.
So this is the metric of a time-dependent space.
It's a space-time.
And if a is a growing function,
then it's an expanding space-time.
That's all it means to say
that space-time is expanding in this language,
in this language of a metric tensor.
Uh,
we'll come back to it.
Next time we'll talk about curvature and parallel transport.
And,
uh,
try to get to the Einstein equations.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.