This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
All right,
let's,
we want to,
we want to move on to a slippery and
somewhat abstract and frankly
a little bit difficult subject.
The notion,
well,
first of all,
the subject is tensor calculus.
We've done about everything that you
can do with tensor algebra and
tensor arithmetic,
adding,
subtracting.
We haven't talked about adding and subtracting tensors,
but
you can add and subtract tensors.
Just make sure the things
that you're adding have matching indices.
Don't try to add something
like Vn to W sub m.
That will not work.
That will not be a good operation.
If you want to add V and W,
add contravariant components or
covariant components.
Don't try to add a tensor with
two indices to a tensor with three indices.
That won't make sense.
What we have at the end,
a scramble of garbage.
But as long as you're adding things which are compatible,
that they have their indices in the same place,
same type of indices,
then tensors add.
That simply means that the sums
and differences of tensors are again tensors,
meaning to say that they transform
the same way as the originals.
Now,
why do we introduce,
first of all,
why do we introduce tensors?
Let's go back a step
and talk about why they're important.
Are there any differences of color
between a point of the emperor's sinkасс
and a point of the meanderer's sinkass?
Let's start with barbering out
a point that glacier exists in,
and what we can draw from
a point of view of that state
properties of the earth
without actually introducing coordinates,
most likely we
could express all of physics without coordinates,
without introducing
coordinates,
but it would be difficult when
we actually come to compute things.
It's very convenient to be able
to discuss the components of vectors,
tensors,
and so forth.
After all,
I mean,
computation is about numbers,
not
abstract symbols,
and when you come to actually compute,
to throw it onto a
computer or something,
you want to put in numerical values for things,
and the
components of vectors and tensors and so
forth are the way that you describe them
in practice.
Now,
tensors have the very important property—oh,
wow,
all right,
let's start.
The relationships that we're actually interested in are
relationships which,
in a sense,
are independent of the coordinates,
that's the way I see it.
The relationships that we're interested in are the
ones that don't depend on your choice of coordinates.
The fact that the earth is a
sphere doesn't depend on what coordinates you use.
The fact that its curvature is everywhere is the same,
well,
of course,
it's not quite true.
So let's say,
well,
it's true.
The fact that the earth is almost a sphere,
which is slightly flattened,
you don't need coordinates to express that.
The fact that Mount Everest is a
lump on the surface of the earth,
again,
you don't need coordinates to describe that.
Those things are things which are coordinate independent.
But what we want to do
is express those same kinds of facts,
geometric facts,
in terms of coordinates.
That means we want to write equations which perhaps the numerical
left side and the numerical right side do depend on the coordinates,
but the fact that the left side equals
the right side should not depend on coordinates.
So it's important to isolate
quantities that have the following property,
that if their components are equal,
if there's a rule or if there's a fact,
that the components of one tensor,
for example,
or one object,
and this object happens to have indices,
may or may not be a tensor,
may or may not transform the right way,
it has some indices,
in other words,
there are whatever number of such objects there are,
you lay them out in a matrix if you like,
if we know that in one coordinate system,
let's say the x coordinate system,
if we know that two matrices or two,
sorry,
two tensors,
are equal in the x coordinate system,
then it must follow,
or looking for definitions,
so that the equality in one coordinate system
will imply the equality in all other coordinate systems.
In that sense,
if we can write our equations and
our laws of physics in terms of objects,
which,
if they are equal in one coordinate system,
then they are necessarily equal in all coordinate systems,
then effectively we've expressed the laws in
a way which don't depend on the coordinates.
They don't depend on the coordinates,
maybe perhaps the numerical value of the
left hand side and the right hand side
depend on the coordinates,
but the fact that they're equal doesn't.
Alright,
we can write that another way,
we can always take any such equation,
subtract this and write that it's equal to zero.
It's an interesting fact,
the equality sign is completely unnecessary in mathematics.
You could make it a rule,
put everything over on one side,
and whenever you see an expression,
assume that it's zero,
and then you never need the zero sign,
you never need the equality.
This is zero,
because that's our definition,
but we don't do that.
We allow ourselves to use equals at zero.
And so the same statement is,
the same statement that I just made,
is that we would like to express
our equations of physics in a form,
something is equal to zero,
and if that something is equal
to zero in one coordinate system,
then it's zero in every coordinate system.
We would like to find objects which have that property.
Those objects are tensors.
How do I know that?
Well,
let's just remind ourselves how tensors transform.
A tensor,
for example,
a vector,
let's just take the simplest case,
vn of y,
in other words,
the components of a vector in the y coordinate system,
are equal to the components of y,
sorry,
of v,
the same vector in the x coordinate system,
we can put an r here,
and then there is a,
let's see,
which way does it go?
n is downstairs,
so there's a dyn dxr.
Whoops,
put the,
nr.
Alright,
so now it's quite easy.
If all of the components,
not just one of the components,
but if all of the components
of vx are equal to zero,
then all of the components
of vy are equal to zero,
obviously,
just from this equation here.
If all of the components
of v are equal to zero,
in other words,
if v is a vector which is equal to zero,
then its components are zero,
either in the y coordinates or the x coordinates.
So with transformation properties like this,
or more complicated ones involving several inputs,
we can put some indices,
for example,
if we have some tensor,
let's put one index upstairs,
another index downstairs,
in the y coordinates,
that would be equal to
dym by dxr,
dxs by dyn,
times trs.
Alright,
again,
if all of,
in the x coordinates,
if all of the components of
t are zero in the x coordinates,
then all of them are zero in the y coordinates.
That's the importance of tensors,
that if you have an equation which
is true in one set of coordinates,
and you know that the objects are tensors,
you don't have to check them in other coordinate systems.
Now we're going to discover
that not everything is a tensor.
In particular,
ordinary derivatives of tensors are not tensors.
Not everything that you can write down is a tensor.
But still,
we want to define some sort of notion
of the way a tensor varies from place to place.
It's going to be important to have an
idea of how things vary from place to place,
so we have to have some concept of
the notion of a derivative of a tensor.
Let's go through why it's problematic.
Okay?
Let's start with scalars.
Incidentally,
the transformation property of a scalar is trivial.
If the scalar is phi,
we call it the typical scalar phi,
if its value at a certain point
in space is phi in the x coordinates,
then it's also phi in the y coordinates.
If the points x and y correspond
to the same actual material point here,
on the blackboard,
just different coordinate representations of the same point.
So phi transforms in a trivial way.
It doesn't transform at all.
Obviously,
if you know that phi is
equal to zero in one reference frame,
you know that it's zero in all reference frames,
simply because it's the same in all reference frames.
Now let's come to the derivative of phi.
With respect to x.
The derivative of phi with respect to xm,
let's say.
That is in fact a vector.
It's a vector with a covariant index here.
But let's just see,
why is it true,
mathematically it's straightforward,
the fact that if d phi
by dx is equal to zero,
then d phi by dx is equal to zero,
mathematically it's just that d phi by dy,
let's call it yn,
is equal to dxm by d yn,
times phi,
times the derivative of phi with respect to xm.
So if phi is constant,
and has no derivatives with respect to x,
clearly its derivatives with respect to y are also zero.
But let's just think about it
from an intuitive point of view.
To say that phi has no derivatives,
in particular,
let's imagine it has no derivatives anywheres,
what does that mean?
That means it's constant,
and it doesn't vary from place to place.
It's a scalar,
you could go and measure
it in every point in space,
and it's constant.
Like the temperature being the
same everywhere in the room here.
If a thing is constant,
it's going to be constant
no matter what the coordinates are.
I don't care whether I use polar coordinates,
I use elliptical,
hyperbolic,
Shmulevitz coordinates,
it doesn't matter.
Whatever coordinates I use,
if the temperature is constant in this room,
it's going to be constant in every set of coordinates.
So,
it stands to reason that if the
derivative of phi is equal to zero,
everywheres in space,
with respect to x,
then it's also going to
be zero with respect to y.
So,
a perfectly good description of the
air in this room in thermal equilibrium
is that the temperature with respect,
the derivative of the temperature with respect
to the x coordinates is equal to zero,
and you don't have to ask,
will it also be zero in the y coordinates,
for the reasons I've just explained.
Now let's come to vectors.
We're going to see that the problem is more complicated.
Let's begin with a vector,
which is constant on the blackboard in space.
Flat space,
good old Cartesian coordinates.
Let's not get fancy with curved space or anything,
just ordinary flat space.
Could be two dimensional,
could be three dimensional,
but let's take the blackboard,
which is two dimensional.
Let's put some Cartesian coordinates,
and let's also imagine a vector field,
which is constant in space.
Now what that means is it
points in the same direction everywheres,
and it has the same length everywheres.
Just the obvious meaning of saying a vector is constant.
So every place in space,
that vector is exactly the same.
Now,
what can you say about the components of this vector
as you move from point to point?
In the same coordinates,
in these same coordinates,
x1 and x2.
For example,
let's take the covariant components.
Covariant components being the projections onto the axes.
It's pretty obvious that the components are also constant.
So to say that a vector is constant,
it looks like what it says
is that the components of the vector,
what did I say,
a covariant vector or a contra,
let's say a contravariant,
covariant components.
And vary it in any direction.
If the vector is constant,
it looks like it says that the components are constant.
But now,
let's come and introduce some curved coordinates into space.
Same physical fact,
the vector points in the same direction everywheres,
but now let's,
let me redraw it,
I think I'll redraw it with some curvy linear coordinates,
exactly the same situation.
So the situation now is,
we have some curvy linear coordinates,
and we have a constant vector,
that means physically the vector
points in the same direction everywheres.
What about the covariant components of the vector
as I move from place to place?
You think they're constant?
Remember what the covariant components are.
They're the projection onto the axes,
but the axes are bending and moving around on you.
In one place,
the axes might look like that,
someplace else they might look like this.
The same vector will have the same vector,
and the same vector will have the same vector,
this might be your x1 component,
this might be your x2 component,
now this might be your x1 component,
and this might be your x2 component,
pointing in entirely different directions,
the same vector,
exactly the same vector,
pointing in exactly the same direction,
I don't think I made that look the same direction,
did I?
The components will be different,
the lesson is that just
because a vector is physically constant
from point to point in space,
it does not mean that
its components are constant in space.
Why not?
The components of a vector depend on two things,
they depend on the direction and magnitude of the vector,
and also the orientation of the axes.
Even if the vector doesn't change
when you move from place to place,
the axes do.
So,
yeah?
To say the vector is pointing in the same direction,
and has the same magnitude,
implies a third coordinate system that is transposable,
it applies to both of them,
right?
I don't know what that means.
Two coordinate systems,
in this particular case,
one of them is good
old Cartesian coordinates on the blackboard,
and we imagine,
you know,
there's just good old intuitive Cartesian coordinates,
and the vector is constant,
which means in Cartesian coordinates,
it means the components are constant.
The same situation when we lay some curvy linear coordinates
on the blackboard,
or incidentally,
we could change from one
Cartesian coordinate system to another.
We could rotate or translate the Cartesian components,
as long as the coordinates are Cartesian,
then the components of the
vector will be the same everywhere.
But now we lay on top
of it a curved coordinate system,
where the direction and spacing,
for example,
between the coordinates varies from place to place,
and now the components will not be constant.
As I said,
it's because the components depend both on the vector
and the orientation of the coordinates.
If the coordinates are flopping around as you move around,
the components will also be.
So,
dv by dx equals zero
does not imply,
does not imply
that dv
in the x coordinate system,
the coordinate,
the components in the x coordinate system,
relative to the x axes,
them being constant,
which is the same as saying the derivatives are zero,
does not say that
dv m in the y coordinates,
this means the components,
not only are they functions of y,
but they're the components in the y,
along the y axes,
it does not say
that these are zero.
No such implication.
What does that tell us?
That tells us
that the derivatives of v
with respect to x,
or with respect to y,
don't transform as a tensor.
If they did,
then if they were zero in one frame,
it would imply they were zero in the other frame.
Frame means a set of coordinates here.
So derivatives of tensors,
derivatives of scalars
are perfectly good vectors,
but derivatives of vectors,
meaning to say,
the derivative of the components,
they don't transform
as the components of tensors.
That's a general rule,
and you have to do something,
you have to do something a little trickier,
and a little more complicated,
to define derivatives of tensors.
To make them tensors.
The process is called covariant differentiation.
Now the covariant is not because
it has to do with a lower index here,
it's another completely different use
of the term covariant.
What it means,
what it implies,
is it's a form of differentiation,
which you can apply to tensors,
which gives you back tensors.
In particular,
you can apply it to vectors
and get back vectors.
So let's see if we can figure out
what kind of thing
the covariant derivative might be.
Let's start with a thing
which is not actually a tensor,
but let's check whether it's a tensor or not.
In other words,
let's sort of assume it's a tensor
and then prove that it's not.
Alright,
exactly this object.
Let's write Tmn.
In fact,
I'll tell you what,
this is intended to be a tensor,
but this is intended to be a tensor
in the x coordinate frame.
Supposing there exists some tensor
whose x components,
components in the x coordinates,
and x coordinates I now mean,
again,
rectangular Cartesian coordinates.
Let's suppose that there is some tensor,
Tmn of x,
which is equal to the derivative
of some vector
with respect to x
in the x coordinate system.
Then the question is,
what must it be
in the y coordinate system?
And in particular,
when you transform it as a tensor,
does it or does it not become
the derivative,
this is in the x coordinate,
does it or does it not become
the,
let's call it,
um,
well,
derivative of v with,
of y with respect to yn.
Question.
And the answer,
as you might guess,
is the answer is no.
The,
if I try to transform this object,
pretending it was a tensor,
I will not get the set of components
that look like that.
So let's go through it.
It,
uh,
it's worth our while to do it.
I could just tell you what the answer is,
but let's not do it.
Let's do it,
uh,
with some care.
Okay.
We have an object which
I tell you is a tensor,
and it happens that in the x coordinate system,
its components are the derivative of x,
of v with respect to xn.
It happens.
Let's ask,
what must its components be
in the y coordinate system?
Well,
if it really is a tensor,
then its components must be
dxr by dym.
This is under the assumption that
it really does transform as a tensor.
In the y coordinates,
it must be,
that's the assumption,
that tmn is a tensor.
And if you know it in the x coordinates,
then you can write it
down immediately in the y coordinates.
But now we can substitute what
it is in the x coordinates here,
and that would just give us
the derivative of xr with respect to ym,
derivative of xs with respect to yn,
and now I'm just going to plug in
the assumed value of tmn of x,
and that's dvm of x
with respect to,
oh,
I want trs,
excuse me,
so that's dvr by dxs.
And my question is,
is this,
or is this not equal to,
question mark,
is this or is this not equal to
the derivative
of
dvm,
I think,
let's see,
dvm of y
with respect to yn.
The symbol equals with a question mark
doesn't mean it's equals,
it means,
is it equal?
Not it is equal,
but is it equal?
Is this true?
This is how we might have thought,
just like derivatives of scalars transform as vectors,
we might have thought the
derivatives of components of vectors
transform as tensors.
So we're checking out,
is this object over here equal to this?
Okay,
so let's see if we can work it out.
Not,
it's not terribly hard.
Okay,
let's see.
What can we do with this?
dvr of x by dxs times dxs by dyn,
does that ring a bell?
Focus on this piece right over here.
That's chain rule.
Yeah,
that's the chain rule.
So what's in the red box there,
let's put what's in the red box over here,
it's first of all,
well not just what's in the red box,
but the whole thing,
it's dxr
by dym,
and now if I use a chain rule,
I simplify this,
and I just find it's the derivative of vr
of x,
but not with respect to x,
but with respect to y,
with respect to yn.
And we're asking,
is this the same as this?
No,
no,
no.
Is that what I'm asking?
I guess that's what I'm asking.
dvm by dyn,
yes.
Okay.
Ah,
yes.
Now notice on the right side,
we're checking is this equal to this?
Over here,
I have something involving y,
vy.
Over here,
I have something involving vx.
So let's change everything on the right hand side,
so that it's related to components with respect to x.
That's easy to do.
We just write that vm of y,
this is derivative with respect to yn,
and now,
how do I write vm of y
in terms of x components?
Well,
I just write that vmy,
is the derivative of xr
with respect to ym of vr of x.
All I've done here was use the transformation
from y components to x components
to rewrite what's over here,
over here.
Just pure substitution.
So now we have the question,
is this equal to or is it not?
Let's write it out again.
Derivative with respect to yn.
I realize that this is
a bit tedious and a nuisance,
but I wanted to do it,
the whole thing.
What is it?
dxr,
dxr by what?
Can somebody read it to me?
dy sub m.
And then?
In vm of x,
right?
vr of x?
The r of x.
Okay,
well,
let's look at it.
We have here the derivative of a product.
The derivative of a product
is the sum of two terms.
Just the usual rule for the derivative of a product.
Derivative of a times b is
a times the derivative of b
plus b times the derivative of b.
And so first of all,
this derivative can hit v.
That will give me a
term which looks exactly like this.
It'll give me the term dxr by dym
times dvr of x with respect to yn.
That's exactly what I have here.
Looks good.
But it's not good because
it's only one of the terms
when I take the derivative here.
There's another term.
What's that?
I did.
I did?
No,
I didn't.
Where?
The derivative of this is equal to this.
Sorry,
what did I do?
these are not the same.
Here.
Here the derivative is outside the product.
Here the derivative only acts on the v.
Look at the difference.
Here we have derivative with
respect to y of a product.
Here we have a product of two derivatives.
Not the same thing.
Who asked the question?
I did.
Yeah,
are you happy?
Yes.
Okay.
Good.
All right,
so now we work this out.
The first term is gotten by allowing the
derivative with respect to y to hit v.
That does look exactly like this.
So far so good.
But there's something else in there.
And let's see what that other thing is.
It's derivative with respect to yn
of the derivative of xr
with respect to ym.
That's a thing.
Times vr.
So the answer is it is not equal
to the right hand side.
Let's just call it the right hand side.
In other words,
this thing which I called a tensor
has not transformed as a tensor.
If I insist that this is
the x components of the tensor,
then it is not true that
the y components of the tensor
are just derivatives of v with respect to y.
Not true.
Okay.
Let's see what we can say.
Yeah.
At this point,
can you give a clinical example of an electric field?
Just an electric field which varies from place to place,
but not in Cartesian coordinates,
in some other coordinates.
And this is what happens.
What happens is,
just because the components of a vector may be constant,
doesn't mean it's constant in all frames of reference.
This extra term gets picked up here.
This is the term that's due to the fact
that the coordinates are varying from place to place.
Okay.
After all,
all the directions of the coordinates
are varying from place to place.
If we had,
if the x coordinates were linear functions
of the y coordinates,
then these derivatives here would just be numbers.
And derivatives of numbers are zero.
It's because the coordinates are curved
that this is not zero in general.
And as I said,
it has to do with the fact
that the relationship between the coordinates
is varying from place to place.
That's the way to think about it.
The xr by dym,
that's the relationship between the x coordinates
and the y coordinates.
And now,
if it varies from place to place,
then there's an extra term.
And the extra term is proportional to v
with no derivative.
Alright?
So,
uh,
yeah.
Yeah,
exactly like the picture right above.
Except the red vectors could also be varying
from place to place.
And we see that there's an extra contribution.
Look at the form of this.
Let me write this in some,
um,
let's see.
Let's see.
What was the,
the left hand side,
that's I guess this over here,
that's what you would get if v,
if t really did transform as a tensor.
Alright?
So if t really does transform as a tensor,
this has to be the right answer.
It differs from,
this over here.
It differs from what you might have expected,
namely,
uh,
this over here,
by this extra term.
That suggests that we have to
do something a little bit different
to differentiate a tensor
and to get another tensor.
Okay.
And the difference
involves an extra term
which has not got derivatives of the vectors in it,
but's got,
but has funny derivatives
associated with the relation between coordinates.
Um,
let's see.
The right hand side is by definition
tmn of y.
I just read it off here.
Assuming this is tmn of x,
then this must be tmn of y
because it transforms in the right way.
I forced it to transform in the right way.
And what we see
is that,
um,
it,
uh,
well,
that it has this extra term over here.
It's not just,
where is it?
It's not just what you might have
thought it was.
Okay.
Let's try to guess then
what the right way
to differentiate tensors is.
The right way must have an extra term
that'll cancel this out.
Let's just write this in another form.
Uh,
let me call this object over here.
Let me give it a name.
Capital gamma.
How many indices does it have?
It has an index n,
m,
and r.
One index upstairs,
two indices downstairs.
And it multiplies vr.
Okay.
Let's,
that's what we'll call this.
Here's more or less what we discovered,
in another way of saying it,
that if we want to differentiate
a tensor,
its components,
we have to do,
and get another tensor back,
we have to do something a little bit trickier
than just differentiate its components.
Namely,
what we have to do
is take the derivative
of v
with respect to y,
or x,
doesn't matter,
x,
the,
um,
let's call it,
the,
m,
n,
and then add something to it.
And the thing we have to add to it
is just this gamma,
n,
let's say,
uh,
m,
r,
vr.
What this represents,
what this term over here represents,
is the fact that,
when you differentiate a tensor,
you have to take into account
the fact that the coordinates
are varying from point to point.
And so the components have some variation
that's just due to the fact
that the coordinates themselves
are flopping around,
so to speak.
There's something here
that has to go there.
I haven't told you yet,
well,
I've told you in this language over here
what this gamma is,
but let's suppose
that,
now we're making a guess,
we're making a guess
that if we could find the right object gamma,
we could construct a new kind of derivative,
a new kind of derivative of a vector,
which contains an extra term,
not just a derivative,
but an extra term,
which will make this into a tensor,
which will make it into a tensor,
which we can call,
t,
m,
n.
This process of differentiating
is called covariant derivative.
It's usually written
as an upside down triangle
with an n downstairs.
That means covariant derivative
with respect to xn
of vm.
And it's by definition
equal to this thing over here,
if we can figure out what gamma is.
If we can figure out
what gamma is,
another way to ask it
is can we find a thing called gamma,
and I'll tell you what gamma's going to depend on.
It's going to depend on the metric tensor.
It's going to depend
not only on the metric tensor,
but the derivatives of the metric tensor.
If the metric tensor has derivatives,
that means in some way
the coordinates are flopping around.
If the metric tensor is not constant,
it means the coordinates are flopping around.
We're going to discover that this thing
depends on
the derivatives of the metric.
Is there an object
which has the property
that when we construct
the covariant derivative,
what occurs is actually a tensor,
really is a tensor
and transforms as a tensor.
That'll be a brilliant achievement
because then we'll be able to write equations
such as the covariant derivative
of a vector might be equal
to some other tensor,
maybe a completely different object.
The left-hand side could be the derivative
of some electric field.
The right-hand side could be some other tensor
of a particular physical character,
and we might have a situation,
an equation,
which says that the covariant derivative
of the electric field
is equal to some tensor.
Will it be true in all reference frames?
Yes,
if the left-hand side is a tensor
and transforms as a tensor,
and also the right-hand side.
So the question is,
can we find this gamma,
and that,
whose nature it is
to make derivatives equal to the tensors.
Well,
you wrote a gamma there.
Yeah,
yeah,
that's one gamma,
but remember this was a special case
where the x's were Cartesian coordinates.
Now it can happen that we have a geometry
that cannot be described
in terms of Cartesian coordinates.
But still,
we'll discover that we can find a gamma
which has the right property.
Alright?
So the main purpose of this
was just to show you
that derivatives of tensors
are not themselves tensors.
You have to do something else.
I'll give you the general rule.
I'll tell you what the general rule is,
in particular for tensors with lower...
I'll give you the general rule right now.
For things with lower components,
for things with lower components,
it's...
this is...
yeah.
Because the coordinates vary
from place to place,
there are contributions
of this type
for each one of the components.
I'll show you how it works,
and then we'll see if we can find out
any piece of information
about what this gamma is.
At some point,
I'm going to leave for you
to work out.
But I'll show you what the rules are,
and then you can go home
and check yourself
that I have the right object.
Okay,
so...
Let's...
Here was the way you write
a covariant derivative of a vector.
What would happen if I wanted to make
a covariant derivative of a tensor?
Oh,
incidentally,
what's the covariant derivative of a scalar?
That's easy.
It's just the ordinary
derivative.
Ordinary derivative is a tensor.
Okay?
But for a tensor,
we have to do a more complicated operation.
Let's take some tensor,
not necessarily this tensor over here,
any tensor,
with two indices,
for example,
Tm in,
and supposing we want to
find its covariant derivative,
again,
with respect to
with respect to y,
covariant derivative,
let's give it,
let's...
I'll tell you what.
I want to change notation here
a little bit.
I want to call this p.
If I call that p,
I have to call this p.
So let's see.
I have Tm in,
and I want to take
its covariant derivative
with respect to p,
with respect to yp.
What does it have in it?
Again,
it starts out
with the ordinary derivative.
Derivative of Tm in
with respect to yp.
It starts out with just the ordinary derivative.
That's all that would be there in Cartesian coordinates.
But now,
because the coordinates may be varying
from place to place,
and remember,
we have two components here,
each component
can...
each index here
is like a vector index.
And here's the rule.
Just make a blind eye
to n.
Let's make a blind eye by
circling it in red.
Oh.
I wanted a p over here.
Let's see.
I don't want p.
Thank you.
Yeah.
P over here?
Yeah,
and also over here.
Right.
Okay.
So,
we're doing a similar thing now
to Tmn.
First of all,
let's turn a blind eye completely
to n.
Whoops.
Really blind.
Okay.
And we'll do that by circling it
and ignoring it
on both sides of the equation.
If there was no n here,
this would just be a vector.
Let's write down what we would do
to write the covariant derivative
of T.
The answer would be
derivative,
sorry,
derivative of
Tm with respect to yp
is equal to
I'm going to just never say n.
Derivative of
Tm with respect to yp
plus
gamma m
gamma pm
times
七
r in.
Look what I've done.
I've done exactly what I did over here,
except with an extra index here,
just riding along,
just traveling along for the ride,
doing nothing.
But that's not the whole story.
The rest of the story is
to add another term in which you
turn a blind eye to the index m.
So now let's be blind to m,
ignore it,
and write another term,
which will be gamma pn.
Now the index of interest is n,
again r,
and tmr.
Let's see,
this time we,
which one did we,
yeah,
that was okay,
that stays like that.
You turned the blind eye to m now.
Now we turn the blind eye to m.
So m just went along for the
ride over here in the second term.
For each index,
let's concentrate on covariant
indices.
For each index,
let's concentrate on covariant indices.
So we have a term
called the index and a tensor.
No matter how many of them are,
there are,
when you covariantly differentiate it,
you get another term with
a gamma times the tensor itself.
And then other terms,
the terms are simply one by one,
you go through the various indices,
turning a blind eye to all the other indices.
That's the rule.
Yeah,
once that 따라 asta bATA always
does it'saza sempre jvRA Iya anyways,
wants to ask us.
cNhEwwN keen lamn.
Yeah.
In other words,
let's just erase n over here from it.
First of all,
let's get rid of this.
I don't want to erase it because I
don't want to have to write it again,
but just forget it.
And let's erase n.
Then this would just be
exactly the way a vector transformed.
But let's put back the blind index now,
n.
Now let's turn our blind eye to the other index.
Which one is the other one now?
I lost track.
In the second term,
the blind eye is turned to the m index.
So let's erase it on both sides.
And notice,
again,
this is transforming exactly the same
way that a vector would transform with an index n.
You put them together,
and you have the full transformation
property,
or not the full transformation,
the full covariant derivative of a tensor.
If there were more indices,
you would simply
have more terms exactly the same form
of the term,
gammas times t's.
But index by index,
you would pretend it was a vector
and transform it or do the same thing.
That's the covariant derivative.
The t is always the first term.
The derivative of t occurs in the first term.
Yeah.
And it's always the first lower subscript in the gamma.
And the rest in the other.
Yeah.
That's right.
So in particular,
here's an interesting fact.
You could have a tensor with completely constant components
from point to point.
Then there would be no derivatives,
but still the covariant derivative of a tensor
would be not 0.
Somehow,
this tensor has a covariant derivative,
whatever that means.
I'm going to show you an example in a moment.
Even though the components of the tensor
are absolutely constant.
Now,
let me give you an example of such a situation.
Is g and n equal to Tnm?
T,
no.
Not in general.
So the n's went back into the wrong place.
Did I get them in the wrong place?
You are right.
I did get them in the wrong place.
Tmr,
I think,
right?
Nmn.
Let's see.
n is on the right side here.
And m is on the left side.
m should be on the left side here.
So that should be like that.
Right.
In the first term,
it should be nn.
Here?
Yes,
you're right.
Good.
Thank you.
But the basic rule is the
same as the rule for vectors,
except you go through it one by one.
And then you run curves over them.
And we eat out of получается in solidarity matters.
Got it.
So it's all right to do.
Now,
I also took this colleague from El favour差's
And I told him there's going to be
some sort of a capture of this kind of training.
And then you get into therapeutics.
And?幂
werd wait.
Yeah?
I assume that you can swap
an index with a repeated index.
Yeah.
In the middle term there,
you could have also written T
sub nR if you wanted to.
No,
you can't put an R here.
no.
Here.
T sub nR would have been okay.
nR.
It is nR.
You want R?
No,
no,
no.
Not okay,
not okay,
not okay.
You can't interchange in general.
No,
no,
that's a repeated index.
n is not a repeated index.
Well,
that means you can change
it to S if you like,
but you can't interchange it with n.
You can give it a different name.
That's fine.
Okay.
But you can't substitute one index for another.
Unless it happens to be
a symmetric tensor of some sort,
in which case T is the same.
T is the same as T .
Okay.
Let me give you an example of a
tensor or a vector which is clearly not constant,
even though the derivatives of its components are zero.
Go to polar coordinates.
In polar coordinates,
here's our polar coordinates.
And let's consider a vector with the following property.
Yeah.
Ignore the origin.
The origin,
as I said,
is a nasty point,
so we'll forget the origin.
It's not important.
But this vector has zero for its theta component.
What would a theta component mean?
A theta component of a vector,
the radial component of a vector,
means the component along the radial axis.
The theta component of a vector
means a component along the tangential direction.
All right.
So now I have a vector where the theta component,
let's call it V theta,
is identically equal to zero.
All right.
But the radial component,
let's say,
is equal to one.
What does that vector look like?
It has a radial.
It has no theta component anywheres.
Anywheres.
Everywhere is on the plane.
Its radial component is the same,
equal to one.
But it points outward from the origin.
That's a vector which has radial component equal
to one and theta component equal to zero.
Quite obviously,
the components are constant.
The components are constant,
one and zero.
But nobody would look at that and
say that the vector field is constant.
It's varying from place to place.
Obviously,
the vector over here is
different than it is over here.
So here's an example of a vector field whose
components are constant in a particular set of coordinates.
Their components would not
be constant in Cartesian coordinates.
In Cartesian coordinates,
here's a vector.
Here it has an x component.
Here it doesn't have an x component.
But in polar coordinates,
the components are completely constant,
and yet the vector is not constant.
All right.
What would happen if we calculated
the covariant derivative of this vector?
We would find that it's not zero.
And so it's the covariant derivative which picks up the
real geometric fact that the vector varies from place to place.
Now,
I haven't told you what gamma is.
Gamma is an object which can be
constructed from the components of the metric tensor.
So let's see if we can make a little
bit of progress in finding out what gamma is.
Okay.
What about the covariant derivative
of the metric tensor itself?
Let's go to Cartesian coordinates first.
In Cartesian coordinates,
the metric tensor is what?
What is the metric tensor in Cartesian coordinates?
It's just delta mn.
It really is constant from place to place.
In Cartesian coordinates,
it's absolutely constant.
And incidentally,
you can do this.
If an object is constant in Cartesian coordinates
where the coordinates don't flop around and change direction,
if an object is constant in
Cartesian coordinates from place to place,
then it's really constant.
You pointed out before that you could
have a non-flat space with Cartesian coordinates.
No,
no.
Cartesian coordinates means coordinates in which
the metric tensor is delta mn.
It's not just that you've drawn,
it's not just that they've laid out coordinates like this.
It means that the metric
tensor is equal to delta mn.
That's what I mean.
It means the space is flat,
and it means that the...
Do you mean linear or Cartesian?
I mean,
when I speak about Cartesian coordinates,
I'm now speaking about the flat blackboard.
I'm speaking about a flat
space with rectangular Cartesian coordinates.
That's what I mean.
So the metric tensor...
If I took some other space,
for example,
I take the surface of a sphere and I
lay it out on a plane by Mercator projection,
then you draw the Mercator projection and
it looks like it has Cartesian coordinates,
but the metric tensor is
not constant from place to place.
That's why Greenland looks bigger than South America,
because the metric is not uniform from place to place.
Okay.
What I mean by Cartesian coordinates,
I mean Cartesian coordinates in flat space,
the metric is just delta mn.
This is clearly constant,
and if the space is identical at all places,
the coordinates don't flop around.
Not only is the derivative of
the metric tensor equal to zero,
it makes good sense to say that...
to expect that the real physics...
the covariant derivative of the metric tensor is also zero.
What would it be if not zero,
if everything is exactly the same from point to point?
And the space is completely flat.
So it's natural to expect that
the covariant derivative of the metric tensor,
let's write a dr of gmn
of y is equal to zero.
Now why do I write that?
I expect that the covariant derivative is
going to be zero in the x coordinates,
but the covariant derivative is supposed to be a tensor,
and if a tensor is
zero in one set of coordinates,
it will be zero in all coordinates.
So it better be that if
I've defined the covariant derivative correctly,
then in flat space like this,
it had better be that the covariant
derivative of gmn is also equal to zero.
That's a property of the metric tensor
that its covariant derivative is equal to zero,
which is another way of saying physically,
it doesn't vary from place to place,
and in particular,
in Cartesian coordinates in flat space,
it doesn't vary at all.
Okay,
let's assume that's true.
Let's take that as given,
that the covariant derivative of
the metric is equal to zero,
and let's see what it says.
And we'll do it by,
well,
just by substitution here.
gmn.
gmn,
gns,
and gmr,
I think.
And this should be equal to zero,
if the covariant derivative of
the metric is equal to zero.
This is an identity which,
if you struggle with it a little bit,
you can actually solve it for gammas.
In terms of derivatives of g.
I'm not going to work it out on the blackboard.
It's a little bit tedious.
You can either look it up in a book,
or you can try working it out yourself.
A few tricks you need to write down.
You need to write down a few,
I'll tell you what to
do when we get to it.
I'll tell you what the solution of this equation is.
This,
regard this as an equation for the gammas.
It's an equation for gammas in terms of g's,
and in terms of derivatives of g's.
That's what it is.
Since g with lower indices multiplies gamma here,
supposing I wanted to get
rid of g with lower index.
I have something which,
let's first of all write
that this thing here is equal to minus
derivative of g,
what was it?
Oh yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
I lost the derivative with respect to yp of gmn.
Yeah.
Approximately that.
Okay.
So here I have an equation.
If it didn't have two terms like this,
it would be very easy to solve.
I would just multiply by the inverse of g.
I have a gamma times a g,
and g is an invertible matrix.
So all I would have to do is
run through the invertible matrix,
and I would wind up with a g inverse.
I would wind up with a gamma,
something like pms,
with a derivative of g on this side,
and a g inverse,
lower components here,
and a g with upper components here.
Just by inverting g,
and bringing it over to the other side.
It would bring an inverse
of g to the other side.
Is that clear?
Well,
we're doing it.
But because there are two terms here,
it's more complicated.
It's more complicated.
I'm going to write down the answer,
and then what you do is you go home
and you check that the answer that I write down
satisfies this relationship.
I'm going to write down what gamma is,
and it's your job to go home and check
that if you plug in for gamma,
it really does satisfy this condition.
So I'm going to write down what it is.
Does anybody know what these things are called?
The gammas?
I forgot to tell you.
They're called Christoffel symbols.
They're called connections.
Affine connection.
Christoffel symbols.
Whatever you like.
Christoffel symbols,
not Christoffel.
They're not called gammas?
They're called gammas,
too.
Yeah.
There's a lot of things called gammas.
What's that?
Yeah,
but not too many of them
with three indices like that.
So if you want to give them the right name,
their right name is Christoffel symbol.
There are all kinds of things
which are called connections.
They're all similar,
and they're all related.
They all are doing the same kind of job
in various contexts,
but in geometry,
in this metric geometry like this,
these objects are called Christoffel symbols.
Is there a Christoffel symbol of two kinds?
Yeah.
But they're just related by raising and lowering indices.
I just noticed,
it looks like you can lower indices
on those terms,
can't you?
Which two terms?
The right-hand side.
Yeah.
Yeah,
you could.
Indeed.
You could pull,
this could be written,
this could be written as gamma P M
with another index N downstairs.
Right.
And how about this one over here?
This one could be written as gamma P N M.
They're identical except one of them has M N,
the other one has N M.
Okay.
So they're not the same.
In general,
they're not the same.
You can't,
you can't obviously equate them,
they're not the same.
And for that reason,
you can't just solve this equation
by saying that this thing
is basically half of this thing.
Not so.
It's more complicated.
But I'll write down what the answer is
and you can check that.
In fact,
yeah,
let's write down the answer.
All right.
I'm going to use other letters now
so that we don't confuse them with the letters here.
I'll use A,
B,
and C.
Gamma A,
B,
C is equal to one-half G A D.
I need another letter of the alphabet.
That's going to be a summation index.
And then it's the sum of three terms.
Three terms.
Each one has a derivative.
Each term has a G with a superindex here,
upstairs index,
and then derivatives of G with lower indices.
It's just the indices are a little bit intricate.
G A D times the
partial of the derivative of G,
let's see,
what is it?
D C with respect to X B.
D C with respect to X
B plus the partial of G,
now let's see,
wherever I see B,
see G D B with respect to X C
minus the derivative of G A.
B C with respect to X D.
Um,
the question is,
sir,
when you're over on the southern coordinate,
do you think you're doing a derivative
with respect to the Y coordinate?
Oh,
sorry.
Depending on whether,
in any coordinate system,
it has this form.
Right.
So if I was working in the Y coordinates,
I would put Y there.
Right.
But then,
of course,
I would use the metric
in Y coordinates.
Metric in Y coordinates,
if I wanted these,
and this would be the Christoffel symbol
and Y coordinates.
Now the Christoffel symbol itself is not a tensor.
It's not a tensor.
For example,
one way to see that it's not a tensor
is if we were in conventional Cartesian coordinates
in flat space,
the derivatives,
and with X coordinates,
the derivatives of G are all zero.
So this whole thing would be zero
in X coordinates.
On the other hand,
if we changed coordinates
to some other kind of curvilinear coordinates,
the G's would not be constant anymore,
and the Christoffel symbol would not be zero.
So the Christoffel symbol is not a tensor,
but it's to be used in conjunction with tensors
to construct covariant derivatives.
That's its whole goal in life,
is to be used together
with the rules that I outlined
for constructing derivatives of tensors.
It's the extra term,
or it's a piece of
the extra term which is there
because the coordinates wiggle from place to place.
All right,
so your job then is to test
how you can take this expression,
feed it into here,
and check that what you get on the left-hand side
is just dG by dy.
That's the...
I don't remember.
Forgot,
It's a...
I don't know.
I'm not sure why.
If we plug it in,
it ought to work.
I don't remember.
Oh,
yeah.
And the important thing is,
look at the structure of it.
The two...
the BC components,
in one term you have B downstairs,
in the other term you have C downstairs.
Those come in with plus sign,
and then the last component has D downstairs.
Okay,
you can play with it and work it out.
But the important thing about it,
it's not so important exactly what it is.
You can memorize it if
you like or don't memorize it,
but the important thing is it is the connection,
it is the object,
which allows you to differentiate tensors.
So,
you can use the derivative of V...
M with respect to X,
N plus gamma N...
M R V R.
Covariant derivative.
Okay.
Well,
that's a funny,
strange question.
Is there some kind of convention
where you have downstairs indices
that are underneath the log
and then you have downstairs indices
above the log,
over here on the right hand side,
right?
はい
y sub v is a downstairs index.
It's a downstairs index.
It's upstairs in y,
but because it's below the line,
it's downstairs.
Right.
You have three downstairs indices,
but it isn't obvious to me what the order of those
indices should be written as if you wrote them all as downstairs.
You mean this one too?
No.
Just the part inside brackets.
Basically,
we have three downstairs indices,
but should I call that v,
d,
c,
or d,
b,
if I was thinking of it as
one of the identity with three downstairs indices?
It's not symmetric with respect to them.
It is symmetric with respect to b and c.
It's symmetric with respect to b and c,
but not with respect to d.
And that you can see because there's
a minus sign here among other things.
It has three downstairs indices.
Yeah.
It does.
So we could call it gamma b,
c,
d.
No,
it's got two downstairs indices plus a third one.
Okay.
You just have to remember which one goes where.
And it happens,
if you look at it carefully,
you'll see that it's interchange symmetric
with respect to b and c,
but not with respect to d.
Okay.
I thought the d disappeared.
I just made it.
Yeah,
yeah,
but nevertheless,
we have to give this thing a name in here.
That gets multiplied by g,
a,
d.
And then the d disappears.
Okay.
And before we disappear it,
we give it a name.
Okay.
Using g to write lower indices,
that works with non-tensors?
It happens in this case,
it does.
Yeah.
It happens in this case.
And furthermore,
furthermore,
you can use gamma
to differentiate contravariant tensors also.
For example,
I'll show you.
I'll show you the rule.
The same object,
as it happens,
enters into the derivative of contravariant tensors,
contravariant components of tensors.
For example,
if you have a vector with an index n,
now it has an upper index n,
again,
y components,
and you want to differentiate it with respect to ym.
Okay.
So,
you have a vector with an index n,
again,
y components,
and you want to differentiate it with respect to ym.
That itself is not a tensor.
For the same reasons,
the contravariant components also depend
on the direction of the axes.
So,
as the axes move around,
you've got to keep track of that.
And the derivative of the
contravariant components are not themselves tensors.
All right.
This would be a tensor with
one upper index and one lower index,
but it's not.
You have to add something to it.
And the thing you have
to add to it has gamma.
Now,
it has a lower index m,
an upper index n.
We're going to have to put in another index.
Let's call it r.
That's going to be a summation index.
And then a vr of y.
So,
the same set of objects is
useful in differentiating things with upper indices.
Once you construct this family of objects,
and there's a lot of them.
How many of them are there in three-dimensional space?
Three times three times three,
27 of them.
In four-dimensional space,
it's 64.
Of course,
they're not all independent.
They do have some symmetries.
But there's a lot of components.
And so,
if you're actually doing some computation,
you might want to write
them all down in your notebook,
make a list of them,
what they are,
what their values are,
and then start playing with them.
So,
it's...
It's a tedious business working out these things.
But the logic...
It's the logic that I want
you to understand that differentiating tensors
and doing it in a
way that gives you back tensors
is a slightly complicated process that involves a new thing,
namely the so-called connection or Christoffel symbol.
That's the basic lesson.
Okay,
yeah.
So,
the reason that the metric has a zero...
covariance derivative is because it's zero in Cartesian,
and it also must be zero in the other.
Yeah.
It makes a lot of sense to say
that in the Cartesian coordinates in flat space,
flat space is the same everywhere.
It makes a lot of sense to say the basic
object in that space is constant from position to position.
You don't have to define it that way.
You could have defined some crazy definition,
but in flat,
homogeneous space,
the blackboard going on...
going on and on forever,
perfectly flat and perfectly homogeneous.
Homogeneous means the same everywheres.
It makes good sense to say that the
metric has no variation from place to place.
So,
in the flat coordinates,
the tensor that you would make
by differentiating the metric would be zero.
Once it's zero in one coordinate system,
if it's a tensor,
then it has to be zero in all coordinate systems.
And so,
one comes to the conclusion that the
covariance derivative of the metric should be zero.
That's what we use to find a basic relationship which,
when solved,
gives us this formula.
Yeah.
Do you have a way of looking at the derivative,
the covariance derivative of a
vector that doesn't involve the coordinates?
In other words,
you're taking the nearby things and doing something to them.
And what precisely is it?
I mean,
here we've gotten a lot of information.
Well,
okay.
Yeah.
It's very hard to describe
what you're doing without introducing coordinates.
But maybe it helps a little bit,
the following idea.
Any space,
any Riemannian space like this,
with metrics like this called Riemannian spaces,
any Riemannian space,
curved or not curved,
locally,
that means if you look at
a very small patch of it,
looks like flat space.
It's indistinguishable from flat space
for a small enough region.
That means on a small region there,
you can introduce Cartesian coordinates.
You can introduce perpendicular,
perpendicular coordinates.
And you can even do it so that the derivative,
first of all,
so that the metric at
that point is delta m n,
by introducing,
you know,
on the surface of the Earth.
The Earth is not flat,
but just drawing two perpendicular great circles,
basically.
Wouldn't even realize they were great circles if we're,
looking at some small region.
We just think they're straight lines.
And introduce locally,
in the vicinity of a point,
Cartesian coordinates.
Then the metric at that point,
at that point,
the metric will just be delta m n.
But it's possible to do even a little better than just
saying that the metric is delta m n at a point.
It's also possible to keep the
coordinates straight enough and perpendicular enough,
so that the derivatives of the metric at that point,
at a single point,
are zero.
So that up to first derivatives,
the metric is constant,
and,
uh,
and just of the form delta m n,
at a particular point of space.
With a given set of,
well,
with a given space,
you can't make the metric constant everywhere,
unless the space happens to be flat.
If the space is flat,
you can make the metric,
like this,
everywhere.
But if it's not flat,
you can go to a particular point and do that.
Now there was a reason why I raised that,
but I forgot what the question was,
though.
You were talking about the derivative.
The covariant derivative.
Yeah.
The covariant derivative of what?
The vector.
You can see from the form of that,
the covariant derivative is symbolized
as having zero in that coordinate.
Yeah.
Okay.
So what it means,
at such a point,
if you go to these locally Cartesian coordinates,
then the locally Cartesian coordinates like this,
the derivatives of g at that
point are all equal to zero,
and at that point,
focusing on that particular point,
the covariant derivative is just the ordinary derivative.
In those coordinates.
In other words,
you erect as close as you can get
the flat space,
the flat coordinates,
the Cartesian coordinates,
you can't do that everywhere simultaneously,
but you can do it in a tiny little region,
and then the covariant derivative
is just the ordinary derivative
in those kind of coordinates.
So it's telling you how the vector varies
in coordinates which are as flattened
out as is possible to make.
How the vector is turning
and growing at the same time.
Yeah,
turning and growing.
In each direction.
Right.
That's right.
Yeah.
So if gamma is zero,
is that a definition for flat space?
No,
no,
that's not quite right.
If you take flat space
and you use curvy linear coordinates,
then gamma is not equal to zero.
Remember,
gamma is not a tensor.
It depends both on the nature of the space
and the coordinates that you use.
In flat space,
what is true
is that it's possible to find coordinates
in which gamma is equal to zero.
But it's also possible to make coordinates
in which it's not equal to zero.
Here's an exercise.
Work out the gammas for polar coordinates.
There are gammas for polar coordinates.
Why is that?
It's because at least one
of the components of the metric,
GRR,
is equal to R squared.
That means the derivative of GRR
with respect to R is not equal to zero.
That begins to give you the possibility
of having a Christoffel symbol in polar coordinates.
And there is a Christoffel symbol in polar coordinates.
That just means in polar coordinates,
when you differentiate a vector,
you have to include...
Remember what happened with the vector
which had constant components in polar coordinates.
It wasn't really constant.
So in polar coordinates in flat space,
covariant derivatives are not entirely trivial.
And that means that there are Christoffel symbols
for polar coordinates.
What is true for flat space
is that you can find coordinates,
namely,
just your good old rectangular Cartesian coordinates
in which the metric is just delta mn
in which all the Christoffel symbols are zero.
In a general curved space,
you cannot do that.
in general,
the Christoffel symbols will not be zero.
Yeah?
Is the term external derivative the same as the derivative?
Say it again?
External derivative?
I see that here in the index.
External.
You mean exterior derivative?
Exterior,
yeah.
Completely different thing.
It is a kind of derivative for sure,
but...
The exterior derivative is a tensor.
You know what the exterior derivative of a vector is?
In three dimensions?
It's the curl of the vector.
It's called an exterior derivative.
So we won't get into that now.
Yeah?
The exterior derivative is a tensor,
but if we ever need it,
we'll come to it.
Let's...
I don't want to stop tonight.
I want to continue tonight
because I want to get finished with this.
With the mathematics,
so that we can start thinking about physics.
All right,
let's...
Take...
Let's see,
what do we need to do here?
Yeah.
Supposing I have some curve.
Now,
let's start with ordinary flat space,
ordinary conventional flat space.
I have some vector field
which varies from place to place.
In particular,
I can evaluate that field along the curve.
And I want to know how the
vector field varies just along the curve.
Ordinary flat space.
What do I do?
I want to know how the components
of the vector vary along the curve.
This is easy.
We just write the field,
v,
let's say the nth component of it,
again,
as a function of y.
And I want to know how it varies...
First of all,
I want to invent a parameter
that varies along the curve.
What's a good parameter that varies along the curve?
Arc length.
Length along the curve.
We can start here and call it zero,
and then measure in some units,
whatever units we like,
distance along the curve.
And of course,
we call that s.
In the same sense that we call ds squared.
The square of a little interval.
We can invent a variable along the curve,
which is just arc length along the curve.
I would like along the curve
to ask how v is varying.
How do I do that?
Well,
I differentiate it.
Let's take first a scalar.
Take a scalar.
How does a scalar vary along the curve?
Its derivative along the curve.
In particular,
its derivative with respect to the parameter.
S.
We evaluate it on the curve,
and I want to differentiate it with respect to s.
So I'd like to find along the curve
the derivative of phi with respect to s.
Whoops.
Just telling me how phi varies.
Well,
if I know how phi varies throughout the geometry,
I just write d phi by ds,
the dx,
dx,
m,
let's say.
That's the partial derivative.
And then what do I do to
make it into the derivative along the curve?
We multiply it by dxm by ds.
So everywhere along the curve,
there's an object dxm by ds.
That,
of course,
is a vector.
dxm is a little vector,
and when I divide it by ds,
s is a scalar,
just the distance along the curve.
dxm by ds is a vector.
You know what that vector is called?
Slope?
The slope would be dy by dx.
I mean,
dx1 by dx2.
So it's connected with the slope,
but it's not quite the slope.
It's a vector.
First of all,
it's not a number.
It's a vector.
It has two components,
dx1 by ds and dx2 by ds.
Okay,
let's look at it a little more closely.
Here we are along the curve.
We take a little interval of size ds,
and we look at dx.
Here's dx.
It's the vector dx along here.
First of all,
what direction is it in?
Tangent to the vector.
Tangent to the curve.
And how long is it?
What's the length of dx by ds?
One.
Yeah,
one.
One.
Why is that?
Well,
it's one.
It's a unit vector along the curve.
It's called the tangent vector.
It is a tangent vector along the curve,
a unit vector along the curve,
called the tangent vector.
Okay?
All right,
so that's why here's what you do.
If you want to differentiate phi along x,
sorry,
along s,
you differentiate it with respect to the coordinates.
That gives you a covariant vector,
and you multiply it by the contravariant vector,
the x by the s.
And that gives you the derivative of phi
with respect to s.
Very simple.
Now,
supposing we want to differentiate a vector,
or a vector,
not a tensor,
not a scalar,
but a tensor,
in particular a vector,
along a curve.
Well,
you might think that the right thing to do
is basically the same thing.
Take the vector v,
let's take a,
a contravariant vector.
It depends on x,
I guess,
well,
x and y are the same thing here,
x.
All right.
And now what do I do with it?
Well,
differentiate it with respect to position.
x,
what do we call it,
let's call it n,
m times dxm.
m by ds.
This actually gives us the
derivative of the component of v
with respect to s.
Would you guess that this is a tensor?
It's not likely to be a tensor,
because,
the whole thing is not likely to be a tensor,
because the vn by dxm is not a tensor.
Remember,
the ordinary derivative
of components of tensors is not itself a tensor.
So this object is not a tensor.
It doesn't represent,
let's see why.
Well,
it's the usual reason.
Even if v were completely constant along the curve,
what would that mean?
That would mean it's completely constant,
pointing in the same direction
everywhere as along the curve,
because the coordinates flop,
not because the curve is floppy,
incidentally,
but because the coordinates are floppy,
the v by dx won't be zero,
and so even for a vector which was absolutely constant
in space like this,
this wouldn't be zero.
You're not assuming that's coordinates,
those are Cartesian coordinates.
No,
I'm not assuming they're Cartesian coordinates.
Right,
no,
particularly not.
No,
I guess I should have stuck with my convention,
x being Cartesian,
so then we should use y here.
All right,
so let's use y.
Well,
what can I do to
make a vector out of this,
a tensor out of it,
a tensor that varies along the curve?
Well,
we just replace this
by the covariant derivative.
Wherever you see ordinary derivative,
replace it by covariant derivative.
At least the covariant derivative
has the property
that if the vector isn't really varying,
the covariant derivative is zero.
All right,
so if we replace this
by the covariant derivative,
that's just
covariant derivative
with respect to m
of v n of y
times the tangent vector,
that we can think of as
the covariant derivative,
the notation for it is
it's the covariant derivative
with respect to the parameter s
of v n.
In other words,
we've defined
a covariant derivative of a vector
along a curve.
How?
Now,
you just take the ordinary
covariant derivative
and you multiply it by
the tangent vector.
Tangent vector just tells you what
direction you're differentiating in.
You take the covariant derivative
and that defines the covariant
path derivative along the curve.
Important concept.
Okay.
In particular,
it has the property that in Cartesian space,
in flat space with Cartesian coordinates,
if the components are constant,
then the vector doesn't vary along the curve.
Okay.
That's the notion of
the covariant derivative
of a vector along a curve.
Just...
Good.
Let's write out,
let's write it out in detail.
Let's write it out in detail
in detail.
What is it?
It's the derivative of v n
with respect to y m
times...
Well,
let's add the other term.
What's the other term?
All right.
Tell me where to put the gamma,
the indices of the gammas.
Where does the n index go?
It's upstairs.
It better go upstairs in the gamma.
The m index has to go downstairs
and then we need another index
and write v r.
That's the covariant derivative
of v.
Then we have to multiply it
by the tangent vector.
So let's multiply it here
by the tangent vector plus
dy m
by d s
by d s.
What is this thing over here?
The derivative of the component,
the nth component with respect to y
times dy by d s.
Chain rule,
right?
This object over here
is just the derivative,
the ordinary derivative,
the ordinary derivative
with respect to s
of v n.
So along the curve
we differentiate the first term
but then there's another term
and the other term is
gamma n m r
the vector that we're differentiating
times the tangent vector.
So if I have a vector
which is defined along a curve
and I want to differentiate it
along the curve
in a way that makes it a tensor
I just differentiate its components
and then I hit it with a gamma
along the curve
the gamma is defined along the curve
times v r and also multiplied
by the tangent vector.
See the pattern?
Okay,
now let's go
another step.
Let's ask how
the tangent vector varies
along the curve.
For v,
let's just put in
the tangent vector itself.
And then I would be asking
how the tangent vector
varies along a curve.
Here's the tangent vector.
And obviously in general
the tangent vector varies
from place to place.
In particular if the curve is a curve
on the flat blackboard
the curve is really a curve
then the tangent vector varies.
We can work out the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector.
Let's do it.
What's the component of the tangent vector?
For v n
we're going to substitute
d y n
by d s.
That's the component of the tangent vector.
And I'm now computing
the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector itself.
The covariant derivative
along the curve
so let's just plug it in.
First of all,
what do I get for
d v n by d s?
That becomes
the second derivative
of y n
with respect to s.
It's just the derivative
with respect to s
of the derivative
of y with respect to s.
So that's a second derivative.
A certain second derivative of y
along a path length.
And then what's the other term?
Gamma
m r n
Let's write down
d y m
by d s
and then v
is just d y
r by d s.
So the first term
is just
the second derivative
of y with respect to s.
And the second term
look at it
that has an m and an r
down square.
It has a d y by d s
a tangent vector
the mth component
and a tangent vector
the rth component.
Nice and symmetric with respect to these two.
And it has an extra index
representing the uncontracted index here.
This is
the covariant derivative
of a tangent vector.
And the covariant derivative
of a tangent vector
is a tensor.
That means if it's zero
in every reference frame
it's zero in every reference frame.
What do you expect the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector of a straight line to be?
Zero.
If I have a straight line
in flat space
the tangent vector is
the same everywhere.
So
if I am in flat space
and I have some funny coordinates
I have some funny coordinates
which aren't ordinary flat
you know,
ordinary Cartesian coordinates
but I give you the tangent vector
I give you the components of the tangent vector
and the Christoffel symbols and so forth
that's what you know
how do you test if it's a straight line?
Its components are not constant
because the coordinates aren't constant
they flop around.
How do I test whether
whether my vector
sorry,
whether my tangent
whether my tangent vector
whether the curve is a straight line?
Well,
I compute
the covariant derivative of the tangent vector
and if it's zero
all along the line
all along the curve
then that curve is a straight line.
It's just telling me that the tangent vector
is unchanging as I go along the line.
You could do this
with funny coordinates
even if those coordinates
aren't flat coordinates.
Now,
can it be
that in curved space
really curved space
which cannot be brought to the flat form
because there's some obstruction
called curvature
which doesn't look like we'll get to tonight
but
can it be that the covariant derivative
of a tangent vector
can be zero anyway
even though the space is not flat?
What would you guess?
Yes.
What are curves
whose tangent vectors
are covariantly constant
covariantly constant
is another way of saying
the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector is zero.
Here it is.
Where is it?
Supposing I have a curve
a curve means some y
a curve means a curve
y is,
and along the curve
the curve has a set of coordinates y
that depend on how far along the curve you are.
Everywhere along the curve
y is given.
Here's
the tangent vector.
Can it be
that the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector is zero?
It certainly won't be true for every
curve.
In flat space
it's only true for straight lines.
Can it be true in a general curved space
that you can find curves
special curves which have the property
that the covariant derivative
along them is zero.
The answer is yes.
And
those curves have a name.
Geodesics.
Geodesics are if you like
the straightest possible
curves in the space.
They have the property that the
covariant derivative of the
tangent vector is zero.
In particular that means
if you take coordinates locally
which are as flat as possible
then along then
the components of the vector are constant
for a little ways.
Until the coordinates start to bend.
But a geodesic
that's the general definition of a geodesic
a geodesic is one
is a curve
whose tangent vector is
covariantly constant.
Covariantly constant means
that it's
that the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector is equal to zero.
And that's it.
That's the
definition of a geodesic.
In a certain sense
it's the straightest possible
curve in the space.
Or it's a family of curves.
Yeah?
Quick question.
You defined this all in terms of a covariant derivative.
Yes.
Could you just as arbitrarily
use a contravariant derivative
and get to the same point?
Yes.
You could have used
yeah we could have used
sure,
definitely.
We could have used
used the
contravariant defen...
covari...wait sorry
just a moment just a second.
The term covariant derivative does not mean
that the object is a covariant vector.
Completely different use
of the word.
It's unfortunate.
This is the
covariant derivative of a contravariant
component.
Too bad.
That's the way it is.
But like the key
point is the inclusion of this gamma thing.
Yeah.
That's right.
Now,
just to
tell you where this is going
let me tell you where this is going.
Um
Straight lines in space time
in special
relativity,
special relativity
space time is flat.
Straight lines in space time are the
orbits of particles that have no force
on them.
Okay.
The orbits of
particles that have gravitational
forces on them
are
geodesics
in space time.
That means
they satisfy equations like this.
Now if you look at this
equation and you think of
path length along
a world line
as being
like time,
ticking off time
along the world line.
And this is almost like acceleration.
It is.
It basically is acceleration.
The
uh
we don't want to prove this now.
We just want to tell you
where it's going.
This looks like the second derivative of a
coordinate with respect to a parameter.
And that parameter could
be proper time.
It would be proper time.
So it's
essentially a relativistic
version of acceleration.
What does this say?
It says that
acceleration is
equal to something on the right hand side.
What would you call that thing on the
right hand side?
Force.
Right.
So where we're going
eventually is that
this is the equation which determines
the orbits of particles in a
gravitational field.
The force is proportional
first of all to the Christoffel symbol.
That's the most important thing about it.
Uh
forget these things for a moment.
They're there.
They're important.
But uh
here's the important thing.
What does this contain?
It contains derivatives of the metric
with respect to position.
How about Newton's
equations?
What's Newton's equations
for the motion of a particle in a gravitational
field?
It's F equals M A,
right?
Alright.
Uh,
F equals F.
M A is mass
times the second derivative of
position,
let's call it
position Y,
with respect to time.
It looks
sort of like this.
And then
what's on the right hand side?
The gravitational force.
But what is the gravitational force proportional
to?
Well,
in general,
in a general gravitational field,
it's proportional to the mass
times the derivative
of
the potential,
the gravitational potential
Let's call it,
let's give it a name.
Phi or V?
I don't know.
V U
V.
With respect
to Y.
Masses cancel out.
You can see
there's some similarity.
An acceleration type term
being related to
derivatives of something
with respect to position.
What are the Christoffel symbols?
They're composed out of derivatives
of the metric with respect to
position.
So somehow we're
going to find that the derivatives
of the metric with respect to position
are the analogs
of the
Newtonian gravitational
force.
That's where we're going.
So I thought I would
tell you rather than just blindly
write formulas on the blackboard.
Particles move
on geodesics,
which means
the straightest possible paths
in space-time.
But of course you can't have a completely
straight path in a curve
space.
And deviation from
what you might think of as
straight
is proportional to these gammas.
So the gammas are very
very closely related to gravitational
force.
They are the gravitational force.
What else
can we say at this point?
Yeah,
we haven't gotten around to curvature yet.
But we have all the apparatus
that we need.
We need one more concept.
Namely the concept
of parallel transport.
But I
will tell you what that is next time.
Parallel transport.
And then we will get to the idea of curvature.
We have some ideas that are going to be
useful for how particles move.
Next we need to understand
more deeply the
obstruction to spaces
being flat,
to flattening them out.
And that's curvature.
Okay,
we're done.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at
stanford.edu.