This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Today,
I want to do two things.
One is to discuss geodesics a little more
and to explain a little more thoroughly
the connection between gravitational forces
and geodesics or the motion of geodesics through space-time.
So for the first part of the lecture tonight,
we're going to be thinking about space-time,
not just space,
but space-time.
But the mathematics for space-time is very similar
to the mathematics for ordinary space.
Okay.
There's also a metric.
When we're talking about space and time,
instead of using m and n for indices,
we use Greek indices,
mu and nu.
And again,
there's a notion of distance,
which is called proper time.
I'll also write it,
well,
I guess I usually write it,
I have to write it,
but I have trouble keeping my notations entirely consistent.
I'll try to keep them consistent as I can.
Instead of calling it ds squared,
s is usually the label for distance in space.
One calls it d tau
squared because it's more like time,
proper time,
the proper time along a trajectory
has a little interval along the trajectory.
It has a set of different degrees of time,
and it's called the differential displacement,
which are called dx mu.
Remember,
mu runs from zero,
one,
two,
and three.
One,
two,
and three represents space.
Zero represents time.
And
the square of the proper time along the trajectory,
along a little interval like that,
is defined again in terms of a metric.
In general,
this metric,
in special relativity,
this metric is constant.
Everywhere is the same,
and it's usually taken to be
the symbol eta mu nu.
Eta mu nu is the analog for space-time
of the Kronecker delta symbol,
delta mu nu,
delta mn,
for ordinary space.
And it's given not by one,
one,
one.
It's a 4 by 4 matrix,
but it's given by one,
zero,
zero.
Zero minus one,
zero,
zero.
Zero,
zero,
minus one,
zero.
Zero,
zero,
zero.
Zero minus one.
All right,
so in other words,
it's of the form dt squared minus,
if we wanted to replace these by t,
x,
y,
and z,
then in special relativity,
the metric here would just be d tau squared,
or the proper time would just be d tau squared,
which is equal to dt squared minus dx squared
minus dy squared minus dz squared.
That would be the rule in units
in which the speed of light is equal to one.
Where would I put the speed of light
if I wanted to include it in this formula?
Well,
if I wanted tau,
which is called proper time,
to have units of time,
not of space,
but of time,
then I wouldn't want to put the speed of light
in front of dt squared
because the speed of light has units.
What are those units?
Units of velocity,
kilometers per second.
But the place that it
would go would be in here,
over c squared.
Uh,
we'd...
like that.
All right,
so,
um,
notice,
first of all,
that if the speed of light is large,
which it is in ordinary units,
in ordinary units
where the speed of light is large...
Now,
what does it mean to say
the speed of light is large?
The speed of light is the speed of light.
It's neither large nor small.
It is what it is.
What it really means is that
the things that we're interested in
are moving very slowly with
respect to the speed of light.
So that,
uh,
so that we can think of the speed of light
as much faster than anything we might be interested in.
Under those circumstances,
if this object here is moving slowly,
then,
uh,
then we can treat the speed
of light as being very large,
and this piece here is essentially negligible.
And d tau is the same as dt.
So for slowly moving objects
in a frame of reference which,
uh,
in a frame of reference
in which everything is moving slowly,
then time and proper time
are very close to being the same thing.
But more generally,
if we're interested in things which are moving fast,
then this is the proper time along a trajectory.
It's the time as recorded by a clock
moving with the object.
A standard clock made in the standard clock factory
moving with the object
will record proper time,
not coordinate time.
This would be called coordinate time,
this would be called proper time.
Now in general theory of relativity,
general theory of relativity
is related to special relativity
in the same way that flat space
is related to curved space.
We haven't discussed yet what curvature means.
We're going to do that tonight.
But,
um,
Yeah?
I have a question.
Isn't dt the one that the clock would record
if it's moving with the object?
No,
d tau is the one that the clock records.
The clock moves and ticks off
proper time in the same way
that if you have a curve in space
and you lay out a tape measure along it,
the tape measure doesn't record
y or x,
it records distance along the curve.
Alright?
Think of the clock moving with the object
as a kind of space-time tape measure,
keeping track of proper time along the trajectory.
Each tick of the clock can be thought of
as a marker along this fictitious tape measure,
the space-time tape measure.
The only peculiar thing is that
there's a minus sign in here.
Alright?
So that we need to keep track of.
But as I said,
general relativity is related to special relativity
in exactly the same way,
or exactly in an analogous way
to the way that
flat space,
that would be,
flat space would be like special relativity,
and curved space would be like general relativity,
except it's curved space-time.
Other than that,
the rules
are basically the same
for geometry,
the existence of a metric,
the notion of covariant derivative,
exactly the same.
The Christoffel symbols are made up
out of the metric tensor.
The metric tensor is a tensor.
There are covariant,
contravariant tensors,
covariant derivatives,
Christoffel symbols,
and they're all made exactly the same way
as they would be in space,
except that you use the space-time measure,
rather than the space metric by itself.
Notice there's one time direction,
one direction with a plus sign,
and all the others have a minus sign.
Okay.
No,
this is last week's.
Quick question.
Yeah.
The matrix size,
whether it's four or five or six,
is this what accounts for
the extra dimensions in string theory?
Yes.
The number of Xs
and the size of the matrix
is related,
not just related to,
is exactly as you say,
the number of dimensions.
It doesn't have to be string theory.
Whatever space-time we're talking about,
the dimensionality is just the number
of entries here,
and it's also the size of the matrices.
But,
you know,
apart from that,
the rules are basically the same
in every dimension,
and whether it's space-time
or just plain space.
Now,
excuse me.
When we're dealing with flat space
or space-time,
we don't ever really need
to introduce curvilinear coordinates.
We may or may not.
We may not want to.
In fact,
it almost seems like
a stupid thing to do
because it's going to complicate
the description of things.
When do we do it
and why do we do it?
We do it because we're sometimes interested
in accelerated frames of reference.
An accelerated frame of reference
is basically one in which
the coordinates of space
are being accelerated.
Let's say they start coming in from the left
and run off to the right.
You know what I mean.
And the mathematical description
of an accelerated frame of reference
in terms of an original unaccelerated...
What's an unaccelerated frame of reference called?
An inertial frame.
Yeah,
the description of an accelerated frame
in Newtonian mechanics.
Forget relativity for a minute.
In Newtonian mechanics,
it's just a frame of reference...
Well,
let's see.
If we have our inertial frame of reference,
Tx,
that's our inertial frame of reference.
In this frame of reference,
all objects move along straight lines.
Then the accelerated frame of reference
is one whose coordinates
are curved like this.
They form hyperboles.
And in this frame of reference,
an object which is moving
along a straight line in X-T coordinates
would in fact not be moving along
a linear trajectory in the new coordinates.
And so it appears to be accelerated.
Of course,
the object is simply accelerated
with the equal and opposite acceleration
to the way the coordinate frame is being accelerated.
It's just the old elevator story.
And had it not been for Einstein thinking about elevators
and acceleration and its relationship to gravity,
nobody would have been stupid enough
to introduce curved coordinates into physics.
Why would you do such a foolish thing?
It makes things more complicated.
And of course,
the answer was the equivalence principle.
The curved coordinates are the
same as a gravitational field.
Now,
I'm going to talk about the equation of the equation.
So we do introduce curved coordinates.
That itself is not the same as space-time curvature.
We'll come to it.
But once we introduce curved coordinates and so forth,
the whole apparatus of tensor analysis,
transformations of things from one frame of reference
to another,
all of that gets inherited
from the geometry of space
that we've discussed up till now.
All right,
let's see.
I'm not sure what order to go in.
I think we'll begin with curvature.
Uh,
I had...
Or should we begin with geodesics?
Take a vote.
Who wants geodesics?
Who wants curvature?
All right,
we hear curvature.
Okay.
So I'm not even sure why I talked about this.
All right,
we'll come back to it.
We'll come back to it.
Oh,
yeah,
I do remember.
Yeah.
Curved coordinates are sort of a luxury
that you can use or not use in special relativity.
But they're not a luxury
when you come to think about gravity.
If you...
Well,
in the general theory of relativity,
but in particular,
even in Newtonian gravity,
it's not possible to remove a real gravitational field
by changing coordinates.
One of these fake gravitational fields,
which is just due to accelerated coordinates,
that can be removed by
just replacing the gravitational field.
You can remove the accelerated coordinates
by non-accelerated coordinates.
But a real gravitational field,
you cannot remove that way.
For example,
if you have a star,
and there's a gravitational field
pulling you toward the star,
then in a small elevator over here,
you might be able to remove
the effects of the gravitational field
by just letting the small elevator freely fall,
and then all experiments inside the,
uh,
the falling elevator
would be exactly as if there was no gravitational field.
And that's not quite true.
It's not quite true because of tidal forces.
Because across the elevator,
the gravitational field varies a little bit.
There's a little bit of tidal forces.
But if you make the elevator small enough
so that the gravitational field doesn't vary very much,
then you completely remove the
effects of gravity inside that elevator,
by just letting the elevator fall.
Well,
that's like kind of introducing a coordinate frame
inside the elevator,
which is like the straight line,
which is like the,
um,
the inertial frame.
And the coordinates which are not falling,
those are like the curved coordinates.
You can't,
however,
get rid of the curved coordinates
or the gravitational field everywhere simultaneously.
There's an obstruction.
If you introduce an acceleration vertically,
that's not going to get rid
of the gravitational field over here.
Or,
over here,
if you introduce a coordinate system
which is accelerating vertically,
let's say in the down direction,
that's only going to make things worse over here.
It might remove the gravitational field
in the falling accelerator on this side,
falling,
um,
uh,
elevator on this side,
but the same coordinate transformation
will only increase the gravitational field down here.
So there's an obstruction,
uh,
to removing the effects of gravity,
or an obstruction to finding coordinates
which sort of straighten out all the effects of gravity
and get rid of them.
That obstruction,
mathematically,
is the same obstruction
as the obstruction
of taking a general space,
or general space-time,
and thinking of it as flat.
First of all,
what does it mean
for a space or a space-time to be flat?
In the case of a space,
it means that you can find coordinates.
It doesn't mean that every
coordinate system has this property.
It means you can find coordinates
which have the property
that the metric tensor is just delta mn.
More specifically,
it really doesn't need to be delta mn.
The metric is constant in space.
Incidentally,
there are coordinates
in which the metric is constant in space,
but which,
in which it's not delta mn.
If you choose coordinates
which are at angles like that,
on this blackboard,
but which are completely uniform,
made up out of straight lines,
equally spaced,
then the metric is not delta mn,
it's some other numerical tensor like this,
but it's constant from point to point.
So another way of saying it is that
a flat space-time is one in which
the metric can be chosen to be absolutely constant
everywheres.
To put it slightly differently,
the metric can be chosen
so that the derivative of the metric
with respect to coordinates
Notice this is a thing with three indices.
The general derivative of the metric
with respect to position
can be chosen to be equal to zero.
You can find a metric,
you can find a coordinate transformation,
which will make the derivatives of the metric
all equal to zero.
That is a flat space-time by definition.
One,
alright,
now,
I assert,
not only do I assert,
I will give you an argument
that you can always,
at a particular point,
here's some curved space,
a general space,
without even knowing it,
without even knowing what curvature means,
I will tell you right now
that it is always possible
at a particular specific point
to choose coordinates,
to choose coordinates
so that at any specific point
the derivatives of the metric
equal zero.
That's always possible to do.
Let's see how we can argue that.
That there's,
in other words,
there's enough freedom
in the choice of coordinates
so that at one point
you can choose g
to have derivatives equal to zero
in every direction.
First derivative,
the first derivative,
not the second derivative
and the third derivative
and the fourth derivative,
but that the first derivative of g
can be chosen to be zero at a point.
Let's figure out how many equations
and how many unknowns there are.
Supposing we have some coordinates,
let's call them x coordinates
in which the metric is not constant
or does have derivatives at this point.
In other words,
where the g's are not without derivative
at this point.
And let's make a coordinate transformation.
To a new set of coordinates,
I'm going to call them y.
I'm going to choose the origin
of the y coordinates
to be exactly the same
as the origin of the x coordinates.
For example,
a simple example would be
ym equals xm.
That's a dumb coordinate transformation.
It's no coordinate transformation at all.
But now I want to
make it more general than that.
And I'm going to assume
that we can tailor series expand,
that we can expand y's and x's
that we can start with ym equals xm
plus a deviation
which is going to be quadratic.
And then of course,
there can be cubic terms,
higher terms than that.
But let's add in some quadratic terms.
And the quadratic terms
will be quadratic in x.
The left hand side has an index m
associated with it.
So we better put here some coefficients.
These are numerical coefficients,
just numbers.
At the moment,
they're not even functions
because we're just interested
in one particular point.
At one particular point,
we'll add in,
and I'm going to put a cmrsxrxs.
This is the most general thing
that I can write down,
which is quadratic in the x's,
and of course,
has an index m from here,
and xr and r and s
that combine with the x's here.
That's in fact the most general
coordinate transformation
which is quadratic in the x's
and which has the property
that the origin of coordinates,
namely y equals 0,
is the same as x equals 0.
Alright,
x equals 0
and y equals 0 are the same.
Alright,
so all that means
I've just introduced other coordinates
located with the same origin over here,
but they're curved relative to the x's.
That they're curved has to do
with this term here,
relative to the x's.
Okay,
how many variables
do I have to play with
in making such transformations?
Let's figure out.
How many such variables are there?
One question.
It looks as if,
if you're saying
that's like a Taylor expansion,
does it look like you've already
almost assumed,
did you drop out
the first derivative?
Or I guess you didn't.
Oh,
that's actually here.
And I could have made it
a little more general in this,
but I just decided that the leading term
would be y is equal to x.
Alright,
the leading term y equal to,
I could have made it more complicated
so that the linear term here
was a little more complicated,
but there's no need to do so.
Alright,
so how many constants
C are there?
Just for fun,
let's see how many there are.
C,
let's forget the M for a minute
and just think of CRS for fixed M.
C is a matrix.
Just putting our hand over M here,
And furthermore,
it can be taken to be
a symmetric matrix.
It can be a symmetric matrix
because there's no difference
between xR times xS
and xS times xR.
So C is symmetric,
with respect to interchange of R and S,
or can be chosen to be so.
If we have a space
with a certain number of dimensions,
let's say d dimensions,
then how many independent entries
are there for a symmetric matrix?
No,
no,
d dimensions.
6 is right in 3 dimensions.
5 times d minus 1 over 2?
d times d plus 1 over 2.
Yeah.
Remember,
we've got to get 6.
6 for 3,
so 3 times 4 is 12,
divided by 2 is 6.
So it's d times d plus 1 over 2.
We're not going to use this.
I just wanted to do a little bit
of combinatorics.
But now,
this one matrix like that,
for each entry M,
how many possibilities does M take on?
d.
So the answer is d squared times d plus 1
constant C that I can play with.
I haven't chosen them yet.
We're going to think of
them as unknowns in a minute,
unknowns subject to a condition.
Now,
when I construct the metric
in terms of Y,
how do we do that?
We transform from Y to X.
We transform from Y to X,
and we'll get a metric starting with GMN of X.
We will get a new metric,
which we can now call G,
well,
let's just continue to call it MN of Y.
It's the new metric in Y coordinates.
Okay?
I'm going to require of the constants C,
the condition,
in other words,
I'm going to try to choose
the C coefficients here,
so that the derivative of G
with respect to Y is equal to 0.
How many unknowns are there,
and how many equations are there?
When I write this out,
this will just become an equation.
Given what GMN of X is,
I'll transform it.
I'm not going to go through the whole business.
We're going to transform G,
find G of Y.
That's going to involve the constant C,
because they'll enter into the coordinate transformation,
and then I'll write down the equations
that the derivative of G
with respect to any given direction is 0.
Those become equations for C.
How many equations are there?
How many such equations are there?
Well,
there's a symmetric matrix
that's D times D plus 1 over 2,
but how many such symmetric matrices are there?
In other words,
there's exactly the same number
of components of this object,
GMN with an index S,
as there are of this object.
A thing with three indices
with two of them symmetric.
Same thing here.
Three indices with two of them symmetric.
These equations,
there are just exactly the same number
of these equations
as there are coefficients C.
The conclusion is
there's just exactly enough equations
so that you can always find
a coordinate transformation
which sets the first derivatives of G
equal to 0.
So that's something you can always do.
Once you've done the first derivatives,
if you start looking at the higher derivatives,
there are just too many of them.
If I wanted to write down higher derivatives here,
there are too many higher derivatives
to allow you to solve the equations.
So at most,
you can set the first derivatives
of G equal to 0.
Supposing we've done that,
supposing we've done that,
and we've found coordinates
where this is equal to 0.
Alright,
there are various things we can say.
First of all,
the derivative of G with respect to X
is equal to 0 at that point.
But we can say a little bit more.
We can also say that the Christoffel symbols
at that point are equal to 0.
Why?
Because the Christoffel symbols,
what are those?
Let me write them down for you again.
One half G R S
derivative of G
S M
with respect to X N
plus derivative of G S N
with respect to X M
minus the last one,
derivative of G M N
with respect to X S.
This is the Christoffel symbols.
And of course,
if I have chosen
the first derivatives of the metric,
if I've chosen coordinates
which get rid of the first derivatives
at the point,
at the origin,
for example,
then at that point,
the Christoffel symbols are also 0.
They're made up out of these derivatives.
So at the point in question,
the single point in question,
the origin,
for example,
doesn't have to be the origin of coordinates,
but at the specific point in question,
I have succeeded in simultaneously
finding coordinates in which
the derivative of G is equal to 0
and in which the Christoffel symbols
are equal to 0.
From that,
it follows
that the covariant is equal to 0.
The covariant derivative of G is equal to 0
because the covariant derivative of G
is just the derivative of G
with respect to X
plus Christoffel symbol times G
plus another Christoffel symbol times G,
one for each index of G.
I won't bother writing the details.
So once we have found coordinates
in which this is true,
and in which this is also equal to 0,
we know that at that point,
at that point,
the covariant derivative of G
is equal to 0.
But on the other hand,
the covariant derivative of G
is a tensor.
The ordinary derivative of G
is not a tensor.
The Christoffel symbols are not tensors.
But the covariant derivative of G,
that was the whole purpose
of inventing covariant derivatives,
to make things which really are tensors.
So the covariant derivative of G
is equal to 0.
It's a tensor.
And if a tensor is equal to 0
in one coordinate system,
then it's equal to 0
in every coordinate system.
Well,
there was nothing special
about the origin of coordinates.
I could have done exactly the same thing
at every point.
And so I conclude
that the covariant derivative of G
is 0.
Everywhere is.
Just because I can choose coordinates
at any point
where the derivative of G
and the Christoffel symbols
are equal to 0.
So that's the theorem that...
How do we know that the C's
will,
when we make them be non-constant
from point to point...
We begin by doing this at a point.
Right,
but now we are able to extend that
to,
say,
through a curve or something.
Well,
you can't know...
If you go to a new point,
there'll be new C's.
If you go to another point...
The functions going...
They won't necessarily be continuous,
would they?
They'll be continuous,
yeah.
The function C will be continuous,
but they will vary from point to point.
The argument's a little circular.
I mean,
have you used...
You used that...
The...
The very derivative of G being 0
to derive a theorem...
ありがとうございました
You know,
that's true.
That's true.
The argument is a little bit circular.
The argument is a little bit circular,
but what it proves is the consistency of the definitions,
if you like.
You could introduce other kinds of geometric structures
where the Christoffel symbols are replaced by other objects.
There are other definitions of the Christoffel
symbols where the covariant derivative of g,
for example,
is not equal to zero.
Such things are possible.
I guess what we really prove here is the consistency of
the idea that the covariant derivative of g is equal to zero.
We assume the covariant derivative
of g is equal to zero.
We calculate from that the
definition of the Christoffel symbols,
and then we go back
and we discover with that definition.
The covariant derivative of g is equal to zero.
So actually you're right.
The definition is circular.
Not completely circular.
Yeah.
In any case,
the definitions are consistent,
and they are the standard definitions of
how you covariantly differentiate tensors to get tensors.
Question.
Yeah.
If this is related to...
An intuitive notion of flatness.
Yeah.
What would happen if somehow or another,
like you had a wiggle,
and then inside of every wiggle you
put another wiggle inside of every wiggle?
So is there a constraint on g such that you can't get a situation that is
sort of infinitely wiggly so you could never find a coordinate system that would be flat?
No.
You're asking,
for example,
whether g...
Could be such an unpleasant function that its derivatives
don't exist or aren't continuous or something like that.
So yes.
So the usual assumption is that
the g's are continuous and differentiable everywhere.
Just once or...
Let's say just once.
Um...
There will be exceptions.
For example,
exceptions are places where the geometries become singular.
There will be exceptions,
but in general,
a place where the geometry becomes singular...
I'll tell you what singularity means in a second.
I've given you examples of polar coordinate singularities,
which are funny right at the origin.
All right?
Polar coordinate singularities are not well...
Sorry.
Polar coordinates are singular at the origin.
That's because...
At the origin,
you can't give a well-defined angular coordinate to a point.
It can happen that you choose coordinates that are defined in
a way that make g's not be properly differentiable or something.
But on the other hand,
you can also find other
coordinates at exactly the same point,
which are not singular at that point.
So polar coordinates are kind of
bad coordinates right at the origin.
But there's nothing wrong or funny
about the space at the origin there.
It's not singular.
And the way to prove it is just
to go to other coordinates where there is...
Where the metric is nice and continuous and differentiable.
There may be places,
honest places,
where there's nothing you can do
to make the metric differentiable and...
Uh...
Friendly function at a point.
And if that's the case,
then one says there's a singularity,
a real physical singularity.
A real physical singularity is a
place where there's nothing you can do,
not only not to make the coordinates flat,
but also to make them smooth,
to make the metric continuous
and differentiable at that point.
I'll give you an example.
We're about to come to an example now.
The cone.
The tip of the cone is a real singularity.
It's a singularity in space where there is no coordinate system that you
can choose which will make the metric at the tip of the cone smooth.
There's something real going on there.
And that's called a singularity.
I have a quick clarification on the
last term in the denominator of the Christopherson.
Oh,
yeah.
Sorry.
Yeah.
Yes.
Is this...
When you solve for the C,
the constant,
is that like trying to find a
coordinate system where the physical systems vanish?
Yeah.
Is that...
But you can do that by making
sure the derivatives of the metric vanish.
Right.
This,
incidentally,
among other things,
proves that the Christoffel symbols can't be tensors.
Because by a coordinate transformation,
you can make Christoffel symbols which are not equal
to zero equal to zero at a particular point.
So the Christoffel symbol is not a tensor.
The derivative of a tensor is not a tensor.
But combining together derivatives of tensors
with Christoffel symbols gives you tensors.
All right.
So...
Good.
Yeah.
So with this definition of the Christoffel symbols,
it follows that the covariant
derivative of the metric is zero.
Right.
And whether it's a good thing or a bad thing,
it's a true thing.
Now,
let's come to the idea of curvature.
As I said,
curvature is a mathematical obstruction.
Its presence prevents you from finding
coordinates in which the space is flat.
Uh...
And to understand...
Curvature,
you first have to understand something
we've already spent some time with.
The idea of covariant derivative
of a vector along a curve.
Let's go back.
We talked about this previously,
but let me go back to it.
That's the starting point.
The notion of the covariant derivative along a curve.
The question...
I'll tell you what question we want to answer.
We want to answer a question like this.
Supposing I start with a vector somewhere in space.
And I would like to move it to another point,
keeping it parallel to itself.
In other words,
I would like to move this vector over to here.
And I would like to know
what its components are over here,
if it's moved in a way
which keeps it parallel to itself.
That's the notion of parallel transport.
That's the notion of parallel transport of a vector.
Keeping it parallel to itself as you move it.
We'd like to move it over here.
Now,
in flat space,
it's pretty clear what you do.
You just keep the vector parallel to itself.
But when we are...
We can just choose Cartesian coordinates.
Cartesian coordinates where the metric is just delta m n.
And in those coordinates,
keeping the vector parallel to itself
just means keeping its coordinates constant.
Keeping its components constant.
But,
if either we have curved coordinates or a really
curved space where we can't choose the metric like this,
then we have to find some definition of what
it means to move a vector parallel to itself.
It's not clear that we can find such a definition,
but I will tell you what it is.
What an appropriate definition is.
Alright,
first of all,
take your curve.
Take your vector.
And make the covariant derivative along the curve.
I'll remind you what that means.
I'll tell you what that is.
If we have a vector.
Let's say it's a vector with contravariant indices.
Then...
And it's defined all along the curve.
All along the curve it's defined.
It might even be defined in the rest of space.
But I'm not interested in the rest of space.
Just along the curve.
Then,
first of all,
we differentiate the components with
respect to distance along the curve.
Right?
ds.
Where s just represents distance along the curve.
Measured in whatever units we like.
But this in itself is not a true vector.
The derivative...
The v's may vary for reasons having nothing to
do with an actual physical variation of a vector,
but having to do with variation
of the coordinates as you move along.
What do you have to do
to make a vector out of it?
You have to make the
covariant derivative which involves the gammas.
Gamma nu.
Oh,
I'm using now the notation of relativity.
Nus and mus instead of m's and n's.
It doesn't matter.
We could...
Somewhere I jumped into space-time.
Let's do space instead of space-time.
M...
Mn...
And...
S...
Let's say no.
P.
Let's call it P.
And then there is a v.
N...
dx...
P...
By ds.
dxp by ds.
That's a vector.
Remember what this vector is?
What is the name of this vector?
dx by ds.
That's the tangent vector.
That's the tangent vector along the curve.
And we worked out last time that this is
the covariant derivative of a vector along a curve.
Along a curve,
it's the covariant derivative,
where this is the tangent vector,
and this is the derivative
of the vector along the curve.
Now,
I'll just remind you,
we defined the geodesic last time
by saying this curve is a geodesic
if the covariant derivative of the tangent vector is zero.
So let's just put that down.
Let's write that down,
the condition for a geodesic.
v now is going to be replaced
by dxm by ds.
In other words,
we're going to replace v by the tangent vector itself.
And then the derivative of the
tangent vector with respect to s
becomes a second derivative.
d second xm by ds squared
plus gamma mnp.
Now the tangent vector,
now v is the tangent vector,
so that's dxn by ds,
and then dxp by ds.
Now,
if the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector is equal to zero,
if,
I'm not saying it's always true for any curve,
but if the curve is
chosen so that the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector is zero,
then the curve is a geodesic.
In a sense,
it's the straightest possible kind of curve
that you can have in the space.
If it's flat space,
then the geodesics are just straight lines.
If the space is a sphere,
then the geodesics are great circles.
In general,
they're nothing of the sort.
They're curves that go through the space,
but they're the straightest possible curves.
They're the curves you would get by just focusing
and going incrementally straight ahead.
Okay.
But now let's define something else.
Let's define parallel transport of a vector.
Supposing we have some vector
which is not the tangent vector now.
Let's come back to a general vector like this.
This vector may not be the tangent vector.
Here it is.
It's v.
And it's allowed to vary along the curve.
Well,
if this covariant derivative
is equal to zero,
then we say that that vector
has been transported parallel to itself
along the curve.
In other words,
this is as close as you can get
to saying the vector is constant along the curve.
If its covariant derivative along the curve
is equal to zero,
one says that this vector
has been parallelly transported along the curve.
Okay.
Can we always do that?
Can we always take a vector at this end
and parallel transport it?
In other words,
can we take a vector at this end
and now move it along here in such a way
that it remains in this sense parallel to itself?
Yeah,
we can.
Let's just rewrite this slightly differently.
Let's just write this.
The small change in vm
as we move from one point to another
Let's get rid of the ds.
Just multiply through on both sides.
The small change in vm is minus
gamma mnp vn dxp.
So if I have a small incremental distance,
dxp here,
oh sorry,
this should be a minus sign,
right?
Not equal to zero.
dvm,
all I've done is solve this equation here,
multiply through by ds,
that's not important.
And this tells me how I should vary
the components of vm
as I move along the curve
so that the covariant derivative is zero.
In other words,
this tells me how to
move from one point to another.
It tells me how to change v,
the components of v,
given the components of v at a starting point
and the Christoffel symbols
and the little differential displacement dx,
it tells me how to
change v to the next point.
In fact,
it tells me,
once I've updated it from here to here,
I can do it again and again and again.
And so it's always possible,
to choose the components of v along the curve
so that the covariant derivative is equal to zero.
All you have to do is to solve
for how vm changes as you move along the curve
by knowing that at any one point
you can find out how
it moves to the next point,
and so forth.
So that's not hard.
That's the construction and the definition
of parallelly transporting a vector along a curve.
To move it from one place to another,
you just change v
by an amount that's proportional to v
and that's proportional to the
amount that you're displacing it
and is proportional to the Christoffel symbols.
Parallel to itself.
In other words,
you have some curve in space,
I have a vector,
and I want to move
it along the curve in space,
so that it always stays parallel to itself.
That's what we're trying to do.
Okay?
Just a little aside.
I always like the Hot Wheels car example.
If you have a globe,
and you move a Hot Wheels car along it,
so that the direction never changes,
you get the great circle.
Or even on an inner tube,
the Hot Wheels car is the
thing that always has the same direction,
and it will give you the shortest distance.
That'll give you geodesics.
Right.
But now we're taking a
curve which is not a geodesic.
First of all,
a geodesic is a curve,
is a vector which has been moved parallel to itself.
I was just using that as an example
as keeping the same direction
is the same as minimizing distance.
That's for a geodesic,
yeah.
But you can also parallel transport
something which is not a geodesic.
For example,
we can parallel,
sorry,
you can transport a vector
which is not the tangent vector.
I want to transport this vector along that line.
Now if I take that vector
and transport it along that line,
then the tangent vector is the thing that I'm transporting.
If the derivative of the tangent vector is zero,
it's a straight line.
But I can also take any vector,
which is not necessarily a tangent vector,
and start transporting it along the curve,
whether or not the tangent vector is a tangent vector,
or whether or not the curve is a geodesic.
Take any curve,
any curve,
take a vector,
and transport it so that it stays parallel to itself.
That you can always do.
Parallel to itself and of the same magnitude.
Now would this be the same as
saying that the angle between the vector
and the tangent vector is always constant?
No.
That's definitely not what it says.
Why?
Because the tangent vector is itself changing.
Let's do it a little differently.
Here,
let's take a circle.
And let's take a vector.
There's a vector.
Now I'm going to transport it along itself.
I'm going to transport it parallel to itself.
I'm having trouble keeping it exactly parallel.
But notice by the time it gets down to here,
it's become the tangent vector.
Keeping it parallel to itself,
along the circle,
will make it the tangent vector over here.
Over here it's perpendicular to the tangent vector.
And up here it's the tangent vector again.
So if I take a circle,
in flat space,
a flat space circle,
and transport a vector parallel to itself,
the angle relative to the curve changes.
It's the angle relative to the neighbor
which hasn't changed.
The neighbor to this point,
or to the vector over here,
is this point over here.
It's relative to the neighboring value
that it hasn't changed.
So we're moving it along incrementally,
along the curve,
crazy directions,
but always keeping it parallel to
its neighboring value.
That's called parallel transport.
Yeah?
S of ds is any parameter.
S of ds could be any parameter along the curve.
Right.
It's canceled out of this equation here.
So there's a notion of parallel transport
along a curve.
Okay?
But now you could ask an interesting question.
Supposing...
Does everybody understand what it means?
It means as you move along the curve,
even if the curve is turning,
you make sure that the vector stays parallel to itself.
Let me give you an
example how you could do that,
physically in the real world.
A gyroscope.
You take a gyroscope.
A gyroscope is a spinning object.
All right?
If you don't really forcibly change its direction
and you just hold it by
its tip or whatever it is,
and you move it around,
it will always face in the same direction.
You don't have to move it along a straight line.
You can move it along a curve.
That gyroscope will transport
parallel to itself.
So a gyroscope is a physical implementation
of parallel transport in space along a curve.
Okay?
You move it around.
Pay no attention to it.
Just move the tip of it.
And because of its angular momentum,
it will continue to point in the same direction.
Even if you transport it along the wildest,
wiggliest curve,
that's the idea of parallel transport.
So this would be the equation then
that would govern,
in three dimensions for example,
would govern the components
of the axis of a gyroscope
as you move it around.
Now that's not the same as Cartesian coordinates
relative to that point though.
We haven't even introduced any coordinates.
Well,
we have introduced the coordinates.
I'm saying there's perpendicularity implied here.
What's that?
Is perpendicularity implied with parallelism?
Perpendicular to what?
Well,
in order to be parallel,
it must be perpendicular to something
that's perpendicular to it.
Yes,
yes.
So let me say it a different way.
Take two distinct vectors,
which happen to be perpendicular to each other,
and now parallel transport both of them.
They will stay perpendicular.
Okay.
Three vectors forming a tetrahedron,
a triad,
which you could make by three perpendicular gyroscopes
and transport them around,
and they'll stay perpendicular to each other.
So parallel transport sort of preserves
the angles between vectors and so forth,
and it's the closest thing that you can have
to the notion of moving a vector around
so that its direction and its magnitude stay fixed.
Okay.
That's the notion of parallel transport.
In fact,
it's possible to prove that the magnitude
of the vector stays fixed,
but mostly I'm interested in the direction now.
But now I come to a funny question.
How do I know that
if I parallel transport a vector
from one place to another along curve A,
let's call that curve A,
I start it over here,
and I transport that gyroscope,
I transport that gyroscope
over here till I get to here,
how do I know that if
I did it along a different curve,
I would come to the same final conclusion?
How do I know that if
I transported it along a different curve,
it wouldn't come out in some other direction?
No.
That equation is just a definition of parallel transport,
and it refers to a curve.
How do I know if I chose another curve,
then in fact I would get the same result?
Well,
I'm just saying you already canceled ds,
so it doesn't refer to a curve.
It does refer to a curve.
The dx's here refer to the curve.
The s is only the parameter along the curve.
The dx's are the sequence of little differentials
along the curve.
Okay.
Right.
So this definition of parallel transport,
and in particular,
the idea of transporting it all along a curve,
we could ask,
does it guarantee that the result of a parallel transport
leads to a unique final answer
independent of the curve connecting the two points?
Well,
the answer is no,
it does not guarantee that,
and in fact,
in general,
it's not true.
If you,
or you could say the same thing another way.
Instead of parallelly transporting
it along two different curves,
let's imagine parallelly transporting a curve,
sorry,
a vector around a closed curve.
That's an even better situation.
Take the gyroscope,
and parallelly transport it around a closed curve.
Does it necessarily come back to the same direction?
Okay.
The answer is,
in flat space,
yes,
that's intuitively obvious.
Well,
right.
But the question is,
in a general space,
in a curved space,
is it necessarily true
that if incrementally,
from point to point,
you make sure that you keep
the vector parallel to itself,
the gyroscope,
must the gyroscope come back to itself?
And the answer is no.
The
obstruction,
or the fact,
or the condition,
the situation,
in which it doesn't come back to itself,
is the situation in which there is curvature.
That's the diagnostic test
to find out if a space is flat or not,
is to transport vectors around curves,
and if you ever find
a curve that you can take the vector around
where the vector does not come back to itself,
somewhere in there is some curvature.
That's the definition of curvature,
that parallel transport around a closed curve
does not bring you back to the same vector.
If there is curvature,
it's quite obvious that you cannot,
uh,
flatten the space out
to give it a metric
which looks like a conventional
flat space metric.
Yeah?
Does a Mobius strip have this property?
Sort of,
yeah,
let's see.
A Mobius strip,
actually,
when you go around a circle,
a vector can flip,
it's a flipper,
yeah,
yeah.
Yeah,
but there's,
there's,
uh,
yes,
a Mobius strip does have
a kind of global,
I'll call it global curvature,
and I'll come back to
the Mobius strip in a minute.
Uh,
Mobius strip is a non-orientable surface,
and so it's a little bit peculiar,
but,
uh,
we can certainly find examples
without going to non-orientable surfaces.
The cone is the sort of simplest example of all.
The cone is a space which is,
by the cone,
everybody know what I mean by a cone?
Heh.
Like an ice cream cone.
It's what you get if
you take a sheet of paper,
cut out an angular wedge.
Alright,
there's an angular wedge.
I wish I had a knife.
Does anybody have a,
uh,
scissor with them?
Hmm?
Yeah,
I,
I know I can do a,
I can do a trick,
but let me,
uh,
what I do with the cover to this?
Oh,
okay.
Ah,
my knees.
Oh,
cool.
Okay.
Okay,
so let's cut out
the angular wedge.
It's called an angular deficit,
or an angled deficit.
I should have brought a big piece of,
uh,
what do we call that kind of paper in kindergarten?
Oak tag,
oak tag,
yeah.
Uh,
big piece of it,
and
cut it out.
So you cut out a wedge,
like that,
and then you sew it together
along,
along the wedge like that,
and you make a cone.
Is that obviously a cone?
Yeah.
Yeah,
that's obviously a cone,
right?
Now,
once you sew it together that way,
you could cut it and slice it some other place
and open it up,
so it doesn't matter where you cut it
but wherever you cut it and open it up,
it looks like that.
Now notice,
it looks pretty darn flat,
but when you put it together like this,
it no longer looks flat,
and in fact,
you can't flatten it out,
not without smooshing it in the,
uh,
and stretching it.
So the cur- the cone is a curved space,
but it's a curved space of a very special type
where there's no curvature anywhere except at the tip.
Let's see if we can refine that and,
uh,
and understand it.
So let's start with a cone.
I'll first draw it as a cone.
Here's the tip up here.
And of course,
a real mathematical cone
goes on and on forever.
It doesn't terminate at this point over here,
but we can terminate it
because I can't draw it forever.
And then we come with our scissors.
I don't think I need this anymore,
but let's leave it here.
I might want to do some more.
We cut it,
open it up,
and it looks like,
I guess like,
um...
What's that?
Yeah,
a pie with a,
uh,
slice taken out.
Alright,
so that's a cone with a rule.
The rule is that point over here
is identified with a point over here.
For example,
if a fly walks around across here
and crosses the red line,
then in this map over here,
think of this as a map of the cone,
the fly walks around over here and then jumps.
Jumps over to here.
The red line
has been sliced open,
but then we have to remember to identify points
in the appropriate way.
That's the mathematical construction of a cone
in terms of a flat space.
Now,
notice that this sheet of paper,
as well as this drawing over here,
is completely flat.
Everywhere's along here,
and it's not flat.
As long as we keep away from the problematic areas
where we've cut it,
and the tip of the cone over here,
it's completely flat.
So first of all,
let's take a closed curve over here.
That's a closed curve
on this flat sheet of paper.
And now,
take our gyroscope
and transport it around.
Taking the gyroscope
and transporting it around the closed curve,
parallel to its center,
it moves itself at every point.
Alright,
so,
whoever's doing this parallel transporting,
as he moves it,
he makes sure that incrementally
it stays in the same direction.
And as he goes all the way around,
guess what?
What happens to it?
It comes back to itself.
Alright?
So,
there's an example
of a parallel transport
around the closed curve
where the vector did come back
to its original value.
But now,
let's parallel transport
around the tip of the cone.
Alright,
so now we're going to take
a curve that circumnavigates
the tip of the cone.
Alright?
And in particular,
let's start with a vector,
just for the sake of clarity,
I think I find it a little clearer.
Let's start with the vector being
aligned along the red line.
And let's parallel transport
along the curve.
Alright,
first of all,
the curve on here looks like that.
It's a circle.
It's a piece of a circle
when we open it up.
And the vector starts out
in this direction.
Oops.
Starts out by assumption
along the red line.
Now we move it parallel to itself.
Parallel to itself does not
mean that we move it
so that it's pointing radially out.
That's not parallel to itself.
Parallel to itself means
we keep its direction fixed.
And by the time we get over to here,
it's now pointing,
in this case,
practically perpendicular
to the red line.
What's going to happen,
supposing we now close this up.
We might slice it along
some new place.
a new place
and close it up over here
so that we close it up
back into the curve over here.
Look what it's done.
It's gone from something
which is parallel to the red line
to something no longer parallel
to the red line.
And that means when we
parallelly transported it around,
it's going to come back
to some new vector
which is going to be
perpendicular,
or not perpendicular,
but at some end
at some angle
relative to the original vector.
In other words,
it's quite clear.
When I close this up,
this vector will wind up
coming out in this direction.
Just think about closing this up
and this vector over here
will wind up pointing
in some new direction.
So here's an example
of parallelly transporting a vector
at every stage,
keeping it parallel to itself,
and by the time it goes around
a closed curve,
it's not parallel to the starting point.
Notice that only happens
if we go around the tip.
If we steer clear of the tip,
that doesn't happen.
The tip is the point
at which there is curvature.
So the tip,
the diagnostic test,
has,
I don't know whether
we should say it failed
or it succeeded,
it's failed to demonstrate
that the space is flat.
It has succeeded in finding
a point of curvature.
Why do I say a point of curvature?
Because if I circumnavigate
any other point,
I find no shift in the direction,
but only,
but every circumnavigation
of this point gives me
the same angular shift.
So what does it do?
The presence of this point of curvature
has the effect of rotating vectors
which have been parallel transported
around in a closed curve.
It doesn't matter that this closed curve
is a circle,
it could be any closed curve
around the tip.
It will always rotate the vector
by the same angle.
Incidentally,
if we started with a vector
which was not along the red axis
but some other direction,
and we went around,
again,
it would still come out
in some new direction.
And how about this angle,
the angle that the vector gets rotated?
How much is that?
That depends on this angle here.
This is called,
the angular deficit here.
It's the amount that was bit out of the pie.
Let's call it theta.
When you take a vector
around this closed path,
it gets rotated by the same angle theta.
So one might say that there's an amount
of curvature
which is parameterized by the angle theta.
The bigger theta is,
or is it,
yeah,
if theta is a very small angle,
in other words,
if just a very,
very tiny piece of pie
were taken out,
then there's very,
very little
change in the direction of the vector
that's been parallel transported.
The bigger that the angle theta is,
the more rotation there is in this vector.
So that's an example of a point of curvature.
Now let me point something out that,
here we are,
we're going to parallel transport
around this particular curve.
Nothing can depend
on whether the tip of this cone here
was truly pointed
or whether I came along with my sandpapering machine
and whittled off and made it smooth.
So somehow,
the effect of going around this curve
is the same whether this has been smoothed or not.
However,
supposing I go around the curve
very close to the top here,
then I'll get a different answer than on the cone.
Then I'll get a different answer.
In fact,
I'll get a much smaller angle
at the top of the cone here
than if I go around
this particular curve here.
Okay,
so somehow,
this operation of going around this particular curve
has located the fact that there's some curvature in there,
but it hasn't told me the details.
This particular curve has not diagnosed
whether there was a point of curvature here
or whether there was a smooth curvature there,
but it's told me there is some curvature in there
because when I go around the curve,
because when I go around the closed curve,
I don't come back to itself.
So,
let's see now.
Oh,
let's do a sphere.
Let's do a sphere.
A sphere is also curved.
Question?
Yeah.
When you say parallelly transported,
can you nail that down a bit more?
No.
Because if that's the angle
to the circle going around,
then that basically defeats the argument.
Sorry?
It's not radially out.
I can understand why it's not radially out.
If it's pointed towards infinity,
then again the argument...
We take the curve
and we break it up
into lots of little straight lines,
okay?
And then we parallel transport from one to the other,
and I'm not sure how to say this right.
We're not transporting out
the vector so that it stays
at the same angle to the curve.
We're transporting it so that it
stays the same angle to itself.
But if it's a geodesic,
does it stay at the same angle to the tangent?
Right.
I have a question.
I think that helps answer that question
because in a sense,
if that's constant direction,
then parallel transport is constant
with respect to the constant curve.
That's right.
If you parallel transport something
to a geodesic,
it will stay at the same angle to the geodesic.
At least in two dimensions.
Three dimensions gets a little more complicated
because a vector can twist around.
So there's something called torsion
where the vector can twist around.
But at least in two dimensions,
that if you transport a vector on a geodesic,
then it will stay at
the same angle to the curve.
But on a column,
that would be sort of a spiral.
Say it again.
On a cone,
a geodesic would look like a spiral.
It wouldn't be just a circle perpendicular to the axis.
The geodesics on a cone
are simply the geodesics that it inherits from flat space.
So straight lines in here
are geodesics on the cone.
Yeah.
Well,
they will get curved when you curl them up.
Say it again.
They'll get curved when you curl them up.
Well,
when you...
You see the straight lines on here?
They're geodesics.
Also,
the straight line here is a geodesic.
The straight line here is a geodesic.
I don't know,
would you say they get curved when you...
Yeah,
sort of.
Looking at it from the top,
they appear to get curved.
Yeah.
The point is,
what happens when a straight line crosses the identified...
When a straight line crosses where?
The lines that were identified.
It is no longer a straight unless it actually has...
Okay.
Right.
What you do,
if you're interested in a geodesic which crosses here,
then what you do,
that's like a geodesic which crosses from here to here,
then the thing to do
is to close it up over here,
and this is going to be hard,
and...
I don't want it to fall apart.
And open it up over there.
Okay?
It's the same space,
and now the geodesic that goes
across the original thing can be drawn.
All right?
And you're right.
What will happen is that
when I open it up again,
that geodesic which went across here will look bent.
The geodesic which crosses across here will look bent,
but when I close it up again,
it'll look straight.
Okay?
So there is a geodesic,
for example,
which connects this point to this point,
it doesn't go around here,
it goes across here,
and then changes angle and goes over here.
And that angle would be repeated on
the slice you made on the other side
to make it parallel.
Yeah,
for example,
if the angle was 90 degrees over here,
then it'll be 90 degrees over here.
What I'm saying is once you close that up,
by making the other slit,
the angle becomes the same in the other...
Oh,
yes.
Absolutely.
But this curve from here to here
will then become a smooth straight line.
Right.
So if you're interested in curves
that go from here to here,
the thing to do is not to use this representation,
but close it up over here
and open it up somewhere else.
And you can always do that.
So cutting and pasting is
the way to think about cones.
So we do see that there are situations
where parallel transport along a closed curve
does not bring you back to the same thing.
And when you don't come back to the same thing
under such circumstances,
that is the diagnosis of curvature.
Somewhere is in the geometry.
Usually,
I mean,
typically it means that this curvature
somewhere is inside that curve,
somewhere is in the interior of that curve.
Curvature in higher dimensions is a little more complicated.
We'll come to it.
But let's just do a...
Let's draw a sphere for a moment.
Let's take a hemisphere.
I'm interested in the sphere,
but I just want to
draw a hemisphere for the moment.
And now I want to parallel transport
a vector around
not a great circle,
but some other circle.
A great circle is a geodesic.
A great circle being,
for example,
the equator.
So transporting
parallel transporting a vector
along a great circle
just means keeping the angle
relative to the great circle fixed.
But that's not true
of a curve which is not a great circle.
Parallel transporting is a little more complicated.
And here's a simple way to think about it.
Think about the bug moving along here,
carrying his little gyroscope with him.
Can that bug,
who can only see an
infinitesimal little distance around him,
can he tell,
he or she,
can he or she tell
that this curve was not a curve
on a cone?
A cone which has been fit
so that it's tangent to the sphere.
Can everybody visualize that cone?
Yeah,
I don't think you can.
You just said so.
Right.
It's a dunce cap.
It's a dunce cap on a spherical head.
And it just happens to be tangent
right along that curve.
What's going to happen when I transport
parallelly a vector around there?
It's going to do exactly the same thing
as it would have done
on the corresponding cone.
Okay?
How big is the angle deficit
of the cone?
Well,
that depends on where I draw this curve.
For example,
if I draw the curve up here,
the angle deficit,
there'll be less of an angle deficit.
It'll be a flatter cone.
It'll be more like this.
In fact,
if I make the circle
a very small one,
way,
way up close to the North Pole,
then that cone is practically a flat cone
with a very,
very small angular deficit.
So the answer is,
if I take a vector around the North Pole,
staying very close to the North Pole,
transport it around,
the angle may deviate a tiny bit,
but not very much.
If I take it around at 45 degrees here,
it'll,
you'll discover
a fairly large angular deficit.
And so,
but in any case,
the point is that the sphere is curved.
We've diagnosed the curve,
the sphere,
by transporting vectors
parallelly to themselves along closed curves
and found out that they don't come back to themselves.
Not surprisingly,
that means that there's curvature on the sphere,
that the sphere is a curved surface.
It also means that you cannot find
flat coordinates,
you know,
delta mu nu type coordinates
on the flat sphere.
So curvature is the obstruction
to flattening a geometry out
and making it everywhere flat.
Uh,
I'll tell you
the fact now
that if you have a curved geometry
and you go around a small curve,
a small curve,
then of course
the angle deficit is small.
Okay?
So if you take,
in any geometry,
as long as you take a small enough curve
and you take a vector
and parallelly transport it around,
the deviation of the direction
will turn out to be small.
You can see that on the sphere here
that,
uh,
that up near the north pole of the sphere,
the corresponding cone
has a very small angular deficit.
Alright?
How much of an,
how much of an angle,
how much of a rotation do you think occurs
for a given circle up here?
Is the angle
here proportional to the distance
or what?
Anybody know?
The area.
Right.
This is something that's worth working out.
You can work this out by yourself.
It's just a question of
taking a small circle up here,
fitting it to a cone.
All that means is you have,
here's your circle,
you,
uh,
here you have your two points
that correspond to the circle
and,
uh,
draw the tangent vectors.
How much of an angle is involved?
The angle will be proportional to the area
of that little region.
So it's the area that controls
how much of a,
uh,
how much of a deficit
or how much of a,
um,
a displacement you get
when you go around a small circle
or a small curve.
Yeah?
Even if the area is not a circular...
Even if it's not a circle,
the,
uh,
the displacement and angle
will be proportional to the area.
All right.
So we can write down,
let's call it delta theta.
Well,
let's,
yes,
let's just call it delta theta.
The angle that the vector,
uh,
fails to reproduce the original direction,
that delta theta will be proportional
to the area of the enclosure,
the closed curve,
times something,
a number,
and that number is called the curvature,
R.
For example,
if I have a very big sphere
and I take the same little area over here,
I'll get a very small angular deficit.
On the other hand,
if I take a small sphere
and take the same ang,
uh,
the same size circle over here,
I'll get a rather large angular deficit.
The smaller the geometry,
the bigger the curvature.
That's called,
that's the curvature of a two-dimensional surface,
is the relationship between the area
of small little curves
and the angular,
let's just call it the angle deficit
that's suffered when you go around the curve.
Yeah?
The area here,
the area on the surface
or the area of the projected surface?
Well,
it really doesn't matter
because we're talking about,
yeah,
we should be talking only about very small areas,
so let's call this delta area.
In other words,
the right thing to say
is that for an infinitesimal area,
you get an infinitesimal angle
and the coefficient is called the curvature.
And it doesn't matter in detail
what the shape of the curve is.
That's something you need to prove,
but it's a true statement.
Yeah?
In case of the conical example,
vectors that we're talking about
must lie on the surface of the cone
in the two-dimensional space,
correct?
Yeah.
In the case of the three-dimensional sphere,
is that also true?
No,
the surface of the sphere is two-dimensional.
The vectors,
however,
do not lie on the surface of the sphere,
do not have to lie
on the surface of the sphere.
You can think,
that is a good question.
You don't usually think of vectors
as lying in the space.
You usually just think of the vectors
as having a magnitude
and having a direction.
So you can think of the vectors
as sort of lying in the tangent space
to the surface.
The vectors,
you don't think of the vectors
as being creatures
which live on the surface.
They're creatures which have a direction
and a magnitude,
and they point along the surface,
but they don't stick to the surface
when the surface changes.
So you think of them as things
which live in the tangent space.
Okay,
that's the official words.
But yes,
you're right.
I mean,
the vectors don't really
literally exist in the space itself.
They're mathematical objects
which live in the tangent space.
Okay.
Well,
if you,
if you go around the equator,
the tangent vector,
that's going to work just fine,
and yet there's an area deficit there,
isn't there?
Yeah,
yeah.
But that's,
this formula is only for small areas.
For large areas,
you have to work it out in general.
There's some integral to do.
And that's right.
Now somebody asked me about the Miebius strip.
The Miebius strip is a funny thing.
How do you define a Miebius strip?
You define a Miebius strip
by taking a strip,
like that,
and then making identifications
that this point over here
is equivalent to this point,
A,
A.
This point over here is equivalent to this point,
B,
B.
The vector from,
or the segment from A to B
is equivalent to the segment over here
from A to B.
But quite clearly that means
if you take a vector
around the Miebius strip,
it changes,
it flips its direction.
So that's an example of a kind of curvature.
But Miebius strips are so weird
that they don't fall into the,
into the same classification.
They're non-orientable surfaces,
and they get confused.
Did you call it,
what is it you're calling it?
That's,
in my language,
it's called a Möbius band.
Möbius.
And you're calling it what?
Miebius strip.
Not just neither.
It's M-O-U-M-L-A-U-T.
Is it U-L-A-U-T?
Möbius.
Oh,
okay.
It's pronunciation,
same word,
different pronunciation.
Möbius.
Forgive me for being American.
Excuse me.
Well,
it's Möbius in the same sense
that a Mieba is.
Is it?
I don't know.
No,
no,
it's M-O-E-B-A,
right?
A Mieba.
Wait a second.
Möbius was a person.
No,
no,
I'm just saying that
it's anglicized,
it's pronounced the way we do.
Oh,
okay.
Right,
right,
right.
That's what I meant.
I'm raising the question about the Taurus.
The Taurus,
good.
All right.
Because that's also a rectangle with identifications.
Right.
So the mathematically idealized Taurus,
which is made in the way you just said,
is flat,
is strictly flat
when the Taurus is defined
in the way that you said,
which is a rectangle with identifications
across the rectangle.
A real Taurus,
like the bagel,
the surface of a bagel,
is curved,
but it has an integrated curvature,
which is zero.
We'll come to that.
Well,
maybe we'll come to it.
The problem is you can't construct a flat Taurus
in three-dimensional space.
You can do it in four-dimensional space.
You can't embed it in three-dimensional space.
Actually,
you can.
I just realized you can.
Not so.
Hmm?
It's,
well,
it's intrinsically flat,
but you can't get a flat embedding.
Yeah,
I'm going to make a flat embedding for you.
All right,
here's the rectangle.
What we want to do is
identify this edge with this edge
and this edge with this edge.
Some people don't know what I'm talking about,
so I'll explain it.
A Taurus is the surface
of a bagel or a doughnut,
and it looks like that.
Just think of the surface.
We're not thinking about the interior,
not the good stuff that you eat,
but just the surface.
And now cut it.
Cut it open.
Open over here and open it up.
What does it become?
It becomes a piece of a cylinder,
right?
I mean,
just topologically,
it has the properties of a piece of a cylinder.
And now when you've done that,
cut it along here.
Cut it along here and open it up.
And what does it become?
It becomes a rectangle.
It becomes a rectangle,
this edge over here is identified with this edge,
so that means this edge over here,
A,
B,
C,
D,
becomes A,
B,
C,
D.
A fly which walks across from here to here
walks across here and reappears over here.
And the bottom,
A,
B,
C,
is identified with the top,
A,
B,
C.
Okay,
that's a Taurus.
And clearly that Taurus can do this.
It can be drawn on the
blackboard so that it is flat.
Normally when you draw a Taurus,
it's curved.
Over here at this edge here,
it almost looks like a sphere,
so it must be curved over here.
In the inside over here,
it has negative curvature.
On the outside,
it has positive curvature.
So far we haven't defined the sign of the curvature.
But,
you know,
question,
can you take this sheet of paper,
and fold it together so that it forms a Taurus?
Well,
yeah,
you actually can.
You fold it together.
You gotta put a fold in it.
Alright,
now this edge,
this edge has been identified with this edge.
I could take a piece of tape and fold it.
Now I want to identify this edge with this edge,
so I fold it again,
like that.
I don't even need to fold it.
I just do this.
And now think of a bug walking around.
The bug walks around from here,
comes out on this side,
comes around over here,
comes out on this side.
So that's going around the Taurus this way.
Or,
it can go around this way.
That's going around the Taurus this way.
So in fact,
I can make a flat Taurus.
It's just a little bit...
Not much nourishment in it.
Well,
actually there is no integrated curvature.
on the edge.
No?
It's got a little bit
of positive curvature on one side,
a little bit of negative curvature on the other side.
Yeah.
So it's a little bit degenerate,
as you say.
But in four dimensions,
in four dimensions,
you can draw a surface,
a two-dimensional surface,
that is an absolutely flat Taurus.
So a Taurus can be flattened.
A sphere cannot be flattened.
Interesting difference.
And...
Yeah.
Now,
notice what we're doing.
Yeah.
The constant,
I mean,
if you draw small circles
at various points in place on the Taurus,
do you get angular deficit in circles?
As you go around?
Are you asking me about positive and negative curvature?
I'm asking you if delta theta equals r delta a,
what does...
You're asking me about...
What value do you get from r?
You don't always get zero.
On a flat plane,
zero.
No,
but on the Taurus.
Oh,
no,
that's...
On a real Taurus,
meaning one which is embedded in three dimensions,
there's curvature all over it.
So you get r as a different value.
Different values,
and in particular,
on the outside of the Taurus...
I'm going to explain now the sign of the curvature,
and then we'll come back to...
And I'll tell you about the Taurus.
Okay.
There's a notion of the sign of the curvature,
and here's the way it works.
Look down from the top,
and let's go around clockwise,
or counterclockwise,
either way.
Let's see.
We're going to go around this cone.
Around the cone.
Oh,
incidentally,
in the case of the cone,
what is the curvature?
How much curvature?
What is the numerical value of the curvature?
The numerical value of the curvature is zero everywhere,
except at the tip,
and the curvature at the tip is...
You think that's the angle deficit?
No,
it's infinite.
It's infinite because the curvature
is the ratio of the angle deficit to the area,
and I can take an infinite way
of the curvature,
and I can take an infinitely small area
and still find that angle deficit.
So the curvature at the tip of the cone
is actually infinite.
It's an example of infinite curvature.
Infinite curvature means a singularity in the geometry,
a place where it's not smooth.
Okay.
So we have the idea of curvature,
but now what about the sign of the curvature?
So let's take a vector,
let's say,
pointing perpendicular.
Let's amuse ourselves
by taking a perpendicular vector
and parallelly transporting it around to here.
By the time it gets over to here,
it will be pointing in the same direction,
be sort of pointing this way,
parallel to itself,
and now close up the angle.
Close up the angle,
and which way is it pointing
after you close up the angle?
It's pointing kind of this way,
right?
All right.
We've transported the vector
in the counterclockwise direction.
We've transported it counterclockwise,
and which way did it rotate?
Same way.
Rotated the same way,
and so we could give signs to these things.
We could say that,
um,
that going around this circle
in the counterclockwise direction
is a positive little area.
Let's imagine now that areas can have signs.
Here's the way we assign a sign to an area.
If we have a little area
and we go around it counterclockwise,
we call that area positive.
If we go around it the other way,
we call it negative.
So areas are things which have a sign.
You don't usually think of
an area as having a sign,
but think of it as having a sign.
Think of the area as having a sign
because it's not just an area.
It's an area plus an oriented boundary.
There's a sense that we're imagining
a sense of direction around the boundary.
For counterclockwise,
let's call it positive.
For clockwise,
let's call it negative.
Then on the sphere here
or on the cone,
if we go around clockwise,
delta theta is also clockwise,
and that corresponds to positive curvature.
Since delta theta and delta area
have the same sign,
in other words,
if we go around the area clockwise,
we transport around a curve which goes around clockwise,
delta theta is also clockwise,
that's positive curvature.
Is there such a thing as negative curvature?
And the answer is yes.
It's not hard to manufacture geometries
which have negative curvature.
It's a little harder to see,
not nearly as easy to see.
But if you take a saddle shape,
the,
you know,
a mountain pass,
is it clear what shape that is?
Pringles potato chip.
What's that?
Yeah,
potato chip,
right,
exactly.
Uh,
that's right.
A Pringle,
is it Pringles?
Yeah,
those are the ones that mold it.
They are truly...
They're bad.
They look like it.
No,
let's take Kettles potato chips or something.
The good ones,
some good one.
Yeah,
that's right.
The potato chip or the saddle surface,
the saddle surface has the property,
believe it or not,
that if you go around the closed curve,
clockwise around the closed curve,
the transported vector rotates in the opposite direction.
All right?
Here's the way you can
think about negatively curved surfaces.
In particular,
we made a positive curvature singularity
by cutting out the surface,
by cutting out a piece of the pie,
right?
I'm going to show you
how to make a negative curve,
and you go home and do this
and prove to yourself that what happens
is what I say happens.
We're going to make a cut.
And now instead of cutting out a wedge,
we're going to add something,
we're going to add an extra angular piece in,
an angle excess instead of an angle deficit.
Here's the way we do it.
All right,
here's our angle excess.
Right here,
I take my surface,
I open it up.
Notice it gets kind of floppy.
And stick the angle excess in.
And now tape it along
here and tape it along here.
And I have now,
instead of an angle,
can everybody see it?
Instead of an angle,
a piece of angle missing,
it has more than 360 degrees going,
instead of having less than 360 degrees going around,
it has more than 360 degrees going around.
Doing that makes a piece of negative curvature.
If you transport a vector around that,
you'll find out that if you transport
counterclockwise,
the vector rotates clockwise.
That's a surface of negative curvature.
So negative curvature and positive curvature both exist.
Negative curvature is a little bit less intuitive
because it doesn't involve things like spheres,
but rather things like,
I don't know how to describe them,
I'm not sure.
Hmm?
Say it again.
It is the inner surface of the torus.
Absolutely.
That's what I was going to come to.
Right.
It is the inner surface of the torus.
So the outer surface of the torus,
by the outer surface,
I don't,
what I mean,
I don't mean looking at the torus from the,
from the dough,
I mean the outer surface is the part around here.
The inner surface of the torus is that part.
The inner surface is more saddle-shaped.
The outer surface is more sphere-shaped.
You'll discover that the outer parts of the torus,
in other words,
the boundary out here,
is positively curved.
The portion in,
near the whole layer is negatively curved.
And the total integrated curvature,
if I integrate the curvature,
what does integrating the curvature do?
Forget it,
not important right now,
but there's as much positive curvature
as there is negative curvature on the torus.
On the other hand,
the sphere is,
everywhere is positively curved.
Okay,
so we now have the basic idea
in two dimensions,
of what curvature means.
And the most important thing for us
is that curvature
is an obstruction
to flattening the geometry.
Flattening the geometry by definition means
finding coordinates
where the metric is just delta mu nu.
All of these words are exactly the same
in space-time.
They're exactly the same.
There are curves in space-time.
You can take closed curves in space-time.
You can transport vectors
by exactly the same rules,
the rule being right here.
The Christoffel symbols
are constructed from the metric
in exactly the same way.
And the notion of curvature,
space-time curvature,
is the same as the notion
of just spatial curvature.
It is harder to visualize.
It's much harder to visualize
the geometry of space-time
than it is of just ordinary space.
We weren't equipped
with the mental architecture
to visualize space-time.
But the rules are essentially the same.
So a curved space-time is one,
if you like,
which when you go around closed paths
trying to keep a four vector,
a space-time vector parallel to itself,
you won't be able to
because there's curvature in the middle.
We're going to define next time
the curvature tensor.
But the basic idea of general relativity
is first of all that space-time is curved.
And second of all,
the curvature is due to masses,
is due to mass
or more generally energy and momentum.
E equals mc squared,
of course,
is the,
it goes to the mass.
And the equality or the equivalence
between energy and mass,
energy and mass are the same thing
except for a conversion factor,
the square root of,
the square of the speed of light.
Energy and momentum
will find out,
come together.
But energy and momentum
are the things which create curvature.
That's the analog of the statement
that mass creates gravitational force
and gravitational field
that cannot be removed
by a coordinate transformation.
Gravitational field that cannot be removed
by going to an accelerated frame of reference.
That's the presence of a chunk of mass.
It's an obstruction
to getting rid of the gravitational field.
Energy and momentum create curvature.
Curvature is also an obstruction
to getting rid of the curvature of space-time.
So that's the basic theme.
We're going to write down,
if not derive,
the equations relating the curvature
of space-time
to the presence of energy and momentum.
And then we're going to talk about
how particles move
in a curved space-time.
And the answer is they move along geodesics.
So what we're going to do,
here's the goal.
Start with some energy and momentum.
Some mass.
Calculate the curvature around it.
And then that gives us a set of geodesics.
And what we're going to want to see
is that those geodesics behave
almost identically to the way
Newtonian trajectories move
around a mass in Newtonian gravity.
Of course,
we're going to do a little better than that.
We're going to see that
there are some corrections to Newton.
But that's the goal.
Curvature is like gravitational field.
It's created by mass.
Solutions of F equals mA
are essentially just geodesics in space-time.
That's the goal for the next couple of lectures.
And then we'll try to study some particular examples.
In particular,
the Schwarzschild geometry
of a chunk of mass.
And I think,
I'm not sure where we'll go after that.
Any questions?
Absolutely none.
I have a question.
A space embedded in another space,
they said the upper space,
the higher space is flat.
Then is parallel transport
equivalent to keeping parallel
in the higher dimensional space?
Well,
okay.
So,
let's see.
no,
not,
no.
Parallel transport is not defined
by staying parallel in the embedding space.
But we would lie outside it.
Then we'd just project it in there.
Yeah.
Let's put it this way.
Take three-dimensional space
and now make a curved surface in it.
If the rule for parallel transport
was to keep the vector parallel
in the three-dimensional sense,
then when you went around any curve,
there would be no such thing as curvature.
No,
no.
You keep the parallel a little ways
and it's objective.
好
OK,
when you parallelly transport a vector
in the two-dimensional space,
you
keep it in the two-dimensional space.
It's always pointing in the two-dimensional space.
Yeah,
you can probably think of it.
You can understand it better if you
think that for it to be a vector,
it has to be just two numbers.
It cannot be three numbers.
That's right.
But let me give you
another way to think about it.
As we said,
we can always find coordinates
at a point which are delta mn.
All right,
that means that the coordinate axes locally
at that point are perpendicular to each other.
And in fact,
they're as straight as possible.
Parallel transport from one point
to another point in the vicinity of this point
where we've made the metric look like this
is just keeping the components of the metric
I'm sorry,
the components of the vector
fixed,
transporting it as if space was flat.
The problem is that when you go over to here,
the original coordinates here for which the metric was just
delta mn are no longer the coordinates at this point
where the metric is delta mn.
There's a little bit of shift of coordinates
to keep them to the new coordinate system.
And so,
well,
it's not that simple.
OK.
It's a little more complicated.
Anyway,
familiarize yourself as much as you can
with the idea of parallel transport.
And the next time,
we will define the curvature tensor.
And again,
the curvature tensor is always
related to what happens to a vector when you parallelly
transport it around a curve.
It's more complicated in three dimensions.
Why?
Because.
Because the curve could be oriented along any plane.
And furthermore,
the rotation of the vector
could be a rotation about any axis.
In four dimensions,
it's even more complicated.
But the basic idea is
go around a little curve oriented
along some plane and see
how the vector rotates in space
or in spacetime.
And that rotation of the vector,
when
you go around a little circle,
that is what defines curvature.
That's the notion of Riemannian curvature.
And it's the notion that's at the heart
of the gravitational field.
OK.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford
University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.