This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Tonight we want to start,
not start,
but
we want to continue with the concept of curvature.
I explained to you the idea of curvature for surfaces.
Surfaces mean two-dimensional surfaces.
Let me just review the basic concept.
If you have a curved surface,
you still have a concept of parallel transport.
You have a concept of going as straight as possible,
not deviating to the left,
not deviating to the right.
But nevertheless,
the effect of the curvature will have an effect on
the direction of that curvature.
What does curvity meaning?
Curvity means when the surfaces are left and right.
This is just an example
of the Yeah think about here.
So yeah,
yeah.
In that here.
The curvature moment is bike-shape.
This is the curvature when the surfaces separate off.
Time is number two,
eye- Google that.
How about the curve of the
surface and the curvature of the surface?
the curvature of a curve.
Incidentally,
a straight line is a special case of a curve.
It's a curve which is uncurved.
Yes,
if you go around in a little closed path,
and you take a vector,
start it somewhere on that closed path.
Now,
a vector means a vector
that points in the direction in the surface.
Roughly speaking,
you can think of it as pointing
in the direction of the tangent plane of the surface.
So it points in the direction of the
surface.
That unfortunately looks like it's
pointing out of the surface,
but I can't figure
out any way to draw a vector that it
won't look like it's pointing out of the surface.
So you keep in mind it's in the surface.
And then we transport it parallelly to itself around
the closed curve.
If the region inside the closed curve is flat,
then the vector is in the direction
of the tangent plane of the surface.
The vector will come back to itself.
If there's some curvature in there,
then typically it will undergo some rotation by some angle.
That angle,
let's call it theta.
Now,
there are two senses of angle here
that we have to keep track of.
Question?
When you're talking about these curves,
do you mean they have to be small curves?
do you mean they have to be small?
I have in mind small curves,
but...
If they're low curves...
Yeah,
I'm speaking about small curves.
We're going to be taking
the limit of very small curves,
infinitesimal curves,
curves which contain infinitesimally small area.
So we can concentrate
on curves which are small by comparison
with the radius of the whole thing.
Okay,
and that's the
situation we're interested in.
Curvature is a local thing.
In other words,
you can monitor the curvature by looking in some
small little region and not going around whole big...
You don't have to walk around the entire circumference
of the Earth to discover that the Earth is curved.
If you had sufficient accuracy,
you could walk around a small little area and
discover that the surface of the Earth is curved.
Yeah.
In this example,
you have a surface that's a space
that's embedded in a higher dimensional space.
Yes,
but I want you to forget that.
I want you not to think about that.
I want you...
Yeah,
there's no...
The problem...
This is a problem of the architecture of our brains.
We simply don't have the architecture to be able
to envision surfaces and spaces out of three dimensions.
So there's no way I can draw them.
Well,
what connection do you have with
one dimension on top of two dimensions?
So that's what he was saying,
right?
I don't know.
Well,
this one is two dimensional,
and the other one is three dimensional.
Mm-hmm.
The curvature is actually curved.
No,
no,
no.
The thing is,
we want to...
That's exactly what we don't want to analyze.
We don't want to analyze the curvature that's due to the
fact that it's embedded in a curved way in the space.
We want to ask the question,
supposing a little bug lived on the surface.
That bug can only receive light...
Light from inside the surface,
can only see inside the surface,
has no capacity to probe in the direction perpendicular,
and can do all sorts
of geometrical experiments involving little rulers,
but rulers which are attached to the surface,
parallel to the surface,
little protractors which also lie in the surface,
and can do geometry on the surface without ever
pointing their ruler or their protractor out of the surface.
That's the term that comes up is intrinsic.
In other words,
properties which are intrinsic to the surface.
The opposite are things that has to do
with the way that it's embedded in space,
and those are called extrinsic.
Intrinsic and extrinsic.
We are now interested only in
the intrinsic properties that this very,
very small bug would discover.
Right.
By doing experimental geometry on the surface with
tools that can only lie in the surface.
Okay.
All right.
So we're talking about the
intrinsic curvature of the surface,
and the idea of parallel transport is an intrinsic idea.
If that little bug had wheels,
think of a little bug with little wheels.
Little dumbbell shaped affair.
Two wheels that could roll on the surface.
If the wheels had exactly the same size,
and they couldn't,
and of course I'm assuming that
they cannot rotate relative to each other,
then if I rolled it along the tabletop here,
it would describe a straight arc,
right?
Okay.
If I rolled it across the surface of a sphere,
it would move as straight as possible along the surface.
Along the surface of a geodesic,
in that case a great circle.
So this is an experiment.
Well,
I suppose you'd say the wheels stick
out of the surface a little bit,
but we could make the whole thing smaller and
smaller until the dumbbell bug here was infinitely small,
and allow him to sweep
out geodesics across the surface here.
So the idea of a geodesic,
and not only the idea of a geodesic,
but the idea of parallel transport
and the idea of covariant derivative,
are ideas which are intrinsic.
Intrinsic,
that bug could move around.
Of course,
we're really thinking about ourselves
as bugs in three dimensions,
and we're trying to disconnect
the intrinsic properties of three-dimensional space
from the possibility that it might
perhaps be embedded in some fourth dimension,
or something like that.
Well,
we wouldn't want to use rollers,
but we could use gyroscopes.
And gyroscopes are things which only
point in our own three-dimensional space.
They don't point out into any hypothetical fourth dimension.
And so exploring space with gyroscopes,
and rulers,
and so forth,
would be exploring the
intrinsic geometry of three-dimensional space.
In any case,
one of the things we can do,
with gyroscopes,
is we can define parallel transport.
A gyroscope will naturally move in
a way which moves parallel to itself,
and it does define parallel transport,
physically.
It has the same properties as
the parallel transport that we describe mathematically.
In any case,
we can proceed to parallelly transport that vector
from one point to another,
and,
in fact,
around in a closed curve.
When it goes around in a closed curve,
it will not necessarily come back to the same configuration.
What'll happen to it is it will rotate in general.
Parallel transport does not change the length of vectors.
It changes only their orientation.
It does not change their length.
And so,
at most,
what can happen to a vector
is when it comes around,
it gets rotated by some angle.
Okay.
Now,
there are two senses of rotation
that we have to keep track of.
Senses,
I mean now senses in the sense of sign,
S-I-G-N.
First of all,
there's the direction that we go around the loop.
We can go around one way or the other way.
Depending on which way we go around,
the vector will either shift in
one direction or in the other direction.
That's one sense of angle that
we have to keep track of,
which direction we circumnavigated around.
We took our vector and we went around,
let's say,
let's say counterclockwise.
The other angle that we need to keep track of
is the amount that the angle deviates.
So,
for example,
if we go around counterclockwise
and the vector,
as it's transported around the curve,
gets deflected in the counterclockwise direction,
counterclockwise excursion
produces counterclockwise rotation,
then we say that the curvature is positive.
If counterclockwise excursion produces
clockwise rotation of the vector,
we say the curvature is negative.
Whatever the curvature is,
it's a single function
on the space,
and it's simply defined by
going around with your little probe,
measuring,
let's by definition say we go around counterclockwise,
we measure the angle.
For small,
for very,
very small curves here,
the angle will be small.
So let's just call it d theta,
the small change in the angle
when we go around the closed loop.
And if we divide that,
by the small area contained in that closed loop,
then we get the curvature.
The curvature is the limit of the deflection angle,
let's call it the deflection angle,
divided by the area as the area goes to zero.
Because as the area goes to zero,
the deflection also goes to zero.
That's called the curvature scalar,
the curvature.
And there's a curvature at every point on the surface.
It can be positive,
it can be negative.
It's positive on surfaces that are spherical-like,
sphere-like.
It is negative on surfaces that are saddle-like,
saddle-shaped-like.
Now the situation is clearly
more complicated in higher dimensions.
Let's first take three dimensions.
In three dimensions,
we can proceed around small closed loops,
but we have to orient the surface somehow.
For example,
in three dimensions,
I can go around a little closed curve here,
I can go around in this direction.
I need to describe an axis.
The axis is not the
axis of rotation of the vector,
the axis is the axis around the vector.
The axis is the axis
around which my little bug travels
doing his experiment.
So there's one axis in the problem,
which we can just say is the axis
around which the excursion takes place.
So our little bug,
or our little gyroscopic setup,
in this case,
is transported around an axis.
Now,
in three dimensions,
you can use the concept of an axis
to describe a plane.
It's just the axis perpendicular to the plane.
In higher dimensions,
or in lower dimensions,
it's not useful to think of a little closed curve
or a surface as having to do with an axis.
It always has to do with two directions of space.
You describe a plane by picking two directions of space.
A direction over here,
a direction over here,
two perpendicular directions of space.
Define a plane.
It doesn't matter if you're in five dimensions,
ten dimensions,
twenty dimensions.
Two directions define a plane,
and then you can go around in that plane.
So you characterize the excursion that you go around
by giving two axes.
As I said,
in three dimensions,
you can replace the two axes by a third axis,
which is perpendicular to it.
But that's special to three dimensions.
All right,
so that's one orientation
that you have to keep track of.
The other orientation,
the other thing you have to keep track of,
is a vector taken around here
will typically rotate.
But it won't necessarily rotate
about the same axis.
If I take my apparatus,
the gyroscope,
my gyroscopic...
I can take three gyroscopes all hooked together
to define a coordinate system.
There.
And I move them around,
and I see how they move,
how they parallelly transport,
and I take them around an axis,
around the axis of my arm.
If this curvature in the region of my arm,
when I go around to the other side,
the axes will have rotated.
What axis will these rotate about?
Not necessarily the axis
that you transported them about.
For example,
this might be the z-axis.
I might take my little device here
around the z-axis
and discover that it rotated
around the x-axis.
So in diagnosing what's going on in space,
an understanding of the z-axis
and understanding the curvature,
there are two and three dimensions.
There are two axes to keep track of.
In general,
there are two planes to keep track of.
The two planes to keep track of are...
One of them is the little plane
that you move around in.
The other one is the plane
in which the vectors rotate.
Rotation within a plane.
All right,
so I'm going to write down now
the general formula
for...
Yeah?
When we take this vector
and we track around the surface
and we come up with an angle of stiffness,
that means that the concept of parallelism,
which goes along with the flag,
is deviated from the change
that it's going to play.
Right.
You discover that when you try to...
So we run into the same problem
with the concept of perpendicularity.
No.
In principle,
you could imagine
that that does happen.
That does not happen in Riemannian geometry.
In Riemannian geometry,
you can imagine more generalized kinds of geometries,
affine geometries,
other kinds of geometries.
The notion of perpendicularity
is an invariant notion
in a Riemannian geometry.
Things which are perpendicular stay perpendicular.
All right,
that's an important point.
That parallel transport in Riemannian geometry
and in general relativity
is defined in a way
that vectors,
when you transport them,
if they are perpendicular to begin with,
they stay perpendicular.
So perpendicularity is an invariant concept.
Okay,
so let's write down the general formula.
Supposing...
Now,
I'm not even going to tell you
how many dimensions we're in
because it doesn't matter.
It could be 2,
3,
4,
100,000.
It doesn't matter.
Pick two axes.
Let's see what I called them.
I called one of them
x nu
and the other one x mu.
And now what we're going to do...
And they're two different axes.
Mu and nu are intended to be different here.
It could be x and y.
It could be x and t.
It could be whatever you like.
We're going to go around in a small rectangle
or as close to a rectangle as we can build.
In other words,
we're going to have a small dx mu,
and a small dx nu.
Okay?
That characterizes the excursion
in the x mu,
x nu plane.
We go a little bit along x mu,
and we go a little bit along x nu,
then we come back along x mu,
and then we come back by
the same amount along x nu.
That creates a little bit of area,
and that area will be proportional
to the product
of dx mu times dx nu.
It won't be exactly dx mu times dx nu,
because I haven't particularly said
that these two directions are perpendicular,
and I haven't told you what the metric is.
But whatever the metric is,
the area in here will be proportional
to dx times dx,
dx mu times dx nu.
The area will be proportional to that.
And so to begin with then,
we have two axes
and a little bit of area in there.
We carry a vector,
we start a vector at one end,
and we bring it around,
and we look at it,
what it's done.
Now,
what are the rules?
The rules are we do it by parallel transport,
which we've already defined.
We'll come back to that definition,
but it's the definition involving
the Christoffel symbols.
So we parallel transport that vector
around the curve,
okay?
Bringing it back to itself.
Parallel transporting it means that,
that the derivative along,
that the covariant derivative along the curve is zero.
So you would think it must come back to itself
if the covariant derivative is zero.
But the thing is,
the covariant derivative
is not the ordinary derivative.
And so if we start with a vector v,
and we transport it around the closed curve,
there will be a change.
And that change,
let's write down a very general one,
a general formula.
It will be proportional to dx mu and dx nu.
Why?
Because we expect it to be proportional
to the area that we've enclosed.
So it will be proportional
to dx mu and dx nu.
You want to use mu on the superscript for v?
You already used mu.
Oh,
you're right.
We shouldn't.
dx nu,
dx,
same amount.
Good point.
We shouldn't.
So it's going to have dx nu and dx sigma,
the x nu and,
alright.
It is going to also involve
the vector that we started with.
It's basically going to be a rotation of the vector.
The change in the vector will be proportional
to the vector that you start with.
If you start with a vector which is zero,
it will stay zero.
If you start with a vector which is very long,
it will stay very long because its length is preserved.
And so we expect that the change in the vector
when it goes around the closed curve
will involve the vector itself.
Let's give it an index v tau.
And the rest has to be some object
which defines the curvature.
It's the curvature tensor.
So let's see if we can build a formula.
We have three indices upstairs,
one index on the right-hand side,
one index upstairs on the left-hand side here.
The only thing we can have here is some tensor
which has an upper index
mu to match this index here,
a nu and a sigma and a tau.
So it's a very simple formula.
All right,
now you can work this formula,
you can work this out yourself.
All you have to do is use the formula
for covariant differentiation,
say that along the first curve...
Let me write it down.
Do you remember what the formula
for covariant differentiation along a curve is?
Let's just write it down.
It's something like dv mu by ds,
s is length along the curve,
plus gamma mu,
I don't know,
alpha beta
times the...
v alpha times the tangent vector,
dx beta by ds.
That was the covariant derivative of the vector v
along the curve parameterized by s.
If I want to set that equal to zero,
then I have an immediate formula
for how v should change along s,
how the components of v should change along s.
I don't need the ds here.
The ds is not playing any role.
Just divide through by it.
What it says is that
the change in the vector v
going from here to here
is equal to minus gamma alpha beta mu
v alpha dx beta.
That's the formula for the change of the vector
in going from here to here.
Now what do you think the
change in the vector would be
if I parallelly transported it to here
and then parallelly transported it right back?
The answer would be zero,
no change.
Parallel transport is not so weird
that when you transport a thing
and then transport it back...
Yeah,
it doesn't do anything.
You need some area enclosed
in order to get an answer.
All right,
so if you transport from here to here,
you get that.
When you transport back,
you're going to get something entirely similar
except along a neighboring curve.
It's not going to be exactly the same.
Why not?
Because the Christoffel symbol over here
and over here are not exactly the same.
They vary a little bit.
Also,
when you go from here to here,
the change in v does not cancel the change
when you come back along this arc of the...
of the rectangle.
Why?
Because the Christoffel symbol varies from here to here.
Okay?
So because the Christoffel symbol varies
as you move around,
by the time you get back,
the changes,
which is this v mu,
the change in v mu is not equal to zero.
In fact,
it's clear that what's going to come into it
are derivatives,
derivatives of gamma.
It's the derivatives of gamma,
the fact that gammas vary from place to place,
that means that you don't cancel out
deviations along one arc
by deviations along the arc coming back.
Okay?
Here's the formula.
I haven't told you what r is yet.
I haven't told you what r is yet,
but you can see that,
in order to get something,
you'll have to have a shift along one axis
and a shift along the other axis.
So it has to have a dx times another dx.
That's clear.
You have to enclose a little area.
The change in v will
always be proportional to v itself.
So even when you go around the closed loop,
it's going to be proportional to v itself.
And what would you expect
r to be made out of?
From what I just told you.
The derivatives of the Christoffel symbol.
The derivatives of the Christoffel symbol
are going to enter into r.
This is a tensor equation.
dx,
v,
delta v on this side here are,
these are all,
this is the difference of
two vectors at the same point.
Those,
delta v,
difference of two vectors,
vector and a slightly shifted vector,
this is a tensor equation,
and this is the curvature tensor.
It's the Riemann curvature tensor.
And what it tells you,
as I said,
is per unit area,
it tells you how a vector changes
when it goes around in a closed loop.
In fact,
it rotates.
The vector rotates.
But even if it did something more complicated than rotating,
this would be the formula that you would use.
And that's what the curvature tensor is all about.
It tells you how vectors fail
to return to their original direction
when you parallelly transport them around a closed curve.
Indication that this curvature somewhere is inside.
Okay,
now,
notice that two of these indices here,
nu and sigma,
have to do with the
plane that you moved around in.
The x mu and the x sigma.
The other two indices,
tau and mu,
have to do,
they contract,
or they have to do
with the indices of v itself.
Tau over here goes with tau over here,
mu over here goes with mu over here.
So two of the indices have
to do with the directions in space
that you go around,
and the other two indices
have to do with the vector themselves
and tell you how it changes.
Alright?
So that's the pattern.
That's the structure of
the curvature tensor.
Not the structure of it,
but that's what a curvature tensor is.
It's the general definition of the curvature tensor.
And as I said,
it always has four indices.
Two of them telling you about
the plane that you're moving around in,
and two of them telling you about
the plane of rotation of the vector.
That's why it has four indices.
Two to tell you what
the directions you're moving around in,
and two to tell you the plane of rotation,
if you like,
that the vector undergoes.
Those are the four indices of the Riemann tensor.
This is the Riemann tensor,
and I'm now going to write down,
it's too tedious to derive this,
I've given you the principle,
you know how to parallelly transport
a vector around a closed curve.
You could make your closed curve be a little rectangle,
you could carry out the process,
and find R.
And I advise it,
it's a nice exercise,
it's not too hard to do.
I'm just going to write the answer down,
because it's more than,
it's more than is appropriate to
do on a blackboard in ten minutes.
But the answer is not hard.
I memorized it years ago,
and,
no,
I could write this in my sleep,
this,
okay,
so let me write down the answer for you.
The Riemann tensor with index rho upstairs,
notice that the way I've defined it,
it has one index upstairs and three indices downstairs.
Of course,
I'm going to write it down,
and of course you can change that.
You can lower an index of a tensor
by contracting it with a metric.
But the way that it's been defined here,
from the definition here,
it has one index upstairs and three indices downstairs,
and for some reason I have used different letters,
but it doesn't matter.
Sigma,
mu,
nu.
Same tensor,
except I've rearranged the indices,
and I'm going to write down what they are.
They're in terms of derivatives of the Christoffel symbols
and also products of the Christoffel symbols.
D mu.
Then there are two terms which are just products
of the mu,
lambda,
rho,
gamma,
nu,
sigma,
lambda,
minus gamma,
nu,
lambda,
rho,
gamma,
mu,
sigma,
lambda.
Okay.
That's the Riemann tensor,
and as I said,
it involves derivatives of the Christoffel symbols,
and it's not hard to work out.
That's it.
Any questions up until now?
And,
um,
hmm?
How do you know it's a tensor?
You know it's a tensor,
you actually know it's a tensor from its definition.
Um,
so,
uh,
you know it,
well,
how do you know it's a tensor?
Um,
the left-hand side,
first of all,
how do you,
how do I know that
the left-hand side is a vector?
It's a difference of two vectors,
and it's kind of like a derivative of a vector,
isn't it?
But a derivative of a vector is not a tensor.
The covariant derivative is a tensor.
But that's because the coordinates
may vary from place to place.
If we're comparing two vectors at the same place,
at the same origin,
then the difference of vectors is a vector.
It's only when we're trying
to compare vectors at different places
that the difference between two vectors,
or the derivative of a vector with respect to position,
may not be a true vector itself.
When we're comparing vectors at the same point,
in other words,
subtracting two vectors,
each of which refers to
exactly the same point in space,
that is a vector.
Okay?
So the left-hand side is a vector,
transforms as a vector.
dx sigma,
dx nu are vectors.
V by definition,
by assumption,
V is a vector.
And if an equation like
this is true for any vector,
the assumption here is
that this equation is true for
any vector that you start with,
that when you take it around the closed curve,
that this is what you get.
If you have a vector equation such as this,
this is a theorem.
If you have a vector equation like this,
which is true for every possible
vector that you can start with,
then R must be a tensor.
So there's a theorem involved
here that R is a tensor.
It's not obvious from here.
Is the second half of
that some kind of a commutator?
Yes.
Indeed it is.
If you think of,
alright.
Alright,
so let me tell you what it is.
It is some kind of commutator.
Think of these indices as being matrix indices
with a parameter nu over here.
Alright.
So,
I'm going to write this.
Alright,
then you could,
here's a matrix,
here's another matrix.
Let's see,
do I have this right?
Nu,
wait a minute,
did I write this correct?
Rho,
yeah,
yeah.
You can see here that there's a product of matrices.
The index that's summed over is lambda here.
Alright.
And so you could think of
this as the product of two matrices,
one that you could call gamma mu,
and the other that you could call gamma nu.
There's hidden indices in here
because each one is a matrix.
This one is exactly the same,
except it's minus gamma nu times gamma mu.
So this is in fact a commutator of two matrices.
Alright.
Uh,
and in fact,
the whole thing is also a commutator,
but that's a little more complicated.
It's a commutator of two covariant derivatives.
Is it obvious that this does
not depend on the directions you took
when you started with the x
and the x nu and x mu?
Well,
it does depend,
but it only depends through the
product the x times the x.
We're imagining two different vectors here.
We shouldn't call this dx.
We should be more careful here.
Um,
these are just two different displacements.
dx with an index nu
and dx with an index mu.
Two different displacements.
One over here,
one over here.
Um,
we might have called one of them delta.
We might have called,
in fact,
we might have done it this way.
We might have defined the displacement over here,
which is delta x,
and another displacement over here,
which is dx.
Then we would have put
one delta x and one dx.
I'm not sure if that helped.
Uh,
but it's proportional to the
product of the two displacements.
Aren't those both summed over?
Hm?
Those are both summed over.
Yeah.
So they'll take on all values.
They're both summed over.
Question?
Yeah.
Can you illustrate what it means to keep a vector
parallel to itself when you move in a curved surface,
like on the surface of the Earth,
I have a vector that's parallel to the surface.
How do I know that
I'm keeping it parallel to itself
as I move along the surface of the Earth?
Well,
as I said,
you,
along the surface of the Earth,
it's easy.
You just drive straight ahead.
You aim your steering wheel straight ahead.
You don't care,
and you don't allow yourself to turn it.
You don't care whether there are
bumps or curves in the surface.
You don't care whether you're going over mountains,
through mountain passes.
You keep that steering wheel dead straight ahead.
And that is the definition of a geodesic.
In other words,
locally,
in small little patches,
you go perfectly straight ahead.
Now,
the technical definition is you find coordinates locally
which are as flat as possible,
which means that all of the first and second derivatives
of the metric are equal to zero,
and then you can go straight ahead.
And in those coordinates,
the vector is constant.
The derivative of the vector is equal to zero.
So the technical definition is in terms of coordinates
which are chosen to be as close as possible
to Cartesian coordinates,
first and second derivatives of
the metric all equal to zero.
In that case,
the only variation of the vector
will come from the variation of the vector
and not the variation of the coordinate frame
if the first and second derivatives
are all equal to zero.
Okay,
look.
So if I move along a geodesic
and the vector moves with the curvature of the geodesic,
that's parallel?
If you have a geodesic
and you have a vector
which is pointing along the geodesic,
it will stay pointing along the geodesic.
If you have a vector
which is perpendicular to the geodesic,
it will stay perpendicular to it.
All right?
Now,
that's not enough.
In two dimensions,
that's enough
to tell you exactly what covariant differentiation means.
In three dimensions,
it's not,
in particular along the geodesic.
The problem in three direct dimensions
is you might have a geodesic.
Anything which is along the geodesic
will stay along the geodesic.
But something which is perpendicular to it,
it's not enough to know that
it stays perpendicular to the geodesic
because it could spiral around it.
So it's a little more complicated.
So,
uh,
to,
um...
What you can do in higher dimensions
is you can do the following trick.
You can take two neighboring geodesics,
take a point,
and draw a geodesic through it.
Ah,
let's first think about it in flat space.
If I have a geodesic
pointing through my shoulder here,
there's another geodesic that
also points through my shoulder.
There's many of them,
of course.
But take another one which is
almost parallel to the starting one,
just slightly shifted at a different angle.
All right?
Those two define a plane.
Now,
if I transport a vector along the geodesic,
not only will it stay perpendicular,
not only will it stay at
the same angle to the geodesic,
but it will stay at
the same angle to that plane
which is defined by two neighboring geodesics.
Is that clear in flat space?
Yeah.
Okay,
that almost becomes a
definition in higher dimensional space.
You take...
It could be used as a definition.
You take another neighboring geodesic.
Now,
neighboring means infinitesimal angle relative to it.
They define a plane in here.
And...
As you transport along one of the geodesics,
the angle relative to that plane,
something which is perpendicular to that plane
stays perpendicular to the plane.
So you can do better in higher dimensions
with a family of geodesics,
a family of geodesics which
all pass through the same point.
But,
of course,
you don't want to take geodesics at wild angles.
You want to take almost parallel.
That gives you a good definition.
That gives you another definition of parallel transport.
Okay.
But it does come down to the same thing.
In a frame of reference which
is locally as flat as possible,
it means that the vector has no derivatives
in that frame at that point.
All right.
Now,
this is,
as I said,
this is the definition,
the geometric definition of curvature.
It's a complicated definition.
The concept may not be so complicated,
but the actual mathematical formula for it is,
as you can see,
rather complicated.
How many components does the curvature tensor have?
Let's say in four-dimensional space,
space-time.
Well,
yeah,
four times four times four times four.
It's not that bad.
It's not that bad because there's a lot of symmetry.
There are a lot of
redundancies and a lot of symmetry
that you can read off this formula.
You can read them off this formula.
To see the symmetries best,
it's best to lower this index.
I can lower this index the usual way.
Supposing I want to define r lambda sigma mu nu,
I just multiply by g lambda rho
times r rho sigma mu nu.
All right.
You can lower and raise indices using the metric,
and so there's nothing special
about one index being raised here.
I can lower them back down
so that they're all lower indices.
It's still called the Riemann tensor.
It's the Riemann tensor with all covariant indices.
It's in this form that the symmetries are simplest,
the symmetries of this object.
All right.
So if you work them out using the definitions
of the Christoffel symbol,
and it's not hard,
but it's tedious.
It's a little bit tedious.
There are simple ways to do it,
but they all involve a degree of sophisticated notation,
which would take us beyond what
I want to do in this quarter.
Forms and other fancy tricks.
Question.
Yeah.
For the d theta dA equals r,
is theta dependent on the direction
of the clock?
Yeah.
Theta is dependent on the direction you go around.
If you go around one direction,
you get theta being plus.
If you go around the other direction,
you get theta being minus.
Yeah.
The sine switch.
And it's the relationship between the signs
of going around and angle rotating
which tells you whether the curvature
is positive or negative.
All right.
And all the components of this curvature tensor
can be either positive or negative.
Some of them can be zero.
Some can be zero and others not be zero.
That's quite possible.
OK.
So let me tell you what the symmetries are.
Let's see.
First of all,
let's remember it's the two,
let's see,
the two middle indices here,
which have to do with the
plane that you go around in.
The two middle indices parameterize the plane
that you move around in,
the new sigma plane.
The mu and tau indices,
if I'm not mistaken,
let's see,
do I have this right?
Let me just check it.
Yeah.
The two middle indices have to do with the plane
that you go around in,
and the two outer indices
have to do with the directions of the vector itself,
how it rotates.
OK.
So same is true here.
These two indices have to do with the plane
that you move around in.
The two inner indices.
All right.
I'm going to write down the symmetries.
I hope I have them right.
OK.
First of all,
it's anti-symmetric with
respect to interchange of alpha and beta.
All right.
That just says if you interchange alpha and beta,
it's anti-symmetric.
It's also anti-symmetric if you interchange gamma and delta.
So it's also equal to minus r alpha beta,
the original alpha beta,
delta gamma.
Anti-symmetric with respect to these two
and anti-symmetric with respect to those two.
That's one thing.
And the only other important thing is that it's symmetric.
Yeah.
It's symmetric with respect to taking these indices
and these indices and changing them,
interchanging them like so.
In other words,
this is equal to r,
gamma delta,
beta alpha.
No,
gamma delta alpha beta.
Now these are not going to play
any big role in what we do.
I'm just putting them down for completeness.
The point is that there are a lot of relationships
between the components.
There aren't as many as it looks.
There's a lot of symmetries between them,
just following from the definition in terms of the
Christoffel symbols and in terms of the symmetries
of the vector.
The Christoffel symbols,
I believe there are 24 independent ones.
That's a lot.
So when you start doing calculations in general relativity,
it's awful.
No,
no,
they are unpleasant.
Is it the sign of the permutation in S4?
What's that?
Is the sign the same as whatever the permutation is
in the symmetric group?
No,
I don't think so.
So if you interchange beta and gamma,
it doesn't become negative?
Well,
let's see.
I've given you all of the symmetries.
Now we would have to,
if you interchange gamma and beta,
I don't think so.
I don't think there's any special symmetry.
Let's see.
I'll tell you how many
components there are in two dimensions.
Let's make a table,
and then you can tell me
whether it's anything special.
Dimension two,
dimension three,
and dimension four.
I have no idea what the answer is.
In dimension five,
I would have to work it out.
I can work it out.
But in dimension two,
there is one component.
In dimension three,
there are three components.
And in dimension four,
there are 24 components.
Does that strike any bell?
They are equal to factorial.
No,
they're not.
Three is not factorial.
No,
no.
When you switch the rotation around the loop,
you don't get a minus sign,
don't you?
When you do what?
When you go around the loop,
the loop in the opposite direction from the wave.
We get a minus sign.
That's the same as interchanging gamma.
Yeah.
Well,
those are the middle two,
right?
Oh,
God.
I hope I don't have babies.
You know what?
I think I do.
Those are the middle two.
Let me just look at it for a minute.
Row is up here.
No,
I definitely have something inconsistent here.
It's...
Yeah.
I think it's a partial.
And those have to do with
the two directions that you move in.
Mu and nu,
all right.
These two terms here have to do with the fact
that the Christoffel symbols vary along the mu and nu direction.
So these two,
mu and nu,
those are the two that have
to do with the directions here.
I think I made a mistake.
This does not look right to me.
Let me correct it.
Yeah.
I think this should be r
sigma nu mu tau v tau.
I think I have a misprint typo in my
notes because you are right that this is clear.
Yeah.
It's quite clear.
This is antisymmetric under interchange of mu and nu.
If I interchange mu and nu here,
these two will be the
same except for a minus sign.
So it's antisymmetric under mu nu interchange.
Is that what I said?
Yeah.
This is antisymmetric under mu nu interchange.
Antisymmetric.
It's also antisymmetric under lambda sigma interchange.
That I know for a fact.
And it's symmetric with respect to
interchanging lambda sigma and mu nu.
So do I have it right?
I think that's what I wrote here.
I think that's consistent with this,
isn't it?
Let's see.
Antisymmetric with respect to these two,
yes.
And symmetric with respect to moving them in pairs.
That's correct.
And somehow what I wrote down here originally was incorrect.
So let me correct it.
It should be R with a mu.
Let's call it sigma.
Yeah.
R.
I think I have it right now because delta x,
delta x tau.
Yeah.
No.
This is too distant.
Overall at all.
It's totally equivalent to sophisticated in inertia.
Does that make sense to you?
Yeah.
But I don't think we'll do it.
Direct melanon?
Exactly.
Parallel.
So there's one number,
is that the radius of the Earth?
Yep.
The numerical curvature is the inverse
square of the radius of the Earth.
The smaller the Earth is,
the larger the curvature.
You don't have to know where
the center of the Earth is.
In the case of a sphere,
you don't have to know where.
you don't have to know where,
and for a sphere,
the curvature is just equal to one divided
by the square of the radius of the sphere.
The smaller the sphere,
the bigger the sphere is,
the closer it is locally to being flat.
So the bigger the sphere,
the smaller the curvature.
The smaller the sphere,
the bigger the curvature.
Yeah?
How do you know that
the loop actually does not move?
Does it just close upon itself?
Is it just that the transform works out,
or is there some other way to check?
When you take your little loop that encloses the area,
how do you enforce the fact that
you do in fact close the loop?
Well,
you describe a little curve that comes back to itself.
I'm not sure how you...
You invent an x of sigma,
such that x of sigma
is equal to x of sigma.
x of sigma plus a little bit.
So you invent the function
for each one of the components.
You invent functions which come back
to themselves after a small excursion.
Well,
it just looked like when you picked those two directions,
a coordinates,
you could imagine that if you went,
you know,
followed the coordinates,
you wouldn't get back to where you started.
That's in fact true.
But what you're saying is...
All right,
so what you're saying is,
if I took a vector over here,
and then took another vector over here,
then parallelly transported this one...
Sorry,
parallelly transported this one up to here,
then it wouldn't quite close.
And that's true.
But the failure to close would be a second-order thing,
which would be quadratic in the dx's themselves.
And so the failure to close would be...
You would have to correct this
a little bit to make it close.
But the amount that you have to
correct it by wouldn't affect any of this.
It would be a small correction that
would also be proportional to the area.
Not there,
but it can.
Three.
其實會
What we're doing here is proving that some of the
internal angles do not fit into the periods of its curve.
Yeah.
Because it was 1990,
1990,
and it was for black.
It occurs to me,
the fact that this doesn't quite
close is connected with these terms.
It's connected with those terms.
Why are those terms there?
They're there just because the rectus...
Can you look at it,
therefore,
as a good part of transforming like a tensor,
and whatever that departure is basically tells you?
Yeah,
yeah,
you can think of it that way.
There is another,
for those who are mathematically minded,
I will give you a very,
very simple definition of the,
if you're a little bit...
mathematically minded,
then there's a...
the covariant derivative with respect to X mu
is defined how?
It's derivative with respect to X mu
plus gamma mu dot dot whatever.
And it acts as an operator,
as a differential operator on vectors.
It's a thing which acts on vectors.
It's a differential operator.
It contains derivatives,
and it contains multiplication by gammas,
which are also matrices and act as matrices.
The curvature is defined in terms of commutators
of covariant derivatives in different directions.
Covariant derivatives in different directions
don't commute with each other,
and the curvature is defined in terms of that.
Now,
that's too abstract.
Let's try to abstract a definition for our class.
For our class,
it's just geometrically the small change in a vector
when you go around a closed loop.
It contains the derivatives of the Christoffel symbols,
and it contains quadratic things in the Christoffel symbols.
And the reason that it contains Christoffel symbols
is because it's Christoffel symbols
that determine how parallel transport works.
How a thing gets parallelly
transported from one point to another
depends only on the Christoffel symbols.
So that's the only thing that it could,
could involve.
And derivatives of them.
Okay,
so that's a definition that's worth committing to memory
if you're interested in the subject.
And I honestly don't really know any
way to make it simpler than that.
I simply memorized it,
worked it out a few times for a sphere,
for a cone,
for a couple of geometries,
for a three-dimensional geometry,
and after a while you get familiar with it.
And it's a,
it's not as remote an idea.
But again,
what it has to do with
is intrinsic properties of the geometry
that are obstructions to its flatness,
and to diagnose it,
you go around in little closed paths,
and you see how things change under
a circumnavigation around a little closed path.
All right,
more definitions.
They give you these definitions now because they
come into general relativity in an important way.
The geometry of them is obscure.
They're not particularly easy
to understand the geometric quantities.
Uh,
There's something called the Ricci tensor.
The Ricci tensor doesn't have four components,
it has two components.
In that sense it's easier than the Riemann tensor,
but the only way to get the Riemann
tensor is to know the Ricci tensor first,
and it's gotten from the Ricci
tensor by taking the upper index here,
mu alpha,
nu,
and contracting it,
what we're doing now,
let me remind you,
two of these indices are in the same area,
and they're not in the same place.
The other two indices have to do with
the two directions that you go around in.
The other two indices have
to do with the rotation plane.
If you take one index
having to do with the circumnavigation,
and one index that has to
do with how the vector rotates,
and you contract them,
you get what's called the Ricci tensor.
To try to fathom it geometrically is very hard.
There's nothing easy to picture about it.
If you like,
it is simply a tensor that you make by contracting,
you can write it another way,
you can write it in terms of
the tensor with all of its indices,
let's write it with all of its indices downstairs,
alpha,
beta,
gamma,
delta.
Then you contract index alpha
with index gamma by the metric,
G alpha gamma.
Alpha with gamma,
you contract them together,
sum them,
and you have a thing which
only depends on beta and delta.
It has no simple geometric picture that I know of.
It's made out of the Riemann tensor,
but it has only two independent components,
it has only two components,
not two components,
two indices,
and it's symmetric.
The symmetries of the Riemann
tensor assure that this is symmetric.
So this is also equal to R delta beta.
That's the Ricci tensor,
and it plays a very,
very big role in the dynamics of gravity,
even though it is not,
I suspect the reason it took Einstein
ten years to work out general relativity
was in finding the Ricci tensor,
because it doesn't have any simple pictorial significance.
In any case,
it is what it is,
and it will play an important role in what comes.
Ricci?
R-I-C-C-I.
How else would you spell it?
Depends on what language it is.
What was Ricci's problem that
he had to come up with?
You know,
I don't know.
I've looked that up several times
and I could never find out.
I don't know.
Oh,
oh,
okay.
No,
I'll tell you.
In three dimensions,
Ricci was interested in three-dimensional space.
the Ricci tensor and the Riemann
tensor are completely equivalent to each other,
and I'll tell you why.
It's very simple.
In three dimensions,
a plane is in one-to-one correspondence with an axis.
So if I have a thing
which depends on a pair of planes,
that's four indices altogether,
that's four indices,
two for each plane,
because a plane is the same
as an axis perpendicular to it,
it can also be thought of as
a thing which depends on only two vectors.
So a thing which depends
on two planes in three dimensions
can be thought of as a thing
which depends only on two vector directions.
The Ricci tensor is the
way of describing the Riemann tensor
when you describe it in
terms of axes instead of planes.
It takes two directions to define a plane,
and so four directions to define a pair of planes,
but in three dimensions it's simpler.
It really only takes two axes.
So I believe that Ricci discovered this form of it
by...
when he was working in three dimensions.
Why it turns up to be
so important in the theory of gravity
will come to that,
but it's not because it
has any easy-to-picture geometry to it.
Okay,
we've covered the idea of curvature as much
as I can cover it in one hour.
Geometry is half of the theory of gravity.
The other half of the theory of gravity is matter.
Mass.
Mass affects geometry.
Mass curves geometry.
John Wheeler used to like to say,
he had a phrase,
a slogan,
Mass curves geometry,
and geometry tells particles how to move,
or something like that.
I don't remember.
It was more elegant than that,
but...
The idea being that the presence of mass affects geometry.
That's another way of saying the
presence of mass creates gravitational field,
and gravitational field affects the motion of particles.
So they affect each other.
Particles,
masses affect the gravitational field.
That means that they affect geometry,
and geometry affects the way particles move.
The...
The curvature,
incidentally,
is the,
as we'll see,
is the analog in general relativity
of tidal forces in Newtonian gravity.
It's the thing that you can't remove,
it's the obstruction that you
can't remove by a coordinate transformation.
So,
think of it that way,
and we'll see more clearly how
it works as we go along.
All right.
I want to define some notions which are important,
not only in general relativity,
but in field theory in general.
We've talked about them in earlier classes.
Let's begin with electric charge.
Electric charge is a typical thing which can flow,
which has a density,
which has a flux.
A flux means a current of it,
and which is a material quantity.
A flux is a quantity that
has a sense of being a substance,
if you like.
All right.
First of all,
let's take a box of space,
a small box of ordinary space now.
This is not space-time.
Not space-time.
I'll tell you when it is space-time.
Just ordinary space.
And now let's imagine the
world is full of charged particles,
tiny,
tiny charged particles,
smoothly distributed,
and I can ask,
what is the total charge in the box?
The total charge in the box,
total electric charge in the box,
let me call it,
since the box is going to be
taken to be small in the end,
I'll call charge,
q is charge.
The amount of charge in the box we'll call dq,
because the box is small.
And of course it will be
proportional to the volume of the box.
But if I divide,
let's call the volume of the box,
let's call it dv,
a small box,
infinite small box,
divide the charge by the volume,
and I get the density.
Let's call it rho.
Now this is the density not of mass,
but the density of charge.
So I'll just put a little q down there
to remind you that it's the density of charge,
not the density of mass.
That's,
if you like,
the definition of charge.
So what's the charge density?
It's,
go to a particular point,
take a small box,
take the total amount of charge in it,
divide it by the volume,
shrink everything to zero,
and the limit is the density.
It follows,
of course,
that the total charge in a finite box
is the integral of the density over the box.
So that's charge density.
Let me picture it another way.
I want to now picture it in four-dimensional,
a four-dimensional picture.
Unfortunately,
I can't draw four-dimensional boxes very well.
So what I'm going to do
is think of the three-dimensional box
as being two-dimensional.
Here we're going to,
now we are going to draw space-time.
Here's time,
here's space,
x and y.
And unfortunately,
I cannot draw,
I can draw another axis,
but it would only make things a little more complicated
than they need to be.
So let's imagine another axis but not draw it.
What does this box look like?
It gets,
it just becomes a little square.
A little square in space,
a little square.
It's not really a square,
it has three dimensions,
but due to the limitations
of the blackboard and our brains,
I will simply draw it as a little square
with two directions,
x and y,
and implicitly a third direction.
Now,
there are charged particles.
Charges don't disappear.
Charges are conserved.
A charge moving around in the space-time
is just a world line
that never begins and never ends
because charges don't come and go.
And now we can imagine asking how many charged lines,
how much charge passes through
this box.
This box.
That's just another way of asking,
at a given instant of time,
how much charge is in the box.
How much charge is passing through the box
in a space-time sense
is equivalent to the question,
how much charge is in the box
at a given instant of time.
We could follow the box,
of course,
we could follow the box in time.
Here's the box,
same box,
a little bit later.
Is the charge in that box necessarily the same?
No,
because charge can enter the box over here
but then go out here
and not pass through the upper box.
That's just another way of saying
that a charge can move out of the box.
So,
charge is conserved,
but that doesn't mean the
amount of charge in the box
in a particular box stays the same.
Alright,
so that's the notion of
charge in a box,
charge density,
and here I've drawn the charge density
in a way that makes it seem as though
it has something to do
with charges going through a box.
Alright,
so that's rho.
Now let's talk about the current,
the electric current.
The electric current is a similar kind of idea.
Now you take,
now we're going back
to space,
let's go back to space,
and forget space-time for a moment,
and let's draw a square.
Now I don't mean a three-dimensional box,
I mean a two-dimensional box,
a window,
think of it as a window,
there's no windows on the wall here,
but think of it as a window,
and think of the actual motion of charges
as they move
and pass through the window.
Some charges will pass through the window,
some charges will not pass through the window.
Take the charges which pass through the window,
how much charge will pass through the window?
Well,
it's going to be proportional to the area
of the window,
but what else?
What else might it be proportional to
besides the area of the window?
The time,
the amount of time.
Alright,
so there's a flux of charge,
and the amount of charge through the window
per unit time is related to what's called the current.
So let's write that.
The amount of charge that goes through the window,
and I'm going to call
the window now a small window,
with a differential area dA,
per unit time,
what do I call that?
I'm going to call that the current.
But this area has an orientation.
The area has a normal vector to it,
so I'm really talking about the charge,
for example,
flowing in a given direction
through a window perpendicular to that direction.
It's got a vector index attached to it.
So for example,
if this is the x window,
the x window means a window in the yz plane,
the charge going through the x window per unit time
is called jx.
It's called jx.
J is the symbol for char,
for current.
It's called the current.
You can call it the flux of charge,
the current of charge,
the flow of charge,
whatever you like,
but it's the charge,
through a window perpendicular to x,
in per unit time.
And likewise for jy and jz.
If you want to know what jy is,
you take your window-oriented perpendicular to the y-axis,
and you ask how much charge is going
from the negative side of the y-axis
to the positive side of the y-axis,
per unit time,
and that becomes jy.
Now notice,
both rho and j are charges per unit,
how do we say this,
how many powers of a length does a volume have?
Three.
Now remember that time and length
are measured in the same units.
We are going to set throughout
the speed of light equal to one.
Time has units of length.
So how many units of length
are in the denominator here?
Also three.
The only real difference between these
is here I have charge per unit
three-dimensional space-like directions.
Here I have charge per two-space-like,
one-time-like direction.
So these are clearly closely similar kinds of things.
Charge per unit length cubed,
if you like.
You can think of the window
as a window of time.
So,
as being the window persisting
for a length of time t,
that has an area delta x times delta y,
but a duration of time delta t,
you can think of it as being like a volume,
a three-dimensional volume,
but a three-dimensional volume
with one of the directions being time.
So both the flow of charge
and the density of charge
are components of a single thing.
A single thing of a flow of charge
through various kinds of windows.
This window is a space-space-space window.
This window is a space-space-time window.
There are no windows which are time-time-space
because there's only one direction of time.
So this is all the kinds of windows there are.
And these objects form together
to form a four vector.
It's natural to group them together
into a four vector.
And that four vector is called
the current,
the four-dimensional charge current.
You group together rho,
Jx,
Jy,
and Jz.
And those you just call Jmu.
In other words,
the charge density
becomes the time component
of a four vector.
The other three components
are characterized by the direction
of the flow of charge.
And if charges are just sitting still,
it's as though they're moving in time,
if you like.
You can think of it that way.
A thing which is sitting still
is still moving through space-time,
and it's passing through these windows
in space-time.
And so rho together with J,
form a four vector of current.
Now I'm going through this rapidly
because we did it last quarter,
the idea of the four vector of charge.
How do we express the notion
of charge conservation?
The continuity equation.
Everybody remember the continuity equation?
I'll remind you what it is.
The continuity equation is the basic equation.
I don't want to erase this.
I want this there.
It's the basic equation
which tells us a little more
than just the charges conserved.
If charge is conserved in the whole universe,
it just says the amount of charge
in the whole universe doesn't change.
But there's a little more
to charge conservation than that.
I've explained this to you more than once.
We'll do it once again,
though.
If a charge disappeared over here
and reappeared on the moon,
then instantly,
we would say charge was conserved.
But an experiment taking place in this room
would be clearly deceived
into the idea that charge is not conserved.
It doesn't really work that way.
We don't get deceived into the idea
that charge is not conserved for some reason.
And if you don't like the Earth-Moon,
you say,
well,
we could always do experiments
involving the Earth and the Moon,
make it the Earth in Alpha Centauri
or the Earth in the next galaxy over,
whatever you like.
It's quite clear that charge conservation
by itself really doesn't have any real implication
for experiments done in finite volume.
The real notion of charge conservation
is what's called local charge conservation.
It doesn't mean that the amount of charge
in the room doesn't change.
It means that any change
in the charge in the room
is due to observable flows of charge through the walls.
The only way the charge can change in the room
is if it flows through the walls.
So an increase in charge
would correspond to a flow of charge in.
A decrease of charge in the room
would correspond to a flow of charge out.
What mathematical object is there
that could represent the flow
of charge radially outward from a point?
The divergence.
The divergence is the mathematical quantity
which expresses the idea of a flow outward.
So if you take a small region of space
and you ask how much charge is in it,
or not so much how much charge is in it,
but how does the charge change with time,
Well,
the charge that's in that small region
is the volume of the small region.
Let's take the volume to be fixed
and let's set it equal to one for simplicity.
Then the charge in that small unit volume is rho.
I could multiply it by the volume,
but I'm setting the volume equal to one.
In any case,
I'm going to hold it fixed.
All right,
now how does that charge change?
Well,
it changes by charges going
into and out of the room,
but let's take the time derivative of it.
If there's a time derivative to the charge density,
it must mean that there
is a current at the boundary.
But that current,
for example,
a uniform current flowing straight through
in the x direction,
that would do nothing because there would be
as much current coming in from one side
as going out the other.
It's the divergence of the current
which tells you the charge,
the charge is passing out.
So if the charge is increasing,
then that must mean charge is coming in.
It must mean the divergence is negative.
The right equation is that
the change per unit time of the charge density
plus the divergence of the current,
now this is the three-dimensional current,
Jx,
Jy,
Jz,
must be equal to zero.
What it expresses is that the rate of change
of charge in the box
is equal to the negative
of the amount of charge
that's flowing out of the box.
If the charge is flowing out of the box,
the amount of charge must be decreasing.
We can write this explicitly.
It says that,
let's say partial of rho with respect to t,
the partial of rho with respect to t,
and then what is the divergence of the current?
Anybody remember the form for the divergence of a vector?
Right.
It's the derivative with respect to x
of the x component
plus the derivative with respect to y
of the y component,
Jy,
plus the derivative with respect to z
of Jz,
and that's equal to zero.
But if I now call rho
the time component of J,
we can just write this as J0,
the time component.
And we can call t
the time component of the four-vector of position.
This becomes x1,
In other words,
the continuity equation
just becomes the very simple,
nice looking equation
that the derivative of Jmu
with respect to xmu
is equal to zero.
Summed over mu.
To basic kinds of definitions,
definition of current and density
and the continuity equation,
that's the basic ingredient
that goes into the conservation of electric charge
or any other kind of charge that's conserved.
Okay.
Now,
one thing about charge
is that charge itself,
the components of the current of charge
are a four-vector,
but the charge itself,
how about the charge itself?
Supposing I have,
well,
what are the units of charge anyway?
Coulombs,
huh?
Yeah.
Coulomb is a huge amount of electric charge.
If you could somehow assemble a Coulomb of charge
on this table,
you would want to get
far out of the room because...
Okay.
Supposing I say there's a Coulomb of charge
on the table over here.
And supposing you're moving by on a railroad train,
how much charge would you say is there?
Coulomb.
Charge is an invariant.
It's a scalar,
if you like.
Charge is a scalar.
The charge current is not.
The charge current and density are not scalars,
but the charge itself,
the total amount of charge that's there is a scalar.
And so you should...
Are you afraid of a Coulomb of charge?
What's that?
Why are you afraid of a Coulomb?
Well,
that's so much charge that the repulsive force...
Here's what I mean.
Coulomb charge is what?
About 10 to the 19th...
I think it's 10 to the 19th electrons,
if I remember.
Okay.
So you say,
okay,
you have 10 to the 19th atoms.
10 to the 19th atoms has 10 to the 19th...
Hydrogen atoms has 10 to the 19th electrons.
Who's afraid of 10 to the 19th atoms of hydrogen?
But now take those 10
to the 19th atoms of hydrogen
and remove the protons.
Then you have 10 to the 19th electrons,
and that is a highly explosive situation.
With all the electrons repelling each other,
they would repel each other
and just make a huge explosion.
I have no trouble putting that amount of charge
in one ferret capacitor on your desk.
A whole Coulomb?
Yeah.
They're opposites.
They're close to each other.
They're close together.
I have no trouble putting
it in a one ferret capacitor
on your desk,
and I can go to Fry's and buy it.
No,
no,
no.
It might go cool on the plates,
both positive and negative,
very close together.
Yeah,
that's right.
You'll have a positive and negative charge
right next to each other.
I can charge up the capacitor to one volt.
It has one Coulomb in it.
It'll go boom.
It doesn't go boom.
10 to the 19th electron is a lot of electrons.
That's only 10 to the 19th electron volts.
10 to the 19th electrons would be...
That's only...
That's 10 to the 19 EVs.
That's 10 to the minus...
That's a lot of energy.
It's a nice bang,
but it's not like...
Yeah,
it's a bang.
I know we would explode the world.
I mean,
we'd make a nice little explosion in the world.
Nice little bang.
You've got to do something with it.
As I say,
you go to Fry's and for a buck,
you buy one pair of capacitors
and you charge it up to a volt.
And you've got a Coulomb
sitting right there on your desk.
You've got two Coulombs.
No,
you've got no Coulombs.
You've got one Coulomb of positive charge,
one Coulomb of negative charge next to each other.
Are you saying there's no energy in the capacitor?
No,
no,
there's energy in the capacitor.
But the energy in the capacitor depends on the distance
between the capacitor plates.
Cool.
It's a plate for you.
If you were to take the capacitor plates far away,
you would make a big energy.
Yes.
I was objecting to your
saying that a Coulomb of charge
in your desk is something to be afraid of.
A Coulomb of charge uncompensated
by a Coulomb of opposite charge would be,
I think that would be fairly dangerous.
Yeah,
move on.
Who cares?
Capacitor has two plates,
positive and negative.
They can't be both.
They cancel each other.
Let's put it this way.
If you were to take a cubic centimeter of water,
a Coulomb of charge is,
I think it's about 10 to the 19th electrons.
That would mean something like about
one part in 10 to the 4th
of the atoms had been ionized.
That would be 10,
okay,
so one part in 10
to the 4th of the atoms,
10 to the 23rd atoms,
10 to the 19th electrons.
That would mean one part in 10 to the,
so that would be 10 to the 19th electrons.
That would be 10 to the 19th electron,
10 to the 20th electron volts about.
Ionizing one hydrogen atom takes about 10 electron volts.
So that would be about
10 to the 20th electron volts.
How bad is 10 to the 20th electron volts?
Well,
it's actually not that bad,
but it's a noticeable perturbation.
It's a noticeable perturbation.
10 to the 20th electron volts
is like the highest cosmic ray energy
that can hit you.
It's 100 million TeV.
100 million TeV,
right.
But only one particle.
It's not like an accelerator beam hitting you.
So it's one particle with 100 million TeV.
That's about the highest energy cosmic ray.
So if you get hit by a high,
high,
high energy cosmic ray,
it can do some damage.
You're right,
it's not a big explosion.
I think it's an unpleasant
event taking place in your body.
Anyway,
let's go on.
All right,
now let's come to energy.
Energy and momentum.
Energy and momentum are also conserved quantities.
They're like charge in that respect.
They're conserved.
But energy and separately momentum themselves,
not their currents and not
their flows or not their densities,
but the total energy and
the total momentum of a system
are not scalars,
are not invariants.
This is more or less obvious.
If I have an object here standing at
rest and I tell you that it's energy,
and remember,
keep in mind E equals mc squared,
so m and mc squared.
m and e are similar things.
This object has a certain amount of energy,
namely its mass times c squared.
And now somebody's going on a
really fast railroad train going past it,
they will see the mc squared
plus the kinetic energy of the eraser.
So energy is not something
that all observers will agree about.
Total energy is not an invariant.
It's not a scalar.
Neither is total momentum.
I say the momentum of this is zero.
You going by in the railroad train
will say the momentum is not zero.
So energy and momentum are not,
they are conserved,
but they are not invariants.
And together,
the energy and the momentum of
a system also form a four vector.
We've gone through this when
we studied relativity more than once.
The energy of a system,
again,
speed of light equals one.
The energy of a system and the momentum,
the momentum is a three vector.
It has three components.
The energy and the momentum of
a system together form a four vector.
The energy being the time component,
and the momentum being the space components.
So you can,
if you like,
think of the energy as the time component,
and the momentum,
x,
y,
and z,
as the space components of another four vector.
But this time,
it's not the four vector of density and flow.
The total quantity of momentum,
or the total quantity of energy of a system,
together form a four vector.
The four vector is conserved.
Each component of it is conserved.
一番怖いのは
Yes,
the X component of momentum is conserved,
the Y component of momentum is conserved,
the energy is conserved.
So there are four separate conservation laws.
Now,
again,
energy conservation and momentum
conservation would be operationally useless
if it was just that energy could
disappear at one place and reappear on Mars.
It would be operationally useless in this laboratory.
So again,
there is a notion of a flow of energy.
Same thing,
a flow of momentum.
And it's the same kind of thing.
Changes in the energy of a system,
of a closed system like this,
can only happen if there is
a flow of energy or momentum
or whatever.
Whatever it is through the walls of a system.
And so there must also be a notion of
a density of energy and a flow of energy.
That's likewise for momentum.
Let's give them some names and then let's see
if we can make a guess as to what kind
of quantity the density and
flow of energy and momentum is.
I warn you now that I am
setting the speed of light equal to one.
So some of the formulas may differ from elementary
textbooks in which there are speeds of light floating around.
You can always restore the dimensions
by making the dimensional analysis consistent.
But all right.
Energy.
First of all is a
notion of the density of energy.
Energy in a volume divided by the volume,
take the volume small,
defines a quantity which is the density of energy.
Let's give that a name.
Energy is the time component of something.
Remember,
energy and momentum form the four vector P naught,
P1,
P2,
P3.
So first of all,
it's a density of something.
And let's label this quantity by
who it is we're talking about.
We're talking about energy.
And energy,
I'll simply use a shorthand.
I'll use a shorthand notation.
The time component of the four vector.
So energy is a time component of something.
This T is going to
be the analog of a density.
It is a density.
It's the density of energy.
But let's go back over here.
Where is it?
Yes,
up here.
Notice that the density itself,
quite apart from whatever it's the density of,
the density is also the fourth component of something.
So this is the density of energy
is the density of the fourth component.
In other words,
it's the fourth component of a fourth component.
It's the fourth component because it has to do with
energy and it's the fourth component because it's a density.
All right.
It's a fourth component because it's a density,
and density is like the time component of a flow.
flow.
So we'll give it two zeros.
Two zeros because it's the fourth component of a fourth
component.
Now,
what about the flow of momentum?
If we were talking about charge,
the flow
of momentum in the x direction would be called J1.
We're now talking about the flow of something
whose name is naught.
Just to label the fact that we're talking about energy,
we put a naught there,
but it's a flow of energy in the one direction.
So we need to put a one there.
T naught one is the flow of the
zero component of the energy momentum four vector,
in other words,
the energy,
along the x-axis.
How about...
What would T naught two mean?
That would be the flow of energy along the two-axis,
and so forth.
Okay,
that takes care of energy and its flow.
What about the x component of momentum?
The x component of momentum is just another quantity
which is conserved.
We ought to give its density a name.
How much x component of momentum is in this volume?
Well,
I don't know how much is.
It depends on the microscopic particles.
But if there was a
flow of particles through the volume,
there might be an x component to the...
All right,
so let's talk about the x component of momentum.
What should I call its density?
All right.
This indicated it was a density.
This indicated it was the energy.
All right,
so now let's write a T,
which this index is now one,
because we're talking about the x component of momentum,
but we're still talking about its density.
So the first index tells us who we're talking about.
The second index tells us
what direction the flow is in.
The flow is in the time direction.
It's a density.
So this is the density of x component of momentum.
The amount of x component of momentum in a volume.
How about the flow of x component of momentum?
Can you imagine a flow of x component of momentum?
Yeah,
that's easy.
I mean,
you just have some particles going along.
They have x component of momentum,
and moreover,
the x component of momentum is flowing.
So,
along the x axis.
This becomes T1,
because we're talking about the x component of momentum.
But now we're talking about
the flow along the one direction.
How about a flow of
x momentum along the y direction?
Does that make sense?
Well,
supposing I had...
There's my x axis.
There's my y axis.
Supposing I have a bunch of
particles moving off in an oblique direction.
They are carrying x momentum from one
value of y to another value of y.
A bunch of particles going off that way are taking...
They also have some y momentum.
But in particular,
they have some x momentum,
but that x momentum is
being transported along the y axis.
So yes,
it does make sense to talk about the transport,
or the flux,
or the flow,
of x momentum along the y axis.
And along the z axis.
Okay,
what comes next?
Well,
the next thing that comes
is the y component of momentum.
The density of the y
component of the momentum is T20.
And then the flow along the one axis.
T21,
T22,
T23.
And finally,
T30,
T31,
T32,
T33.
And finally,
T30,
T31,
T32,
T33.
And finally,
T30,
T34,
T35,
T36.
These are the four sets of objects.
One,
two,
three,
four.
Each composed of four pieces itself.
Which represent the flows and the densities
of the components of energy and momentum.
This whole object is a tensor.
Now,
is it obvious that it's a tensor?
No,
it's not obvious that it's a tensor.
We will have to do some more work to
convince ourselves that it ought to be a tensor.
But it's called the energy-momentum tensor.
And we can write it in
the condensed notation T mu nu.
Isn't it obvious that it's a
tensor because it's a physical thing?
Yeah.
Yeah,
I would say that that's...
I guess the right way to say it is it
better be a tensor or else it's not a physical thing.
So...
And you write it this way because
each component is considered unlike the charge equation.
Yeah,
each...
Well,
first of all,
this in itself doesn't say that each component is conserved.
It just says that each...
That they exist.
Now we can ask what does
it say to say that they're conserved?
Okay.
So let's make our best guess as to
what it would say that they are conserved.
Let's look at the...
At the energy.
What I want to do is
write down for the energy itself,
which is just the first row here,
I want to write the analog of the continuity equation.
In fact,
I'm going to write the continuity equation.
The first index here,
that's completely passive.
It just says that I'm talking about energy.
The second index tells me whether I'm talking about
density or X or Y or Z component of flow.
Okay,
so if I just mimic or
just parrot the top equation there,
mimic the top equation for energy,
what will it say?
It will say that the derivative with respect to T...
Why don't you tarot the bottom one?
I will.
I'll do all of them.
All right.
But it says the derivative of T of
the energy density plus the derivative of X
with respect to the flow along the X axis
plus the derivative with respect
to Y of T naught Y.
I'm getting tired of this.
I'm getting tired of writing them,
but you see the pattern.
I guess we could call these one,
two,
and three.
Equals zero.
All right,
now I could do the
same thing for the next line.
The next line is also...
It refers to a conserved quantity.
It refers to the X component of momentum.
The only way the X component of momentum can change
in the room is if X component of momentum flows
through the walls of the room.
Same deal.
So we will write the same
equation except wherever I see naught...
In the first entry,
I will write one,
then naught,
and so forth and so on.
I'm getting a little tired of writing it.
D by DX,
T11 plus D by DY,
T12 plus...
plus D by DZ,
T13...
No,
T...
Yeah,
T13 equals zero.
And likewise for the third...
How many...
There are two more equations like this.
Each one of these rows has
a continuity equation associated with it.
Now,
I can also write this in
a single common notation like this.
And it is just...
I have exactly this form,
D by DX mu of T nu mu equals zero.
Nu here is the index which
tells us what we're talking about.
Energy or first component of
momentum or second component of momentum
or third component.
In other words,
it just names the quantity we're talking about.
It's the mu index here which
tells us which direction we're talking about
and gets combined with the derivative here.
That's the conservation of energy equation,
local conservation of energy in special relativity.
You say,
why special relativity and why not general relativity?
The answer we'll come to next time.
The equation is slightly modified in general relativity.
The way that it's modified
is the derivative becomes covariant derivative.
You say,
why not covariant derivative over here?
We'll come to that.
We'll come to it.
It is covariant derivative.
Some slippery trickery happens
here that doesn't happen here.
But this is the basic idea of energy momentum conservation.
Okay,
so now we have the
basic ingredients for the general relativity.
We have geometry which represents gravitational field.
And we have energy and momentum which
represent the source of the gravitational field.
Normally we think of the source
of the gravitational field as mass.
But E equals MC squared.
So if C is equal to 1,
energy and mass are the same thing.
So it's natural to think of mass as mass.
It's the source of the gravitational field.
But on the other hand,
energy or mass comes together
with these other things called momentum.
If energy is the source
of something about the gravitational field,
then in some other frame of reference
where energy gets mixed up with momentum,
momentum will become the source of
some piece of the gravitational field.
So Einstein's job was to figure
out how to write tensor equations
which expressed the sense in which the
gravitational field was sourced by energy and momentum.
And to write them in a way that
made good sense in any frame of reference.
I'm going to,
we're not going to do that today.
That's a little beyond what I wanted to do today.
I did want to do one more thing today.
I don't know,
are we really shot?
Or is there time for...
Alright,
one more thing we'll do.
Now we're coming...
I've set up the basic ingredients
for thinking about energy and momentum
as the source of the gravitational field.
All it will take is an equation which has
on one side something to do with the geometry.
What's it going to be?
It's going to be the curvature tensor.
The curvature tensor on one side and
on the other side of the equation
it will be the energy and momentum.
Curvature caused by energy and momentum.
That's half of the story.
That tells us how energy and momentum curves space.
The other half of the story is
what geometry does to the motion of particles.
I want to spend a
little bit of time on that.
And because I don't want to
have to do it next time,
although we'll probably wind up
going through it the next time.
The basic rule that Einstein settled on
for the motion of particles through a gravitational field
is that they move on geodesics.
They move in the simplest possible way.
Particles have little steering wheels,
but the steering wheels are
locked in the straight ahead direction.
But not just in space,
but through space-time.
Space-time has a geometry.
It's described exactly the way
we've described it up till now,
with a metric tensor,
a curvature tensor.
The whole story goes through.
And particles move through
space-time on space-time geodesics.
That was the principle,
a very,
very simple principle.
What would it say in flat space-time?
In flat space-time it would say that
particles move through space-time on straight lines.
That has two pieces to it.
It first of all means that
they move along trajectories in space,
which are straight.
But it also says that
they move with a constant velocity.
A straight line in space-time is
something which moves in a fixed direction,
but with a fixed speed.
So the principle that a particle
moves on a geodesic in flat space-time
would just say that an object moves with no acceleration.
Now of course that's ignoring
all the other kinds of forces,
but if all we had was
gravitational forces that would be correct.
What's the analog of that more generally?
More generally the statement is
that particles move on geodesics.
The straightest possible paths.
Let me remind you what
the equation for a geodesic is.
It's just the equation of zero
covariant derivative of the tangent vector.
The tangent vector is the x mu by d tau.
Tau being proper time along the trajectory.
That's the tangent vector.
And to differentiate it with respect to tau,
now we have a tangent vector along the curve,
the tangent vector is doing whatever it's doing.
And now we're asking how the tangent vector
changes as we move from point to point.
Well,
that's another derivative with respect to tau.
But that's not the covariant
derivative of the tangent vector.
The covariant derivative of the
tangent vector involves the Christoffel symbol.
And it's plus gamma mu nu sigma,
tangent vector dx nu by d tau,
tangent vector dx sigma by d tau.
This tells us what the orbit
of a particle is in space-time.
It's a differential equation telling us,
in terms of the Christoffel symbol,
what the motion is.
Now I want to restrict myself.
We have five more minutes.
I'm going to go through this again,
but I want to do it now
to give you some food for thought.
Supposing we're in the limit
where Newton is almost exactly right.
What does that mean?
It means that the gravitational fields are not too strong,
and it also means that things are moving slowly.
All right?
It means that everything is moving slowly.
In fact,
I'm beginning to move slowly.
I think we're going to
come back to it next time.
I think we're too close to the...
Yeah.
All right.
If you want to play with this a little bit,
see if you can say,
see what this says.
Here's the goal.
Put in the fact that
all the particles are moving slowly.
Okay?
That means that dx by dt,
not d tau,
but dx by dt is small.
The ordinary velocities of particles are small.
Are there any components of dx
by d tau which are not small?
Yeah,
the time component,
because the time component is almost exactly equal to one.
It's essentially dt by d tau,
almost equal to one.
So when particles move slowly,
only the time components of
these tangent vectors are appreciable.
All right?
Now,
tau and t are almost
the same if particles move slowly.
So this is almost the ordinary acceleration.
This is almost the ordinary acceleration.
On the right-hand side here,
these things are either very
small or they're close to one.
So what does it say?
It says the acceleration is equal to the Christoffel symbol,
to a certain Christoffel symbol.
The Christoffel symbols evidently
are the gravitational field,
the gravitational acceleration.
They're like the things we called in the beginning A,
the field of acceleration.
So this is the connection.
Here's how we're going to
make the connection between Newton's equations,
Newton's second law of motion,
and Einstein's principle that things move on geodesics.
These are negligibly,
they're essentially one when this is time components.
And the gamma becomes,
which gamma is important here?
What are the relevant indices here?
Remember that the x by the tau
is only appreciable if it's a time component.
So that means that the gravitational force
is basically just gamma mu zero zero.
The gravitational force along a given direction,
let's say the y direction,
is the Christoffel symbol gamma y zero zero.
That's going to be the link
to guide us to the motion of,
well,
to the connection between various gravitational things
and other things in Newton's equations.
We might as well write it down right now.
The field of acceleration is
equal to the Christoffel symbol.
We'll come back to that,
and then we'll try to put the whole thing together,
and find equations which express
the connection between the gravitational field
and the masses on the one hand,
and the gravitational forces on particles on the other hand.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Thank you.