This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
And if you were to calculate the Gaussian curvature,
remember in two dimensions the Gaussian,
the curvature is just a,
it just has one component,
only has one independent component.
And it's the curvature scalar.
If you were to calculate the curvature scalar,
then on the outer rim of
the torus here,
you would find it's positive.
And in the inner region here,
you would find it's negative.
And it is in such a way that the
integral of the curvature over the torus is zero.
Okay,
and that's true for any object
which has the topology of a torus.
Here,
I'm gonna modify it.
It's still a torus.
We can modify it into a coffee cup or whatever.
What I've done is add some negative curvature
over here and some positive curvature out here,
but without changing the integral of the curvature.
So there's a theorem about the integral of the curvature.
The integral of the curvature is called the Euler number,
and it's related to the
number of holes in the curvature.
So I've got two holes and handles.
On the other hand,
if I put another hole in here,
then I would change the integrated curvature,
and this cannot be flattened.
This has an integrated curvature which is negative,
more negative than positive.
So you can't unfold a torus,
a dominant,
so it's flat.
Mm-hmm.
Because the integrated curvature is zero.
Yeah.
That doesn't prove you can unfold it.
It just,
here,
the integrated curvature is not zero,
and moreover,
the integrated curvature
is something which only depends on the topology.
That's a theorem.
That's Euler's theorem or Gauss's theorem.
喂喂
the integrated curvature in here
is equal to
the integrated curvature for sphere
in certain units is plus one
the integrated curvature for any torus
is zero
the integrated curvature for a
torus with two holes in it
is minus one
integrated curvature with three holes
minus two
and so it goes
uh...
the number of holes is called the euler number
so the integrated curvature is related to the euler number
i can't remember is the euler number the integrated uh...
is it uh...
yeah well the euler number is related
to the number of holes and handles
and the integrated curvature only depends
on the topology it doesn't change
if you put a bulge on it
it doesn't change if you
put a bulge on the sphere
and so forth
good so here's what we know
the integrated curvature of this
is zero
the integrated curvature of a plane
is clearly zero because its curvature is
everywhere zero
and so this is the only one
that would have any chance of being flattened
the integrated curvature of this cannot
be flattened because it's always a
going to be minus one
is it possible to put a metric on the torus
that's everywhere zero
everywhere zero
in other words make it flat
not the
well making the metric zero doesn't make it flat
well i mean
picking a metric
where the curvature
where the curvature is zero yes
yes yes yes yes you can put
a metric that's the point you can
put a metric on a torus
which makes it everywhere flat
now suppose i have a sphere
and i take one point out of a sphere
that doesn't make a torus out of it
i know
but can i make that everywhere flat
can i choose a metric for the
for the sphere minus a point
which would make it
ah can you choose you're not going
to choose the standard metric of the sphere
the question is can you choose and yes you can
then it begins a sphere less one point
becomes the infinite plane
and a way to see that
in other words it's a question can
you map a sphere to a plane
can you map a sphere into a plane
one-to-one correspondence
of a sphere onto a plane
if you can then you can just use
the metric on the sphere that it inherits
from the plane
now you can almost do that
there are many ways to do it of course
you take the sphere
and you imagine that it's tangent to a plane
it's it's just sitting it's resting on a plane okay
you take every point on the sphere and you
map it to a point on the plane by
doing the following you go to the north pole
here's the north pole here's the south pole
and you draw a straight line from
the north pole through the point in question
p over here
and you continue it until you hit the plane
okay
every point on the sphere
gets mapped to a point
on the plane in this way
the south pole gets mapped
right to the point where this sphere is resting
every point gets mapped to a point
on the plane except for one point which
is the north pole
if you include the point at
infinity if you imagine one extra point
which is really the point at infinity
and of course it seems odd
to think of infinity as a point,
infinity that way
doesn't seem to be the same,
but suppose you identify them all,
then that's
equivalent to the sphere.
So here's what you can do.
You can place a metric on the
plane,
the standard metric on the plane,
dx squared plus py squared,
and say
every pair of points,
every pair of neighboring points,
has a certain
distance between them as given by the
simple-minded metric on the on the plane,
and then map those two points,
the two points on the sphere,
I don't think I did
it very well,
but simply give them the same
distance as the two points on the
plane had,
and that way you will have
a metric which flattens the sphere.
Okay.
But this point at the North Pole here,
since it corresponds to points very,
very
far away,
this metric,
the distance between this point,
let's say this point
and that point,
what's the distance between that point and that point?
It's
going to be huge,
or infinite,
right?
This point maps out to infinity,
this
point over here next to it maps
to some other place which is finite.
So that
means that the metric,
the components of the metric,
are going to be infinite.
So the metric up near the North
Pole here are going to go to infinity,
the components
of this peculiar metric which flattens the sphere
are going to diverge at the North Pole.
So at Nth on the sphere their measuring rods
would shrink as they head to the North Pole,
and when they measure triangles,
they'd always get 180 degrees.
Yeah.
Right.
Where,
if they made triangles by
the rules of constructing geodesics,
the rules of
geodesics will no longer be great circles on here.
Or they may be,
but if they are,
they're actually,
uh,
actually they are.
There must be some geodesics that are not great circles,
right?
Uh,
I think every,
um,
I have to think about it.
The question I had was back to the rod
and the torium and the change in two variables.
Mm-hmm.
Is there any,
just when I saw it,
is there any meaning to that,
that could be,
how did the two strings come together in the marine?
I'm sure we could find
one if we tried hard enough.
Offhand,
I can't think of any.
Okay.
Yeah.
Yeah,
is it possible to,
uh,
define a,
a port transformation from,
you know,
like two space to three space?
Not a continuous one.
Um.
Because,
you know,
for example,
if you,
No,
no.
Two space for a sphere,
you know,
a word.
Mm-hmm.
Uh,
you can,
it appears you can map
that into a flat three space.
No.
The sphere cannot be,
the sphere cannot be mapped,
it depends on what you mean by mapped.
Um.
Every point in a,
you define a curvature with a,
some kind of tensor,
you know,
that defines a sphere.
Um,
it's the same like,
like what you're doing here.
Can you map that,
not from two space,
but from three space?
Because again,
it's embedded within a three space.
No,
no,
wait,
it's different to,
you can place a sphere
and embed it in three space.
That's not the same as mapping it,
well,
mapping it into,
onto,
one to one.
When I say mapping,
I mean one to one correspondence.
One to one.
Right.
Every point in the three,
in the three dimensional space corresponds to a
unique point on two dimensional space and vice versa.
That is possible,
but it's not possible to do in a continuous fashion.
In fact,
it's the only way you can do it is
by scrambling up the points in a monstrously complicated way.
So we could give you a rule for,
here's a rule.
Two dimensional space is characterized by,
um,
by pairs of real numbers,
right?
Pairs of real numbers,
we can write down the first real number,
and let's,
let's take the region from zero to one,
just for simplicity.
So I take a two dimensional square,
and I'm going to map a two dimensional square.
And I'm going to put
the two dimensional square onto a,
um,
one dimensional line.
In each case,
it's going to go from zero to one.
Okay,
can we do that?
Can we really do that?
Yes.
Take the two dimensional point and
characterize it by a real number.
A real number means a decimal.
Point three seven nine four one six,
blah blah blah blah.
Uh,
if it's a,
if it's a rational number,
then it's a repeating decimal.
If it's an irrational number,
it's a non-repeating decimal,
and so forth.
Uh...
We need two of them.
Point eight four six,
blah blah blah blah blah.
And now,
take a new number that we're
going to make out of them,
by intertwining the numbers here with the numbers here.
So first we pick the point three.
Then we go down to here,
eight.
Then we go up to here,
seven.
Then we go down to here,
four.
Then we go up to nine.
Then six.
You see what the pattern is.
I've taken a one from here.
Followed it by this,
up to here.
Followed it by that,
and so forth.
This is a unique number.
Given a point here,
there's a unique real number that
you can make by this construction.
And furthermore,
given this real number here,
I can take it apart and disassemble it.
Put the three up here,
the eight here,
the seven here,
and so forth.
So,
for every one of,
for every one of these,
which means every pair of real numbers,
there is,
by this construction,
a unique real number.
So long as you omit zero,
right?
What's that?
So long as you omit the zero point.
Why and why?
Well,
that'd be good.
Fine.
You're going to have a zero point here.
And it maps to the zero point here.
Okay.
Right.
But,
if you were to take a point like this,
and a close-by point,
let's,
sorry,
this is,
excuse me,
let's take two numbers here
which are close to each other.
Let's see.
No,
I don't want these two numbers
to be close to each other.
I want to take pairs of real points.
Here's one,
and here's another one.
And we take them to be close to each other.
In general,
they will not be close to each other.
They're not going to be close
to each other on the line.
So...
It will be close because if
the differences are out of the part,
and the changes in the image
will be out of the part,
too.
Well,
let's see.
But it won't be differentiable,
I think.
Yeah,
it certainly won't be differentiable.
It certainly will not be differentiable.
No,
I think it's always going to be very,
very scrambled.
There will always be points which are close together here,
which are far from here.
I think it's...
Say it again.
Point three,
eight.
You could take point one and then
point zero with a whole string of nines.
Those are very close.
Right.
So there's always going to be a lot of scrambling.
You can't map it in any kind of continuous fashion.
Uh...
And so,
in particular,
functions which are smooth on this plane here
are going to be mapped to here.
We take a function of x and y here,
and we reconstruct from it a function on the line.
How do we do it?
Well,
if we want to know what the value
of the function is at point whatever it is,
we reconstruct from this number here
the real number,
the pair of real numbers,
go to that point,
and take f,
and just bring it down to here.
That function is going to be wildly varying.
Neighboring values of x here will correspond to wildly,
in general,
divergent values of...
Not divergent in the sense of infinite.
It also depends on your starting point,
whether you start with the eight or the three.
Yeah,
it does.
This is interesting.
I got a question about curvature.
If you use...
So,
needless to say,
incidentally,
we're not going to consider this a proper,
reasonable,
coordinate transformation.
If you're describing,
let's say,
ありがとうございました
with geodesic coordinates,
then the Christoph...
Let me say exactly what that means,
so not for your benefit
but for the rest of it.
I think by geodesic coordinates,
we mean we have some curved space.
At some point,
strictly at some point,
we construct some geodesic like that.
We construct a perpendicular geodesic like that.
We call that the x and y axis,
for example.
And then any point we can...
Any nearby point,
point close to this point over here,
we can assign a coordinate.
We can assign a pair of coordinates
by dropping perpendicular geodesics to here
and perpendicular geodesics to here,
and then assign...
this point the coordinates equal
to this distance and that distance.
Is that what you mean by geodesic coordinates?
Yeah.
Yeah,
those are the coordinates.
Those are the coordinates in which
the metric tensor at this point
is delta ij or delta mn,
and in which the first derivatives
of the metric are equal to zero.
Okay?
There are the coordinates which sort of match
most closely to a flat coordinate system over here.
But the...
And so some of the terms
of the Riemann tensor go away.
It's probably true,
some of them may.
Because they're just the
products of the Christoffel symbols,
but other terms of the Riemann tensor are derivatives.
That's right.
I'm wondering if they also go away.
No,
they won't go away.
Oh,
sorry.
Yes,
of course.
Of course,
in general,
of course they will go away.
Yeah.
The Christoffel symbols at this point are all zero.
Yeah,
but they don't...
But the derivatives with respect to...
Oh,
I'm sorry.
Sorry,
sorry.
The Christoffel symbols are zero.
The derivatives of the Christoffel symbols will not be zero.
But you're right.
You're right.
There are two terms,
and the Riemann tensor has two kinds of terms.
It has derivatives of the Christoffel symbols,
and it will have plus
quadratic things in the Christoffel symbols,
just schematically.
These,
of course,
will be zero.
Why?
Because at that point,
only at this point,
at that point,
the Christoffel symbols will be zero.
Why?
Because the Christoffel symbols all
contain derivatives of the Gs.
And if those are zero,
these are zero.
On the other hand,
these things here will contain second derivatives of G.
And those won't be zero.
And I was wondering,
if you could give any insight into the Ricci tensor
by looking at that particular case.
It's possible.
I wouldn't be surprised.
Good.
So what you'd want to do is to relate the...
Both the Riemann tensor,
the Ricci tensor,
and the scalar curvature,
you would want to relate it to
the various second derivatives of the metric.
So it's the second derivatives of the metric,
which come in.
Very likely there is some picture
that you can make from it,
from this construction.
But it would involve the second derivatives of the metric.
Now what kind of nice geometric picture do you have
about the second derivatives of the metric?
Yeah.
Right.
But nevertheless,
it's correct that the Riemann tensor
in those coordinates simply involves the collection
of second derivatives of the metric.
And that's it.
Doesn't involve first derivatives.
And so you can reconstruct it from those.
And maybe vice versa also,
that you could reconstruct this,
or a lot of information about
the second derivatives of the metric
from the Riemann tensor.
Okay.
Any other questions?
Special relativity.
Yeah,
we're going to talk about that.
I'll give you an example.
First of all,
geodesic minimizes the,
or maximizes the proper time for a time.
Okay.
Maximizing.
You did an example where you had flat space
and actually for small v,
you showed that if you maximize the,
the path that maximizes the proper time
is the path that minimizes the kinetic energy,
which is the,
with our,
Yes.
Minimizes the kinetic energy,
which is the .
They show those for a code.
Can you put that in a more general sense?
Say it again?
Can you do,
can you show that those two are the path?
Yeah,
well,
okay.
But you have to understand that the kinetic energy
is related to the path length with a negative sign.
Right.
Right,
okay.
So it's not a crazy thing
that minimizing one maximizes the other.
Can you do that in general
if you just had a bunch of,
say,
a density mass,
no other force in it?
No other force.
So it's just gravitation.
And show that the geodesic that
you get is equivalent to minimizing Lagrangian.
Minimizing the Lagrangian for the point particle.
Yeah,
what you can't show,
because it's not generally true,
is that every geodesic is
an absolute minimum of the distance.
It's a local minimum.
You know what the difference is?
I know in a regular function
the difference is local and global.
Yeah,
correct.
And that's a minimum.
Okay.
Oh,
if you just take any small variation,
it's a minimum.
That's right.
If you take any small variation,
it's a minimum,
but you may be able to find
some large deviation which finds some path of,
So you get a whole collection.
Yeah.
Yeah,
you may have more than one
geodesic connecting pairs of points in particular.
In fact,
as a rule you do.
In general you do.
Yeah.
And when you see like a ring around the star,
do you notice that?
Well,
for example,
but a simple example would be you
take a nice symmetric hill in two-dimensional space.
Let's make a very high hill.
Now I'm not talking about space-time.
I'm just talking about ordinary space,
just to illustrate the point that
there can be more than one geodesic.
Typically there will be a geodesic.
Between here and here,
let's plot it horizontally so I
have a contour map for this thing.
Here's the contour map for it.
Big hill.
Typically there will be a geodesic which will,
it will find a compromise.
If I went all around here,
that would cost me some
path length in avoiding the hill.
On the other hand,
if I go over,
right over the top of the hill,
there's a great big distance around.
So there typically will be a geodesic which will
find a compromise and go somewhat up the hill,
but not very far up the hill.
Just think about taking a string,
attaching it to here and here,
and pulling it tight.
Alright?
It'll climb partway up the hill.
There'll also be another geodesic by
symmetry which goes around the other way.
I'm assuming these two points are
symmetrically related to the hill over here.
In fact,
there's even a third one.
And the third one goes right through the center here,
but it probably somehow is a local,
that's a local maximum of the distance.
It's a geodesic by virtue of the fact that it's,
the tangent vector is covariantly constant.
It is not a geodesic if
what you meant was a minimum distance.
It's a minimum of the distance between two points.
It happens to be a maximum.
It has the peculiar property that if you had a string
and you pulled it tight and you kept it perfectly symmetric,
you would pull it right over the
top of the hill and it would form,
it'll go right over the top of the hill,
but if you displaced it a little bit,
it would be unstable and it would
slide off the top of the hill.
So it's actually a maximum of the length.
Local.
What's that?
Only a local maximum.
Oh yeah,
yeah,
of course.
It's only a local,
yes,
it's a local maximum.
But it is a geodesic.
According to the official rules of geodesics,
it's a geodesic.
Where the official rule means that
the tangent vector is covariantly constant.
So,
good.
Those are good questions.
Any more?
Is the second thing a stable and unstable geodesic?
Well,
you can have a maximum
or a minimum of the distance,
yeah.
If it's a maximum,
then it's an unstable.
Yeah.
What it means,
what that means for the motion of
a particle or something is another story,
but that's a little...
So what you did back then is you actually
showed that you didn't even do the calculus of variations,
you just took the proper time
expression and you broke it up.
Can you do that in more generality,
just to say a mass distribution,
and show that you come up with a geodesic equation?
The geodesic equation will always be the
equation that the tangent vector is covariantly constant.
Now,
what are you asking now?
I'm asking,
you've got two calculus of variations problems.
One says minimize the logarithm,
the other says maximize the proper time,
and you show those were equivalent in
special relativity with flat space and no other...
That's almost the definition.
Yeah.
The question is,
what's the definition of the action?
Well,
sorry,
we compared variation of distance with variation of action?
Variation of action,
yeah.
Yeah.
The variation of proper time with variation of action.
Well,
that's just because by definition,
the action for a particle moving in space-time,
by definition,
is minus its mass times...
times the proper time.
So that's essentially a definition.
Lagrangian,
so we get to that.
Right,
and you can get the Lagrangian from this.
We could do that.
I mean,
it doesn't take very long.
It's pretty easy to do.
Let's do it.
Good.
Let's do it,
and you can work out Lagrange's equations
and show that they are the same
as demanding that the covariant derivative
of the tangent vector is zero.
Okay,
so the definition of the action along a
trajectory is minus the mass times the proper
time along the trajectory,
and the proper time squared
along a differential little piece
of it here is d tau squared equals g ij,
let's say,
g mn of position,
won't bother writing
what it is,
dxm dxn.
Good.
All right.
Now all we have to do
is take the square root of this,
that's d tau,
and then integrate
it to find the total
path length from here to here.
So the total path length is the integral,
this is kind of a funny thing to see,
an
integral of a square root with a dx dx,
but I'll make sense of
it for you in a moment,
g mn dxm dxn minus m.
That's the minus m which appears here.
All right.
That's the action.
Now what can I do to
it to make it look more familiar?
Pick one of the coordinates,
a time coordinate.
Let's pick time,
x naught,
and let's call it time.
This is g mn,
mn,
and so forth.
Okay?
And let's write this whole thing out.
It first of all has the space-like components,
in other words,
when mn and nn are both space-like.
Then there's the mixture.
So this space-time components plus twice
g m naught dxm dx naught.
Why did I put a 2 there?
Because g m,
because it's symmetric.
There's an equal one from g
m naught and from g naught m.
All right.
So I just wrote it this way.
g m naught dx m dx naught.
And then the last term is plus g mn,
mn,
dxm,
dxm.
Now let's call dxm,
mn,
let's call it t.
Let's call it xm,
mn,
t.
So this just becomes dt.
Okay.
Now let's divide and multiply by dt squared.
Let's divide,
multiply here by dt.
And now divide this whole thing by dt.
But if I do it inside the square root,
that means dividing by dt squared.
Right?
If I want to divide by dt,
but then I want to put
the dt into the square root,
I make it dt squared.
Okay.
Let's look at what we have.
dxm by dt times dxn by dt.
What is that?
It's the same thing.
That's the product of velocities.
This is the mth component of the velocity.
This is the nth component of the velocity.
Here we have 1 dt cancels,
and we have dxm by dt.
That's also a component.
That's something linear in the velocity.
And what about this here?
What did I do here?
Yeah,
I forgot to call this dt squared.
But I'm dividing it by dt squared,
so this goes away.
Well,
now I have something that really looks like a Lagrangian.
Here it is.
It involves the positions.
Remember,
the g's depend on x.
We have dependence on position
and components of the velocity.
It's a rather complicated Lagrangian.
It's not like the good old nonrelativistic Lagrangian,
which only has 1 half m
x dot squared plus v of x.
Everything occurs in the square root.
That's a big nuisance,
particularly when you start differentiating it.
But you take this Lagrangian,
which depends on the velocities and the coordinates,
and you just do the Euler-Lagrange equations.
And that will give you the
equations of motion for the particle.
It is also the same thing as minimizing,
maximizing,
making stationary the proper distance,
or the proper time.
And it will allow you to
construct an energy function and so forth.
So this is the Lagrangian for a
point particle moving in an arbitrary gravitational field.
You can take this.
You can work out Lagrange's equations.
And prove that they are the same as...
Let's see what they're the same as.
Okay,
it's a little bit of
a nuisance for the following reason.
The equation for your geodesic
in terms of the tangent vector
has been d second x by d s squared,
or d tau squared,
plus...
Anybody remember what else there is?
d...
That's the equation for a geodesic.
Now,
the nuisance part of it is that
this is going to give you an equation
where the independent variables are the same.
is going to be time.
You're going to work this out
and you're going to write equations
for x as a function of time.
So the equations are going to be second order equations,
good
old Euler-Lagrange equations,
and they're going to involve things like dx by dt,
whereas
this is in terms of dx by d tau.
So what you'll have to do
is you have to convert everything
to t notation instead of tau notation.
So let's,
for example,
say this is a space-like
component,
let's call it m,
m,
and the other ones stay the way they are.
All right,
the
first thing we have to do
is deal with this guy here.
This is dx m by d tau,
d by d tau,
but we simply use the rule
that differentiating with respect to t,
to tau is the same as differentiating with
respect to t and then multiplying by dt by
d tau.
But what is dt by d tau?
d t by d tau is not one.
It's not one.
We have to remember
what t is in terms of tau.
t and we have to work
out what dt by d tau is,
but we know
what it is.
the,
all right,
let's work it out.
d tau squared is equal
to g naught naught dt squared
plus g naught 1 dx1 squared,
blah,
blah.
And then we simply divide this by d tau squared,
1,
d tau squared,
d tau,
same thing,
sort of thing.
And then we solve for dt by d tau.
We just solve for dt by d tau.
That tells us what dt by d tau is.
And it's just some complicated thing
involving the metric and the velocities.
So something complicated but known goes
in here for dt by d tau.
And then we do the same thing again.
d by dt,
d by d tau is d
by dt times dt by d tau.
Do the same thing here.
Gamma,
dot,
dot.
And instead of writing dx by ds,
we write dx by dt,
dt by,
this is tau,
sorry,
tau.
I'm getting myself mixed up.
We just rework it so that it becomes an
equation of motion for x as a function of time.
It's easy to do.
It's just elementary calculus.
And it's the same equation as this.
Let's not do it.
It's more of a nuisance than anything.
But the point is the logic.
Logic is that the principle of least action and the principle
of least proper time are the same thing in any metric.
So if you plug in a metric,
you'll automatically retrieve a Lagrangian
for the motion of the particle.
Notice this g naught,
naught here.
Let's start.
Let's do a simple example.
Let's suppose that only g naught,
naught was interesting.
By interesting,
it means different than the flat space metric.
Let's suppose that g naught,
naught was different.
What is g naught,
naught in flat space time?
One,
right?
One.
All right.
Let's leave.
Let's simplify these by going to flat space.
Then what's g m n?
Delta m n,
right?
No.
g m n.
Delta m n or minus delta m n.
All right.
So this becomes essentially the x
m dot the x m squared.
I may have the sign wrong.
We may need a minus sign.
This one I'll take to be zero.
In flat space time,
g m naught is just zero.
So let's forget this.
And then we have g naught,
naught of x.
Okay?
Supposing that,
have I missed anything?
I did miss,
what did I miss?
I missed something.
I think I missed the term
which is dt by dt squared.
Oh.
Add me to the scale.
No,
that's here,
right?
Yeah.
That's here,
that's here.
That's just one.
That's just one except that
I don't wanna make that approximation.
I want to let g n,
n vary.
Newtonian approximation.
The only thing that's not absolutely Newtonian,
or the only thing
that's not absolutely flat space here is
that g naught naught might depend on x.
Alright,
now suppose the velocity is small.
The velocity is small.
How do you expand out
something like this?
How do you expand out,
what do we have?
We have square root of 1
plus something small.
This is 1 plus something small.
It's 1 plus something small,
and the
something small consists of delta g naught
naught and the square root of the velocity.
Okay,
so what's the rule for
square root of 1 plus s?
1 plus s over 2.
Okay,
so let's work it out.
First of all,
we get minus m.
I'm making a mess of this blackboard,
but let's keep going.
Minus m times,
now it's 1 plus s over 2.
Let's start with 1.
And now plus s over 2.
So what's s over 2?
Plus delta g naught naught over 2.
Minus,
let's just call it x dot squared over 2.
That's this term over here.
Hmm?
Yeah.
Okay.
Do I have it all right?
Yeah.
Okay.
So,
the first term is just,
why is it minus m?
Oh,
it is minus m.
It's actually correct,
minus m.
The first term is minus m.
M.
Right?
The next term is minus
delta g naught naught over 2.
And then plus m x dot squared over 2.
What's this term?
Well,
that's very familiar.
It's just mv squared.
1 half mv squared.
What's this term over here?
This is not the energy,
incidentally.
This is the Lagrangian.
The Lagrangian is related to the energy
by changing the sign of the potential energy.
These two are potential energies.
These two don't depend on velocities,
they're potential energies.
So basically,
yeah.
M where?
Oh,
m here,
right?
Yeah.
Okay,
so in terms of energy,
you would change the sign of these two.
The first term,
what would that be?
Risk.
It doesn't matter,
does it?
Any energy.
No,
it doesn't matter.
But what would it be?
The energy.
Yeah.
It's the energy when the particle has no motion.
And if I kept all the speeds of light,
this would just be minus m c squared.
Why minus m c squared?
Because it's in the Lagrangian,
not the energy.
The energy,
you change the sign here.
What's this one over here?
The potential energy.
It's the potential energy.
And then the potential energy
here is the센 in this form.
But now we remember something.
We come back to something familiar,
that the gravitational potential,
normally we would
have,
I think it's minus the gravitational potential here.
So minus m times the gravitational potential
is just delta G naught naught over two.
Minus or plus.
I think we'll,
I think we'll do a plus if I,
no,
I think with a minus,
if I remember.
I always,
I always did a minus.
always lose track of the sign.
M,
with an M.
So what do we find?
We find the equation that
says that the gravitational potential
is just equal to delta G0 0 over 2.
Now,
why delta G0 0?
Do you remember earlier we identified G0 0 over 2
with phi?
Do you remember that equation?
Right.
Why do I write delta G0 0?
Well,
the point is that we don't
really identify G0 0 with phi.
We identify G0 0 with phi plus a constant.
It was the derivatives of G0 0
that we identified with the derivatives of phi.
So we can add a constant to G0 0.
And delta G0 0 just means the deviation from
the constant.
So this is just a good old equation
that we had relating G0 0 to the gravitational potential.
So you can work with these equations.
It wasn't my goal in this
class to spend a lot of time
working with these equations,
but just mainly showing you
what they are.
And of course,
they're much harder
than Newton's equations in the sense,
not conceptually,
but in the sense that.
Ha.
Whenever you have a square root to start differentiating,
you're going to have trouble.
So solving the equations is more difficult.
But conceptually,
it's just the same Euler-Lagrange equations
that,
OK,
where were we?
Let's get started.
I did want tonight to
study black holes a little bit,
the black hole metric.
Actually,
this was a good starting point.
But let's just go through the Schwarzschild black hole.
Now,
before we do that,
it's very important
to understand the concept of an accelerated reference
frame in relativity.
An accelerated reference frame is
something which can have meaning in special relativity
or in general relativity.
And we begin with special relativity,
in particular,
the accelerated reference frame
is simply the reference frame in ordinary special relativity
as seen by an accelerated observer.
But it's a little bit different.
It's a little more subtle
than it is in normal physics,
normal Newtonian physics.
Let's draw spacetime.
Here's spacetime.
Here's a light cone.
Light travels on 45 degree axes.
Time is vertically upward.
X goes out of the blackboard this way.
And y and z are
only going along for the ride.
We don't even need to think about them.
They stick out of the blackboard,
but we're not going to play very much with them.
All right,
now,
if you remember,
an accelerated reference frame
in Newtonian mechanics is one whose coordinates are curved.
And they're parabolas,
the parabolas all of which are sort
of parallel to each other.
And they just correspond to the acceleration
of the motion of an observer
at rest in the moving frame.
So at rest in the moving frame means
moving along one of these lines.
And that observer is an accelerated observer.
Notice one point.
Well,
that is what an accelerated observer is.
The acceleration is uniform.
We assume the acceleration is uniform.
And that means at any given time,
if that observer measures
his own acceleration,
and you can measure acceleration,
you know,
you could feel acceleration.
Acceleration has an uncomfortable effect.
The acceleration all along here is constant.
So that poor observer who is being accelerated
with 25 g's of acceleration is uncomfortable,
but equally uncomfortable at all times,
including times at which he's coming in from far away.
All right.
What kind of observer in special relativity
corresponds to a uniformly accelerated observer?
It's one who feels the same amount of acceleration
at all times.
You might think,
again,
that that's a parabola.
In other words,
x equals,
let's say,
constant x0 plus tc
plus.
Acceleration times t squared.
Acceleration over 2 times t squared.
Well,
that's going to quickly make that observer move faster
than the speed of light.
Remember,
with a uniform acceleration,
velocity is equal to acceleration times time.
So if you wait long enough,
you'll
be moving with faster than the speed of light.
That can't be what a real accelerated reference frame is.
Anybody moving faster than the
speed of light feels something
very,
very different than what we feel.
And I don't know what it is.
OK.
So that can't be the right idea.
The right idea is a hyperbola.
I'll explain why in a minute.
An observer moving along a hyperbola in special relativity
is a uniformly accelerated reference frame.
Now,
you can take that hyperbola to be the hyperbola,
which is an elliptic.
So x squared minus t
squared is equal to a constant.
x squared minus t squared
equals a constant is a hyperbola.
And it's a hyperbola of radius,
let's call it c squared.
It's a hyperbola of radius c.
In other words,
the distance from the origin here,
at closest
approach.
This is at closest approach,
the distance of the hyperbola is c.
Now,
a hyperbola like this is Lorentz invariant.
That means if you do a Lorentz transformation,
the hyperbola goes into itself.
How do I know that?
I know that because x squared minus t
squared is an invariant of a Lorentz transformation.
We've gone through this several times.
x squared minus t squared is the thing
which doesn't change when you do a Lorentz transformation.
And that's because x squared minus t squared is the
thing which doesn't change when you do a Lorentz transformation.
In other words,
if I do a Lorentz transformation and I have a
point at which x squared minus t squared equals c squared,
if I Lorentz transform it,
after the Lorentz transform,
it will still be on the same hyperboloid.
The mathematics of this is almost the
same as saying you have a circle,
which would be x squared
plus y squared equals a constant,
and saying that a rotation preserves the circle.
A rotation preserves the circle.
A rotation about the origin preserves the circle.
In the same way,
if you do a Lorentz transformation,
this curve will simply slide into itself.
That curve is Lorentz invariant.
And that means what's going
on at this point over here,
as far as the observer moving along here,
is exactly the same as what's going on over here.
He feels the same thing here as he feels here,
as he feels here,
and so forth.
The mathematics is very similar to
saying that somebody going in a circle
would feel the same thing here as here,
as here,
as here.
There's a symmetry to the problem.
And the symmetry is such
that somebody traveling along this trajectory
will feel a constant influence
of the acceleration at all times.
Okay.
That's the idea of a uniformly accelerated,
accelerated object in special relativity.
Now,
does it ever exceed the speed of light?
What are the asymptotes of this hyperbola?
It's asymptotic.
Its asymptotes are simply the light cones.
It never gets up to the light cone.
It never exceeds the speed of light.
It just asymptotically gets closer and
closer to the speed of light.
That's what a uniformly accelerated
object is in special relativity.
Something which is approaching the speed
of light with uniform proper acceleration.
Proper acceleration means the acceleration
in the observer's rest frame.
As the observer is being accelerated,
that observer in his own frame of reference
senses always identical acceleration,
point by point as he moves along.
Very,
very much like an observer moving in a circle
would experience the same acceleration
moving around in a circle.
Okay.
So this is what is called a uniformly accelerated object.
A uniformly accelerated reference frame
is a reference frame
that is really just you start at t equals zero.
Here's t equals zero.
And you mark off a bunch of meter sticks.
And then you let each meter stick
whoops,
I didn't draw that very well
move on its own hyperboloid.
On its own hyperbola.
And that becomes a uniformly accelerated reference frame.
But what that means,
if this hyperbola here is
x squared minus t squared,
equals c squared,
let's call it one.
Let's say this is one meter.
One meter,
meter stick,
the end of the one meter meter stick is at
x squared minus t squared equals one.
What about the two meter stick?
What's its equation?
x squared minus t squared equals,
what do you want to write?
Four.
Two squared.
x squared minus t squared equals nine.
And so forth.
Okay,
that's a uniformly accelerated family,
a family of uniformly accelerated
ends of meter sticks.
Now what about time?
Time along these meter sticks
ticks off along here.
And it corresponds,
a good,
this is a definition,
a definition of time
is to do the same kind of Lorentz transformation
on this line here
to move the line forward
from one time to the next
time along each of these hyperboloids.
That would look like this.
Here would be time.
Remember when you do a Lorentz transformation,
the surface of constant time,
the surface of simultaneity,
what an observer calls simultaneous,
gets tilted.
So what we're doing is we're
making a series of Lorentz transformations
along this trajectory to make them go
faster and faster and faster and faster,
and the surface of simultaneity
is getting more and more constant.
And the surface of simultaneity
is getting more and more tilted.
I'll write the equations for these things in a moment.
But this is what a uniformly accelerated reference,
this is the closest thing that there is
to a uniformly accelerated reference frame.
Each one of these observers
sees something going on which is time independent.
It sure looks like it's time dependent,
looks like it's going faster over here,
but what they feel in their own rest frame
is identical,
all along the trajectory.
But does this one feel the same as this one?
As the same as this one?
No.
You can see that
from the circle analogy.
From the circle analogy,
imagine
a family of observers
moving in circular orbits
all attached to the same
rigid rods here.
Would these observers all see the same acceleration?
No.
Who gets the biggest acceleration?
One on the outside.
One on the inside.
You make a tight turn,
and it's a bigger acceleration.
Am I right?
Did I get it right?
Yeah.
You're right.
The horn latch on the outside,
they're observed on the outside.
Yeah.
More curved on the inside here
than the outside.
Okay,
actually the right thing to be thinking about
is uniform velocity,
not the...
If it was the same velocity,
they all have the same velocity.
That's the appropriate analogy.
Not that they're attached to sticks this way.
Yeah.
They all have the same velocity.
They all move with the same velocity.
That corresponds to the...
Well,
okay.
That's the right thing to do.
All right.
These observers see different accelerations,
not with time,
but with where they are along here.
In fact,
the deeper in you go,
the larger the acceleration of these observers.
The acceleration,
in fact,
is basically one over the distance from the origin.
One over the proper distance from the origin
is the acceleration.
That's the closest thing that there is in special relativity
to the concept of a uniformly,
accelerated reference frame.
You might ask,
why not just take one of these uniformly accelerated guys,
which is a hyperbola,
and then take another hyperbola displaced from it
by the same...
by a given distance,
so that each one is
sort of parallel to the other
and they all experience the same acceleration.
Well,
what would happen?
This would be a very odd coordinate system.
The reason being,
the distance between each neighboring observer
would change with time.
Why is that?
Because things are...
In my frame of reference,
standing here,
I've kept the distance fixed.
This distance is the same as this distance,
is the same as this distance.
But what happens in the reference frames
which are accelerating?
In the reference frames which are accelerating,
the moving observers see these points
get further and further apart.
So that's not a good definition
of an accelerated reference frame.
This is the best that you can do.
All right?
And notice that it has the feature,
as you get closer and closer to the center here,
the acceleration goes up and up and up.
Another way to say it
is that people moving on these trajectories
experience effective gravitational fields.
Why?
Because acceleration and gravity
have the same effect on things.
So if we had an elevator over here
that was being accelerated this way
and another one over here being accelerated this way
and another one being over here accelerated this way,
they would experience different gravitational fields
larger and larger and larger
until you got to the observer
who was
at such a small distance here
that they have an enormous acceleration
as they go around this bend.
As they go around this bend in space-time
is an enormous acceleration
in a very small amount of time,
proper time,
from here to here,
the velocity has changed a great deal.
Get even closer
and in an even smaller distance,
the velocity changes a lot.
Smaller amount of time,
so these ones are the ones
that are maximally accelerated.
These ones out here
have a very negligible acceleration.
That's a constant acceleration.
Constant along the trajectory,
but not constant from observer to observer.
So effectively,
what we have here
is a series of people
in this reference frame,
a series of people separated
by fixed distances,
but each one of them
The other one is you go down the line
feeling a stronger and stronger
gravitational field.
The one in here is experiencing
an enormous gravitational field
because he's so highly accelerated.
The one out here experiences
a very negligible gravitational field.
Or you can think of it as a sequence
of accelerators,
not elevators,
where the elevator lowest down,
very close to here,
is experiencing a very large acceleration.
The elevator up high
is accelerating with a small acceleration.
And so in this kind of geometry
and special relativity,
there really is no such thing
as a uniform gravitational field.
The effective gravitational field,
from the equivalence principle,
the effective gravitational field
for a uniformly accelerated observer
becomes infinite at that point.
Now there's nothing happening there,
nothing special happening there.
This is flat space-time.
It's just that we're accelerating
these observers.
Somebody is giving them rocket ships
or doing something
to accelerate these observers.
Maybe in this picture,
of course,
x corresponds to
the vertical direction of space,
t being the vertical direction
of space-time,
is not the direction
that elevators move in.
These elevators are moving horizontally.
So that's the vertical direction.
What happens,
supposing this observer
who is being accelerated,
he's being accelerated,
a rope is pulling him,
okay?
A rope is pulling him
and causing him to accelerate,
or a rocket is accelerating him.
Some thrust is causing him
to accelerate and move
down this trajectory.
What happens
if this observer,
out of his rocket ship,
drops a rock or anything else?
What does that rock do?
It is not connected
to the accelerating device.
It's not connected to the rockets.
It's not connected to the cables
that are pulling the...
What does it do?
It moves in a straight line.
Right.
It's going down from one hyperboloid
to the next.
And eventually passes through
that point over there.
So when he throws this rock
out of the rocket ship,
let's say he just drops it,
just drops it,
doesn't throw it,
just drops it.
So the rock is moving
with the same velocity
as the spaceship over here.
Just drops the rock out.
But of course,
the rock is not being accelerated.
So the spaceship is being accelerated
away from the rock,
but from the observer's point of view,
the rock is falling.
Where is it falling toward?
It's falling from one hyperboloid
to the next hyperboloid
to the next.
And so it's falling down.
It's falling down
into this region
of enormously large acceleration.
Is it getting accelerated?
No.
But does it look like
it's getting accelerated
relative to these observers?
Sure.
So this object...
What's that?
Well,
we're going to see
that it takes forever.
Yes.
We're going to see
it takes forever.
Well,
we have to define
these time sections correctly.
Yes.
Okay.
But before we do,
we can get a general picture
of what's going on.
Now,
there's one other thing
which is kind of interesting.
Think of all these observers.
Think of this rock passing here.
This is a very special kind of rock.
It's a musical rock.
Well,
maybe...
And it's a special kind of music.
It's carried by light waves
instead of sound waves.
All right?
So it's a music
that's flashing music
and sending out light rays.
The observer over here...
Let's draw him more clearly.
Let's get rid of this rock over here.
This rock which falls through over here,
the musical rock over here,
sends out light rays.
And this observer over here
experiences them.
Okay?
But once he has passed through
this point here,
this light cone here,
no signal that he ever sends
will ever get to this observer.
No signal from here
will ever get out past this light cone.
That's the restriction
that nothing moves faster
than the speed of light.
So any signal that this rock sends
will never get out
to the observers out here.
This geometry has what is called...
Or this geometry or this coordinate system
has what is called an event horizon.
This...
Now,
there's no black hole around.
There's not even anything gravitating.
There's just a uniformly accelerated
coordinate system,
musical rocks
which fall through the light cone here
because they move in straight lines.
But from outside,
once that rock has passed,
once the musical rock has passed the...
the light cone,
or the light-like surface here,
it's gone.
It's gone.
It cannot report any activity
beyond that point.
It might help to notice
that the rock actually isn't moving.
The only thing that's happening
is the time is allowed.
So it's not moving.
Well,
it might be moving,
but it also might be not moving in...
Yeah.
That's correct.
It wouldn't be moving
in the stationary reference frame.
Yeah,
let's draw that more accurately.
That's correct.
It's not...
If it happened to be let off the ship
at exactly this point here
where the hyperboloid was vertical,
it would just move up straight,
and in our reference frame
where we're drawing this picture,
the rock would be standing still.
Okay.
And it might be emitting signals.
Those signals would go up,
but once it passes this point,
it can no longer send any signal
to what I'll think of
as the outside world now.
We'll think of this as the outside world,
and we'll think of this
as some place behind an event horizon.
Question?
Yeah.
At this point,
is the origin there...
Is that arbitrary,
or...
Is what?
Is the origin...
Yeah.
The origin...
Right,
right,
right.
But let's...
I'm thinking of these
as real material observers,
not just a coordinate frame for a moment,
but real material observers
connected by meter sticks
watching what's going on.
The origin is...
Right.
Well,
of course,
this observer over here
could always decide at some moment
to disconnect himself
from the accelerating device
and just fall through
and make contact with this.
That's fine,
but no observer who stays on the outside,
no observer who makes sure
that he stays to the right of this light cone,
who doesn't allow himself
to fall through that light cone,
can ever get a signal from behind here.
So that's the...
Yeah.
Wouldn't the rock move in a path
that's sort of tangent to the hyperbola?
Over here.
Since it has an increasing...
X with time.
If it was dropped off
right at this time,
okay,
let's see.
If it was dropped off later...
If it was dropped off later,
yes,
it would move this way.
So it's more of an angle like that...
Yes,
but it would still pass this light cone
because it's moving slower
than the speed of light.
Right.
Yeah.
So at some point,
it would pass this point of no return,
shall we call it.
The rock can still get signals
from the observer?
Yes,
the rock can still get signals
from the outside.
Right.
The rock can get signals
from the outside.
Right.
So the horizon is a kind of one-way door
or one-way membrane,
I don't know what to call it,
one-way filter...
One-way mirror.
One-way what?
Mirror.
One-way...
Well,
no,
it's not a mirror.
I don't think it's a mirror to anybody.
Nobody sees anything reflected off it.
It's just a one-way,
that's all.
Why?
Because it's a mirror.
Right.
One-way door,
a doorway to...
Okay.
Now,
let's actually write some coordinates.
I'm going to actually tell you in detail
what the coordinate transformation is.
Was there a question?
From the ordinary reference frame
to the uniformly accelerated one.
Questions?
No questions.
Good.
Is it clear what's going on in that picture?
I think it's pretty clear.
And this is kind of a quintessential example
of a horizon.
And one of the interesting things
that you can see about the horizon
is that for somebody who falls through it,
nothing special happens.
It's just a non-event.
Whereas for the person from the outside,
they're seeing something rather peculiar.
And we'll try to figure out what it is
that they see peculiar
as the rock rides on its trajectory.
Okay,
let's go back to circles for a minute.
Here's circles.
Here's X,
and instead of calling this T,
I'll call it Y.
But not Y.
So you'll notice that Y
is a great deal like time here.
What is the coordinate transformation
from polar coordinates to,
or from X and Y to polar coordinates?
That's the relationship,
in fact,
between the accelerated reference frame
and the ordinary reference frame.
The ordinary reference frame is like X and Y,
and the accelerated reference frame
is more like polar coordinates.
Okay?
So the polar coordinates here are R and theta.
Theta is angle,
and it sweeps you along a circle.
As theta varies,
keeping R fixed,
you stay on a circle,
but you sweep along it.
That sounds awfully much like staying on a hyperbola
and sweeping along it.
So theta must be something like time.
Time along this trajectory here,
because it varies along a circle,
but doesn't vary as you go in and out.
Okay.
What's the connection between X,
Y,
R,
and theta?
I think we've done this more than once.
X is R cosine theta,
and Y is R sine theta.
And notice that X squared
plus Y squared equals R squared.
That's because cosine squared plus sine squared equals 1.
Okay?
What's the relationship over here?
The relationship is almost identical,
except that you replace sines and cosines
with hyperbolic angles.
Now,
do we all know what hyperbolic angles are?
Do you know what sine and cosines are?
We do,
don't we?
Because we've learned it before.
We learned it in the fall.
Good.
So at least some of us who remember,
remember.
All right.
The answer is X equals...
We can use the coordinate R again,
and R just tells us which
one of these hyperboloids we're on.
It tells us how,
at the moment of closest approach over here,
it tells us how far we are from the origin.
That's the same R as appears over here.
But instead of theta,
I'm not going to call it theta.
I'm going to give it another name.
I'm going to call it omega,
and I'm going to write R hyperbolic cosine of omega,
and Y equals R sinh omega.
Omega is the thing which varies along here.
Let's see what it is at this point over here.
It's R equals 1.
What is,
and let's call this now omega equals 0.
This is omega equals 1.
This would be omega equals 2,
and so forth.
This would be omega equals minus 1.
And omega is the thing which varies along here.
Which the observer along here
experiences as a kind of time.
It varies from here to here to here to here.
Hyperbolic cosine,
what does hyperbolic cosine range over?
From what to what?
Or what does omega range over?
Minus infinity to plus infinity.
Hyperbolic angles are not like ordinary angles.
They don't go from 0 to
2 pi and come back to themselves.
They vary from omega equals minus infinity way down here.
So this observer coming in from a long
way off starts at omega equals minus infinity,
comes up,
and then goes back out,
and eventually is omega plus infinity.
So omega equals plus infinity is way,
way out here on the ends of the hyperboloids,
the asymptotes of the hyperboloid.
Omega equals 0 is over here.
And this is the coordinate transformation.
From hyperbolic to hyperbolic
to accelerated coordinate system.
I don't call this t.
It is the time that
the accelerated coordinate observer will use.
I don't call it t because
we've already called t something else.
So omega is a kind of time.
Notice that it does vary in a time-like direction.
It doesn't vary as you move horizontally.
It moves,
at least over here,
varies as you move vertically.
Okay,
that's the...
Why is that y instead of t?
Sorry,
t.
My mistake.
T.
Okay.
Right.
That's the coordinate transformation.
And what about the other two coordinates of space?
Z and y.
Different y.
Not that y.
Just the other two coordinates of space,
y and z.
What do we do with them?
Nothing.
That has to do with the fact that if you're...
Lorentz transform along a given direction,
the perpendicular coordinates don't change.
All right?
So as this fellow is being accelerated,
and he has meter sticks oriented
in the direction perpendicular to the acceleration,
nothing happens to them.
Okay,
so y and z,
nothing happens to them.
That's the uniformly accelerated reference frame.
And this is the event horizon
for the uniformly accelerated reference frame.
What else do we have to say about this?
Uh...
I wanted to say something else about this.
Oh,
yeah.
Let's work out the metric.
The metric of flat space.
Now we're talking about flat space.
All right?
This is flat space time.
But I want to write its metric
in terms of r and cosh omega.
Okay?
Uh,
we can do this in a number of ways.
Let's just brute force it.
What is dx?
dx is equal to dr times cosh omega
plus r times the derivative of cosh omega,
which is sinh omega,
times d omega.
All I've done here was write this.
This is the differential of a product.
This is the differential of
the first factor times the second
plus the second factor times the differential of the first.
And the differential of cosh
omega is sinh omega d omega.
What about dt?
dt is equal to dr,
sinh omega,
plus r,
cosh omega,
d omega.
omega.
I've used the fact that the
differential of sinh omega is cosh omega.
Now let's calculate the metric.
We know what the metric is.
The metric is dt
squared minus dx squared,
right?
Flat spacetime.
I'm not even going to worry
about y and z,
they just go along for the ride.
So let's write down the
metric,
d tau squared equals dt squared minus dx squared.
Okay,
let's see what we get.
From dt squared we're going to get a dr squared.
So first of all we'll get a dr squared,
but then from dx squared we'll also get
a dr squared term.
And what are we going to get?
We're going to get dr squared
times,
let's see,
I've got to be careful here,
I'll get the,
yeah I'll get,
I've got
to keep my negative sign straight.
dt squared,
d tau squared equals dt squared.
Yeah,
we're okay,
we're okay.
Okay,
so good.
So what do I get from
the two terms with the dr squared?
We'll get
sinh squared minus cosh squared,
right?
Sinh squared minus cosh squared.
What's
sinh squared minus cosh squared?
Sure it's not minus one?
I think it's minus one.
So we get the r squared with a minus sign.
Now we're going to get another
term with a d omega squared.
That one's going to have cosh squared minus sin squared,
there's an r here,
cosh squared minus sin squared.
What's cosh squared minus sin squared?
One.
But we're also going to have an r squared.
So there's going to be
plus r squared d omega squared.
And then there's going to be some other terms.
There's going to be a term,
for example,
from dt squared here,
we'll have a term with dr times d omega.
A cross term in the metric.
But let's look at it.
What's it going to have?
It's going to have sin omega,
cosh omega times r.
Well there's going to be a cross term from here.
Cosh omega,
sin omega times r.
The two cross terms are the same,
except that we're subtracting dt squared from dx squared.
The result is they cancel.
There are no cross terms.
This is the metric of flat
spacetime in uniformly accelerated coordinate system.
Now a uniformly accelerated coordinate
system should be thought of
as only a linear equation.
That's the only thing that's going to
be thought of as a linear equation.
It's only covering the part out here.
It doesn't cover the region in here.
We can make it cover the region in here.
But think of it as r greater than zero.
This is the metric.
And it's the metric that describes everything
in this uniform accelerated reference frame here.
It's flat spacetime.
It's just flat spacetime.
But notice what it has.
It has g naught naught equals one.
And it has g r r equal to r squared.
Incidentally,
the other components of the minus r squared?
Sorry,
do I?
Just,
just,
yeah,
yeah.
g omega omega equals one.
g r r equals minus.
No,
no,
no.
r squared.
And g r r equals minus one.
This is kind of an interesting metric here.
g omega omega is like
the time-time component of the metric.
Notice that it varies from time to time.
It's like r squared.
It varies.
And remember that g naught naught
is very much like the Newtonian potential.
We have a Newtonian potential which is
growing as we move out in r.
That's the reason that things fall toward the origin.
They fall towards the origin because
the time-time component of the metric,
which is like the gravitational potential,
is increasing as we go away from the origin.
So in this accelerated coordinate system where g
naught naught is not just equal to one,
but where it varies with distance,
there's an effective force on an
object which is pushing it toward the,
toward r equals zero.
So that's everything there is to know,
I think,
about the uniformly accelerated coordinate system.
There's another name for this
region of space-time over here.
When it's described in terms of these coordinates.
It's called Rindler space.
Rindler space.
I don't know why it's called Rindler space.
I presume Rindler was the first one to,
he's certainly not the first one to have studied it.
But his name got attached to it.
He did something,
I'm not sure what.
But that's the uniformly co-ordinate,
uniform acceleration coordinate system.
And Rindler space has a horizon.
That's what makes it interesting.
I have read that the Rindler quadrant for uniformly
accelerated beverage frames are a subset of the Minkowski space.
Well,
it's obviously a subset of Minkowski space.
It's a quadrant,
though.
Yeah.
What is the geodesic movement in this?
Well,
that's,
okay,
good.
First of all,
what does it look like in,
here's the geodesic.
What does it look like in R and omega?
Well,
R equals zero is not just a point over here.
R equals zero,
or R very,
very tiny.
R very tiny is this whole hyperboloid
which is very close to the light cone.
The whole light cone can be
thought of as R equals zero.
It's an extension of R equals zero.
All right.
So what happens is the particle
pops out of R equals zero.
Let's plot its motion,
or let's draw its motion.
Now let's plot omega and R.
Omega and R,
these are the coordinates
in the accelerated reference frame.
Okay.
So let's start at omega equals,
this is omega equals minus infinity.
Omega way,
way down here is omega equals minus infinity,
which means from this point of view,
the very remote past,
very remote past these incoming asymptotic hyperbolas,
the particle comes in,
crosses R equals zero.
So long in the past,
it's at R equals zero.
It pops out.
It pops out and goes all
the ways out to R equals,
let's say,
one.
It pops out,
goes to R equals one,
turns around,
and falls back in.
That's what happens over here.
It's gone from the remote past to the remote future.
Jumped out in the remote past,
gone through some maximum R.
In other words,
it's in a gravitational field.
There's a gravitational field pulling everything that way.
It threw it out in the remote past.
It jumped out and fell back in.
It never crossed R equals zero.
Well,
I say it never crossed R.
You say,
sure it crossed R.
It crossed R equals zero.
It crossed R equals zero over here.
But what Rindler time does that correspond to?
This omega is called the Rindler time.
It corresponds to omega equals minus infinity.
So from the point of
view of the accelerated reference frame,
the observer sees the particle jump out at the very,
very remote past
and then fall back in.
Once it's fallen back in,
can't see it anymore.
But at what point in time
does it fall back in over here?
Omega time equals infinity.
So from the perspective of this
observer here in his coordinate system,
it never passes through the horizon over here.
It just takes an infinite amount of omega
time to see it pass through the origin
or to have it pass through the origin.
In fact,
an observer out here can
never see it pass through here.
Any observer looks back and sees the particle,
no matter how late he looks back,
he always sees the particle
on the outside of the horizon.
So what somebody outside sees when
we drop a rock through the horizon
sees it just go slower and slower and slower
and take an infinite amount of
his time to pass through the horizon.
Yeah?
What does the rock see if he looks back?
Rock sees,
if he looks out,
nothing very special.
He looks out and he does see these hyperboloids,
these hyperbolas receding away from him all right.
But he can see them.
Well,
let's see,
sorry.
No,
here,
let's redraw the picture.
Let's redraw the picture to
make it a little bit clearer.
I've got too many things on it already.
You're always sitting on the red ship.
Yeah.
I drew that,
yeah,
I drew it the wrong way.
Let's redraw it.
Okay.
So the rock goes through.
Here's the hyperbola.
Now,
the rock cannot send a signal to the outside.
It tries to send a signal to the outside,
it will not go out.
But it can receive signals from the outside.
So this observer can send a
signal that the falling rock will detect.
Yeah,
whatever.
in other words,
this rock will have no difficulty seeing this observer.
In fact,
he will see him recede away from him.
You know,
the later,
over here,
he looks back,
sees him moving practically with the same velocity.
Over here,
he looks back,
and he sees him moving away.
A little later time,
looks back,
and sees him moving away a little bit faster.
But as long as he lasts,
he will look back and be able to
see all of the observers on the outside,
every single one of them.
But the observers on the
outside cannot receive signals from him.
So he can absorb signals,
detect signals,
get information from the outside,
but cannot send it back out.
On the other hand,
from the outside observer's,
the outside means the Rindler space here,
from the outside observer's perspective,
watching this rock fall.
Let's watch,
let's have him watch.
I wish we had more colors.
We've run out of colors.
Alright,
so here's the observer.
Let's get rid of some spurious lines.
And how does he watch?
How do you watch?
You watch by collecting light signals from things.
Alright?
Collecting light signals from the rock means looking back,
along a backward light-like direction,
looks back,
and sees the rock over here.
Goes a little further,
sees the rock over here.
But keeping in mind that this
hyperboloid here asymptotes to the light cone,
as time goes to the very
remote future for the accelerated observer,
all he sees is the rock
get closer and closer to him.
Closer to the horizon,
never passing it.
Yeah?
This is all special relativity,
but in accelerated coordinate systems.
Right.
Now,
what should we find about a gravitating mass?
We should find something about a
gravitational mass that looks like this.
Yeah,
and we will.
It's paradoxical that the
accelerated observer kind of appears,
is missing from a great bit
of the history of the rock.
I mean,
until the rock actually passes the lower acid,
he can't see the accelerated observer.
The accelerated observer doesn't exist.
Yeah,
but there's no accelerated observer in that past.
Right.
But only when he crosses the...
So at some time...
Yes.
That's the sort of inverse...
Inverse of the...
You understand what I mean?
Yeah.
So at some time,
the observer...
The...
The rock.
The rock suddenly sees from very,
very far away,
he sees the observer coming in.
It's created at that time.
It's effectively created at that time.
And then sees him coming in.
Starts seeing,
starts seeing a huge velocity.
Coming in with no message.
If he really can see him,
that would mean that this person was sending photons.
If he was really sending photons and he was
moving with close to the speed of light relative
to the rock,
of course he would be sending very,
very blue shifting photons.
Right.
So he'd get a blast of
radiation from the Earth at this point.
But...
But when I...
Okay.
On the other hand,
the observer out here sees the
rock and sees radiation from the
rock getting redshifted because he's
moving away from the rock.
So he sees...
What he sees is the rock
moving slower and slower to the horizon,
never getting quite
getting there,
and getting all of the signals back to the horizon.
And then he sees the rock
moving progressively more and more redshifted.
That's the nature of our...
What I'm not going to do is
to write down Einstein's equations and solve them.
It's a real mess.
To write them down,
we would have...
First have to work out the curvature tensor,
which means the Christoffel symbols,
and then
differentiate them and then multiply them together
and then contract them to make the
Einstein tensor.
And it is a big,
long mess.
Somebody has done it for us.
There are ways to do it which are more
sophisticated and clever where you can see what the answer
is faster.
But with the straightforward brute force methods,
it is a big mess.
And furthermore,
there are a lot of Einstein equations.
How many of them are there altogether?
Well,
d times d minus 1 over 2 or something.
they're not all independent,
and so it's not really that bad.
Really,
there are only two independent ones that are important.
But they're still quite unpleasant.
What I'm going to do is to tell you
the solution for a particular situation and then analyze
that solution,
analyze the geometry that comes from it,
which is far more fun than solving
the equations.
Now,
what we're trying to do is put together
something which is the analog of a point mass.
Keep in mind that in Newtonian physics,
the solution for a point mass has a degree of
generality which goes beyond the point mass.
If you have any spherically symmetric distribution of
material and you're out of the point mass,
outside the region that encompasses that material,
then the standard Newtonian solution for
the gravitational field is exactly the same
as the point particle at the center.
The same is true in general relativity.
In Newtonian physics,
I believe it's just called Newton's theorem.
In general relativity,
it's called Birkhoff's theorem.
B-I-R-K-O-F-F.
Birkhoff's theorem.
What Birkhoff proved was that any
spherically symmetric distribution of material which is
bounded outside the boundary of the material,
the metric is exactly the same as the metric
of a black hole.
You can think of,
to some extent,
the metric of a black hole
as being the analog of the
metric of the point particle.
Although it is hardly point-based.
It's not particle-ish in any ordinary sense of the word.
Okay,
so I'm simply going to write the answer down.
And we'll look at it,
and some pieces of it we'll recognize.
We'll recognize everything about it,
but some pieces we'll recognize why
they are the way they are.
Other pieces I will simply have to tell you.
But before I do that,
I want to write down flat spacetime.
In polar coordinates.
Now,
not these polar coordinates.
These are the polar coordinates of space.
Not polar coordinates of spacetime,
but just ordinary polar coordinates of space.
Let's just start with space.
Now,
we've written polar coordinates for space many times,
but now I'm talking about three-dimensional
polar coordinates,
not two-dimensional polar coordinates.
We have three-dimensional space.
Now,
this is ordinary space.
not spacetime.
Three-dimensional ordinary space.
And I want to describe it in polar coordinates.
What does polar coordinates mean?
What do polar coordinates mean?
It means that you describe every point as
being at a certain distance from the origin,
r,
having nothing to do with the r's
that I might have written earlier over here.
It doesn't have to do with this.
Forget that.
We're now concentrating on three-dimensional.
Three-dimensional space.
Just put into your notes
now that I have changed notation.
Well,
maybe I should call it capital R.
Perhaps if I called it capital R,
it might be less confusing.
Let's call it capital R.
Distance from the origin.
No?
Oh.
Curvature.
I think it's less.
I don't think you're in too much
danger of confusing a coordinate with a curvature.
But you might confuse this coordinate with that one,
so I won't.
Call it p over 2.
Call it what?
P over 2.
P over 2?
You could call it p over 2.
Let's call it r for radius.
All right.
It's really the radial distance from the origin.
And not a single angle as
you would have in two dimensions,
but rather you think of a
point on the origin.
Imagine a sphere.
A point on a unit sphere.
Imagine a unit sphere.
Begin with a unit sphere.
A unit sphere means one of radius 1.
So it's the Earth except measured in
units in which the Earth has radius 1.
And it takes two angles to describe
a point on the surface of a sphere.
One of them the polar angle,
the other the azimuthal angle.
Which would you prefer to call phi?
I think it's also a point.
Phi is polar angle.
So that means an r,
and a phi and a theta.
Now,
first of all,
let's think about the metric on a sphere.
The metric of a sphere itself.
Let's begin with a unit sphere.
A unit sphere of radius 1.
What is the metric on a unit sphere?
Let's just call it ds squared.
I'm not using d tau squared here,
because I can do it.
because I don't want to
think of it as proper time,
I want to think of it as spatial distance.
ds squared,
anybody remember what it is?
You said that phi was polar coordinate?
Alright,
so it's d phi squared.
And now what are we taking?
Theta,
we're imagining,
is the angle from the
equator or from the north pole?
We can either make a...
Sorry,
wait,
that's this,
this is a...
That's this,
that,
that's...
Are we taking this to be the angle
from the equator or the angle from the equator?
Alright,
okay,
so from the equator,
north pole.
North pole,
angle from the north pole.
Okay,
if it's angle from the north pole,
then we get sine squared theta d phi squared.
And I'm not going to explain that,
I'm going to let you work that out.
That's the metric on a sphere.
Okay?
What's that?
Ah,
d theta squared.
No.
Wait,
what's,
I'm sorry,
what's the definition of the polar angle?
Is it the angle from the pole?
The angle from the pole,
okay,
so from the angle,
that's phi,
right?
We said that's phi.
Yeah.
Oh,
sine squared phi,
good.
I'm getting tired,
I'm getting tired.
So,
sine squared phi,
d theta squared.
Sine squared phi,
good.
Do I have it right?
Yes.
Good.
Good enough.
Alright,
so here's the north pole.
Phi is measured relative to the north pole,
and theta is measured around the equator.
This is the metric of a unit sphere.
Now,
supposing the sphere has radius r.
What do we do with it?
We just multiply it.
We multiply it by r squared.
Every length is r squared times,
every squared length is r squared times bigger
than it would be on the unit sphere.
So,
it just becomes r squared times d phi
squared plus sine of phi squared d theta squared.
Hm?
Did I get it wrong again?
Plus d r squared.
Yeah,
yeah,
not yet,
not yet.
This is,
this is the,
yeah,
you're right.
This is the metric on the sphere itself.
Alright,
so that's the metric between points
on a sphere of radius r.
Now,
what happens if I want to talk about
points which are not on the same radius?
Then I have to include
here ds squared equals dr squared.
Plus that.
In other words,
for points which are separated by radial distance,
it's just the r squared.
And then for points which are separated by angles,
it's r squared times the metric on the unit sphere.
There's another way to write this which everybody usually,
which,
you know,
is common.
Is to write it ds squared is
equal to dr squared plus r squared.
d omega squared.
d omega squared is a shorthand for
writing out the metric on the unit sphere.
So omega d omega squared is a shorthand that,
that's convenient.
And we don't want to
keep writing the thetas and phis.
That's the metric of ordinary flat space.
Uh.
In spherical polar coordinates.
And remember now that omega stands for two directions,
theta and phi.
And the r squared here is just there
because as you go further and further out,
the sphere just gets bigger and bigger.
That's all.
Okay,
that's,
now what about space time?
Supposing we're doing flat space time.
This is the metric of space.
It really is equal to.
Just good old dx squared
plus dy squared plus dz squared.
That's all it is in some other coordinates,
x,
y,
and z.
But what about the metric of space time?
The metric of space time.
Which is d tau squared.
Let's,
let's put it over here.
d tau squared.
Is equal to.
Let's call it dt squared.
Minus dx squared minus dy squared minus d t squared.
That's d z squared.
Right?
That's.
Where do the c's go if we
wanted to put speeds of light in?
I think they would go over here.
If we wanted to put speeds of light in,
they would go over there.
I'll include them a little bit for the moment.
How do we rewrite that in the polar coordinates?
Well,
we just rewrite it as d tau squared
equals dt squared minus exactly what we see here.
The r squared plus r squared
d minus r squared d omega squared.
And I'm not going to.
If I wanted to put the speeds of light in,
they would go in here.
In the denominator.
dt squared minus the r squared
minus r squared d omega squared.
That's the metric of absolutely flat space time.
Just using spherical polar coordinates.
The Schwarzschild metric being the metric of a spherical distribution
of mass is conveniently described in spherical coordinates like this.
When you have a problem
with the symmetry of a sphere,
it's always convenient to use polar coordinates.
If you use polar coordinates,
then I'm now going to write down the
metric and I'll tell you what goes into it.
This is the solution.
It's a solution of Einstein's
equations with any spherically symmetric,
let's say,
energy distribution,
or t naught naught,
with any spherically symmetric distribution of energy.
Outside the boundaries of that range.
So here's the region.
And we look outside the region.
The general solution outside the
region has the following form.
d tau squared equals one.
You know what?
Before I do this,
let me remind you about the Newtonian solution.
The Newtonian solution,
of course,
is in terms of a.
Gravitational potential.
Now we're going to get into trouble.
Gravitational potential is called phi.
Because it's like an angle.
It's not like an angle.
Gravitational potential is capital phi.
Right.
Gravitational potential is gravitational phi.
And what's the solution of
Newton's equations for point mass?
It's just phi equals the mass of the gravitating object,
g,
divided by r,
with a minus sign or a plus sign.
I can't remember.
Minus sign,
right?
Right?
Minus sign.
That's because it's attractive.
It pulls you towards the origin.
Okay.
Now remember what the connection between g naught,
naught,
and phi is.
g naught,
naught,
at least approximately,
is equal to a constant.
Let's write it out.
Is equal to some constant.
When I say constant,
it's a piece which doesn't have a derivative.
And then the piece which has
the derivative is supposed to be plus.
Is it phi over two?
Or is it two phi?
Two phi.
My mistake.
That was the connection that we discovered
several times in discussing motion of particles.
That the motion of a particle connects g naught,
or in relativistic theory,
g naught,
naught replaces phi,
or at least its derivatives do.
There's a factor of two there and an
additive constant which doesn't matter when you differentiate it.
Okay.
That's g naught,
naught.
So,
we would like now to write the metric.
We'll start with some d t squared.
It's the thing which replaces the coefficient one over here.
Flat spacetime has a coefficient one.
Let's see what it has to have.
It's going to be g naught,
naught.
And what I expect is it will have the form,
some constant plus twice phi period.
But phi is just minus mg over r.
Now that may or may not be exact.
Happens that it is exact.
Minus,
there's a factor of two.
And so it's minus two mg over r.
Now what shall I take this constant c to be?
Well,
let's go very,
very far from the black hole.
This is a black hole of stellar mass.
We go 75 billion trillion
zillion light years away from it.
We don't see it,
right?
I mean,
it's a negligible perturbation on our geometry.
And our geometry originally was just d t squared.
With a one.
There's only one thing this could be.
It's got to be one.
Very far from the black hole,
when r is extremely large,
this is negligible.
When r is extremely big.
And we have to go over
to what would be just flat space.
So it's got to be one.
This term here is unaffected.
This is the angle.
This is the angular part on the sphere.
It turns out,
when you work out the equations,
turns out no effect on it.
Just exactly the same.
So minus r squared,
d omega squared.
And this term is also slightly affected
in a manner similar to this one.
This is the hard part.
This is actually not so hard to show,
that this one's unaffected.
This one is easy.
We just use the correspondence between g naught,
naught,
and 2 phi.
The hard one,
which requires the extra
labor of solving Einstein's equations,
is this.
One divided by one minus 2 mg over r.
dr squared.
Now again,
when you go far away from the black hole,
or from the,
it doesn't have to be a black hole,
when you go far away from the mass,
r becomes large.
2 mg over r becomes small.
One just stays there.
And this just becomes one.
So it goes right over to this formula here.
But there are two corrections,
one in the dt squared
and one in the dr squared.
They're identical,
except one occurs in the denominator
and one occurs in the numerator.
That is not an accident,
but it's not something I can easily explain
without spending some time going through the equations.
But it's good enough.
We don't really need to.
This is a nice structure.
Let's see.
If I put the speeds of light in,
let's see if we can
figure out where they would go.
Let's figure out what the units of capital G are.
All right.
So this,
let's figure out what the units of capital G are.
Force is equal to mass squared g over r,
right?
No,
energy.
Energy is mass squared g over r.
I don't literally mean equals,
although I mean the same units.
Okay?
So what's the energy,
what's the units of energy?
Units of energy are mass times velocity.
Velocity squared,
let's use c squared,
has units of mass times velocity squared,
where c has units of velocity
because it's the speed of light.
And that's got to equal m squared g over r.
So we cancel out a m.
We divide by this m over here,
and we multiply by r.
So whatever g is,
it has units of length,
velocity squared,
divided by m.
Hmm?
Did I get it wrong?
No.
Oh,
okay.
I think I got it right.
I'll just call this r,
capital R.
All right.
Now,
twice mg over r,
it has to have the same dimensions as 1,
because you can't add something
with different dimensions to something else.
But it doesn't.
If I work out,
let's see what we have.
Then over here,
I can see that mg over r
has units of the speed of light squared.
Then you have c squared times 1.
I need a c squared in the denominator.
Yeah,
no,
we don't want to put the c squared here
because we want to match on to flat space-time.
Okay.
So we don't want to put the c squared there.
All right.
Now,
that same c squared has to go over here.
But let's put back our c squared,
our original c squared here.
There's a c squared here.
That means there's another c squared downstairs here.
If I put back all the c squares,
I believe it would look like that.
That's what it would look like.
Right.
Notice
that the speed of light
down in here makes this very,
very small.
So it's a very small perturbation on the metric.
This is characteristic.
Don't expect that an ordinary mass like
the Sun is going to make tremendously big
perturbations on the structure of the metric.
It won't.
Space is not highly deformed near the Sun,
even though the Sun has a large mass.
And there's a significant gravitational
potential of the Sun,
but it doesn't translate into a large
deformation because of the c squared downstairs.
Right.
So the c squared is what keeps
the geometry around the Sun from looking highly curved.
All right.
So that's the Schwarzschild metric.
This is the whole metric of a black hole,
and
it's the simplest of black holes.
It's not rotating.
It doesn't have any electric charge,
but it has all the basic
features that we're going to explore.
The next time what I'm going to show you is
how similar
this metric,
it doesn't look anything like it,
but how similar the metric of the black hole is
to the metric of Rindler space.
Let me just write it down for you again.
R squared d omega squared.
Minus the R squared.
Well,
that's a different R,
different R.
R squared d omega squared minus the R squared.
That was minus the x squared minus the y,
minus the z squared minus the y squared.
All right.
Looks very,
very different.
Doesn't look anything like it.
We're going to find out that the
horizon of the black hole is very,
very similar to the horizon
of the Rindler space.
space and that's going to be our
goal that really will carry us through through
the quarter so as I said our next
our main goal is going to be to understand
the horizon of this black hole from this
point of view you can't even see that it
has a horizon any questions before we leave
the preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
Stanford dot edu