Stanford University.
All right,
the last time I started to
set up a little bit of mathematics,
some very elementary mathematics,
but let me just review it,
and then we'll use it.
The purpose of using it today is going
to be to get to the Boltzmann distribution.
The Boltzmann distribution is the probability distribution that
a system in thermal equilibrium with a heat bath
remember what thermal equilibrium means,
it means that a small system is
in contact with a large heat bath.
When we focus on that small system,
energy goes back and forth,
there are fluctuations in the energy,
over time.
And if we have timescales which are sufficiently long,
and not very long for most systems,
the energy will have some average value in the subsystem,
but it will also fluctuate some,
and so there will be a probability distribution.
That probability distribution is the special
probability distribution associated with thermal equilibrium,
and we want to try
to find out something about it.
In fact,
it happens to have a rather universal form,
which is called the Boltzmann law.
It's a kind of Boltzmann distribution.
Sometimes Maxwell-Boltzmann distribution,
but it was really Boltzmann who really got it right.
So let's begin with the idea.
Instead of a heat bath of arbitrary kind,
it turns out to be simplest.
This is a mathematical convenience,
this is not the fundamental point.
We could take the heat bath to be anything,
but it turns out to be simplest if we're
interested in a system that we will call A.
The other thing about the system is we want
it to have a lot of degrees of freedom.
In terms of molecules,
we want it to have a lot of them.
That's the system.
It has a collection of level,
a collection of states.
Let's put an axis over here
to represent the states of the system,
and the little tick marks here
could represent the energy levels,
possible energy levels.
If the energy is continuous,
if it's a continuous variable,
as it really is in classical mechanics,
we'll have to take that into account,
but for the moment let's just simplify things and say
this is a discrete collection of states,
which we label with an I.
The lowest one is called the ground state,
the state of lowest energy,
and up we go.
In most systems of interest,
there's no ceiling to the energy levels.
They go up and up and up.
So there's an infinite number of energy levels.
And in place of a heat bath,
well not in place of a heat bath,
but as a special case of a heat bath,
which is particularly interesting,
because it's very easy to analyze,
we just imagine a bunch
of copies of the same system.
Why make things more complicated
than just repeating the same system over and over again?
No particular reason,
and as I said,
that does make things easier.
Now,
in order that A comes to thermal equilibrium,
of course,
in the heat bath of all the other replicas,
or copies of A,
it's necessary that heat can be exchanged,
or that energy can be exchanged between them.
And that,
for example,
could happen in a variety of ways.
Possibly molecules go back and forth
through a permeable partition.
Other ways,
radiation could go back and forth.
Whatever the way that energy goes back and forth,
let's just indicate it by drawing little pipes
connecting all of the copies together.
And we'll say that there are n copies.
n is a very big number,
and n,
we'll really be interested in what happens
when n goes to infinity.
Now let's focus on a set of numbers,
which we can call occupation numbers.
Now,
if you've heard of occupation numbers before,
in particular in the context of quantum field theory,
don't confuse it.
This is a different concept.
The question is,
how many of these boxes
occupy a particular energy level,
r?
So,
to represent this,
we could draw some lines.
The lines could indicate the first box here
is in state 1,
2,
3,
4,
5.
r equals 5.
The second one,
and of course,
this changes with time.
They rearrange.
But at a given instant,
we could imagine drawing lines,
and those lines would simply tell us
this box is in this state,
this box is in this state.
Now,
of course,
you can have several boxes
all in the same state.
No reason why there can't be two boxes
in the same state,
or three,
or four,
or five.
And so we can define a collection of integers
that are in the same state.
So,
let's say that the number of copies,
let's call it little n,
little n is the number of copies
drawn from big N,
which occupy the state i.
I'm not sure that the copies occupy the state,
or the state occupies the copy,
but you know what I mean.
So that's n i,
and of course,
most of them are zero.
Most of them are zero,
the n i's,
because there's an infinite number of states,
but only a finite number of boxes.
And besides,
I'm going to also assume
that the total energy of the whole collection
is fixed,
let's call it e total.
And I might as well
now not even define e total.
There's an average of,
the average energy that each box has.
Since they're all identical to each other,
when they come to thermal equilibrium,
they will all have the same average energy,
just by symmetry.
So they'll all have the same average energy,
and of course,
the total energy,
which is fixed,
frozen,
will simply be n times the average energy.
Let's write it down.
E total is of course n times the average energy
in each box.
I'm not going to always indicate
that I mean averages.
I've gotten tired of using this symbol like that.
It takes too much space.
I will sometimes use the Ova bar,
and sometimes I'll just ignore it.
Please ask me if you're confused about whether
I'm talking about averages or not.
But since the total energy is fixed,
it must be n times the average energy
in each box.
So this is one fact.
What other facts do we have?
Well,
first of all,
each energy level has a certain
n out of a certain value.
These n's are subject to two constraints,
and really only two constraints.
Things fluctuate,
energy goes back and forth,
things change with time,
but certain things don't change.
First of all,
the number of boxes doesn't change.
So,
by assumption,
that's our system,
a fixed number of boxes.
This is the number of boxes in the i-th state,
and so it must be the case
that the sum over i
of n sub i,
that must equal the total number of boxes.
The number of boxes in the first state
plus the number of boxes in the second state,
and so forth and so on,
must altogether add up to n.
And obviously since n is bounded,
it can't get in the first state,
since n is big,
sorry,
since n is bounded,
none of these n sub
i's can be bigger than n,
and that means most of the states must be unoccupied.
Most of the n's must be zero,
most of the little n's must be zero,
but that's okay,
nevertheless.
First statement.
Next statement.
If we take the number of boxes
in the state i
times the energy of the i-th state,
that gives us the total energy.
Sum over i,
sum over...
Let's be very clear now.
This sum is not the sum over the boxes.
It's the sum over the energy levels.
The number of boxes in the state i.
So i labels states,
not boxes.
So don't get confused by that.
Second,
the number of boxes in the state i,
with each energy level,
when added up,
has to add up to the total energy.
So that must add up to
either e total,
depending on the way we want to write it,
but we can also remember
that that happens to be n
times the average energy of any given box.
The energy,
total energy,
and the total number of boxes
are fixed and frozen
and will never change in this discussion,
and so these can be thought of as constraints.
Whatever we do,
we will not change these things.
Now,
the next question is,
how many ways are there,
given a set of occupation numbers,
how many ways are there
that those occupation numbers
can be realized?
Let me just give you a simple example.
Supposing
there are a bunch of states
and only two boxes,
and let me take the case
n1,
that's the ground state,
is equal to 1,
and n2 is equal to 1.
How many ways are there
that n1 can equal 1
and n2 equal 1?
Just one way.
Both boxes have,
are in the first two boxes,
and both boxes have
so we represent that
by drawing a line like that.
The line at this point.
On the other hand,
what's the,
just to illustrate the concept,
what's the number of ways
that n1 can be 0?
Is that what I want?
Wasn't that n1 equals 1
and n2 equals 0?
Say it again.
n1 equals 2.
Yeah,
And n2 is 0.
And n2 is equal to 0.
So,
that's the number of ways,
it's also 1,
isn't it?
No,
no.
The sum of the left and the right,
this is correct.
Correct.
This is correct for what you put in.
Sorry,
I thought I'd run out.
For what I drew,
n1 is 2
and n2 is 0.
Good.
On the other end,
I see.
Right here.
Okay.
How many ways are there
of missing the number of ways
of making n1 equal to 2?
One.
One way.
Okay.
In general,
there may be many ways
of doing it,
many ways of having a given set
of occupation numbers.
For example,
we could have n1 equal 1.
Let's see.
And,
The sum has to be 2.
The sum has to add up to 2.
And what's another possibility?
Yeah,
you can have them both.
One go to 1
and the other go to 2.
Right.
So,
n1 is 1
and n2 is 1.
Right.
So,
now we have
either
this situation
or
what's the other situation
was
just a reverse.
Not the reverse,
the
inverse.
That's the reverse.
The inverse.
The first box
goes to the lowest energy level
and the second box
goes to the
just
cross them all out.
So,
there are two ways
to have
n1 equal 1
and n2 equal 2.
In general,
there will be a multiplicity
of ways
of
obtaining
a given set
of
occupation numbers.
What is that multiplicity?
Well,
what is the multiplicity
in general?
I told you what the answer was last time.
I assume you've all worked it out.
It's not very hard.
It's a simple combinatoric problem.
Standard
combinatoric problem.
And I'm not going to prove it here.
We'll just write down the answer.
Let's call that number,
I just call it
number.
The number of ways
that
the energy can be partitioned up
among
the boxes
such that
we have a given set
of n sub i's.
And that is equal
to n factorial
divided
by n1 factorial
n2 factorial
n3 factorial
dot dot dot.
In other words,
let's write it
as n factorial
over
the product
over the product
over i,
the product
over all the states,
and the product
好
the occupation number
n sub i factorial
that's the answer to that combinatorial problem
now let me tell you first of all
that in practical applications
these kind of things
think of them as functions of the n's
first of all,
all the n's in the problem
are going to be very large
capital N is a huge huge number of copies
so huge that the occupation numbers of every state
will also be assumed to be large
now of course that's a bit of a contradiction
because we don't expect to have occupation
numbers way way way up on the top
but those occupation numbers
which are non-zero and non-negligible
will typically be
proportionally
in itself
if you double the total number of particles,
the total number of boxes
you will double the number of
of boxes in each one of these configurations
so by making capital N big
we also make the little n's big
one fact
second
think of this
object over here
as a function of the little n's
it's a highly
highly peaked function
we're not going to prove it so
I'm just going to tell it to you
when the n's get very very very large
actually I will wind up doing a calculation
for you which will show you this fact
but when the n's get very very large
if you were to think of
this quantity over here
as a function of the n's
now the horizontal axis stands for many horizontal axes
namely all the n's
typically this number here
is a very sharply peaked
I didn't draw it sharply enough
as the n's get large it
becomes a rather sharply peaked function
so that
it doesn't fluctuate very much
it doesn't fluctuate nearly as much
as the size of n itself
that means when the number of boxes
is very large it's not a big deal
when the number of boxes gets very very big
you can be pretty sure
and as the number of boxes gets bigger and bigger
you can get surer and surer
of
what these little n's are
now more specifically
that sounds a little ridiculous
can I tell the difference between having a box n1
with 5271
occupation number
versus 5272
no of course not
what I mean by saying it's narrow
is that it's narrow on
the scale of capital N itself.
In other words,
that you
could be pretty sure what the value
of N sub i over N is.
That the N's don't fluctuate
very much.
The numbers get bigger and bigger,
they get tighter and tighter.
That means that for very,
very large systems,
these N's get pretty definite,
or
at least the fractional N's become pretty definite.
That suggests that we give them a name,
the fractional N's.
Let's give the fractional
N's a name.
Let's call it P of i.
Why P?
Well,
if you have a large number of identical replicas
subject to some fluctuation,
but you know the ratio
of the number of each type
of box to the total number,
it makes a lot of sense to think of
that as the probability that any
given box is in the state i.
What is probability,
after
all?
It's essentially the same thing as saying you
have a large number of replicas of the
same thing,
and you take the ratio between each
given outcome relative to the total number
of copies that you have,
and that's what's called probability,
or at least that's one
way of representing probability.
So N sub i over N can be thought of,
or at least N
sub i over N at the maximum up here,
the most likely value of these occupation numbers,
they
can be identified with the probability that
any given box is in the state i.
That's the
basic tool.
It's as simple as that.
So we'll define P sub i to
be little n sub i over N,
and now let's rewrite the two constraints
that are up there.
The two constraints that are up there are,
first of all,
the sum of
N sub i equals N divided by capital N.
What does it become?
It becomes the sum of N sub
i over N is equal to 1,
or simply the familiar statement
that the sum of the probabilities
So N add up to 1.
Divide through by N and that tells us
that the sums of the probabilities add up
to 1.
Not a big surprise.
The other statement,
let's write it down,
summation over i of N
sub i e sub i,
equals capital N times the average Scripture number.
The horizontal command
energy in each box.
I'll continue to use the
overbar notation for a little while
until I get tired of it.
Now divide this by capital N.
This becomes n sub i over n,
and
that's p sub i.
The average,
in fact this is a
much more general formula than just
for the average energy.
In general,
the average of a quantity
is the weighted sum over the
states of the system of the probability of
the i-th system times the value of that quantity
in the i-th state.
In this particular case,
it's the energy.
So these two constraints,
or those two constraints up there,
become the very familiar…
Is that the total energy?
No.
No,
no,
no.
Okay,
let's go back over it again.
Not the right-hand side is not.
We started with
sum of i,
n sub i,
p sub i is equal to the total energy,
but the total energy is n times
the energy of any box.
Then we divide it by capital N.
So I have gotten rid,
effectively,
of the large number of boxes,
but of course the large number
of boxes are still the problem
here because they're going to tell
us it's the large number of boxes.
So the large number of boxes and
how they equilibrate the energy between them,
that's
going to tell us what the energy distribution,
what the p sub i's are.
I haven't told you
Okay,
so these are constraints.
Now,
what are the p sub i's?
The p sub i's are
simply the values of the n's,
not the values of the n's,
but the ratio,
the fractional value of the n's.
Constraints are
necessarily entitled to the maximum oxygen saturation,
and if it is,
how do you out
But now let's go back,
we have a nearly happened.
My name is Wheremed Object
Paul reflect into the engaggending of
i equal r
r of a sorry i'm going to bring you,
what's now rice a老
So,
we then have to find the maximum of pound here.
I don't know when I started calling it pound,
but a long time ago.
The maximum of this thing as a function of the ends subject to
these constraints can either be written this way or the way I'm talking.
This is the mathematical problem.
And it sounds like a terrible mathematical problem,
but fortunately it's extremely easy,
surprisingly easy.
It's a couple of lines.
Now,
the first thing to do,
you don't have to do what I'm going to do.
There's other ways to do it.
I'm going to take you through the most efficient procedure,
which I didn't invent.
It was invented a long time ago.
Probably people tried other procedures.
But the most efficient procedure begins
by saying if you're maximizing pound,
you can also substitute maximizing its logarithm.
Why?
If a function is maximized at some point,
so is its logarithm.
And the reason is because logarithms...
are monatomic functions of their arguments.
So we might as well maximize it.
The logarithm.
Why is the logarithm interesting?
We're going to find out that the logarithm is interesting because
it's easier to work with a sum than with a product.
Pound is a product.
The logarithm of it will be a sum.
And that will help us analyze it.
So what's the logarithm?
Of pound.
The answer is the logarithm of n
factorial divided by the logarithm of n1...
Sorry.
Minus the logarithm of n1 factorial plus n2 factorial.
In other words,
it's just log n factorial minus the sum
of the logs of the n sub i factorial.
But now here the simplification happens
when we use the Stirling approximation.
The Stirling approximation is the trick that makes
all of this work and work out beautifully.
So let me remind you what it is.
The Stirling approximation can be
written in one of two ways.
It can be written as either n factorial is approximately
equal to n to the n e to the minus n.
Or you can take its logarithm.
Incidentally,
the...
If you did it numerically...
You would find out that this is
not all that accurate as n gets big.
But if you take its logarithm,
you'll find it's really accurate.
The logarithm of n factorial is equal
to the logarithm of n to the n...
That's n log n...
Minus...
Or plus the logarithm of
e to the minus the n.
e to the minus n.
The logarithm of e to the
minus n is just minus n.
So again,
I think I proved this last time
by doing a little integral for you.
Yeah.
We did this last time.
Or at least motivated it.
And this is what we have here.
Logarithms of n factorial.
And so we're going to use
the Stirling approximation in this form.
If you actually go and numerically study these things,
you find out that this formula is very accurate.
This one is not so accurate.
This one is...
You know,
you take the thing which is
pretty accurate and you exponentiate it.
Well,
you can flop around because of the exponential.
But the logarithm is a highly accurate formula.
When I say it's accurate,
I mean it becomes very,
very good for large n.
The corrections to it get
smaller and smaller with large n.
Okay.
So let's now substitute that into here.
We have this equals log of n factorial,
which is n to the n.
No,
n log n.
Can you just leave that out?
n log n minus n.
That's this term here.
Okay.
And then we have minus the summation of n
sub i log n sub i minus n sub i.
That's it.
Now let's work on it a little bit.
Let me take it over here and I'm
going to take this piece of it over here.
Let's see.
I want my signs right.
This one is plus.
This one is minus.
And I think this one is plus.
I all bright.
How about I put a bracket around here.
Minus,
I put a bracket around here.
All right.
Let's work on the second term a little bit.
The work that I'm going
to do with is very simple.
I'm going to simply substitute that n
is equal to capital N times p.
For each i.
Therefore the q.
That's the same as saying n sub
i over capital N is p sub i.
I'm just going to plug that
into here and grind it through.
It's quite easy.
So let's take the thing in the brackets.
The thing in the brackets then is equal to each
n sub i that's replaced by n times p sub i.
So that's going to give
you an overall factor of n.
Then each n sub i
will be proportional to capital N,
be an overall factor of n,
and then there will be a sum,
and the first factor will be p of i.
That's the n sub i here.
Then we have logarithm of n sub i.
So that's logarithm of p of i times,
n.
That's this term over here.
And then we get the
subtract off minus n sub i.
Incidentally,
I left,
no,
this is fine.
I think if I were really doing it right,
I would have put the bracket over here.
Summation,
n sub i log n sub i minus,
summation,
n sub i.
So I won't bother writing,
yes,
I will bother writing,
minus summation of n sub i.
Okay.
Why don't you just write p sub i there?
Where?
On the n sub i,
the last n sub i.
Oh,
I could write p sub i there.
You mean leave it to the factor of n here.
Yeah.
I could.
You're right,
it doesn't matter.
But either way,
it'll,
the summation,
the summation of,
so this,
this piece,
the way I've defined it,
this piece does not multiply capital N.
And it doesn't matter.
You can do it the way you want also.
The summation of n sub i is capital N,
right?
Okay,
so let's replace this by minus capital N.
And now,
that,
that cancels this capital N here.
Right?
Okay.
That one cancels this.
So,
I think we can safely replace this,
and this,
and ignore that.
Finish with that.
Now,
what about this?
Log of p times n is just
log of p plus log of n.
So,
this becomes n times summation,
of p of i,
log p of i,
that's the first term,
and then plus summation,
sorry,
n,
summation of i,
of p of i,
times log n.
See where that came from.
The first term is gotten by just
taking the log of p sub i.
The second term is gotten by replacing the log here
just by log of n.
So,
that's this.
Now,
what's the sum of p sub i?
One.
Which is pretty much what you would have done
if you would have done it the way you said.
Alright,
so this just goes away.
And this gives us n log n.
It comes in with a minus sign,
and so it cancels this n log n over here.
This thing is gone.
All that's left is this term over here,
with a minus sign.
The minus sign coming from here.
So,
the whole thing is just minus n
p of i log p of i,
sorry,
log p of i,
summed over i.
So,
if we know that,
if we had the probability distribution,
we would count,
well,
if we had the probability,
it is just n p
sub i log p sub i.
Now,
we've seen this before.
Anybody remember what it is?
Well,
the minus sign,
excuse me.
The minus sign.
Entropy.
It is the entropy.
It's n times the entropy,
which appears there.
Why did it come out n times the entropy?
Well,
the reason it came out n times the entropy
is because there are n boxes.
But,
our problem,
let's take our mathematical problem now.
Our mathematical problem,
first of all,
has a minus sign in it from here.
The number of ways of rearranging things,
so we're given the logarithm of
the number of ways of rearranging things,
to get a given set of occupation numbers,
there's just minus n times the sum over i,
p of i,
this is just going away,
log p sub i.
That's it.
Yes,
you can remember that this is the entropy,
but let's just take it for what it is.
How can it possibly come out to be negative?
Well,
it's negative.
Yeah.
The log p sub i is less than one,
and so the logarithm is negative.
That's really log,
log p?
Hmm?
では、
ご覧ください。
ln,
same as log.
Log pound minus n times p
sub i log p sub i.
And we want to maximize this whole thing,
including the minus sign.
We want to maximize it.
In other words,
we want to find out
what little a's give us the most likely distribution
of occupation numbers,
but subject to two constraints.
The first constraint is that the sum of the probabilities
we want to do is add up to 1.
So we have to remember
that when we're varying and trying
to find the maximum of this,
we have to keep two things fixed.
We have the sum of the p's equal 1,
and the sum of the p sub
i e sub i's is equal to e.
How do we do that?
Well,
the answer is the method of Lagrange multipliers.
We add a Lagrange multiplier for each constraint.
And then later on,
afterwards,
we figure out
what the Lagrange multipliers have
to be in order to make the constraints actually
satisfied.
So what we do then is we take this quantity,
log of pound.
And remember,
what is it a function of?
See,
you can think of it either as
a function of the n sub i's
or a function of the p sub i's.
In this problem,
the variables that we're maximizing,
with respect to,
are these probabilities themselves.
We're trying to find
the most likely probability distribution.
So the p sub i's are the unknowns.
And we're going to maximize this expression,
log of pound minus,
now we have to put in Lagrange multipliers.
The first Lagrange multiplier I will call alpha.
That's the one that multiplies this constraint.
And then the second Lagrange multiplier,
I'll call beta minus beta.
Summation over i,
p sub i,
p sub i.
And the second Lagrange multiplier,
I'll call beta minus beta.
And we might as well now
write in what log of pound is.
Here it is right here.
O.
Incidentally,
one step that I didn't,
we might as well throw away this n.
We're trying to maximize this subject to some constraints.
Well,
maximizing n times something is no
different than maximizing the something itself.
Let's get rid of all n's.
We want to maximize this thing right here,
subject to the constraints that the sum of
the p's is 1.
And the sum of the e
times p's is equal to e.
So we have sum of i,
p of i,
log p of i,
with a minus sign.
Plus,
no minus.
I think I chose the
Lagrange multiplier to be minus here.
p.
Now,
is there any questions?
I'm going to stop this for now.
Yeah.
來
I'm envisioning that most of the n-thes
of i's are either 0 or 1,
because the ones which are appreciably non-zero,
let's put it this way.
Okay,
let's think of it the following way.
I think maybe it will be helpful to
pretend that there is a highest energy level.
The n-i's would be proportional to n.
Yeah,
yeah,
but of course,
of course,
yeah.
But let's for simplicity suppose that there
is a ceiling to the energy levels.
In other words,
that there are a finite number of n's.
And then take capital N to be much,
much bigger than the total number of states.
That will make sure that every n is large.
So the approximation here,
which...
seems a little bit ridiculous,
but nevertheless quite legal,
is to imagine the number of replicas
there is larger than the number of states.
And that's the approximation.
It's not really an approximation.
It's just a useful trick to keep in mind.
What of course is true is that the p-sub
i's go to 0 as the energy gets very,
very large.
But we can take that into account.
By being very careful.
The easiest way to be careful is just
to truncate the energy levels at some point.
Yeah?
Can you just say that
when the n survives a small...
that it counts for a very
small part of the sum anyway?
Yeah.
Yeah,
absolutely.
Absolutely.
So that is not a problem.
But as I said,
the easiest way to handle it without the least number of words is just to
say there's a maximum number of states and capital N is much bigger than those.
So that's a good question.
But yes,
you're right.
That's correct.
That doesn't seem physical.
You have just one particle in a box.
It can go 10 million different...
10 million states.
So if you have a number in a box,
you've got 10 million states times...
You can always make the number of
boxes bigger than the number of states.
As long as the number of states is bounded.
Now in practice,
the number of states is bounded.
Because you sure don't want to have an energy in
any one box which is bigger than the total energy.
So in practice,
there is a bound.
But let's just take it simply to say that there's an upper
bound here and capital N is much bigger than that upper bound.
That simplifies the argument.
Alright,
the interesting thing is
the actual mathematical argument here.
The interesting thing is
Now notice all of these are summs over i.
There's no term in here.
No single term in here which
involves more than 1p at a time.
p2 doesn't ever get multiplied by p1.
p1 gets multiplied by the logarithm of p1.
It doesn't get multiplied by the logarithm of p2.
So this is a function
which is a sum of functions
of individual variables.
You maximize it,
by maximizing each,
maximizing it for each i separately.
How do you maximize,
or what do you do next?
The next thing you do is you differentiate this
with respect to p sub i,
or some,
this i is a summation variable here,
so let's not differentiate with respect to p sub i,
let's differentiate with respect to p sub j,
where j is some specific number.
p sub j enters into one term here,
one term here,
and one term here.
j could be 46 or 59,
it enters only into one term
of each of these.
So when we differentiate with respect to p j,
let's do it.
First of all,
the derivative here is the sum of two terms,
one is the derivative of the first factor
times the second factor,
that will give us
a logarithm minus logarithm,
and then the second factor is
the logarithm of p of j.
I wonder if it helps to factor p.
Factor p?
In first place.
Mm-hmm.
Is it inverse of i times,
as a product?
We can take the summation on the outside,
if that's what you mean.
Well,
you can take the p i outside.
No,
no,
it's a sum over i.
No,
but I mean.
You can't take the,
no,
no.
No,
no,
you can take the summation,
the summation on the outside.
Get rid of the sum here,
get rid of the sum here.
But that's it.
You can't take the p i on the outside.
No,
I'm saying take the p i on the outside
with parentheses.
No,
well,
yes,
oh,
you can certainly take p i
on the outside with the parentheses,
sure.
You want to do it if you like.
I don't see that it helps anything.
Here it is.
All right.
So the derivative of this term here has two terms.
The first one is just logarithm of p j.
It's gotten by differentiating this piece.
And the other one is minus.
The minus sign is all
coming from this overall minus sign
on the outside.
So it's minus log piece of j.
And then what do we get from the differentiating log?
One over p.
One over p times p,
which is minus one.
Now what happens when we differentiate this term
with respect to p j?
You just get minus alpha.
And what happens when we differentiate this term
with respect to p j?
We get minus beta times j.
And that all we set equal to zero.
That's the method we've learned from the fliers.
Pretend that we're minimizing this whole quantity
with respect to all of its variables.
So for each j,
we find that minus log of p j minus one,
plus alpha,
and so forth,
has to add up to zero.
I can throw away the minus signs
since it appears in all of them.
Minus.
Plus.
And now what do I have?
I actually have the probability distribution,
or better yet,
or not better yet,
but it's a logarithm.
So logarithm of p j equals minus one plus alpha,
that's from here,
minus beta e j.
Final step to go from the
logarithm of p to p itself,
we exponentiate.
Exponential of the left-hand side is p j.
That's p j equals e to
the minus one plus alpha times e
to the minus beta e j.
Now,
first of all,
look at this for a little bit.
This is just a number.
Well,
it's a number that depends on the Lagrange multiplier,
but it doesn't depend on which state we're talking about.
It doesn't depend on j.
All of the j dependence,
in other words,
the dependence on which state we're talking about,
is all in this factor here.
And this tells us that the probability for
the j-th state is proportional to e to the
minus,
this Lagrange.
So we have the Lagrange multiplier times the energy.
It tells us that the probability for
different energy levels falls off exponentially as a
function of the energy.
That's the basic property of the Boltzmann distribution.
We've got a bunch of magic,
a bunch of sleight of hand,
but all of it was good,
genuine
mathematics.
And we discovered that maximizing the entropy
subject to the constraint of the given energy,
the comparison factor,
and the
alternate.
What?
We're going to figure out soon enough what beta is.
I'll tell you right now what beta is.
Beta is 1 over the temperature.
Or if I include Boltzmann's constant,
it's 1 over k times the temperature.
In most places,
when I write 1 over temperature,
I really mean 1 over kT.
In other words,
for most purposes,
I will set k equal to 1 and work
in units in which temperature has units of energy.
Okay,
so beta then is actually 1 over the temperature,
proportional to 1 over the temperature.
But why that's true,
we have yet to establish.
We have an independent definition of temperature.
If you go back in
your notes from the first time,
there was an independent definition of temperature.
Which I'll remind you of.
And we need to establish that they're the same thing.
But for the time being,
beta is a Lagrange multiplier.
And we'll find out later
that it's 1 over the temperature.
Now,
this object over here,
I'm going to give another name.
This is just naming things now.
The Lagrange multiplier was alpha.
But I'm going to give
this whole thing here another name.
I'm going to call it 1 divided by z.
Why am I doing that?
Historical.
It's a historical notation.
That's all.
1 divided by z.
I can't help it.
It replaces the Lagrange multiplier.
I don't know what the Lagrange multiplier is yet.
I don't know what z is yet.
I haven't really done anything.
I just made a change of notation.
And this I'll leave in this form.
That may or may not be familiar to you.
Some of you who know
a little bit of statistical mechanics.
This is a very famous formula.
For those who don't know it,
it's less famous.
All right.
What is z?
When I say what is z,
I mean what we should do
now is fix the Lagrange multipliers.
By making sure that the constraints are satisfied.
Remember,
after solving the problem,
we have to go back and say,
let's pick the Lagrange multipliers
so the constraints are satisfied.
First constraint.
The sums of the probabilities add up to 1.
Let's see what that says.
The probability of the j-th
state is 1 divided by z.
And now we want the sum of all the states,
e to the minus beta.
I'll now use the e sub i.
This is the sum of p sub i.
The sum,
I factored out the 1 over
z from all of the terms,
e to the minus beta e sub i.
And the total probability has to add up to 1.
Well,
just to make sure.
So,
by multiplying by z,
that tells us what z is,
at least in terms as a
function of beta in any case.
Remember,
beta being temperature.
So this gives us a formula for what z is.
We don't know what the temperature is.
We don't know what beta is.
But whatever beta is,
that's equal to z.
And z,
think of it as a function of beta.
Or as a function of temperature.
z is called the partition function.
Again,
very famous formula.
z is defined by the sum.
You take e to the minus beta e sub i.
And you add it up for all the energy levels.
And that defines the partition function.
Knowing that,
that doesn't seem like very much,
the partition function.
It's one little piece of,
who cares what the partition function is.
It's just a normalization factor that makes sure
your total probability is add up to 1.
Well,
in fact,
as we will see,
as we go along,
if you know the partition function,
you know everything.
Partition function,
as a function of the variables of the problem,
is a way of codifying or representing all the thermodynamic,
and even beyond the thermodynamic information,
all the statistical information in your system.
So this is not only an important function,
it contains everything.
We'll see why.
I don't expect you to see why yet.
Alright,
how about beta?
How do we choose beta?
The other constraint,
the other constraint,
is that the sums of
the probabilities times e sub i
has to add up to the average energy.
Now I'm assuming that we know the average energy.
The whole ensemble of copies
had a total fixed amount of energy.
If I just divide it by n,
that tells me what the energy of each replica is,
of each copy.
So I will assume for the
moment that I know what e is,
e bar,
or the average energy of one copy.
Let's write down the formula.
Summation over i,
it's again a 1 over z on the outside,
that's because each piece of
i has a 1 over z,
and then there is e to
the minus beta e sub i.
That's not finished,
we have to multiply by e sub i.
And that's equal to the average energy.
Now,
one,
it would be simple to say,
look,
this does determine what beta is,
this is an equation for beta,
I already know what z is in terms of beta,
so this is an equation for beta,
and this is an equation,
if I know e bar,
this is a relationship between the temperature,
if you like,
and the average energy,
but we can do a slick thing with this.
We can actually express all of this nicely
in terms of the partition function itself.
So let's see,
let's find another blackboard here,
and move that.
This is the object here,
whose sum defines the partition function.
But we have an extra e sub i here.
The trick,
this is a trick,
but this is such a
standard trick that by this point,
well,
anybody who has done,
a little bit of mathematics from time to time
would rather quickly realize that the next step
is to replace the e sub i
by the derivative with respect to beta.
If I have a thing
like e to the minus beta
times e,
and I want to multiply it anyway,
and I want to multiply it by e,
one way of doing it is just to differentiate it
with respect to beta,
and then we have to change the sign.
The derivative with respect to beta
of an exponential e to the minus beta e
is just e times the exponential,
not this e,
this e.
This is equal to e times
e to the minus beta e.
Alright,
so every place here
where you see e times
e to the minus beta e,
let's write it as 1,
1 over 0,
sum on i,
derivative with respect to beta,
I'm going to write it as
partial derivative with respect to beta.
The reason is later on,
not now,
but later on there are going
to be more variables in the problem,
volume,
magnetic field,
all sorts of things,
and I mean differentiate
and all those other things based.
For our purposes here,
I could just use ordinary derivatives.
But later on,
we'll want to remember there may
be more variables in the problem,
and now I mean differentiating the data,
keeping all the other things in the problem fixed,
of e to the minus beta e sub i,
period.
Now,
minus sign,
thank you.
Alright.
Now,
the derivative can be taken outside the sum.
The sum of derivatives,
is the derivative of the sum.
Alright.
So the derivative can be taken out on the outside.
Let's take it on the outside.
It becomes d by d beta,
of the sum.
And what is this?
This is the partition function.
So we have a lovely formula now,
that the average energy,
is equal to minus,
one upon z,
derivative of z,
with respect to beta.
Beta,
remember,
is the inverse temperature.
So again,
if you know the partition function,
as a function of beta,
then,
here is z of beta,
and all you have to do,
is construct one over z,
times the derivative of z with respect to beta,
at that temperature,
that will give you the average energy.
This gives you a relationship between average energy,
or just energy,
let's call it,
and the temperature.
The right hand side is a function of temperature,
the left hand side is the average energy.
This can be rewritten as minus,
the derivative of logarithm of z,
with respect to beta.
One over z,
d z by d beta,
is the derivative of logarithm of z.
The logarithm of z occurs
over and over and over again,
and it occurs so much,
that we give it a special name.
That's the average energy.
Oh,
before we talk about the name of this thing,
let's just see what it says.
The left hand side is a well defined,
I mean,
if we can calculate,
to the extent that we can calculate z over z,
it's a function of beta.
It's a function of beta,
and a function of beta is equal to the energy.
We can invert that,
and we can find out
what beta is as a function of the energy.
Whatever that relationship is,
if we can invert it,
we can find out beta
as a function of the energy.
Beta is the Lagrange multiplier,
but it is also the inverse temperature.
So this is the relationship between temperature and energy.
In many examples,
we actually don't want to invert this.
We may know the temperature,
in which case we may be more interested…
We know the temperature,
we may be more interested in finding the energy.
In some cases,
we may know the energy,
and we may be interested in finding out what the
temperature is at that energy.
This formula,
together with the formula that z is summation
of e to the minus beta e sub
i,
g of theta.
That,
as I said,
contains a good deal of information,
more than a good deal,
just endless amounts
of information,
about the statistical system.
Let's see what we're going to…
Yes,
I told you that logarithm
of z has a special name.
Let me just get the signs right.
T,
temperature times logarithm of z,
with a minus sign,
which is the same as logarithm
of z divided by beta.
Anybody know what that's called?
With a minus sign.
Before I tell you its name,
let's just notice z is
not itself actually a single x-axis.
It's a single exponential.
But it sort of looks like
an exponential of beta times energy.
If I take the logarithm of z,
I expect it to be…
to have at least have units,
or be
similar to beta times some kind of thing that
I might call a thing which has units of energy.
So the logarithm of z is
sort of like what's up here.
It's not really,
but I mean,
it's sort of like the sort
of thing which goes in the exponent
here.
And if I divide it by beta,
then it's some kind of
thing which has units of energy.
The logarithm of z divided
by beta has units of energy.
Of course,
really,
z is the sum of such terms,
but that doesn't prevent us from calling this
a kind of energy.
It is what it is.
It is not the energy of the system.
It's the Helmholtz free energy,
it's called.
A is that.
The Helmholtz free energy has units of energy,
and it's just minus the logarithm of z divided
by beta.
Why minus the logarithm?
Because the exponential here carries a minus with it.
So it's natural to put
a minus in front of it.
All right,
so that's… and that's definition.
There's no proof of that.
That's the definition of a-phi.
The Helmholtz free energy.
Okay,
what is not definition is a relationship between the energy,
the Helmholtz free energy,
and the entropy.
We've defined entropy already.
We certainly know what energy is.
And we now have a
definition of the Helmholtz free energy.
So what is the energy?
There is a relationship between the three of these things,
energy,
entropy,
and Helmholtz
free energy,
which we should derive.
It's easy enough to derive.
You might be saying to yourself by this point already,
when the hell are we going to get
to molecules and gas?
The answer is pretty soon.
But it is worth exploring the
general mathematics before we do particular systems.
Once we have some mathematics in place,
once we know and understand how to use this partition
function as a generator of all kinds of answers,
we will have a machine that we can mindlessly
use to crank out all kinds
of things about statistical mechanical systems.
So it's worth exploring the general principles
before we actually try to attack a system.
Let's just see what we…
Let's see what we've got here.
We have Helmholtz free energy is equal
to logarithm of z divided by beta.
And let me just write down next
to the key f the energy itself.
That was not by definition,
but by calculation was equal to
minus the derivative of the logarithm
of z with respect to beta.
They're kind of similar.
One is actually the logarithm of z divided by beta,
and the other is the derivative of
the logarithm of z with respect to beta.
They're not the same thing.
If z…
Well,
you can see that they're not the same thing,
but they have some relationship with
each other.
If z…
If logarithm of z was a straight line,
which it is in general not,
but if it were a straight
line as a function of beta,
then they would be the same.
But of course,
they're not…
It's not a straight line in general.
All right,
those are the two important quantities.
And one more quantity is…
You know,
the first one is the…
The entropy.
So let's calculate the entropy.
And we're going to find that the
entropy is closely related to a and e,
and of course,
beta.
What is the entropy?
The entropy is minus…
Minus…
The sum of p sub i,
logarithm of p sub i.
But now we know what p sub i is.
We know that it's just up there.
1 over z e to the minus beta ej,
er e for p sub i.
So let's plug that in and grind
away and calculate what the entropy is.
Maybe we'll get stuck and we won't be able
to do it in any useful or interesting way.
We can just do it in some other way.
So let's try it.
S is equal to minus.
Now what's p sub i?
1 over z…
There's a sum on the outside.
1 over z times e to
the minus beta e sub i.
And now what's the logarithm of p sub i?
That's the logarithm of p sub i.
of that expression up there,
except change j to i.
The logarithm of that is
minus beta
e sub i.
That's the
logarithm of the second factor,
the exponential,
and then we have
to subtract off minus log z.
I need a stick.
I don't have a stick to point with.
Does everybody see what I've done?
I've written p sub i as 1 over z
e to the minus beta e sub i,
and then the logarithm of p sub i
as minus beta e sub i
minus log z.
That's s.
The minus sign goes away.
I've taken the minus sign,
the overall minus sign,
and the minus sign's here,
and canceled it.
Okay,
what's the first term?
1 over z e to the minus beta
e sub i times beta e sub i.
Suppose the beta wasn't there first.
That's the average energy.
So we can say that s is equal,
the first term is just the average energy,
times beta.
Sorry,
It's this beta over here.
And what about the second term?
The second term,
there's no i dependence in here.
This is just logarithm of z.
It doesn't depend on i at all.
So in doing the sum here,
all we're doing is summing
e to the minus beta e sub i.
What is that?
Sum of e to the minus beta e sub i?
Z.
And that cancels the z here.
So all we're left with is logarithm of z.
Plus.
Log of z.
Go over that again.
We've taken care of the first term here.
That was just the average energy.
The second term,
we can factor out,
no,
sorry,
we can factor out the
log of z on the outside.
That's log of z.
And then it's just the sum of 1 over
z e to the minus beta e sub i.
That's just 1.
So,
that's it.
What do we have?
We now have a formula relating entries.
We have entropy,
energy,
and Helmholtz free energy.
The Helmholtz free energy,
let's,
I don't want to erase it in this form.
Let's just put it up here.
And again,
logarithm of z is minus beta times a.
So here we have it.
S is equal to beta times e minus a.
しょー!
The Helmholtz free energy,
or the difference between the
energy and the Helmholtz free energy,
is just the entropy.
Or the entropy divided by beta.
Another way we can write it,
by using that beta is one over temperature,
we can write it as T
s is equal to E minus A.
So whatever the Helmholtz free energy is,
the difference between it and the real energy is just,
or the average energy,
is just temperature times entropy.
This allows us to express the
entropy in terms of the partition function.
Let's see what it is.
We have to take E minus A.
So E minus A is...
Well,
it's the logarithm of Z divided by beta minus the
derivative of the log of Z with respect to beta.
This is what the entropy is.
This is a formula for the entropy.
I don't mean this is
not the definition of the entropy.
This is A,
and that's equal to T s.
Did I get that right?
If I'm lucky...
The temperature will cancel from this one.
Yeah.
This is also one over beta.
Alright,
so we can multiply by beta if we like.
Multiply by beta.
Another form.
S is equal to log Z minus
beta E log Z divided by beta.
A whole bunch of formulas.
The main upshot.
The main upshot is when you know Z,
you have tools for calculating energy,
entropy,
Helmholtz free energy if it means anything to you,
which it will because we will
use it for all sorts of applications.
Thus far I haven't told you what it's good for,
other than calculating the entropy from the energy.
But you can see that there's
some power in knowing the partition function.
Each one of the various
thermodynamic variables can be represented fairly...
...in terms of the logarithm of Z.
It's always the logarithm of Z which comes into things.
So the logarithm of Z is
often more interesting than Z itself.
Question?
You haven't really demonstrated that probability.
Yeah,
we haven't.
We haven't.
The way to demonstrate it...
Variance or something?
What's that?
You have to compute like a variance or something?
Yeah,
it's a variance.
Oh.
Okay,
let's...
Good.
I was going to jump into the ideal gas.
But let's,
before we do that,
let's do variances.
Statistical fluctuations.
Let's see if we can learn
something about the size of statistical fluctuations.
What we'll find is that they're very small.
But let's see if we can do that.
We have our choice now.
Either to jump into an application,
which is theory of gas and so forth,
or to do a
little more theory,
the more theory being the theory of fluctuations.
And the theory of fluctuations
is a sort of general theory.
The theory of gas is a special case.
Which would you rather do?
Theory of fluctuations.
Fluctuations.
I mean,
it's awfully interesting.
So are gases,
but let's generalize.
All right.
Let's do fluctuations.
Let's take a quantity.
Let's call it x.
x is of course a thing which has
a value for each state of the system.
For each state of the system,
x has some value.
And I'm interested in the probability distribution.
I'm interested in the variance of x.
Now,
I can't do any of that.
Or if you like,
let's call it the uncertainty or the fluctuation of x.
The fluctuation of x,
how do we define it?
Well,
I'll give you a definition.
The definition is,
first of all,
subtract from x its average.
So subtract from x its average value.
So if we have a probability
distribution for x which looks like that,
we subtract the average value which is in here somewhere,
and that effectively just moves the probability distribution
so that the center of the probability distribution
or the average of the probability
distribution is now located at zero.
Other than that,
the interpretation.
An x-bar does not depend on i,
it's just a number.
Now we take this and we square it.
And then we take the average of the whole thing.
So we have some probability distribution
which is centered at the origin,
and centered at the origin because I've shifted it.
We take x squared and we average it,
and that gives us,
that is a measure of the width of the distribution.
It's always positive because it's a square of something,
and when averaged,
it's always positive,
and it measures the width of the distribution.
All right?
Call it the variance.
Mean square,
root mean square,
something or other.
Yeah.
Okay.
So that's the statistical variance in x,
and I want to calculate it for,
well,
first of all,
let me simplify it.
Let me re-express it.
First of all,
this can be expressed as the average,
it's an overbar and the bracket.
The bracket and the bracket rotation are the same thing.
I just didn't want to write brackets inside brackets.
All right.
So what is this?
First of all,
let's take the thing inside the bracket.
It's x squared minus twice x
times x bar plus x bar squared.
If you like,
you can call this x of i,
x of i.
And now we have to average this.
First of all,
what's the average of x of i squared?
Well,
it's just the average of x squared.
So this here is just the average of x squared,
first term.
What about the average of x bar squared?
Well,
it's just the average of x squared.
好
It's just x bar squared.
x bar doesn't depend on i,
it's just a number as far as i is concerned,
and averaging the number is just the number.
So this gives us plus x bar squared.
Now,
notice that,
I'll deal with this one in a moment,
but notice this is not the same as
this.
This is the average of the square,
this is the square of the average.
Okay?
Two different
things.
The square of the average,
the average of the square,
and then what about this one?
What's the average of this?
It's just minus two x bar x bar,
x bar squared.
Averaging
x gives you x bar,
and it just multiplies this x bar,
so it's minus twice x bar squared.
Two of these,
one over here,
the result is just x.
Okay?
This one squared minus this one.
So this is a standard statistical fact,
that the variance
in a variable is the difference between the
average of the square and the square of the
average.
If I want to write it in a single notation,
I will write it this way.
The difference
of the average of the square and the
average of the average is the difference between the
average of the square and the square of the average.
That's the variance.
For a narrow
distribution,
when the distribution is narrowly peaked,
this is small.
The smaller it is,
the narrower the distribution.
So let's try to calculate.
Let's see how smart we can be.
Let's see if we can
calculate the variance in the energy.
Let's try to calculate the
variance in the energy.
What would it mean,
incidentally,
for the distribution to be sharply peaked?
It would
mean that the variance in the energy
is much smaller than the energy itself.
I guess we
would call this the square of the variance.
Call this the variance or the square of the
variance?
The variance.
All right.
But it's also the square of the uncertainty in X,
if you like.
It's the square
of the width of the distribution.
So we might want to
compare this quantity here with the
square of the energy itself.
In other words,
we might want to compare the difference of
these two to either one of them separately.
When that's small,
we say that the peak is
sharp.
But let's see how well we can do,
how far can we go,
in calculating this variance
per energy?
Man-hanna.
We've calculated the average of the energy.
Let's write down the formula.
The average,
there it is right here.
Let me set it right over here.
The energy is equal to minus
d log z with respect to beta.
Let's see if we can calculate the
average of the square of the energy.
This is the average energy.
Now I'm going to use the fact that
it really was the average of the energy.
Most of the times I don't bother writing this average,
but this is the average of the energy.
Minus d log z with respect to beta.
We'll wind up squaring it because
we're instructed to square it over here,
but first let's calculate the average
of the square of the energy.
So for that we need a
formula for this average of the square.
Average of the square.
The average of the square of the energy
is p of i times e sub i squared.
That's the average of the square of the energy,
which is equal to 1 over z sum
e to the minus beta e sub i,
that's p sub i,
times e sub i squared.
Remember what I did to find the average energy.
I just,
in that case we only
had one power of energy here.
We just differentiated with respect to
beta to bring down that e here.
What should I do to get the e squared?
Take the second derivative.
When I take the second derivative,
you'll find out that the average of e squared
is just 1 over z times the second derivative
of z.
With respect to beta squared,
correct?
I think now there's no minus sign.
Is it z or log z?
Uh,
z.
e squared gives you two derivatives.
Right.
z squared.
Now we can write down the variance.
The variance is first of all,
z squared.
1 over z d seconds z by Express.
by the beta squared.
Now we have to subtract
The average of e squared.
Which is minus
v log of z
by the beta
squared.
In fact,
let me write this slightly differently.
The log z by d beta is 1 over z,
dz by d beta.
So actually this is just 1 over z squared,
1 over z squared,
dz by d beta,
1 over z,
dz by d beta squared.
So it's the difference
between 1 over z times the second derivative of
z with respect to beta minus 1 over z squared,
dz by d beta squared.
That's the variance.
We're not finished with it yet.
This is simpler
than it looks.
This is,
I believe,
I think it's just the second,
or let's try it out,
the second derivative
of log z with respect to beta,
which I think what it is.
Let's try it out and find out.
The derivative of log z with respect to beta,
let's see,
the derivative of log z with respect
to beta,
that's 1 over z,
dz by d beta.
That's the first derivative.
And now we want to differentiate
it again with respect to beta.
So what happens when we differentiate this product here?
When I differentiate this product here,
I get one term,
which is 1 over z times the
second derivative of z with respect to beta.
That's here.
Now what's the other term when
I differentiate 1 over z with respect to beta?
That gives me minus 1 over z squared,
another
factor of 2 factors of dz by d beta.
Is that clear?
When I differentiate,
to get this here
for a moment,
let's put it over here,
dz by d beta.
When I differentiate 1 over z squared,
over z with respect to beta,
I get minus 1 over z
squared another dz by d beta.
So that gives me this term here.
So here's what I found.
I found out that the
that the variance is just the second
derivative of log z with respect to beta.
Okay,
let's examine it a little more closely.
The log z by d beta
Thank you.
That's equal to minus the energy.
So what this whole thing is,
I mean,
we've made a number of steps.
Whenever I do this,
I always feel
like I've done too many steps.
Like I've done the same
steps backward and forward and back.
physical interpretation
of z on
as to what z ..
part of the solution alpha for the
But I don't have a sense of this ..
Is this not a consequence?
No,
it's a function of beta.
It's a function of beta.
And whatever it is,
it contains all the information
about the thermodynamics.
It's a thing which you differentiate.
You take its logarithm.
You do all sorts of tricks with it.
And it generates the full thermodynamics.
What can I tell you?
It's free energy.
Or its logarithm is the free energy.
Or its logarithm is divided by beta.
We're going to calculate these things over and over.
And eventually,
you'll get some sense for what it is.
But I think there's no ..
Is it an intermediate type of variable?
Well,
it's a generating function.
It's a generating function that generates lots of answers.
You do things to it.
You know what it is?
It's the Laplace transform.
What is the Laplace transform?
It's the Laplace transform of the density of states.
Does that help you at all?
It doesn't have a simple interpretation,
something
you can measure.
It's something you do something to generate answers.
The action in mechanics is a thing
that you do things to generate equations of motion
and so forth.
The partition function is also a generating function
that you do various operations.
And you do things to it.
It's just about everything you
can think of in thermodynamics.
Fluctuations take us beyond thermodynamics,
incidentally.
So what are the units of z?
Say that again?
The units of z.
z is dimensionless.
Things in exponents are always dimensionless.
So when you sum things in exponents,
it's always dimensionless.
So it has been dimensionless.
I would say rather than
saying what its physical interpretation is,
which means,
I suppose that means how does it relate
to measurable quantities?
Is it a measurable quantity?
No,
it's not in itself directly a measurable quantity.
It's not what its physical interpretation is.
It's what you can do with it to generate things
whose physical interpretation you do not.
So we'll play with it a lot.
But in any case,
we've now seen that we can calculate
the fluctuations in the energy
as well as the energy itself.
But let's do a little more with it.
We're calculating the,
I guess I could call it,
the fluctuation in energy squared.
Let's think of it that way.
Uncertainty of the spread in the energy
is the unaccounted for.
And what we find out is that
it's the second derivative of log z
with respect to beta squared.
Now,
the first derivative of log z is just the energy,
or minus.
Minus the energy.
And so we have d
by d beta of the energy.
Now,
what is beta?
Beta is 1 over temperature.
So this can be related
to the derivative of the energy
with respect to temperature.
This is dE d beta,
which is dE by dT temperature,
times d temperature,
d beta.
But beta is just 1 over temperature.
So what's the dT d beta?
1 over T squared,
right?
Minus 1 over T squared.
No.
T squared.
T by d beta.
Let's write that out.
T is equal to 1 over beta.
dT by d beta is equal
to minus 1 over beta squared,
which is equal to minus T squared.
OK.
So did I lose a minus sign?
You have a minus sign.
Here it is.
dT by d beta is just minus.
That gets rid of a minus.
And this becomes T squared upstairs.
Now,
what is this,
dE by dT?
ありがとうございました
It's got a name.
The heat capacity.
It's the heat capacity.
The heat capacity
dE by dt
is the heat capacity.
It's the definition
of a heat capacity.
It's the amount of
well
numbers.
Hmm?
Yeah.
Amount of energy to change the temperature
by one unit.
How much energy do you have to put in
to change the energy by one unit?
Could we go back just a second here?
Yes.
We showed that the delta E squared
is the second derivative
of log Z with respect to theta squared.
Right.
Now where do we get from?
How do we get?
The first derivative
is just the energy.
The log Z by d theta
apart from the sine.
The log Z by d theta is energy.
So the answer is
the derivative of energy with respect to theta.
The log Z with
Okay,
so
I said it's your second.
Yeah,
the equation is right there.
The first derivative
is just the energy.
Now I want to differentiate this again
with respect to theta.
So it's just the E by d theta.
Which if I decide I would like to use temperature
instead of just for familiarity's sake,
if I like temperature better than beta,
which I do,
I mean,
essentially temperature,
I substitute the E d beta d beta d t,
and it gives me t squared times the specific heat,
not the specific heat.
I always say specific heat when I mean the capacity.
Heat capacity.
T squared times the heat capacity.
Okay.
First of all,
how does the heat capacity grow
with the number of particles in the system?
Remember what it is now,
or the size of the system.
Let's say the number of particles.
It's the amount of heat that you need
to change the temperature by one unit.
That's proportional to the number of particles.
The bigger the system,
the heavier the system,
the more energy you have to put in
to change the temperature by a given amount.
And in fact,
the heat capacity is proportional
to the mass of the system,
depending on what you use.
Let's just say the number of particles in the system.
So the right-hand side here is proportional
to the number of particles.
What about the energy itself?
Also proportional to the number of particles.
So the number of particles is
proportional to the number of particles.
But the square of energy is
what we should compare it with,
is the square of the energy.
As the units of squares of energy,
the square of the energy is proportional
to the square of the number of particles.
So in that sense,
the fluctuation is very much smaller
than the energy itself.
We should take the square root of both sides
in order to have a fluctuation in the energy.
The uncertainty in the energy
is T times the square root of the heat capacity.
Heat capacities grow linearly
with the number of particles in the system.
So this side here grows like the square root
of the number of particles,
but the energy itself grows linearly
with the number of particles.
So the fluctuation divided by the quantity itself
gets smaller and smaller,
like one divided by the square
root of the number of particles.
That's the demonstration,
if you like,
that fluctuations are small by comparison
with the quantities themselves.
So that's one way of seeing it.
I might also add one more point.
Let's keep track.
I rarely keep track of Boltzmann's constant.
But let's keep track of Boltzmann's constant.
In order to keep track of Boltzmann's constant,
I'll give you some standard,
let's call them undergraduate textbook definition.
According to the standard undergraduate textbook definition,
I'll call it temperature little t.
And little t is such
that it times the Boltzmann constant
is what I call big T.
That's the definition of Boltzmann's constant.
That's where the Boltzmann constant comes in.
And also the standard
undergraduate textbook definition of entropy,
which I will call little s,
you also multiply that by k Boltzmann
to get what I call big S,
what I call entropy.
No decent information theoretic physicist
would ever define anything except this.
Except if you're trying to compare things
to a definition of entropy
which was in some ancient textbook.
Then you would put a k Boltzmann.
Notice that k Boltzmann will cancel out,
let's see,
do I have this right?
Do I have this upside down?
kT is what I call temperature.
Well,
let's see.
The E equals TES.
Which should equal little t d little s.
So I think I have this upside down.
I think it's k Boltzmann of the denominator.
Yeah,
I think that's right.
This is standard textbook definition.
And it's such that when you write
that the E equals TES
it's the same as writing
in the undergraduate textbook sense.
The k Boltzmanns cancel out.
Just engineer the definition of entropy
so that they cancel out at the end.
T times s,
the Boltzmann counter.
Yeah,
that's correct.
These are standard definitions.
Is it very hard to prove
that beta is 1 over T?
We're going to do it at some point.
It's in the notes and we're going to do it.
But at the moment let it be a definition.
Okay,
yeah.
Well,
that's a definition.
But this was also a definition.
We have two definitions.
They could clash.
They don't.
So yeah,
we'll do that.
But not now.
Right.
Now let's go back to this formula over here
that the uncertainty in the energy squared
is equal to T squared times the heat capacity
which is what?
It's TES.
TES.
It's E by DT.
Does this formula make dimensional sense?
Well,
it does make dimensional sense.
But where does the Boltzmann constant go into this?
The answer is wherever you see capital P
and you want to use what's called an undergraduate
physics notation,
put K times little t.
So that means that we can put little te F,
little t squared,
little t here,
and then I think there's
one k Boltzmann in the numerator
here.
This is in fact the first place
in anything we've discussed where k Boltzmann actually
appears.
k Boltzmann appears in fluctuations.
This is the heat capacity.
It's a thing you measure in a laboratory.
It's neither terribly small nor terribly big.
It's just whatever energy it takes.
How much heat,
how many BTUs,
or how many calories,
or how many joules you have to pump
in to change the temperature by a certain amount.
So this is neither a terribly
small quantity nor a very big quantity.
This temperature could be room temperature,
300 degrees or whatever.
It's also not a very
big number or a small number.
We do expect for a big box of gas,
for a mole of gas,
for example,
we expect the fluctuation
in energy to be very small,
at least by comparison with the energy itself.
Here's another source of smallness.
k Boltzmann is a very small number.
How small?
10 to the minus 23rd.
So this number is 10 to the minus 23rd.
1.4 times 10 to the
minus 23rd or something like that.
So this tells us for a mole of gas,
the fluctuations in the energy at a reasonable temperature,
are very,
very small for no other reason because
k Boltzmann appears in the form of
that.
So yeah,
fluctuations are small.
Probability distributions are highly peaked when
the number of particles becomes large.
I think I found the
same C as the other one.
Yeah,
it was,
I think.
Well,
the other one was .
Oh,
you're right.
So what happened?
Maybe canceled,
like .
No,
kB shouldn't cancel.
Oh,
right.
I don't think it should.
Oh,
right.
It destroyed.
The e to the t,
the other e squared is equal to
the e to the t times t squared,
right?
Correct.
No.
It's going to be kb and
the denominator is going to be t.
Let's put t here,
and that would put a kb here,
right?
Yeah.
And then p squared would
be p squared times kb squared,
right?
Yeah.
You have the right thing.
The thing is just that what you wrote c
as equal to is the e by the h.
Oh,
you're right.
The standard definition of heat capacity
is the e by the little t,
all right?
So you're right.
I was careless.
Okay.
So here we have two kb's in the numerator,
one kb in the denominator,
and this is the thing that
you would normally call heat capacity,
the e by the little t.
Okay.
Good.
Thank you.
Very good.
All right.
So we see two senses in which,
first of all,
it's got a numerical constant in front of it,
which is very small.
But in the second sense,
it's also true that the fluctuation in
energy only grows as the square root
of the number of particles,
whereas the energy itself typically grows
as the number of particles itself.
That's characteristic,
of course,
of fluctuation growing as square root
of the quantity that's the fluctuation.
So that's the sense in
which the probability distribution is narrow.
Well,
let's see.
I think that's a good place to stop.
I really haven't.
Oh.
We have 15 more minutes.
The next time we're going to go
into the next part of the lecture,
we're going to go into
the next part of the lecture,
which is going to be the theory of the ideal gas
and not so ideal gas and do some things with it.
But let me just.
No,
I think we're going to stop here.
Let's stop and field some questions.
And if there are no questions,
yeah.
I think we should leave a little bit
early today because I didn't get my cookie.
I had a dog.
It was a dog.
I think I'm going to have
a pony show with the bankers today.
My wife,
who doesn't know anything about computers,
gets very,
very annoyed when the computer,
when some things happen,
and says,
your cookie has been deleted.
I also don't know what a cookie is,
but I don't get so annoyed.
I know that you want a cookie.
My cookie was deleted.
OK.
If there are no questions or other questions.
I've got a question from last.
You said the.
Good.
The quantities that are conserved like charge,
you would actually take the total quantity
of the universe as zero.
And.
Oh,
well,
that's where.
Yeah,
OK.
I did say that.
Last week,
I think he said the same thing with energy.
Yeah.
So where's the negative energy?
In a closed universe.
OK,
OK.
In a closed universe.
Yeah.
So I see all sorts of positive energy.
I don't see any negative energy.
No,
the negative energy.
The negative energy.
There's the a dot over a squared
term in the expansion of the universe.
It's the kinetic energy of expansion of space.
And it's purely got to do with geometry.
It's the expanding geometry of space.
And it's the term that
corresponds to the gravitational energy.
Gravitational energy.
Yeah.
The energy stored in the gravitational field.
And the gravitational field is geometry.
In this case,
the geometry is four-dimensional geometry.
Spatial geometry is expanding.
That means the four-dimensional geometry
is something that looks like that.
OK.
It's expanding.
It's not flat.
It's not flat space.
It has some energy of its own.
And that's the.
And that's associated with gravitational fields.
It's associated.
It's associated with gravitational fields.
If all the other energies are positive,
then it forces the universe to expand.
I see.
Yeah.
What about information?
You're saying that was more fundamental.
But it seems like all
the information of all the bubbles
was in this one .
All the information in what?
For all the bubbles in the energy term inflation.
Yeah,
yeah.
Are we getting it?
Are we going in there?
No.
Let's not go in now.
I'm too hungry.
Somebody wanted to ask me a question about the lecture.
You wanted to ask a question about Alex's lecture,
about the Lincoln's lecture.
That was that question.
He said that the total energy was zero.
Another thing is the argument for closed universe,
whether the total charge is zero,
is it's sort of.
It's sort of.
The lines of force came back.
Why doesn't that work for mass?
Let's say we have a closed universe.
Mass is energy.
OK.
So you would have gravitational lines.
Yeah.
And would they not all
converge the same way that they?
No.
You have to keep in mind that there's also
a gravitational component to the energy.
There's only one conservation law.
It's energy.
Mass is a.
It's not conserved in relativistic sense.
Mass itself is not conserved.
I say there's only one conservation law.
There are many conservation laws.
But energy and mass are not separate conservation laws.
Right.
And in general context,
it's just energy.
And energy has various components.
And in addition to all the usual stuff,
which by itself
is not conserved,
in an expanding universe,
the ordinary components of the energy are not conserved.
And the non-conservation is compensated for by a change
in the gravitational energy.
That's this.
OK.
Yeah.
So you can either say that in general relativity,
there's no concept of conservation of energy.
Or you can keep track
of pieces of the energy which
are a little unfamiliar.
And then you would say,
not conserved.
Not only is it conserved,
but it's exactly zero.
OK.
Didn't he say the cosmic horizon is
a million billion light years away from us?
Yeah,
that was his other one.
He said it's 15 billion less.
It's not.
He's probably more accurate than I was.
He said earlier time that things that are now
40 billion light years away
could affect our current universe.
And it's still significant.
OK.
Yeah.
He's probably a good guy.
He's probably more accurate.
15 was an order of magnitude within a factor
of three,
yeah.
No,
I'm sure he's right.
I didn't sit down and calculate it.
I think basically the difference is that there
isn't some expansion since the light that's
further related to the ..
Back down to the torus.
Yeah.
That's what makes that happen.
He's been cool.
I thought it was basic understanding of this.
The Boltzmann distribution.
Boltzmann distribution,
yes.
Does that increase energy?
If you increase,
let's see.
Just up to the top,
where we have the distribution of the I.
Yeah.
OK.
That's dj.
It seems that the lowest energy state is always
going to have the highest .
Yes,
it does.
So we have this long tip that gets longer
as the energy goes up.
So the ground thing always is the one that has
Yeah.
OK.
But right.
That is correct.
So let's put the key.
Let's put the key in over there.
At very,
very low temperatures,
the probability distribution
is sort of squashed toward very low energy.
As the temperature goes up
and you go to enormously high
temperatures,
what happens?
What happens?
And these are,
of course,
the states.
These are all states.
The distribution gets flat.
All states become equally probable at infinite temperature.
At infinite temperature,
that's a state of absolute maximum entropy
that you can possibly have.
Infinite temperature.
You know nothing about the system,
so all are.
Now,
there's another element here.
The typical temperature.
The typical states of a system
are not equally spaced like this.
If you were to write not state number here,
I,
but energy,
you would find out that the
low energy states are fairly well
separated from each other,
and they get denser and denser
and denser and denser and denser.
So if you asked about
the probability for a given energy,
not the probability for the I-th state,
you would find out that
hooks it toward higher energies
because there are just more states
with higher energy.
There are many,
many more states with higher energy than there are with
lower energy.
So if you wanted to know what
the probability is that the energy is
between two limits here,
you would have to say at a given temperature,
you would take the probability that
you're in the I-th state and multiply
it by the number of states in that narrow bin.
And that narrow bin gets more and more states.
You understand what I'm saying?
It's easy to get it right.
You get more what?
You get more.
There are more states within a given range of energy.
Let's say within a given range of energy,
delta E over here and delta E over here.
There are just many,
many more states here than there are here.
So the curve doesn't come up.
Is that a rule that there
are going to be more things?
It depends on what you're plotting.
If you're plotting the probability for the I-th state,
then it should be higher than the number of states.
Then it's just flat.
But if you're calculating the
probability for a given energy,
then it's tilted up a little bit.
Have you ever had a system where
you had a different kind of distribution
where you think about those low
energy states and everything just frees up?
You mean a very specific approach?
You're asking whether there's any
interesting situations where the probability
let's plot the I-th state,
not the energy itself,
where the probability distribution,
and so on and so forth.
Well,
it won't be equilibrium.
It won't be equilibrium.
But you can see from this incidentally why
it is that both the energy and the entropy
increase monotonically with temperature.
What happens as temperature increases?
At low temperatures,
the distribution looks a lot like that.
At higher temperatures,
the distribution gets spread.
It's completely obvious that the average energy grows.
But why does the average entropy grow?
Remember what entropy is.
It's the width.
It's the average number of
states contained within the distribution.
As the distribution gets flatter and flatter,
it contains more states with significant probability.
So both the entropy and the
energy are typically monotonically increasing functions
of the distribution.
So the temperature goes up,
the energy goes up,
the entropy goes up.
Can you give a pump laser an example of
a situation where you get that kind of modulation
in the region?
Yes.
And in those cases,
you get negative temperature.
We can talk about that next time.
Yeah.
But of course,
if you take the laser,
it really isn't the system in thermal equilibrium
where there's environment and everything else.
It's a…
But yes,
the answer is yes.
Question about the EI.
The EI is some number proportional to I.
I assume.
Is that correct?
What do you mean proportional to I?
Hmm?
Proportional,
you mean linear?
No.
Yeah,
because you're numerically…
No,
these states are not really equally spaced like that.
And what determines how they're spaced?
The system itself.
A prime mechanical particle in a
box would have a level density which…
Density.
Okay.
No,
I mean that's something you have
to know what the system is.
So you have to answer it.
That's a characteristic of the system.
I can tell you what the answer…
Well,
I will tell you now what another way…
The answer is that the density of states…
The density of states is
a function of an individual's body.
usually called rho of E
is the number of states
per unit energy.
It's the number of states,
let's call it delta N divided by delta E.
This is the number of states.
That's
E to the entropy.
We haven't proved that,
but that's a fact.
That
E to the entropy is the
density of states from all systems.
And so since entropy
is an increasing function of energy,
the density of states is also
an increasing function of...
So for
gas,
then,
it would have some
characteristic distribution?
Oh,
yeah.
Yeah,
We'll calculate that distribution.
It's equivalent
to calculating the entropy.
That's not obvious.
This is
the
questionable
result.
We're going to get into that next time.
Next time we will have to talk...
We're not
going to be speaking about quantum mechanics.
We will have to talk about
what happens when the energy distribution is continuous.
Okay.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.