Stanford University
Alright,
I was going to talk
about the second law of thermodynamics,
which I don't remember
if I talked about it all or not.
Did we talk about the second law?
But this is,
but,
remind
me,
did we talk about the second law?
No.
Alright,
so let's talk about the second law of thermodynamics.
It's a very tricky law.
On the one hand it says that a
certain something associated with the system always increases.
On the other hand,
Newton's laws of motion are reversible.
Any trajectory that is in
motion can be reversed and is another
possible trajectory where just everything runs backward,
where the movie runs backward.
What do you have to do?
Supposing I pick a solution of
Newton's equations.
Again,
let's take x and p.
That's a phase space and now a very simple
system with one coordinate and one momentum.
What is the trajectory of a system that is,
in the phase space,
supposing we start over here at
some instant of time and follow the
system and it goes to here.
That's a particular trajectory of the system,
early times,
late
times,
and it goes this way.
There is another trajectory of the system,
which is the time
reversed trajectory.
Is it just a trajectory from here to here?
Not quite.
It's
not quite.
The reason is that in order to reverse the trajectory,
you have to reverse
the velocity.
A trajectory which goes from here to here,
in order to find the inverse
trajectory,
the time reversed of it,
you have to start with the object going in the
opposite velocity.
That means you have to reflect
all velocities which may reflect all
momenta.
There's another trajectory,
let's see if I can draw this,
which looks like that,
which is just a reflection and the reflection just means that
at every point along the trajectory it's running with the opposite velocity
You know if you see a movie and you see a car
going over the certain velocity and you run the movie backward the car
Is going with the opposite velocity,
but it but other than the
fact that the velocity is reversed
Newton's equations are completely reversible
and so for example if there's a trajectory of a many particle
system where the particles start off in the corner of the room over
here and
then move to fill up the entire
system and come to thermal equilibrium and
After a time of order a few seconds or something.
Well,
it's probably longer than that.
But after a time of a few hours the
the
molecules just distribute themselves in thermal equilibrium
Then if we could get into that
system and reverse the motion of every molecule
In other words change the sign of its velocity
and run it it would according to Newton's equations
Just run backward and all the
molecules go back into the corner
Nobody ever sees that
And it seems to violate it
does violate the second law of thermodynamics
So what's going on?
How can it be that
Newton's equations are not the same?
Well,
the first law of thermodynamics is that the two equations are
time reversible and the second law of thermodynamics is a complete one-way
Job it tells you that systems always go
in one direction and never in the other direction
This was an extremely confusing point
That was sorted out relatively late,
you know the last 30 years or so
Boltzmann had much of the right ideas
But he didn't quite clinch
it then it took some time
The key is the idea of chaos.
So let's talk
And of course the answer is that
Not that this can't happen and the
system go to some very unlikely state
It's just that it's unlikely for the
system to go to an unlikely state
state.
So a sudden reversal of entropy
of a system going from a maximally
disordered state in which all the
particles are in random positions filled
up this volume here to a highly ordered
state where all the molecules are in the
same corner of the room,
that's not impossible,
it's just very unlikely.
So we
have to understand better,
if we want to understand the second law of
thermodynamics,
we have to understand the system,
the way systems move in phase
space,
because that is what it's all about,
how systems evolve in phase space.
Now again,
phase space is multidimensional and I will have to
represent it,
just necessarily because we don't
have enough dimensions on the
blackboard,
we will have to represent it in a
way that is more or less the same.
I will represent it as just two-dimensional,
P and X,
well X and P.
Now there is a rule in
phase space about the way systems evolve.
If you start with
a lump,
let's start with a lump in phase space,
there's a lump,
a nice round lump,
it's not particularly round,
but a nice round lump in phase space.
What does
that mean?
That means all of the possible
starting points in this lump here,
and evolve them,
evolve each one of them,
the lump evolves into some other shape.
Follow each point in the phase space with time,
it evolves into another shape.
What's the rule about the evolution
of the lump in phase space?
Equal volume.
Now,
if you have a lump,
now what a lump means is a probability distribution.
And let's
just take it for simplicity
to be the probability distribution,
which is zero on
the outside of the lump and not one,
but constant on the inside of the lump.
Alright,
so it's a probability distribution
which tells you no more and
no less than the system is in the lump.
And the lump evolves,
and after a time,
all
you know is that the system is
someplace in the displaced or evolved lump.
What is
the entropy of,
this is a probability distribution,
okay,
this is a
probability distribution,
and so it has an entropy associated with it.
The
entropy is logarithm of the number
of states that are in the probability
distribution.
If the probability distribution is flat or
over some set of states,
then the probability is simply logarithm of the number.
But wait
a minute,
we can't quite say that when the probability,
when the states are continuous
like this.
The number of states in there is quite infinite,
continuously infinite.
And
so in classical physics,
again,
we divide the phase space into little cells,
and the
right statement is that the
entropy is proportional to the volume,
to the logarithm of the volume,
did I say,
the logarithm of the volume in phase space.
That's the classical analog of the
logarithm of the number of states,
the logarithm of
the volume,
and the volume is conserved as the system moves,
as the system moves.
So
as time goes on,
no matter what the system does,
the lump in phase space has exactly
the same volume that it started with.
The implication is that the entropy,
since it's
just the logarithm of the volume in phase space,
stays the same.
But that's not consistent
with what we know about the way systems behave.
Entropy increases.
So we can state the puzzle
either through the puzzle of reversibility,
that what goes one way can go the other way,
that seems to be inconsistent with
the law of increase of entropy.
But we can state it
another way,
through the principle that the volume
in phase space is constant with time,
and that says that the volume's constant,
the logarithm of the volume is constant,
and
the entropy simply can't change.
Whatever the probability distribution is,
the entropy
can't change.
So where,
what is,
what is the meaning of the second law of thermodynamics?
And to understand that,
we have to first have
an idea of what chaos is.
Chaos,
to illustrate
chaos,
my favorite example is a billiard table.
Okay.
But let's make it an idealized,
frictionless billiard table with no pockets,
please.
No
holes in the billiard.
Everybody's played three cushion billiards,
right?
You know that
there are billiard tables that don't have holes in them.
Right.
So we got,
but we'll
put a whole bunch of billiard balls in.
We have all the numbered balls,
one through 15,
plus the cue ball.
The cue ball's over here.
Eight,
eight ball over here,
seven ball over
here,
and the cue ball.
Okay.
All right.
Now they're all in,
perfectly at rest.
It's a completely frictionless billiard
table.
The cushions are perfectly,
perfectly reflecting.
They're not made of rubber.
They're
made of,
they're perfectly reflecting cushions.
And so it's an idealized,
dissipation-less.
This is the game of dissipation-less billiards.
All right?
And we shoot the cue
ball at a very definite angle,
at a very definite velocity,
extremely precise.
the laws of mechanics tell us that the
system will follow in a deterministic way a
Trajectory which is infinitely predictable if we
know the infinite initial condition with perfect
exactitude
but
What happens if we make a tiny mistake in
the direction that we shoot the billiard ball in?
Well a tiny mistake here instead of
sending this billiard ball off this way
We'll send it off at a slightly different angle
It'll reflect
This one reflects over here and
as you can kind of see the
Now this one might hit this ball where
this one not hit that ball and boy then
Really the evolution after that point is entirely different
Okay
errors small errors are small deviations in the
initial conditions build up exponentially for most systems
Now there are special systems where this doesn't happen.
Let's just take one billiard ball on
a square billiard table
Then the motion
Or even better a one-dimensional billiard
One dimensional billiard and we shoot the ball this way
With a certain velocity just go
back and forth and back and forth,
and there's nothing to there's no
there's nothing to build up exponentially
All right,
this is quite stable
But most systems almost all systems are chaotic
chaotic means exceedingly sensitive to the
initial conditions in such a way that
Two initial conditions which are
close together in phase space
Will start exponentially deviating from each other
All right,
so if we take two points in phase space
And we follow them they're very close
We follow them they exponentially depart from each other
So the distance between those are between these two points
Let's say the initial separation was just
F epsilon the initial separation is epsilon
Then after a time the separation
will be epsilon times e to a
epsilon
because we have a very large number of points
and we have a very large number of points
I'll call it Delta times T
That Delta depends on the system
It may even depend on where
you are in the phase space
But in general it's a number that
exponentially increases the separation between phase points
If epsilon is exactly zero to begin with
The separation after time Delta T is also zero
But if epsilon is a
small very small number but nonzero
The separation after time Delta T is also zero
Then in not too long a
time depending on this Delta here
The separation will become large
Once it becomes large they
go off on their own way
And the trajectories don't resemble each other
This number here is called an
exponent or it's called a Lyapunov exponent
Lyapunov
Oh boy
U n I think
Yup
I think it's a U n
The Lyapunov exponent
And it just represents the degree of instability
It's always,
it's generally positive
And away you go
Okay now how can this be consistent with
the statement that the phase space volume stays fixed
If all points sort of,
whoops
If all points sort of deviate from each other exponentially
How is it that the phase space volume doesn't grow?
Okay how come it doesn't grow?
What happens is a little bit different
It's not that it grows
It separates into a kind of fractal
So let me try to draw
Roughly speaking what happens in a chaotic system
You start with a phase space
blob which is nice and regular
And you evolve
Well it starts to get a more complicated shape
And it starts to grow tentacles or filaments
Forms a filamentary structure
Where the filaments get kind of narrow
But the total volume doesn't change
You go a little further
And the filaments start to break up into very narrow
Lots of them
Oh god I hesitate to try to draw it
And
It becomes a kind of very complicated fractal
With exactly the same volume as it started with
But with a shape which
sort of spreads out its tentacles
So it's like a piece of cotton wool
You know a large piece of cotton
Yeah
If it's connected it stays connected
Yeah the topology does not change
If it's simply connected it stays simply connected
If it's multiply connected it stays multiply connected
But no matter how you start in a chaotic system
It starts to grow tentacles
And the tentacles cause the phase space blob
To sort of spread all over the place
And not only spread all over the place
But in a certain sense get very dense
Now its volume does not increase
So it's like a piece of great big fuzzy cotton
That could fill this whole room
Even though its volume if
you were to squeeze it down
So that you were actually looking
at the volume of actual material
Might be small
Okay
That's the way things evolve in phase space
Okay yeah
But how do we get thinner in the point
Well okay then we have to deal with quantum mechanics
And incidentally
The Planck unit
Planck's constant
Forget Planck length
We're not getting into quantum gravity at the moment
So forget Planck length
But Planck I think you meant Planck's constant
Yeah
Okay Planck's constant is a unit of area
Not a unit of length
Planck's constant is a unit of momentum times length
So it's a unit of area in the phase space
Okay
So
It's a proper question
But at the moment we're doing purely classical physics
Where Planck's length or Planck's constant
Corresponds to an infinitely small
An infinitely small volume
Or an infinitely small area in phase space
So there's no in classical physics
You never get to the Planck size
Now to do quantum mechanics
you have to do quantum mechanics
And there is a version of this in quantum mechanics
But this is the classical version
Okay so
The phase space volume gets very complicated
But without changing its volume in phase space
On the other hand
We should take into account
And we should always take into account
That in general our ability
To distinguish points in phase space is limited
Right
Not just limited because
Because the bathtub full of hot water
Just has a given temperature and not much else
But even if we had microscopes
That could see every particle
There still would be a limitation
Or we should assume that there is a limitation
On the
On our ability to resolve those points
Whatever that ability is
Let's represent it
By a small little
Cell
Not a cell
A small little blob in phase space
Which is itself much smaller than the original blob
And let's just say
Every point in this phase space
Is replaced
By a blob of that big
In other words we can't
We can't distinguish one point in the blob
One point in the mini blob
From another
And so we just fill it up like that
Alright we're gonna
Since these blobs are a little bit coarse grained
They might actually make the volume
If we replace every point on the inside
By one of these small blobs
It will increase the volume a little bit
Just because each point on the boundary here
Will be spread out a little bit
But on the whole
That won't be much of an effect
As long as the blob is
a nice regular blob like this
Okay
So if you start with a nice regular blob
The volume in phase
Of the coarse grain
This is called coarse graining
Coarse graining the phase space
Means
Looking at the phase space
There's a collection of coarse grained
Little areas like this
Coarse graining
A nice smooth configuration
In phase space
Doesn't change its volume significantly
But
As this starts to
Blossom more and more tentacles
You can see what starts to happen
I should
Let me try to draw this in a way which
Makes clear what begins to happen
Okay
So eventually we get to a configuration where
It just bristles out structure
Very very thin filaments
In every direction in the phase space
And now let's coarse grain
The
Fibers
On any one of the fibers
Right
We will trace back
To here
But on the other hand
If we start nearby
One of the fibers
The fibers have gotten so thin
That this chaotic behavior
The yapenoff exponent here
Instead
Whereas this point over here
Might have traced back to here
This point neighboring to it
Will trace back for a while
And then go off
To some wildly different place
Lesson is
That yes
If you did literally reverse
Every particle exactly
After the particles had left the corner of the room
They would go back to the corner
But make the tiniest mistake
In one particle
After a couple of collisions
The system will have essentially lost memory
Of the fact that it was just a time reverse
Of this very unlikely state
That you started with
And what will it do
It will just continue to fill up the room
With particles
Okay
So
Yes
It is possible to reverse the law of entropy
But the likelihood is extremely small
This whole blob of phase space here
This whole coarse grain blob of phase space
Is very big
Most of the points look a lot like each other
And it's only a terribly tiny fraction of it
That traces back to this extremely unlikely state
Most of it leads to configurations
Which are even bigger
And spread out even larger
That's the second law
That's the nature of the second law
That,
yeah
The two points you're talking about
That are close to each other
They're both within one of the filaments
No,
no,
no
One of them is outside the filament
And the other is inside the filament
Right
If they were both inside the filament
They would both lead back
They might lead back to different points here
Alright
So if they were both in the filament
Or in rather distant pieces of the filament
They would lead back to the same blob here
But if one of them
And remember these filaments are very fine now
Extremely fine
And so even if one point is just
A tiny minute distance outside the filament
With time the exponential growth
In the error
Will lead you to some wild
Really different point in the phase space
Most of those points that this filamentry
This coarse-grained filament will lead to
Will be of yet larger entropy
In other words if you follow them
Either backward or forward
It doesn't matter
Let's follow backward
If you follow backward
This point will go to here
But this point over here
Will go out to here
So if you follow all the points
In this filamentry structure backward
You will not get most of these points
Back into this tiny little volume here
Of phase space
They will go off
And make yet an even more complicated
Filamentry structure
The second law goes
Yeah
Sorry
Would you say that if you actually did
The full integral of that whole filament
Spider web
That you would always get the original volume
But that really you can't
I'm not sure what integral you want to do
Integral over the whole phase space
The implication of integrating over phase space
Is that you can go to every
Integrating
You can go to every point of phase space
And retrace it back exactly
Whereas if you're summing
Then you're sort of coarse-graining
Yeah
When you sum
You're effectively coarse-graining the phase space
So the amount of coarse-graining
Is related to the
Size of your delta x
It is
But it hardly matters
The answer is it hardly matters
How much coarse-graining you do
This filamentry structure grows so quickly
And gets so dense
That it doesn't matter very much
What the size of the coarse-graining is
It will define a blob
Whose size is pretty much independent
Of the size of the coarse-graining
Just because
These coarse-grained fibers
These fine-grained fibers here
Get very very close together
And it hardly matters
What your coarse-graining size is
The result of coarse-graining
Will be to fill up
The whole volume of this branched structure
Yeah
In that picture of the
guy jumping off a diving board
Into the pool
Yes
Okay
If he goes
If he ends up going back onto the diving board
Being pushed out of the pool
And being pushed out by the
molecules of the water in the pool
Yeah
Does that violate any basic law of physics?
No,
it violates no basic law of physics
Other than it's extremely unlikely
Because just one little molecular accident
Of the wrong kind
Will completely undo
So one little molecular accident means
A slight shift in the initial conditions
Will simply lead him plop back into the water
What I like about the Dulli ball one
And I think something calculated by Jupiter
Could have the gravitational effect of Jupiter
To change the path of space-to-space
To some degree
And that's how it's set
Say that again
That the gravity of the people sitting
Standing around the pool table
Oh
Could change
Could change the orbits of
The trajectory
Of the trajectory of
Of the building walls after a while
Oh sure
Yeah
Yeah,
just a butterfly waving its wings
A thousand miles away
Yeah
And then the day can
What about the question
What about the
I've heard that the second law of thermodynamics
Is the fact that it's obtained from this universe
Is a function of the initial conditions
Yes,
yes,
yes
Yeah,
no,
no
Yeah,
it does,
it does
If you follow this blob forward
It'll increase its volume
Follow it backward
In detail
From each point within the fibrous structure
And the volume will decrease
But coarse-grained it
Now you're going backward
You're going backward in time
But following the system backward in time
It'll still increase the volume of phase space
When you go backward
So the second law of thermodynamics
Would work in both directions
Start with an initial configuration
Run it forward,
run it backward
The most likely thing to happen
Is that entropy will increase
So then what is the meaning
of the fact that entropy increases
In one direction and not the other
The meaning of it
Is that the world started with a very low entropy
For reasons that have to do with cosmology
And that we don't completely know
For some reason
The world started in a state of very low entropy
Why?
Nobody knows
Because nobody knows that much
About the initial state of the universe
And why it was that it started
But what we do know
Is that the entropy was very low
That means we started out
In a very tiny blob of the phase space
If we ran it backward
That blob would expand
If we ran it forward
But
The fact is
Cosmologically
We know that the universe started
In a very ordered small volume of phase space
So the second law of thermodynamics
Also entails something about initial conditions
That the universe didn't start
In a random configuration
It started
In the analog
Of all the molecules off
in the corner of the room
And then they spread out
That's not exactly that
That of course is just an analogy
So yes
The meaning of the second law of thermodynamics
Is among other things
That the initial conditions
Were a configuration
Of very low entropy
Analogous to all the molecules in the room
Being in the corner
Yeah
If this is all predicated on
the idea of this heat path
Well actually not
If the
Actually not
Not really
No
This is not predicated
This is just predicated on the idea of chaos
This does not mean the system comes to thermal equilibrium
That's not the implication of this
It just means
That you spread out
And lose memory of where you started
Doesn't say that the system's energy levels
Are populated with certain probabilities
Okay
That's a separate story
Yeah
So is there a physical meaning to the coarse graining
Is it a statement about what we can observe?
What we can distinguish
What
Yeah
I think it's
I think it really does correspond to a
But the main point is
That the degree of coarse graining is not very important
Because eventually
No matter how small a coarse graining is
No matter how small these coarse grain volumes are
In not too long a time
These branches will get within that
Will get closer together than that volume
The smaller we make it
The longer the time it will take
For the branches to get that close together
But it's not
It doesn't depend very much on
the nature of the coarse graining
And so
Pretty much independently of the
nature of the coarse graining
Of the detailed numbers of the coarse graining
Just wait not too long
And the coarse graining will fill up the whole volume
Of course
There is a degree of coarse
Of fine graining or coarse graining
Which is so precise
That it will not get filled in
But then just wait a little longer
And it will get filled in
Even beyond the blank scale?
Look this is classical physics
If we want to do quantum mechanics
We have to do quantum mechanics
We have to get into what quantum chaos means
And we have to get into what
And that's already a separate subject
So this is classical physics
So there is a relationship between
the size of the coarse graining
And the amount of time it
takes for the system to become
That's for the amount of time for
Yeah
But it's not very sensitive
Okay
But can that
Is sensitive
Insensitive enough that it can be mapped
Over to the physical world
So this is the coarse graining
You could
You could imagine doing that
It may take 500 trillion years
In which case
Remember exponentials get big very fast
Right
So if this Yampanoff coefficient here
Is not very small
What corresponds to what here?
This distance between neighboring points
Which we might think of as the coarse graining
Is this epsilon here
How far apart they get from each other
Is epsilon e to the delta t
So two points which are close
Will get far very quickly
And that means that this branching structure grows very fast
It grows very very fast
Exponentially fast
And yes it's true
That given a time scale
Given a time scale
Given a time a thousand years
I can prescribe the coarse graining to be
Fine grained enough
So that your coarse graining will not fill up
The fractal structure here
Will not
What's the right words
You know smush it out
Okay
But on the other hand
Given a degree of coarse graining
As a general rule
Very very quickly that coarse graining will
Will be sufficient to
Smush the phase space
Is the coarse graining density
Constant after a while
Or is there a possibility
Yeah that's right
It gets
That's right
It becomes constant after a while
Right
On or okay
Up to a point
Energy is conserved
Okay
So you cannot fill up the phase space
If you start with
If you start
With the phase space blob
Being concentrated at some energy
All right
So what does it really look like
What it really looks like
Is in phase space there are surfaces
Of given energy
There's a surface of a given energy
In the phase space
Really this whole discussion should take place
On the surface
So starting on the surface with a blob
The surface
We will not get off the surface
That's just energy conservation
But on the surface the blob will
Begin to do this
Fractalating behavior
So apart from the conservation law of energy
Yeah after a while
This thing will really cover the phase space
Very uniformly
Yeah
With this very very intricate fine threads of
Question
Does this
Is there something about information
That you can say about this
So as time goes by
Do you lose information
Well you lose information
You lose information
Not because some fundamental law
Is not predictive
But because of the fine graining
Yeah I mean so information now
When you speak about information
You have to decide whether you're talking about
Fine grained information
Or coarse grained information
You never lose
Coarse grained information
Yes you do lose it
And you lose it in just this way
So what's the difference
Between the two
What's the difference
So that distinction has to be made
It always has to be made
Question
How come after 13.7 billion years
That little blob hasn't smeared itself
Over everything
And we're still structured here
Well okay so
The time scale
13.7 billion years is not long enough
That's all
What is the right time scale
Right time scale is probably about 40 billion years
More like 100 billion years
But it's exponential
This divergence is exponential
The universe
The universe is very big
You start on all the molecules
In the corner of the room
If the room is big enough
It will take a long time
For them to fill up the room
But it won't take a long time
For the entropy to start to increase
It will take a long time
For the entropy to increase
This tentacle structure here
Still hasn't grown
To fill up the whole phase space
So how big is the phase space
The phase space is very big
And it takes a long time to get filled up
But still the entropy starts increasing
Long before this thing fills up the whole phase space
ありがとうございました
In a critical way,
a dendritic growth.
Is what?
A dendritic growth.
A dendritic growth,
yeah.
Is a fractal structure?
Yeah.
Yeah,
it's similar to that.
It's quite similar to that.
Right.
It's similar to that.
Yeah.
But it's not just a fractal,
but it's a space-filling fractal.
A space-filling fractal which really
doesn't fill the fine-grained space,
but fills the coarse-grained space.
Yeah.
And it's not so easy to do that.
Well,
it's not so easy to picture it,
but that's roughly what happens.
You've emphasized the initial conditions as
being the thing we don't know exactly.
Say it again?
You've emphasized the initial conditions as
being the thing we don't know exactly,
but we never know the Hamiltonian exactly.
Right,
right,
right.
That's another point,
yeah.
If halfway,
if after we started,
let's say we're...
So we started here,
and we got to here.
And now we want to time-reverse it,
but we're going to time-reverse
it with a slightly different Hamiltonian.
It doesn't go back to here.
It does essentially the same thing as what would
happen if you displaced the point a little bit.
So,
yeah,
a slight change in the laws of physics
could completely undo the ability to reverse the...
Right.
What is this?
Is coarse-graining a result of a
violation of the prime conservation of information?
No,
coarse-graining...
Well...
So the information is destroyed if it's coarse-grained.
Yeah,
information is destroyed if it's coarse-grained.
Is that part of the violation of the...
Of the conservation of information.
No,
the conservation of information is the theorem
that says that the fine-grained entropy never increases.
Right.
So that's the big distinction.
Fine-grained.
Fine-grained versus coarse-grained.
The very,
very precise equations of mechanics say that
the volume of phase space doesn't increase.
And it doesn't increase or decrease.
Incidentally,
you can imagine laws of physics in
which the volume of phase space shrinks.
It's not too hard to imagine laws of physics where...
A blob in phase space would be allowed to shrink.
It's not allowable in standard classical mechanics.
But we could imagine differential equations
which sort of push things together.
That would correspond to
the Yop-Enoff coefficient being negative.
And things sort of coming together.
That would violate the second law of thermodynamics.
In a world like that,
the second law of thermodynamics would not be true.
So...
It's not...
It's not a law which is
true for all possible differential equations.
It's a law which is true for
those differential equations which result from standard mechanics.
You can't imagine systems
with negative Yop-Enoff coefficients.
I've been trying to understand the size
of this little coarse-grained parameter in terms
of entropy like Bs equals the
change in energy divided by temperature.
That's pretty much a fixed formula.
You said a moment ago that it's
not very sensitive to the size of that.
You have two objects and you put
them together and they reach the same temperature.
So the entropy goes up.
How does the size of that
little fine grain come into play there?
Is that too complicated?
It does a little bit in the formula for entropy.
Actually,
it's an additive.
It's an additive constant.
You know what it's connected to.
It's connected to the same
issue of replacing integrals by sums,
and replacing the integral
by the sum at worst
adds a constant to the entropy.
So when we talked last week
about the entropy of the black hole,
we're talking about a coarse
Absolutely.
Yeah.
And in fact,
in all of statistical mechanics and in thermodynamics,
the entropy that's
being talked about is coarse-grained.
In information theory,
one sometimes speaks about the fine-grained entropy,
but in statistical
mechanics and thermodynamics,
entropy means coarse-grained entropy.
Right?
So,
it means the coarse-grained or logarithm
of the coarse-grained volume in phase space.
Okay,
this is a deep and profound
point that puzzled people for many years,
and I think
it's more or less resolved.
This behavior,
this chaotic behavior,
I'm not exactly sure what the difference is between
something called mixing and something called...
And what's called chaos.
Mixing I think is the idea that
this branched tentacle structure covers the whole phase
space pretty uniformly.
Chaos is a little bit weaker,
I think.
I think it just says that the trajectories separate.
This I think is called mixing.
But they're closely related,
and I'm not sure if there
is a difference between them or not.
I've never been clear about that.
What the difference between mixing and chaos is,
if any,
if any.
Going briefly into the typology of quantum mechanics,
wouldn't the parameters of quantum
mechanics give a definition
of the degree of coarse-graining?
Yeah,
Planck's constant.
sure.
You can't make it smaller than Planck's constant,
absolutely.
But the reason that I say that...
Yeah.
You see.
if you replace
the sum by the integral
well that's this h bar to a power here
h bar to the n
that's the little cell in phase space
what happens if you multiply the
integral by the partition function by a
small
cell size
well all it does is add a
constant to the logarithm of the partition function
I just multiply the partition function
by this coarse graining here which just
replaces d3 px by you know it's
this business of the difference between the
sum
times the volume element
and the integral itself
that's just a numerical constant in
the entropy and doesn't affect anything
very significant in the thermodynamics
but wouldn't you need to factor
for the uncertainty principle in that
you need the only thing you really
well okay
in quantum mechanics when you're
thinking about real quantum mechanics
yeah this this thing does matter
but in discussing the classical limit
of quantum mechanics in a classical limit
this just factors out as an all-over multiplicative
factor
in the partition function approximately
to the extent that you can replace sums by integrals
this just factors out as a multiplicative constant
and when you take the
logarithm it's just an additive constant
an additive constant in the ah in a
in the free energy
and in the entropy
okay so it's not a significant thing
no other questions about the second law?
okay that's uh...
all right we have twenty minutes
let's do some
is that right?
we have twenty minutes
and in the twenty minutes i want to start some
we actually did some
quantum statistical mechanics didn't we?
we did the problem of
the rotor
and quantized the angular momentum
that had to do with this funny paradox about
complex or structured molecules
why the structure disappears at low temperature
why you don't have the equi partition
of energy distributed among all the various
modes of uh...
motion of a molecule
why you can pretend molecules are point molecules
i want to do another example of it
and this example
has many many applications
it is nothing but the harmonic oscillator
we didn't do this,
we didn't do the quantum oscillator
in fact i don't even
think we did the classical oscillator
let's suppose
that
a molecule
has the structure of a harmonic oscillator
in other words the internal degrees of freedom
are described by an oscillation of some kind
not the overall motion of the molecule,
the overall motion of a molecule
it's similar mass motion
it still moves exactly as
it did in the point- ‫
molecule case,
but the internal structure of the
molecule is just described by an oscillation.
We haven't done that yet.
Again we can start classical and see how much
energy we expect to be stored in the oscillations.
So let's do that.
Let's take the case of,
now this is a fictitious molecule,
and the fictitious molecule is just
two points on a spring,
described by a Hamiltonian or an
energy function which is just p squared
over twice some mass parameter.
It's not the overall mass of the molecule,
it might be some,
what's it called,
the relative
mass,
reduced mass.
It could be the reduced mass of the two particles,
and it oscillates about its center of mass,
but whatever it does.
This is the kinetic energy
of the motion of the molecule,
and then there's a potential
energy,
and the potential energy is the
amount by which the molecule is stretched.
It's proportional to some spring constant,
which we call k,
k squared,
k squared x squared,
where x is not the position,
k squared x squared over two,
x is not the position of the center
of mass of the molecule,
it's just the coordinate which describes the oscillations.
So let us not confuse the two.
Let us not confuse it.
I could have given it different names,
but I don't have,
you know,
I'd rather just call
it p squared plus x squared.
k squared or just k?
k,
sorry,
k.
Thank you.
So this molecule is now an oscillator,
and the limit that k becomes very large,
that's
the limit of an extremely stiff spring.
It becomes prohibitively expensive.
It's very expensive to stretch the string by,
by the spring by any finite amount.
So you might expect that in that limit,
when k becomes enormously large,
that the molecule
will behave like a point molecule.
It'll become exceedingly difficult to excite
any significant amount of vibration because
the spring constant is so large.
And that should be right.
I mean,
if anything is right about,
about molecular physics,
then that should be right,
that,
that internal structure should be frozen
out at very low temperatures in particular.
All right.
Let's,
let's just imagine now the statistical
mechanics of a single harmonic oscillator
in thermal equilibrium.
Let's focus on just one molecule,
and let's focus,
let's forget the center of mass motion.
That we know how to deal with.
That's just the usual description of the molecular motion.
Let's just focus on the internal vibrations of the molecule.
Let's focus on the internal vibrations of the molecule.
And to do that,
we just think of the molecule or its internal
motions as a system in thermal equilibrium with everything else,
and the probability distribution for the p's and the
x's is just governed again by the Maxwell-Boltzmann distribution.
Now just a single molecule,
a single x and a single p,
and the partition function for that single molecule is
just the integral dx dp e to the minus beta,
where beta is inverse temperature as always,
times p squared over 2m plus kx squared over 2.
Now before I go and calculate this,
let me just point out one connection.
What's the frequency of this harmonic oscillator?
The frequency of vibration,
omega.
Square root of k over m.
You can do that by solving Newton's equations.
Newton's equations are f equals ma.
The force is kx.
Mass times x double dot.
And you can see that the important quantity
is k over m by dividing by m.
That's the frequency.
k over m,
square root of k over m is the frequency.
So let's keep track of that.
Frequency of the oscillator omega equals
square root of k over m.
Now,
here's the partition function.
It's easy to compute.
We've done this sort of thing before.
The two integrations,
notice that in the exponent,
the p squares and the x squares add.
That means that this factor is a product.
It's a product of e to
the minus beta p squared over 2m,
e to the minus beta p squared over 2m,
kx squared over 2.
And the integrals,
also,
the integral is also a factorized structure.
dx and dp.
So dp,
integral dx.
Just two separate factorized integrals.
We know how to do this integral.
We've done this integral before.
Anybody remember what it is?
Just a p integration?
Square root of pi.
Well,
it's not quite the square root of pi.
It's the square root of pi times 2m,
2pi m over beta.
Right?
That's what this integral is.
You have to change variables to get 2pi,
to change variables so that this is
just e to the minus x squared,
or e to the minus something squared.
We've done that integral.
And it's just the square root
of 2m pi divided by beta.
The important thing here is the beta dependence,
but let's track the whole thing.
Now,
what about this integral?
This integral is exactly the same kind of integral,
except instead of integrating over p,
we're integrating over x.
Well,
x is just an integration variable.
That doesn't matter.
And the only difference is that whereas
you had a mass in the denominator here,
you have a spring constant in the numerator here.
So I can immediately read off that the answer is,
2pi,
and instead of m in the numerator,
we'll have k in the denominator.
And that's it.
That's the partition function for one harmonic oscillator.
And that altogether is equal to 2pi over beta
times square root of m over k.
But that's just 1 over omega.
That's the partition function.
Really easy.
Classical partition function.
What's its logarithm?
Log of z is equal
to log of 2pi over omega.
Those are constants.
Omega is a fixed constant plus or minus log beta.
What is the energy?
Oh,
incidentally,
minus log of z,
which is the thing that we differentiate.
What is the average energy of the oscillator?
It's the derivative of minus
log z with respect to beta.
That's just 1 over beta.
So the energy of this
oscillator is just 1 over beta,
which is just the temperature.
Not a half the temperature,
not three halves the temperature,
but just the temperature.
The reason it's 1 times the temperature
and not a half times the temperature
is because there are two integrals here.
You get two factors of the square root of beta
in the denominator,
and that gives you temperature for the energy.
Notice that it doesn't depend on the spring constant.
The partition function depends on the spring constant
through omega here.
Incidentally,
very,
very large spring constant
means very large omega,
very large frequency,
very rapid vibration.
On the other hand,
no matter how large omega gets,
the energy stored in that oscillator
is always just T.
So,
again,
we have the same paradox again,
that no matter how stiff we make the molecular bonds,
this harmonic oscillator molecule
always stores this much energy
in the internal vibrations,
and there does not seem to be a limit
in which it goes over to the point molecule.
The point molecule would be the situation
where the internal energy was just zero.
You might have expected
that when the spring becomes so stiff,
that the molecule would behave as a point molecule,
and then there would be no internal energy.
There would still be the energy of translation,
but no energy of vibration.
So,
again,
the same paradox
as with respect to the rotational motion of an oscillator.
The solution,
and there's a paradox,
I mean,
molecules at low temperature
do behave like point molecules.
At low enough temperatures,
they do behave.
And this doesn't say only at high temperatures,
it's at every temperature there's this much energy.
But in fact,
it's not true.
The solution is,
again,
quantum mechanics.
And so,
in order to understand it,
we have to think about the quantum mechanics
of the harmonic oscillator.
Now,
the quantum mechanics
of the harmonic oscillator
may or may not be known to you in detail,
but I think almost everybody,
at least in this class,
knows the result.
And the result is that the energy levels,
and this is all we need,
that the energy levels are discrete,
and the nth energy level is
n,
n now is an integer,
times h-bar,
times omega.
Did I leave anything out?
Zero energy.
But it doesn't make any difference,
because adding a constant to the energy
doesn't affect anything in statistical mechanics.
You can check that yourself.
Adding a constant would affect no
observable quantity.
Of course,
it would affect the energy per,
it would affect the energy,
but that's only because you added
a constant to the energy,
so it will shift all energies by that same constant.
All right,
so that's good enough.
That's good enough for our purposes.
And now we can calculate the partition function
of the quantum oscillator.
I think we can do it in ten minutes.
Z is now not an integral,
but it's a sum.
And it's a sum over n,
all the energy levels,
of e to the minus beta
times the energy.
h-bar,
omega,
times n.
All right,
so for example,
what is this?
This is one.
That's n equals zero.
The first excited level,
plus e to the minus beta h-bar omega.
The next level,
plus e to the minus twice beta h-bar omega,
but I'm going to write that as
e to the minus beta h-bar omega squared.
And then plus the same thing,
plus the same thing again,
plus the same second,
minus half,
and plus the same thing,
minus the sum of all myственно,
plus one over one minus e
to the plus beta h-bar omega squared.
So to do the final German logic,
so that LIKE2 is mod of 0 to the
factor n times,ucher,
whole here
in this end.
And so
we have what we call the square
root of three.
We get
two numbers,
that one,
every two numbers,
trướcrat and thsult,
divided by one minus e to
the minus beta h bar omega
that's z
this is just the oscillator,
just the oscillator
this is the other 2 pi
the 2 pi m over beta
is the other 2 pi m
no this is the full harmonic oscillator,
this is the harmonic oscillator,
the classical harmonic oscillator
this is the quantum harmonic oscillator
but doesn't it have,
didn't one of those things come
from the p squared over 2 m?
no,
the p squared over 2 m plus
the kx squared over 2 is what's quantized
right,
it's the sum of these two which are quantized
remember this is not the overall translational motion
no,
it's the sum of them which comes in discrete levels
it is the full energy of the oscillator
the oscillator vibrates in discrete
right?
good?
yeah,
ok
alright,
so here's the partition function,
that's it,
it took 2 minutes to do
and now we can calculate the average energy
and see what the average
energy of the quantum oscillator does
at low temperature and at high temperature
and see exactly what it does
alright,
so what do we want to do?
we want to calculate the logarithm of z
or minus the logarithm of z to be precise
that's what we're interested in
and that's equal to the logarithm of 1
minus e to the minus beta h bar omega
the minus sign came because
this thing is in the denominator
and logarithm of a denominator involves a negative sign
ok,
who's strong enough to differentiate
this with respect to beta?
alright,
I am
superhero will now differentiate
ok
first of all logarithm gives you 1 over the argument
1 over the thing in the logarithm
1 minus e to the minus beta h bar omega
now we have to differentiate the thing inside here
alright,
the beta,
that means differentiate the exponential here
there's a minus sign from here
and now we have to differentiate
the exponential with respect to beta
that's going to give us another minus sign from here
so it'll become plus
and then just h bar omega e
to the minus beta h bar omega
we differentiate it with respect to
beta which gives us the exponential back
but then h bar omega from differentiating,
you see what it is
that's the formula
this is the energy of the harmonic oscillator
in thermal equilibrium at temperature 1 over beta
it is not exactly,
it's not in general equal to the temperature
the temperature being 1 over beta
not at all that
but let's look at it at different limits
let's first look at it
in the limit of high temperature
we expect classical physics
why do we expect classical physics at high temperature?
the reason is that at high temperature
this tiny little unit of energy
that's in the oscillator is irrelevant
the energy,
the oscillator is excited to such high energy
that it doesn't give a damn that the
energy is quantized in these tiny tiny little steps
so we expect the classical answer for high temperature
okay,
let's look at it for high temperature
high temperature means small beta
okay,
did I get this right?
yeah
okay
no beta in the numerator
no,
no beta
incidentally,
I can write this a little neater
multiply the top and the bottom by
e to the plus beta h omega
that'll turn into something a little bit simpler
h bar omega
if I multiply by e to the plus beta,
this one will go away
and I'll get e to the beta h bar omega
omega minus one
that's a little neater
hmm?
yeah,
minus,
no,
plus
plus,
okay
let's look at it at very high temperature
high temperature means small beta
small beta,
we expand the exponential
we have a small number here
and what's the expansion of e
to the beta h bar omega?
e to the beta h bar omega
is equal to one plus beta h bar omega
plus higher order stuff
plus higher order
alright,
the only reason I have to keep
the first correction here
is because the one cancels
okay,
so the one cancels
and after the one is cancelled,
this is just h bar omega
divided by beta h bar omega
the h bar omegas cancel
and one over beta is temperature
so at high temperatures,
when beta is small
we just reproduce the classical behavior
so when the temperature is high enough
to be able to excite the discrete vibrations
of the harmonic oscillator
we reproduce this situation where
the oscillator has temperature t
but what about low temperatures?
at low temperatures,
beta is very large
e to the beta h
omega is very large in general
the one can be ignored
in that limit
this is now low temperatures
and you can see that the
energy in the oscillator is exponentially small
beta is very large at low temperature
this exponential here is very large
and the energy in the oscillator is very very small
exponentially small
alright,
so the oscillator at low temperatures
is frozen out
it's frozen out by quantum mechanics
the h bar omega in the numerator is insignificant
by comparison with the exponential in the denominator
exponentially small energy
and so the internal vibrations,
as I said,
are all very small
and so the internal vibrations are frozen out
is there anything else worth
seeing about this at the moment?
well,
that is the important thing
oh yeah,
one other point
where is the crossover?
at high temperatures,
it's t
at low temperatures,
it's this exponentially small thing
where does it go?
so let's see,
what does it look like?
at small temperatures,
as a function of temperature
let's say
this is extremely small
and it goes to zero
very very quickly at small temperatures
okay
and then,
at some point
it takes off and it goes linearly
like this,
with temperature
somewhere in here,
there's a transition
it's not a sharp transition
it's sort of spread out
from exponential behavior to linear
but where does it occur?
it occurs
when the exponential behavior
when this exponent gets to be about of order one
somewhere in the vicinity
when the exponential gets to be of order one
that's where the transition happens
and that means when beta h bar omega
well,
order one or order two
or order three or some number
not order one,
because order one happens when beta is equal to zero
but at some numerical value of this exponential
it turns over and goes from one thing to another
that means it happens when beta h bar omega
is about equal to one
but what is beta?
beta is one over temperature
so it happens when the temperature
is about equal to h bar omega
in other words,
when the temperature is high enough
that the classical approximation
would allow the system to
have one quantum's worth of energy
below that temperature
the oscillator is frozen
above that temperature
it doesn't realize that it's
not a classical harmonic oscillator
and somewhere in between the transition happens
so that's what tells you at what temperature
the transition between quantum
mechanics and classical mechanics happen
the lower the frequency of the oscillator
the lower the temperature at
which the transition takes place
so if you have a very floppy
oscillator with a very very small frequency
then at low temperatures
it starts to get excited
the transition happens at the
on the other hand if
you have an extremely stiff oscillator
it takes a high temperature before
it starts to behave classically
alright,
that's the basic theory of the harmonic oscillator
and it governs just about every system in nature
that we can solve
but in particular it governs black body radiation
so next time we'll talk a
little bit about black body radiation
and get more confusion about integrals again I'm sure
because we'll discuss black body radiation