Stanford University.
The last time we discussed both the classical,
I think,
and the quantum mechanical
description of harmonic oscillators.
And we found classically that
every harmonic oscillator has an energy
which is independent of its
frequency and equal to the temperature.
In thermal equilibrium.
We calculated the partition function,
and we calculated the average energy
of any harmonic oscillator and found out
that the energy was just equal to T.
When I say T,
it would be the textbook
KT equals what I call temperature.
Alright,
that's a true statement.
It led to this puzzle
about molecules which have little oscillators.
How come in a very low temperatures,
also the molecules don't exhibit this energy,
because it's not there.
We know that the molecule will not
exhibit internal energy at very low temperatures.
And we found out that the
answer had to do with quantum mechanics.
Instead of the energy being
equal to T in quantum mechanics,
we found out,
well,
let's just go through it.
I'll go through it very briefly.
There's some points here that are worth emphasizing.
The energy levels of the quantum mechanical oscillator
are E sub N equals H bar omega N.
We can drop this ground state energy,
it's not important,
or put it in.
It doesn't matter,
it won't make any difference to anything.
Incidentally,
there's an interesting point here.
The uncertainty principle is a correct principle,
but you can think of it a little more broadly.
Any given quantum state always corresponds.
Now,
I'm using the word correspond loosely,
and I'm not going to
tell you precisely what it means,
but it corresponds to a little patch in phase space,
X and P.
It corresponds to a little patch in phase space,
where the area of that
patch is equal to Planck's constant,
and maybe it's Planck's constant over 2,
I don't remember offhand.
And it's not a question
of greater than or equal to.
It is equal,
any given quantum state,
to a patch of size H bar,
of area in the phase space equal to H bar.
Now,
if the area is a little circle,
that's sort of the most tightly knit kind of thing,
that's a kind of quantum state,
then a little circle in phase space,
then clearly delta X and delta
P will be equal to each other,
and delta X,
delta P will equal H bar,
will be proportional to H bar.
If the size of the area of
the circle is of order H bar,
and I'll use the term of order,
of order H bar,
then if we take a
nice little symmetric disk like this,
then delta X times delta P
will be equal to H bar.
There are other quantum states which have the same area,
which might look like ellipses.
Again,
for an ellipse like this,
if delta X times delta
P is equal to H bar,
or if the,
sorry,
if the area of this
patch is equal to H bar,
then again,
delta X times delta P
will be equal to H bar.
But then there are much more peculiar states.
There are states,
quantum states,
which correspond to the area H bar,
but which are spread out
in some other kind of way.
Uh,
like that.
The properties of the quantum state
can be identified with a patch of phase space
whose area is equal to H bar,
but it's quite apparent for this kind of configuration,
this snaky kind of configuration whose area is H bar,
that delta P times delta X
is really greater than H bar.
Delta P means the spread in momentum.
Delta X means the spread in X.
And if you don't keep the configuration
tightly knit into some circle or ellipse or rectangle
or something like that,
but let it get spread out
into this kind of snaky configuration,
then you can take a quantum
state which occupies area H bar
and nevertheless make it have delta X and delta P
such that the product is greater than H bar.
So,
it's kind of interesting,
and I'm going to give you an example now.
An example where this is useful in thinking,
it's the harmonic oscillator.
Let's just take the Hamiltonian to be
P squared plus X squared over 2.
I don't want to introduce any constants into here.
It just makes it simpler.
And the ground state,
the ground state is this wave function
or this probability distribution,
which is concentrated at the center,
and it has an area H bar.
Delta X times delta P is H bar.
Now,
what about the first excited state?
The first excited state,
if you think about a harmonic oscillator,
harmonic oscillators oscillate,
and they oscillate in both momentum and position.
And if you think about the way
the phase point moves in phase space classically,
it moves in circles.
When the circle is projected onto the horizontal axis,
you have the ordinary oscillation of position.
When it's projected onto the vertical axis,
you have the oscillation of the velocity or the momentum.
The next excited state represents a harmonic oscillator
with a little bit of increased energy
moving around in a semi-classical
and an approximate classical description in a circle,
and so it occupies a little ring of phase space.
But how big is that ring
or how thick is that ring?
That ring must be such that the
area is again equal to H bar.
The next excited state is
another ring of area H bar.
As you move out,
as you move out,
the width,
since the total area of each
state is equal to H bar,
as you move out further and further,
the thickness or the thickness of the annular ring
describing each quantum state does get thinner and thinner,
but the area stays the same.
What's the radius of the nth circle here?
Anybody figure that out?
If we take the nth circle,
what...
H bar is the area.
Now,
nH bar,
yeah,
nH bar is the area of...
Yeah,
nH...
Wait.
H bar is the area of the circle,
of the annular ring.
Okay.
All together,
nH bar is the total area.
Yeah.
And then divide by the number.
Well,
I'll tell you what the answer is.
The answer,
I believe,
is the square root of n
is the...
is the radius of the circle,
the square root of n.
Okay.
So the radius of the circle
here is the square root of n,
the square root of the nth circle,
just fitting them together.
Yeah,
question.
Is there a question?
Does pi r squared have to be...
There's pi r squares,
but...
Again?
Oh,
I think...
No,
we're just talking about...
We're talking about the radius of an annular ring,
the nth annular ring,
such that each one butts up against the next one
and gives you a disk of...
of area n.
Yeah,
the area that there's n such...
We're talking about the nth ring,
each one has area h bar.
So what is the area of the whole disk here?
The whole area of the
whole disk is proportional to n,
but the area of the annular ring...
All right,
let's...
Okay,
let's do it.
The area of the whole disk is n.
So the area n times h bar.
I just want to figure out
whether it's n to the 1 half,
n to the 3 quarters,
what it is.
The area of the whole thing is n,
yes,
times h bar.
That's the area of the whole thing.
And that's equal to pi r squared,
where r is the radius
of this disk in phase space,
right?
Pi r squared.
All right,
so that tells us that n h bar over pi,
the square root,
is equal to r.
Now,
what...
What does that mean about the...
Oh,
that does it,
doesn't it?
That tells us that the radius
of the annular ring out here,
the nth annular ring,
is proportional to the square root of n.
That's the important thing.
It's proportional to the square root of n.
In fact,
it's proportional to the square
root of n times h bar.
Now,
what is this radius?
If you look at this formula over here,
you see that this radius is
proportional to the square root of n.
So the square of the radius is essentially the energy.
The square of the radius,
we can think of this as r squared,
and it is just the energy,
apart from a factor of 2.
I'm being loose with factors of
2 and even with factors of pi.
So p squared plus x squared is the energy,
and that's equal to r squared.
r is of order n h bar,
so that means that the energy is of order...
n h bar.
n squared.
No,
no,
no.
r squared is just of order n h bar.
So the quantization of energy can be just thought of
as the uncertainty principle for
the case of the harmonic oscillator,
but the uncertainty principle
not thought of as delta e,
delta p greater than h bar,
but a different kind of uncertainty principle,
which tells you that every quantum state
occupies a little region of phase space,
which is of order h bar in area,
but that doesn't mean that the
shape has to be a little circle.
In this case,
the shape is annular rings.
The uncertainty of delta x times
delta p of these excited states
is much bigger than h bar.
If I take this nth excited state here
and ask what is its
delta x and its delta p,
they're this big and that big,
and it's much bigger than h bar.
So that's a useful way to think about quantum mechanics,
that quantum states are to be identified
as patches of phase space whose area is h bar.
Each one of these is a unique quantum state,
distinguishable,
discrete,
and so in any one of these states,
no matter how big delta x and delta p get,
every single one of them
is a unique definite quantum state,
and if you know that the
system is in that discrete quantum state,
then the probability distribution in quantum states
is just localized at one unique quantum state
and the entropy is zero.
In thermal equilibrium,
of course,
these different rings,
have a probability distribution,
and it's the Boltzmann distribution,
and the entropy is whatever it is.
All right,
so I got sidetracked into an interesting discussion,
but let's go back to the classical
and the quantum mechanical harmonic oscillator.
The classical harmonic oscillator up in the left-hand corner
has energy E equals T.
The quantum mechanical oscillator,
did we write down the answer?
Okay,
let's write down the answer.
The energy of the quantum mechanical oscillator
is omega H bar.
Oh,
let's just go through again
where it came from very quickly.
We calculated the partition function.
The partition function came from summing up
over all the quantum states,
which means summing up over all those annular rings,
E to the minus beta.
We start with the partition function,
E to the minus beta times
the energy of the nth level,
which is H bar omega times n.
That's a geometric sum.
Let me just very quickly go through it.
Sum,
that's equal to one over one minus
E to the minus beta H bar omega,
or equal to E to the,
that's good enough.
That's a good way to express it.
Okay,
and then from that,
we can calculate the energy of the oscillator,
this is Z.
Log Z we can calculate.
Log Z is just a logarithm of this,
and we can calculate the derivative of minus log Z
with respect to beta.
That's the energy,
average energy of course,
of the oscillator,
and that's equal to omega H bar
divided by E to the
beta omega H bar minus one.
The one coming from the one,
you know,
you see what it is.
All right,
so that's the energy,
and if you look at it
and stare at it for a minute,
you realize that at high temperature,
when beta is small,
we can expand this exponential,
it becomes one plus beta
omega H bar in the denominator,
minus one omega H bar,
and one minus one,
one cancels,
omega H bar cancels,
and the answer is one over beta,
which is temperature.
So at high temperatures,
we reproduce the classical physics,
but at low temperature,
when beta is very large,
when temperatures are low,
beta is large,
this exponent here is very large,
you can forget the one,
and the energy is just
omega H bar
e to the beta omega H bar,
and that's extremely small.
When beta is large,
temperature is small,
the energy is tremendously suppressed
compared to the classical answer.
So that's the solution,
if you like,
of the puzzle of what happens to the,
to the
classical energy stored in,
at very,
very low temperatures.
It's much less than you would have gotten
from classical physics.
At high temperatures,
they're the same,
at low temperatures,
it's very hard to excite the oscillations,
basically.
All right,
one other thing,
the n which appears here,
we can just define,
by definition,
we will call it the number of quanta
in that oscillator.
We'll think of the oscillator
as having an occupant,
or occupation number,
whatever that means.
Just definition.
The occupation number
of the harmonic oscillator
is just which of these rings
you're on,
or which quantum state,
in the sense of
how many units of energy
does the quantum state have,
units of energy in units of H bar omega.
So that's,
if you like,
a definition of the number of quanta
in that oscillation.
The next thing we're going to come to
is blackbody radiation.
Blackbody radiation is a historical,
of enormous historical importance,
and of course it's also of importance
in many,
many other ways besides history,
but it has a glorious history
in being the origin of quantum mechanics,
or the historical,
yeah.
Was this thought of as a paradox?
Which?
The,
the,
the fact that the,
the classical result
of the,
energy being equal to the temperature?
Yes.
Yes,
but it wasn't,
it wasn't,
it was...
What I'm wondering was,
I mean,
it could have been interpreted
as a need for other physics
at one time,
you know.
Okay.
The answer is,
I don't know the degree
to which people actually are worried about that,
about the molecular,
you talk about the molecular internal motions.
Right.
I'm quite certain that they did worry about it,
but remember that they knew very little
about molecules at that time,
and the whole idea of molecules
had yet to be really established.
So my own guess is that,
yes,
they knew about it,
they worried about it,
but it wasn't in the front burner
the way that the black body radiation was.
Radiation,
they thought they knew everything about.
Wave theory,
electric and magnetic fields,
they thought they really understood
electromagnetism.
And the puzzle,
which was very similar,
a very,
very similar type,
was that a box of radiation,
by a box of radiation,
I mean we take some cavity,
I guess we would call it,
with reflecting walls.
Now,
of course,
we don't have perfectly reflecting walls,
it doesn't matter much.
In fact,
it's even better
if they're not perfectly reflecting,
but they allow,
they transmit some energy through them,
then we can say
that whatever's in the box
will come to a thermal equilibrium on the outside,
with the outside at a given temperature,
and then we can say
that whatever's in the box
But what can be in the box?
Radiation can be in the box.
Radiation bouncing back and forth,
waves of radiation bouncing back and forth,
radiation of different wavelengths.
Now,
it was known from very early times,
early times from,
you know,
from Maxwell theory and so forth,
that the radiation inside a box
could be thought of
as a collection of harmonic oscillators.
In the same sense
that a vibrating guitar string,
I always mean to bring my guitar in
for this purpose,
but like a vibrating guitar string
can also be thought of
as a system of harmonic oscillators,
not a single harmonic oscillator.
Hey,
that's pretty good.
Not a single harmonic oscillator,
but it can vibrate in any one of its,
ooh.
Yeah,
yeah,
you get the point.
This is the first mode of oscillation,
and that's a harmonic oscillator.
Completely independent of that,
the system can vibrate in its second mode.
Now,
I'm not gonna try to make the,
well,
yeah,
I can do the third mode.
There's a third mode and so forth,
and each one of these oscillations is separate,
and the system is described
by a collection of harmonic oscillations.
Each harmonic oscillation,
and this was not an invention of Einstein
or this goes back to original wave theory,
everything we knew about wave theory,
not everything we knew,
everything they knew about wave theory,
that waves could be described
as collections of oscillators,
and in thermal equilibrium,
each oscillator ought,
according to classical thermodynamics,
have an energy equal to kT.
Okay?
But there's an infinite number
of possible modes of oscillation.
I could only exhibit a handful,
because I'm not clever enough
to make this thing oscillate
in arbitrarily short wavelengths,
but there was no reason to believe
that there was any cutoff
in how short wavelengths could be.
There is a cutoff
on how long wavelengths can be inside a box.
It doesn't make sense to think about a wave
longer in wavelength than the size of it.
Another way of saying it
is if you have a
guitar string of a certain length,
there are not going to be waves
of longer wavelength on that guitar string
than the distance between the endpoints of the string,
but there can be arbitrarily short wavelengths.
Now,
of course,
for a real guitar string,
it has a certain thickness,
and there comes a point
where you can't really make it oscillate
with very,
very short wavelengths.
In particular,
it doesn't make any sense
to think about wavelengths
shorter than the intermolecular spacing along the...
So,
for a guitar string,
there's a natural cutoff.
But for radiation,
nobody knew any reason
why there should be a smallest wavelength.
And if not,
then in thermal equilibrium,
every single wavelength should have the same energy,
kT,
and the damn thing should have
an infinite explosive amount of energy,
simply because there's an infinite number
of possible ways you can oscillate.
Of course,
most of these wavelengths
would be very,
very high frequency,
but nevertheless,
thermal equilibrium
should populate them.
The same way the thermal equil...
thermal equilibrium should have populated
the oscillations of a very stiff molecule,
it should also have populated
the oscillations of a very stiff string,
for example,
of very high frequency oscillations.
So that was the real puzzle.
People knew enough about electromagnetism
that they had confidence in the theory,
and the theory was failing.
It was failing because it was an observed fact
that the radiation inside a box
was not infinite in energy.
In fact,
if you looked at the radiation
that was in the box,
you would discover,
in fact,
that there was a cutoff in its wavelength.
The cutoff,
in other words,
a shortest wavelength
that the box could oscillate at.
So you might have said,
okay,
that just means
that physics has some smallest length.
We didn't expect that,
something new,
something entirely new,
but still,
it can be made to coexist
with basic classical physics
if we were to have said
there was a smallest length.
But it doesn't work that way.
The smallest length wave,
or oscillation,
that's present in the thermal equilibrium
of a box of radiation,
that smallest wavelength,
depends on temperature.
How can the shortest distance in the world
depend on the temperature?
That doesn't make sense.
So when a box of radiation was considered,
and studied,
and,
you know,
how do they do this?
They let a little bit of radiation out
and studied the spectral decomposition of it.
At each temperature,
there was a shortest wavelength,
or approximately a shortest wavelength,
but that shortest wavelength
depended on something
that didn't make sense,
that depended on the temperature itself.
That was the puzzle.
The solution of the puzzle
was simply the quantum mechanics
of these harmonic oscillations.
So I want to go through that
and show you the basic theory
of the harmonic oscillations,
of radiation.
And we'll work out
the Stefan-Boltzmann law,
or one version,
one particular version
of the Stefan-Boltzmann law.
The Stefan-Boltzmann law
applied to the energy density
of radiation,
blackbody radiation.
We're talking about blackbody radiation.
Okay.
Any questions before I begin this,
the derivation of the energy
in blackbody radiation?
Yeah.
It seems like the minimum wavelength
would be cut,
eventually the wavelength
would get to be about the size of an atom,
and that should cut off
the minimum wavelength.
Why should it?
Why?
Because then it's not
perfectly reflecting well,
and it's just a jagged bunch of atoms.
No.
In thermal equilibrium,
everything gets populated.
Everything gets populated
that can get populated.
And there's no reason
why an atom cannot in principle,
or why an atom cannot excite
the modes of oscillation,
of yet shorter wavelength.
It might take a long time.
It might take a long time
to populate.
Atoms of a certain size
aren't readily going to convert.
I'll tell you what can happen.
How can an atom create
a high frequency photon?
Okay.
Well,
one simple way
that it can create
a high frequency photon,
we haven't talked about photons yet,
but let's talk about photons.
One way that it can do it
is to absorb several simultaneously,
several low frequency photons,
and then re-emit the energy
as one high frequency photon.
So it can happen.
It's one of the possible processes
that can happen
that an atom can,
it's a non-linear process.
The frequency of the radiation changes,
but a whole bunch of photons
come together.
You can think of it as accidentally
excite the atom,
and the atom then de-excites
and gives back a very high frequency photon.
Or scatters,
just scatters a lot of low frequency photons
and creates a high frequency photon.
They say that's very improbable,
and you're right.
That means that it would take
a long amount of time
for the system to come
to thermal equilibrium.
And that's true.
That classically,
it would take a long time
for the system to come
to thermal equilibrium.
But when it did come
to thermal equilibrium,
it would have this odd property
of having every mode filled with energy
and an infinite amount of energy.
And that was intolerable.
But let me say it another way.
At low temperatures,
the cutoff in wavelengths
was much longer than the size of an atom.
So it didn't make sense
to just say atomic diameter
cutoff things.
It depended on the temperature.
At low temperatures,
only very long wavelengths were present.
As the temperature went up,
shorter and shorter wavelengths
become important.
And this just didn't jibe
with anything that anybody knew.
It was a real crisis.
Planck had an idea,
and the idea didn't really make a lot of sense.
I will just tell you very briefly.
It's one of these things
that made sufficiently little sense
that I can't even reproduce
what the argument was.
It was Einstein,
of course,
who really got the argument right.
What Planck said is that
the walls of the container
are filled with atoms.
Atoms emit radiation.
And for reasons he didn't know,
but reasons that didn't seem
all that incredibly revolutionary,
the oscillators in the walls
oscillate only with very definite frequencies.
And he said the energy of an oscillator,
he spoke about oscillators
in the walls of the system,
meaning atoms.
But again,
remember,
this was 1900.
Atoms still hadn't been identified
and still were not understood.
So Planck said,
for reasons unknown,
the frequency of oscillations of atoms
Do atoms even oscillate?
Not all atoms oscillate.
I mean,
they do oscillate,
but they don't oscillate
as harmonic oscillators.
But his idea was,
atoms oscillate like harmonic oscillators.
And each harmonic oscillator atom
has a frequency omega.
And he said the energy of the atoms
or the oscillators in the wall
satisfied that the energy
is equal to an integer multiple
of the frequency times a new constant,
which he called,
I don't think he called it Planck's constant,
he called it h,
he called it h bar or h.
H bar came a little bit later.
h nu equals h bar omega.
And through some kind of mumbo jumbo
that I've never completely understood,
this was supposed to explain the fact
that the radiation in the box
was cut off at some highest wavelength.
This is not the right explanation,
although the formula that he concocted
out of this was correct.
The formula he concocted
for the amount of radiation
in each oscillator was correct.
In each oscillation
of the electromagnetic field,
the real truth was that
the quantization of energy levels,
was not the quantization of energy levels
of the atoms in the walls of the box,
it was the quantization of the energy levels
of the radiation itself inside the box.
In other words,
the radiation was made out of
discrete quanta of energy,
where every frequency
of possible oscillation
would have an integer number of quanta,
and the energy of each possible oscillation
would be some integer times h bar
times the frequency of that oscillator.
These,
the thing that I called quanta now,
which just correspond to the amount of energy
in each one of these oscillations,
got to be called photons.
Einstein knew very well
that he was talking about some kind of
particulate theory of radiation,
and he was saying something like,
this is something extremely radical,
extremely,
extraordinarily radical.
In fact,
you know,
when you think about it,
there was this young man
who was completely unknown,
nobody had ever heard of him,
there were all these famous physicists,
and this young man out of nowhere,
out of the patent office in 1905 said,
you know,
everybody who has ever thought
about radiation and electromagnetic radiation
had it completely wrong,
all you people were wrong,
electromagnetic radiation comes
in some sort of particles.
Now,
it was not because he didn't understand
that the wave theory of radiation
was very effective,
he just somehow had an inner sense
that it was the radiation in here
which was quantized
and not the oscillations of the wall.
Nobody believed him,
incidentally,
it took about 20 years before people
really believed there were photons,
even this,
not the,
it was a long time,
but having told you the history,
let's go back to the beginning
and let's go through the mathematics.
This is not what Einstein did.
Einstein didn't have the mathematics
to do this,
he didn't do it
the way I'm doing it,
he did it
using lots of thermodynamics
and lots of clever insight,
but we can do it really mathematically
and very cleanly.
All I want to do is calculate
the total amount of energy
in this box of radiation,
so to do so,
we have to state more clearly
the nature of these oscillators,
not the ones in the walls of the box,
but the oscillations in the radiation field,
which are very much like the oscillations
of a guitar string.
In particular,
if the walls of the box
are reflecting,
that implies
that the electric field at the boundaries
of the box is zero.
Take that as given,
that the electric field
at the boundaries of the box is zero,
and that's analogous to the gamma field
of the guitar string,
where the deviation
of the guitar string from equilibrium
is zero at the boundary of the string.
Electric field can be thought of
as sort of a height of the oscillation here,
and so the guitar string is constrained
to be attached,
to have zero oscillation
at the ends of the guitar string.
Same thing for the electromagnetic field,
for the electric field.
So let's think about an electric wave
propagating along the x-axis here.
This is an idealized box with balls
that are not irregular and things like that.
Yeah,
actually that doesn't make
any difference at all if you're deep inside the box.
There are some surface effects at the boundaries
of the box that...
Wouldn't it mean that there would be
a lot of different frequencies?
I mean,
it'd be like having a whole lot
of different guitar strings.
No,
no,
no.
What is true...
Different locations of the wave.
You're asking,
if you were to expand
the box a little bit,
you would say
the frequencies would be a little bit different,
and if you would shrink it a little bit,
they would be a little different.
If you reflected them a little bit
towards one wall or another or something like that.
Yeah,
yeah.
What you have to do is you have to read...
You don't just add those things together.
You can't add the oscillations of one theory
of the guitar string to the oscillations
of another theory.
For example,
you could have,
instead of fixed
boundary conditions here in the guitar string,
here's another kind of guitar string.
It's not a real guitar string.
You have a pole.
And another pole over here.
Pole,
I mean literally,
like a pole.
And you have a ring around this pole
and a ring around this pole,
and the guitar string is connected to the rings.
The rings can move up and down now.
They're not confined to be attached
to fixed positions.
And this is an entirely different kind of waves.
The waves that now can
exist are such that they don't
have to vanish at the end points.
Something else has to be true.
Namely,
the derivative has to be equal to zero
at that point.
But it's a different,
simply a different system.
This system,
if you worked it out,
would give you exactly the same answer
for the thermodynamics of the guitar string
when the whole system got large.
The end effects are not important.
The end effects turn out not to be important.
That you have to prove.
You have to work that out.
You don't add the oscillations of this theory
to the oscillations of this theory.
They're just two different theories.
Now,
another possibility is you could have friction
at the end of the walls here.
Friction would lead to yet a different description
of what goes on in the guitar string.
But all of them would lead to the same thermodynamic
behavior of the guitar string.
So it's sufficient just to study one particular case.
And far from the end points,
the answers don't depend on the details
of the boundary conditions.
I agree.
That has to be proved.
That's not obvious,
but it's true.
So let's consider the waves that can exist
on a finite string of length L.
If they have to be,
if they have to be,
if they have to vanish,
if the height of this wave,
let's call the height of the wave here,
let's call it x.
No,
let's not call it x.
Let's call it capital Y.
And it's a function of position.
It's a function of x.
And a given wave has to
have the form sine 2 pi.
No,
sine pi.
Pi over Lx times n.
What is n now?
N is the number of,
well,
the number of oscillations,
number of half oscillations,
this would correspond to n equals 1,
this would correspond to n equals 2,
and so forth.
Let me call it m.
I'm going to get,
I don't want to call it n
because I've used n for something else.
I've used n for the
number of quanta in the oscillation.
This has nothing to do with the number of quanta
in the oscillator.
It just has to do
with how many nodes there are
in a particular electromagnetic wave.
It's a completely classical concept.
And it's just the kind of sine waves
that can fit onto an interval of length L.
All of these sine waves,
okay,
let's just look at it.
If x,
if m is equal to 1,
then this just becomes sine pi over Lx,
x,
but what is x?
At the other end,
x starts at 0 over here,
and x is equal to L over here.
At x equals 0,
the sine of 0 is 0,
and at x equals L,
the sine of pi is 0.
So this wave fits into the box
with proper boundary conditions at the end.
Any integer here will work.
So there are an infinite number of patterns
of oscillation characterized by these sine waves.
But the sine waves,
each one of them has an amplitude,
an amplitude of oscillation,
which means the magnitude of the oscillation
of each one of these.
And so you'll have to put
a coefficient in front of it,
y,
let's call it sub m.
And it's just a number for each oscillation,
but it's time dependent.
The oscillator oscillates up and down,
or the,
let's take this case here.
It oscillates up and down,
and that corresponds to y oscillating.
y is an oscillator.
y is a function of time,
and it is an oscillator.
It's a harmonic oscillator.
So these are the oscillators here.
And in general,
you can write that
y of x is a sum over m,
of y sub m,
sine m pi over l,
x.
These are the dynamical degrees of freedom.
Think of this as a function of time.
y is also a function of time.
And these are the things that oscillate.
These are just fixed functions.
So the system is a system of harmonic oscillators.
And the next question is,
what is the frequency of each oscillator?
The answer depends on the velocity of propagation
of the waves.
There's a relationship between m
and the frequency of oscillation.
And I'll tell you what it is.
Let's write this in another way,
another useful way.
Let's write this as y of m
sine kx.
kx.
m pi over l,
I have called k.
That's a standard terminology.
m pi over l is called k.
And k is called the wave number.
It's called the wave number.
It's itself not necessarily an integer.
But if you know m,
then you know k.
What I want to do is,
what's the connection between the frequency and k?
The larger k is,
the shorter the wavelength.
That's large k.
This is low k.
The shorter the wavelength,
the higher the frequency.
I'll tell you what the relationship is.
The frequency is equal to the velocity of propagation,
let's call it c,
times k.
The higher k,
the larger k,
the higher the frequency,
and they're just related by
the velocity of propagation of waves.
For light,
c is of course the speed of light.
All right,
so let's summarize then.
A given wave,
a given wave-like motion,
has,
is parameterized by an m.
It has a frequency which
is equal to c times k,
which is the same as
c times m pi over l.
Each one of these oscillations stores energy,
independently of all the others.
And classically,
each one of them would
store the same amount of energy,
and the whole thing would
have an infinite number of waves.
So,
the whole thing would have an infinite amount of energy.
Now,
what about,
now here I'm talking about one-dimensional waves.
What about three-dimensional waves?
Three-dimensional waves,
you do almost exactly the same thing.
Let's write the general pattern for three-dimensional waves.
We're not now talking about the height of a string.
We could be talking about a wave field,
such as the electric or
magnetic field in a light wave.
But let's just,
let's not call it electric.
Well,
we can call it electric field.
No,
let's just call it F.
It could be electric field,
it could be magnetic field,
or it could be some other wave field,
gravitational,
well,
no,
let's not,
let's not get into quantum gravity today.
The electric or magnetic field.
And it is also a sum over different independent oscillators.
Now the wave pattern involves all three dimensions.
And the general wave that can propagate in a box
in three dimensions with boundary conditions on the walls
that it should be zero looks similar to this,
except it has three factors.
It has sine,
or we can write it in several ways,
m sub x,
let's see,
pi over l times x,
that's a product,
times sine m sub x,
times sub y,
pi over l times y,
times sine of m sub z,
pi over l times z.
These are the three domain directions of space.
And mx,
my,
and mz are integers.
Three integers.
A given wave has to fit into the box horizontally,
it has to fit into the box vertically,
and it has to fit into
the box in the other direction.
And that's ensured by this form here.
And then there's a coefficient which depends on time,
which can be labeled y of,
or y sub m,
meaning y of mx,
my,
and mz.
We can also write this,
oh,
and this is a sum,
of course.
We sum over all possible modes in the box.
All right.
And of course,
this is nothing but Fourier analysis in a box.
There's nothing special here.
We can also write this as a sum of y,
and use a different notation,
sine kx times x,
sine ky times y,
sine kz times z,
where the relationship between the k's and the m's
is exactly as it was before.
k sub x is equal to m sub x pi,
k sub y is equal to m,
over l,
and so forth.
All right.
This is the pattern of
oscillation of a general electromagnetic wave
inside a cavity.
With y being the thing that oscillates.
The point is that there is one harmonic oscillator
for each way of choosing mx,
my,
and mz,
and we have to add together all of their energies.
Once we know how to label the oscillators,
and we know how many of them there are,
then this is the way of keeping track
of how many different oscillators there are.
One more thing we need to know.
We need to know the frequency of an oscillator,
and the frequency of an oscillator,
namely the oscillator that has wave number kx,
ky,
and kz,
is just equal to k,
the magnitude of k,
square root of kx squared
plus ky squared plus kz squared,
times c,
equals the square root,
kx squared plus ky squared,
plus kz squared,
times c.
Just the magnitude of the wave vector,
magnitude of the wave number,
times the speed of light.
That's its frequency.
So now we have laid out for us
all of the harmonic oscillators.
We've labeled them,
labeled them by three integers.
We know the frequency of each one.
We could write it in terms
of the m's if we like.
And we can ask how much energy is there.
How much energy is stored in this whole thing?
Classically,
it's quite infinite.
It's quite infinite because each oscillator
has the same amount of energy.
Quantum mechanically,
the answer is different.
Let's sum it all up.
Let's do it.
Let's really get into it,
get into the thing,
and calculate how much energy is in this
oscillating box of radiation
at a temperature T.
The temperature T,
where does that come from?
Well,
the box of radiation,
the box of photons,
or box of radiation,
could be sitting on somebody's stove.
That's all.
It's just heated up by whatever means
it's heated up by.
The walls of the box become hot.
They emit radiation.
They absorb radiation.
The radiation comes into thermal equilibrium
with the walls of the box,
which have been heated to some temperature.
How?
By emission and absorption of radiation,
which,
of course,
is emission and absorption
of the quanta of the oscillators here,
photons.
Okay,
that's our theory,
and let's see if we can work it out now.
The energy,
let's write down the energy
stored in the wave
which is characterized by a given
wave number k.
Wave number means a set of three wave numbers,
kx,
ky,
and kz,
or mx,
my,
and mz.
All right,
that's equal to,
now we go back to the theory of harmonic oscillators.
It is omega h-bar
divided by e to the beta omega h-bar minus one.
That was the formula for the harmonic oscillator energy
as a function of frequency
and as a function of temperature.
That's the energy of the harmonic oscillator
of a given oscillator,
and we can write that in another way.
Our omega
is k,
the magnitude of k,
times the speed of light,
h-bar,
divided by e to the beta kc,
let's see,
yeah,
h-bar.
In this formula here,
k is the same thing as
the magnitude of k.
I don't want to try to stick too many symbols
into this exponent,
minus one,
excuse me.
I've just rewritten the fact that omega
is equal to kc h-bar,
but nothing else.
That's the energy of the oscillator
with wave number k.
So,
what kind of energy is there altogether?
We've got to add up all the oscillators.
So,
the total energy
is equal to the sum
over all of the possible modes of oscillation.
That means sum of mx,
my,
and mz,
kc h-bar,
divided by e to the beta kc h-bar minus one.
It's a big sum.
Any questions up till now?
All right.
To carry on,
we're going to approximate the sum
by an integral.
The point is that,
let's look at this here.
k is m pi over l.
Imagine the box is very big.
l is large.
Large now means large by comparison
with the wavelengths of light in there.
If l is large,
the difference between neighboring values of k is small.
Neighboring values of k mean neighboring values
of the wave number m.
All right.
What's the difference between
neighboring adjacent values of kx?
Let's call it delta kx.
The difference is just pi over l.
In other words,
if we change m by one unit,
k changes by pi over l.
When l is large,
this change in k is small.
So if we think of this as a sum,
not over m,
but as a sum over the values of k,
then we're summing up a large number of numbers,
each of which is a function of k,
and the k's are very,
very closely separated,
very,
very dense.
Here's a function of k.
It's got k in the numerator,
and it's got this stuff in the denominator,
and we're adding it all up.
And it's just the ideal situation
when l gets large to
replace a sum by an integral.
So let's do that.
We're going to replace this by an integral over k.
But before we do,
we have to remember that integrals and sums
are related in a particular way
that involves a factor that
we have to keep track of.
Just abstractly,
a sum over integers mx,
my,
and mz
is going to be replaced by an integral
over k.
So we're going to have dkx,
dky,
dkz.
At the moment,
I haven't told you what I'm summing,
but of course what I'm
going to be summing is this.
But just the abstract idea of a sum
is going to be replaced by
the abstract idea of an integral.
But an integral does mean a sum.
That's what this wiggly s means.
And this dkx,
dky,
dkz
is just the volume in k-space
of the little cells
that you're summing over.
Well,
each cell has a size
delta kx equals pi over l,
delta ky equals pi over l,
and delta kz equals pi over l.
A simple way to think about it
is dkx,
dky,
dkz.
Integral is replaced by sum.
The volume element,
dkx,
dky,
dkz,
is replaced by delta kx,
delta ky,
delta kz.
And so we should really write
that this is equal to delta,
let's call it delta 3k,
which means the product
of delta kx,
delta ky,
and delta kz.
That's the way to replace sums by integrals.
You can either approximate an integral by a sum
or approximate a sum by an integral,
but you gotta keep track of this factor.
Now,
what we have here is just a sum.
If we wanna convert it to an integral,
we have to divide
by 1 over delta k cubed.
That's the right prescription,
the right mathematical prescription
to go from sums to integrals.
And so we can write
that this is approximately equal to
the integral dkx,
dky,
let's just call it d3k,
times the same integrand,
kch bar divided by e to the beta,
kch bar minus 1,
but we have to put
in 1 over delta k cubed.
What is that?
That's l cubed over pi cubed.
l cubed.
That's interesting.
That's the volume of the box.
Not too surprising.
We would expect that energy being extensive
or energy being typically proportional to,
I was gonna say,
we would expect that energy is proportional to volume
at a given temperature.
At a given temperature,
here in this calculation
is where the volume comes from.
Happens to be volume over pi cubed,
that number is there.
So the first familiar fact
is that the total energy in that box
is proportional to the volume,
and the rest of the integral
is just the energy density.
Does it,
first of all,
does it converge?
Is it finite?
Yeah,
it's finite.
The denominator goes to 0,
or the denominator gets to 0,
and it gets big when k gets large.
What are we worried about?
We're worried about the very short wavelength oscillations,
and that means very large k.
When k gets large,
the denominator here gets big exponentially fast,
and this integral is very convergent.
So the first,
second observation
is that the total energy in the box is finite.
It's extremely well cut off
by this exponent,
and there is not an infinite number.
There is a finite amount of energy.
But let's see if we can calculate it.
Let's see,
so what do we have?
Let's calculate it and find the final law
of black body radiation
for its energy density in any case.
All right.
L cubed,
the energy is equal to
L cubed over pi cubed
integral decay,
and we're going to write the integral now.
I'm going to replace,
I'm going to change the integration variable.
We have e to the beta k c h bar.
That's a monstrosity,
but we can change variables.
We're integrating over k,
incidentally.
All right,
we're integrating over the three directions,
the three components of k,
and the k that stands down here
is the magnitude of the wave vector.
Okay?
But if I make the change of variables,
and let me now change variables,
from k,
namely beta k c h bar,
beta,
c,
and h bar are just constants.
Let me call that u.
And of course,
there are three components.
There's kx,
this will give ux,
and same thing for y,
and same thing for z.
We're changing variables from k to u.
And when I do so,
I just have to be
careful and keep track of it.
So let's work it out.
We have l cubed over pi cubed.
What happens to the integral d cubed k?
For that,
we can solve for k.
k is equal to u
divided by beta c h bar,
right?
So what is dk?
du over beta c h bar.
So that means there's going
to be a d cubed u,
the three components of u,
and there's going to be
downstairs beta c h bar cubed.
That can come outside the integral.
We'll take it outside the integral in a moment.
Then we have omega,
or we have k c h bar.
What is that?
u over beta.
The magnitude of u.
So we have omega squared over u over beta.
And we then have 1 divided
by e to the u minus 1.
That's it.
That's the thing that we have.
Let's take all the constants
and take them on the outside.
Now that we've found the answer or written the answer,
let's put all the constants on the outside
by constants,
I mean the things independent of u.
What do we have?
We have equals l cubed over pi cubed.
And then there is c cubed
h bar cubed in the denominator
and beta to the fourth.
Beta to the fourth power downstairs.
A beta from here and three betas from here.
And then an integral,
d cubed u,
u,
I'll just write u meaning the magnitude of u,
divided by e to the u minus 1.
This is an integral.
It's a definite integral.
They're going over positive values
of the three components of u.
Only positive values.
Why?
Because the original things that we started with,
which were,
where are they?
Well,
the m's.
The m's were positive integers.
So u is positive and the
integral is from 0 to infinity
for all three integrals.
That's it.
This is a number.
I'm going to tell you in
a little while what this number is.
This number is a famous integral.
And we'll,
I'll tell you what the number is.
Anybody know what the number is?
It's pi to the fourth over 15.
No,
not quite.
Not that,
it's not.
It's 4 pi times pi pi to the fourth.
4 pi to the fifth over 15.
Some such number.
Some silly number.
It's a definite integral.
You'll find it in tables.
It's a three dimensional integral.
How do you make a
one dimensional integral out of this?
Well,
you can't.
You can't.
Yes,
you can.
Spherical coordinates.
Integral 0 to infinity.
OK.
Go ahead.
Tell me what to do next.
4 pi,
right?
4 pi.
4 pi u squared,
that gives you u cubed all together.
e to the u minus 1.
So there's a factor of 4 pi out here.
Let's put the 4 pi.
And it becomes this integral.
But that's not quite right.
You know why it's not right?
Because this integral would be integrating,
you went to spherical coordinates.
In three dimensions,
there are eight octants.
Eight octants that this integral is integrated over.
But we only want the octant
where all components of u are positive.
So there's a factor of 1 eighth.
Not important.
I mean,
there is a factor of 1 eighth because we've overcounted.
But that's it.
That's the number.
So let's put the 4 pi outside.
There's an 8 downstairs.
And then there is this integral of u cubed.
Over e to the u minus 1.
Famous integral.
Can be written in terms of Riemann zeta
functions and gamma functions and this and that.
But it actually has a numerical value.
And it's equal to pi to the fourth over 15.
Pi to the fourth over 15.
Almost the final answer.
L cubed 4 pi.
Pi to the fourth over 15.
My god.
All these other things.
8 pi cubed.
C cubed.
H bar cubed.
And finally,
1 over beta to the fourth.
That's the interesting piece here.
Why?
1 over beta to the fourth.
Why is 1 over beta to the fourth interesting?
Because this is t to the fourth.
Yeah.
Stefan Boltzmann.
t to the fourth.
t to the fourth power.
Times some number.
Oh,
sorry.
t to the fourth times l cubed.
Volume times t to the fourth.
It's telling you,
first of all,
that the energy density in thermal radiation is proportional
to t to the fourth.
The total amount of energy is finite.
The energy density is finite.
And this coefficient here is apart from
a numerical factor like a quarter or something.
It's called the Stefan Boltzmann factor.
The Stefan Boltzmann number constant.
Let's see.
I want to write it down correctly.
Oh,
anybody know what's missing?
There's a factor of 2 missing.
Anybody know where the factor of 2 missing is?
Two polarization states of the photon.
Yeah.
Each wave vector.
Each wave vector can
support two distinct orthostatic states.
So it's a way of calculating
the number of orthogonal kinds of oscillations.
A wave vector going in
a given direction can oscillate vertically.
The electric field can oscillate vertically.
It can oscillate horizontally.
Or anywhere in between.
But in between can be made up
out of the horizontal and the vertical polarizations.
So in fact,
there's another factor of 2.
Could that be 2 cubed?
No.
It's just 2.
Two polarization states.
That's it.
Not 2 cubed.
OK.
For each direction,
there's two possible polarization states.
All right.
All of this is called,
well,
it's not quite the standard Stefan Boltzmann constant.
But it's related to it by some
numerical factor and a factor of c.
Let's see if I have the precise formula here.
Yeah.
Here's the final formula.
But the whole story is a long story,
and a complicated story.
But it's really just adding up the quantum mechanical energy
in each harmonic oscillator,
each mode of vibration.
And the important thing is this exponential downstairs,
which really kills off the
energy in the high frequency oscillators.
Yeah.
May I ask how far a
plane got along with the .
No,
no.
Well.
I don't read German,
so I've never tried to read it.
Did you get to the t to the fourth?
Yeah.
Oh,
yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah,
certainly.
Yeah.
Oh,
we got the whole formula.
But through what logic is a little bit unclear.
Quite unclear to me.
Here's the final formula.
E equals volume t to the fourth.
And I have pi squared over
15 c cubed h bar cubed,
which I believe is also equal to the volume
times t to the fourth times 4 over c times
the thing which is called the Stefan Boltzmann constant.
The Stefan Boltzmann constant.
The Stefan Boltzmann constant is,
of course,
just c over 4 times this.
So this is the constant that appears there.
Number one,
it agrees with experiment.
But that was simply Planck's choice of Planck's constant.
So there was no great triumph in
the numerical value fitting the Stefan Boltzmann constant.
But there was something else that we've forgot,
that sort of passed by us.
Where is the cutoff in frequencies
that rescues the energy from being infinite?
And the answer is,
if you go back to the
energy stored in these harmonic oscillators,
you go from classical to quantum mechanical.
In other words,
the suppression,
the suppression happens at a frequency
which is related to the temperature.
When h bar omega,
that's the energy stored in a single quantum,
is about equal to the classical
energy that would be in that oscillator.
All right,
we can put in Boltzmann's constant if we want,
the different k,
k Boltzmann,
but I'm going to leave it out.
When h bar omega is about equal to the temperature,
or when the temperature gets up to a certain temperature,
to a magnitude h omega,
that's when that oscillator starts to begin to oscillate.
When the temperature becomes high enough,
that oscillator begins to oscillate.
Another way of saying it is the cutoff,
the cutoff in frequencies is omega
equals the temperature over h bar.
Frequencies higher than this,
the energy in a single quantum
is too high to be excited.
So omega is equal to t over h bar,
and remember what omega is,
omega is k times c,
and so the wave number cutoff,
let's call it cutoff,
cutoff is at t over h bar divided by c,
or is it times c,
let's see,
k omega is that,
omega is k times c over c.
So we see another feature that yes,
it is as if the short wavelengths were cutoff,
but not by a cutoff
which is independent of the temperature,
the cutoff,
this corresponds to a wavelength,
one over a wavelength of
order t over h bar c.
When the wavelength is shorter than this,
those oscillators can't oscillate,
they have too much energy in a single quantum
to be able to oscillate,
and so we see here
that the cutoff is temperature dependent,
exactly,
and what's more,
exactly equal to what the
experimental cutoff on frequencies was.
So this was a great success.
In a sense,
this was the great success
that the shape of the spectrum was cutoff,
the classical spectrum was cutoff at wave numbers
equal to t over h bar c to x,
did I have that right?
Yeah,
I do.
T over h bar c.
Okay.
Does that mean if there
was an oscillation at high frequencies
then Planck's uncertainty principle would be violated
because you would know too much about the position
and the momentum?
Well,
I would just say the energy of a single quantum
is way above the classical energy.
So the classical energy corresponds to
a small fraction of a quantum,
but you can't split quanta.
I think that's the right way to say it.
So is there a problem with zero-point energy?
Hm?
Is there a problem with zero-point energy?
Zero-point energy is a constant,
of course.
It's there whether the temperature is zero
or the temperature is anything else.
Right.
So there is an infinity in the zero-point energy,
but it's just a constant,
and so it doesn't affect...
Adding a constant to...
Look,
this is a problem that has
plagued physics for a long time.
The zero-point quantum mechanical energy is not zero.
What does zero-point energy come into,
since it's only an additive constant?
Well,
it comes into gravitation.
Energy is the source of the gravitational field.
So the question is,
why isn't the vacuum,
empty space,
gravitating?
And we won't get into that now.
But short of that,
it really has no implication.
It's just an additive constant
in the energy of the world
that doesn't have any effect on energy differences,
if you like.
So that's not to say that it's not important.
I mean,
it...
It may be important,
and it's important to understand why it doesn't gravitate,
but that's a mystery.
It's important to understand why it's not important.
Yeah,
it's important.
Right.
And this has been argued about...
I think there was an argument between Dirac and Pauli.
Pauli said,
What about this vacuum energy?
And Dirac said,
It's infinite,
so it can't be there.
And Pauli said,
Just because it's infinite,
that doesn't mean it's zero,
and so forth and so on.
And...
But...
But as far as energy differences goes,
this is it.
And that's good enough.
All right.
Let's...
Yeah.
The experimentalists have been measuring this.
It seems like a very difficult experiment,
because you have to control
the temperature of the gas hole
to...
Maybe a few degrees,
and you're working at several thousand degrees.
So,
do you really think that the...
I can't imagine the experimental data being better than...
I don't think the...
...five or ten percent.
Better than what?
I can't imagine the experimental data
being better than five or ten percent.
You mean at that time?
Yeah,
especially at that time.
Probably wasn't better than five or ten percent.
I don't know.
These days...
These days,
you can do these things highly accurately,
with great accuracy.
Yeah.
Another question.
This is all derived by,
you know,
having a volume for radiation.
It turns out that lump coal also has its distribution.
Can you explain why?
I mean,
a lump of coal is pretty
far from a box with reflecting size
and a little hole in it.
Why does a lump of coal have such a distribution?
Thermal equilibrium is done
by a thermal equilibrium.
If you...
Yeah,
no.
First of all,
we haven't talked about emission of radiation.
We've just talked about the energy density inside a box.
But you're right.
A lump of coal,
of course,
is just an object which
absorbs and doesn't reflect much energy.
Okay.
So if you take the box
of radiation as we've defined it,
and we put a lump of coal into it,
that lump of coal will absorb and emit radiation.
It will absorb and emit radiation
in such a way as to come to equilibrium.
It'll eventually come to equilibrium
with the thermal radiation there,
and that means it will be
emitting as much as it's absorbing.
So it's emitting as much
as it's absorbing at each wavelength.
At each wavelength,
otherwise it would get out of equilibrium.
So it's emitting and absorbing at each wavelength,
and each wavelength is being kept in equilibrium.
And now all you have to
do is suddenly remove the box,
remove the reflecting walls,
and the lump of coal is emitting,
but it's not absorbing because nothing's coming back.
It's emitting exactly the way it was emitting before,
but it's no longer absorbing.
And the emission should be such
that it's not absorbing.
If there were the walls there,
it would be the right amount of emission
to balance and keep the system in equilibrium.
But we haven't talked about
emission of radiation from this box.
We can.
That's another subject.
What is the connection?
This was not the emission of radiation.
This was the energy density in the radiation.
Now you can ask,
what does this have to do
with the original Stefan-Boltzmann law?
The original Stefan-Boltzmann law
was about the luminosity,
a different luminosity.
And what it has to do with it,
if you take the box,
let's see how to think about this.
Well,
just take the surface of a hot region.
The region could be the box,
or it could be the box
with a little pinhole in it.
Radiation is bouncing off the walls.
It has a certain energy density.
And it doesn't bounce off the opening here.
It just goes out.
It goes out with the speed of light.
Well,
let's come back to the luminosity later.
I hadn't planned to talk about it.
We'll talk about it next time.
What I did want to talk about was the pressure.
In thermal radiation.
The pressure is something we can calculate
by straight thermodynamics and statistical mechanics.
The statistical mechanics we've already done.
The luminosity is a little bit beyond
what the thermodynamics can do,
for the simple reason that the luminosity
is an out-of-equilibrium thing.
It's radiating because it's out of equilibrium
with its environment.
So let's not do that now.
Let's come to the pressure,
which we can calculate by formulas
that we've already learned.
Just as an example,
just as an example of the thermodynamic relations
and the statistical mechanical relations,
let's see if we can find the pressure.
To find the pressure,
let me remind you,
the pressure is equal to minus the derivative
of the free energy,
the Helmholtz free energy,
with respect to volume at 50.
That's the fixed temperature.
So we have to calculate the Helmholtz free energy.
The Helmholtz free energy,
A,
is equal to minus the temperature
times the logarithm
of the partition function.
So we have to calculate the partition function.
Now one way to calculate the partition function,
or its logarithm,
is to go back to the original oscillators
and,
you know,
go all the ways back
to the starting point and calculate z.
But there's an easier way.
We've already done most of the work.
And the easier way is to use the fact
that the energy,
the energy
is equal to minus the derivative of log z
with respect to beta.
You remember that?
That was the energy gotten from the partition function.
You calculate the log.
You take the minus of it.
And you differentiate it with respect to beta.
And that gives you the energy.
Well,
we know the energy.
We know the energy in terms of the temperature.
Where is it?
It's 4 over c sigma times vt to the fourth.
4 over sigma,
that doesn't matter.
Not important.
Over c,
I think.
Temperature to the fourth,
which is 1 over beta to the fourth,
equals minus d log z by d beta.
That's just an ordinary derivative,
incidentally.
I write partial derivative,
but it's just a derivative.
How do I calculate z?
Integrate.
If we know the derivative,
the log z by d beta is equal to this,
then z,
let's put the minus sign here,
z is equal to the integral d beta.
Yeah,
log z.
Sorry,
Log z is the integral d
beta of minus 4 sigma over c,
1 over beta to the fourth.
Well,
we can do that integral.
It's just a simple integral,
d beta over beta to the fourth,
and it's just given by minus 4 sigma over c.
What's the integral of 1 over beta to the fourth?
1 third beta to the minus 3?
Yeah.
1 over beta cubed with a
1 over beta to the fourth.
Okay.
How many times were we able to do it?
A thing about the age males.
respect to volume is the pressure at fixed temperature.
So all we have to do
now is differentiate this with respect to volume.
That's pretty easy.
The volume
is just in the numerator here.
And what do we find?
We find that the pressure has
the same numerical coefficient as the energy density,
4 sigma over C,
but then
an extra factor of 1 third,
well it's t to the fourth,
but then an extra factor of 1 third.
Now 1 third came from doing the integral,
the beta over beta to the fourth.
What's
the result?
The result is a relationship between
the pressure and the energy density.
There's a famous relationship,
the pressure is equal to 1 third the energy density,
E
over volume.
You remember seeing that anywhere before?
In cosmology.
When we studied the radiation
dominated universe,
we used pressure is equal
to 1 third the energy density.
So this is
a famous relationship between pressure of
a radi- it's not a general relationship,
it's
a relationship for radiation.
For radiation,
the pressure is 1 third the energy density.
So,
I'm going to show you a little bit
of a picture of the radiation dominated universe.
As I said,
famous rule of- and so that tells
you what the force on a wall,
on the walls
of a box is.
Okay,
let's see,
should we stop here and get questions?
That went faster than I thought
it would,
which may mean that I went too fast,
in which case we can collect some questions
now.
Yeah.
Just a comment,
this is about the third or fourth time that,
you know,
the first time
was when you looked at a molecule
rotating and where you- the same problem
rose its head that things broke down
either very low temperatures or high temperatures
classically and you had to go to the
mechanical kind of things to make it work out.
Right.
Is this replicated all throughout the framework?
Yeah,
I mean,
yeah,
I'll give you another example.
The specific heat of solids.
The specific heat means the relation between energy and
temperature and so it does have
to do with the energy of solids.
What are solids?
Solids
are crystals.
I mean,
real solids,
good solids are crystals.
I mean,
you're going to have
two larger particles and they vibrate,
they oscillate.
The crystal lattice oscillates.
So another example of this is
the energy stored in a crystal lattice.
Again,
classical mechanics
of the lattice overestimates the energy because
it attributes a significant energy to every
possible oscillation of this crystal lattice.
Okay.
Most of the oscillations,
or many of the oscillations,
are too high frequency.
So at low temperatures,
classical mechanics overestimates the
amount of energy stored
in the thermal oscillations or crystal lattice.
And you get the wrong
answer for the specific heat of...
So yeah,
it does recur over and over again.
I'm not sure how many
other examples of it there are.
What else is there besides molecules,
solids?
I suppose it also happens in liquids,
although I never thought very much about it.
Radiation,
molecules,
what else can you think of that oscillates?
Just to blame the idea of gas,
I mean,
after both the indistinguishability of particles.
Well,
we're thinking about...
We're thinking specifically about this issue
of energy stored in high frequency oscillations.
Offhand I can't think of any other,
but I'm sure there are.
Yeah?
When a solid like that melts,
it's not a much pressure-volume change,
you're adding energy.
Does that mean entropy goes
up a lot during that phase?
Yeah.
The entropy does go up a lot,
because all of a sudden
the molecules are no longer locked
in place,
and they're sort of moving randomly through the...
Right,
certainly the entropy does go up.
There's another interesting thing you can calculate.
The entropy...
Well,
you can calculate two interesting things.
We calculated the energy.
We could calculate the number of photons.
Let's think about the number of photons.
Let's go back to the harmonic oscillator.
What did we find?
We found that the energy of
a single harmonic oscillator was h-bar omega,
I think,
divided
by e to the beta h-bar omega minus one.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
That's the energy.
Okay.
Now,
each oscillator...
Each oscillator has a number of photons.
Each quantum of the oscillator has
an energy equal to h-bar omega,
right?
h-bar omega is the energy of each quantum of oscillation.
Let's use the term that we now use.
H-bar omega is the energy of each
photon in an oscillation of the electromagnetic field.
So,
this is the energy.
If I divide it by h-bar omega,
it will give me the number of quanta.
So,
let's divide it by h-bar omega.
The number of photons in each mode of oscillation,
let's call it n omega,
is e to the beta h-bar
omega,
minus one.
Okay?
Now,
you can take all of the modes of
oscillation and add up all of the photons.
It's a similar integral.
The only difference is that it's not a single photon.
The only difference is that it doesn't have the h-bar,
you know,
the numerator here.
Almost the identical integral,
a little bit different,
you can calculate the number of photons.
That's not so hard to do.
And you can calculate the entropy.
How do we calculate the entropy?
We use the statistical mechanics that we've...
Well,
we've calculated the free energy.
Let's see.
Anybody remember the formula for relating energy,
entropy,
and free energy?
It's E minus T-S,
E minus minus.
E minus T-S is?
E minus T-S.
A is E minus T-S,
right?
A is equal to E minus T-S.
So,
S is equal to A minus E,
no,
E minus A,
divided by T.
Well,
we've calculated the energy.
We calculated the energy,
we calculated the free energy.
They were proportional to each other
except for a factor of one-third,
right?
That's what went on here.
The energy and the free energy
differed by a factor of two-thirds.
So the energy minus the free energy
is going to be basically two-thirds of something.
It's...
what's it going to be?
Two-thirds of the energy.
And the energy is proportional to
T to the fourth times sigma.
Times the Stefan-Boltzmann constant.
So T to the fourth times
sigma is the numerator divided by T.
So T cubed times the Stefan-Boltzmann constant or
something like that is the number of photons.
Sorry,
is the entropy.
If you work it out,
you'll find out that it's essentially
equal to the number of photons.
The total number of photons.
The total number of photons,
a numerical constant distinguishes them.
This number here,
if you work it out,
is basically the same as the integral.
Let's just look at it for a moment.
Supposing I wanted to count the total number of photons.
Here's the number of photons at a given frequency.
It would be integral,
the same integral that we did before.
Exactly the same integral we did before.
What was it?
DKKH bar,
what?
Omega?
No,
omega KH bar C.
E to the KH bar C minus one.
That was the integral that we
did before to calculate the energy.
D3K.
Right?
Okay.
We did that integral,
but now we have a different integral.
It differs by not having omega in the numerator.
It's exactly the same integral,
except this factor is no longer
there when calculating the number of photons.
The result is going to be,
incidentally,
do you know where the one
over beta to the fourth came from?
It came from changing variables.
It came from the four
powers of K in the numerator.
When we changed variables,
we said that U is equal to,
there's a beta here,
beta H bar C times K.
So in the change of variables between K and U,
there are four powers of K in the numerator.
D3K times K.
That gave us a one over beta to the fourth.
In the integral without this,
we're just going to get one over beta cubed.
Which is temperature cubed.
So,
the number of photons will be proportional to the entropy.
That's a nice thing.
What it says is that the total entropy at any
temperature is essentially the same as the total number of photons.
One bit of information,
if you like,
for each photon.
It's not one,
it's some numerical number.
But the entropy and the number of
photons are linearly proportional to each other.
So,
entropy in thermal equilibrium counts the
number of photons in the radiation.
You can work that out.
It's a nice integral to do.
You work out the integral associated with the
number of photons and compare it with the entropy.
And that will give you the entropy per photon,
if you like.
The entropy per photon in the thermal equilibrium.
And that's the entropy per photon in the thermal radiation.
And,
you know,
it's not temperature dependent.
It's just some number which I don't remember.
It's got pi's in it and other things.
Yeah,
I think it's a nasty integral.
You can't do the integral.
But you can express it
in terms of Riemann zeta functions.
But it's a number.
Okay.
Yes.
If you had a gas of electrons with one...
One electron equal to one bit of...
No.
Not in terms of...
Only at very high temperatures would that be true.
Take the case of low temperatures.
At very,
very low temperatures,
the electron gas freezes into a...
Not into a solid.
It freezes into a...
Well,
it freezes into a ground state.
Some ground state where every electron occupies its own...
Its own special state because
of the Pauli exclusion principle.
And it has zero entropy.
So,
no,
it is not true that...
That entropy is equal to the number of electrons.
No,
it's rather special to this system.
Because this zero state is...
The zero energy is not zero in this system,
is that it?
Say it again?
Because the zero energy isn't zero in this system.
Zero energy isn't zero.
Ground state.
That's not the reason.
As you remove heat from a box of radiation,
you decrease the number of photons.
Photons are not conserved.
And cooling the box of gas
just eliminates the number of photons.
It eliminates,
removes photons from it.
So as you cool it down towards its ground state,
and eventually when you get down to very,
very low temperatures,
there are no photons left.
So the number of photons and the entropy
both go to zero in the ground state.
For a system of electrons,
electrons are conserved.
You start taking out the energy from them,
the electrons don't go away.
So if you cool a system
of electrons down to zero temperature,
there's a lot of electrons but no entropy.
So the entropy can't be
equal to the number of electrons.
But photons are not conserved,
and as you cool it,
the photons are just eliminated.
They're absorbed into the walls.
Okay.
Any other questions?
If not,
we'll go home a little bit early.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.