Stanford University.
The last time,
as I remember,
and I have a poor memory,
so correct me if I'm wrong,
we talked about magnets
and we talk about phase transitions
and mean field approximation,
and I showed you how the phase transition
between a magnetized,
well,
how the phase transition happens
to a magnetic system,
a simple magnetic system,
a magnetic system being the system
on a lattice where every spin
is coupled to its nearest neighbor
by a term in the
energy which seeks to align them.
In other words,
the energy is lowest
when the neighboring spins
are aligned.
The ground state of that,
the lowest energy state,
and which describes zero temperature,
is all spins perfectly aligned.
As you begin to heat it up a little bit,
the spins begin to jiggle a little bit,
but any spin still has
a bunch of neighbors around it,
and particularly if the dimension
of the system is very high,
and actually,
for our purposes,
three dimensions is pretty high,
then the number of bonds connecting
that spin to its neighbor,
neighbors are also high,
and so I showed you how to use
the mean field approximation
to calculate mean field approximation
simply means postulate an average
for all the spins,
and in particular,
in this case,
it means all the spins neighboring
to our target spin,
to the spin that we are going to focus on.
And just imagine
that they are frozen at their average value.
These spins are frozen at their
average value.
That gives you an expression
for the energy of the one
spin that is left over,
the one at the center.
And in a sense,
the other spins
surrounding it give it a bias to
point in the same direction as the average
spin of the others.
The higher the dimensionality,
the more neighboring
spins there are,
the better the approximation of saying you can average
over them.
But that's the basic idea of the mean field approximation.
And then
let me remind you what you do.
You calculate in the background of the other
spins,
you calculate the partitioning
function for the one extra spin.
You then calculate the average magnetization
of the extra spin.
In other words,
you calculate the average value of sigma of
the extra spin there.
What was it equal to?
Anybody remember the formula for it?
I
don't remember the formula for it.
I just want to go back and...
Minus the average energy over 2...2 sd?
No,
no,
but there was a formula with a tangent,
a hyperbolic tangent...
Yeah,
hyperbolic tangent 2 beta sd.
Hyperbolic tangent of...
2 beta sd.
d is the dimensionality of space,
and it simply represents
the number of nearest neighbors to this fellow over here.
All right.
Beta is the inverse temperature.
Where did the 2 come from?
Oh,
I remember
where the 2 came from.
2 times d.
Hmm?
Yeah,
because the number of nearest
neighbors is twice the dimensionality.
And s was the average spin at the...the
average spin of the entire ensemble of spins.
And then the consistency requires...
that this be the same as s.
In other words,
this spin is no different than all the others.
I said that all the
others have an average spin s,
and we get a consistency equation.
s is equal to tanh 2 beta s times d.
And if we can solve that equation,
then we will determine what the average magnetization is
as a function of the other variables in the problem.
Beta,
d,
and so forth.
All right.
So let me just remind you what that looked like.
We plot s.
s is just a linear function.
s of what?
s of s.
All right.
We plot s of s.
s of s is just a straight line.
s equals s.
And then we superimpose on that the graph
of tanh.
tanh 2 beta s d.
And that looks something like this.
Let's see.
If the temperature is high...
When the temperature is high,
that means that beta is small.
Then the tanh function looks like this.
It's very flat.
It asymptotes to 1.
It's linear at the origin here.
But the slope is less than the
slope of this straight line over here.
And so there's no intersection.
There's no intersection of this blue curve
with a black curve other than the origin.
And that means the only solution to
this problem is that s equals 0.
Now we start decreasing the temperature.
That means increasing beta.
And we discover that this curve moves in.
And eventually its slope at the
origin will become equal to 1.
When you go beyond that,
the curve will look like this.
And you have two new solutions.
These two solutions are in fact the stable solutions.
It's possible to prove that this
solution over here really is unstable.
That if you try to make the
magnet behave as this solution tells you,
any tiny little perturbation will...
In other words,
over here,
what does it say?
It says that the magnetization is 0.
How do you make the magnetization equal to
0 if it doesn't want to be 0,
if it wants to all line up?
Well,
you say...
You simply take the two possibilities all lined up
one way plus all lined up the other way.
In other words,
you make a probability of half that
they're all lined up in one way,
probability of half that they're all
lined up in the other way.
And sure enough,
there will be a solution
which will correspond to no magnetization.
But that's a highly unstable situation.
Any small stray,
very,
very tiny magnetic field pointing either up or down
will tend to flip the magnets to the preferred...
in the preferred direction.
And you will either get this or this,
depending on which way the...
Well,
two possibilities.
You'll either get this or this,
depending on the direction of
that extremely weak magnetic field.
Now,
I have not included that very
weak magnetic field in the calculation.
We could,
but that's just a nuisance.
We simply know that...
We know that if we have a lot
of spins and they all want to line up
and they're reinforcing each other,
binding each other to be in the same direction,
that at low temperatures they will tend to line up,
and either they will line up positively or negatively.
S will either be positive or negative,
depending on nothing more than the value of,
let's say,
an infinitesimally small background field,
which is of such insignificance that we
don't even need to worry about it.
So,
we can just say that the magnet is in the same
direction as the magnet is in the dynamics of the magnet.
There's a critical point.
The critical point...
The critical temperature is the
temperature of the beta over here,
which makes the blue curve have
the same slope as the black curve.
In other words,
it's the first point...
It's the point at which...
you're just on the cusp...
of having spontaneous magnetization.
I didn't draw that well over here.
I meant it to be tangent to the black curve.
So,
as I vary beta,
I eventually hit a point where the
blue curve is tangent to the black curve.
There's only one solution at that point.
The magnetization is zero,
but then when I just go epsilon past that,
just a tiny bit past that,
then the magnetization,
the spontaneous magnetization happens,
and that point is the critical point.
Alright?
It's the critical point,
and it's the point where tanh has unit slope.
So,
what does that mean?
What's the slope of this tanh here at the origin?
It's the derivative of tanh with respect to s.
So,
what's the derivative of tanh with respect to s?
At the origin.
I think it's just twice...
twice beta d.
So,
when twice beta d...
Is that right?
I mean,
if we differentiate tanh...
Can anybody do that?
Alright,
let's do it.
Let's do it just to convince ourselves that I'm right.
What is tanh?
Tanh is sinh over khash,
right?
Sinh over khash.
So,
sinh...
Let's write just sinh x over khash x.
We'll differentiate first with respect to x,
and then we'll differentiate x with
respect to the argument of the tanh.
Alright?
Just usual rule for calculating derivatives.
The derivative of sinh is khash.
Alright?
So,
let's do the...
What's the usual rule?
Denominator times the derivative of the numerator.
Derivative of this with respect to x
is equal to the denominator,
khash x,
times the derivative of the numerator.
Derivative of the numerator is also khash x,
khash squared x,
minus the numerator times the derivative of the denominator.
So,
I think that should be minus sinh squared x?
Plus or minus?
We'll see in a minute.
Hmm?
Let's see.
We have denominator times the derivative of the numerator,
minus numerator times the derivative of the denominator.
So,
it looks to me like khash squared minus sinh squared.
Derivative of khash is equal to sinh,
and derivative of sinh is equal to khash.
As the numerator is minus sinh squared.
So,
that's the derivative of sinh squared.
As the numerator is 1.
The numerator is 1 at x equals 0.
The numerator is 1?
Oh,
khash squared,
yeah.
Khash squared minus sinh squared is 1,
and this is just equal to
1 over khash of x squared.
Okay?
So,
um...
And that,
at x equals 0,
right at this point over here,
that's 1.
Khash of 0 is 1,
so this is all equal to the number 1.
That's the derivative of the tanh
with respect to the argument here,
but then we have to differentiate
the argument with respect to s,
and that will give us a 2 beta d.
So,
that's where the 2 beta d comes from.
The derivative of this with respect to
s at the origin is 2 beta d.
And when that becomes equal to 1,
in other words,
when the derivative of this curve just matches,
just kisses the 45 degree line here,
that's the critical point.
That determines the critical temperature,
and so the critical temperature...
Let's see,
did I miss a j out of this?
Wasn't there a parameter j that...
Yeah,
you used that as a temperature.
It was 1 over beta.
Yeah,
it's there.
There's a j there.
A j.
J.
All right,
so this is 1 over temperature here,
and if I shift it to
the other side of the equation,
it just gives me the critical temperature.
The critical temperature at which the...
T critical is twice d times j.
Notice,
among other things,
that the critical temperature gets higher
with increasing dimensionality.
Why is that?
Well,
low temperature,
you're in the magnetized phase.
The question is,
how long,
or how high can you heat it
before the temperature thermal fluctuations
disrupt the magnetized phase?
And the answer is,
the more neighbors that you have,
the higher the temperature you can get to
before you'll escape from their...
from their tendency to hold you in place.
So that's why the critical temperature increases with d.
You get to higher temperatures
before the magnetization disappears in higher d.
That's proportional to j.
j was just the strength of a coupling
between neighboring spins.
The stronger the coupling between neighboring spins
also increases the temperature,
and the two came from someplace.
All right,
so now,
if we...
if we go back...
I know I explained this,
but let's do it again.
If we go back to the phase diagram,
let's go back to the phase diagram.
And the phase diagram is a diagram
which on the horizontal axis
is just the temperature,
and the vertical axis
is the external magnetic field,
which may be up or down.
It plays the role in the magnet
of the chemical potential in the fluid.
All right,
so let's put vertically here h.
And if h is less than zero,
in other words,
the magnetic field is pointing down,
it will bias all of the spins down,
and throughout this entire quadrant here,
the average spin will be down.
That's for sure.
But if you approach this line
where h is equal to zero,
it may or may not be
that when you just get to that line,
the magnetization is still there.
Or it may be absent.
Okay?
If it's there,
that means there's a jump discontinuity,
because certainly if you approach
from the other side,
you'll find that the magnetization
is still there.
So the line is positive on this side,
negative on this side,
and if there's anything left of it
right at the edge of this line here,
it will have to jump.
And that's a first-order phase trans-
called a first-order phase transition.
It is the sort of thing that happens
as you increase the density of a gas.
The chemical potential can be used
to increase the density of the gas.
You increase the density of the gas
at fixed temperature,
and eventually you will go from gas to liquid.
All right?
When does that happen?
Well,
it happens when the molecules
get good and close together
so that they're almost butting up
against each other.
Not quite.
If they're butting up against each other too much,
of course what'll happen is it'll freeze
into a crystal lattice.
But somewhere in between freezing
in a crystal lattice
and high-temperature boiling water,
somewhere in between,
you'll have a jump in the density.
Okay,
or a jump in the magnetization.
If you go to too high a temperature,
this is T-critical,
as we've seen,
if you go to too high a temperature,
then the spontaneous magnetization
disappears over here,
and so the phase diagram contains
spontaneous magnetization over here,
and it disappears over here.
As I said,
you can go...
I'm sure I did say this,
but I need to remind myself as well as you.
I can go from,
let's call it,
the downward magnetized phase over here,
which is also the gas phase,
let's call it the gas,
or magnetization negative,
over here,
liquid,
magnetization greater than zero.
You can go across this boundary,
in which case you see a sudden jump,
and there's no doubt in that case
that you've made a jump in the density,
or you can go around here
and pass from gas to liquid
without a discontinuity.
So if you go around the critical temperature,
of water,
around in this way,
increasing the density,
you can avoid the sudden jump.
有
In the case,
let's say you're going from the bottom to
the top through the critical to the left,
the lower arrow,
does that imply that you're changing
the magnetic field at one point?
No,
no,
no.
All over.
All over?
Right.
What we're doing is we're changing the chemical potential.
Changing the chemical potential is
a trick for changing the density.
That's all it is.
It's a trick for changing the density.
If you like,
you can simply think of yourself as squeezing the water,
keeping the temperature fixed.
We don't even really have to keep the temperature fixed.
In fact,
here I didn't keep the temperature fixed.
It wandered from here to here.
But if we wanted to
have a precise version of it,
we might cross at a fixed temperature.
So in that case,
you would be increasing the pressure,
at the same time increasing the density,
but keeping the temperature...
What did I say?
Increase the pressure.
Increase the density,
but keep the system in
thermal equilibrium with its environment,
so that the temperature stays the same.
At some point,
the system will jump from gas to...
from vapor to liquid.
So that's the basic physics of
the very simplest kind of phase transition.
So what do you see
if you go around the outside?
I can understand that if you go...
If you go around the outside to the right...
If you go around this way.
Yeah,
if you go the other way,
you see it go from gas to liquid.
That makes sense.
But on the top,
it's liquid,
and on the bottom,
it's gas.
So what do you see if you go around...
You just see gas continuously change into liquid.
The density increases at no point that you
see a sharp discontinuity between liquid and gas.
The lesson is there is no sharp discontinuity.
There is no infinitely sharp way to say,
Okay,
I'm going to go around this way.
This is a gas,
and this is a liquid.
You can go continuously from one
to the other without an abrupt change.
Now,
this is not true for going to a solid.
Something...
The solid-liquid phase transition has a different character.
What happens when you go from liquid to ice,
let's say?
What happens when you go from liquid to ice...
You know,
both the...
You get a fog,
basically.
Yeah,
you get a kind of fog,
or with a fog which
gets denser and denser and denser,
and then just becomes basically...
So are you saying that if
both in liquid and solid state,
like 5% liquid,
95% solid,
I mean,
liquid and gas...
There would be no way to
go from the liquid and gas continuously.
There's always an abrupt change from...
Sorry,
from solid to liquid.
Right,
right.
I meant gas to liquid.
Gas to liquid.
So when you go around,
you've basically got like a fog of 5% liquid...
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Right,
right.
There's...
Yeah,
there's little droplets in it.
You start down here.
And it's mostly gas,
but there are little droplets.
Little droplets are part of the gaseous phase.
Having little droplets.
If you look at it through a microscope,
you'll find little droplets in it.
But the little droplets come and go.
What happens to them?
They form and they evaporate.
Likewise,
up here,
sort of symmetrically,
the liquid will sometimes have formed little bubbles of gas.
There'll be little bubbles of gas,
but the little bubbles of gas will also...
They won't evaporate,
but the liquid will squeeze them out.
The liquid will squeeze them out,
and the little bubbles of gas will...
The little bubbles of gas
that accidentally form get squeezed out.
And so there is a kind of symmetry between these.
On one side,
you have gas with little droplets of liquid.
On the other side,
you have liquid with little bubbles of gas.
But as you said,
as you move around here,
the little droplets of liquid
begin to become more prominent.
They grow.
They are more numerous and maybe bigger.
And the little...
And the gaseous phase sort of
smoothly goes over to the liquid phase.
But right along here,
right along here,
you have sort of both liquid
and gas at the same time.
You have little lumps of liquid,
little lumps of gas,
and so forth.
Just in the same way that if
you looked at the magnet through a microscope,
you would discover islands of
downspin and islands of upspin,
equally numerous along here.
Down here,
you would find more islands of downspin.
Up here,
you would form more islands of upspin.
Right on here,
you would find an equal population,
and you would go smoothly from one to the other.
Quite different what happens when you go across here.
When you go across here,
you'll see mostly gas or mostly downspins
until you get right to here,
and then you jump to mostly upspins.
In the case of...
In the case of the magnet,
the y-axis is the magnetic field.
The external magnetic field.
Right.
And in the case of the liquid and gas,
what is the y-axis?
The y-axis is the chemical potential.
Remember,
what the chemical potential is,
is it's just a device for increasing the density.
It's a device for increasing the density.
The bigger or smaller you make the...
depends on your definition.
But pushing the chemical potential
one way or the other tends
to make it more or less dense.
Remember what the chemical potential was?
It was a...
I don't think you covered it in this class.
Oh,
I didn't.
I didn't explain what the chemical potential is.
Oh,
okay,
why don't I do that right now?
Okay,
good.
My apologies.
Let's talk about chemical potential.
All right,
chemical potential is...
a tool for problems...
Let me erase the blackboard.
All right,
let's imagine we go back to the very beginning
where we have a bunch of identical boxes.
And remember what the game was.
We allowed energy to be interchanged between the boxes
by a weak interaction,
which allowed the boxes...
to exchange energy between them.
And then what we calculated
was the probability distribution
for a given box
given a total amount of energy.
In a situation in equilibrium
where they come to equilibrium
and where energy is going
back and forth at equal rates
so it's at equilibrium,
then there's some total energy
and given the total energy,
we can calculate the probability distribution
for a given box to have a...
Now when we did that,
we introduced the temperature
or the inverse temperature
as a Lagrange multiplier.
We said we want to maximize the entropy
subject to a constraint.
And what was the constraint?
The constraint was that the
total amount of energy was fixed.
So we said let's maximize entropy
given that
that E1 plus E2 plus E3
blah blah blah blah blah
No,
that's not right.
That's not what I want to write.
I want to write
that the number of boxes
with energy E1
plus the number of boxes with energy E2
and so forth
all add up to the total energy of the system.
E total.
The number of boxes with energy E1,
the total energy that they have is N times E1,
so let's call that N1,
N2,
and so forth.
I'm just...
Just go back to your early notes.
I just want to remind you.
And how did we implement this constraint?
This was a constraint.
We had a problem of minimizing or maximizing something.
We wanted to maximize the entropy.
I'm not going to go through it.
We wanted to maximize the entropy
given that the total energy is fixed.
The way to do that
was to introduce a Lagrange multiplier.
We introduced a Lagrange multiplier.
I can't remember now if it had
a plus sign or a minus sign,
but we called that Lagrange multiplier beta.
And that beta multiplied sum
N sub i E sub i.
Or...
Well,
that's good enough.
That's what we did.
We went through this.
We maximized the entropy.
And what do we find?
We found that the probability distribution...
The probability distribution for a given box
was E to the minus beta times the energy.
And if we want to normalize it,
we had to put one over the partition function there.
Now that's just back to first...
Back to first lecture or
second lecture or whatever it was.
Now supposing that it is also possible
not just for energy to be exchanged between these boxes,
but particles to be exchanged.
Helium atoms,
if this was helium,
for example,
or whatever it happens to be.
Or water molecules,
if it's water.
In other words,
there's little thin pipes here.
Little thin pipes.
And those little thin pipes allow water or fluid
to be exchanged back and forth
then we will not know with absolute certainty
what the number of particles in each box was.
Remember that we've assumed previously
that each box had a given number of particles.
But now we don't know what the
number of particles is in the box.
It also has a probability distribution.
But here now is what we will have to do.
We will have to add...
We had two Lagrange multipliers.
We'll have to...
The one Lagrange multiplier is for the total energy.
And so that's summation of n sub i,
e sub i.
Incidentally,
the n sub i's,
if you remember,
were proportional to the probability...
What was i in this formula?
Anybody remember?
Which box?
No,
not which box.
Not which box.
Okay,
let me...
I'll remind you because you probably have forgotten by now.
So have I.
Okay,
what n sub i and e sub i were,
each box can be in any
one of a whole bunch of states.
Here are all the states.
Energy.
Here's the first state,
the second state,
the third state,
the fourth state,
and so forth.
The states are labeled by i.
n sub i is the number of boxes
that occupy the i-th state.
The number of boxes in which you
will find the system in the i-th state.
n sub i times the energy at the i-th state,
if I sum it over all i,
that gives me the total energy.
It's the number of boxes in the first state
times the energy of the first state
plus the number of boxes in the second state
times the energy of the second state.
And so forth and so on.
This has to equal the total energy.
That's the first thing.
Now,
do you remember if there were n boxes here,
do you remember the formula that
n sub i over total n
is equal to the probability of the i-th state?
In other words,
the probability that any given box
is in the i-th state is just proportional
to the fraction of...
total number of boxes that are occupying the i-th state.
And we call that the probability.
So we could divide this formula...
I'll just go through it with you again.
We could divide this formula by n,
e total divided by n.
What's e total divided by n?
It's the average energy in any given box.
So we'll just call this e.
The average energy in a particular box.
And this becomes summation over i,
p of i,
e i,
equals the energy.
This was a constraint.
And what we want to
do is to maximize the entropy.
Maximize the entropy.
Remember what s is?
What's s?
Minus summation over i,
p of i,
log p of i.
That was the entropy.
And we want to maximize it,
subject to a constraint.
And the way you do that
is to introduce a Lagrange multiplier beta.
Forget this over here.
Introduce a Lagrange multiplier beta.
And then maximize this expression with respect to p i.
The p i's are the variables.
We're trying to find out what
the probability of the i state is.
We want to maximize the entropy,
subject to the constraint of a given energy.
And if you remember,
we went through it.
It gave us that p i is equal to what?
e to the minus beta e sub i,
divided by z.
Z is just there to make
the total probability add up to one.
That's the probability of being in the i state.
Now we've done something new.
We've allowed particles to jump back and forth.
But the total number of
particles is not allowed to change.
The total number of particles,
we'll assume,
is conserved.
The total number of helium atoms
or water molecules or whatever it is,
is conserved.
And so we can write another constraint.
The other constraint is that the
number of particles in the first box,
let's see,
the number of particles in the first box,
and one plus the number
of particles in the second box,
plus the number of particles in the third box,
and so forth,
not plus,
all have to add up
to the total number of particles.
n1,
n2,
and n3,
and so forth,
they can change,
but the total number of particles has to remain constant.
Yeah?
I just wondered,
when you did this the first time,
you had two constraints.
Yes,
yes,
yes.
There was a total...
Yeah,
that wasn't the number of particles.
It was the number of boxes.
Right.
Yeah,
you're right.
There actually were two constraints.
The total number of boxes added up to n.
But that's right.
All right.
I had hoped to...
to get around that.
It's there.
All right.
So there's another Lagrange multiplier that has to be added,
and that Lagrange multiplier,
instead of multiplying the energy,
multiplies the number of particles in each box.
I'll tell you what the net result is.
The net result is...
We can now think of the probability
as a joint probability
that the system is in the i-th state
and it has n particles.
It's not just a question now
of which quantum state the system is,
but also how many particles it has in it.
So there's a probability which is a function
of the number of particles in the box
and also which of the many
quantum states the box is in
for that many particles.
And the answer that you
get by the same exact analysis
is another term up in here,
which is minus beta mu
times the number of particles in the box.
This beta times mu
is a somewhat artificial decomposition.
You could have just called beta and mu
the original Lagrange multiplier.
It's beta times mu,
which is the Lagrange multiplier.
It's just a historical definition
that this wasn't called a single thing,
beta times mu,
but that's the way it is.
That's the way it is.
What does mu do for you?
What does tuning mu do for you?
Well,
first of all,
mu is very much like a temperature.
Or beta times mu,
this combination here,
is like a temperature,
but what does temperature do for you?
Forget this.
What does temperature,
what does changing temperature do?
It allows you to tune the energy.
By changing the temperature,
if you know you have a given amount of energy,
the way you would deal with this
is you would change beta
until the average energy is equal to the average energy
that you think is in the box.
So beta is the tuning device.
The temperature is the tuning device,
the knob that you change,
to change the energy in the box.
Mu is the knob that you change
to change the number of particles in the box.
if you want to change the
number of particles in the box.
And why is that?
Well,
you can see if the probability,
let's forget this factor over here,
if the probability goes as e
to the minus beta mu times n,
then the average number of particles in the box
is going to be controlled by this mu here.
Let's see,
the smaller mu is,
the more particles will be in the box,
or whatever it is.
So chemical potential is just a device
for tuning the number of particles in a box
in a situation where the
number of particles in the box
can fluctuate or change in one way or another.
All right,
I didn't want to spend
a lot of time on that,
but let's come back to here now.
How do you change mathematically,
in terms of the statistical mechanical partition function,
how do you change,
oh,
incidentally,
the partition function z,
let's think about the partition function z.
The partition function z satisfies
z is equal to the sum
over all of the states of the system
in the box.
And the number of particles in the box,
the number of particles in the box
and the various states that the particles can be in,
of e to the minus beta e sub i
minus beta mu
times the number of particles in the box.
That's just to make sure
that the total probability adds up to one.
So that's z.
And notice it has a new thing in it.
It has a thing which allows you to control
the number of particles.
Is the capital N in that formula
supposed to be N sub i?
No.
It's the number of particles in...
The average number of particles in all the boxes.
That's right.
All right.
So this is a device.
And how do you choose mu?
You choose mu by calculating
the average number of particles
from this probability distribution
and then set it equal to mu.
And that's equal to what you think
the average number of particles is,
whatever it happens to be.
By changing mu...
Isn't N the possible number of particles in the box?
Because N can be anywhere...
In this formula,
it's the possible number of particles in the box.
That's right.
And you sum over it.
But you can also use this now
to calculate the average number of particles.
How would you calculate the average number?
You take the probability distribution,
multiply it by n and sum.
So you also have a
formula for the average number of
particles in the box.
So if you know there are altogether n total particles
all together divided up among all the boxes,
then you think you know what how
many particles should be in each box,
you simply tune mu until you get that
many particles.
Yeah,
but obviously tuning the number
of particles in a given box
of a given size is
the same as changing the density.
You can think about
how to do that,
you just divide by the volume.
And so the chemical potential is
a trick in the partition function
for changing the density of the gas.
What is
that?
Mu is the chemical potential.
And I have a strong feeling that my
definition of mu differs from everybody
else's on earth by a sign.
I'm sorry.
I discovered that sign the other day.
I've been going out through my entire
life with the chemical potential having
the sign that I've given it here.
I'm not
going to try to correct it now.
Whatever it is,
it is the thing which allows you
to vary the density.
Now what is the density in this lattice fluid?
The
density in the lattice fluid is,
roughly speaking,
the number of up spins divided
by the volume.
Capital N,
becomes the number of up spins here.
A down spin is empty.
An up spin
represents a molecule.
So capital N is just the number of up spins.
How do you
change the number of up spins?
How do you tune the system from,
essentially,
no
up spins,
and bias it towards lots of up spins?
You change H,
right?
When H is down,
it pushes all the spins down,
and when H goes up,
it pushes all the so-called up spins,
Now no matter what the temperature is,
if H is down,
it will bias the system toward few upspins.
And if you want to change the density of upspins,
what you do is move along this H-axis.
So the H-axis is closely connected.
It's essentially the same as the chemical potential.
And it's the thing that you tune
to change the density of the gas,
the density of the fluid.
Quick question.
The terminology is one Lagrange multiplier is beta
and the other Lagrange multiplier is beta mu?
Well,
yeah,
it's a historical fact.
We could have just called it lambda.
Okay,
so it's different than beta.
It's different than beta.
And historically,
lambda was set equal to beta times mu.
A little confusing there.
Yeah,
I know.
Great.
All right.
So we could have just called it lambda.
But that wouldn't be,
that would be ahistorical and it
would be different than the standard terminology.
So the standard terminology is
to replace lambda by beta mu.
But think of beta mu as itself a quantity.
Incidentally,
you calculate the average number of particles by differentiating
the logarithm of the partition function with respect to mu.
Differentiating with respect to mu,
well,
differentiating with respect to beta mu,
brings down an n and allows you
to calculate the average number of particles.
So you calculate the derivative of the logarithm
of the partition function with respect to beta mu.
And that gives you the mean number of particles,
which is very similar to
how we calculated the mean energy,
differentiate the log of the
partition function with respect to beta.
Similar idea.
Okay,
that's,
that is the basic setup for...
Yeah.
How does an experimentalist measure the chemical potential?
I know how they do temperature,
but how do you...
I'm not sure you do measure the chemical potential.
Yeah.
How do you measure the chemical potential?
I would say you measure the
density more likely than the chemical potential.
I don't know.
I never think about measuring the chemical potential.
I think of it as a
tunable parameter that changes the density,
and that the density is the thing that you...
Does that have anything to do with the work function?
Yeah,
it is the amount of energy that it
takes to remove a system from a box.
Yeah,
it is related to the work function.
So the work function is the energy?
Yeah,
how much energy it takes to
remove a particle from a box.
Yeah.
It's true.
Okay,
so...
Good.
But now I want to talk about something very exotic,
extremely interesting,
and took many years.
It took many years to really get right.
It has had an enormous influence
on statistical mechanics and quantum field theory.
I doubt that that's obvious to anybody in the room,
what all of this has
to do with quantum field theory,
but let's not worry about that.
It has to do with the behavior of
the system as you approach the critical point.
Let's say moving along h equals zero.
We don't even need h for this here.
We just move along from the high temperature side,
getting closer and closer to the critical point.
What is it that happens at the critical point?
And something very interesting
happens at the critical point.
The first idea that you need
in order to understand the critical point
is the idea of a correlation length.
We talked,
I think we talked,
did we talk at all about the correlation function?
No,
we didn't.
So I'll tell you what the correlation function is.
We don't need to talk about how you calculate it.
It's an average.
It's an average of the product
of spins at two different points.
Let's say sigma of A and sigma of B.
It's the average value of the
product of sigma A and sigma B.
It measures the degree of correlation
between the spin at point A
and the spin at point B.
These could be two points on the lattice.
They could be near each other.
They could be far from each other.
What happens if A is equal to B,
incidentally?
Sigma squared is just equal to one.
So the correlation function at the origin,
let's call it,
in other words,
when A and B are the same point,
that's always equal to one.
But now let's separate the points.
Okay?
All right.
So how do I calculate the correlation function
at these two different points?
And let's imagine,
let's go to extremely high temperatures.
Let's start at the high temperature end of things.
All right?
Not at the magnetized phase,
but at the high temperature end.
Infinite temperature,
enormously high temperature.
And what happens at very high temperature?
Eh,
jiggling around like mad.
And the temperature is so high
that the bonds are not very potent
at holding the spins aligned with each other.
So let's talk about the correlation,
or the average,
of the product of two spins
neighboring to each other at very,
very high temperature.
What would you expect that it would be?
Zero.
Zero,
because even if you freeze,
you can think of it this way.
You can think of calculating
it by freezing this spin up
and then calculating in the presence of this spin up,
calculating the average of this spin.
And then...
That's the way you can think about it.
It really represents the probability
that if this spin is up,
then this spin is also up,
or also down.
Some average,
given that this one is up,
what's the probability that this one is up or down?
And that represents,
that's the correlation function.
Or better yet,
given that this one is up,
what's the average of this one?
All right.
So,
what would you expect,
again,
at very high temperatures?
Just zero,
because they're fluctuating.
They're fluctuating completely independently,
because the temperature is so high
that the bond joining these is ineffective.
What happens as you start to lower the temperature?
As you start to lower the temperature,
if this spin is up,
it will bias this spin to also be up,
because the energy will be lowered if they're parallel.
If this spin is down,
it will also bias it.
So what starts to happen,
is that sigma times sigma
starts to not be zero anymore,
and in fact is usually positive.
It's positive because if this spin is up,
this one is more likely to be up,
so sigma times sigma is positive.
If this spin is down,
then this one is also more likely to be down,
and so again,
sigma times sigma is positive.
And so this correlation function
between neighboring points
at moderately high temperatures
will stop being zero
and be small but non-zero.
What about the correlation function
between second nearest neighbors?
Square?
Square is a negative one?
It'll be more or less,
that's right,
it'll be more or less the square
of the correlation between first nearest neighbors.
That's right.
That in fact is about what it is.
What about you go way,
way down the line here?
And there's nothing that's special
about moving along the horizontal axis here.
We move vertical axis,
or we can move at a 45 degree,
but what would you expect
as you move way down here?
Again,
you'll expect each time you move,
you'll lose some correlation.
And in fact,
you lose the same fraction
of correlation,
roughly speaking,
and that means that this is going to be
exponential in the distance between these points.
If each time you lost,
let's say,
half the correlation,
if the correlation between nearest neighbors
was a half,
and second nearest neighbors
was a quarter,
third nearest neighbors
was an eighth,
and so forth,
you might expect that this would behave
like e to the minus
some parameter m
times the distance between them.
Let's call it distance between them
d.
Distance means number of lattice sites
between them.
So when you're very,
very far away,
the correlation is extremely weak,
exponentially weak.
When you're close by,
the correlation function is stronger.
The correlation is stronger.
This m depends on the temperature.
At very,
very high temperatures,
the correlation falls very rapidly
to zero.
Let's imagine plotting it
at different temperatures.
Correlation function is always one
at d equals zero.
So this is d.
At extremely high temperatures,
the correlation function just drops
like a bomb down to zero.
And so by the time you get over
to the first lattice point,
it's negligible.
Small at very high temperatures.
And then it just stays small.
Gets even smaller,
smaller,
exponentially.
What happens as you lower the temperature?
As you lower the temperature,
the correlation function continues to drop
as an exponential,
but the rate in here at which it falls
becomes more and more gradual.
As the temperature gets lower,
the rate at which it falls becomes more gradual.
And that means that m
is a function of temperature.
So,
if you look at the graph,
m is a function of temperature.
And what does it represent?
It represents the distance
that you have to go out
in order that the correlation has dropped
by a factor of e.
Alright?
How far do you have to go out
in order that the correlation function
has dropped by a factor of e?
That's what m represents.
It's also called the inverse correlation function.
So,
the inverse correlation function
The inverse correlation length,
the correlation length is the width of this curve.
Here,
the correlation length is very,
very small.
And m is very large.
As you lower the temperature,
the correlation length gets longer and longer,
and the inverse correlation function
gets smaller and smaller.
Okay?
When m is very small,
this function very gradually goes to zero.
Okay?
So,
m is a function of t.
It represents the inverse of the correlation length,
correlation length being the distance out
to which you have to go
in order that the,
that you've lost a factor of e
in the correlation.
And those are a set of definitions,
but they're clearly a useful set of definitions.
And what the correlation length tells you
is it just tells you exactly what it says.
How long,
how far out on the lattice
will you feel
the effect of nailing one particular spin in place?
Supposing you nailed one particular spin in place,
either up or down,
how far away is it felt?
That's called the correlation length,
and it's inverse to this m of t.
So,
m of t decreases,
obviously decreases with temperature.
Correlation length increases,
m of t decreases.
Okay.
Yeah?
In all these cases,
you're assuming there's nothing
between the two test points,
right?
Yeah.
So,
you're making an assumption
about the density in there implicitly.
You're making an assumption
that it's not so dense
that you're squeezing...
Dense in the sense of...
Particles on every lattice point.
Mm-hmm.
So,
you're getting...
Dense in the sense of...
Particles on every lattice point.
Oh,
there could be a particle
on every lattice point.
Then the correlation length...
It could be.
So,
it's just a two-position...
Mm-hmm.
It's just a two-position
of all the effects then?
Yeah.
But at very high temperatures,
with no chemical potential,
you will not find
that there's a particle on every point.
You'll find it's about half filled.
Okay.
Half filled
at high temperatures.
Half filled,
half empty.
Doesn't that depend on
how finely you draw the lattice?
How finely you draw the lattice?
Yeah.
No?
No,
we just...
No.
Nothing depends on how I draw the lattice.
Drawing the lattice is just...
I can draw on a piece of paper.
I can draw on the blackboard.
I can draw it on the ceiling.
Same system.
The spin could be up or down.
So,
at each point in the lattice,
the spin could be up or down.
So,
half of them are up
and half of them are down.
Right.
Half of them are up
and half of them are down
at high temperatures,
typically.
Yeah.
Okay.
Good.
But the interesting thing is
this correlation length
gets longer and longer.
Okay.
Now,
imagine you now pass
below the critical point.
What happens to the correlation function
below the critical point?
Let's think about that.
Take sigma of A times sigma of B
below the critical point.
And below the critical point,
here we are below the critical point.
We could be here or we could be here.
Below the critical point,
the bias of just one spin being up
is enough to bias...
Remember what happens below the critical point.
There's this sort of instability
that the tiniest little perturbation,
which biases it one way or the other,
will lock all the spins,
not all the spins exactly into the same direction,
but will bias all the spins
so that the average magnetization
is in one of the two directions.
So,
supposing we freeze sigma A to be up.
And now we look at sigma B.
Well,
the sample has been up,
but the average has been biased by sigma A.
And we're in the magnetized phase.
We're below the critical temperature.
And so what's going to happen
is sigma B will,
on the average,
be in the same direction as sigma A,
but right out to infinity.
Right out to infinity.
One...
In this magnetized phase here,
one spin pointing up is enough
to tell all the others that,
on the average,
they will point up.
That's what happens in...
to this...
down below the critical temperature.
So,
what we can say then
is that sigma A,
sigma B
will go to some constant,
some positive number...
positive number...
I don't know what to call it.
Let's just call it number...
constant.
As you move further and further away,
mm-hmm,
sigma A,
sigma B will go to some constant.
That constant will also depend
on the temperature.
If you're at very low temperatures,
the spins will tend to align each other
rather rigidly.
If you're at zero temperature,
the only two possibilities are
all spins up and all spins down.
What happens to this at zero temperature?
It's one.
If sigma A is up,
then sigma B is up.
If sigma A is down,
then sigma B is down.
So,
at zero temperature,
let's approach now...
I'm going to use red
to approach from the low temperature side.
This is what happened from the high temperature side,
and this always goes to zero
as long as the temperature is high enough.
But now,
here's temperature zero.
What happens at a little bit higher temperature?
You're still in the magnetized phase,
and
you still go to a constant out here,
but a little bit less constant.
Things are not rigidly held in place as well.
Eventually,
you come down to the critical temperature,
and as you get to the critical temperature,
that's the temperature which divides these two behaviors.
What's the behavior here?
Exponentially decreasing correlation.
The correlation function doesn't decrease.
What divides them?
What divides them is the critical behavior...
Let's see,
I have trouble drawing it.
The critical behavior
which is neither constant at infinity,
nor is it exponentially falling.
Every one of these eventually falls exponentially.
Every one of them falls exponentially.
What about this critical one here?
What's in between being constant
and falling exponentially?
Well,
there's a lot of things,
but...
Hmm?
Hyperbolic means what?
1 over x.
Well,
how about just 1 over x to a power?
1 over d,
1 over d to a power.
Hmm?
At infinity,
it's zero.
Yeah,
this falls and falls and falls and falls,
but it never falls as fast as an exponential,
and it fails to have
a finite limit at the end.
Right.
So what is known...
This requires a proof,
and it requires some work,
but what's known is right at the critical point,
right at that critical point,
this just falls off as a power law.
This falls off gradually as a power law,
not as an exponential.
That's the characteristic critical behavior,
that the correlations are long-range,
sort of 1 over r to a power.
For the two-dimensional Ising model,
it's 1 over distance to the 1 eighth,
so it gradually falls off.
The number is not terribly important.
Okay,
so that's one of the things that happens
at that critical point.
Now,
as you approach the critical point,
imagine that you looked microscopically
at the magnet.
The correlation length here,
the fact that it has some size,
what it's really telling you
is that the magnet is
filled up with blobs of spins,
bubbles of spins,
more or less pointing in the same direction.
There are blobs of spins up.
There are blobs down,
but they're not exactly all up.
They're somewhat biased toward up.
They're somewhat biased toward down over here,
somewhat biased toward up.
Down.
A kind of patchwork
where the patches tend to be
about as big as the correlation length.
If you take two points beyond the correlation length,
out way past the correlation length,
there isn't much correlation between them.
Something over here is as
likely to be up or down
if this is up.
But if your two points
are within one of these blobs,
then most likely they're pointing the same direction.
All right,
so it's this blob,
it's this formation of these bubbles
or blobs of material.
It could be,
it's really,
what is it,
it's liquid gas in the case of the fluid,
or up spins and down spins
in the case of the magnet.
These structures more or less follow in size
the correlation length.
So this M of T is basically just the inverse
of the size of the blobs that you would see
if you looked carefully.
Size one over M?
Yeah,
size one over M.
Right.
And as you get closer
and closer to the critical point,
what happens to M is it goes to zero.
M goes to zero.
It's no longer a exponential,
but gives way to a power law,
and that corresponds to M going to zero.
All right,
or the correlation length blowing up.
The correlation length gets bigger and bigger,
bigger and bigger blobs like this.
So that's what,
now what happens?
Of course,
I should say this,
that each one of these
blobs is not a pure phase.
It is not pure all spins up.
This one is not all spins down.
This one just has all spins up.
This one has a preference for ups.
This one has a mild preference for downs.
What happens as you get closer and closer
to the critical point,
two things happen.
First of all,
these blobs get bigger and bigger.
But second of all,
they tend to fade.
Fade means they,
what's the word when you put
your nice colored shirt with lots of contrast
through the washing machine too many times?
Bleed.
Well,
fade.
Fade.
If you were to look at
this as you move closer and closer
to the critical point,
what you would see is these blobs blowing up.
Okay.
Now,
you could say,
all right,
let me just try to restore some,
some,
just for convenience,
let me squeeze the whole thing down
so that the blobs have the same size.
I'll have to make the lattice smaller.
All right.
I'm just going to do that.
I'm going to do it
as I move closer and closer
to the critical point.
The blobs indeed get bigger and bigger.
But just as a matter of convenience,
so that I don't have to draw the whole thing
on a blackboard which is 20 miles long,
what I'll do instead is rescale
the whole diagram so that
the blobs remain the same size.
The blobs remain the same size.
Moreover,
there are blobs within blobs.
There are blobs within blobs.
But the net effect in the biggest
blobs is to be on the average upspin.
In the biggest blobs of the downspin type,
the net effect is to be downspin.
So that's what the correlation length is.
But what happens to these blobs,
even if you plot them always in such a way
that their size looks the same,
this is just an arbitrary rescaling of the lattice,
just so that we can redraw it.
So that I don't have to run out of the
room to the next room out there to get closer and
closer to the critical point.
Instead,
we imagine in our heads making the
lattice spacing much smaller so that the blobs
occupy more and more lattice spacings.
But in addition to the blobs getting bigger,
they get fainter.
They get,
what's the right word,
bleached I think somebody said.
Faded.
Faded like putting your polka dot
black and white shirt through the dishwasher,
not the dishwasher,
the washing machine too many times.
And what will happen?
After a while,
the contrast between the up blobs and
the down blobs will get weaker and
weaker and weaker.
That's what happens at the critical point.
In fact,
at the critical point,
you have blobs of every
size right at the critical point.
When the biggest blobs grow to infinity,
there are still smaller blobs.
The biggest blobs grow to infinity but are infinitely faded.
The next biggest blobs,
they're still there,
they're still there pretty big,
they're not quite as faded.
Smaller blobs within blobs,
not quite as faded as their predecessors,
and smaller.
What happens at the critical point
is a kind of self-similar fractal structure.
A self-similar fractal structure that on every scale,
if you look at it,
you see the same
thing,
namely blobs within blobs within blobs,
but as you look on smaller and smaller scales,
the contrast,
the density contrast gets stronger and stronger.
If at the same time,
that you rescale the lattice,
push the temperature closer to the critical point,
rescale the lattice,
and also rescale the density,
the contrast,
you know,
you have your television
and you turn down the
contrast or turn up the contrast.
As you look at smaller and smaller blobs,
if you turn down the contrast,
then you literally see the same thing at every scale.
The only distinction between what you see at
one scale and another scale is the intensity
of the contrast between the blobs.
If you allow for that,
if you allow for the decrease
or the fading of the contrast from,
as you get closer and closer to the critical point,
then what you see is just a self-similar
fractal which looks the same on every scale.
Everybody know what I mean by self-similar?
It just means it looks the same in every scale.
You could not tell by
looking at it through a microscope,
unless your microscope,
of course,
was strong enough to see the actual lattice structure.
I'm assuming we have a microscope
which can't see the actual lattice structure,
but it sees blobs.
Then at the critical point,
at the critical point,
you cannot tell,
or close to the critical point,
you cannot tell how big the,
well,
you can't tell which blobs you're looking at,
they all look the same,
except for the strength of the density contrast.
The smaller they are,
the stronger the density contrast.
In fact,
if you get down to the lattice spacing itself,
you will see upspins and downspins.
Upspins are absolutely black,
downspins are absolutely white,
and so you'll see spins next to each other,
slightly biased maybe,
but with very strong contrast.
On the other hand,
these very big lumps here,
those very big lumps will have weak contrast.
In fact,
the fact that the contrast gets more and more faded
is just the fact that this
correlation function gets smaller and smaller
as the distance between things gets big.
As the distance between points gets big,
right at the critical point,
there are blobs of every size,
but if you take two points,
the correlation will mainly be due
to blobs of about the scale
between the two points.
What is it that will lead
to a correlation between these two points?
The likelihood that there's a blob about that big.
The further apart you take them,
you'll be sampling bigger and bigger blobs,
but bigger and bigger blobs have less contrast,
and that's why the correlation function falls
and goes to zero,
because for very,
very big blobs,
the contrast has faded.
You can actually see this
in simulations of magnetic systems.
You look at the simulations,
and you see patterns of blobs
and blobs and blobs inside blobs.
It's hard to really see anything.
More or less,
you see white noise or black noise or whatever.
But if you look carefully,
you can see some slightly overdense regions,
some slightly underdense regions,
and then as you tune
the system toward the critical point,
the overdense regions and the underdense regions grow,
and you'll also see that they have blobs inside them
which are even more overdense,
and blobs inside blobs inside blobs.
And so this pattern of self-similarity
is the first thing that happens at the critical point.
Something else happens at the critical point.
If you look at these blobs,
the theory of these blobs,
the actual lattice itself was not very symmetric.
It certainly did not have circular symmetry.
It has just square symmetry.
It's a square lattice,
for example,
and so it's not isotropic.
It's by no means isotropic,
and you would not expect the properties of the magnet
to look isotropic.
You wouldn't expect the correlation function
to be truly isotropic.
You would expect it to be different along the axes
than it is along the 45-degree angles.
But as you get closer
and closer to the critical point,
the system loses memory.
And so you have this theory
of the basic underlying lattice theory,
and it just gets more and more rotationally symmetric,
more and more isotropic,
until right at the critical point,
by looking at these big,
big blobs,
you cannot tell which direction the lattice is oriented.
So that's another thing that happens,
a washout of the basic starting point,
if you like,
the basic starting point being some specific lattice,
with a given orientation.
I'll give you another example.
We might have made a more complicated structure.
Instead of the magnet having only nearest-neighbor coupling,
we might have had a lattice with nearest-neighbor
and second-nearest-neighbor coupling,
or neighboring couplings
this spin times this spin,
but maybe also diagonal couplings,
spins,
energy of the spins,
depending on diagonal couplings,
and maybe second-nearest-neighbor couplings,
and so forth.
We might have invented a more complicated model,
sigma times sigma,
nearest-neighbor,
plus sigma times sigma,
times next-nearest-neighbor,
and so forth.
Let's suppose that all the bonds
favor parallel spins.
Let's suppose that it tends to favor parallel spins.
Then there are detailed differences
between a magnet with second-nearest-neighbor couplings
and first-nearest-neighbor couplings.
They're in detail different.
The details of the thermodynamics are different,
and in particular they're
quite different at high temperatures,
where the correlation length is very small.
In general,
the details of the lattice
and the details of the structure
will be remembered at the high-temperature limit,
but as you lower the temperature
and these blobs get bigger and bigger,
the system starts to forget what the details were.
So the critical behavior
of the second-nearest-neighbor coupled lattice
is exactly the same as the critical behavior
of the first-nearest-neighbor coupled lattice.
The diagonal bonds don't do very much.
They may shift.
What they will do is they will shift
the critical temperature a little bit.
The effect of changing the bonds
and the nature of the microscopic interaction
between molecules,
it will have the effect in general
that it may change the critical temperature a little bit.
But whatever the critical temperature is,
as you approach it,
whatever it is,
you'll always see exactly the same pattern
of fractal self-similar type of structure,
which will forget the details of the lattice.
That's the nature of critical behavior.
Bubbles or blobs at every length scale,
stronger ones at small length scale,
more faded ones at large length scale,
contrast going down and down and down.
There's an interesting experimental consequence of this.
Has anybody ever seen critical opalescence?
Critical opalescence is a wonderful phenomenon.
If you take a liquid,
helium is a good example,
but any transparent liquid,
and you tune its temperature toward the critical point,
you tune temperature and density,
move along here,
getting closer and closer to the critical point,
what happens is exactly this.
Blobs of every length scale
are in the critical form of every length scale,
and the effect is that it scatters light.
Light passing through it will
be scattered at every wavelength.
Every wavelength will be scattered
pretty much the same way as every other wavelength.
If you're away from the critical point,
the largest blobs will have some given size,
and wavelengths longer than that will not be scattered.
But as you tune toward the critical wave,
the critical point,
longer and longer wavelengths will be scattered,
and light passing through a
material close to its critical point,
just a...
It's called critical opalescence.
You can imagine what that means.
It means...
How would you describe opalescence?
Well,
all colors,
it gets very milky.
You have a filter.
You have a filter,
basically.
You have a...
Filter.
A filter.
Well,
you have a filter,
but the point is that it scatters light.
It scatters light that...
If you're close to the critical point,
but not that close,
you'll scatter all wavelengths down to microwaves.
Get closer to the critical point,
and you'll start scattering radio waves.
I'm being a little bit extreme,
but...
At first,
you scatter optical light,
then you scatter optical light and infrared,
then you start scattering optical light,
infrared,
and microwaves,
then you start scattering everything.
And the whole thing just looks like a milky,
um,
opalescent material.
It loses its transparency
because it just scatters at every wavelength.
So that's called critical opalescence,
and it's a real phenomenon.
I wish I had...
I wish I could show it to you here,
but I don't have any liquid helium.
I think liquid helium is probably the best example.
Is this approaching the critical mass
by cooling to it or...
Critical.
By cooling or by heating to it?
It doesn't matter,
really,
but I think it's best to do it by cooling.
Yeah.
Normally,
it would be done by cooling.
You would start above the critical temperature
and slowly cool down to the critical temperature.
And as you cool down,
you'll discover the thing becomes
a better and better scatterer of light.
It doesn't really absorb the light.
It just becomes not opaque.
There's another word.
What's in between opaque and transparent?
Translucent.
It becomes translucent,
but translucent at every wavelength.
Would that be because of the different refractive index
between the solid and...
I mean,
the liquid and the refractive index?
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
There's a difference between the index of refraction
and the liquid in the...
And so it scatters the light.
Yes,
and at all scales.
There are structures there at all scales
that scatter the light.
Right,
exactly.
And in fact,
one word that's used to describe
this self-similarity is it's called scale invariance.
Scale invariance means the phenomena
of things looking the same at every scale.
But as a rule,
you have to keep in mind
that the contrasts tend to fade,
and so you have to artificially jack up.
As you look at the bigger and bigger things,
you have to artificially renormalize,
is the word,
renormalize the density contrast
so as to keep it the same.
Then what you see at
every length scale is the same.
Quick question about the fading.
I'm trying to understand.
If you have 100 molecules or whatever,
if,
like,
the ratio is,
97 are spin up
and 3 spin down,
that's very contrasty.
If it's 85-15,
that's less...
more fading.
Right.
Wouldn't that be just the entropy of it?
It is.
It's certainly connected to entropy.
But the fact that this correlation
function falls at large distances,
like a power law,
tells you that the intensity
of the,
or the contrast,
within a blob of a,
of a big blob is less than the intensity
of the contrast of a smaller blob.
So that's exactly what this falling
correlation function tells you.
So it's a pretty interesting phenomenon.
And more than interesting,
it's sort of at the root
of how quantum field theory works,
but we haven't talked about quantum field theory.
And it is the ingredient in many approximate schemes.
In many approximate schemes,
you take a system
which you expect at the
end to be isotropic and homogeneous.
You're really talking about
some isotropic homogeneous thing.
A quantum field theory would be a case in point
where things are rotationally symmetric,
translationally symmetric,
and so forth,
and you want to model it.
You want to model it
as a system on a lattice.
Why?
Because it's convenient to a pro...
to replace the continuous distribution of field variables
that fill space by an approximate version of the theory
where all the degrees of
freedom live on individual lattice sites.
Right?
What's going to happen?
Well,
you're going to wind up with a description
where the lattice behavior will stick through
and get in your way.
The system will not look translational invariant
because the lattice is not translationally invariant.
There will be corners to
things because the lattice has corners.
But how do you restore in such a system
the behavior that you were
looking for in the first place,
which was this smooth,
translationally invariant,
rotationally invariant behavior,
and the answer is you
tune yourself to a critical point.
Whatever the example is,
whether it's statistical mechanics or quantum field theory,
you tune the parameters until you get to a point
where the correlation length is much,
much longer
than the lattice length.
And that limit,
the artifacts,
the lattice artifacts disappear.
So this is a common tool in quantum field theory.
And in statistical mechanics and so forth.
Okay,
so let's see.
Where are we?
Any questions?
Yeah.
I've got one.
Is this related to superconductivity in any way?
Not particularly.
This is called,
incidentally,
the rescaling that I've described here.
This rescaling and constantly pushing the
blobs back to the same size,
that's called renormalization group.
Got to do with renormalization in quantum field theory.
Does it have to do,
well,
yes and no.
In some systems,
there is a phase transition in a superfluid
or in a superconductor which behaves exactly this way.
Yeah,
but it's not really got
much to do with the phenomena
of superconductivity itself.
ありがとうございました
Are there applications of this to cosmology,
like the microwave background radiation?
Yes.
Yes,
there are.
Right.
That's a good point.
The fluctuations that are seen in the sky,
the microwave background is very homogeneous,
of course,
extremely homogeneous or isotropic across the sky.
But if you look at the
level of 10 to the minus 5,
you see over densities and under densities and so forth.
In other words,
you see blobs.
You see a blobiness.
And in fact,
you see the same blobiness at every scale.
You see exactly the same sort of self-similar scale
invariant kind of behavior as at a critical point.
Now,
is it connected with critical points?
Yes,
it is,
but not in a completely
obvious way.
But it looks very much
what is seen in the sky.
When you look at the microwave background
and you see these maps of the microwave background
and so forth,
is self-similar in the same way
that the critical point,
self-similar or scale
invariant.
Scale invariant is the word that's used.
So it's almost as though the early universe was generated
from a Monte Carlo simulation.
Monte Carlo just means a statistical averaging
of a magnetic system.
But that's not the case.
That's not the real reason for it.
The real reason for it is quite different.
We didn't,
the organization in the sky
did not come from a second order phase transition.
Incidentally,
jumping across here,
where you have a real jump in the density,
that's called a first order phase transition.
The order of the transition,
the lowest order transition,
corresponds to the biggest,
most abrupt jump.
So a first order phase
transition is one in which density
or magnetic field or whatever the appropriate variable is,
the obvious variable,
makes a discontinuous jump.
If you approach along here,
along the temperature axis
with no bias,
you come right down to this critical point
over here.
And then if you go a little bit further,
you'll see spontaneous magnetization.
Here you don't see anything.
You don't see anything discontinuous.
Right at this point over here,
the magnetization is zero.
And as you move in,
the magnetization,
the magnitude of the magnetization continuously increases.
So there's no sudden jump in the magnetization here.
It's just zero,
zero,
and then it starts increasing from here,
but smoothly.
That's called a second order phase transition,
when the density or magnetization,
uh,
is absolutely zero until a critical point
and then starts to increase smoothly from there.
Uh,
something is discontinuous over at this point over here.
If you differentiate the magnetization enough times,
you will find that there's some singularity in it.
But it's a subtle,
it's a more subtle effect.
Second order phase transitions are more subtle,
and third order phase transitions are even more subtle
and almost never happen because they're so subtle.
OK,
yeah?
What is the third order?
I can't think of one offhand.
I once knew one.
I don't remember what it was.
But they're rare.
And offhand,
I cannot remember what
system had a third order phase transition.
Chemical opalescence phenomenon,
is that what happens?
Critical opalescence.
Is that what's happening when water vapor condenses
into clouds?
Well.
I don't know.
I think snow.
No.
It's not.
It sort of looks like it,
but it's not.
The critical point,
anybody know what
the critical temperature of water is?
1000 degrees.
Something like that.
I don't remember exactly,
but it's way,
way above boiling.
It's about 300.
360 or something.
360 degrees,
something like that?
306 degrees.
Right.
So this temperature here is
at 306 degrees and some pressure.
Some pressure and some temperature,
or some density and some temperature.
Some density and some temperature
is a critical point.
And that critical point is
the second order phase transition.
And if you want to see it,
you've got to,
in water,
you have to be up at 306 degrees.
On the other hand,
in helium,
it happens at a very low temperature,
a much lower
temperature.
And so you can see
liquid helium boiling into helium vapor.
And if you bring the helium
to just the right density and temperature,
you can see the critical opalescence.
OK.
In the cosmology example,
if you look at over time
when dark energy thing took over
from the matter,
could that be considered like a critical point as well?
No.
That's not a critical point.
In cosmology,
the main analog of this kind
of critical behavior is what's called the
scale invariant fluctuation spectrum.
OK.
So the scale invariant is the
spectrum of fluctuations and perturbations over densities
and under densities that were there
at primordial times before galaxies formed,
just the surface
of last scattering.
The surface of last scattering,
if you look out on the sky,
looks like this kind of behavior.
And I mean quantitatively.
Quantitatively,
it looks scale invariant.
Now it's actually not completely true.
It's not completely true because the
system gets processed a little bit.
I mean it's quite obvious that gravity
took over and started manipulating the overdense
and the underdense regions.
But if we could have seen what that sky
was like before gravity started to work on these
overdense and the real primordial fluctuation spectrum,
it would look very much like the
critical point of this magnet.
OK.
Thank you.
On inflation,
I hear when you go from the vacuum steroids,
the really high one,
down
to the regular one,
I've heard that they had
some original problem with the theory.
It's called reheating.
That's called reheating.
Yeah.
Why reheating and not just heating?
They said,
and it didn't make any sense to me then,
but they said it was originally modeled
as a first order phase transition.
Oh,
OK.
Yeah.
Right.
We can talk about that next time a little bit.
Remind me.
Yes,
it was originally modeled as a first order phase transition.
That was a disaster.
And I can tell you why.
We have enough things I can tell you why,
but I'm not going to tell you why now.
I'm fading.
My contrast is diminishing.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.