Stanford University
Alright,
this evening I want to get started
on talking about particle mechanics in the
special theory of relativity.
How particles move,
notions of momentum,
energy,
we will
get to E equals mc squared,
and that sort of thing.
The next time,
or maybe even tonight
a little bit,
we might even get to move past that
if we get finished with it and start
to talk about classical field theory.
Let me just do one thing on the blackboard that
we will need recurrently and over and over.
Okay.
For various purposes,
mostly for purposes of
showing that the relativistic formulas
that we write down have the limit of
the non-relativistic formulas that we may have written down,
that
we did write down two quarters ago in classical mechanics.
We are going to want to show that
when objects move slowly compared to the speed of light,
Okay.
that the newfangled relativistic theory of
particle motion and particle mechanics reduces
to the oldfangled Newtonian.
Okay,
for that we are going to need to make approximations
which become better and better
for slower and slower velocities,
and in particular the
thing that we are going to have to approximate,
now I know you all
know this but I am going
to do it just for completeness on the blackboard.
Okay.
So we have this quantity which recurs over and over,
1 minus v squared,
square root
of 1 minus v squared.
It really means square root of
1 minus v squared over c squared.
If we measure the velocity in
units of the speed of light,
then it is just 1 minus v
squared,
but we remember that v represents the
fraction of the speed of light of the
object which is moving with velocity v,
so typically it is very small,
and we just want
to write down how we approximate this for small velocities,
in particular how we approximate
it to order velocity squared.
This is just an example of the binomial theorem.
I will
write it down once and for all,
we will use it a couple
of times tonight and I assume
everybody knows it.
The binomial theorem says that
1 plus a small number epsilon,
it doesn't
matter if it is small,
but 1 plus a small number
epsilon equals 1 plus a small number
epsilon to a power p,
where p can be anything as a matter of fact,
it can be positive,
negative,
imaginary,
complex,
it doesn't matter,
that this can be expanded in powers of epsilon,
a Taylor series if you like.
If you don't know Taylor series,
we just expand it in powers
of epsilon.
For epsilon equals 0,
it is just given by 1,
and then the next term is p times
epsilon.
Now I am not going to work,
I am not going to prove this.
This is something,
this is the standard binomial theorem,
and the next term,
everybody remember
the next term?
p times,
hmm?
p choose 2,
which is the same as p
times p minus 1 over 2 factorial,
2 factorial is incidentally just 2,
times epsilon squared,
and then it keeps going like
that.
I will write the next one,
and you can write all the ones after it,
it is a homework assignment
to write out all the infinite number of them.
What?
Yeah,
pi.
Over 3 factorial epsilon cubed and so forth.
If epsilon is not too big,
then this series
will be 0.
will converge.
And the meaning of saying it
converges is that each term is significantly
smaller than the previous in such a way
that it is a good approximation to terminate the
series after an appropriate number of terms,
where appropriate depends on just how much
precision you want.
But in particular,
if epsilon is really very small,
it is usually
the case that the first
term is the most important one.
Of course,
it is the zeroth term,
which
of course is the most important one,
but the zeroth term is awfully boring here.
We are
going to find for the various
applications that the zeroth order term,
the 1,
is just
too boring to be relevant to us,
and it is the first
order term here which is important.
So let's terminate the series at that point.
Of course,
it does break down if epsilon is
not too small.
So supposing we want to expand 1 minus v squared,
square root of 1 minus v squared,
where epsilon is now,
we are now using epsilon equals minus v squared.
In other words,
minus epsilon,
1 plus epsilon is the
same as 1 minus v squared,
and the power p,
which
is the same as 1 minus v squared over 2,
is equal to 1 half.
Square root of a quantity
is that quantity to the 1 half power,
and so this becomes 1 plus epsilon,
which is 1,
sorry 1 plus p epsilon,
which is 1 plus 1 half,
that's the p,
and then epsilon is minus
v squared,
minus v squared,
which is the same as
1 minus v squared over 2.
So we have 1
plus 1 half,
so that's a pretty damn
good approximation for small velocities,
in particular
for non-relativistic velocities,
so the square root of 1
minus v squared is just 1 minus
v squared over 2.
That's where a lot of
2's in classical physics come from,
if thought
about as the limit of relativistic physics,
most of the 2's,
and I'll show you some examples,
come from here.
I'll show you some examples as we go along.
The other example that we will need
will be 1 divided by the same thing.
This case is
the same as 1 minus v
squared to the power minus a half.
The only difference relative
to what we just did above
is that p is minus a half,
that has the effect of 2 minus 1 half,
so that's 1 plus v squared over 2.
So we're changing the sign here so that this becomes
1 plus v squared over 2.
Two signs have conspired to cancel each other.
The sign from the half
up in the exponent and the minus v squared
here give us 1 plus v squared over 2.
Alright,
so that is just by way of setting
up a little piece of calculation for the equation
of mathematics that we'll use in various situations.
Alright,
now we're going to be interested in particles.
Now a particle can be anything
that holds itself together.
It doesn't have to be an elementary particle.
It could be
the sun,
it could be a box of chocolate,
it could be a cookie,
no cookie.
It could be anything.
And when you think about the location of the particle,
you can see
that it is kind of like an egg.
So a particle can be anything.
It could be a donut.
If
you think about the position of an object,
it's generally the center of mass.
When we
talk about the mechanics of the motion of particles,
we're speaking really about the
mechanics of the center of mass of an object.
In the case of a donut,
the center of mass
is where there is nothing,
but that's okay,
we know where the center of mass is.
And motion,
according to the center of mass,
is governed,
for example,
by Newtonian mechanics of F equals mA.
Momentum is mass times velocity.
Does it matter whether it's an
elementary particle or a donut or cookie?
No.
Its momentum is its total mass times its velocity.
Its kinetic energy is one-half
mV squared in Newtonian physics.
That's the energy of motion.
Does it have any other energy if it's a donut?
Does a donut have any
other energy besides one-half mV squared?
Yeah,
calories,
exactly.
It has all the internal chemical energy and
that sort of stuff that's inside the donut.
That part of the energy does
not depend on its overall motion,
on its state of motion.
It's a constant.
It's a constant with respect to how fast.
The object is moving.
So you can say that the energy of a
moving donut is one-half mV squared plus the internal energy.
And the internal energy doesn't
depend on the state of motion.
Okay,
so those are just some reminders about classical mechanics.
Another reminder about classical mechanics is to
go back and read the classical mechanics book,
where you will find things
like the principle of least action,
which we will use.
We're going to use tonight.
Lagrangians,
canonical momenta,
and all that stuff.
And we're going to use them.
So very quickly,
review in your head now
the previous quarter of classical mechanics.
The important idea about the principle of least
action was the idea of a trajectory in space-time.
Not just a trajectory in space,
but a trajectory in space-time that if you plot,
position,
of a system,
it could stand,
x could stand for a one-dimensional coordinate,
it could stand for a three-dimensional coordinate.
In fact,
it could even stand for the
coordinates of a large number of particles.
And we can just call it space,
or coordinate space.
Vertically,
we plot time,
and the trajectory of a system between two
instants
is a curve that goes
from one point to the other.
And then it goes from one point to another curve.
And we can call it a world line.
If it's a particle,
if it's a single particle,
we call it a world line.
We call it the world line of the particle.
Now this concept is just as good a concept
in non-relativistic physics as it is in relativistic physics,
but it takes a certain primacy in relativity
because of the connection between space and time.
Space and time can morph
into each other by Lorentz transformation.
We tend to focus more on the space-time connection.
We tend to focus more on the idea of space-time.
The trajectory of a particle is time-like.
Now what do I mean by time-like?
Let's define the notion of time-like.
Begin with just two points.
Begin with any pair of points in space-time.
And think of the separation of the coordinates,
the difference between the coordinates of the two points.
The difference of the coordinates,
now I'm speaking about space and time coordinates,
we can call them delta t and delta x.
I discussed for a couple of times already the
notion of the invariant proper time between the two points.
And we wrote that as delta t squared.
Delta t squared minus delta x
squared is equal to delta tau squared.
Where delta tau itself,
the square root of this quantity,
is the proper time connecting those two points.
Now,
this quantity can be positive,
this quantity which I've written delta tau squared,
it can clearly be positive or negative.
It is positive if the,
the separation between these points
is such that the t interval
is larger than the spatial distance between them.
In other words,
if the interval
is like so,
if the spatial distance is less than the time distance,
in that case,
delta tau squared is positive,
and the interval between these
two points is called time-like.
It's got more time in it
than it's got space in it.
When an interval is time-like,
you can always find a Lorentz frame of reference.
You can always transform to a frame of reference
where the two points are at the same position,
where it hasn't moved.
In fact,
you simply go to the,
to the frame of reference
where this line is at rest.
There always exists such a,
such a frame of reference.
And so,
if two points in space-time
are time-like separated relative to each other,
you can always move in such a way
that they wind up being
at the same point in space,
that they haven't moved relative to each other.
Okay.
That's one case.
The other case
is where delta x
is bigger than delta t.
In that case,
the separation
has more space interval than time interval.
Looks like this,
let's say.
It's at less than 45 degrees
relative to the horizontal.
Incidentally,
I should say right now,
when I'm thinking about four-dimensional space-time,
three coordinates of space,
one coordinate of time,
what delta x stands for
is the three components
of the vector delta x,
and delta x squared means
the sums of the squares of those three components.
Delta x squared plus delta
y squared plus delta z squared.
Okay.
I suppose we could,
if we liked,
if we wanted to be fancy,
we would put a little arrow over here
to indicate that it's a three vector.
That delta x is a three vector.
All right.
Now,
if the three vector delta x
is bigger than delta t,
then the interval becomes space-like.
Space-like intervals are,
as I said,
are more space than they are time.
And in this case,
you cannot find a reference frame
in which the two points
are at the same position in space.
What you can do
is you can find a reference frame
in which they are at the same position.
They are at the same time.
You can always find,
so that means
that there's no invariant significance
to one end being later than the other.
You can always find a frame of reference
in which the two points
are at exactly the same time,
and even worse,
I've drawn this
so that point B,
let's call it B and A,
point B appears to be later than point A,
but there exists a reference frame,
this you can work out,
it's very easy to work out,
you can find a reference frame
in which point B is earlier than point A.
So there's no invariant significance
for points which are separated
by space-like interval,
there is no invariant significance
to which one occurred first,
one being later than the other,
or being simultaneous.
This is the relativity of simultaneity.
Okay.
Particles move,
move on time-like trajectories.
Everywhere's along the motion of a particle,
if we break the trajectory up
into little intervals,
every little piece of that trajectory
is time-like.
That's just a statement that particles can't,
nothing can move faster than the speed of light.
We've already seen how frustrating it can be
to try to get something to move faster
than the speed of light.
You try to compile up a whole bunch of velocities,
each of which
is nine-tenths the speed of light,
you know,
a stationary observer shoots out something
with nine-tenths the speed of light,
a moving thing shoots out something else
with velocity nine-tenths the speed of light,
something else shoots out a third thing
nine-tenths the speed of light,
you never get anywhere.
It's like Zeno's paradox,
you just get closer and
closer to the speed of light
without ever getting there.
And so it seems like a reasonable hypothesis
that nothing ever goes faster than the speed of light.
And that's a good thing,
because it would get very confusing
if we said a particle goes from A to B,
but we can't make sense
out of which one is earlier,
the starting point of the particle
or the end point of the particle,
we'd get us very confused,
we'd get into all sorts of
questions of time travel and so forth,
but the physical fact is nothing,
including a photon,
can move faster than the speed of light.
And I would,
I would generalize that and say that information,
information is carried by physical systems.
Signals,
signals that signal information from one place to another
can also not propagate faster than the speed of light.
We can take that as a postulate,
but if it were otherwise,
we'd get into some very paradoxical
and inconsistent situations.
All right,
so that's the notion of time-like and space-like,
the notion of the world line,
of a system,
and the world line of a system
is made up out of small time-like intervals.
Now let's focus on one of those time-like intervals.
Let's redraw it over here.
Here's one of the time-like intervals,
imagine in your head that it's a small interval,
because eventually we're going to let
that interval get smaller and smaller.
I don't think we talked about,
did we talk about relativistic four velocity?
We did.
We didn't do it.
We didn't do it in any detail.
All right,
so along the trajectory,
the particle moves from one point to another point
with a separation delta x,
but delta x is a four-dimensional delta x.
It consists of a delta t
and a delta of the three other coordinates,
which are of course called
delta with an arrow above them.
That's delta x mu.
Sometimes I will call these spatial delta x's,
sometimes we'll call them delta x i.
When you see an i,
it just runs over space.
When you see a mu,
it runs over all four coordinates of space.
This is an interval along the trajectory here,
has four components to it,
and it defines a delta tau,
between the two endpoints of the interval.
Delta tau is equal to the square root
of delta t squared minus delta x squared.
Incidentally,
just once or twice every so often,
let's put in the speed of
light just to remember where it goes,
t has units of time,
x has units of space.
To make this thing,
and since this is a,
this is called proper time,
let's assume that it has units of time.
This one's okay,
it has the same units as the left-hand side,
but this one is not okay,
it has units of length,
this one has units of time.
Where do we put the speed of light?
Divide by c squared.
Right.
I'll do it now and then,
every so often.
Do it once more over here.
And then stop doing it,
because it gets annoying.
Now we have the concept of velocity.
Now basic ordinary velocity is the
derivative of x with respect to t.
But there's a notion of four-dimensional velocity,
it is a four vector,
it transforms as a four vector.
Delta x mu transforms as a four vector.
Delta tau is an invariant,
it doesn't transform.
Every observer,
no matter how they're moving,
ascribes the same delta tau,
but different delta x mus to this interval.
The velocity,
ordinary velocity,
let's call it v with a vector here,
the ordinary velocity is,
its components are simply
the xi by dt,
or the limits.
And the limit that the delta x's get small,
is the delta t.
It just becomes the limit of
delta xi divided by delta t.
That's a three-dimensional notion of velocity.
And of course,
this also has,
this should be written this way.
Or,
vi is equal to dxi by dt.
Alright,
that's one notion of velocity.
A more invariant relativistic notion of velocity,
is instead of using t down here,
refer the separation of coordinates to the proper time,
instead of the coordinate,
instead of the frame-dependent ordinary time.
That gives rise to something called four velocity.
It doesn't have three components,
it has four components.
So it has a mu up here,
the mu stands for the four components.
Incidentally,
mu runs from zero to three.
Zero is the time component.
This is equal to dx mu by,
not d tau,
not dt,
but d tau.
So there are four of them,
and they constitute what is called the four velocity.
The four-dimensional analog of the velocity.
First question is,
what is the connection between the
four velocity and the ordinary velocity?
So let's work that out.
Non-relativistically,
of course,
there are only three components of the velocity,
so that must mean something funny
happens to one of the components here,
and we'll see what happens.
Alright,
let's start with dx sub i by dt.
Let's start with v sub i,
that's equal to dx i by dt,
but let's write it as dx i by d tau,
d tau divided by dt.
That's a triviality,
I've just divided and multiplied by d tau,
but it's useful.
Sorry,
yes,
this is correct.
Alright,
now dx i by d tau,
what is that?
u sub i.
u sub i,
where i now,
in particular,
concentrating on the space components of u,
times dt by d tau,
d tau by dt.
We'll come back to d
tau by dt in a moment,
in fact we're going to
come back to it right now,
but let's consider the...
yeah.
Before we go ahead,
let's consider exactly this quantity,
u naught.
What is u naught?
u naught is the fourth
component of this relativistic velocity,
and what it is,
is it's dt by d tau.
That's exactly what it is.
dt by d tau.
The fourth component,
or the zeroth component,
I should say,
of x is just t,
where is it?
t.
And u naught is just dt by d tau.
d tau by dt is just the inverse of this.
Alright?
So,
we're interested in figuring out
what d tau by dt is.
Let's figure out what d tau by dt is.
d tau is the square root of one...
nope,
it's the square root of dt squared minus dx squared.
That's just rewriting this thing here,
but with differential notation.
dt squared by...
times dx squared,
and this means all three components,
the sums of the squares of all three components.
Let's take out of the square root dt.
Let's take it outside the square root of t,
and let's factor it off this stuff,
and then we get in here
one minus dx squared by dt squared.
Or,
just dt times the square
root of one minus v squared.
So,
what do we know?
We know that d tau by dt is equal
to the square root of one minus v squared.
That's what this one minus v squared is,
or the square root of one minus v squared.
It's the rate of change of
proper time relative to ordinary time.
If v is close...
If v is small by
comparison with the speed of light,
if it's close to zero,
then this is close to one.
In other words,
in a non-relativistic limit,
dt by d tau is just one.
There's no difference between tau and t.
If the object is moving with
close to the speed of light,
there can be a large difference.
All right,
let's see,
where were we?
I,
uh...
Ah.
All right,
so what we want from
here is this equation over here.
I've crowded too many equations together.
I was working on this.
Here's where I was working.
All right,
so first,
I'm making a little bit
of a mess out of this.
A mess of the blackboard,
in any case.
All right,
first of all,
this is equal to dt by d tau.
What is dt by d tau?
d tau by dt is the
square root of one minus v squared.
What is dt by d tau?
One over that,
right?
So u-naught,
whatever it is,
is one divided by the square
root of one minus v squared.
It's a thing which non-relativistically just goes to one.
In the non-relativistic limit,
where v is much smaller than the speed of light,
this is just one.
That's why we never think about it.
We never think about dt by d tau,
because tau is t,
and d tau by dt is just one.
Good,
all right.
On the other hand,
relativistically we worry about it.
What about here?
v sub i is u
sub i d tau by dt.
But d tau by dt is again just...
Which way is it?
The tau by dt is the
square root of one minus v squared.
Divided by?
Let's see.
Yeah.
v sub i is dx d tau d tau dt.
Looks like it's multiplied.
Why does that surprise me?
No,
it doesn't surprise me.
That's correct.
So now we can assemble together
what is the meaning of the four velocity
in terms of the normal velocity.
First of all,
u-naught,
the time component of the four velocity,
is just one over the square
root of one minus v squared.
What about the space component?
u sub i,
that we read off from here,
that's equal to v sub i
divided by that same square
root of one minus v squared.
So this is the basic computation you would do
to find the components of four velocity.
Again,
if we're talking about the non-relativistic limit
where v is very close to zero,
then the square root is trivial,
and u sub i and v sub i,
the two notions of velocity are the same.
As you get up closer and
closer to the speed of light,
it looks like u sub i
is much bigger than v sub i.
Is that right?
Yeah.
u sub i is much bigger than v sub i.
Or v sub i is
much smaller than u sub i.
Okay,
this is the notion of four velocity.
This is the notion of four velocity.
And everywhere along the trajectory of a particle,
the particle is characterized by a position.
You can add in the
time at which you're characterizing it.
So that's a four vector of position
and also a four vector of velocity.
Now,
the four vector of velocity,
doesn't really have four independent components.
It only has three independent components.
Let's go through why that's true.
Let's take the...
Okay,
I'll explain very quickly why
it doesn't have four independent components.
There is a relationship between
the three components of spatial velocity
of u sub i and u sub 0.
And it's just a relationship that u sub i,
let's call it u squared,
which happens to be v squared over square root of...
v squared over 1 minus v squared.
That's the space component squared,
is v squared,
divided by 1 minus v squared.
If I...
It seems like you can just see
it from the definition of u sub 0.
Yes,
we can.
we can,
but I'm halfway through it,
so let's finish it.
Let's take u sub 0 squared minus this thing here.
All right,
so that gives us a minus sign here,
plus 1 over square root of 1 minus v squared.
I'm making this more complicated than it is.
The answer is that the right hand...
Not square root,
just 1 minus v squared.
Oh boy.
What's the right hand side?
1 minus v squared over 1 minus v squared.
So all four velocities,
no matter how fast the
particle is moving or not moving,
the square of the...
The square,
or the difference of the squares of components,
time component and space component,
is always equal to 1.
All right?
It's always equal to 1,
and that's why there are not four independent components
of the four velocity.
Only three independent components of the four velocity.
They're related by a single relationship like this.
Otherwise,
they're independent.
Could you also say that...
Can you conceptualize it by saying
that it's because you're differentiating with respect
to one of the components?
Say it again?
Can you also...
Can you alternatively conceptualize it independently
by saying that it's because you're differentiating
with respect to one of the components?
Yeah.
Yeah,
sure.
Yeah.
There's an easier way to...
I said this badly.
Let's go through a very simple version of it.
All right.
Delta tau squared
is equal to delta t squared minus delta x squared.
Okay?
Boy,
did I make a mess over there.
Let's just divide both sides
of this by delta tau squared.
We get 1 is equal to delta t squared
over delta tau squared
minus delta x squared
over delta tau squared.
Delta tau...
Delta t by delta tau,
that's u-naught.
So the first term here is just u-naught squared,
and the other one is u-vector squared.
Okay?
So that's all that went on here.
A complicated way to say this.
All right.
But let's go back now to the world line.
Here's a world line.
It's characterized by a 4-velocity and a 4-vector,
only one redundancy,
and that's that the four components of u
are not completely independent.
We want to know...
Okay.
Now,
what law governs the motion...
Let's take a free particle,
one with no forces on it.
What law governs its motion?
And the law that we're going to abstract
from a quarter's worth of classical mechanics
is the principle of least action.
All right?
The principle of least action...
The only thing new is that
the action is going to have...
We want our laws of physics
to be the same in every reference frame.
That means we should try to cast them
in terms of quantities which are the same
in every reference frame.
If we have a principle that says
that in going from here to here,
the particle goes along a trajectory
which minimizes or maximizes...
minimizes some quantity called the action,
we are doing good business
if we make sure that that action doesn't depend
on which frame of reference it's evaluated in.
We would like the action to be something
which is the same in every reference frame.
We know of only one...
That's one fact.
The action should be invariant.
And the other thing that we've learned from experience
is the action should be built up incrementally
as a sum over the trajectory
of little infinitesimal numbers.
So that's the idea of the integral.
of the number of infinitesimal pieces
for each segment of the trajectory.
That we can abstract from classical mechanics.
Action being a sum or an integral,
better yet,
an integral over the trajectory,
and the thing of which it is an integral
should be a quantity which is the same
in every reference frame.
There's really only one thing
that is invariant
in going from a small...
from a position to a displaced position.
And it is the proper time along the trajectory.
The proper time from here to here
is an invariant,
meaning to say
that all observers,
no matter what velocity
they're moving with,
will not agree on the delta x's,
but they will agree on the delta tau.
So,
a good guess,
and it's the right guess,
the right guess for the action
is the sum,
we'll convert that to an integral in a moment,
of all the little delta taus
from one end of the trajectory
to another end of the trajectory.
All the delta taus,
that is the action.
Not quite,
not quite.
And that action has to be minimized
holding the end points fixed,
remember your classical mechanics,
the action principle,
you hold the initial and the final configuration fixed,
and you search for the trajectory
that minimizes or makes stationary
the action between the two end points of the trajectory.
So you wiggle around the path
until you find the path,
the path of least action.
Since the action is composed out of invariance,
everybody will agree
that a given path minimizes the action.
So that's our principle.
Add them up.
So what does that mean?
That means
we have a freedom,
incidentally.
We have a freedom,
we could multiply the action by a number,
any number,
it won't make any difference,
why not?
Because if a thing is stationary
with respect to changes of the trajectory,
if I multiply it by
10 or 7 or minus 15,
it will still be stationary.
Of course if I multiply it by a negative number,
I will turn a maximum to a minimum,
but I won't change the fact
that that trajectory makes the action stationary.
Yeah?
What happens to energy?
Why are you getting ahead of yourself?
Because you're not ahead of the game.
We start with action.
Energy we derive.
We will do that.
Before the evening is over,
we will discuss why we didn't start with energy.
But the answer is it's not invariant.
It's not even invariant in ordinary Newtonian physics.
The energy of a particle is not independent
of its state of motion.
So if you see a particle standing still,
and I see the particle moving,
we ascribe a different kinetic energy to it.
So it's not an invariant concept.
It's a good idea to start our discussion
of particle motion by talking about invariants
that everybody agrees upon,
and in that way make
sure that our laws of physics
are the same in every reference frame.
Okay,
so,
yeah?
Could you state again why a relativistic invariant
is a good choice for action
or a good guess for action?
It's a good guess simply because
it's the same for every observer,
no matter how they're moving.
That's what proper time was.
Proper time was the particular combination
of delta x's and delta t's between two points
that everybody will agree on the value of it.
It's the thing which is invariant
on the Lorentz transformations.
If we want our laws of physics to be invariant,
it would be a good idea to base them
on quantities which all observers
have the same value for.
So,
for example,
if I just say,
you know,
it's analogous to the following.
This is entirely analogous to the following idea.
Supposing I am interested in the shortest distance
between two points on the blackboard.
What do I do?
If I'm interested in the shortest distance
between two points,
obviously I search
for the shortest distance.
I search for the curve which has the shortest distance.
Now,
might we find that we get different answers
in different coordinate systems?
That coordinate system or that coordinate system
or whatever?
No,
of course we won't.
And the reason is distance in the Euclidean plane
is invariant with respect to rotations of coordinates.
In particular,
if we think of the distance
from one point to another along the curve
to be a sum of a lot of little integers,
and everybody agrees on the incremental distances,
then the curve that we get will not depend
on the coordinate system that we use to evaluate it.
Why?
It's an invariant concept.
The shortest distance between two points.
What we do then is we add
up all the little Euclidean distances here,
and we're doing exactly the same kind of thing,
adding up all the little proper times along the trajectory.
In fact,
the formulas are almost identical
apart from the science.
All right,
now,
we have a freedom.
We could multiply this action by a number.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
You may have said this,
but I don't remember it.
We arrive at proper time at being
delta p squared minus delta x squared.
Square root of that.
Square.
Yeah.
Was there a reason,
is there a reason
why you inherently choose a positive square root
as opposed to a negative square root?
Well,
we will always choose the positive square root,
yeah.
Yeah,
proper time is by its very definition
a positive quantity.
It's the time read along the clock
from the past to the future.
And we could use the negative root.
If we used the negative root everywhere,
it would simply change the sign of the action.
That's okay.
What would happen if you
change the sign of the action?
It would not change the equations of motion at all.
Instead of saying we were looking
for the minimum of the action,
we might say we were looking
for the maximum of the action.
But remember,
to minimize a function
or to maximize it,
exactly the same equation,
you just say it's stationary.
So it doesn't matter whether you take the action
and multiply it by a number,
including the possibility of a negative number.
It won't change the trajectories
if the rule is the
trajectories should make stationary the action.
Stationary means it could be a minimum or a maximum.
I guess also if you had a coordinate system
in which the x-coordinate didn't change,
then if you chose the positive square root,
then the proper time is the same as the time.
Yes.
Yes,
that's true.
That is true.
All right,
and I'm going to put in one more little sign,
one more little change.
I'm going to put a minus sign in here.
Now,
as I said,
multiplying by minus m changes nothing.
It's a convention.
It's a complete convention.
But the convention was established not by Einstein
when he was doing relativistic mechanics,
but long before Einstein by people who had no idea
what the special theory of relativity was,
but who had some prejudices about
the way classical Newtonian mechanics work.
So we're going to come back.
This minus m is there.
We'll come back.
It's for the purpose
of matching onto nonrelativistic formulas.
It would not change anything
if we didn't put it there,
but in order to match with nonrelativistic formulas,
we'll put a minus m there for the time being.
Okay,
so let's take that to be the action.
And now what we do is we put the interval,
the trajectories have already been imagined
to be broken up into intervals.
And now we move the
points around in space and time
and look for the trajectory which minimizes,
or I'll say minimize,
which minimizes the action,
and that will be the true trajectory.
That's the principle of released action.
But before we do that,
let's convert this to an integral.
Let's convert this by taking
the limit in which the differential,
in which these finite differences
here are replaced by differentials.
So this will become then minus m times
the integral of d tau along the trajectory.
The integral,
and I'll explain exactly what this means in a moment,
the integral of sum of little infinitesimal
d taus from one place to another.
There's a reason why the integral
is written by this curly symbol here.
You know what the curly symbol means?
Sum.
Right?
And delta tau just becomes d tau from
one end of the trajectory to the other,
from the initial end to the other end.
And now we can write down a formula
d tau is equal to the square root
of one minus,
no,
dt squared minus dx squared.
And dx squared means dx squared
plus dy squared plus dz squared.
Now this is a funny thing,
an integral with a d tau underneath
a thing in a square root there.
I bet you've never seen an integral like that.
Maybe you have,
where the differential things
are underneath the square root.
But it's easy to fix.
It's easy to make it look more standard.
Factor out a dt.
Factor out a dt and
put the dt on the outside.
That means under the square root
we have to divide by dt squared.
And this just becomes one.
And what about dx by dt?
That's the good old fashioned velocity squared.
So this becomes one minus velocity
squared or one minus xi dot squared.
xi dot squared means x dot squared
plus y dot squared plus z dot squared.
All right.
I won't bother writing the sum.
And I won't bother writing x,
y,
and z.
It's just x sub i dot.
And dot now means derivative with respect to ordinary time.
Derivative with respect to ordinary time.
So by factoring out a dt,
I converted this to something more
recognizable than it might have been before.
It's an integral of something that depends on the velocity.
Remember about the ordinary principle of least action.
And the ordinary principle of least action for an element,
for a particle,
for example,
the action is an integral over a quantity called what?
The Lagrangian.
And the Lagrangian depends on what?
Positions and velocities.
What about for the case where there are no forces?
Then it only depends on the velocity,
not the positions.
And here's what we got.
We have something like that here.
We have that the action is minus m times
the integral of 1 minus the square of the velocity
from the initial starting point,
let's call it a to b.
So we have a Lagrangian now.
And now we can just take off and do
all the things that we would do with a Lagrangian.
Let's write what the Lagrangian is.
The Lagrangian is minus m.
Which I say is a convention.
Minus m over here.
Times the square root of 1 minus,
now I'll write it,
x dot squared plus y
dot squared plus z dot squared.
It's not as simple as the
usual Lagrangian that Lagrange first wrote down.
The Lagrangian that Lagrange,
what did Lagrange write down?
He just wrote down for the Lagrangian the kinetic energy.
He didn't even know,
I don't even know if he knew it was energy.
He wrote down for the Lagrangian
just one half m x dot squared.
That's nice and simple.
Lagrangian of Lagrange.
L sub L.
That was just m x dot squared over 2.
One half m v squared.
Where x dot squared does mean x dot
squared plus y dot squared plus z dot squared.
This is the Lagrangian Lagrange would have written down.
This is the Lagrangian that a relativistic
version of Lagrange would have written down.
What's the connection between them?
Well,
the first connection between them and the
most important for our purposes right now.
Oh,
before I say that.
What is the value of this Lagrangian?
The value of this Lagrangian is that it encapsulates
the motion of a free particle
in a way that is independent
or that is the same for every reference frame.
It is guaranteed because this quantity of
the action is independent of reference frame,
making it stationary,
you'll get the same answer in every frame.
So this is the translation of that to Lagrangian language.
Okay.
First let's ask what this is approximately like.
Not approximately.
But what it's like in the limit
where the velocities are much smaller than one.
One being the speed of light.
So this is one minus m
square root of one minus v squared.
Velocity squared.
To that we go back to the good old
binomial theorem.
The binomial theorem tells us that the
square root of one minus v squared
is approximately equal to minus m
times one plus v squared over two.
So first of all,
there is a contribution which is just minus m.
It doesn't depend on anything.
It doesn't depend on position.
It doesn't depend on velocity.
It's just a number.
What does adding a number to the Lagrangian do?
It does nothing.
Adding a number to a Lagrangian does nothing.
Because the trajectory,
the action of the trajectory,
you know,
comparing different trajectories,
the constant piece here doesn't depend on the trajectory,
it doesn't depend on the x,
it doesn't depend on the velocity.
It plays no role at all.
So it's not important to us.
The important piece,
oh,
do I have something?
I'm sorry.
Minus,
right?
One minus v squared over two.
All right.
So apart from the constant piece,
the piece with the juice in it,
the piece with juice in it
is plus mv squared over two.
Minus m plus mv squared over two.
In other words,
it's just the Lagrangian of Lagrange.
In this way,
we can be certain that the laws
of motion that we derive in this way
will,
in the limit of small velocity,
be the same as good old Laplace,
Lagrangian,
Newton,
and so forth.
So far,
we haven't put in anything that resembles
a potential energy or a force law.
So far,
we're simply working with a free particle.
Okay.
So that's a good thing.
Now,
next concept.
I'm not going to work out the equations of motion.
I will tell you,
right now,
the equations of motion
have the brilliant,
the ability to simply make this particle
move on a straight line with constant velocity.
We'll see that.
But the equations of motion are not
the interesting things for this evening's lecture.
The interesting thing is to identify
the notions of momentum and energy.
That's where we want to go.
We want to understand where the relativistic
formulas for momentum and energy come from.
They're not quite the same as the non-relativistic formulas.
So let's go through them.
Momentum and energy
are important because they're conserved.
If we account for all the particles in the universe,
or at least all the particles in a closed system,
they may be interacting with forces and this and that,
but the net momentum is conserved,
what was that a consequence of?
Do you remember what that's a consequence of?
Translation invariance.
So translation invariance,
and translation invariance is true here.
We're actually in a special case of Lagrangian mechanics.
Everything we said about Lagrangian mechanics,
Lagrangians,
Hamiltonians,
conservation laws,
it all applies here.
It's just that the Lagrangian is a little bit strange.
It has a square root
of 1-x.square plus y.square plus z.square.
But other than that,
the rules of the game are the rules of Lagrangian,
Hamiltonian,
whatever we derived previously,
and we can use it.
All right,
so the first question then is
what is the meaning of momentum?
It will be conserved.
It will be conserved because
this Lagrangian is translation invariant.
It only depends on the velocities.
It does not depend on position.
It's translation invariant.
The momentum will be conserved.
There's a consequence of everything
we learned the first quarter.
Okay,
so I would like to identify,
for example,
p sub x,
the x component of momentum.
So we go back.
We open up our book on classical mechanics,
and we go back to the definition of momentum,
not the definition which began by
saying momentum is equal to mv,
but the definition which came
from the Lagrangian point of view,
and that was,
anybody remember the definition of momentum?
In terms of the Lagrangian?
Everybody have it at their fingertips?
It was partially L,
partially Q dot.
Yeah.
The derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to the component of velocity.
Derivative of Lagrangian with respect to x dot.
Hmm?
I won't bother redoing classical mechanics
in front of your eyes here.
It's a little bit too late for that.
At this point,
the thing to do between now
and next week is to review this.
I should have told you last week.
P sub x is partial of
L with respect to x dot.
Same thing for p sub y,
p sub z,
and so forth.
So let's apply that.
Lagrangian is minus m times the
square root of this thing here.
All right,
so this is going to be,
first of all is a minus m.
Then there's a derivative of this
square root with respect to x dot.
All right,
what do you get when you
take the derivative of a square root?
You get one over a square root.
One over a square root
of everything inside the square root,
which happens to be one minus v squared.
Yes,
there's a half.
Thank you.
There's a half there.
Now we have to take the derivative of the
thing inside the square root with respect to x dot.
All right,
that's going to give us a minus from here.
So there's another minus sign,
plus,
and then the derivative of this
thing with respect to x dot,
which is twice x dot.
So that will eat up the two in the denominator,
and it will put an x dot here.
Or mv sub x divided by the square
root of one minus the total velocity squared.
Well,
we've seen this before,
have we not?
Right here.
v sub i,
in this case v sub x,
divided by the square root of one minus v squared,
is just u sub x.
So what do we get?
We get p sub x.
Here it is,
p sub x.
It's nothing but the mass,
not times the ordinary velocity,
but by the ordinary velocity divided by
the square root of one minus v squared,
which is u sub x.
The relativistic four velocity times the mass
is equal to the x component of momentum.
Likewise,
for the y component,
and so forth and so on,
the y component,
p sub y,
is equal to m u sub y,
and likewise for z.
m is less mass.
m will...
m is the rest mass.
m is mass.
Okay,
let's talk about a convention.
The use of the term mass,
rest mass,
and all that stuff.
There's an old convention and a new convention.
The new convention is older than I am.
More or less.
Nobody that I know who does physics,
uses the term rest mass anymore.
Rest mass is an anachronism.
That's the word,
anachronism.
In other words,
right.
It's an anachronism.
The only place where it's ever used
is in undergraduate textbooks.
Undergraduate textbooks cannot seem to
get their head around the idea
that the mass of a particle
is a tag that goes with a particle
which characterizes the particle
and not the motion of the particle.
The mass of an electron,
if you look up mass of an electron,
you won't get something that's different
if the electron is moving or stationary.
You will simply get whatever it happens to be.
I don't remember the mass of the electron in kilograms,
but it's some small number.
So the way that mass is used in modern language
is it's a number that goes with the particle,
but it is exactly what used
to be called the rest mass.
What used to be called the rest mass
is now just called mass.
What used to be called mass is what?
Energy.
Energy divided by the speed of light squared or something.
We use the term energy for the thing,
which characterizes the moving object,
and the energy at rest we just call the mass.
Now,
there's the speed of light factor,
that's just a conversion factor,
and we'll come to it.
All right,
so when we talk about the mass of a particle,
we mean what used to be called the rest mass.
From now on,
I will never use the term rest mass.
I will always use the term mass meaning
the energy at rest.
Okay.
Good.
That was an important distinction.
I normally don't even think in that way.
I'm not in the language of rest mass,
so I didn't mention it,
but it was good that Warren brought it up
so that we don't get confused.
Okay.
Now,
let's talk for a moment about four vectors.
Four vectors are the things
like delta x and delta t.
Supposing I have a four vector.
In this case,
it would simply represent a little interval.
That's the four vector of displacement,
I guess you would call it.
Four vector of displacement that has
a delta t and a delta x.
Now,
supposing I told you that delta x,
as opposed to delta t,
that delta x was equal to zero,
could that be an invariant characterization
of this interval?
What happens to delta x when you Lorentz transform?
It changes,
right?
In particular,
it will pick up a little bit of delta t.
So it cannot be an invariant description of this vector.
A vector with delta x equals
zero would be a vertical vector.
But in some other frame
of reference that we're moving to,
if you were moving past the stationary axis,
the same vector would be tilted.
In other words,
if you were moving past it,
the beginning and the end point
would be separated by some delta x.
So the statement that delta x is equal to zero,
that might have some significance
to a particular frame of reference,
but it can't possibly be an invariant distinction.
What about the statement that delta x and delta t
are both equal to zero,
or all four of them,
not just delta x and delta t,
but delta y and delta z?
Is that an invariant statement?
All components of this vector are equal to zero,
of this four-dimensional vector are equal to zero.
Well,
if you think about the way things transform,
a delta x,
when it transforms,
will pick up a little bit of delta t.
Delta t will pick up
a little bit of delta x.
But if delta x is equal to zero,
and delta t and delta x
is zero in one reference frame,
then it will be zero in every reference frame.
So saying that a vector,
a four vector in particular,
is zero,
the whole thing,
all components of it,
that's an invariant statement.
To say some specific component,
or even a specific subset of components,
less than all of them,
is equal to zero,
that is not an invariant statement.
The same is true of the four velocity.
The four velocity,
here are its components.
Is it an invariant statement to say
that u sub i is equal to zero?
i meaning just the space components.
No,
it isn't,
because if you,
what it means to say that
u sub i is equal to zero
is just that you're in a frame of reference,
where the particle happens to be stationary.
Change frame of reference,
u sub i will not be zero.
Okay?
So in general,
if you want to express invariant statements,
you want those statements to be
about all components of a four vector.
A four vector means a
thing like delta x or u.
You want it to be a statement
which is true for all the components.
You want it to be a full-fledged vector statement.
Full-fledged four vector statement.
Okay,
let's come to the concept of momentum conservation.
Momentum conservation.
We so far identified three components of momentum.
Only three components.
Those three components of momentum
happen to be proportional
to the components of four velocity.
They happen to become proportional
But that's incidental for a moment.
The important thing is that momentum is conserved.
If I have a collection of
particles and we add them all up,
the initial momentum must be equal to the final momentum.
Now that's a vector statement.
That's a vector statement that,
the three components of momentum,
and let's label them this way,
initial must equal,
the total initial momentum must
equal the total final momentum.
Or we can subtract and just write,
the law of momentum conservation says
that this is equal to zero.
Initial momentum minus final momentum.
This is equal to zero.
This in itself is a vector equation.
Is it an invariant vector equation?
If it's true in one frame,
is it necessarily true in another frame?
Not unless we can make an
equivalent assertion about some fourth component.
If there is a fourth component that
turns the momentum into a four vector,
and then we say all four components are conserved,
then it becomes an invariant statement.
Then it becomes an invariant.
It's only an invariant statement if
we can identify a fourth component
and say that the fourth component is also conserved.
A fourth component such that the
three components together with the fourth component
add up to a four vector.
Well,
it's pretty darn clear what the fourth
component of this thing has to be.
What must the fourth component be?
It must be m times u zero.
We have three components.
If we didn't have the m there,
we would have three components of the four velocity,
and the fourth component of the fourth velocity would just
be the thing which fills out the full four vector.
So,
question.
Is there a significance?
To m u sub naught,
whatever it is,
we can give it a name.
We can call it p sub naught.
We can give it a name.
Is there a significance to it,
and is it something that we already
recognize as something which ought to be conserved?
And of course the answer is yes.
There is a fourth thing
which is conserved for particle mechanics.
It's energy.
So it's natural to ask the question,
is this the energy?
Is this fourth component,
the fourth momentum,
nothing but the energy of the particle?
Well,
how do we decide that?
How do we decide what the energy is?
Anybody got a clue about how
to decide what the energy is?
Ah,
look at the Hamiltonian.
Right.
And that's the only way.
That's the only systematic procedure.
Look at the Hamiltonian.
So,
the next step is to figure out the Hamiltonian.
We're going to erase some of the blackboard here
and go to the Hamiltonian.
In a sense,
from the point of view of relativity,
all the work that we did in the same quarter
was just to set ourselves
up for this kind of problem.
So let's go to the Hamiltonian.
I know that not all of us remember
what the Hamiltonian is,
so I will remind you.
The Hamiltonian is given in terms of the Lagrangian.
Again,
I don't expect you to remember it,
but I do expect you to
be able to look it up
and remind yourself where it came from,
why this was an important quantity.
It's a conserved quantity.
It's an important quantity.
I will write it down for you.
It's the sum of all the coordinates,
sum of all the coordinates of a system,
of the velocity associated with that coordinate.
I sometimes put the indices upstairs
and sometimes I put them downstairs.
Pay no attention to where
I put them at the moment.
And what does it multiply?
Remember?
The momentum associated with that same direction.
I'll put that one upstairs just for variety.
And then,
but that's not finished.
What else is there?
Minus?
Minus the Lagrangian.
That's the Hamiltonian.
As I said,
if you want a systematic way
to think about mechanics,
so we don't just make
up stuff as we go along,
we fall back on the basic principles of mechanics
all our Lagrange,
Hamilton,
and so forth.
Okay,
so now we can write it down.
I don't know what it is.
Let me write the Lagrangian over here.
And the P is,
what is P sub i?
P sub i is equal
to m x sub i dot
divided by square root of 1 minus v squared.
That is the same as m u sub i,
but I'm not going to use it that way.
I'm just going to use
it the way it is here.
P sub i is that.
And the Lagrangian is minus m u sub i.
So that's m square root of 1 minus v squared,
where that means v x squared plus v y squared
plus v c squared.
That's the Lagrangian.
We have everything we need now to calculate
the Hamiltonian or what is essentially the energy.
Okay,
so we have then summation over i
x sub i dot times P sub i,
that's m x sub i dot squared
over I think square root of 1 minus v squared.
Is that right?
That's the first term here.
The x sub i dot squared picks
up 1 x sub i dot from here,
1 x sub i dot from here.
The mass is over here.
And now minus the Lagrangian.
So minus the Lagrangian is plus m
square root of 1 minus v squared.
Looks like a bit of a mess,
but it is not.
It's just simple.
First of all,
x sub i dot squared.
That's just the total velocity squared.
x dot squared plus y
dot squared plus z dot squared.
That's what I call v squared.
So the first term here is
just not even a sum anymore.
It's just m v squared over
square root of 1 minus v squared.
Then we have to add plus m
times the square root in the numerator.
How are we going to add
a thing with a square root
in the denominator?
Well,
we'll put everything in the denominator.
So we have to multiply and divide
by square root of 1 minus v squared.
That gives us in the numerator 1 minus v squared
and then square root of 1
minus v squared in the denominator.
There we are.
Now it doesn't look so fearsome anymore
because we notice immediately that m v squared over here
cancels m v squared over here.
And the whole thing is m squared over here.
And that's the Hamiltonian.
So that's the Hamiltonian.
So let's add to the momentum a fourth component here,
which,
sorry,
p naught,
which is m.
And do you recognize what the momentum is?
Do you know what this thing is?
This is u naught.
So indeed we find that apart from a possible,
yeah?
When you wrote down the Hamiltonian,
that was the classical .
No.
No,
no,
no.
This formula for the Hamiltonian is extremely general.
All systems that we've ever studied,
this is the formula.
That was the general formula for any Lagrangian,
any action principle.
We derived this,
the conservation of H,
in very,
very general grounds.
Depending on what you put in for the Lagrangian,
it might be non-relativistic physics,
it could be any number of things.
Good.
All right,
so now we're in business.
The conservation of momentum becomes
the conservation of four momentum.
Conservation of x momentum,
y momentum,
z momentum,
and the conservation of energy.
Before we go on,
we should figure out what this new concept of energy
has to do with the old concept of energy.
How different is it than
the energy that we've already established?
Okay.
So let's...
The one thing that we're going
to have to be careful about
is the factors of speed of light.
They are conventions,
largely.
They're conventions.
If the energy defined in one way is conserved,
it won't make any difference to its conservation
if we,
in order to make it match with units,
if we multiply it by
the speed of light or something.
Conservation is conservation.
And we will probably have to do that.
Okay,
let's look at mu naught.
That is m over the square
root of 1 minus v squared.
That's what we're calling the energy of the particle.
Now,
of course,
if we want to restore some...
Well,
before we restore...
Yeah,
before we restore units,
let's use the...
Binomial theorem.
Let's use the binomial theorem to approximate this.
Here it is.
Here's the binomial theorem for 1 divided by
the square root of 1 minus v squared.
And it gives us 1 plus v squared over 2.
All right,
so this becomes...
m plus mv squared over 2.
This,
of course,
is completely recognizable.
It is just the ordinary Newtonian kinetic energy.
Had Newton known about energy,
this would have been what he
would have written down for kinetic energy.
It is what kinetic wrote down.
I have no idea who
first thought of this as energy,
but somebody did.
What about this term over here?
Well,
first of all,
this equation is not dimensionally consistent.
Not dimensionally consistent.
Here we have m,
and here we have an m times the velocity squared.
To make it dimensionally consistent,
all we have to do...
We can do it in a number of ways,
all right,
to make it dimensionally consistent,
but to give it units of energy,
we're thinking that it's the energy,
to give it units of energy,
this already has units of energy.
It's just a good old kinetic energy.
In order to give this term units of energy,
we have to multiply it by
some power of the speed of light.
What power of the speed of light?
Well,
we already know.
This thing is missing two powers
of a velocity compared to this one.
So what's it going to be?
It's going to be mc squared.
All right,
I won't...
I will just write that this is the energy.
So here we see,
coming out of the basic principles of mechanics,
the conservation of a quantity
which when it's evaluated for a
system at rest is just mc squared.
For a system at rest,
its energy is related to its inertial mass,
to its mass by mc squared.
How do we know that this is the inertial mass?
Well,
it's the inertial mass because it enters into the energy
the same old way that inertial
mass entered into the old energy.
It enters into momentum,
at least for slow velocities,
in the same way that the inertial mass
entered in here.
And so this must be
the inertial mass times c squared.
That is...
That's the origin of...
Einstein had another way to think about it.
He asked himself in a
collision of objects of various kinds,
given...
He worked a little bit differently.
He didn't know about Noether's theorem.
He had to work from the ground up,
so to speak.
He talked about collisions of objects,
objects come together,
break up and scatter and go flying off.
And he said,
look,
I know that the momentum is conserved.
What do I have to think of as the energy
in order that the energy and momentum together
would form a complex that would be conserved
in any frame of reference?
We've short-circuited that
and found the formula for the energy
by standard methods.
Okay,
so that's the origin of E equals m c squared.
It doesn't apply only to a particle.
It applies to any object
that can be identified as a closed object
that its energy,
when the object is at rest.
Now what does the object being at rest mean?
Inside here,
there are lots of molecules
moving around like crazy.
So in that sense,
this object is not at rest.
On the other hand,
its center of mass is at rest,
but what we mean by the velocity here
is the velocity of the center of mass.
And what's left over when you set
the center of mass velocity to zero
is the rest energy.
The rest energy is related to the mass
by a factor of speed of light.
Another way to say that
is that the speed of light
is just a conversion factor
from one way of defining energy to another.
It's just a conversion factor.
So,
you want to make the dimension consistent,
so you multiply by c squared.
You could have multiplied by c squared over 10 megabit,
or a lot of different things.
No,
no,
no.
It has to reduce to this when c is one.
Right.
Good point.
That's right.
On purely dimensional grounds,
we never could have deduced
that this would be one here.
But,
on the ground,
on two grounds,
that it has to reduce to this
when c is equal to one,
we say there's only one
thing we could do with it.
So that one in the binomial expansion is important?
Oh,
yes.
Absolutely.
There are higher order terms missing,
right?
Yes,
there are higher order terms,
and they are simply very,
very small
when the velocity is...
Well,
I mean,
for some purposes,
we might care about them,
but the leading piece for slow...
You know,
we could evaluate them,
and we could see how small they are
for a baseball moving at 90 miles an hour,
and believe me,
they would be really,
really small.
What's the right physical way to
think of those higher order terms?
Corrections to the kinetic energy?
Yeah,
well,
they're corrections to everything.
Everything gets corrections.
Those corrections are quite significant
when the object is moving
close to the speed of light.
In fact,
I mean,
they become huge.
Let's just think about it for a minute.
If I were to plug
in the speed of light here,
well,
this would get pretty darn big,
but it wouldn't get any bigger than this.
It's perfectly finite.
On the other hand,
if I plug it into this formula,
v goes to 1,
the kinetic energy of an object
moving close to the speed of light
becomes infinite.
That's another way to see
that you can never get up,
because it would take an infinite energy
to get up to the speed of light.
Also,
an infinite momentum.
These u's also are v's divided by
square root of 1 minus v squared.
So as you push the particle faster and faster,
its momentum and its energy increase and explode,
diverge,
become infinite when the velocity
becomes the speed of light.
That means it would take an infinite force
to accelerate a particle to a speed of light,
and
infinite forces are simply not part of nature.
I was just wondering,
what is the thing that now becomes a barrier
as a result of
The conservation law.
Right.
The four momentum.
Conservation of four momentum.
That's exactly right.
Okay.
Yeah.
There was an earlier statement that
we were only going to heaven,
because of the variables,
because of u squared minus u squared minus 1.
Yes,
we're going to come back to that in a minute.
Right.
That's just a statement that momentum,
that energy is determined in terms of momentum.
If you have two particles with opposite velocities,
does the mass of the combined system,
is it greater than the sum of the two masses?
Typically,
yes,
of course.
If you wanted the mass of the combined system,
by that I mean the energy of the combined system
when the combined system is at rest.
Now what does it mean
the combined system is at rest?
It means exactly what you said,
that the two objects might be moving in opposite directions.
Then the energy is definitely larger
than the sum of their masses.
In this convention,
the rest mass is greater than...
The rest mass...
All right,
now we have to be careful about definitions.
Some things are simply purely definitions.
Some people might react at this point,
well,
what I mean by the rest mass
is simply the sums of
the rest mass of two particles.
That is not a very good invariant concept at all.
Another person might mean,
no,
I don't mean that.
What I mean is think
of the thing as a unit
and discuss its energy in the frame of reference
where its total momentum is equal to zero.
That would be what we would
call the center of mass frame
or the rest frame of the combined system.
Now since all ordinary systems
are made up out of particles
that are moving hither and thither all over the place,
an invariant concept is the energy of a system
in a reference frame where its momentum is zero.
If we call that the mass,
then the mass of the composite system in your case,
in your particular case,
would be greater than the sums of the two masses.
If there were forces,
particularly attractive forces,
it might be less than,
but that's another case.
What does the mass term do when you
include it in the phase of a wave function?
It gives an e to
the i m squared c squared,
mc squared.
Times time.
So I've got a lot of,
I mean,
I have trouble forming this into a question,
but I mean the way we got this expression was,
it's a lot of abstract mathematics
to Raj is having to tell you.
Let's not call it abstract,
let's call it systematic.
Systematic.
Whatever,
I mean,
the,
this mc squared term is very significant.
I mean,
it describes things like an atomic bomb,
for example.
I mean,
it's...
Yeah,
the thing that's conserved is the total energy,
not the individual masses of particles.
So let's talk about an example.
You know,
before I talk about the example,
let me first take a
little digression into massless particles.
Massless particles are a little bit strange.
Here's the energy over here,
m divided by 1 minus v squared.
Now what's the velocity of a massless particle?
One.
Okay,
we're in trouble.
Well,
maybe the trouble's not too bad.
The numerator is zero and the denominator is zero.
It doesn't tell us what the answer is,
but at least it tells us
at worst it's zero over zero.
That's better than one over zero.
Okay,
right.
Maybe not a lot,
but it's a little better than one over zero.
It doesn't seem like such a good
idea to try to think of massless particles
in terms of the energy of
massless particles in terms of their velocity,
since all massless particles move
with exactly the same velocity.
Can they have different energy if
they all move with the same velocity?
Well,
yes,
they can.
And...
The reason is because zero over zero is not determined.
Thinking about massless particles is
not good to think about them
or to distinguish them by their velocity.
All their velocities are the same.
Okay?
We have to think about it differently.
The way to think about massless particles,
and in fact we can
think about any particle this way,
but to think about massless particles in particular
is to think of the energy as a
function of the momentum instead of the velocity.
We could even do that quite often in ordinary mechanics
when we write the energy of a particle,
kinetic energy.
It is one half mv squared.
Okay,
that's one way of writing it.
But another way to write it
is momentum squared over twice the mass.
This is,
I'm talking now not about relativistic mechanics,
just old-fashioned mechanics.
We write the energy of a
particle as a function of the momentum.
We write the energy in terms of the momentum.
That's another way,
an alternative way to express the energy.
What happens if we do the same thing in relativity?
Can we find the expression for the energy
of a particle in terms of its momentum?
Well,
there's a very simple trick.
The simple trick is just to use
the fact that u-naught squared minus u-x squared.
Let's do that.
Let's add them all in.
Minus u-y squared minus u-z squared.
That's right,
you said it.
u-z squared is equal to one.
We worked out that before.
And now let's,
I'm going to set c,
for the moment I'm going to
set c equal to one again.
c equal one.
Alright,
if I multiply,
let's see,
the,
yeah.
The components of momentum,
all four of them,
are the same as the components of
four velocity except for a factor of mass.
So what I want to do
is multiply this equation by m squared.
m squared,
m squared.
And then this becomes,
this is the square of p-naught squared,
but p-naught is just the energy.
So this becomes the square of the energy,
minus,
and each one of these is the
square of the corresponding component of momentum.
e squared minus p squared,
I forgot to multiply this side by m squared.
e squared minus p squared equals m squared.
In terms of the four velocity,
it's u-naught squared minus u-vector squared equals one.
In terms of the corresponding components of the four,
momentum,
energy and momentum,
it's e squared minus p squared equals m squared.
Or I can write that as e squared,
or e,
equals square root of p squared plus m squared.
I just,
I moved the p squared over to the
right hand side and took the square root.
Let's put back the speeds of light.
I'm going to leave this as an exercise for you.
I'll tell you what the answer is.
This is the square root of
p squared becomes p squared c squared,
and m squared becomes m squared c to the fourth.
Check that out.
It's just an exercise in getting your units straight.
And there it is.
That's energy in terms of momentum,
square of momentum,
and the mass.
Now,
from this formula,
we can immediately take the limit
that the mass goes to zero.
We had trouble thinking about
a photon in terms of velocity,
but we have no trouble in thinking
about photons in terms of this formula.
What does it say?
It says...
Hmm?
Yeah.
The right hand becomes zero and the left becomes c.
Yeah,
that's right.
Energy becomes equal to the square root of the
square of the momentum times the speed of light,
which is just the speed of
light times the magnitude of the momentum.
Let's call it magnitude of momentum.
Square root of p squared is
just the length of the momentum vector.
Energy for a massless particle is
simply the magnitude of the momentum vector,
but in order to keep the units correct,
you have to multiply by the speed of light.
This is true for photons.
It's approximately true for neutrinos.
Neutrinos have a tiny little bit of mass.
It's true for gravitons.
It is not true for particles which
move significantly slower than the speed of light.
All right.
Now that we know how to
express the energy of a massless particle,
we could solve the following equation,
the following problem.
Let's take a particle.
I'm going to give this particle a name.
It's called positronium.
It happens to be an electron and
a positron in orbit of the same number.
They orbit around each other.
But it's not important what we call it.
It's not important what it is.
It's important what we call it.
We'll call it positronium.
It's an electrically neutral particle and it has a mass.
Its mass is approximately the mass of two electrons.
But I don't care whether you
call it two electrons or not.
It's a little bit...
Is it more than two
electrons or less than two electrons?
Less than.
And why is it less than?
It's bound.
Yeah.
It's...
Right.
It's got a little bit of kinetic energy,
so that makes it a
little bit more than two electrons,
but it has even more negative potential energy.
All right.
So whatever the positronium particle is,
it doesn't matter what it's made of.
It's simply an electrically neutral
particle with a mass of...
I don't know.
I'm not going to ask you to
look up the mass of the electron.
Yes,
let me ask you to look
up the mass of the electron.
.51 MeV.
That...
Yeah,
it's .51 MeV,
but it's something in joules.
I was hoping somebody would
give it to me in joules.
9.1 times 10 to the minus 31.
What is it?
Is that true?
I don't remember.
I have no idea.
I mean,
I know it's...
9.1 times 10,
that's the electron mass.
All right.
So 9.1,
that's 1.8...
Some number of joules.
That's the positronium.
So there's positronium.
And if you leave positronium around for a while,
positronium will decay.
What will it decay into?
It will make two photons.
Two photons will go flying off.
Positronium will disappear.
The two photons will just go off.
In other words,
you've made electromagnetic energy out of them.
You've made just plain old
electromagnetic energy out of the positronium.
Positronium disappears and becomes,
in its place,
two photons going off,
separating from each other.
Can you calculate what the mass...
Not the mass.
What the energy and...
and momentum of those two photons are?
All right.
So let's go through the exercise.
This is something which would not make
any sense at all in non-relativistic physics.
In non-relativistic physics,
the sums of the masses of particles are always unchanged.
Chemical reactions happen.
Some chemicals turn into other chemicals and so forth.
But if you weigh the system,
if you weigh the mass of the system,
the masses,
the sums of the ordinary masses never change.
That's non-relativistic physics.
Here the sums of the ordinary masses is changing.
This has a mass of whatever it was in joules.
This has a mass of whatever it is in kilograms.
And each of these is massless.
The photons has no mass.
So the numerical sums of the
masses of particles is not conserved.
Not if this process happens.
And this process does happen.
But the right rule is not
that the sums of masses is conserved.
It's that the energy and the momentum is conserved.
So the first question is what is the momentum?
Let's do momentum conservation first.
Let's assume that the positronium atom,
positronium particle is at rest in our frame of reference.
If it's not at rest in your frame of reference,
just move your butt and get into
the frame in which it is at rest.
Okay?
Right.
Get into the frame in which it is at rest.
So it's at rest.
What's its momentum if it's at rest?
Zero.
So the total momentum of the
system to begin with is zero.
Now it decays to two photons.
The first conclusion is the photons must
go off back to back in opposite directions.
If they don't go off in opposite directions,
it's quite clear the total momentum will not be zero.
So they have to go off in opposite directions.
Uh...
By the...
Yeah,
they will go off in opposite directions,
and they must have equal,
exactly equal,
back to back,
equal and opposite momentum.
Why?
The initial thing had zero momentum.
The final thing has zero momentum.
All right,
so that means that this particle
goes off with a momentum p,
and this particle goes off with a momentum minus p.
Good.
Now let's use energy conservation.
The energy of the initial molecule,
not molecule,
positronium atom,
is its mass,
whatever its mass is,
times the speed of light squared.
This is not the mass of the electron,
not exactly.
Very,
very close to it,
but not exactly.
A little bit less than
twice the mass of an electron.
But it is the mass of the positronium atom.
So you get out your spring balance,
or whatever it is,
your scale.
You put a positronium atom on it,
and you weigh it.
And that's the mass of the positronium atom.
And when it's at rest,
in the rest frame,
it has an energy equal to mc squared.
That has to equal the energy
of the resulting two photons going off.
So this has to equal
the energy of the two photons.
The energy of the two photons is the same
because they have the same magnitude.
And it's just equal to twice the speed of light
times the momentum,
times the absolute value of the momentum,
p.
So that tells us what the absolute
value of the momentum has to be.
It's mc over 2.
That's the momentum of each one of the photons.
That's the simplest example of calculation.
Calculating a relativity decay,
and calculating what happens.
This is the momentum of the photons that go out.
We could convert this,
using a little bit of quantum reasoning,
we could convert this to a
wavelength for the photons going out.
If we use the connection between wavelength and momentum
that we learned last quarter,
we could convert this to a
statement about the wavelength of the photons.
It's very small.
It's much,
much smaller than optical.
So this is the mechanism by
which a mass turns into energy.
Of course,
the mass was always energy,
but it was in this frozen form
of rest energy of the positronium molecule.
And when the positronium atom decays,
it results in two photons going out.
The two photons collide with the atmosphere,
with everything else,
and heat it up.
They can be absorbed by electrons,
generate electrical currents,
and so forth and so on.
So it becomes,
the energy gets converted from the two photons
into this frozen form of rest mass
into dynamical,
useful form of electromagnetic energy.
How is spin conserved?
Well,
if the atom to begin with has zero angular momentum,
and these guys are going off back to back,
they better have opposite angular momentum.
So if the electron and positron are...
lined up together,
they won't decay?
No,
no,
they won't decay.
They'll always decay.
You have enough freedom,
you have enough freedom in the photon angular momentum
to make it go.
ご視聴ありがとうございました
you explain why massless particles have two nodes,
smetalite,
or Z2-polyrhabotoxides?
Well,
let's put it this way
In order to have a finite energy
in order to have a finite,
well-defined energy
if v goes to one
the denominator goes to zero
the mass in the numerator had better also be zero
You said it'd be the same for all massless particles,
that if the resulting particles were gravitons,
what would the initial particles be?
Some fraction of the time,
the positronium atom,
for example,
will decay into a pair of gravitons
Now,
that percentage of the time is 10 to the minus,
I don't know,
some large number
but some percentage of the time
the
electrically neutral positronium atom will decay
into just a pair of photons
As I said,
don't look for it in the laboratory
That decay has to be
instantaneous because of time-damage also?
Instantaneous means what?
What does it mean that the decay...
If you have,
let's say,
the two photons emitted
the positronium decays into those
because of time-damage.
And there is a time-damage to do it.
risk-relief going at the speed of light,
that means that the return of the plot to zero,
that means that it's close to it,
so you can't just process it as possible,
right?
Well,
let's see,
so what experimental question
would you ask?
You could detect the photons in some sort of chamber
that leaves tracks,
and you could trace the two photons back
and you would discover that they both come together
at exactly the place where the positronium was,
and so that you could say,
look,
if they decayed,
if the decay was peculiar and the positronium decayed,
first producing one photon that went out to here,
and then later creating the other photon
which only went out to here,
they're both moving with the speed of light,
and you trace them back,
they would appear to come
from somewheres over here.
That doesn't happen.
If you trace back the trajectories of the photon
and as they leave tracks in a chamber,
or something like that,
they will come back
and intersect at exactly where
the initial positronium atom was.
I'm not sure if that's the question you're asking,
but I think that's the only
thing I can make out of it.
The equation I want to refer to.
What's that?
Oh.
You can raise that board again.
Yeah.
I understand you concluded that e squared
minus b squared equals m squared
from that equation up above,
and it looks like that equation is saying that,
u-naughts squared minus u,
x squared minus u,
y squared minus u,
z squared is 1?
Yes.
Why is that?
Oh,
we went through that,
but I'll go through it again.
I'll go through it again for you.
We already had two versions of it,
but one of them was garbled.
And I guess an ungarbled one just cancels
out a garbled one and leaves no exponent.
All right.
So do you remember this formula?
Simula delta tau squared is equal to
delta t squared minus delta x squared?
Okay.
Oh,
here it is right over here.
Right,
here it is.
Right.
Good.
Yes,
Kevin.
So u-naught is dT d tau.
That's correct.
Delta t delta tau.
Right.
What does that mean about energy?
Does that tell us anything about energy?
Well,
it doesn't strike any deep chord in me.
You know,
I know it's true.
Does it really ring something powerful?
Only in the sense,
well,
let's see.
You want to dT d tau.
Nothing really visceral in that.
Because at rest,
dT d tau is one.
In motion,
it's not one.
And it's telling you how the
energy changes as a function of velocity.
But nothing more than that.
Yes?
Yes.
Yeah.
So,
obviously,
the guys got to the Damnatum and,
theatz of momentum is zero.
Yeah.
Is there—
Even,
on effects—
Is it possible for theaz momentum to
be teeny tiny little bit different to zero?
Not if momentum is conserved.
Well,
in a laboratory situation,
in any laboratory situation,
of course there are contaminating effects.
Even if nothing more,
or the presence of some tiny stray field,
magnetic or electric field or something,
could corrupt the thing and
lead to a slightly different answer.
Remember,
the rule is momentum is
conserved for a truly isolated system.
A truly isolated system means that
you've accounted for everything in the system
and nothing else is interacting with it.
Then the momentum of that system is conserved.
Now,
if your laboratory is sufficiently isolated and
the region of space is cold enough
that there are no particles bombarding
and so forth and so on,
the positronium together with the
photons constitute an almost closed system.
But you know,
it's really not completely closed.
If nothing else,
there's gravitational forces between the earth
and the atmosphere.
And the particles,
they're completely negligible,
but they're not zero.
So yeah,
there are contaminating influences.
Like the uncertainty principle.
That doesn't affect it.
Momentum is conserved.
And where it is is .
The better you know the momentum,
and in particular,
the better you know the relationship between the momentum,
it may be that you have
less information about the relative positions.
But that's a small .
.
It's a small effect.
And for our purposes tonight,
I want to separate quantum mechanics from classical .
.
But it's a real question.
Right.
Your formula for energy was just an approximation.
Well,
one .
.
there was an approximation.
This was an .
.
well,
this is not an approximation.
That's right.
But .
.
This .
well,
let's see.
Where is it?
I lost it.
Yeah.
The equation e equals m plus mv squared over 2.
That was an approximation.
So the non-approximation is e equals m over
the square root of 1 minus v squared.
That's right.
This is .
.
With the c in that equation.
Oh,
okay.
Let's do that.
Okay.
Ah,
over here.
All right.
So we have .
.
we begin with e equals .
what do we want to start?
m divided by square root of 1 minus v squared?
Right.
So we look at the
units and in a minute .
.
well,
right now,
a 1 and a v squared
have different units.
The only way to make v squared have the
same units as 1 is divide it by c squared.
There's no other way.
Now the 1 minus v squared
over c squared is dimensionally consistent.
However,
the whole formula is not.
The left-hand side is energy.
The right-hand side now has units of a mass.
Mass and energy don't quite have the same units.
They're related by the square of a velocity.
We know that the units of energy .
.
the units of energy are equal to the units of
mass times the units of a velocity.
Let's put v squared.
An example would be kinetic energy as well.
uku1mannu m个5u".
Then I'm going to use穩 supportive space Euro
.
value.
Bye.
Hello,
everybody.
the positronium experiment,
the electron positron pair has
to decay into two photons simultaneously
in all frames of reference.
Has to decay into two photons and then what?
Simultaneously in all frames of reference.
Yeah,
yeah.
The physical distance between the electron and the positron.
Well,
that's a hard thing to check.
I mean,
if you had the positronium at rest,
now remember,
because of quantum mechanics,
there's going to be some uncertainty in its position.
Okay?
And so there is a region in which
you may have known that the positronium was in.
Then the positronium decays.
And...
If you trace it...
If you trace it back along the
world line of the photon that comes out,
the two photons,
they will intersect.
Now you could draw a space-time picture of this.
Here's the space-time picture.
Here's the positronium.
Time goes up.
This is the world line of the positronium at rest.
Then the positronium decays.
And the photon goes out this way.
Whoops,
that's not very good.
Photon goes out this way.
And a photon goes out this way.
If you trace back along
the world line of the photon,
you will find out that they will intersect,
first of all,
at the spatial location where the positronium was,
but they will intersect at exactly the same time.
Or at least at the same
time if we ignore quantum uncertainties.
Uh...
Yeah?
What determines the axes along which the
two photons come out of the positronium?
Random.
Sometimes that way,
sometimes that way,
sometimes that way.
That's the randomness of quantum mechanics.
Uncertain...
That's...
You know,
it's like taking a spin,
orienting it this way,
and then measuring it along the other axis.
Sometimes this way,
sometimes that way.
So it comes out with some angular distribution,
but randomly in different directions.
And at random times,
to some extent.
When you first defined L,
earlier this evening...
The Lagrangian?
Right.
I think you picked it because it was the
one thing we had available that would be invariant.
The action principle being a statement about
minimizing something or other about a trajectory
will be invariant if you
choose the action to be invariant.
Right,
so we...
Is there more bottoms-up weight?
No.
So when we did the classical mechanics,
I mean,
I understood how this is right,
but we basically chose the action so that
when you get the Euler equations for that pathway,
that they provide the equations of motion...
Newton.
Newton equations.
Yes,
indeed.
So it didn't seem like there
was anything analogous going on here.
Maybe...
Well,
no.
The only reason...
We haven't put anything in concept of force.
Now,
all right.
What we could do is we could take this
Lagrangian and work out the equations of motion and see
what the equations of motion say.
But we already know what they say.
They say that the energy and momentum
and therefore the four velocity is constant.
And that's all they say.
Just as Newton's equations,
when there's no forces around,
just say...
Well,
they say that m...
You know...
Mass times acceleration is zero.
That's the same as saying the time rate of change
of momentum is zero or that the momentum is constant.
All right.
So this will say that the momentum is constant,
nothing more,
or that the four velocity is constant.
Well,
the four velocity being constant,
that means not only in magnitude but in direction,
it says that the particle moves along the space...
A straight line in space-time.
That the motion of the particle
is a straight line through space-time.
And that says it moves along
a line in space with constant velocity.
That's the whole content of the
Euler-Lagrange equations for this particular case.
Now,
we could try putting force...
We could try asking how does this get modified
if we try to put various kinds of forces in.
And we will do that.
One of the things we will do is allow the particle to have a charge
and to couple it to an electric and magnetic field and see how it moves.
But so far,
that's a little more complicated than
anything we've done up till now.
Up till now,
the whole content of the Euler-Lagrange
equations is just momentum and energy conservation.
Or straight line motion,
but not just straight line motion through space-time.
Two of Newton's laws become the same law.
What are Newton's laws?
A particle moves along a straight line and the
other one says the particle moves with constant velocity.
Here it says...
A particle moves in a straight line through space-time,
which entails both straight
line motion and constant velocity.
One more question.
Then I gotta go.
You talked about how in the
limit where velocity is very low,
that relativity...
The laws of Poisson,
the laws of Newton...
Right.
Or at least the laws of
conservation as they would have been defined.
Yeah,
that's what we derived from Newton.
Yeah.
Right.
And in...
I'm just trying to make that connection.
I'm not really sure here,
but in a previous program
we were talking about quantum mechanics,
we were talking about this other
limit where you increase the mass,
you...
The laws of quantum mechanics also approach,
you know?
Yes.
But it's an entirely different limit.
Yeah,
right.
What is velocity?
In the middle is like the mass
or the number of particles or something?
A combination of various things,
but let's say the mass of the object and...
The important thing is the mass of the object
and the smoothness of the forces that act on it.
It shouldn't be abrupt and sudden.
But that's another,
you know,
we gotta separate things.
This has got to do with the speed of light.
Quantum mechanics has to do with Planck's constant.
And you can have a
situation which is highly quantum mechanical,
but non-relativistic.
You can have a situation which
is highly relativistic and not quantum mechanical,
and you can have both.
Relativistic and quantum mechanical.
The two independent limits.
Is this where they say that
there's a compatibility between the two?
I don't know where I read that.
No,
no,
there's no incompatibility.
I think you're thinking about gravity.
Gravity,
there are puzzles about,
but we haven't gotten there yet.
So far we're not dealing with gravity.
Gravity at all.
We'll come to it.
Okay,
I think it's time to go home.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.