Stanford University.
First announcement,
I will not be here next week.
I have to go to Belgium
to give some lecture or other.
I will be back and we will continue this
course until the full set of ten lectures are given.
I have no idea where we are now
because I get lost some time around now.
But I won't chisel you.
You will have the full set of lectures,
but I will be gone next week.
I think we missed at
least one in the very beginning.
I can't remember.
Was it one or two?
One.
Alright,
we're going to miss one next week.
They will be made up.
I mean,
I have many reasons for wanting to make them up.
First of all,
I don't want to chisel.
But second of all,
I want to get this
full set of lectures out there.
And so we will continue until they're done.
Alright,
let's talk about some principles.
And I want to...
I realize...
Did you have notes from last company?
I didn't.
I was really up to my
ears with all kinds of stuff.
I have notes from tonight,
but I simply wrote them
up within the last three hours,
three hours,
and I will get them out.
If somebody would like to take them and
scan them and put them on the website,
I would really like that.
My secret.
My scanner takes for hours and hours.
It's the slowest scanner in the world.
But we'll see.
If somebody wants to do that,
that's fine with me.
In any case,
let's...
Just a moment.
Let me find my place in here.
嗯
Looks like that's my place,
first page.
I appreciate that the last time I
did some pretty heavy intricate mathematics on the
blackboard and I would guess that
some fraction of you followed it fractionally.
I appreciate that,
I understand it.
I'm going to go over it again a little bit.
You know,
you'll be...
My teaching policy is to teach until you cry.
I've always been like that.
But if we are going to
take seriously the goal of this course,
which is to teach the
theoretical minimum necessary to seriously
go on to the same,
to the next level,
there's
no other way.
There's no alternative.
I think I've said this before,
if I knew a way
to do it without the mathematics,
I would
do it,
but I don't.
It seems to sort of be a law
of nature that nature is expressed through mathematics.
I don't know why that's true.
Well,
I actually do think I do know why it's
true because to the extent that the laws of
nature make sense and are exact,
they have to be quantified
and how do you quantify things
without mathematics and so forth.
But it's true that the mathematics gets
more and more arcane as you move forward.
And this is not because physicists want it this way.
It's not because physicists are a bunch of
high priests who are trying to hide what they're
doing and expressing it in a
fancy language that nobody else can understand.
It just seems that it is that way.
Maybe someday,
somebody will crack the code.
Some young person will see a simplicity in
the laws of physics that we don't yet see
and be able to express them in a very,
very simple equation,
x equals zero,
and that'll
be it.
As Feynman pointed out,
you can always do that.
You can take all of the equations of physics,
square them,
sum them up,
and set it equal
to zero.
Because if the sum of squares is equal to zero,
then you can do that.
If the sum of squares is equal to zero,
then every term is zero.
But that's not helpful.
The only thing I was going to say
is why someone young and not in the whole
part like me are yet.
I think it's time that we .
I'm with you.
I got it.
I get it and I got it.
Right on.
Absolutely right.
Can we say somebody young in spirit?
We don't even want to say that.
Okay,
good.
Yeah?
You defined properties last week,
but I didn't hear about the,
for me,
I don't remember the
words.
Aftercase,
lowercase.
Oh.
Super script or subscript.
When do you use which one?
Okay.
The official rule is a coordinate.
This is arbitrary.
Which is up and which is down.
It's as arbitrary as defining your left hand to
be this one and your right hand to be this
one.
Way back when somebody could have
called this right and this left.
I'm sorry.
I apologize,
but you get the point.
But which is up and which
is down is a different thing.
It's not that some indices are lighter than
air and some indices are heavier than air
and float to the bottom.
It's just arbitrary.
But,
all right,
so basically the distinction is the coordinates themselves,
somewhat arbitrarily,
you label with an upstairs index.
The differences of coordinates,
for example,
along a trajectory,
you label as dx mu with
the index upstairs.
Okay.
So you label the index with the index upstairs.
Derivatives with respect to x,
for example,
the derivative of a scalar with respect to
x,
you think of as having a downstairs index.
You think of it as having a downstairs index.
And there are many,
many other things that also have downstairs indices,
things which
transform under Lorentz transformations as coordinates.
Coordinates carry upstairs indices.
Things which transform as
derivatives carry downstairs indices.
There's not much difference between them.
You go from a thing with upstairs index
to downstairs index just by changing the sign
of the time component.
That's all that's involved here,
changing the sign of the time component.
But it saves you writing out a lot of work
to write that ds by ds is equal to x.
So you have dx mu.
Now here's a downstairs index and an upstairs index.
This stands for,
what does it stand for?
It stands for ds by dx0,
the time component,
times dx0 plus ds by dx1,
dx1 plus blah blah
blah blah.
Three terms.
Okay.
And the whole thing is just the change in
s in going from one point to a neighboring
point,
delta s.
So here's an example in which it's much more efficient
to write ds by dx mu dx mu than to
write out the whole damn thing.
But we need some conventions,
we need some rules about when
it is we're allowed to sum
over the indices.
We need to keep track of things carefully.
And so the official rule is whenever you see
a lower index next to an upper index and they're
the same letter,
it means sum.
That's all.
That's the whole rule.
There is a deeper geometric meaning to it,
but I don't want to go into it now.
We'll go into it when we do general relativity.
There is a geometric meaning to it.
But for us now,
the whole thing is to write the sum.
So only difference,
every vector,
let's call it a mu,
has both a contravariant
life and a covariant life.
And the only difference is the component of
the vector with downstairs index is the same
as with upstairs index except for the
time component where you flip the sign.
So it really is just a way.
It's just a way of keeping track.
And not having to write over and over things
like t squared or x squared minus t squared,
x squared.
Things like x squared plus y squared plus
z squared minus t squared times squared is
just equal to x mu x mu.
As far as the space components go,
lowering the index does nothing.
So it really stands for x
squared plus y squared plus z squared.
And as far as the time component here,
the lower time component has its sign changed
relative to the upper one and
so it becomes minus t squared.
That's the whole point of it.
It's just helpful in writing simpler expressions.
But if you follow the rules and you
follow the rules of upstairs and downstairs indices
rigorously,
you will find out that it's very,
very easy.
You can write a lot of things.
But if you're going to write
things that are invariant under Lorentz transformations,
x squared plus y squared blah blah blah
plus z squared minus t squared is invariant.
That doesn't change.
It's the same for one observer and another observer.
That's what it means to be invariant.
And it's equal to x mu x mu.
An upstairs index and downstairs index,
when you contract them,
which means sum over them
like this,
that makes a scalar.
So there are some nice rules to keep track of.
And they're notation.
They're notational devices,
but very efficient.
If you use just a partial
sign as the partial partial x,
is the partial lower lower index
mu?
Yeah.
Any time you take a partial derivative,
it always carries a lower index.
Does it have a covariant form or an uncovariant form?
Yes.
The covariant thing stands for d by dx naught,
which means d by dt,
d by dx,
d by dy,
d by
dz.
This is d by dx mu.
Okay.
When I say it's equal to,
I mean the components of this
object here are this set of operations.
If I want,
let's call it just d sub mu.
d sub mu.
Any time I have a
thing with an index sub mu,
I can construct a related thing,
which
is the same collection of objects with an upper index,
and all it stands for is minus
d by dx.
d sub mu.
From here,
that's basically the derivative of
all tbsp times d by dx.
Can we just do theANT case?
Well,
the harder I write the three-dimensional section,
the harder I can niin which is so
How much time do we have left?
How many frequencies has struck
us from in the two-dimensionalbbodcast?
1234 times d by dx,enta.
things which are Lorentz invariant,
it's a trick for easily recognizing and
writing Lorentz invariant things.
All right,
let's discuss,
I want to go back
a little bit through the thing
we did last time and just
sort of sketch it out again,
since it was probably kind
of tough,
and maybe seeing it twice but
not the full thing might help.
But before
I do,
let's talk about principles.
Let's talk about the basic principles.
Now when
I say the principles,
I mean the principles in the sense of a theoretical
physicist today discovers a new phenomenon,
well it's usually
experimental physicists that discover a new phenomenon,
but then a theorist wants
to make a theory of it.
The usual rules,
now someday the rules might break down,
but so far they haven't.
The usual rules for whatever reason are that the physics
is not the same as the theoretical rules.
The rules are the same as the theoretical rules.
The humanist should be described,
phenomena should be described by an action principle.
There is nothing that we know in nature
that is not describable by an action principle.
Is this an accident?
Probably not.
Is this something that's a whim of physicists?
Certainly
not.
We don't know anything that doesn't form this pattern.
Is it important that it has
that form?
Yes,
it is.
For example,
the derivation of the concept of energy conservation,
momentum conservation,
all the conservation laws of physics,
and especially the relation
between conservation laws and symmetries,
is entirely through the action principle.
If you just write equations,
the equations may make perfectly good sense,
but if they're not based on an action principle,
they will not have energy conservation,
momentum conservation,
even charge conservation is also an aspect of this.
But in particular,
let's focus on energy conservation.
That is a consequence of the action principle,
together with the assumption that things are
invariant under changes of the time axis,
changes which we call translations of the time variable.
So,
yes,
it's a very interesting concept.
If we stop writing down physical equations
that don't derive from an action principle,
we would be giving up the guarantee of energy conservation,
momentum conservation.
So,
as far as we can tell,
this is a deep principle.
So that's principle number one.
We look for an action such that the
equations of motion which follow from that action,
the equations of motion which follow from that action,
describe the phenomena that is discovered in the laboratory,
we look for an action description.
That guarantees that it will fall into the
category of things with energy conservation and so forth.
The action principle means an expression
for the action which is minimized,
but minimized by the true
solution of the equations of motion.
And the equations of motion
follow by the Euler-Lagrange equations,
the stationary equations for the action.
Number two.
Locality.
Locality is basically the principle that if you poke
a system at some point of time and space,
it has no immediate effect except on
things in the immediate vicinity of it.
Its direct effect is on things
in the immediate vicinity of it,
of course,
if I had a string here,
a violin string,
and I poked it over here,
it would only affect the neighbor instantaneously,
that's locality,
but then the neighbor would affect the
neighbor down the chain and so forth,
and time,
poking it over here,
would affect it everywhere,
but the instantaneous effect,
or the short time effect,
is local,
nearby,
and that is guaranteed,
by requiring a principle of locality in the action,
namely,
that the action,
that the action is an integral,
if it's a particle trajectory that we're talking about,
then it's an integral along the trajectory,
and it becomes an integral dt.
If it's a field theory that we're talking about,
a field contained in a volume of space and time,
let's paint the space-time region green,
to represent the existence of a field in there,
then the action,
action,
then the action is an integral not only over time,
but also over space,
and we can write that integral d4x.
The principle of locality,
says that the thing that we integrate here,
the Lagrangian,
or the Lagrangian here,
this Lagrangian here depends only on
the coordinates of the system,
if it happens to be a particle,
it depends on the positions of the particle,
the position components of the particle,
and only the time derivatives,
x dot.
In other words,
Lagrangian at this point here depends
only on the position at this point,
and neighboring points,
points very nearby.
That's the principle,
that things only affect nearby neighbors,
nearby neighbors either in space or in time.
Okay.
And,
for a field theory,
it says that the Lagrangian depends on the fields,
I'll just call it generic field phi,
and the various derivatives.
Partial of phi with respect to x mu,
let's just call it phi mu.
That means the derivative of
phi with respect to x mu.
This is enough to guarantee
that things only affect their nearest neighbors directly,
their near neighbor,
and it's the principle of locality
that Lagrangians depend only on
fields and their first derivatives,
not on fields at one point
times fields on a very distant point,
for example.
You could imagine,
there's no question,
you can imagine a world
in which poking something over here
has an instantaneous effect over here.
In that case,
you would not write that the Lagrangian
was an integral over something only involving
nearest neighbor derivatives,
but more complicated kinds of things.
This was the question?
Yeah.
For the last semester of quantum mechanics,
we spent some time talking about quantum nonlocality.
What's that,
David?
For the last semester,
we spent a couple of
lectures talking about quantum nonlocality.
I've never talked about quantum nonlocality.
Never use the word.
You guys keep using it.
I do not.
We talked about entanglement.
Entanglement is not nonlocality.
You cannot affect the thing over here instantly
by doing something over here.
I tried to make that extremely clear.
I tried to make it clear by showing you,
for example,
how the density matrix of
a degree of freedom over here
will not change if you
try to do something over here.
Now,
you guys have gotten into your heads
something,
some scientific American mentality,
some New York Times mentality,
that there's something mysterious and nonlocal
about entanglement,
and this is not true.
You cannot send signals,
you cannot affect things at a distance
by doing something over here.
Period.
That's not what entanglement does.
Entanglement is basically the quantum version,
I'm just going to spend one more minute at this,
the quantum version of me
having two coins in my pocket,
a nickel and a dime,
closing my eyes,
shuffling them up,
and giving Alice one of them.
I don't tell her which.
She doesn't know.
I don't know because I've done it some way.
I give Bob the other one
and then send them off home.
There is no way that Alice
has any direct effect on Bob
by looking at her coin.
But instantly she knows what Bob
has if she looks at hers.
Alright?
It's correlation.
It's not effect.
Good.
We're going to do it right now.
Locality is fundamental.
Third thing,
third principle,
you require the physics to be Lorentz invariant.
In other words,
that the rules,
the rules of the game,
the equations of motion,
should be the same in every reference frame.
That is easy to do.
The rule is the Lagrangian should
be the same in every reference frame,
and that means it should be a scalar.
How do you make scalars?
You make scalars by following the rules about indices.
So the Lagrangian should be a scalar.
That's Lorentz invariance.
Let's write it down.
Lorentz invariance.
And the last rule which we're going to discuss tonight,
this is a mysterious rule.
This is one that you won't get the first time.
Well,
you'll get it.
Hopefully you'll get what I'm saying.
But you won't understand the depth of it
and what it really means
unless we go through it from various directions,
which we'll do.
Fourth is another principle of invariance,
this is a principle of invariance
that the physics doesn't change
in going from one frame of reference to another.
Incidentally,
this includes rotation invariance and so forth.
And the fourth rule
is a rule called gauge invariance.
How many people have heard of gauge invariance?
Okay,
the majority of you have heard of gauge invariance.
How many can tell me what it is?
All right.
Yeah.
All right,
so tonight we're going to talk...
What's that?
You can get away with adding stuff to the Lagrangian.
Certain kinds of stuff.
Gauge invariance.
Excuse me,
I have a question about number three.
Yeah.
Lorentz invariance,
that has to do with circle relativity.
It does.
Okay,
we're not there yet.
You're right.
This is special relativity.
So let's suppose that what the
experimenter has discovered in the laboratory
has nothing to do with gravity.
He's quite sure it has nothing to do with gravity.
Then these would be the rules.
Right,
but the reason I ask that is
you said that these are very general principles,
but it sounds like...
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
They're very general,
but not completely general.
You're right.
Yes,
yes,
you're right.
Actually,
they are very general.
They are very general.
Making the Lagrangian be a
scalar has to be slightly modified.
It has to be a scalar density.
Now,
don't worry about it.
That's a concept which comes up when
we think about curved space-time and so forth.
But apart from a very minor change in words,
these are the same rules that
you would use for general relativity.
But in the case of general relativity,
the Lorentz transformation doesn't play a second role.
That's right.
It's a bigger invariance called
invariance under arbitrary coordinate transformations.
That's correct.
I didn't get the word make.
A scalar what?
Density.
Scalar density.
Yeah.
So...
One other question about...
But,
you know,
we...
Okay.
Yeah.
About item three.
So in the mechanics course way back when...
Mm-hmm.
We made all...
We made Lagrangians...
Lagrangians all had...
Terms had dimensions of energy.
Yes.
And so is it correct that that's not a requirement?
That as long as they're scalar...
Okay.
It is a requirement,
but...
Yes.
This Lagrangian would have units of an energy.
Now,
this Lagrangian that goes here would
have units of an energy density.
And the reason...
Let's write it this way.
Let's write it dt...
dt...
times dxdydz,
okay?
Now...
dxdydz has units of a volume.
So there's a factor of a
volume here that is not here.
Okay?
In order to compensate,
the Lagrangian of a field theory
has to be a energy per unit
volume.
So that when it's integrated with a volume,
it becomes a volume.
So it becomes an energy.
Okay.
So there's...
There is some kind of restriction...
Yes.
...that has to do with dimensions.
Right.
That's true.
But you rarely have to worry about it,
because you tend to work in units where everything
is one.
So yeah.
Right.
Okay.
Good.
So let's go back.
Let's go back through the example we did last time.
And I want to work it
out quickly on the blackboard again,
because it is so central.
It is so important.
And we're going to get the gauge invariance soon.
But I first want to go back and
just remind you what we learned last time.
Try to do it really quickly.
And I can do it quickly,
I think,
if we...
Okay.
So I'm going to hold the questions until the end.
Not the end of the class,
but the end of the demonstration.
All right.
So we said,
let's just think about the motion
of a particle in an electromagnetic field.
The first thing we did was introduce a four vector,
which is the four vector vector potential.
It's got four components.
Now where the hell did it come from?
Well,
we will see where it comes from.
But it is necessary...
It is necessary in order to...
Okay.
So we have an action principle,
which leads to the equations
of motion of a charged particle
in an electromagnetic field.
What are those equations?
They're Newton's equations,
F equals ma,
but with the force given by the Lorentz force
law,
electric and magnetic forces.
You cannot derive that.
You can write that down.
You know,
we can write down,
what is the equation?
Mass times acceleration is equal
to electric charge times electric force.
Electric field plus velocity cross magnetic field.
Many of you have seen that before,
and there's no vector potential in it.
That's correct.
You can write the equations without the vector potential,
but you cannot express these laws
of physics in terms of an
action principle without having a vector potential.
No way to write it without an action principle.
Okay.
So what happens is that the action
for the charged particle contains two terms.
The action...
I don't want to confuse action and vector potential.
I'll just write out the word action.
The action is an integral dt.
Now this is a particle.
It's not a field theory.
It's just a particle in a given electromagnetic field,
so it's just an integral dt.
Then there's the usual term,
which is minus m...
No,
let's not write that.
Let's write just integral...
The action is integral minus m times d tau.
What is d tau?
Along the trajectory of the particle,
we break the trajectory up into infinitesimal segments
and calculate the proper
time along each infinitesimal segment,
multiply by minus m,
and add them
all up.
This is guaranteed to be a scalar.
So it's Lorentz invariant.
And then the other term we
wrote down was minus e times...
It's still an integral,
under the integral sign.
A mu dx mu.
So just to specify exactly what that means,
for every little segment here,
along that
segment at the position of the segment,
right at the position of the segment,
there is a
vector potential.
A vector potential is a field.
It depends on space and time.
So let's just call it A of x.
X stands for x,
y,
z,
and t.
A at the position of
the segment there times dx mu.
And this is a scalar.
This is a scalar.
If A is a four vector
and dx mu is a four vector,
this combination is a scalar.
And now we have a potential candidate for an action.
And from it,
we can derive a log.
We can derive a Lagrangian.
The Lagrangian,
we can write this as the
integral of minus m d tau dt.
Remember,
the Lagrangian always has the
form of an integral over time.
Ordinary time.
So d tau is the same
as d tau by dt dt.
And if you remember what d tau by dt is,
you can work it out.
It is the square root of 1 minus the velocity.
So this is the square root of 1 minus
the sum of the squares of the components of the
velocity.
We worked that out several times.
This is the Lagrangian for
the particle without the electromagnetic field.
And then in the presence of
the electromagnetic field is another term,
minus E.
And now we can write this.
The trick is always the same,
right?
A mu d A.
The x mu dt dt.
Just a trivial little operation here where
I multiply and divide it by dt.
But now,
what is the x mu by dt?
What is the x mu by dt?
Has four components.
What are the four components?
Well,
there's first of all the time component.
The time component is the silly thing,
dt by dt.
So that's 1.
And then there are the components of the velocity.
The components,
ordinary components of velocity.
So what this becomes,
what this becomes is the sum of four terms.
Let's write them out.
The time component times dt dt.
Plus.
The time component.
Let's call it A sub m x m dot.
All right,
if you didn't get that,
I'll show you over here.
It's A mu dx mu.
And we write dx mu dx mu by dt dt.
And now let's go through
the various terms that are here.
First of all is the
time component times the time component.
That's just A naught.
Time component.
Times dt dt.
We don't have to write that down.
And then the next term is
A sub x times dx by dt.
And then A sub y
dy by dt and so forth.
That's this over here.
The index m.
It doesn't matter for the space components.
For the space components,
you can,
you don't care.
Right.
You're right.
We could put this upstairs.
But it doesn't matter for the space components.
Space components are the same upstairs and downstairs.
All right.
So this is vector potential dot the velocity.
And that's our Lagrangian times dt.
So now we can read out what the Lagrangian is.
The Lagrangian for the particle.
Is minus m.
So that's the Lagrangian.
Square root of 1 minus x dot squared.
X dot squared means x dot squared
plus y dot squared plus z dot squared.
This is Lagrangian now.
And then minus the electric charge times A naught of
x and t plus A m of x and t times
x dot m.
That's the Lagrangian.
Oops.
Let me put the bracket here.
Okay.
So.
From the point,
from the starting point where we guess a Lagrangian,
we work very mechanically.
The mechanical rules are straightforward,
sometimes a little bit tedious.
Sometimes a little bit tedious.
And in some deep sense,
trivial.
They're just mechanically following out the
Euler Lagrange equations for a given Lagrangian.
And this is what gets tedious in physics.
This is where the tedium comes in.
And sometimes there's huge amounts of tedium.
I mean,
Lagrangians can be very complicated.
Or Lagrangians can be simple.
But the steps necessary to work out and
solve the equations of motion can be tedious.
So basic principle,
that's the fun part.
Working out what the Lagrangian is,
that may be fun.
And then deducing the consequences of it,
that you give to your graduate students.
Right.
Okay.
All right.
So let's.
So let's remember what the
consequences of this Lagrangian were.
We begin with dl by dx dot.
Let's say we pick some component,
the mth component,
m being one,
two,
or three.
And we compute the l by dx dot.
We get something from here.
That's equal to m.
And if you work it out,
it's xm dot.
The velocity.
The velocity in the mth direction divided by
the square root of one minus x dot squared.
Okay.
That's dl by dx dot.
I'm not going to work it out.
You can do it.
It also happens to be,
for further,
for future reference,
m times dxm by d tau.
It also happens to be m times the four velocity.
Oh,
sorry.
xmm.
The mth component of the four velocity,
m times what we called um.
Yeah,
there's another term in the Lagrangian.
Yeah.
We'll come to it.
Right.
That's correct.
I'm sorry.
I.
That's correct.
This is not an.
This is an equation which
is not finished being written yet.
Why isn't it finished being written?
Because there's another term which depends on x dot here.
So,
there should be another piece here which is just minus,
it's minus,
electric charge
times am.
Times am.
Am of x and t.
And let's now.
That's it.
This is this minus.
Let's write it.
Let's write it correctly.
Let's write the equation so
that it really is an equation.
This minus this happens to
be equal to m times um,
the four vector of velocity,
minus e
a sub m.
Now you should jump up and down and
scream like hell that my equation is not consistent.
I have upstairs indices and downstairs indices.
I have two indices in the same place.
But it's okay because it's purely the space component.
The space components don't care whether
their indices are upstairs or downstairs.
So trust me,
it's okay.
This is the L by dx dot.
Now what do we do
with the L by dx dot?
Lagrange's equations.
We differentiate it with respect to time,
right?
D by dt of dl by dx dot.
D by dt of this.
So what do we get?
Let's go right down to over here.
The left side of the Lagrange equations,
the left side of the Euler Lagrange equations
is d by dt mass.
D by dt of um.
Minus e d by dt of
the mth component of the vector potential.
What is the time derivative of
a given component of the vector potential?
Now what do we mean,
first of all,
by the time derivative?
First of all,
a may have explicit dependence on time,
but it also depends on x.
So what does that mean?
Well,
we're talking about evaluating the vector
potential at the position of a particle
along the trajectory.
So a can vary for two reasons.
It can vary because it explicitly depends on time,
or it can vary because the position
of the particle is varying with time.
So there are two contributions to the time derivative.
We have to take the time
derivative of this thing over here.
It's going to be minus e.
And there will be two terms.
I'm going to write them down.
Derivative of a sub m with respect to t,
which I will write derivative with respect to x
naught.
Same thing.
That's one term.
And then another term,
which is minus.
I want to compute the change in
a sub m because x is changing.
Not because t is changing,
but because x is changing with time.
And that's the derivative of am.
And that's the derivative of a sub m.
So I'm going to write the sum over
n with respect to position xn times xn dot.
Summed over n.
There's a term,
derivative of am with respect to x times x dot,
derivative of am with respect
to y times y dot,
derivative of am with respect to z times z dot.
So this is a sum here.
It's a sum over n.
That's the left-hand side of the Euler-Lagrange equations.
So I'm going to write the sum over n.
It's not so hard to understand.
It comes as two terms,
one coming from the first term
in the Lagrangian and the other
coming from the second term in the Lagrangian.
There's an E here.
Do I have the sign right?
Yes,
I have the sign right.
But the electric charge multiplies the whole thing.
Minus the electric charge times the whole thing.
That's the left side.
Now,
what about the right side?
What's the right side of the Euler-Lagrange equations?
Let's just write Euler-Lagrange equations.
The right side is the derivative
of the Lagrangian with respect to xm.
That's it.
Okay,
so let's go and compute.
Where is the Lagrangian?
Here's the Lagrangian.
What's the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to the x's?
How does it depend on the x's?
This doesn't depend on x,
it only depends on x dot.
Only depends on the velocities.
Lagrangians depend on positions and velocities.
This term only depends on velocities.
Forget it.
This is a velocity over here,
not an x.
But a0 and am depend on x.
And remember,
a0 and am are just fixed
things which somebody has told us.
Okay,
so let's write the right hand side.
Minus derivative of a0 with respect to x.
Is that minus?
Do I have it right?
I think I have it right.
Minus E times the derivative
of a0 with respect to x.
Let me see,
I think,
yes,
that's correct.
Derivative of a0 with respect to x.
And then from here,
I have minus E.
Times the derivative of am,
let's call it am with respect to x.
Let's see,
now let's call it,
okay,
derivative of an.
This is 0.
Okay.
Xm,
xm,
derivative of an with respect to xm,
axn dot.
Let's see where it came from.
It came from here,
yeah.
All right,
I should have gone slower.
This is a summation index here.
I can change it.
I can change its name.
I'll call it xn.
xn,
doesn't matter.
I'll call it axn.
All right.
On the left-hand side,
I'm evaluating the equation of motion
for the mth component of position.
So there's an m here.
It's not a summation index.
That's why I didn't use
the summation index m over there.
I changed variables,
changed summation index.
All right.
So here,
I differentiated an with respect to xm.
And then just multiplied it by the xn dot,
which is 0.
And then I multiplied by the xn dot,
which is already here.
It's already there.
Just differentiating this whole thing with respect to xm.
And that's what you get.
All right.
Now,
that's a lot of stuff.
That's a lot of stuff
for a simple equation of motion.
But we can combine it together now.
Let's combine it together.
And it doesn't look so complicated.
Okay.
So let's get it complicated once we combine it together.
First of all,
the left-hand side,
the left-hand side looks like an acceleration.
u is a velocity.
It's a 4-velocity,
but it's still sort of a velocity.
For slow particles,
it looks like a,
particles aren't moving too fast.
It's just,
sorry,
the left-hand side is an acceleration.
It's the derivative of a velocity.
So it looks pretty much like an acceleration.
So we'll put that on the left-hand side.
And it looks like ma.
It's a little bit different because that's the 4-velocity,
not the 3-velocity.
But for slow particles,
it's approximately the same.
So the left-hand side looks like ma.
Let's leave it that way for the moment.
We're going to come back to it and change it.
We're going to come back to
it and manipulate it a little bit.
Let's put everything else on the right-hand side.
What's on the right-hand side will
evidently and obviously be the force.
Alright?
ma is equal to the force.
So let's put everything on the right-hand side.
And I'll temporarily just call this
mass times the mth component of acceleration.
With a little bit of cheat
here about what I mean by acceleration.
A little bit of looseness
in what I mean by acceleration.
But whatever it is,
it's the left-hand side of the equation.
And that is equal to.
Now on the right-hand side,
I'm going to push everything over to the right-hand side.
And there's two kinds of terms.
One contains a velocity.
This one and this one contain velocities.
And this one and this one do not contain velocities.
This is x0.
They do not contain velocities.
Let's first take the two terms.
I'm just going to say,
to make that right-hand side,
the equation look more like the left-hand side,
would you like to take the
e out and change the sign?
No.
Put it in brackets?
Why?
Because then it will look the same as the other.
Sorry,
I don't want to write 3 equals 3.
I want to write 3 equals something else.
But I don't want to write something which on the
left-hand side is the same as on the right-hand side.
Why would I want to do that?
Okay,
I'm not sure.
I'm missing your point.
Alright.
Let's take the pieces which don't depend on the velocity.
So first is this one.
When I transpose it to the right-hand side,
it's going to have a plus sign.
dA m by dx0.
Did I get that right?
Yeah,
dA m by dx0.
That's one term that comes from
putting this on the right-hand side.
And then minus dA 0 by dxm.
That's a kind of neat little expression.
dA 0 by dxm.
dA m by dx0.
x0 of course means time.
So this is dA m by
d time minus dA time by dxm.
Nice little symmetry to it.
The second term,
where is that?
It's the one that involves the velocity.
And that is going to
be plus dA m by dxn.
That will multiply xn dot.
But there's another term which also involves xm dot.
And that's minus dA n by dxm.
There's an electric charge,
E.
And there's an xn dot.
So what do I have?
I have mass times acceleration is
equal to a first term here,
which doesn't involve any velocity.
It does not involve a velocity.
It's not a velocity-dependent force.
It's a force which only depends on position,
because position and time in general,
but not velocity.
And this object has a name.
It's called capital E sub m.
Again,
since it's a space component,
it doesn't matter if it's upstairs or downstairs.
This is called a lateral force.
It's a force that's in
the center of the electric field.
Bluntly,
that's the electric field.
The electric field is a combination of time derivatives
of the space component of vector potential
and space derivative of time
component of the vector potential.
That's the notion of an electric field
as described in terms of a four-vector vector potential.
What about the other term?
Whatever the other term is,
it's quite apparent that it multiplies a velocity.
Well,
I'll tell you exactly what it is now.
It is plus v,
the velocity,
cross the magnetic field.
It's the mth component of v cross b.
The mth component of v cross b.
Let's check that.
Should we check that and see
that it really is v cross b?
Velocity.
V meaning velocity.
In other words,
x dot.
I think I will not check it at the moment.
I will leave it for you,
but since I haven't yet told you
the detailed connection between this object...
Does everybody recognize what mathematical structure
dA m by dX n minus
dA n by dX m is?
It's the curve.
It's the curl.
It's the curl of the vector potential.
Let me write down the components of the curve.
This is the curl of the vector potential.
And the curl of the
vector potential is the magnetic field.
So it's not obvious at the
moment that this is the cross product
of a velocity and a magnetic field.
But if we recognize that this is the curl,
we'll come back to that,
that this is the curl
of something,
and that the curl of the
vector potential is the magnetic field,
this is some kind of expression involving the product
of components of the magnetic field
with components of the velocity.
Let's wait a little bit and later
on prove that this is v cross b.
We have to make some identifications
of what b is and so forth.
But that's what's going on.
That's the Lorentz force law.
Derived from a vector potential.
Okay,
so this is b.
Just to tell you how it works.
The a...
Well,
no,
let's wait on this.
Let's wait on the identification,
the detailed identification with the magnetic field.
It's pretty clear that it looks something like that.
Okay.
One last step.
This wasn't truly the acceleration.
It was not truly the acceleration.
It was neither the second derivative
with respect to time of x.
It was not that.
That would be the derivative
with respect to time of v.
But it's the derivative with respect to time of u.
u itself is a derivative with respect to proper time.
So we have this funny mixed thing here.
d by d ordinary time times u,
which is a derivative with respect to proper time.
I would like to write
everything in terms of proper time.
Proper time is a nice relativistic
description of time along a trajectory.
All right.
So let's replace,
let's rewrite this,
the left side of it,
as m d u sub m by d tau.
But that's not right.
It's not that.
We have to multiply this by d tau by dt.
The derivative of u with respect to t
is the derivative of u with respect to tau
times the derivative of tau with respect to t.
Derivatives...
Derivatives are really ratios.
Ratios of differentials of
functions with respect to differentials
of the independent coordinates.
So this left-hand side has
an extra d tau by dt.
All right.
Let's follow it through.
That's equal to exactly what we have over here.
I'm not going to rewrite it.
Times x dot n.
Now what is x dot n?
x dot n is the derivative
of x with respect to t.
So let's put here the xn by dt.
And here we have d tau by dt.
What do I want to do with this?
Anybody have a suggestion how to neaten this up?
Second derivative of u.
I'm going to multiply both sides of
the equations by d t d tau
to get rid of it on this side.
So we multiply by d t d tau.
Both sides.
d t d tau here.
That will put a d t by d tau here.
And it will put a
d t by d tau here.
What is this thing?
That's the xn by d tau.
Which is un.
Not vn,
but un.
So we have over here plus e times d a
m by d xn minus d a n by d xm
times the four vector of velocity.
On the left hand side,
this is the,
we have the derivative of the four vector of velocity.
On the right hand side,
we have the four velocity itself.
Now what about d t by d tau?
Does that look like it belongs there?
Let's write the a m by d x
n minus d a n by d xm.
And now let's write d t by d
tau as d x n by d tau.
We know that's what it is.
d tau.
And the x n by d tau is
just the fourth component of the four velocity.
This is the fourth component of the four velocity.
It's u nought.
So we have,
oops,
I lost the charge here.
There's the charge.
We have something that's shaping up in an interesting way.
Mass times proper acceleration.
We could also write this as m
d second x m by d tau squared.
u is d x by d tau.
The u by d tau is the second derivative.
This is a form of an acceleration,
but it's an acceleration where we're
accelerating relative to tau rather than t.
The second derivative of the coordinate with respect to tau.
So it's called the proper acceleration.
And it's a four vector.
The important thing is this is a four vector.
On the right hand side,
we have something which involves an electromagnetic field.
This is the electric field.
This is the magnetic field.
And a fourth component,
and a four vector of velocity.
I'm going to write this in the form electric charge.
Times f.
Let's see if I can get this right.
f mu nu u nu.
Okay,
I'm not quite right yet.
Not quite right yet.
I'm going to write this in the form m.
Alright.
We've seen this object before,
I hope.
I think I point,
I think we talked about this object before.
Oh,
one last thing.
One last thing.
This m index here,
is it an upstairs index or a downstairs index?
It doesn't really matter.
Alright,
it doesn't really matter.
But if we want to rephrase
this as a four vector equation,
we would like to put a mu here,
and put mu nu.
Now that's a properly constructed four vector equation,
and I will tell you what these things are.
This here is the acceleration,
the mu component of acceleration.
It's a four vector.
Oh,
why am I allowed,
oh,
by the way,
this,
how many equations are here?
Three.
How many equations are here?
Four.
Why was I allowed to put the other equation in?
Well,
if equations are Lorentz invariant,
and if the first three components of a four vector
are equal to some other first three components,
if the first three components
of a four vector are zero,
then it's automatically true that the fourth component,
in other words,
if three components of a four vector equation are correct,
it is automatic that the fourth component is also correct.
That's the consequence of Lorentz invariance,
and since we ensured Lorentz invariance by requiring
that the Lagrangian was Lorentz invariant,
we are allowed free to put in the fourth component.
Yeah?
Can I ask you a question?
You said,
um,
isn't the constant vector like one,
two,
three,
four,
isn't that Lorentz invariant?
The constant vector,
no.
What is it,
what is a constant vector?
No.
A u of x is equal to constant one,
two,
three,
four.
You mean like the numbers one,
two,
and three,
and four?
Yes.
Numerical values one,
two,
three,
four?
Is that,
is that a four vector?
No.
No,
no,
no.
But it's sort of something.
Let's go back to three vectors for a moment.
Let's just talk about three vectors.
Supposing I have,
let's even do two vectors,
two component vectors.
Is the vector whose components are one and two,
what does that mean?
That's a vector whose x components are one and two.
So what does that mean?
It means that the vector whose component is one
and whose y component is two.
But if looked at from another frame of reference,
in fact,
let's pick a frame of reference,
a particular frame of reference.
Let's pick a particular frame of reference
that happens to lie along this axis here.
All right?
In the rotated frame of reference,
the x component of this vector is zero.
And the y component is what?
Square root of three?
One plus two?
No,
one,
no,
no.
Square root of five.
So no,
the thing one,
two
could be the components of a vector
in some particular frame.
But it's not,
it's not a thing
which is a four vector in that
it has the same components in every frame.
No thing which has numerical values like this
is a four vector.
The components of a vector transform.
So no numerical set of coefficients
defines a four vector.
It's a thing which transforms.
Okay,
yeah?
Um,
and we're trying to get rid of
uh,
dt in terms of
Right.
Except in the
electric field where we have
dA m d x naught.
No,
no,
okay.
That's in here.
It's in here.
Let's take a look at it.
Yeah.
Um,
take this term over here.
Now,
the structure that appears
here is a sum.
What's that a sum over?
It's a sum over nu.
Let's write it down sp-
exactly.
Let's take mu.
Let's take the case where mu
is equal to m.
Mu is a space index.
And let's see what this reads.
Let's take the case mu equals m.
In other words,
that mu is a space index
and not a time index.
And this is m,
the mass,
times d second,
x m by d tau squared,
is equal,
electric charge,
now,
mu is m,
so this is f m,
and then nu.
Nu can be any one of four indices.
However,
it can't be m.
Why can't it be m?
It's because f is anti-symmetric.
We'll come back to that.
It can't be m.
The diagonal components of f are zero.
They're zero.
So,
the next thing it can be
is zero.
Nu could be zero.
And then this would be u zero.
And then there's the other possibilities.
Plus f m,
let's call it n,
u n.
What is this over here?
f m zero is exactly what's written here.
This is f m zero,
times u zero.
So,
this is already here,
in this expression here.
Right,
I understand.
My question has to do with the fact
that d a m d x naught
is really just the same as saying
d a m d t.
Yes.
Right?
And my question was,
I thought we were trying to
get rid of all the d t.
not in an expression like this over here.
no,
we weren't trying to get rid
of all of the d t's.
We were only trying to rewrite,
look,
there's d t's here.
This is d t by d tau.
We were trying to write the thing in a form
which is manifestly a four vector equation.
Alright?
The left hand side is a four vector.
It's the derivative,
alright,
x mu is a four vector.
The x mu by d tau is a four vector
because tau is a scalar.
And the second derivative is a four vector.
Alright,
so this is a four vector.
And I've just manipulated it around
until everything is written in
terms of four vector notation.
This is not the important thing here.
The important thing here is that because...
Alright,
let's go through the principles again.
I lost the principles,
but the principle,
first of all was the principle of locality.
Locality.
The principle of locality
comes down to the statement
in terms of equations of motion
that the equations of motion are differential equations.
It says that the force only affects things
nearby at the same time,
or almost the same time.
It says that that's what a differential equation is.
It's things are only affected
by the force at a given time
in the neighborhood of that time.
That's differential equations.
That's the first statement.
Locality tells us that the equation of motion
is a differential equation.
What could you have that
wouldn't be a differential equation?
You could have that the acceleration at one time
is related to the force at a completely different time.
That would be bizarre,
but you could have it.
The acceleration at one time related to the force
at a different time,
or even worse,
not the acceleration,
but the difference of velocity
at two completely different times
could be equal to the force at some third time.
That's exactly the sorts of things that locality forbids.
It says the acceleration of the time
is equal to the force at that same time.
Alright,
differential equations.
Second,
Lorentz invariance.
The equations can be written as four vector equations.
That's the important thing here.
Four vector equations
that they're Lorentz invariant.
F mu nu is a rank two tensor.
It's a rank two tensor.
I'll put up on the blackboard here its components
in terms of electric and magnetic fields,
and then you can go feed them into here
and check that this really is the Lorentz force law.
This is the Maxwell tensor,
the field tensor.
Nu runs this way.
Mu runs this way.
In other words,
this is mu equals zero,
one,
two,
three.
Nu equals zero,
one,
two,
three.
And we're going to write
all sixteen components
there really aren't sixteen independent components,
but all sixteen components
in a four by four array here as a matrix.
One question.
Is this the way you're writing it?
Is that convention standard for a mixed tensor like this?
No,
no,
no.
This is actually F mu nu.
The only difference now,
remember,
when you raise an index,
if it's a time index,
you get a minus sign.
If it's a space index,
you don't.
So once you've raised it,
you don't know which one was first at the bottom,
so to speak.
Like,
if I were to write that tensor,
it...
There'd be a sign change in some of the components.
Yeah.
And basically,
it's just a question,
if you raise the mu index here,
if mu is time component,
there's a minus sign.
If mu is a space component,
there isn't.
So I'll let you...
It's a good exercise to sort out
the relationship between the things
of the upper and lower indices,
but I'm not going to dwell on it now.
I just meant about which are
the rows and which are the columns.
Yes,
that's why I wrote this down.
Mu runs this way,
nu runs this way.
So there's mu and nu.
For example,
F naught 3.
That would be mu equals naught,
which would be up at the top here,
and nu equals 3.
So suppose I'm given some general tensor,
A sub sigma rho,
one at the bottom,
one at the top.
How do I know which ones are
the rows and which ones are the columns?
You just make it up.
You don't make it up.
You just decide on a convention.
That's why I was asking,
is there a standard convention?
No,
this is probably the standard convention,
but it's just a way of displaying them.
It's just a way of displaying them,
and I'm using the convention that nu runs
horizontally and mu runs vertically.
But you just read them off.
Nu equals 3,
mu equals 1 would be over here.
So I'm just displaying them for you.
On the diagonal,
they're all 0.
It's easy to see that the diagonal elements are 0.
It's an anti-symmetric tensor.
Then we have,
I think it's minus E sub x,
minus E sub y,
minus E sub z.
These are the components of the
electric field.
And since it's anti-symmetric,
that means it's plus E sub x,
plus E sub y,
plus E sub z.
And now the magnetic fields come in
in a slightly surprising way,
but not too surprising.
This one is Bz minus By and Bx,
and this one is minus Bz,
because it's anti-symmetric,
plus By and minus Bx.
This is the electromagnetic field tensor,
and it helps you identify which components
of this complex over here,
F mu nu,
are equal to which components of electric field.
So what you can do with this is
you can now take this and plug it in
to this equation and see,
let's just see what it says.
This is a space-time mixed component.
The space-time mixed components
are in the upper row here.
Time,
space.
Everything in the upper row has one index,
which is time,
but then these three things are space components.
So that means there's an electric field.
This component,
a mixed space and time thing,
is an electric field.
Those are those.
And this is a space-space component.
M and N are both space,
and the space-space components
of this tensor are over here.
So those are components of the magnetic field.
Now we'll come back to that.
But,
yeah?
Which form of energy,
what new mu is anti-symmetric?
Either with two upper or two lower.
They're both anti-symmetric.
One upper and one lower,
not quite.
There's a...
Maybe,
I don't know,
do I take that back?
I think by accident it may be anti-symmetric.
I think all that changes if
you have one upper and one lower
is the electric fields change sign
relative to the magnetic fields,
I think.
Magnetic fields stay the same,
the electric fields change sign.
So I think actually they're all anti-symmetric.
I think.
It's only one.
Is that wrong?
When you get one lower or one lower,
they all change sign.
Hm?
Am I wrong?
That doesn't sound right to me,
but...
All right,
I don't want to think about it now.
For sure the things with two lower indices
or two upper indices
are both anti-symmetric.
Right.
And...
I think with one upper and one lower,
the magnetic part is anti-symmetric,
the electric part is symmetric.
Yeah,
I think that sounds right.
I think that's right.
I don't want to think about it.
It would get me distracted.
Right.
Okay,
so that's the basic setup.
But we've never gotten yet to gauge invariance.
I went back through what we did last time
because I thought it was sufficient
to understand the basic principles.
and so...
illustrative of the basic principles
that to go on beyond it without understanding it
would be,
you know,
a big loss.
Okay,
now let's go back...
Let's go back to the action for the particle
along the trajectory,
the electromagnetic part of it.
And discover the concept of gauge invariance.
First of all,
what is an invariance?
An invariance is a change in a system
that doesn't affect anything.
Or it doesn't...
That doesn't affect the action.
Strictly speaking,
it's a change in a system
that doesn't affect the equation of motion.
For example,
I'll give you some examples.
F equals mA is an equation of motion.
It has exactly the same form,
but it's not the same.
So,
if you want to translate the x-axis,
translate the center of the x-axis
from one coordinate from one point to another.
That's translation invariance.
You can rotate coordinates.
Let me give you another example.
Let's take a field Lagrangian now,
a field theory.
The simplest field theory that we wrote down
a couple of lectures ago.
It had an equation of motion which was
d second phi,
this was the theory of a scalar field,
times dt squared,
minus d second phi by dx squared,
and we can put y squared
and z squared in if we want,
is equal to zero.
I won't put it in.
This has a Lagrangian which is given by d phi,
d mu phi,
I think it's with a minus sign.
Maybe it's minus one half of this.
Not important right now.
What kind of invariance does this equation of motion have?
Well,
it has all kinds of invariances,
including Lorentz invariance,
but it has an additional invariance,
which is supposing you just take the field phi
and add a constant to it.
In other words,
supposing I take a field
which is a solution of the invariance,
add the equation of motion,
and just add a constant.
Everywhere is the same.
Does the result satisfy the equation of motion?
Well,
sure it does.
Why?
Because the derivatives of a constant are zero.
So if I take phi,
if I take phi,
and I know that phi satisfies the equation of motion,
and then add a constant,
it still satisfies the equation of motion.
Why?
Because the derivatives of a constant are zero.
Alright?
This is an invariance of
the equation of a scalar field,
of a very simple scalar field.
You can add a constant to phi,
and it doesn't affect the equation of motion.
You can see it in the action.
Here's the action.
Supposing I add a constant to phi.
What happens to the action?
Nothing.
The derivative of the constant doesn't contribute.
So,
if the action is such
or if you have a particular action,
and you have a field configuration
which minimizes the action,
if you add a constant to the field,
it will still minimize the action.
So adding a constant to a field is a symmetry.
It's an odd symmetry.
It's the one you're not used to.
But it's a symmetry.
What happens if I add
to the right-hand side of the equation
Let's see.
I think we're used to putting plus.
I think we called it plus mu.
So,
I'm going to put mu squared phi.
That was the equation with
an extra term in the Lagrangian
which was minus mu squared over two phi squared.
Do you remember that?
We talked about an equation,
a field equation,
where we added phi squared to the Lagrangian.
This is also a scalar.
Perfectly legitimate thing to do.
Now what happens if we
add a constant to the equation?
Is it a solution anymore?
It is not.
There's no change in this term.
But if we add a constant to phi,
this term changes.
Look at the action.
This term doesn't change if
we add a constant to phi,
but this one does.
Phi squared is not the same
as phi plus a constant squared.
So,
with the extra term,
this is not a symmetry.
This is an example of
a
symmetry
of an equation of motion,
which depends on whether the Lagrangian
does or doesn't contain this factor.
You can do both.
Both are perfectly legitimate.
Sometimes you have a symmetry,
sometimes you don't have a symmetry.
Question?
Yeah.
In the previous example,
we didn't add in the...
Invariance.
I should use the word invariance.
What if you said,
well,
phi add x?
Now that satisfies the equation,
but it doesn't satisfy the action.
You just want to add x to here?
Well,
x is not a field.
It's just a number.
I mean,
it's just a...
You want to do it to the action?
Phi is a function of x and t,
right?
Phi is a function of x and t.
So,
if you say,
okay,
change phi to be phi plus x,
which is still a function of x and t.
Oh,
oh,
I see what you want to do.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Now,
phi,
you want to say phi goes to phi plus x,
let's say.
So that satisfies that differential equation.
It does.
But it doesn't satisfy the...
It isn't invariant under the action.
Uh...
First derivative.
Let's see.
That does,
yes,
that does,
let's see,
that does satisfy...
It doesn't satisfy this equation.
No,
no,
forget that part.
Yeah,
right.
It satisfies that equal to zero.
It does.
That's right.
But it doesn't satisfy...
The second derivative of this,
yes,
that's correct.
So let's see what happens.
So let's,
we're getting rid of this.
Right.
And now,
this thing stands for phi
dot squared minus dx phi squared.
So,
if we add,
let's see what happens.
Ah,
okay,
I see what happens.
You're right,
and it's something we're going to come to soon enough.
Um,
if we add,
let's see what happens.
We have dx phi plus x squared,
okay?
That's what you want to do.
All right?
That doesn't change this term because x,
the derivative of x with respect to t is zero.
All right,
so it changes the action
by an amount which contains d,
ah,
sorry,
dx phi squared.
Okay,
so that gives us,
um,
dx phi,
it looks like,
plus one squared.
Why did you say dx t is zero?
Hmm?
Why did you say d,
the derivative of x with respect to t is zero?
x and t are independent variables.
Yeah.
In other words,
if a function only depends on x,
then it doesn't depend on t.
Okay.
So that's,
all right,
so let's,
what does that do?
That adds to the Lagrangian two terms,
namely one,
that's one squared.
All right.
Now,
adding a constant to
a Lagrangian is completely insignificant,
does nothing.
So we don't have to worry about that.
And the other thing is that
it adds d phi by dx,
actually twice d phi by dx to the Lagrangian.
All right.
Adding a total derivative to the Lagrangian does nothing.
It doesn't change anything.
We haven't done any,
we haven't done that yet.
And I'm going to do that in a moment.
We're going to see exactly
why that's true in one moment.
Why adding a total derivative or a
derivative to a Lagrangian doesn't change anything.
We're going to come to it.
That's exactly where I was going,
and you sort of stole my thunder by,
uh,
by giving this example.
Okay.
All right.
Let's go back to the first example.
Let's go back to the
integral of a mu dx mu.
We need to get,
we need to keep going in order
to get to the concept of gauge invariance,
which was the point tonight.
Minus e to be exact.
All right.
Now,
consider the following operation on a.
We're going to add to a,
we're going to add to it,
the gradient of a scalar.
The four-dimensional gradient of a scalar.
a is a covariant vector,
and ds by dx mu is also a covariant vector.
And I'm going to ask whether
that changes the equations of motion.
Does it change the orbits that the particle will follow?
Does it make any change whatever
in the dynamics of the particle?
Let's add this to a.
We're changing a.
In other words,
we're considering two different a's,
an a without the ds by
dx mu and an a with it,
and ask what the effect on
the motion of the particle will be.
Well,
first of all,
it changes the action.
Let's see what it does to change the action.
It changes the action from the
original action to a new thing,
which is minus e times the derivative,
times the integral of a mu dx mu,
plus,
ds by dx mu,
dx mu.
It changes the action of the particle.
Here's the orbit.
The orbit goes from here to here,
from point one to point two,
and it introduces a new term into the action,
which is integral of ds by dx mu.
Now,
what is the integral of ds by dx mu,
dx mu?
It's the integral of the particle.
Each one of these little things
here represents the incremental change of s
along a small little piece of the trajectory.
Here's the trajectory broken up into small little pieces.
ds by dx mu times dx mu is the
change in s in going from one point to another.
If we add them all up,
it gives us the change in s
going from the initial to the final point.
So this expression over here,
the integral of it,
let's put the integral in.
Forget the electric charge.
It's there,
but forget it.
We're interested in this quantity over here,
ds by dx mu,
integrated.
That is equal to s
evaluated at the end point two,
minus s at the end point one.
It's just the difference of this function s,
this arbitrary function,
totally arbitrary function that I added in.
It just gives me s at
this point minus s at that point.
Now,
does putting in such an s into the vector potential
change the dynamics of the particles?
And I maintain no for the following reason.
I've changed the action by something which only depends
on the end points of the trajectory.
On the other hand,
if I go back to the basic action principle,
the action principle states that
we search for the minimum action,
we wiggle the trajectory,
and search for the minimum,
for the trajectory of minimum action,
but subject to the constraint
that we don't move around the end points.
That's the principle of least action.
Don't move the end points,
but wiggle the trajectory in between.
If you want to find the solution of the equations
which goes from point one to point two,
hold the point one and point two fixed,
and wiggle the trajectory around in between.
In wiggling the trajectory around,
this term in the action will not change.
So,
if you find the stationary point,
a minimum of the action,
it will continue to be a minimum of the action
when you put in this change of the vector potential.
The change of the vector potential,
this particular kind of change of the vector potential,
not any change of vector potential,
but the kind which is adding to the vector potential
the gradient of something,
the four-dimensional gradient,
that has no effect
on the motion of the particle.
Why?
Because it only affects the action
through the end points,
and the rule is
vary the trajectory keeping the end points fixed.
So,
S can be any scalar?
S can be any scalar.
But this is exactly the operation
of putting in a derivative,
adding a derivative to the action.
Adding a derivative to the action
typically doesn't change anything
because you can do the action
by putting a derivative into the Lagrangian.
It doesn't change anything
because when you integrate it,
it just gives you some end point contributions.
But here it is.
So,
what we've discovered,
we've discovered a principle of invariance
that the motion of a particle
in an electromagnetic field
does not change
if you take a mu
to a mu
plus dS by dX mu.
For any S,
it doesn't matter what S is,
this is called gauge invariance.
This is the concept of gauge invariance,
that the vector potential itself
can be changed without any effect
on the behavior of the particle,
of the charged particle.
Certain changes,
not every change,
certain changes,
those which are dS by dX mu.
Alright,
so adding a dS by dX mu
to a vector potential
is called a gauge transformation.
Where the word gauge came from,
it's a historical artifact
that had nothing to do with anything.
It just became a terminology
for some confused reason
in the beginning of the 20th century.
This was called a gauge transformation
and it stuck,
but it doesn't really have anything to do
with gauges.
Gauges meaning things that measure length.
That's what it had to do with.
You fail this course
if you say gwa,
that's a gauge transformation.
That's one of the main criteria.
It's a nuclear gwa.
Okay,
so is it really true
that the equations of motion
don't change if you add
to the vector potential,
such a gradient?
To find out,
we just go back to the equations of motion.
Here they are.
Notice that the equations of motion
do not directly involve the vector potential.
What they involve
is the field tensor F mu nu.
So any change that we make
on the vector potential
that doesn't change F mu nu,
which means doesn't change
the electric and magnetic field,
any change that we make
on the vector potential
that doesn't change
these quantities here
will not affect the motion of the particle.
So the last thing we want to do tonight
is show that the electromagnetic field tensor
is gauge invariant,
that it doesn't change
when you add dS by dX mu
to the vector potential.
That will establish,
we know that,
it's got to be true,
it's got to be true
by this argument,
but let's prove it directly.
What F mu nu is,
it's equal to the derivative
of the mu component
of the vector potential
with respect to the coordinate nu
minus the other order.
I can tell you now
do I have it backwards?
I might have it backwards.
I always forget.
Is F mu nu the
A mu by the X nu
or is it the A mu by the X mu?
But up to a sign,
this is correct.
All right.
Now supposing
we add to A
the derivative of S.
So what'll it do to this?
It will add to it
d by dx nu of the shift in A,
but what's the shift in A?
That's ds by dx mu.
And then we subtract off here minus d
by dx mu of ds by dx nu.
All I've done is
shift A by the gradient of a scalar
and add the resulting contribution into f mu nu.
Now,
what is this over here?
This is the derivative of a derivative.
It's the
second partial derivative.
This is d by dx mu
d by dx nu of s.
But what is this?
Same thing.
It doesn't matter which
order you're going to use.
You're going to use the derivative of the derivative.
So,
this is the derivative of the derivative.
This is the fact that partial derivatives
commute.
That it doesn't matter which
order you do the partial derivatives.
This is derivative
with respect to x nu of
derivative with respect to x mu.
And this is just the derivatives
in the opposite order,
but they're the same thing.
This is the unimportance of order of
differentiation.
So,
this is zero.
In other words,
f mu nu itself
does not change when you make a gauge transformation.
So,
this sort of closes the circle here.
And
what's really the main thing that I wanted
to illustrate tonight is that both the action,
you can see in the action principle
as well as in the equations of motion,
this new symmetry,
this new invariance,
invariance with respect to adding a gradient to s.
All right,
so now
you ask.
The natural thing to ask is what is
the gradient of the derivative of the derivative?
Well,
the answer is that the gradient of
the derivative is the gradient of the derivative
of the derivative of the derivative.
So,
the question is why the hell,
if all we were
trying to get was equations involving
the motion of particles and electromagnetic fields,
why did we bother adding in this vector potential?
Particularly if the vector potential isn't
unique,
if you can change it
and it doesn't affect the answers,
if you can change it and
it doesn't affect the electric and magnetic field,
why did we bother?
The answer is that
there is no way to write an answer.
There is no way to write an action principle
for the motion of a particle that does not
involve the vector potential.
There is no way that
we could have written the action
for the particle to go from here to here
directly in terms of the electric and magnetic fields.
It's only possible to write it by
the auxiliary device of the vector potential,
and yet the
value of the vector potential is not a
physically meaningful thing because if you change it
by a gradient,
the physics doesn't change.
Is there some utility in making that change,
like in solving certain problems or something?
Yes,
there's a lot of utility.
Sometimes you can add something to the vector potential
to make the problem simpler.
For example,
one of the things you
can do is you can always
choose an s to set any one of
the components of the vector potential equal to zero.
That
can be very useful.
Yeah.
In particular,
you can set the time component
to the vector potential equal to zero.
That
itself is also very useful.
In fact,
the way it usually goes is that by choosing different
s's to make the vector potential
have this property or that property,
you illustrate
different properties of the theory.
It's called choosing a gauge.
Choosing an s that does
something to simplify the vector potential.
The vector potential may illustrate one property of
a theory at the expense of obscuring another
property.
But by looking at the theory from
the point of view of all possible choices
of this gauge,
then you see all of the properties.
So we'll,
yeah.
And what about,
you know,
in the Lorentz invariance case,
that corresponds to,
you know,
the vector
potential of the vector potential?
So,
you know,
you're trying to measure something
in different situations in parallel.
Say it again.
The Lorentz invariance corresponds to
measurements in different reference frames.
Yes.
Does the gauge invariance have a similar...
No.
Not really.
That's a good point.
Some invariances have obvious
physical meaning.
And in particular,
it has physical meaning.
Physical meaning because you can imagine two
reference frames in the same problem and translating
between them.
Two physical reference frames,
yours and mine.
You're an observer,
I'm a...
Two sets of meter sticks.
No.
Gauge invariance is really not
an invariance in the same sense.
It's really a redundancy of the description.
Many descriptions,
all which are basically
equivalent to each other.
But from a mathematical point of view...
It is an invariance.
What's new about it?
What's new about it is it involves a function
of position.
If you were talking about rotation of coordinates,
you would not want to rotate
the coordinates at one place differently than
you rotate the coordinates at another place.
That wouldn't be an invariance of ordinary physics.
To rotate over here this way and
rotate over here this way.
You rotate...
You rotate by some angle once and only
once and there's no function of position involved.
Here there's a function of position,
arbitrary function of position,
a whole function of
position which is involved in the transformation.
That's what's called a gauge transformation.
So I don't know why we
lost our fundamental principles off the blackboard,
but you can
now add to locality,
Lorentz invariance,
action principle.
You can add to the...
You can add gauge invariance.
Gauge invariance is a feature
of every known fundamental physics...
Theory of physics.
Electrodynamics,
the standard model,
Yang-Mills theory,
gravity,
they all
have their gauge invariances.
So you showed us that by adding a...
I lost the word,
a gradient.
Gradient,
yeah.
By adding a gradient,
you don't change the physics.
Right.
Is that essentially the general statement of
gauge invariance that you can add a gradient?
Well,
it can get a little
more complicated depending on the system.
It can be a little more complicated.
The Yang-Mills theory,
it's a little more complicated
than this,
but in spirit it's the same thing.
We're going to find a
different way to define gauge invariance,
a way that has some more
interesting geometry and a
physical picture associated with it.
And when we understand
that,
we'll understand a better way of
thinking about it that's more general.
Yeah.
So you just use it as a
construct to highlight different parts of the problem?
It's a mathematical construct to
highlight different parts of your problem?
Which,
the vector potential?
The gauge invariance.
Yeah,
well,
yes.
Yes.
That's really where it is.
It doesn't actually affect the problem overall.
It's just a way to...
So you're using it to pinpoint parts of the problem?
Making a gauge transformation can be
a useful device for solving a problem,
for illustrating
a feature of the physics,
but it should not change the final answers.
Right.
And it does
not change the final answers.
So we started with a fairly arbitrary vector potential.
Mm-hmm.
And we got electricity and magnetism.
Does that mean other fields or other field
theories have a different kind of vector potential?
Mm-hmm.
Because A mu is just...
So what does another kind of vector potential look like?
Because it's too early for that
problem.
Excuse me.
I'm swallowing my cookie.
Let's go back to the first question.
Let's wait on that.
Typically,
they are vectors,
and they have...
They're usually called A.
They're almost always called A.
They have
an index mu to represent the direction of space.
So in that sense,
they look the same.
But they have some additional structure
to them associated with other symmetries,
and
we're not prepared to discuss it now.
And we may get to
it next week a little bit,
a
little bit,
but not yet.
Not yet.
Okay.
Any other questions?
Yes.
Yeah.
You said if we started with the fields,
we couldn't have done the action principle.
Is that the kind of
way we're going to have to...
If we started with the field...
Yes,
that's right.
There's no known...
I mean,
it's not
that there's no known.
It's an easy-to-prove theorem,
but I won't prove it.
But there's
a theory that you cannot express the action
of a charged particle in a Lorentz invariant
way in terms of the electric and magnetic
field and position and velocities of the particles.
That's a theorem.
So if you want to
do it in a Lorentz invariant,
in a local way,
and
so forth,
and preserve all of these principles,
the only choice is to introduce this vector
potential,
and then you find out that there's
this invariance that you can change the vector
potential without changing the physics.
So it's a very odd and peculiar situation where
you have to introduce some
auxiliary things into the equations,
but the auxiliary things
are things which can be
changed without affecting the physics.
Very remarkable,
and it pervades
physics.
It's all over the place.
Do we know why?
At the classical level,
there's no reason.
At the quantum mechanical level,
there is a deeper reason.
But I would say we've learned
that theories of this type have
a great deal of beauty,
symmetry,
simplicity that other kinds of theories don't have.
And
we don't understand why nature
always chooses these gauge theories.
But it is very pervasive.
So you can't measure A,
right?
That's right.
You can't measure A,
because if you could measure A,
you would know what
its value is.
On the other hand,
changing its value doesn't change any physics.
And
part of making a measurement is physics.
You can only measure things by physical processes.
If the physical processes are
insensitive to the addition of S,
of dS dx,
you can't measure
it,
right?
That's absolutely correct.
What can you measure about it?
Well,
you can measure
these things,
and maybe some other things,
but you can only measure those features which
are gauge invariant.
Okay,
so that's a...
a...
let's put it this way.
It's a totally non-obvious symmetry of electromagnetism,
and it's...
at this point,
it should be mysterious.
We'll try to illuminate it maybe next time a little
bit.
We should try to do a little bit of illumination.
I assume there are vector potentials that
give you change in the
way that you affect the other.
Oh,
yes,
the vector potential.
Any change that is not of this form will...
Okay.
Yeah.
Any change which is not
of that form will be detectable,
yeah.
Yeah.
In particular,
there are vector potentials which have
absolutely no effect on the motion
of particles.
If we just take the vector potential
itself to be the gradient of a scalar,
nothing
but the gradient of a scalar,
that will have no effect
on the motion of the particles.
Okay.
That should be clear to you.
If not,
think about it.
If the vector potential...
if the full vector potential is just
a derivative of S with respect to X,
it will have no effect
on the motion of particles.
Particles will move in straight
lines with no forces on them.
Right.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.