Stanford University
Alright,
what I want to do first,
I want to go through electromagnetic waves quickly.
Just plain electromagnetic,
plain meaning P-L-A-N-E,
not P-L-A-I-N,
plain electromagnetic
waves.
How do they fit with Maxwell's equations?
What do they look like?
I want to do it quickly
because I don't want to spend
a lot of time at it,
but I want to do it clearly.
First thing,
let's write down Maxwell's equations and
put them on the blackboard here,
on the
whiteboard,
in both their covariant,
the relativistic form,
and the non-relativistic form,
and then
we'll play with them a little bit.
There are two sets of Maxwell equations.
The first set
are identities that follow from
the existence of a vector potential,
and they're called
the Bianchi identities,
and they are del dot B equals zero,
and B dot,
meaning the time
derivative,
the time derivative of B,
if we want to,
I suppose I should really write it
as dB by dt.
Okay.
This is a vector quantity.
dB by dt is equal to
the curl of the electric field.
Okay.
Notice in every one of these equations,
incidentally,
there's always ...
In all sides of the equation,
all terms,
they always come differentiated.
That's important.
All right,
these are two of the equations,
and these two equations are the ones which
are identities.
These are identities.
In the absence of the Everestian identities,
the sight of theORB is the same.
let's take the theory in
the absence of charges and currents.
No charges and currents,
empty space.
Then the two other equations are
del dot E equals zero,
no charges,
and an equation that looks like this,
except E and B are interchanged,
but not quite.
So the other equation is dE dt
is equal to minus del cross the magnetic field.
Those are Maxwell's equations.
They have a lovely symmetry.
They're easy to remember.
Del dot B equals zero,
del dot E equals zero,
and one of them says that
the time derivative of the magnetic field
is the curl of the electric field,
and the other one says the
time derivative of the electric field
is the curl of the magnetic field.
The only thing you have to
remember is where the sign goes.
Okay?
And that takes a couple of minutes to work out,
but I'll leave it to you.
Okay,
these,
the equations on the right-hand side
can be written in a covariant form,
which is called the Bianchi identity.
d mu nu of f nu sigma
plus d nu of f sigma mu
plus,
did I get that right?
Yes,
I did.
Plus d mu nu of f nu sigma mu
plus d sigma f mu nu is equal to zero.
It's just,
this is just a way of rewriting these two equations.
Let's put it over here.
And these equations here,
which are not identities,
which are equations of motion,
they would change if you changed the Lagrangian.
We haven't introduced the Lagrangian yet,
but we will.
These equations have the form
d mu f mu nu equals,
in the case where there are no charges and currents,
equals zero.
Now,
this equation and this equation,
both these equations here,
all of them,
do have a right-hand side that I have not included.
This could be the charge density,
and on the right-hand side
here there would be a current.
I've written the equation in F,
F,
the opening and closing Style.
So when you have a charge density with two waves-
applied Vaseline,
going up Vaseli coment to the d-zone at these points,
and on top of it,
AS0度 F simulations here,
laissez Liquid in this solution on the Slaneaktu 그다음에,
and V to the latitude looking at dimension.
So that's what we've got here.
rotate our coordinates,
we can always rotate our coordinates
so that the z-axis is along
the direction of propagation of the wave.
Let's do that.
The wave is moving down the
z-axis,
along the z-axis,
or is it up the z-axis?
Maybe it's up the z-axis,
from smaller
z to larger z.
It has wavelength lambda equals 2 pi divided by k,
where k is called the wave
number,
and a plane wave of that form,
a typical generic plane wave of that form,
generally
has the functional form sine of kx minus 2 pi.
So we have a wave length lambda equals
omega t,
where we'll have to figure out
in a moment what omega is.
k can be anything.
Fixing k is fixing the wavelength,
and the wavelength can be anything.
Later on we will
discover that omega must be fixed in terms of k.
Omega is determined in terms of k.
And
each component of the field,
electric and magnetic,
all six components,
are...
you know
what?
I'm going to change this.
I said the thing...
The wave was going down the z-axis,
didn't I?
Z.
Z-axis.
This is a wave going down the
z-axis with wave number k,
frequency omega.
But which components of the field are we talking
about?
Well,
we will assume all components
of the field that are non-zero,
those which
are non-zero,
have exactly this form.
So let's write out a generic form of this type.
The x component of the field
as a function of z and t.
This is the x component as a function
of z and t.
We're going to set equal to some number epsilon x.
It's called the polarization
vector,
but it's just a number.
Times the same sine.
Sine kz minus omega t.
Incidentally,
pay no attention to whether I
write upper or lower case z.
It's the same thing.
It's
the same thing.
Ey equals epsilon y,
a different number.
Sine of kz minus omega t.
Ez equals
epsilon z.
The e here means a function.
Epsilon's just mean numbers.
Same sine.
Sine k times z.
So we're going to write...
Epsilon's just mean numbers.
Sine kz minus omega t.
Same for the magnetic field.
Bx,
we'll assume as the form
of a new set of numbers.
We'll call them beta.
Beta x sine kz minus
omega t.
I'm getting tired of writing them,
but we'll write them anyway.
Beta y sine ky
minus omega t.
And finally,
Bx.
Beta z.
And I think I'm going to
give up and not write it.
You know what to write
there.
Well,
I'll write beta z dot dot dot.
Okay.
Now first of all,
you might ask,
how
do I know that the magnetic fields and
electric fields have both the same kind of dependence?
Well I said it's a plane wave.
If I say it's a plane wave,
I mean that it's a sine.
And
I mean all components of the
fields are some sort of sine,
some sort of waves that look
like sines.
And this is a fairly generic thing to write down.
But you could also write down
cosine,
right?
You could write cosine.
I could even do something else.
I could make the electric
field sine and the magnetic fields cosines.
What would happen if I did that?
If I did
that.
Okay.
We go to the equations up there,
the Maxwell equations,
and we note that every Maxwell equation,
in particular those which
relate electric and magnetic fields.
Think about those.
The E dt equals the del cross B.
Alright.
When you write those equations,
in each one of them you will be differentiating
either with respect to z or with respect to t.
What do you get if you
differentiate sine with respect to z?
Alright.
So the left-hand side of any
equation in motion will involve a cosine.
You'll get cosine.
So the left hand side of any
equation in motion will involve a cosine.
The right hand side is also going to be differentiated.
For example,
the curl operation is a derivative.
And so if I differentiate the magnetic field,
I will also get cosines and I'll get something consistent.
I'll have that the left-hand side
of the equation is a cosine.
The right hand side is also going to be differentiated.
So that's going to help us to complete the equation.
Cosine,
the right-hand side of the equation is a cosine.
Supposing I tried to make the electric
field sine and the magnetic field cosine,
then I would get into trouble.
Differentiating,
for example,
with respect to time,
the electric field would give me cosine.
But differentiating the magnetic field would give me sine,
I'd be in trouble.
So you have to have,
if you're going to have sine here,
you have to have sine here.
Now,
I've made a number of conventional assumptions.
I've said that the wave is moving along the z-axis.
There's no loss of generality there.
I just rotate my frame of reference until
the z-axis is along the direction of the wave.
Okay.
I have also,
let's forget the relation
between electric and magnetic field.
I could put cosine.
Or I could put sine kz minus
omega t plus a constant in here,
a phase.
A sine is a wave that looks like this.
Can't I push the wave forward a little bit?
Push it up to here?
Well,
sure I can.
I can have a wave that's slightly ahead
or behind the wave that I wrote down.
But that's a question also of a convention.
I will simply...
If you want to start with a wave
which is slightly ahead at time t equals zero,
fine.
Just move your z-axis until the z-axis
is where the wave happens to be zero.
Once you do that,
again,
the wave gets back to this form here.
So this is pretty general.
But now,
I have not in any way
used any of the equations of motion.
So let's use the equation of
motion and see what they say.
First of all is W.
Let's take del dot e equals zero.
Del dot e,
what is del dot e?
Del dot e is partial of ex with respect to x plus partial
of ey with respect to y plus partial of ez with respect to z.
Alright,
now,
ex does not depend on x.
That's gone.
Ey does not depend on y.
I'm supposed to set the sequence to zero,
incidentally.
But ez does depend on z.
And so if I differentiate it,
I'm going to get something.
But I'm not supposed to get anything.
I'm supposed to get zero on the right-hand side here.
The only way to ensure that
is to say that epsilon z,
for a wave moving along the z-axis,
the z component of the field must be zero.
Otherwise,
the electric field...
It will have a divergence,
and that's not allowed.
So,
this is zero.
a plane electromagnetic wave moving along an axis
does not have any electric field along that direction.
Same is true of the magnetic field.
For that,
we use del dot b equals zero.
Same thing.
This is also equal to zero.
So,
we've used up the del dot equations.
Now,
how about the other equations?
Let's see what they say.
Let's pick one.
Let's take the e dt.
Oh,
one more thing.
One more thing.
Yeah.
This epsilon x and epsilon y are constants.
They don't vary.
They're just numbers.
All right.
They're vectors in the xy plane.
They're vectors in the xy plane,
which determine,
roughly speaking,
the ratio,
or the amount of ex and ey that's there.
You can always rotate in the xy plane.
The wave is going that way.
You can always rotate your axes,
the xy axis,
until one of these is zero.
For example,
you can always line up your xy,
and you can always set your xy axis
so that ex is not equal to zero,
but ey is zero.
These here are a little
two-dimensional vector in the xy plane,
and you can always rotate your coordinates so that
one of the two components is equal to zero.
That's,
again,
no loss of generality.
Just remember that we've used up whatever rotational freedom
we've had to set this also equal to zero.
Okay.
I cannot do it yet for the magnetic field.
I don't know what this implies about the magnetic field.
We'll find out in a moment.
So this is my starting point,
an electromagnetic wave with an
electric field that points along,
let's see,
the x-axis,
and which oscillates as it goes downstream,
or upstream.
Okay.
Let's now use the edt equals minus del cross b.
The edt...
equals minus del cross b,
and there's only one component,
well,
there's two components of it
that we have to worry about.
It's a trivial matter to see that
the z component of the equation is trivial.
Let's look at both the x
and y components of this equation.
First of all,
the x component.
The ex by dt is the
x component of minus del cross b.
What's the x component of del cross b?
That's equal to minus dy bz
minus dz by.
Alright.
So now we have an equation relating
the ex dt to bz and by.
But bz is zero.
We've already said bz is zero.
So,
we get rid of this.
And we just get
plus.
The ex by dt
is
dby by dz.
The first thing it tells us
is that
by cannot be zero.
We set ey to zero,
but now we find out that
by cannot be equal to zero.
So,
in other words,
the electric and magnetic field
cannot be parallel to each other.
You cannot have a situation where by
is not equal to zero if ex,
sorry,
where by,
you know what I mean.
Okay.
So,
the ex by dt,
so let's plug in now.
The ex by dt,
that's just differentiating that.
That gives us epsilon.
I'll just call it epsilon,
since there's only one of them.
Let's just call it epsilon.
And now,
we want to differentiate with respect to time.
That gives us
a factor of minus omega
with differentiating sine
times cosine
of omega
of kx minus omega t.
Everybody follow what I did?
I just differentiated this with respect
to time.
The time,
the time derivative gave me a minus omega,
and that's what we have on the left-hand side.
Say it again?
Right,
thank you,
kz.
Right.
Now we're going to differentiate by,
here it is,
and that's going to equal,
must be equal to beta y times k,
we're differentiating with respect to,
what did I write here?
I keep writing the wrong letter here.
kz.
By,
they're all kz,
times k,
times again cosine.
Alright,
the cosines cancel,
and what we find is an equation,
that by,
here it is,
by,
cosine cancels,
by is equal to minus epsilon x omega over k.
By is equal to minus epsilon,
this was epsilon x,
omega over k.
That's one fact.
Okay,
a second fact,
we can get by applying the
same equation to the y component.
Let's work out the y component here.
Alright,
so here we have dEy by dt,
but that's zero.
We've said that Ey is equal to zero.
What do we get on the right-hand side?
The right-hand side has,
dxb0,
minus dZbx.
Now,
do I have the sign right,
or do I have the sign wrong?
It doesn't matter.
It's either dxbz,
or d,
you know,
this is,
let's see,
this is the y component of the curl,
which means,
I think I have the sign right here,
but it hardly matters,
since the left-hand side is known to be zero.
It says the right-hand side is zero,
but bz itself is equal to zero.
And what is this going to tell me?
If I plug in bx,
if I plug in bx,
the only way it can be zero
is if beta x is equal to zero.
Alright,
that's the only way
that this can be equal to zero.
When I differentiate
bx with respect to z,
I'll get something,
non-zero,
unless beta x is equal to zero.
So this equation tells me
beta x is equal to zero.
And what does this say?
This says that if the electric field,
let's draw some coordinates now,
let's draw a picture of this wave,
what we know so far,
is our x-axis,
our y-axis,
and our z-axis.
And the wave is moving along the z-axis,
so it's a sine wave,
moving along the z-axis.
What this tells,
and we've assumed
that the electric field points along the x-axis.
Okay,
so the electric field looks like so.
At a particular instant of time,
it looks like that,
and it moves.
It moves,
of course,
with the speed of light,
which we've set equal to one.
I've assumed we've set equal to one.
So that's the electric field,
E.
And what these equations tell us
is that the magnetic field
lies along the y-axis.
There's no component along the x-axis,
has only a component along the y-axis,
so it looks along the y-axis.
It's also a sine wave.
I'm trying to draw this
in a sort of three-dimensional way.
Think of the magnetic field as lying along the y-axis,
oscillating as you move down the axis,
and the electric field along the x-axis.
So the first thing you learn,
well,
maybe not the first,
but another thing we've learned,
is that the electric and magnetic field
are perpendicular to each other,
and they're also both perpendicular
to the direction of motion of the wave.
The words for that is
that the electric and magnetic fields
are transverse.
That means they're perpendicular to the direction of motion
of the wave.
All right,
there's one more piece of information.
Here we used the E dt equals del cross b,
minus del cross b equation,
and we got a relationship between beta and epsilon.
Getting rid of the indices here,
there's only beta y is non-zero,
and only epsilon x is non-zero,
so we can write the equation as the equation
like this,
just in the form beta is equal to
minus epsilon omega over k.
That's the equation that comes from the dE dt equation.
There's also the db dt equation.
It looks exactly the same,
has exactly the same structure,
except for a minus sign,
and b and e are interchanged.
With no further work,
I can write down the corresponding equation.
Just interchange beta and epsilon
and change the sign.
And all it says is that,
if you do it right,
you'll find out that the other equation
is that epsilon is equal,
I think it's also minus beta omega over k.
There's a couple,
there are two signs,
the two signs conspire,
I think,
to give you the same relationship.
What does that tell you about epsilon,
what does that,
sorry,
what does that tell us?
It tells us,
do I have it right?
Epsilon is,
what I wanted to say is that omega,
oh,
yeah.
Omega over k equals one.
I was having trouble getting the words out.
It says that omega over k is equal to one.
It says it's the inverse of itself.
It says omega over k is k over omega.
The only way omega over
k can be k over omega
is if omega equals k.
All right,
so that's the last piece of information.
They have different units,
though.
No,
they don't if c is one.
Right.
If c is one,
they don't have different units.
Right.
This has,
omega has units of inverse time,
k has inverse distance,
and distance and time are the same.
All right,
so that tells me then
that I can simplify this
and just write it as
sine of kz minus kt,
or just sine of k times z minus t.
Everywhere.
It's a sine of kz minus t.
Now,
where would the,
where would the speed of light go into this?
k times z minus t.
Well,
it's,
of course,
the speed of light would go
right where it needs to go
in order to make the units correct.
So the speed of light would go over here.
Maxwell's equations
do have speeds of light in them.
I've left them out because,
you know,
when you're doing relativity,
you don't want to be bothered
with c not being equal to one.
Okay,
so that's an electromagnetic plane wave.
It's transverse.
The electric and magnetic fields are
equal to each other,
but orthogonal.
The magnitude of the electric and magnetic field
are equal to each other.
They're both beta.
They're orthogonal to each other,
and the whole blooming thing moves down the axis
sort of rigidly.
Yeah?
Question.
Are the electric and magnetic fields
always in phase with each other,
or can they be other phase?
In a plane electromagnetic wave,
they're always in phase with each other.
Circular polarization is a little more tricky,
but we'll do plane,
plane waves.
Yes,
they're in phase with each other.
I mean,
just as a metric,
but doesn't it,
mine decided to make them 180 degrees out of phase.
Oh.
Yeah.
That's,
yeah,
but they're not 90 degrees out of phase.
Right.
You can't,
right.
That's right.
Okay,
that's electromagnetic fields.
In phase,
is energy conserved?
Yeah.
Energy is conserved.
The fields go from maximum simultaneously
to zero simultaneously.
Yeah,
yeah.
Right.
But the energy that was over here
just moves to here.
It's not that the energy isn't conserved.
True enough,
the energy density at a point changes.
The energy density is related to the square
of the electric and magnetic field.
So if you stand at a point,
the wave goes by you.
First,
you see some energy,
and then you see no energy,
and then you see some energy,
and then you see no energy density.
But the total amount of energy,
energy over here,
after a little while,
is just replaced by energy over here.
A little later,
it's replaced by energy over here.
The only other thing you need to know
about electromagnetic waves
is that you can add them,
you can choose epsilon
to be any number you want,
big or small,
beta will follow,
and you can add waves
or subtract them,
even in different directions,
and you still have a solution
to Maxwell's equations.
All right,
I wanted to go through that
because it's kind of a little ridiculous
to teach a course in electromagnetism
and not write down
the electromagnetic plane wave,
which I suspect many of you have seen before.
So I was pretty quick about it.
Now we want to get on...
Yeah?
You assume that E and B
have the same phase.
No,
I don't need to assume
they have the same phase.
That's the statement that
both sides of the equations
involve a derivative.
So when you differentiate E
and set it equal to some other derivative of B,
you can't afford to have
a phase difference here and here.
Right.
Yeah?
I'm sorry,
I missed your argument on Y.
That last equation,
epsilon is just minus B at omega over K.
The second one there,
you're looking at it right now.
Yeah.
The top one I thought
would derive that because...
Hmm?
How did I get to this one?
Yeah.
Oh,
just by noticing that the...
that the other equation up there
has exactly the same form.
Except B interchanged with E.
Oh,
I see.
All right.
All right,
I'll let you go through that in detail.
It's easy.
You know,
it's fun.
Lagrangian.
As I've emphasized over and over again,
Oh,
I see.
all of the ideas of energy conservation,
momentum conservation,
relationship between those conservation laws
and symmetry laws
follow only if you start
with the principle of least action.
You can write down all sorts of differential equations
for various kinds of things,
and there won't be energy conservation.
There'll be no energy to be conserved
unless those equations are derived from
a Lagrangian from an action principle.
So since we are inclined to deeply believe
in energy conservation,
we should be looking for a
a Lagrangian formulation of Maxwell's equations.
Okay,
so let's go through the principles
and see if we can make our best guess
about what the Lagrangian is,
and then what we want to do,
the first set of equations on the left,
those are identities,
we don't need to prove them,
they just follow from definitions.
We want the second set of equations,
which,
let's add the right-hand sides to them.
Let's write it this way.
This is equal to rho,
which is also equal to the time component
of the four vector of current.
And now let's say,
let's put this on the left-hand side of the equation,
and then the right-hand side of the equation
is the current vector,
the space component of the current vector.
This is a vector,
this is a vector,
that better be a vector.
And on the right-hand side,
in the covariant equations,
this just becomes j nu.
The time component of this equation,
j naught,
simply gives you this one,
and the space components combine and conspire
to give you the other Maxwell equation.
Okay.
How do you get these equations from a Lagrangian?
So let's start with some principles.
The first principle is locality.
Oh,
you know what?
I'm going to take a digression first before...
No,
we're okay.
All right.
Locality.
Again,
that means whatever's going on
at one instant of time is only related
to a neighboring instant of time
and a neighboring position.
And that's always guaranteed
if the action is...
If the action is an integral,
in the case of a particle,
an integral along a world line,
in the case of a field theory,
an integral over four-dimensional space,
dx,
dy,
dz,
dt,
or d4x,
of a Lagrangian density
where the Lagrangian density depends on all of the fields,
however many fields are in your theory.
Let's just call them phi for the moment.
They're,
of course,
going to wind up being the vector potential,
but for the moment,
let's just call them phi.
There could be several of them.
I won't write several of them.
Phi will stand for whatever fields exist.
And also derivatives of phi
with respect to space and with respect to time.
I'm going to use the notation
that the derivative of a thing
with respect to x mu...
Sometimes I'll just write a d mu phi,
but other times I'll use an even more condensed notation,
phi comma mu.
That's a standard notation.
A comma means derivative,
and sub mu means derivative
with respect to the mu component of x.
This is a standard notation,
and I will use it.
So,
locality says the Lagrangian depends on phi
and phi mu.
Same phi.
Phi comma mu.
Now,
this doesn't mean one particular derivative.
It means all of the derivatives.
Phi mu is a generic symbol here.
It means time derivative,
space derivative,
all the derivatives.
That's the condition,
basically,
that the equations of motion
are differential equations
that relate things locally.
Next condition.
Next condition is Lorentz invariance.
Lorentz invariance,
that's simple.
The Lagrangian should be a scalar.
It should not depend on which frame of reference
it's evaluated in.
Okay?
It should be a scalar.
So,
for example,
for a single simple scalar field,
let's just go back over it again.
For a single simple scalar field,
you can write down lots of different things,
but some simple things would be
Lagrangian contains,
for example.
It could contain any function of phi.
Phi is itself a scalar.
Any function of phi is a scalar.
So,
let's see,
what did I call it in my notes?
Either u or v,
I don't remember.
u of phi.
It could contain u of phi,
any function.
And it can contain,
and it must contain,
derivatives.
Otherwise,
it's not a very interesting Lagrangian.
So,
it could contain things like...
It can't contain dx phi by itself.
That would be nonsense.
That's not a scalar.
That's the x component of a vector.
You can't put dx phi in
and expect your Lagrangian to be...
It can be in the Lagrangian,
but not just in this simple form.
What you can have is
d mu phi d mu phi r,
which is the same as phi mu,
phi comma mu,
phi comma mu.
And what's the difference between
the upstairs index and the downstairs index?
Does it mean anything to put this index upstairs?
It's just a change of sign for the time component.
So,
for example,
this object here,
which is a scalar,
is really minus phi dot squared
plus dx phi squared
plus dy phi squared.
And so forth.
It's just this change of
sign of time relative to space.
So,
assume you know about that.
This could go into the Lagrangian.
It's a good scalar.
And by convention,
this is really more of a convention than anything else,
we put a minus one half there.
So,
Lagrangian for a simple scalar,
this is not the only thing you could write.
This is just a simple thing.
Lagrangian could be minus one half
d mu phi d mu phi
minus any,
oops,
this should be a minus sign here,
minus any u of phi.
That's,
as I said,
that's not the most general thing you can write down.
Many,
many more things.
But this is a simple Lagrangian.
Last thing,
before we go on to electromagnetism,
let's just recall how you go from the Lagrangian
to the equations of motion.
These are the Euler-Lagrange equation.
For each field,
now I've only written one field here,
but there could be several fields.
We might add the Lagrangians
for several different fields together.
We might even put them
in in a more interesting way.
That mixes them together in various ways.
For each independent field,
in this case only one of them,
we begin with the partial derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to phi comma mu.
Derivative just means this derivative here.
And then we differentiate that with respect to x mu.
That's the left-hand side of the equation.
The right-hand side of the equation is
the derivative of L with respect to phi.
This is the immediate analog of the
Lagrange equations of motion for a particle,
which would read d by dt of partial of
L with respect to the time derivative of a coordinate
is equal to dl by the time by coordinate.
So what does this give?
I'll let you work it out.
It's very easy.
It just gives you,
we've done this before,
this gives d second phi by dt
squared minus d second phi by dx squared.
I won't bother writing y and z.
Dot dot dot y and z is
equal to minus du by d phi.
So we're going to do this.
Simple wave equation.
We've done this before.
I wanted to remind you because we're
going to do exactly the same thing,
exactly the same process with the vector potential.
It's more complicated.
I'll try to do it in
the simplest way that I can.
You know,
it's got more indices floating around.
One more principle.
Locality,
Lorentz invariance,
and when it comes to electrodynamics,
one more principle,
gauge invariance.
So let's put gauge invariance here.
For the moment,
let's set the current equal to zero.
No charges,
just electromagnetic field.
Gauge invariance tells us the Lagrangian,
or at least the action,
the action should not change
when you make a gauge transformation.
The simplest way to ensure that
is to make the Lagrangian itself
out of things which are gauge invariant.
The things which are gauge invariant are F mu nu.
The electric and magnetic fields.
The electric and magnetic fields are gauge invariant.
They don't change when you add to A.
And since the electromagnetic field F doesn't change
when you make a gauge transformation,
anything that you construct out
of F will also not change.
One thing you can't put in,
is there something you can't put in.
For example,
you can't put in A mu A mu.
Why not?
This is a scalar.
It's made up out of the fields.
Incidentally,
these mu's here don't mean derivatives.
These are the components of the fields A.
If I wanted to differentiate,
I've got to put that comma in.
The comma indicates derivative.
And I'll try to be careful about it.
This just means A naught squared minus,
or A x squared plus A y squared
plus A z squared minus A naught squared.
This is a scalar.
Perfectly good Lorentz invariant.
But it's not gauge invariant.
If you shift A in this way,
this quantity would change.
So this is no good.
Can't put it in.
Illegal.
Not gauge invariant.
You can put in A mu.
You can put in any component of F
mu nu in any way that you like,
as far as gauge invariance goes.
But as far as Lorentz invariance,
you've got to make a scalar out of it.
So how do you make a
scalar out of F mu nu?
Well,
there's a number of ways.
The rules are always the same.
Contract indices.
If you have two lower indices,
if you have a tensor,
some general kind of tensor,
T mu nu.
And you want to make a scalar out of it.
You raise one index.
And then you contract them by setting the indices equal.
And summing.
That's the general rule for making scalars out of tensors.
What would happen if you tried that with F?
That would equal F mu mu.
No.
Sorry.
What about taking F mu mu?
What is that?
Okay,
so what is that?
It's zero.
The reason is the following.
All of the components of F are
such that the diagonal components are zero.
F11 is equal to zero.
F22 equals zero.
F33 is equal to zero.
Raising this index here,
the second index,
that doesn't change anything.
It just changes the sign.
But the sign of zero,
you know,
zero doesn't change when you change its sign.
F11 is zero and so forth.
So taking F mu mu,
which means F naught naught
plus F11 plus F22 plus F33,
that's just plain zero.
Nothing there.
So that's not a good
scalar to put in the Lagrangian.
Just doesn't,
just zero.
Zero.
What else?
Is there anything else we could put in?
I thought I wrote down a couple of things,
but...
Well,
the first non-trivial thing that you can write down,
by first I mean the lowest order in F.
Nothing linear in F works.
You can try things which are quadratic in F.
And then you get something.
You can have F mu nu,
F mu nu.
That means something and it's not zero.
And let's see what it means.
Let's see if we can see what it means.
Let's see if we can work
out exactly what this quantity is.
Okay.
First of all,
there are the mixed components,
space-time mixed components.
There would be F nought n,
F nought n.
Alright?
That's where mu is nought,
time,
and nu is space,
n.
What is that equal to?
That's almost the square of the electric field.
The mixed components of F are the electric fields.
The only reason it's not
the square of the electric field
is because to raise the time component,
you have to change the sign.
So this thing here is equal
to minus the electric field squared.
So that's one kind of term that appears in here.
F nought n,
F nought n.
That's where mu is a time component.
Now,
actually this term appears twice.
It appears twice because you can
have mu be the space component
and nu be the time component.
Alright?
Here we had the first index being time,
the second index being space,
but there's the opposite possibility.
The first index being space,
the second index being time,
and that just gives us twice the same thing.
Alright,
so first of all,
this contains minus twice
the electric field squared.
But what else?
It also contains space space components.
For example,
F one two,
meaning xy,
Fxy times Fxy.
One two.
Raising space indices does nothing.
What is F one two?
In terms of electric and magnetic fields.
It's B three.
Z,
xyz,
one two three.
Alright?
So,
there is plus Bz squared,
but of course all possibilities enter.
B one two,
which enters twice.
It enters because there's F one two,
F one two,
and also F two one,
F two one.
So there's twice B squared.
And that's what it is.
It's twice E squared minus B squared.
It's twice B squared minus E squared.
Again,
there's a convention.
When I say there's a convention,
I mean it would affect
nothing if I didn't do it.
It would not affect the equations of motion.
But some ways along the line,
people started with definite
conventions about the Lagrangian.
The convention is such that the Lagrangian
begins with plus E squared minus B squared.
In other words,
there's a minus sign.
I would make this plus.
Let's make the equation correct,
first of all.
Mu nu,
mu nu.
Okay,
first of all,
conventionally one puts in a minus sign so that
the electric field comes in with a positive sign.
E squared minus B squared times a factor of two.
Again,
the factor of two only
occurs because each contribution appears twice.
F one two times F one two,
and F two one times F two one.
They're both the same thing.
Alright.
Second as part of the convention
is a factor of one quarter.
Minus one quarter.
And that makes this a
half E squared minus B squared.
Again,
there is no content in it other
than to make it consistent with ancient conventions,
the minus a quarter here.
What about F zero zero?
Is that zero?
That's zero.
F zero zero,
all the diagonal elements of F are zero.
F one one,
F two two.
So they're only the off-diagonal elements.
The off-diagonal mixed space-time components,
those are electric.
The space-space components are magnetic.
Alright,
so that's the Lagrangian E squared minus B squared.
It's Lorentz invariant.
That's local.
And it is,
in many ways,
not only the simplest thing you can write down,
it's also the correct thing for electrodynamics.
It gives rise to exactly these equations.
For the moment,
I have not included J.
Okay,
so let's see if we can see that.
It's a little bit of a nuisance,
but not too bad.
I'll try to take you through it reasonably simply.
First of all,
what are the fields?
Let's write down the Euler-Lagrange equation again.
Euler-Lagrange,
here it is.
E-L equation.
For each field,
each field,
and write down first,
the derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to phi,
comma,
nu.
Then,
differentiate the whole thing with respect to x,
nu.
Set that equal to the derivative
of the Lagrangian with respect to phi.
For each field,
you write a separate equation like this.
Now,
what are the fields that I'm talking about?
They are the vector potentials.
A naught,
A x,
A y,
and A z.
Four distinct fields.
Sorry.
Let's stick to either x,
y,
and z,
or one,
two,
and three.
All right.
Those are the independent fields.
Again,
these indices here do not correspond to derivatives.
What about derivatives?
Let's introduce a notation for derivatives of the fields A1,
A2,
and A3.
Well,
you can have the mu component of the field
differentiated with respect to the nu-th coordinate.
A mu,
comma,
nu literally means the derivative of
A mu with respect to x,
nu.
What about the field tensor in this form?
The field tensor,
where...
Let's write it down over here.
Here's the field tensor.
F mu,
nu equals the A mu by the x,
nu minus the A nu by the x,
mu,
which is the same thing as A mu,
comma,
nu minus A nu,
mu.
Okay,
you got the notation?
It saves writing a bunch of partial derivatives,
fraction bars,
x's,
which will simplify the comma means derivative.
Okay,
so now we can write down the Lagrangian
and try to work out the Euler-Lagrange equations of motion.
In working out the Euler-Lagrange equations,
we take the four components of
A to be independent separate fields.
Okay,
so there'll be a field
equation for each one of them.
All right,
so here we have it.
Minus is L.
L is equal to minus one quarter.
A mu,
nu minus A nu,
mu.
That's F mu,
nu.
Times the same thing again.
Oh no,
we have to put the index upstairs.
We have to put the indices upstairs.
And again,
I emphasize over and over,
the only difference between upstairs and downstairs
is a sign change when you move a time index.
That's all.
That's the Lagrangian.
Minus one quarter,
F mu,
nu,
nu.
Let's see if we can work out the field equation.
And let's pick a particular component
of A.
This is all there is.
That's it.
That's the Lagrangian.
And you can write it
out in detail if you like
in terms of derivatives of A.
The things which correspond to phi
are the A's.
And so we should now work out the Euler-Lagrange equations.
There'll be an equation for each component of A.
So pick a component.
Do you mind if I pick a...
What did I pick here?
It won't matter.
They all work the same way.
Yeah.
Let's work out the equation of motion
for the component A sub x.
A sub x,
or what's the same thing?
A sub 1.
Let's see if we can
work out the equation of motion.
The first thing we have to do
is we have to compute partial derivative of L
with respect to the derivative of L.
So we have to compute partial derivative of L
with respect to A
x mu.
That's the analog...
Where is it?
That's the analog of this object over here
except where phi
is given by A x.
And then we have to differentiate it
with respect to...
with respect to x mu.
But let's do that later.
We'll do that in a minute.
So what we need to calculate
is the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to specific derivatives
of specific components of A.
Let's take an example.
Derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to A x,
y.
That's a fairly generic...
This is the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to A x,
y.
Everybody understand what that means?
You look in the Lagrangian,
you look for A x,
y.
That means the derivative of A x
with respect to y.
And you differentiate the Lagrangian.
Okay,
where are we going to find
A x,
y in here?
Basically,
this one term
in the sum over mu and nu,
it's A x,
y minus A y,
x
times A x,
y minus A y,
x.
So let's write down what we get.
Let's see what we get there.
What we get is
minus one half,
I'll tell you why one half in a moment.
Derivative of A x with respect to y
minus the derivative of A y
with respect to x
squared.
There are lots of other terms in the Lagrangian,
but they do not contain A x,
y.
There are other terms,
but they do not contain A x,
y.
Now,
why do I have a
half here instead of a quarter?
Because there are two terms.
There are two terms.
There's one term in which mu
is x and nu is y,
and there's another term in which
mu is y and nu is x.
So you basically get two terms
for each combination,
mu and nu.
Alright,
now let's write this out.
Let's write this out in some detail.
Minus a half,
put a big bracket around it.
This is A x comma y squared.
I've squared this.
Now there's the cross term
minus A x,
y A y,
x
with commas in the right place.
Twice that.
I think I better clean that up.
Not very clear.
Let's try it.
Equals minus one half
derivative of A,
let's use the condensed notation,
A x comma y squared.
Just coming from squaring,
just binomial theorem.
Alright.
Then there's minus twice
the A x,
y A y,
x.
And the last term is plus
A y x squared.
This is the only term in the Lagrangian
which contains A x comma y.
It also contains other things,
but it's the only term which contains A x,
y.
So far,
this is the term in the Lagrangian
that we're interested in.
Now I want to differentiate it
with respect to this particular component.
It appears here.
Let's circle the places where it appears.
It appears here,
squared.
And it appears here,
multiplied,
not by itself.
A x,
y and A y,
x are different objects.
This is derivative of A x with respect to y.
This is derivative of A y with respect to x.
They are different objects.
We're searching out the dependence on A x,
y.
So what's the derivative of this Lagrangian
with respect to A x,
y?
Very simple.
We just...
The derivative...
Yeah.
The derivative of A,
of L with respect to A x,
y
from here is minus A x,
y.
What happened to the factor of half?
It's just,
this is squared.
So when you square,
when you differentiate a square,
you get a two.
Alright?
So this is A x,
y.
And now we also have this one over here,
which gives us minus.
We're differentiating with respect to A x,
y.
That gives us A y,
x.
So,
plus A y,
x.
It took a long time to get there,
but the answer is very,
very simple.
The derivative of L with respect to A x,
y
is just
minus F x,
y.
Derivative of A x with respect to y
minus derivative of A y with respect to x
is F x,
y.
So,
it was a long haul,
but let me write down
the general formula.
Oh,
incidentally,
this is also equal to minus F x,
y.
Space components can go up or down for free.
So let me write down now the general formula.
The derivative of a Lagrangian
with respect to A mu,
nu.
That's what we're going to need.
That is equal to minus F mu,
nu.
If we went through the same exercise
and did it for every component,
we would discover that differentiating
the Lagrangian with respect to
the derivative of A with respect to nu
would just give us F mu,
nu.
What's the next step?
The next step is
right over here.
We differentiate the Lagrangian
with respect to phi mu
and then differentiate again.
Okay?
So,
d by dx,
nu
of dl by dA mu,
nu.
That's just minus the derivative of F mu,
nu
with respect to x,
nu.
That's what's turning up here.
Alright?
Differentiating with respect to x,
nu
just gives us the left-hand side
of Maxwell's equations.
Now what else is there?
Well,
it's the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to the fields themselves.
That would mean the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to undifferentiated A,
but undifferentiated A doesn't appear
in the Lagrangian.
So that's it.
That's all there is.
The Euler-Lagrange equation is that
this is equal to zero.
Alright?
That is...
And that's it.
That's the whole story.
It looks much more complicated than it is.
You just take F,
the squares of all of the elements,
and that's the Lagrangian.
From it,
you work out the Euler-Lagrange equations,
and it's just two of the Maxwell equations.
The two of the Maxwell equations that happen
to have the j's on the right-hand side,
we haven't included j for the moment.
Alright?
The other Maxwell equations,
we don't have to do anything.
They're identities that follow from
the definition of A
and its relationship to F.
Any questions up till now?
This is not hard,
but you have to sit down and do it.
You have to sit down and do it,
work out the details of it,
because you...
It doesn't...
I'm sure it doesn't help to watch me do it.
I have no doubt that it doesn't help
to watch me do it.
Even if you make it
and manage to follow what I did,
you will forget it in five minutes,
but you won't forget it
if you go through the steps yourself.
Yeah?
The very top equation on the top board of it?
Yeah.
Can you set that equal to minus one half?
The difference in those two pieces?
Yeah.
Square.
What's going on there?
Are you assuming that the B field
is in the Z direction only?
I'm sorry.
Yeah,
in writing this over here,
no,
I just pulled out one term.
No,
no,
no.
Plus dot dot dot,
sorry.
Plus dot dot dot.
Yeah,
good.
Plus dot dot dot.
I just pulled out one term for examination.
Yeah,
yeah.
If you used two special coordinates
as an example,
if you used one at a time...
Yeah,
you would have gotten the same sort of thing.
You would have found the L by D,
let's call this naught here,
and this M would have been F M naught,
which would have been a certain component
of the electric field.
When I use two space components,
I get a magnetic field.
When I use one space and one time,
I get an electric field.
And if you reassign,
it doesn't change sign when it goes upstairs?
If you keep track of the signs carefully,
you'll find that it's,
that this is general.
If you push with two time components,
it cancels out or something.
Yeah.
Go through,
go through the indices
and you'll find out that they cancel out.
Question?
Yeah.
There,
it's covered now,
but where you wrote gauge invariance.
Yeah.
You said that,
you were setting the J equals zero,
so are we still...
I did for the moment,
for the moment,
but now I want to come
back to it in a minute.
Okay,
so we're still,
okay.
Yeah.
For the moment,
I,
all right.
Now,
in fact,
there is,
there are no gauge invariant things
that I can make up just out of the A's
that don't involve F mu nu.
And I've given you one example,
in fact,
that is the example that really does give rise
to the real Maxwell equations
to take the Lagrangian to be
this object over here.
The question now is how do you get
the right-hand side of the equation?
Where did that come from?
You have to add something to the Lagrangian.
You must add something to the Lagrangian.
That something had better involve the current vector,
the four component of a current vector.
If it doesn't involve a
four component of a current vector,
that's quite clearly,
uh,
not going to give you what you want.
So let's suppose that there's some pre-established
electric current.
That electric current means a charge density
and,
as I showed you last time,
a flow of charge,
space and time components.
So let's go back and,
uh,
recall the principles of charge conservation first
before we do anything else.
We have four components,
J mu,
which equal the time component,
which is charge density,
and the space components.
And remember what the space components are.
The space components are the charge per unit,
area per unit time passing through a little window
oriented along the M axis.
The charge flowing,
uh,
through a little window,
window oriented along the M axis,
or perpendicular to it,
the charge per unit time per unit area,
and that's called the J.
Okay?
The rule,
if you take a little cell,
and you say the charge in there,
of course the charge in there is proportional to
rho times the volume of the,
uh,
rho dxdy dz,
that's the charge in there,
and the rate of change of the charge in there
is just the time derivative of rho,
times dxdy dz.
If you say the only source of change
of the charge in that region
is charges which pass through the walls of the region,
okay,
then that gives you the continuity equation
and the continuity we worked it out last time
is rho dot,
that's the change of,
that's the change of charge in a little cell,
plus del dot J
equals zero.
Del dot J means partial of Jx
with respect to x,
plus partial of Jy with respect to y,
plus partial of Jz with respect to z.
Alright.
So,
to read this,
this is the change of
charge in the little infinitesimal cell.
This is the difference between the charges,
or the charges passing out through the x windows.
This is the charge passing out through the y windows,
and so forth.
And this is just the balance of charge
inside the box,
passing through the,
uh,
the boundaries of the box.
Alright,
we can also write this,
in a relativistic notation,
d mu J mu equals zero.
Okay,
that's the,
that's the equation.
It's called the continuity equation,
but it represents charge conservation.
It represents the idea that no charge disappears
unless it's accounted for as moving out of the region.
And in fact,
if you want to know where that charge went,
you go to the next box,
and you discover that the current
passing through this window over here
just adds charge to the next box.
So the charge that disappears in this box
goes into the neighboring box.
And that's charge conservation.
Alright,
now,
given the continuity equation,
there's another term,
another gauge invariant thing,
it's a scalar,
and we can write it down involving the vector potential,
and we'll check and see if it's true.
So,
what is this gauge invariant?
It doesn't look gauge invariant to begin with,
but we'll see that it is.
The action associated with the current,
as usual,
is the integral of d4x
of some kind of Lagrangian,
and I'm going to write down the very,
very simplest thing I can imagine,
J mu times A mu.
This,
of course,
means J mu of position,
spacetime position,
A mu of position.
That is a scalar.
It's the four-vector product of a four-vector
and another four-vector.
That's a scalar.
It involves a current,
and it involves the vector potential.
But it doesn't look gauge invariant,
does it?
How can we check if it's gauge invariant?
Well,
we can check if it's gauge invariant.
Incidentally,
by convention,
there's a minus sign in front of it.
That minus sign ultimately is due to Benjamin Franklin.
And,
you know,
as I said,
it is a convention.
Okay.
Why is this...
The Lagrangian here is,
of course,
J mu,
A mu.
Or this term in the Lagrangian is J mu,
All right.
Let's do a gauge transformation.
What happens to this?
It goes to minus the integral,
same integral,
d4x,
of J mu.
And now we're adding to A mu.
I'm going to add something to A mu.
I'm going to add ds by dx mu.
J mu,
ds.
This is the change...
All right.
What is this?
This is the change in action under a gauge transformation.
Under gauge transformation,
gt.
That's the change.
Doesn't look like zero,
does it?
If it's not zero,
then the action is not gauge invariant.
But it is zero.
Let's check that it's zero.
Let's see if we can see why it's zero.
Integral d4x...
What does that mean?
It means integral dxdy dzdt.
Let's write it down.
dxdy dzdt.
Now,
we have times J0 ds by
dx0 plus J1 ds by dx1.
Right?
Plus dot dot dot dot.
And this is integrated over all space.
I'm going to make one assumption.
I'm going to assume that
if you go far enough away,
there is no current flowing.
That all of the currents in the
problem are contained within a big laboratory.
So that J goes to zero far away.
If not,
if there's a current flowing at infinity,
you have to take it especially into account.
But,
you know,
for any ordinary experiment in a laboratory,
currents move and they're not
going to be in the laboratory.
So,
you can imagine the laboratory being isolated and sealed
so that no currents go out of the box.
In that case,
let's see what this gives.
Let's take a particular term.
Let's take the integral J1 ds by dx1.
There's one particular term.
And now that has to be integrated.
x1 means x,
the x,
the s by dx.
dx by dx.
dy by dx.
That is x,
the x,
the y,
the z,
the t.
Everybody know how to do this integral by parts?
You know how to do it?
There's an integral here.
Forget that the x,
the y,
the z.
other factor and change the sign.
We've done integration by parts many times.
I'll just remind you,
if you have an integral over x
of a thing times a derivative with
respect to x,
you can do the integral just
by flipping the derivative onto the other
factor and changing the sign.
So this is minus integral dj1 by dx1,
s,
dx,
and then the rest
of them dy,
dz,
and so forth.
What would happen if I did
the same game with the second term?
The second term is j2 ds by dx2.
Okay.
Well,
what happened is we would get another contribution,
and the other contribution
would be dj2 by dx2.
And supposing I did the third term,
ds by dx3 times j3.
That would
give me dj3 by dx3.
And finally,
there's the time component.
There's also a time integration
here.
If you do the whole thing,
you find out that the change
in the action is the integral
of the integral djµ by dxµ times s.
All right?
We started out with j times ds dx,
we integrated by parts,
and that put the derivatives on
the j instead of on the x.
That's all we did.
Did a trick to take the
derivatives and put them on the j.
That's
what we did.
what we have here.
And that's equal to zero because of the continuity equation.
So that's equal to zero.
So the change in the action,
if the current satisfies the
continuity equation,
and only if the current satisfies the continuity
equation,
then adding in this peculiar looking term,
where is it,
right here,
is
gauge invariant.
Does it satisfy the continuity equation or just you
have to have del dot j equal to zero?
No,
no.
You have to have rho dot
plus del dot j equals zero.
Okay,
let's go back.
Rho dot's the first form of the term.
Yeah,
yeah,
that's the first,
that's right.
That's the first term here.
You have to have all four of them,
right.
Or the sum of all four of them is equal
to zero.
But what's the first term?
That guarantees current conservation.
Okay,
that guarantees the gauge invariance of this
term.
So we can add this to the Lagrangian.
Now what does this do to the equations of
motion?
Well,
we haven't added anything that involves a derivative of A.
We haven't added
anything,
we've just involved something,
we've just added something that involves A itself.
Where's our Euler-Lagrange equations?
Our Euler-Lagrange,
alright,
so our Euler-Lagrange equations
have a left-hand side,
d mu of partial of L
with respect to A nu mu.
It's the left-hand side.
And the right-hand side is partial
of L with respect to A nu.
Okay.
So,
term by term,
component by component,
we write down the Euler-Lagrange equation
for each component of the field A.
On the left-hand side,
we know what that gave us.
That gave us minus partial
of F mu nu with respect,
sorry,
partial of F mu nu,
I think
it was with respect to X nu.
That's what we got from
the previous term that we had.
So,
we have the new term in the Lagrangian.
What is this one going to give?
Well,
we go back.
Here's the new term in the Lagrangian.
What happens if we differentiate it with respect to A?
We just take J.
Taking this term in the Lagrangian and differentiating
it with respect to a component of A,
you just get the corresponding component of J.
So,
we get this is equal to,
I think,
minus J nu.
The lesson here,
there's a couple of lessons,
many lessons.
First of all,
you can write Maxwell's equations in Lagrangian form.
That's important.
Second of all,
the Lagrangian has a very simple form.
Minus a quarter F mu nu
squared minus J mu A mu.
Third?
It's gauge invariant if and
only if the current is conserved.
What happens if the current is not conserved?
Then the Lagrangian is not gauge invariant,
and what you will find out,
that's a disaster.
Because it means that the equations
of motion are not gauge invariant.
If the equations of motion are not gauge invariant,
that's something really strange.
Because the left-hand side of the
equation of motion is certainly gauge invariant.
It only involves the electromagnetic field tensors.
And so that means something very strange is going on.
It just can't be the right equation.
It's not the right equation.
Does that satisfy the continuity equation?
The continuity equation,
yeah.
So,
it has to satisfy.
Well,
that's the conservation of electric charge.
You could imagine a world in which charge just disappears.
What would happen if charge just disappeared?
Well,
maybe nothing so terrible,
but Maxwell's equations couldn't be right.
Maxwell's equations could not be right.
You can derive,
it's a little exercise,
you can derive the conservation
of charge from Maxwell's equations.
Let's,
I don't know,
I'll take a risk and try to do it.
Try to do it from,
let's see if we can derive
the continuity equation from Maxwell's equations.
Alright,
so here's Maxwell's equations.
Rho equals del dot E.
And J equals the E dt plus del cross B.
Okay,
so let's first take rho dot.
What is rho dot?
It's equal to del E dot.
Right?
You differentiate,
time differentiate both sides.
Okay.
What do you think I ought to do next?
Del dot J.
Yeah.
Here we have del dot E dot.
Here we have E dot.
Let's see what happens if
we take the divergence of this.
What's the divergence of a curl?
Always zero.
Divergence of a curl is always zero,
so let's put del dot,
but now cancel this out.
So we have del dot
J equals del dot E dot.
But that's exactly what we have here.
So this gives us...
I hope it doesn't give us del dot
J because it should be minus del dot J.
What happened here?
Did I make a mistake somewhere?
Uh...
Rho equals del dot E dot.
Rho equals del dot E.
And E dot is equal to...
Is it del cross B?
It doesn't matter.
Plus J?
Do I have that right?
That's not going to make any difference.
That's not going to help me.
I think it's right.
E dot...
Unless I have a sign error there,
but I think it's right.
Let's try it out.
Let's see.
So Rho dot is del dot E dot.
That's for sure if Rho
is equal to del dot E.
And that's equal...
Oh,
and that's equal to nothing yet.
That's that.
Now we have E dot is this.
So let's try del dot E dot.
Divergence of the curl gives zero,
and that's going to give us del dot J.
I've got a sign error somewhere,
and I'm not sure where it is.
I have Rho dot is equal to del dot J.
Oh,
oh,
oh.
Um...
I have a feeling...
You can change E and B a little bit.
I have a feeling there's a sign error here.
I suspect there's a sign error here.
I don't remember now.
I can't do it in real time right here.
There's some sign error here because the right equation has to
be Rho dot plus del dot J is equal to zero.
So I'm not sure where the sign error is.
But you can see.
You can see.
Apart from the sign error,
the conservation or the continuity equation can
be derived directly from the Maxwell equations.
So,
in other words,
if Maxwell's equations are true,
the charge has to be conserved.
Just looking them up,
that should be minus J.
It should be minus J?
Yeah.
All right,
so this is one way...
Yeah.
Minus J.
Okay.
All right.
So I don't think that affected anything else we said.
Um...
And,
uh...
Right.
So you can't have Maxwell's
equations and have charge not conserved.
That's another lesson.
And the final lesson is that the charge
conservation is intimately connected somehow with the gauge invariance.
If it weren't for the charge conservation...
And when I say charge conservation,
I mean the continuity equation.
This one here.
Without the continuity equation,
Maxwell's equations couldn't be right.
So those are the things that go together and that,
uh...
That,
Are...
All right.
Question?
Yeah.
Um...
I'm trying to follow the logic,
the high order logic.
Yeah.
I'm curious to think about...
One sec.
That the continuity equation came from Maxwell's equations.
But then,
we're trying to prove Maxwell's equations now.
And part of that proof...
I mean,
you're trying to find the
Lagrangian for the Maxwell's equations.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
But to do that,
we have to have already assumed
Maxwell's equations to have the continuity condition.
You see what I'm saying?
Yes.
You could have started with the Maxwell's equations
and said they imply the conservation of charge.
Knowing that,
you could say,
Aha,
since I know the charge is conserved,
I know that there's a term J dot A,
which is gauge invariant.
And then discover that this is
the right term to reproduce Maxwell's equations.
But there's no sort of circularity
there in the reasoning that he's using?
That you use Maxwell's equations to set
up a Lagrangian to prove Maxwell's equations?
Isn't the continuity equation more fundamental than that?
It's just...
Yeah.
From the definition of current charge,
right?
Yeah.
I mean,
you can derive it from Maxwell's equations.
Yeah,
But it really just says charges don't disappear.
They don't just come and just disappear on you.
They only disappear out of a
region if they pass through the volume.
So these are all connected together.
You can start the logic this way
and say the basic principle is gauge invariant.
That requires J to be conserved and
then use this to derive Maxwell's equations.
And in fact,
then from Maxwell's equations,
you can see that J is conserved,
but there's no contradiction there.
There's no contradiction there.
Or you can start with Maxwell's equations and say,
what Lagrangian would give me Maxwell's equations?
And one of the things you discover from
Maxwell's equations is that J satisfies the continuity equation.
And so that tells you,
ah,
this thing which I have to put in to the Lagrangian in
order to get out the right-hand side happens to be gauge invariant.
So it depends on what you think is fundamental.
If you think gauge invariance is fundamental,
that tells you J has to be
conserved in the sense of a continuity equation.
If you think the conservation of charge,
that charges shouldn't disappear on you,
is fundamental,
then the continuity equation is
just an expression of that conservation.
It just tells you charges don't disappear.
And that tells you J is conserved.
Or you can think that
the Maxwell's equations are more fundamental.
And again,
using the Maxwell's equations,
you derive the continuity.
Things would be bad if they were contradictory.
It's good that they are.
And what is the minimal logic?
I would say the minimal logic
is the combination of gauge invariance,
Lorentz invariance,
and the Lagrangian formulation
lead you to this combination,
and then you derive Maxwell's equations.
But that's a matter of taste.
You could have started other places.
The fact is things fit.
Good.
Any other questions?
Yeah.
You showed us gauge invariance mathematically,
but it leaves me a little cold.
First of all,
the word gauge,
what is it talking about?
It's a historical anachronism that has no...
It kind of implies measurement or something.
Yeah.
We're going to...
It came from the idea that
you have a zero of gauge,
and you can usually rotate the
gauge to change where the zero is.
The zero of what?
Say the zero of pressure on a gauge,
or just a mark.
It comes from the idea of gauge pressure,
which is relative to...
The pressure that's relative to that of spirit pressure.
It came from a mistake,
actually.
which I cannot explain to you.
I can explain to you now.
I can explain to you perhaps,
depending on what lecture I give next week,
I will try to explain it.
But it came from a mistake.
The gauge actually had to do with measurements of length.
And in fact,
gauge invariance has nothing to
do with measurements of length.
It has to do with measurements of phase,
whatever phase is of the Schrodinger wave function.
It's got to do with mixing of quantum mechanics.
And Herman Weyl made a mistake.
He thought it had to
do with something that it didn't.
He very quickly corrected himself,
and the term gauge stuck.
But you can...
What I think was said was correct.
That gauge here meant defining a...
A zero of something.
A zero of what?
Well,
sort of a zero of this scalar field S.
But don't worry about it.
We'll understand gauge invariance in
a deeper way perhaps next time.
It does have a deeper meaning,
incidentally.
It does have a much deeper meaning.
And we'll come to it next time a little bit.
Okay.
Are there any other questions about what we did tonight,
though?
Yeah.
In the upper left,
when you wrote the two families of the question,
the equations,
the one on the left you
said derives from the Bianchi identities.
It is the Bianchi identity.
Right.
The family on the right
we got from equations in motion.
Since E and B are so symmetric,
it seems surprising that
those families don't seem symmetric.
And is there content of that?
You're asking whether they can be interchanged?
Yes,
yes,
yes.
You can invent...
a different vector potential with the
property that these equations over here
become the equations of motion,
and these equations with J equaling zero
become the Bianchi identity.
So this is another example of a convention.
That's not a convention.
That had to do with the absence of magnetic monopoles,
which nobody believes anymore.
So yeah,
yeah.
In some sense it's a convention.
Yes.
It is this interchange of electric and magnetic.
That...
It may be that real physics does
have an interchange symmetry between electric and magnetic,
electric charges becoming magnetic charges.
Now it's not really a symmetry
because if it was a symmetry,
we would have discovered those magnetic charges already.
They would have been similar to electrons.
They would have weighed the same thing as
electrons if there was a real symmetry between them.
And no such magnetic things exist.
So it is not a symmetry in the usual sense,
but we don't want to go there right now.
I'm too tired for it.
Any other questions?
Okay,
we've actually come a long way.
We've come through the Lagrangian formulation of mechanics,
the Lagrangian formulation of field theory,
the Lagrangian formulation of electrodynamics,
gauge invariance,
Lorentz invariance.
That's a lot of stuff.
And as I said,
I think the only way to really digest
it is to go home with the equations
and work them out yourself,
starting from step one to step two.
So good luck.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.