Stanford University
Alright, so what is particle physics about?
Particle physics is about particles.
It's about the question, and
this is a very ancient question,
at least, I suspect, about 2500 years old,
is nature discrete?
Discrete meaning to say, not that it's polite,
but that matter and substances and energy,
they didn't think about energy,
but they thought about matter.
That matter comes in discrete units,
in indivisible units,
which of course the Greeks called atom.
I'm told that the word atom means indivisible,
despite the fact that of course
we break up atoms all the time.
Nevertheless,
the origin of the word,
indivisible,
that all things in the universe
are made up out of something discrete.
Let's call them particles.
Particles is a good name for something discrete,
something indivisible.
That idea is, as I said, extremely ancient.
The opposite idea is also ancient.
Again, I don't know precisely when it was first formulated,
I happen to remember a little more
about the history of the atomic idea,
that was, it doesn't matter who it is.
Incidentally, do not trust my history,
not because I don't know the history,
but I sometimes tell the history
in which I organize things logically,
rather than temporally.
So don't trust the time sequence that I tell you.
It often represents what I wish the time sequence was,
rather than what it actually was.
But it's good for being,
to present the logic of what happened,
to present it in a logically compelling way,
rather than a strict historical way.
In any case,
there were these characters who were the atomists,
and the opposite of them,
the people who thought that matter, material, and so forth,
was continuously distributed.
Continuously distributed means simply not
made up out of discrete elements,
but, I don't know what the right word is,
uniform, continuous is the right word,
a smear, as my grandmother would have said.
A smear.
Smeared out of a space in
some uniform, continuous kind of way.
And we might call that the field theory of matter.
Fields, what are fields?
Fields are functions in space,
for example, they could be the density of material
in a given region of space.
They could be the electric and magnetic fields.
Those are good examples.
Electric and magnetic fields that
determine how charged particles move.
But the fields themselves, the electric and magnetic fields,
are things that we conceive of
as being uniformly distributed in space,
not in the form of particles.
And so,
perhaps, matter, liquids, solids, and so forth,
are also, in some sense, continuous,
just like the electromagnetic field.
That was the opposite idea.
The particle idea, the discrete idea,
had words like molecules, atoms, and so forth,
collisions, and particles.
The continuum idea, continuum is the right word,
the continuum idea had words like fields attached to it,
continuous fields of properties of various kinds.
Which turned out to be right?
In some sense, neither and both.
In some sense, neither and
both turned out to be right.
The subtleties of quantum mechanics got in the
way of either of them being completely right,
but it also got in the way
of either of them being completely right.
But it also got in the way
of either of them being completely wrong.
Quantum mechanics is a subtle and difficult subject,
as are many of the preliminaries to particle physics.
I think I have taught all
of them by now several times,
and they do exist on the internet.
The internet lectures that I've given, they're out there.
And I advise you,
as I said, I will try to keep itself contained,
but I am going to assume to some extent
the knowledge that I have
taught previously in these classes.
It can be picked up off the internet very easily.
I don't know how to do it.
I couldn't do it for the life of me.
I can never access my own lectures.
But everybody else can do it.
And, well, the real reason is
I don't like looking at myself.
So I never do open my own lectures.
But they're out there.
And they're fairly complete.
There are at least two
courses out there on quantum mechanics.
I think one on classical mechanics,
at least one on special
theory of relativity and electromagnetism.
So since I put that effort in,
I'm now going to try to draw on it,
not today, but in the future,
and use many of the
things that I have lectured about.
Okay.
So, as I said,
the particle physics question is
whether nature is discrete or not.
Let's just do a little bit of history,
which I will probably get wrong,
but that's at least chronologically.
To my knowledge, the first real evidence,
again, it's to my knowledge,
the first real evidence that matter was discrete
came, of course, from chemistry.
It didn't come from physics.
It came from chemistry.
The division between chemistry and physics
is a highly artificial one.
Chemistry is simply just the,
basically the physics of atoms and molecules.
But it came from the chemist,
John, John Dalton?
John, I think.
John Dalton,
who realized that the masses of chemicals,
the mass of a given number of molecules,
a given number of molecules,
now how he knew that he had
to deal with a given number of molecules
when he might be talking
on the one hand of hydrogen,
the other hand of a carbon dioxide or something,
how he knew it was a given
number of molecules is itself a story.
Avogadro's name comes into it and so forth.
The word mole,
not the creature that lives under the ground,
but the mole is Avogadro's number of molecules.
How they knew how many molecules,
they didn't know how many molecules,
but how they knew how to compare different substances
and say both of them
had the same number of molecules,
that itself is an interesting story.
But it's not the story I want to tell.
The story I want to tell
had to do with the mass
of a mole of material,
a mass of a given number, Avogadro's number of molecules,
that it came in discrete multiples
of the mass of a mole of hydrogen.
Now not exactly,
but close enough to a pretty good precision
are the mass of a mole of gobbledygook
is an integer multiple,
not three halves, not pi,
not some other silly number,
but some integer times the mass
of the same number of molecules of hydrogen.
That sort of suggested to Dalton
that there were building blocks,
that carbon, what is it, carbon eight?
Carbon twelve.
Carbon twelve had twelve units
of whatever hydrogen one had.
Hydrogen was one unit of stuff,
whatever that stuff was, carbon twelve,
or whatever the other numbers were.
So it seemed like things were being built up
out of basic units,
which basically had the same mass
as a hydrogen atom,
almost as though everything was made up
of units of hydrogen.
Dalton, I think, proposed something like that,
that there were basic units,
and those basic units had the mass
roughly of a hydrogen atom.
So that was the first bit of evidence,
and of course this was essentially right.
Today we understand,
let me just tell you why that's true
from today's perspective,
not to make a mystery out of it.
Everything is made out of atoms,
protons, neutrons, and electrons.
Electrons are very, very light
compared to protons and neutrons,
and in counting up the mass of an atom,
the electrons are not very significant.
An electron has about a mass of one two thousandth,
no, one two thousandth,
one two thousandth of the mass
of a proton or a neutron.
So electrons don't come into the equation,
they do come into the equation,
but only a very, very small term.
Forget about them.
Protons and neutrons constitute most of the mass,
almost all of the mass,
of ordinary material.
On the other hand,
protons and neutrons, surprisingly,
there's no, well, there is a good reason for it,
but at the time there was certainly no known reason.
In fact, protons and neutrons weren't known.
But protons and neutrons have about
the same mass as each other.
As I said, about two thousand times
the mass of an electron.
And so the mass of a molecule
is basically the mass of protons plus neutrons.
They have about the same mass,
and therefore the mass of a molecule
is an integer multiple
of the mass of a proton and neutron.
On the other hand, hydrogen is,
the nucleus of hydrogen is just one proton,
and so it did turn out that Dalton was right.
All materials have a mass which is
approximately, there's an approximation in there,
protons and neutrons don't have quite the same mass,
slightly different, less than a percent, incidentally,
a tenth of a percent or even less,
whereas electrons are so light
that they don't come into it very much.
And so Dalton was right.
And it was the first, to my knowledge,
the first real evidence
that matter came in discrete units.
Now, molecules weren't atoms, of course.
It took a little while longer
to find out that molecules
were made up out of atoms,
and the atoms weren't just protons and neutrons or hydrogen,
that atoms themselves, the things we now call atoms,
that there were about a hundred of them,
a hundred different kinds.
This was, of course, the great triumph of chemistry
of the 19th century and early 20th century,
to identify all of the elements
that go into the periodic table up there.
Incidentally, the periodic table is not very periodic.
You know, if you really look at it,
it's a bit of a fake, the periodic table.
It's not very periodic.
But nevertheless, identifying all
those separate atoms up there,
the elements, the elements are in some things
which are composed of all the same kind,
you know that story,
composed of atoms,
and identifying the atoms,
and at the end of the identification of atoms,
roughly about a hundred of them,
less than a hundred occurring in nature,
92 of them to be precise,
well, more than that if you include isotopes,
but over a hundred different kinds of atoms,
and everything made up out of atoms.
So atoms, at the end of the 19th century,
the things we call atoms or elements
were the building blocks,
the elementary particles of nature.
Now of course it took another five years
after the turn of the century for Einstein
to do something that nailed,
really, really nailed the molecular theory of matter.
It wasn't until 1905 that Einstein explained in detail
how you could prove that matter
was really made out of particles,
but long before that,
chemists, physicists understood,
for the most part,
that everything was made out of these 92 elements.
So they were the elementary particles.
Now, sort of all hell broke loose
in the beginning of the 20th century,
very, very end of the 19th century,
when some discoveries were made.
The electron was discovered.
About three years, I think,
before the turn of the century,
I don't know exactly when it was,
the electron was discovered,
and a number of other things were discovered,
but in particular, radioactivity was discovered.
Radioactivity was the first real signal
of the thing which was later to become
nuclear physics,
and nuclear physics and particle physics,
were all the things that needed to be explained,
sort of there,
in a sort of tiny, tiny little version.
So let me just remind
you about radioactivity, just for fun.
Who was it who discovered radioactivity?
I don't even remember.
I don't think it was
Marie Curie who discovered radioactivity.
I don't think so.
Was it Becquerel?
I think it was Becquerel.
I don't think it was Marie Curie.
What she did was,
lots and lots of experiments to pin it down,
but it was Becquerel.
And he had a chunk of lead.
Don't ask me why he did this.
I do not know.
He had a chunk of lead,
and a little hole in
the chunk of lead like that,
and some material down here.
Radioactivity.
I guess the first thing that happened
was he had some radioactive material,
presumably radium or something like it,
in his laboratory,
and he had a photographic plate,
and accidentally the photographic plate
happened to be near the material.
Not here, over here.
Material, photographic plate.
And the photographic plate got ruined.
Ruined by the presence of the radioactive material.
The radioactive material just ruined,
you know, was like light shining on it,
and ruined the photographic plate.
Anybody else, or not anybody else, probably me,
would have just thrown away the plate and said,
ah, this is ruined, let's find another plate
and start the experiment over again.
But Becquerel realized he had discovered something.
He had discovered that radioactive materials
do something to the photographic plate
as if they had been illuminated by some radiation.
So he decided to study
that radiation a little bit better,
and he put the source of
it deep in a block of lead.
How he knew to use lead, I do not know,
but lead was a good substance because it's very dense.
And he put it into
a hole, drilled into the lead,
and then put his photographic plate out here,
and wanted to see whether it would illuminate
a single spot over here.
Everything was collimated by this hole.
He wanted to see whether it
would create a sharp little spot
as if something were coming up out of this hole.
And indeed it did.
So he got the idea
that a beam of some sort
was being ejected, or something was being ejected
by this radioactive material,
and being collimated along a beam.
That was the first particle beam.
That was the first beam of particles.
What was it? He had no idea what it was.
But then I guess a second fortuitous accident,
I think it was an accident, again,
I'm making up the history as I go along,
but it's close to the truth.
He happened to have a magnet in the laboratory.
And for some reason the
magnet was in a position here
where a magnetic field was created
near where these particles were being ejected.
And what happened when he put the magnetic field,
when he put the magnet near this,
is the beam split into three separate beams.
Three separate beams.
One went straight ahead,
just as if the magnetic field was not there.
One of them got deviated to the left,
and one of them got deviated to the right.
Left, right, right, left, whatever.
One deviated more than the other, in fact.
They were not symmetric.
And Becquerel, or somebody, whoever was around,
knew enough to realize that beams of force
were not the force of the magnetic field.
So the magnetic field is a force of force.
And it's a force of force.
And if you have a magnet,
and you have a charged particle,
the charged particle goes through the magnetic field
and either bends to the right or to the left,
depending on the sign of the magnetic field
and the charge of the particle.
So if the particle was a positively charged particle,
it would bend one way in the magnetic field.
And what Becquerel had found
is that there were three kinds of radiation.
One behaving as if it
was composed of electrically neutral particles.
Which one was electrically neutral?
The one that wasn't deviated at all.
Of course, he didn't know they were particles.
All he knew was that some collimated effect happened
that illuminated the magnetic field.
And that was the first thing he found.
And then he found that the second thing he found
was the detector, the screen, the photographic plate.
One of them got deviated to the right
as if it were a negatively charged particle.
He called that component of the radiation,
he called that component beta.
The component that went straight ahead,
he called gamma.
And the component that deviated in the other direction
as if it were positively charged,
he called alpha.
These became the three components
of the three distinct kinds of radioactive effects,
the three distinct kinds of radioactivity.
Beta radioactivity, gamma and alpha.
Just again, I'm not interested in making suspense here.
Let me just tell you what they were.
You probably know what they were.
Many of you know what they were.
Beta was electrons, negatively charged particles.
Which were just the electrons
that had already been previously discovered
from cathode ray tubes and that kind of thing.
These were electrons coming out.
The alpha particles, we now understand,
and at that time there was no precedent for it,
that they are helium nuclei.
Two protons and two neutrons stuck together.
Atomic number four.
Dalton, had he had access to helium,
which he didn't,
he would have said helium was number four
on his integer collection of materials.
And gamma are photons.
Electrically neutral, no electricity at all.
And these three kinds of...
Now, I think he did...
Again, I don't remember the history,
but he might have.
And so, don't think you know.
But in that case,
the results were that
all of the electrons that the atom had
had a sufficiently dilute source
that these particles arrived,
one at a time,
at their destination.
And in that case,
he would not have seen
a bright spot over here.
He would have seen
blip,
illumination occurring,
or spots occurring,
And he might have said, oh, those are particles.
Particles arriving one at a
time, illuminating a screen discreetly.
He would have done exactly the
same thing for the alpha particles.
He would have found that the
alpha particles arrived one at a time.
In other words, he could have used,
he might have used, he probably did,
used the screen here as a counter,
analogous to a Geiger counter or something.
Whether he did or not, I don't know.
But it's something you can imagine, that he
detected the particles coming one at a time.
That would certainly be feasible with a Geiger counter.
And so, evidence that whatever this radiation is,
it's coming in discreet little
bundles that we could call particles.
What about gamma? Same thing for gamma.
Gamma's coming one at a time.
But at that time, Becquerel had no idea.
Neither did anybody else what gamma was.
It was uncharged. That was all that was known.
And it illuminated the screen just as the others did.
Okay. That was, as I said, in
some sense, the first particle physics experiment.
We'll come to some later
particle physics experiments soon enough.
Let's next talk about electromagnetic radiation.
Ordinary electromagnetic radiation.
Oh, well, I said I wasn't going to make suspense.
Gamma is photons. Gamma is light.
Gamma, well, it's very high energy light.
But gamma is in some way connected to ordinary light.
So let's come to light.
Gamma was the big mystery because there
were no neutral particles known at that time
that
could account for the gamma radiation.
So gamma was a mystery.
And that mystery persisted until fairly
late in the very early 20th century.
Let's put it that way.
Fairly late in the very early 20th century.
It was, of course, Planck and Einstein, really Einstein,
who were the first to
understand that light comes in quanta,
that light comes in photons.
But let's go back.
Light was sort of the strong, strong case
for something which was not made of particles.
Light was something which was clearly made of fields.
It was made of the electromagnetic field.
Okay, the electromagnetic field, electric
fields and magnetic fields forming waves.
When you shake a charge, waves get given off.
The wave fields are continuous wave fields,
at least according to,
according to classical electrodynamics.
And they give off waves
that propagate through space completely continuously.
And Newton, of course, had thought that light was particles.
But Newton, by that time, had
been completely relegated to the dustbin,
at least as far as theory of light went.
There were many experiments, some
of them done by Newton himself,
that strongly said light is waves, not particles.
So let's just talk about
light a little bit, electromagnetic radiation.
If you take electromagnetic radiation, it comes in waves.
So if there's a source
of electromagnetic radiation here, an antenna,
some form of antenna emitting, it could
be radio waves, it could be microwaves,
it could be infrared, it could
be light, it could be ultraviolet.
An atom is a perfectly good,
a good antenna, incidentally.
It doesn't have to be a big macroscopic tower.
An atom with a charge going
around in a circle is an antenna.
Antennas emit waves.
And those electromagnetic waves, when they
also fall on a photographic plate
or other device which is sensitive
to light or sensitive to radiation,
will illuminate that, will illuminate that
and turn it white or
black, turn it black, I guess.
And that's in the character of light.
Now how do we know that these things are waves?
How can we tell that they're also
not bullets shot out of the source here?
So one thing you might do is do
something very similar to what was done over here.
Put an obstruction,
a little hole,
and see whether the light is collimated exactly as if
it were bullets being shot out of a gun here.
If it was bullets, you would
illuminate a little spot over here.
And of course what happens is that
you don't illuminate such a small spot.
You illuminate something which is fuzzier than that.
You illuminate a fuzzy region.
But that in itself did
not prove that light was waves.
Not at all.
You could say, well, just maybe when
these particles go through this opening here,
maybe they have little forces exerted on them
by the edges of the hole here or whatever,
which deflect them, some of them get deflected,
and so maybe you get a more smeary picture,
a more smeary image than you might have hoped for.
So it was not just that the beams got deflected,
the light beams got deflected,
that in itself was not enough to
argue for a particle structure to light,
or sorry, a wave structure to light, I'm sorry.
But you do something else, which is much
more sensitive to the wave character of light.
Here's the screen over here again.
You open up two little holes,
two little holes next to each other.
If light was simply particles,
what you would expect to find here
is basically two smears of the same kind,
just superimposed on top of each other,
maybe a little extra dense
in the center where they overlap,
but just two smears, one the image of this
hole, one the image of that hole, with nothing unusual.
This of course is not what happens.
What happens is each hole emits waves.
You could do the same trick with water waves.
In fact, it's not hard to
do the same trick with water waves.
And the water waves interfere.
If this is the high point
of a wave coming out of here,
and this is the low point of a wave,
places where the high points combine
from the two holes reinforce each other.
Places where a high point from one hole meets
a low point from the other hole cancel each other.
And so the effect is to see when
it hits the screen here, to see bands.
The bands of positive reinforcement
where the high points add,
missing places with no light where
the high points meet low points.
That's an interference pattern.
Interference pattern is a real signal
of wave-like motion, of wave behavior.
Waves, you can do this, as I said, with water.
You just put your finger
into water and wiggle two fingers,
and the two waves, from the two ends,
will spread out.
Some places they'll reinforce, some places they'll cancel.
And so rather peculiarly, but nothing terribly unusual,
places which would have been illuminated by
either of the two holes by themselves,
there's destructive interference, they get canceled,
and places you get constructive interference and they add,
and you get extra intensity.
That is the kind of thing,
this interference property was the kind of thing
that really nailed the wave theory of light.
So light was a wave.
In fact, this did not occur after Newton,
it really occurred before Newton.
Huygens was a 17th century?
Huygens must have been 17th century, but previous to Newton.
Who? What?
Thomas Young?
Yeah.
The physicist that demonstrated the interference.
Yeah, yeah, but Huygens already had
the basic ideas of wave propagation,
and that's from the 1600s sometime.
So this debate went back,
and Newton had done many experiments himself,
which should have been interpreted as interference,
as interference, wave interference.
But he didn't.
In any case,
after these experiments, Young's experiment, others,
it was definitely confirmed,
that light is made of waves.
Okay, what kind of waves?
Well, that took Maxwell.
Maxwell realized that they were
waves of electric and magnetic field.
You know what an electric and magnetic field is?
An electric field, well, I,
look it up if you don't know,
electric and magnetic fields,
and light is a wavy
motion of electric and magnetic fields.
First of all, light is a wave,
and here's a wave moving down the axis.
What is that wave a wave in?
Well, it's a wave of electric field.
Here the electric field is pointing down.
Here the electric field is pointing up.
Let's just draw a line through there.
Alternating electric field up, down, up, down.
And the whole thing moves
off with the speed of light.
The whole thing moves off with the speed of light.
Electric field, incidentally, there's also a
magnetic field attached to the thing.
It's a complicated object.
It has magnetic field also.
The magnetic field is perpendicular to the electric field.
And so it sticks out this way.
And that's what a light wave
would look like if you could see,
if you could sample its electric and
magnetic field as it went past you.
Of course, as it passes you,
it will constantly alternate very rapidly
if it's an ordinary light wave.
Much too rapidly for you to be able to see.
But if it were an extremely long radio wave,
very, very long radio wave,
you might be able to see
the field oscillating in front of you.
And this is, as I
said, what it would look like.
It's a wave.
Being a wave, it will exhibit interference patterns.
And Maxwell had absolutely nailed the
wave and the electromagnetic theory of light.
So let's talk about waves a
little bit before we talk about particles.
Let's talk a little more about
waves and the properties of waves.
The first property of a wave that I want to...
come to is the wavelength.
Wavelength is simply the distance along the wave
before you return one full cycle to the next wave.
All right, so you start here
and you go and you come back
to the same exact kind of thing as over here.
That's one cycle or one full wavelength.
And wavelength, the symbol for wavelength is lambda.
Greek lambda.
Okay.
Lambda for length.
That's the wavelength.
And it's measured in units of distance.
It's measured in meters or it's measured in centimeters,
whatever your choice of units are.
Okay, so lambda equals wavelength.
Wavelength, let's just call it wavelength.
Another property is if you were to stand still
and just watch the wave go past you,
you go ahead and go up and down
and up and down and up and down,
it would have some frequency.
How many cycles per second?
This is not the length of the wave in space.
It's kind of the number of cycles per second
or perhaps even something simpler,
the time that it takes to go
through one cycle as it passes you.
That could be called the period of the wave.
Period.
It's a time.
It's measured in seconds.
So, and a light wave
has a very, very short period.
Up and down and up and down extremely fast,
10 to the minus 15 seconds or something, whatever.
The longer the wavelength, the slower the period.
The shorter the wavelength, the faster,
the shorter the wavelength, the shorter the period.
Okay, what's the connection between wavelength and period?
Yeah.
Right.
So think about the wave moving past you one wavelength.
How long, how far does it move?
It's moved distance lambda.
How long has it taken?
It's taken the period.
The distance that it moves divided by the
time that it takes to move that distance
is the velocity of the wave.
For light, that would be the speed of light.
If it's not a light wave,
it might be moving with different speed.
If it's a water wave,
it would be much smaller speed.
If it's a sound wave, it's a smaller speed.
But for a light wave,
the wavelength divided by the speed
divided by the period
is always equal to the speed of light.
Whatever the wavelength is,
the period is given in terms of the wavelength
or the wavelength is given in terms of the period.
So that's a fundamental relation.
It's usually expressed a different way.
The inverse of the period, one over the period,
is called the frequency.
It's the number of oscillations per second.
The number of oscillations per unit time
is called the frequency,
and that's equal to one over the period.
The faster the period, the shorter the frequency.
And so you can also write this
as the wavelength times the frequency
is equal to the speed of light.
So if I give you the wavelength,
you can tell me the frequency.
If I give you the frequency,
you can tell me the wavelength by solving this equation.
And that's the fundamental connection
between wavelength and frequency.
Now since one of the things
that we really do want
to teach you a little bit
is the terminology that physicists use for things.
And they tend not to use the terminology
of cycles per second for frequency.
They use something else.
It's radians per second.
What does that mean?
Imagine a thing going around in a circle.
It's going around in a circle
with a frequency f.
That means f times around the circle per second.
Physicists tend to use,
physicists and mathematicians,
tend to use not the number of times
you go around in a second,
but the number of radians.
Radian is about 57 degrees.
It's an angle about that big.
How many radians per second?
And the relationship between
the frequency in terms of cycles per second
and the frequency in terms of cycles per second,
the frequency in terms of radians per second
is very simple.
In terms of radians per second,
we call it omega.
And they're closely connected to each other.
Omega is just 2 pi times the frequency.
Why 2 pi?
Because there are 2 pi radians in a circle.
So frequency can be measured in either way.
Physicists tend to use omega,
except when they're writing elementary physics books,
for undergraduate pre-med majors,
in which case they use f.
Okay?
We're all physicists.
We're all grown up.
We're all, you know,
so we can use omega
like the world of physics does.
Omega is the frequency of light measured
not in cycles per second,
but in radians per second.
You say, where is the
angle for a light wave going?
Don't worry about where the angle is.
Just divide frequency,
just multiply frequency by 2 pi.
And that defines omega.
All right.
They're proportional to each other.
So we can also write this then as,
let's write it this way.
Frequency, I'm going to write it,
frequency is equal to c divided by lambda.
And now I'm going to substitute for frequency
omega divided by 2 pi.
And what do we get?
We get omega is equal to 2 pi.
2 pi c over lambda.
Fundamental equation of wave motion
that the frequency measured in radians
and the wavelength are related
by 2 pi times the speed of light.
This, of course, is true for any wave
if you plug in the right velocity.
Okay, we will use that equation from time to time.
So get it down.
Now, as I said,
light comes in different wavelengths.
And those different wavelengths characterize
the different kinds of radiation.
Radio waves are very long wavelengths.
Meters are certainly more than,
certainly more than microscopic lengths.
Radio waves can be anything from, what,
a few centimeters to 10 centimeters or something.
I don't remember exactly where the radio spectrum begins.
Hmm?
It can go up to anything.
Arbitrarily long wavelengths are called still radio waves,
even though no radio could
work on the basis of waves
that had a wavelength of a billion light years.
But still, they're still called radio waves.
And where's the smaller, what's the smallest radio wave?
I think about 10 centimeters.
And it's a highly arbitrary division, of course,
completely arbitrary.
Smaller than radio waves, smaller wavelength.
Microwaves, microwaves go from a few centimeters
down to, what, a micrometer or something like that, micron.
Smaller wavelength than microwaves.
Infrared, infrared waves.
And then from infrared waves,
you have light waves, visible light.
Visible light is a rather
narrow range of frequencies or wavelengths.
And then comes ultraviolet, shorter wavelengths.
X-rays, gamma rays.
Gamma rays are just exactly these objects here.
Very, very short wavelength,
extremely short wavelength radiation.
And that's what Becquerel had
discovered coming out of there.
The only trouble is
that Becquerel discovered discrete bumps,
you know, discrete blips, one at a time,
and not nice, continuous waves.
Okay, that then brings us
to the puzzle of quantum mechanics.
Now, we're not going to go into
it in any great depth, certainly not tonight,
but let's just recount the history a little bit.
Einstein and Planck realized for a variety of reasons,
mostly thermodynamic properties of light,
that Einstein, Planck, and Planck,
Einstein, that light had to be thought
of as being made up out of discrete,
indivisible elements.
He might have, it might have been an experimental discovery.
In fact, in some sense,
Becquerel's discovery was an experimental discovery.
It's just he didn't realize the
thing he was seeing was electromagnetic radiation.
So I won't go through the actual history,
but let's make up an imaginary history
of how the discreteness of light might have been discovered.
It could have been discovered this way.
You, again, shine your light on a,
you shine your light on a screen.
And you illuminate the screen,
and of course what you see
is a nice continuous blob of light.
It could either be an interference pattern,
or it could just be a single hole,
in which case it would just
be a blob on the screen.
Okay.
But now you do the experiment differently.
Here's your source of light.
You put an obstruction in the way.
The obstruction is a filter.
The obstruction is a, not a filter, but a,
a semi-transparent, semi-opaque
thing which blocks out a certain percentage of the light.
What happens over here?
Well, the blob gets dimmer.
Okay. It's not as intense.
You make it thicker.
It's even less intense.
You see less light arriving per unit of time.
And you make it even a little bit thicker.
And at some point, all of a sudden,
the character of what's here changes.
And instead of seeing the blob,
you see discrete events, little blips.
Now, if you wait a long time,
these little blips build up.
And they build up to something
which has exactly the same pattern
as the blob had.
So the blob in this case, then,
is some sort of effect
that has to do with lots of little blips.
So many little blips that you can't recognize them
as being individual.
That's the blob.
But if you attenuate the light
and cut it down
so that the intensity coming through here
is really, really small,
what you see is blips.
This experiment can actually be done.
It was not done in those early days.
But you can imagine.
And this is what Einstein had suggested
really does happen in his photoelectric paper,
that light comes through as absolutely discrete things.
The motivation for it was thermodynamics
and other things.
But this might have been the form of discovery,
discovering these individual blips,
and then,
the light is coming through.
And this is what really would happen.
So, something very, very confusing going on.
Light is a wave.
That had already been proved.
In fact, if we put a screen over here
with two little holes in it,
two little holes in it,
we will again see light coming through
bit by bit.
One at a time.
And if we leave it up there a long time,
the blips will sort of fill in,
and what they will form is an interference pattern.
So it became clear,
clear but still very confusing,
that light is made up out of indivisible elements
called photons,
and that the wave character of the light
really represents, or the wave pattern,
really represents the probability
that the photon appears at different places.
In other words, it's randomly arriving blips,
but they arrive with a probability
in different locations,
which follows the pattern
that was established by the wave theory.
The wave theory gives you a wave theory of probabilities.
That's quantum mechanics.
We may have to talk about,
we will have to talk about quantum mechanics
a great deal more.
But this kind of experiment,
this kind of observation about light
was the first example of a connection
which is really in a sense
what this course is all about.
It's a connection, first of all,
between waves of any kind,
and particles.
They are not two different things.
Somehow, waves and particles
are two manifestations of the same thing.
We'll have to come back to that,
and we'll try to explain it perhaps again later.
Now I'm just filling in some early facts,
mostly just to set the stage.
Waves and particles,
at least when it came to light,
were somehow intimately connected,
and it didn't make sense
to say light is a particle,
or it didn't make sense
to say light is a wave,
but has manifestations of both.
All right, the situation only got more complicated
when electrons were studied.
Electrons are clearly particles.
Everybody knows electrons are particles.
There was no ambiguity about that,
no more ambiguity than there was
about whether light was a wave or not.
It was.
But yet, something funny.
Well, something funny also happened with electrons.
You could do exactly the same kind of experiment
with electrons. You can.
Today, this experiment can really be done.
At the time, it was
a bit of a thought experiment,
but equivalent experiments,
you'd have to put the holes,
you'd have to make a screen,
you'd put the holes much closer to each other
if you want to do it with electrons
for one reason or another,
and you send electrons through.
Of course they come through one at a time.
Everybody knew electrons were little particles
that came through one at a time.
What was totally unexpected is,
or would have been unexpected,
was that the electrons,
when you open two holes,
form an interference pattern.
So it wasn't just that light was funny.
Particles were funny in general.
Electrons exhibited wave properties.
Light exhibited particle properties.
In fact, had we taken the alpha particles,
which are much heavier than electrons,
much, much heavier than electrons,
8,000 times heavier than an electron,
much harder to do these kind of experiments with,
but send them through two little holes like that,
we also would see interference patterns
and interference patterns.
This has been done with objects
which are much, much bigger than helium nuclei,
namely buckyballs.
Buckyballs have been sent through
interference experiments like this
and seen to form the same kind of interference pattern.
So everybody know what a buckyball is?
60 carbons...
In the shape of a soccer ball.
In the shape of a generalized soccer ball.
Yeah, right.
Is it a regular soccer ball?
Yeah, like a soccer ball.
No, it's not really a soccer ball, but...
Well...
So...
And it is widely believed that
if you did it with bowling balls,
well, you can't really do it with bowling balls.
Much, much, much too hard.
I understand that people who did it with buckyballs
are going to try to
do it with living cells, viruses,
to prove that viruses are quantum mechanical.
And then they're going to ask the virus
what the virus felt when it...
Anyway...
Good.
The waves and particles are somehow the same thing,
and if you want to penetrate that more deeply,
you've got to learn some quantum mechanics,
and the place to do it is...
In my lectures,
which don't cost anything.
They're on the internet.
Okay.
That's...
Now let's talk about the
properties of photons a little bit.
Photons are these discrete, indivisible elements of light.
Light has energy.
If you absorb the sunlight,
it heats things.
Obviously has energy.
So therefore, photons have energy.
What do we know about the energy of a photon?
Photons being indivisible,
we know the energy must come in very discrete packets.
Now what is a photon characterized by?
Or a light wave.
Imagine a light wave coming in,
composed out of these discrete photons.
Don't try to picture it.
It's impossible to picture.
When the light wave actually falls on a screen,
it...
It forms these little dots.
So it's particles.
Made of particles,
but we see some sort
of wave phenomena associated with it.
The wave phenomena is associated with a wavelength,
and therefore a frequency,
an angular frequency.
We discover that that light wave
is made up out of discrete units,
each with an indivisible bit of energy.
Cannot be subdivided.
And the energy of one photon,
the energy of every single photon in this light beam,
with a given wavelength and a given frequency,
is given by a number called h-bar,
Planck's constant,
one of Planck's many...
one of Planck's constants.
h-bar times omega.
In other words,
omega is large,
when the wavelength is short.
The shorter the wavelength,
the larger the frequency.
The larger the frequency,
or the shorter the wavelength,
the larger the energy in every photon.
So,
first lesson.
Short wavelength photons have lots of energy.
Long wavelength individual photons
have very low energy.
Now of course,
a radio wave can carry a huge amount of energy.
There's no question.
You can make radio waves with lots of energy.
Lots and lots of energy.
How do you make radio waves with lots of energy?
You pile lots of photons up.
Many, many photons,
all with the same wavelength and the same frequency.
But,
there is something nevertheless,
some remnant of the discreteness.
Namely, the energy of such a wave
is always an integer multiple.
This is the energy of a photon.
The energy of a light ray,
let's just call it a ray,
or a light wave,
is some integer number,
some integer multiple
of h bar omega.
Alright, so the light rays come in indivisible units.
Every light ray,
every light wave,
every pulse of light
with a given frequency and wavelength
has an integer multiple of energy
in units of light.
In units of h bar omega.
So this is an important equation here.
This equation is of absolute central importance
to understanding why particle physics is the way it is.
In particular, it's very, very central to the question
of why we have to build big giant machines
to see smaller and smaller objects.
My grandson, my grandson's not a kid,
he's 26 years old,
but he asked me one day,
how come you have to build bigger and bigger machines
to see smaller and smaller things?
Why don't you build small machines to see...
Alright, we're going to try to answer that question,
but this is the central fact
that the energy is proportional to the frequency
of a single photon.
Alright, we've been through waves and particles,
photons carrying discrete units of energy,
and the way that the energy is being transported
is very important.
So this is the first
thing that I'm going to do.
I'm going to go over the theory of relativity.
And then I'm going to go
over the theory of quantum mechanics.
And then I'm going to
go over the theory of relativity.
I want to come to another set of concepts now.
This is...
We're certainly not abandoning this line of thought here,
but I want to come
to another set of concepts now.
Particle physics is, in
a sense, relativistic quantum mechanics,
the combination of relativity and quantum mechanics.
And so, let me just remind you of
one particular simple fact,
and then be clear about what that fact means.
The most famous equation of physics,
E equals mc squared.
This equation also plays a very important role
in the reason that...
in explaining why particle physics is the way it is.
Energy is mc squared.
Let's just be very clear about what it means.
In the early days of relativity,
people spoke of the rest mass of an object
and the moving mass of an object.
The moving mass and the rest mass were different.
The mass of an object was minimum
when it was standing still,
but when it moved, the mass increases.
You still read that in elementary physics textbooks,
but you never read it in any...
in any work of modern physics.
You never read that the mass of an object
depends on its state of motion.
It's largely a change in language.
The change in language is such
that what we now call mass
is what used to be called rest mass.
Period.
Whenever I refer to a mass of an object,
I'm talking about its rest mass.
All electrons have exactly the same rest mass.
All electrons have exactly the same mass.
Period.
If you look up...
If you look up the masses of particles
in a table of masses and so forth,
you will not find them called rest mass.
You will just find them called mass.
So from now on, we will
never speak about the rest mass.
We will speak about the mass of the electron
as a number that experimental
physicists measure in great detail.
Every electron has exactly the
same mass as every other electron.
And the mass is not something
which depends on the state of motion.
But of course the energy is something
The faster an electron moves,
the more kinetic energy it has.
So there's something wrong with this equation.
Yes, there's something wrong with this equation.
This equation is no longer...
Even though it's the most famous equation in physics,
it's not the right equation.
At least with modern terminology.
Energy is only equal to mass times c squared
for an object at rest.
The right way to say it
is the energy of an object at rest
if the object has no net motion.
Now it could be a complicated object
with all sorts of internal motions,
but it could be a box of gas.
All the molecules flying around like mad.
But as long as the
box of gas is itself stationary,
then we speak of its rest mass,
and we can speak of its rest energy,
the energy of that box of gas,
when it's standing still.
And Einstein's equation says that
the rest energy of an object
is the rest mass, or just the mass,
times the speed of light squared.
Now what exactly...
Let me imagine two experiments
that you might do to confirm this,
just to understand precisely what it means.
You take a pot of...
Not a pot, a box with molecules in it.
And you put it on a scale
to measure its weight or its mass.
And draw a scale.
The molecules are cold.
You begin with the box of gas very, very cold.
And you measure the mass.
So you measure...
Yes, you measure the mass.
You get some number.
Now you feed some energy into the box.
You heat it up.
You heat up the molecules in here.
You increase their energy.
The box is still at rest.
The molecules are not.
The molecules are moving around,
but the box is at rest.
And we can ask,
what is the rest mass of the box of gas?
The answer is,
if you increase the energy
by adding thermal energy,
you add a certain number of calories,
or a certain number of joules,
joules is a unit of energy,
you add a certain amount of energy,
and you add a certain amount of energy.
And so you can measure the mass of the box.
You will discover that the box is mass.
The box of gas, its mass increases.
Its weight increases.
Now, the amount that it would increase
is so tiny,
if you increase the temperature
by a thousand degrees or something,
it's so tiny that it would be quite unmeasurable.
The mass increases, its weight increases.
Also, its inertia increases.
Harder to move it.
Another example,
now this example is not something
that you can really do,
but the other example is something that is,
you know, real experimental physics,
observational physics.
You start not,
you start with an electron
and a positron.
We haven't talked about anti-particles,
let's just,
ignore the fact that we haven't
talked about them for a moment.
Two kinds of particles,
electrons which have negative charge,
positrons which have positive charge.
They have exactly the same mass,
precisely the same mass.
They are in every respect similar,
except for the fact that they have opposite electric charge.
Because they have opposite electric charge,
they can combine and disappear.
They have plus charge and a minus charge,
the net charge is zero,
nothing prevents them from
disappearing.
Well, something does prevent them from disappearing.
They have energy.
Each one has an energy,
let's suppose these two particles are at rest,
we bring them together,
each one has an energy equal to mc squared,
so the total energy is twice mc squared.
mc squared for each particle.
We bring them together,
that energy can't disappear.
Energy is conserved.
What happens to that energy?
That energy becomes photons.
Photons go out.
You bring an electron next to a positron,
you let them annihilate,
poof, out go photons.
The photons, in some sense, are energy.
They can be absorbed by a material
and heat the material.
They can be converted to all forms of energy.
And how much energy do you get
by annihilating an electron and a positron?
The answer is twice the mass of an electron
times the speed of light squared.
That's a tiny amount of energy.
I mean, if you just had one electron and positron,
you couldn't do much with it.
You need, you know, huge numbers of them
to heat a cup of coffee,
but still, in principle, that's what happens.
And of course, this is an observational fact.
That's the meaning of E equals mc squared.
And another way to really say it,
which I think is the right way to say it,
is to say energy and mass,
at least for an object at rest,
are the same thing.
Why do we have to have an equation?
Really, it's just a conversion of units
from what we call mass units
to what we call energy units.
And this tells you the conversion,
roughly like a conversion
from meters to centimeters or whatever.
This is the conversion between energy units and mass units.
All right, but in any case,
if you know the mass of an object
and you want to know
how much energy you would get
if it disappeared,
you multiply by the square of the speed of light.
So you get a lot of
energy for a small amount of mass.
What is the speed of light,
and what is Planck's constant?
Let's write down the numerical values
of the speed of light and Planck's constant.
We need them, one for here,
and one for here.
Photon energy.
On the E equals mc squared,
does the mass have to have a mechanism
for the energy to be released, or...?
Well, yes, it has to have a mechanism,
and we haven't talked about that mechanism,
but just let's stand on the outside and say,
look, this thing happens.
An electron and a positron,
when you put them together, will just disappear.
Let's not ask what the mechanism is.
The one thing we know is,
independent of the mechanism,
energy should be conserved.
If E equals mc squared for the electrons,
that energy has to show up somewheres.
So there are some things you say
without knowing what the mechanism is.
Conservation laws,
where you know that certain things are conserved,
you can often say important things about a system
without knowing detailed mechanisms.
Okay, let's talk about numbers.
The speed of light is a very big number.
Planck's constant is a very small number.
How do I know it's a small number?
Well, the energy of a photon
is a tiny amount of energy.
The frequency of a light wave is very large,
so it better be that
h bar is a small number.
Let's write them down.
Okay, so c, the speed of light,
that is equal to 2.99762458,
I'm not kidding you, this is true,
plus or minus something in the last digit over here,
times 10 to the eighth meters per second.
Units, units are important.
It's not just 2.99762458 times 10 to the eighth,
it's that number of meters per second.
That's the speed of light.
How about Planck's constant?
Everybody, of course, will memorize this number
because it's important to this class
that you know that number.
One point, same thing here,
I'll memorize this one.
0.0545571628 times 10 to the minus 34.
Very small number.
And what are the units?
Anybody know what the units are?
I worked out the units,
but I think I erased them.
Hmm?
Energy times time, right.
But what are the units of energy?
Mass times velocity squared, right?
mc squared.
That'll be mc squared.
Mass times velocity.
So it's mass, kilograms, times
length squared over time squared.
That's energy.
And Planck's constant has another unit of length in it.
Another unit of time.
Okay.
So Planck's constant is measured in,
what's the unit of mass?
Kilograms.
Kilograms?
Millimеличes.
Yes.
So Clean Waves.
Circle- ido,
we've got two people here.
Okay.
Zero?
Zero.
No, that doesn't matter.
Zero, no matter.
Zero.
Zero?
Zero, 1.
Zero, two.
Zero.
Zero?
in using peculiar units
for example, the speed of light
is something which depends on your choice of units
if you measure it, instead of measuring it in meters per second,
you measure it in feet per hours, you will get a different answer
so there's nothing sacred about this number
it depends on your choice of units
length units in this case and time units
you could certainly work with units in which
the speed of light was a more convenient number
you could work with units in
which the speed of light was one
the units would be light years per year, for example
the speed of light is one light year per year
or one light second per second
so it's not hard to choose
the speed of light to be one
you just use different units of space and time
same is true of Planck's constant
you can use units in which
Planck's constant is equal to one
but why is it that
we actually use such peculiar units?
why don't, how come the people who
invented units, Mr. Metric or whoever he was
the British are worse than the metric
system of course, they were really perverse
5280 feet in a mile
how many
how many stone how many pounds on a stone
i i don't know where they got these units from
hmm i don't know is a stone 16 pounds
14 pounds even worse
16 is at least divisible by
two four times but seven okay
14 14 pounds
hmm how many hands high is your horse
that's another good one how about horsepower
yeah i mean just bizarre units metric units
are better but they're also very very arbitrary
for example the meter had to do with
how far a man's hand is from his nose
why because he was using
measuring length of rope or something
so these are highly arbitrary units and have more to
do with biology than they have to do with physics
they have to do with biology in the sense that the real
question is not why they're going to be used in the future
the real question is not why they're
going to be used in the future
but why uh a meter is what it is
why why a meter is what it is it's a question of
why why an arm has to have x number of molecules in it
and there's nothing special about these numbers
all right given that you can ask are there units
are there better choices of units of the three units
what do we need we have we need three units
we need a length
the three things that you need
to have a length of three units
the three things that you need the
three kinds of units we need are length
meters or feet or whatever time
seconds or years or hours or something else
and mass all of the other units in physics can
be re-expressed in terms of these this is a complete
set of uh of units there are three of them
and we can choose them in various ways for example
and we can choose them in
various ways for example instead of using
instead of using the kilogram we
could use the mass of a
the kilogram we could use the mass of a proton
proton as the basic unit of mass
as the basic unit of mass or the
mass of the sun or and so forth use
or the mass of the sun or
and so forth use different units of mass
certain things in astrophysics are a lot
certain things in astrophysics are a lot easier
easier not easier but a lot smaller the
not easier but a lot smaller
the equations are simpler they involve less
equations are simpler they involve less constants
constants fewer constants if you use units in
constants fewer constants if you use units
in which the mass of the sun is
which the mass of the sun is one okay so the environment in which you
can draw planets it makes sense you can toppings you y you draw planets with connections
Okay, equations in nuclear physics are
simpler, only simpler in the sense that
they don't involve as many arbitrary constants
if you use units in which the
mass of a proton is one. So you
can make your equations simpler and get rid of
these weird numbers, and how many numbers can
you get rid of? How many numbers can
you get rid of these? Well you have
a choice of three units, mass, length, and
time, and that means you can simplify
three of the constants of nature, or
three of these type of constants here,
and set them equal to one if you
like. So in astrophysics or in cosmology
you might want to use the light year.
That's a much better unit than
the centimeter. And if you use the
light year and also the year, light year
for distance, year for time, speed of light
comes out one, of course. So we
can simplify three numbers. Usually, and what
are we doing? The question of
which numbers we simplify might depend on
what kind of physics we're doing.
If we're doing astrophysics we might want
to simplify certain numbers. If we're doing
atomic physics we might want to simplify
other numbers. And in particle physics,
in particle physics there are basically
these two constants which we can set
equal to one by appropriate choices of
units. Appropriate choices of units can set
c equal to one. That's easy. You just
use units in which time is measured
in such a way that time and distance
are measured in such a way that the
distance something moves in one unit of
time is one unit of distance. You can
also set h bar equal to one. You
have your choice about one other unit. What's a
good unit to set equal to one? What's a
good unit, a mass unit, to set equal to
one in particle physics? Well, you could use
it. What about the proton? Why not the
proton? Or why not the Higgs boson?
Or why not the mu particle? Well, the
answer is obvious that there isn't the best. There
is no particularly good unit of mass
which will simplify particle physics so that at
best you can set one arbitrary particle to have
a mass of one. And that would be foolish
because there would be no particular reason to
focus on any one particle. Why do we
pick the speed of light and Planck's constant?
DR. Well, they do appear in so many
equations but so does the mass of the proton.
Or the size of the proton. Why…
Okay. I'll tell you why. There are two very, very
fundamental facts about Planck's Constant and the Speed of Light.
The way I'll say it is just technical.
to say the words.
No object in nature moves
faster than the speed of light.
It doesn't matter what it is, no
matter how you try to accelerate it,
you can get it up closer
and closer to the speed of light,
but you can't pass the speed of light.
For any object in nature, any.
So there's something universal about the speed of light.
It's a universal bound, universal for all forms of matter,
that anything that we can
make, it has a certain universality.
All objects are constrained by the speed of light.
So it has some reason to
be thought of as something universal.
What about Planck's constant?
Does Planck's constant come into anything
where you would want to say
everything in the world
necessarily has precisely this property?
Uncertainty?
It's the uncertainty principle.
We haven't discussed the uncertainty principle,
but all objects in nature, the
precision with which you can measure
their positions and velocities and momenta,
are constrained by exactly the same constant.
The uncertainty in position times the uncertainty in momenta
are always constrained to be as
big or bigger than Planck's constant.
Again, everything, all particles, not just particles,
but objects of all kind
are constrained by the same number.
So it's for that reason,
the specialness of these two constants,
that it makes a lot of
sense to set them equal to one.
The size of the proton, for example,
or not the size of the proton,
well, let's say the size of the
proton or the mass of the proton,
there's nothing very special about the proton.
The proton is one of hundreds
of elementary, one of hundreds of objects.
Why didn't we set the mass of,
give me some weird element from a particle.
Rubidium. Why didn't we set the
mass of a rubidium atom to one?
Because you say rubidium is not
in any way more special than thuvonium.
You're learning about my chemistry knowledge.
There's nothing special about rubidium.
It's just one of many.
Same thing is true of the
proton. It's just one of many.
The electron is one of many.
So there's nothing universal about it.
Is there a third universal quantity which is so special
that we can't measure it?
We might want to set it equal to one.
Something which everything is constrained by.
Charge.
Electric charge.
Yeah, the trouble is electric
charge is a dimensionless quantity.
But yes, we could, the electric
charge is a fundamental constant like that.
The equation of gravity.
Gravity.
Gene.
Right. What can we say?
We can say all objects in nature.
Attract each other with a force which
is equal to the product of the mass
divided by the square of the
distance between them times Newton's constant.
We don't make any exceptions.
It's not that there are some objects
which do that and other objects which don't.
Incidentally, in the case of the electric
charge, of course, there are neutral particles.
So not all objects interact in the same way electrically.
But everything in the world interacts exactly the same way.
Product of the masses divided by the square
of the distance between them times Newton's constant.
So Newton's constant is one of these very universal things.
G.
I don't know, what is it?
I assure you it's not known
to anything like that kind of precision.
I think it's 6.7 times 10 to the minus 11th.
Some units or other.
It's another thing that it makes a
lot of sense to set equal to one.
Why don't we do it in particle physics?
The reason is that particle
physics is totally insensitive to gravity.
The gravitational force between objects
in particle physics is absolutely negligible.
So gravity would be a stupid
thing to set equal to one
because gravity just doesn't come
into the equations of particle physics.
Particles are too light to
experience significant amounts of gravity.
Particles that we know about today are
just too light to experience any significant gravity.
And so there's no particular value since none
of the equations in particle physics involve G.
It's better to leave it alone. Just go away.
And not fix one of the units.
Just leave it free.
Isn't it even fair to say that
making the assumption that you're dismissing it...
What's that?
Isn't it fair to say that particle physics dismisses
it all the time because it would be insignificant
if you actually don't even...
It's not even fair to assume that G is dismissible.
That in fact the particles you're examining at
these high energies may not be subject to gravity
in the classical way we know it.
Well of course we know
that they are subject to gravity.
If you take enough particles, they form the Earth.
And you take another enough particle...
Not when they split apart.
Yeah. So that's right.
We don't really really know what...
How elementary particles...
Well...
No, we do.
Well we can certainly take one elementary particle and
see how it behaves in the field of the Earth.
See whether it falls, and they do.
Single particles do fall in the field of the Earth.
But how single particles
would influence each other gravitationally,
that of course has never been measured.
And so, yeah, it's possible to question whether
the universal law of gravitation applies to particles.
I don't think many physicists do question it.
But the main point is a practical point.
There's no benefit gotten by setting
G equal to one in particle physics
because G just doesn't come into particle physics.
At least...
I mean, there are some current versions of particle physics.
There are other attractions, such as attractions
of two electrons, or the other forces.
Wouldn't it make sense...
Are you talking about gravitational attraction?
...to set those to one, instead of G?
The attraction of two electrons, for example.
Electrons don't attract, they repel, but... yeah.
Yeah, you could do that.
But that doesn't go...
But that doesn't go into your particle physics either.
It does go into your particle physics.
Right. It does.
It does.
Yes, you could use units, and we often do,
in which the electric charge is equal to one.
And the attraction, the repulsion, is the third constant.
Yeah, you could. You could. You could. You could.
Traditionally, we haven't.
Yeah, traditionally, we haven't.
There's a reason that we haven't,
and we'll eventually get to it.
Wasn't that your point about
the electric charge being dimensionless?
Once you set C at H bar
to be dimensionless, the charge is also dimensionless?
Yeah, the charge is equal to one over a hundred...
The square of the charge
is equal to one over 137,
is a dimensionless measure of the charge.
And it's a completely dimensionless number.
And we'll come to it.
We'll come to what it means.
You could...
Coulomb's constant is one you're saying?
Or would that be the third
one if you didn't Coulomb's constant?
Well, you can't set one over 137 equal to one.
So there's an obstruction to...
Because Coulomb's constant, you can set it Coulomb's.
Actually, when I took physics, that's what they did.
That would be the third one. They said Coulomb's constant.
Coulomb's constant?
Coulomb's constant.
Yeah, you could.
Right. You could.
For whatever reason, historically we haven't done that.
And there's probably no particular benefit in it.
In any case, we will use units in
which C and H bar are equal to one.
Quite often. Not always, but sometimes.
Only when I want to illustrate the size of numbers
will I put C and H bar back into equations.
So we...
Oh, some equations come out simpler. Yeah.
If we set C equal to
one, then E is equal to M.
That's it. Energy and mass are just the same thing.
We have another equation over here.
This is the equation of a...
energy for a photon.
This is the energy of a massive particle
which has some rest mass.
Energy of a photon is equal to H bar omega.
Well, the equation simplifies if we
set H bar equal to one.
Energy is just equal to frequency.
So that's just an illustration of the use of...
What's that?
No. Well, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
But not for a photon.
Photons have no mass.
Don't forget, this is...
Okay, there's a difference between the
meaning of E in these equations.
In this equation, it's rest mass and rest energy.
But photons can never be brought to rest.
Nevertheless, they do have energy, but it's not rest energy.
It's basically kinetic energy.
Photons have kinetic energy, energy of motion.
So this is just plain energy, whatever the energy is,
and it's equal to their frequency.
So they're two different...
Yeah.
Well, mass and...
rest mass and rest energy are relativistic because...
Mm-hmm.
...foot is zero.
What is rest?
It has to be relative to something.
Yeah.
Yeah, no, no, no, no.
Just forget the word rest now.
Just forget the word rest.
You just use it to differentiate them,
but, you know, what is
mass at rest in the universe?
Where would it be?
Not in the universe.
It's in the laboratory we're talking about.
Yeah, and then it becomes relative to the...
Relative to the laboratory.
Energies are measured relative to the laboratory.
Energies are different depending on the
state of motion of the observer.
If you have a photon or anything
else and two different observers observing it,
they see two different energies.
Obviously, even in Newtonian physics, that's true.
If I have an object here and I
see it, I say it has no kinetic energy.
You're running by at 100 miles
an hour, you look at it,
and you see that it has kinetic energy.
So energy is something both sides...
Yeah.
Energy is something that depends on the state of motion.
It depends on the state of motion of an object.
It makes sense to ask what the energy of
this cup of coffee is when it's at rest.
Then it's just the internal motion
of the molecules and so forth
and no overall kinetic energy.
That's the thing which is the...
When you write energy is equal to mass.
Right, but all I'm saying is that the
counter that it's sitting on is not at rest.
What's that?
In the universe, the counter that
it's sitting on is not at rest.
Okay.
I mean, if it's at rest, then
it's at rest relative to something else.
Yes, and the point is that energy is
measured relative to a given frame of reference.
Energy is not a universal
thing that everybody will agree on.
It's relative to a particular frame of reference.
So relative to my frame of reference,
the energy of this cup of coffee,
when it's standing still relative to
me, is equal to its mass.
Okay.
Question.
Earlier this evening, again, on this
whole subject of naming things and constants,
you didn't like frequency cycles per second.
You said physicists use omega, 2 pi...
To some extent, that's a historical fact.
My question is, it seems to
me, 2 pi using radio 57 whatever,
2 pi times that,
is more complicated than a complete cycle.
I agree with you.
Why would one use something that appears
to be more complex than a single cycle?
Good question.
Engineering math, except for if you do engineering math.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, there's some mathematical
simplicity to radians that is...
I don't know.
I think the answer is you look
at all the equations you write down,
you write them in both terms of frequencies
and you write them in terms of omegas.
And you see in which form
you encounter fewer factors of 2 pi.
I'm not sure what the answer to that is.
It's omega.
Omega, for sure.
It's simpler.
You think so?
Yeah.
Okay.
Do you do a lot of things with b
to the i something along with it or anything?
Great question.
It's time.
That's right.
Good question.
Practically speaking, is it possible to accelerate
2 particles fast enough with energy that
they will interact gravitationally?
In principle, certainly.
Practically speaking, like large
hexagonal lighters, that's proportional.
Very far from it.
Very, very far from it.
No.
Of course, it depends on
what you mean by a particle.
I don't think you'd want
to call the Earth a particle.
But, well, what's elementary?
Yeah.
What is the source of positron?
What's it?
A source of positron.
What is the source of positron?
High energy collisions.
That's the only way to do it?
Oh, you need it.
Yeah.
You need a collision to create positrons.
Nuclear processes?
Yeah.
Nuclear processes.
So nuclear decay, sometimes you yield positrons.
You used Planck's constant.
Planck time and Planck distance and things like that.
Well, we're not doing that.
Planck time and Planck distance correspond
to setting g equal to one.
Yeah.
So we're not doing that.
Okay.
Now, one of the reasons that
we might not want to do that—
This is the sort of thing
called the Planck time and Planck distance.
do that is once you set three of these
equal to one let's say then you have a
natural unit of length a natural unit
of time and natural unit of mass the
natural unit of length when you set G equal
to one and all of them equal to one
is called the Planck length and
it's very very much smaller than anything
that comes up in normal particle physics
so you would not want to measure
particle sizes particle radii and so
forth in units of the Planck
length it's just too small it's much
smaller than anything that occurs in so
that's the reason for not doing it
you use like in black holes or cosmology
yeah anything that really involves
gravity and quantum mechanics together
and relativity it makes sense to put all three
of them to one but if only two of
them are important then you have a
very small particle size and you can't do
anything about it but if it's not important you
may only want to set to two of the
constants equal to one okay let's see
I want to go a little bit further
yeah let's go a little bit further
with the basic concepts that we'll draw on
over and over I mean today
I'm just listing basically the preliminary
concepts prior to the application of
the Planck length and the Lagrangian length
and the Lagrangian Membrane length now there
are okay what are the basic concepts
there's a very small ones but three
I like they're called Pi roof worked
alnya objects protect the what I
mean by put and restricted line
and the I mean though applying only
the training rules fine let's try and get
all
all right
here's a nice example and it's bowing down again
for a second after you get a level Что
If you take an object and it's
at rest, it has no momentum at all.
It may have energy, it
has E equals m squared energy,
but it has no momentum, an object at rest.
If it's moving, it typically has momentum.
Momentum is conserved, just like energy.
When two objects hit each other,
the net amount of momentum doesn't change.
So momentum is a conserved quantity,
and because it's a conserved quantity, it has an importance.
Anything that's conserved is important.
Momentum is a combination of the mass of an object,
or better yet, its energy, and its direction of motion.
Its mass, its velocity, and its direction of motion.
It's a vector quantity.
It's a vector quantity, and as a rule,
it's proportional, or as a vector quantity,
it points along the direction of motion of an object.
It points along its velocity.
For a non-relativistic object,
an object moving with much
slower than the speed of light,
the momentum, of course, is equal
to the mass times the velocity.
The arrow on top means that it's a vector quantity.
It has a direction.
Okay, so mass times velocity
is momentum in non-relativistic physics,
but it's not quite the
right expression for in relativistic physics,
and in particular, it's not quite the right
thing for things moving with the speed of light.
So let's talk about light.
Does light have...
First of all, does light have energy?
Yes.
A beam of light shining on something heats it.
Does light have momentum?
Now, ordinary light, if it hits
you in the chest or something,
doesn't give you much of a push.
Why?
It's because the light is so dilute, and
it just doesn't have much of a kick.
But if you got hit by
this laser beam that they make in...
Where is it? Across the bay on the other side.
What's that place?
Livermore, yeah.
They got this great big laser,
and that laser shines its light,
and when it hits a piece
of material, it just implodes it.
What is it that's imploding it?
It's the momentum of the light, just pure, sheer momentum.
And it can be huge.
So yes, light has momentum, and
a pulse of light moving along...
Let's imagine a pulse of light moving along the x-axis.
Every pulse of light moving along a given direction.
Now, of course, real light might have some dispersion.
It might...
Some of it might go out.
Some parts of the light wave may go one way.
Some parts may go the other way.
But if the light is very collimated, so
that it's moving along a particular axis, then...
The right formula...
Now, I'm not going to prove this.
I'm not going to prove it.
I'm just going to tell you the right formula for a light beam is
that it is the energy of the light beam divided by the speed of light.
Let me just compare it with this.
Or another way to write it is the energy is
C times P, but let's leave it in this form here.
Yeah.
Let me just compare these two things.
Momentum is mass times velocity.
Momentum is energy divided by velocity.
Just a simple question.
Are they dimensionally the same?
So to inquire whether they're dimensionally the same, all you have to remember
is that the dimensions of energy are mass times the speed of light squared.
So just in terms of units, energy is like mc2.
It's like mc2 divided by c.
Just tells you that the momentum of a
beam of light is its mass times its velocity.
Not really its mass.
Its mass...
The rest of the mass of
a light beam is really zero.
It has no mass, rest mass.
But in terms of units, it's
equal to an energy times c squared.
Sorry.
Mass times c squared.
Mass times c squared divided by c.
You get the point?
It's just a question of units.
This doesn't look like this in terms of units.
One has a velocity upstairs.
One has a velocity downstairs.
But it is the same in units
when you remember that E equals mc squared.
Okay.
So this is the formula for the
momentum or the relationship between the momentum and
the energy of a light beam.
Ok.
So, you get the whole momentum sum, the motion.
It points in the direction along the motion.
That's right.
How to write this?
It points along the direction of the light beam.
But the magnitude of the momentum is
equal to the energy divided by c.
The magnitude of the momentum.
The direction is along the direction of the
axis of the light beam, along the direction
of the motion of the light beam.
of it
is equal to the energy of the light
beam divided by the speed of light c
you can see now momentum
is energy divided by c
that's why
that's why the momentum is so small
you can detect the energy of a light beam
sure you can, it heats up a little
bit of water, it heats up, it evaporates
water and so forth, it's
not hard to detect the energy
but it's quite hard to detect
the momentum of the light beam
and that's because there's this c in the denominator here
momentum of a light beam is very small, typically
of course if you
as i said if you
pump up the light beam enough
it can give quite a kick
alright so that, oh, oh, let's do one little exercise
let's just um...
the momentum of a light beam is
its energy divided by the speed of light
now we had a formula, do you remember
the formula for the energy of a photon?
let's take one photon now
one photon is an example of a light beam
let's figure out what the momentum of a photon is
so it is equal to its energy divided by the
speed of light, but what's the energy of a photon?
h bar omega
so the momentum
in magnitude is equal to
h bar
omega
divided by the speed of light
now do you remember the relationship between frequency
wavelength and the speed of light?
we had that before
that
what was it, frequency times
wavelength is equal to c, right?
frequency times wavelength and now if i use
if i put omega in the
denominator, it's equal to c, right?
omega here
omega times lambda is what?
2 pi times c or 2 pi divided by c?
2 pi times c, right?
2 pi times c
no, 2 pi
omega is 2 pi
c over 2 pi?
c over 2 pi, good
c over 2 pi
is that right?
you guys abdominal
aizumi
right
so wait a minute i don't believe you
i have to talk about myself
we have frequency times lambda equals c, right?
equals c, right? So therefore, yeah. So now,
wait. Omega is equal to 2 pi times frequency.
Right. So frequency is omega over 2 pi, so this
is omega over 2 pi, and I say that omega
times lambda is 2 pi times c. I was right.
Right. Omega times lambda is 2 pi c. So let's
get rid of the omega here and write omega
is equal to 2 pi c over lambda. I've just
divided by lambda. Let's just see what we get.
We get momentum of a photon is h bar
divided by c.
And now times omega, and omega is 2 pi
over lambda times c. The c's cancel out. That's
good because I know the c's should cancel out.
And what do we find? We find the momentum
of a photon is 2 pi h
bar, that's a number, divided by the wavelength.
I thought pi h bar equal h.
What's that?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. 2 pi h bar equals h.
Right. Right. That's right. Right. So p is also equal
to just old-fashioned h divided by lambda. There's
an example where we did it. It was
possibly not so smart to use h bar. Right.
Okay. Look, the 2 pi's are going to get you
one way or another. Some place they're going
to get you. The pi's always come up somewheres.
You can't get rid of them. Okay.
What does this say? This says the
shorter the wavelength, the larger the momentum of
a photon. A single photon of a radio
wave has a very, very small momentum. A single
photon of a gamma ray, a gamma ray is
a very, very short wavelength photon, has a good kick
to it. One photon, it won't hit, it's still
a pretty small kick. But what this is telling
you is that the momentum is related
to the wavelength. The shorter the wavelength, the
bigger the momentum. That is an
extremely important lesson. The shorter the wavelength,
the bigger the momentum, and also, of course,
the bigger the energy. The energy and the
momentum are related or proportional to each other.
So if you try to make very short
wavelength photons, the result would be that you have
to speak up.
spend a lot of energy to make them.
Now it becomes clear why physicists
have to build bigger and bigger machines
to see smaller and smaller things.
The reason is if you want to see
a small thing, you have to use short wavelengths.
If you tried to take a picture of me
with radio waves, I would look like a blur.
If you wanted to see any sort of distinctness
to my features, you would have to use wavelengths
which are shorter than the size of my head.
If you wanted to see a little hair on
my head, you would have to use wavelengths which are
as small as the thickness
of the hair on my head.
The smaller the object that you want to
see in a microscope, the shorter the wavelength
of light that you have to use.
Okay?
If you want to see an atom, literally see
what's going on in an atom, you have to illuminate
it with radiation whose wavelength is as
short as the size of the atom.
But that means the shorter the wavelength, the
smaller the object you want to see, the
larger the momentum of the photons that
you would have to use to see it.
So if you want to see really small
things, you have to use very—make very high energy
particles.
Very high energy photons or very
high energy particles of different types.
How do you make high energy particles?
You accelerate them in bigger and bigger accelerators.
You have to pump more and more energy
into them to make very high energy particles.
So this equation and its near
relative, what is its near relative?
E equals h bar omega.
Okay?
Okay.
So the equations are sort of the
central theme of particle physics that particle physics
progresses by making higher and higher energy
particles because the higher and higher energy
particles have shorter and shorter wavelengths and
allow you to see smaller and smaller structures.
That's the pattern that has held sway
over basically a century of particle physics or
almost a century of particle physics.
Okay.
Huh.
Uh, somewhat, uh, the striving for
smaller and smaller distances, that's obviously
what you want to do.
You want to see smaller and smaller things.
And, at the same time the striving for
shorter and shorter wavelengths which means that the
higher and higher momentum, or
higher and higher energy particles.
Is there a theoretical limit?
Is there a limit to shorter and shorter wavelengths?
Yeah, we think there is.
Well, yes or no.
Yes, in some sense — yes.
We think.
the Planck length, something new begins to happen.
And we can talk about that at some point
in these lectures, where it may bottom out, but
we're very far from the place where it bottoms out.
If it bottoms out, it probably bottoms out
at the Planck length, which is, you know,
17 orders of magnitude smaller scale than
what we're trying to see at the LHC.
So we've got a long ways to go.
A very long ways to go,
even if it does bottom out.
All right, those are the basic facts that
I wanted to get out in front of you.
They sort of determine largely how particle
physics has progressed, and as I said, it
has progressed by going at every stage
to shorter and shorter wavelengths, larger and
larger momentum and energy, and smaller and smaller objects.
Question.
Would there be any heuristic?
Saying that the wavelength or the size of
the particle you want to look at is inversely
related to the size of the cyclopron you're building.
I realize it's a ridiculous ratio, but is
that sort of, you know, one mile per...
Roughly speaking, yes, that's correct.
Roughly speaking, that's right.
If you have a given capacity to
accelerate, now what determines your capacity to accelerate?
The size of the electric and
the magnetic fields that you can create.
So let's suppose you take the largest fields that
you can create in a magnet made of steel
this big, and that determines your ability to accelerate.
Ability to accelerate means the energy that
you can pump into something per meter.
Given a meter of accelerator, how
much energy can you pump in?
All right, so to double the amount of energy
that slack produces, it would have to be twice
as long.
Or round.
Or round, but that's right.
But round gives you another problem.
The problem that round gives you is that
when particles move in circular orbits, they radiate.
And when they radiate, they lose energy.
So let's take the case of a linear accelerator.
The longer the linear accelerator is, the higher
the energy that you can pump the particles
to.
And pretty much linearly proportional
to the size of the accelerator.
And it's going to get half the double the resistance.
Double the resolution?
Yeah.
So basically, resolution times size is the constant.
Rough?
Yeah.
So if you wanted to get to this Planck
length, how big an accelerator would you have to have?
Well, as I said, 17 orders
of magnitude longer than the CERN accelerator.
No universe?
No, I think it's more like the galaxy.
Oh.
It's the ring engineer.
Yeah.
I call it the Gdankotron.
Right.
Yeah.
How high are the energies of cosmic
ray compared to cosmic ray in the IFC?
Higher.
I mean, the highest cosmic ray energies are
10 to the 21 electron volts or something like
that, which is 21 minus 9 is what?
Quick.
21 minus 9.
12 GeV, whereas the accelerator in,
well, no, it actually doesn't work.
The highest energy cosmic rays
are 10 to the 12 GeV.
But the problem is, you see, the problem
is cosmic rays, they may have this huge energy,
but they hit stationary targets.
Whereas in the accelerated CERN,
they're going to be colliding targets.
And so you get more bang
for your buck from the colliding particles.
But still, still, cosmic rays have much
more energy than, effective energy than the accelerators.
The problem with them is in order to really
do good experiments, you have to have a huge
flux of particles.
You can't do an experiment with one high energy particle.
It will probably miss your target or it probably
won't be a good dead on, head on collision.
You don't learn anything from that.
You learn very little from that.
So what you want is enough flux of particles
so that you have a good chance of having a
significant number of head on collisions.
That takes a lot of
particles when the targets are small.
So I told you how big
an accelerator you would have to make.
Now I would tell you how many particles
have to collide in order to see something interesting.
And I once worked out how much energy
you would have to make to see something interesting.
So you would have to be able to see
how much energy it would take to fuel this accelerator
in order that you could do
experiments in a reasonable amount of time.
And then I got something like a
hundred trillion barrels of oil a second.
So you would need the accelerator as
big as the galaxy being fueled by something.
I think it was a hundred
trillion barrels of oil a second.
And it's going to be
a while till we do experiments.
experiments like that.
But these are real distance scales.
They really do come into physics.
The puzzle and the question is how to probe
them, how to get at them without being able
to spend 100 billion barrels of
oil and build a galactic-sized accelerator.
So what is the GEV
energy level hopeful from the LHT?
Is it hopeful in what sense?
In what sense would you ask is it hopeful?
Compared to this 10 to the
12 GEV we get from it.
It's not comparable to the 10
to the 12 GEV from, no.
When you have a particle hitting a stationary target.
Take that 10 to the
12 and take its square root.
It's 10 to the sixth.
It's like having 10 to the sixth
GEV in colliding particles, each one colliding.
So if you have two particles colliding, each one
with 10 to the sixth GEV, it's like having
one particle with 10 to
the 12th hitting a stationary particle.
Now 10 to the sixth, that's a million GEV.
That's a thousand TEV.
So we're still very low compared
to what cosmic rays can do.
Okay.
But if you have a
handful of cosmic rays coming in,
the chances are that it's going
to do an interesting collision, a negligible.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.