Stanford University.
This is Sanjay.
Thank you. Did we get Sanjay on the recorded?
Yes, okay.
So we just wanna announce that we're
trying to collect up all the old
lectures, the video lectures that are on
YouTube, in one kind of a collection.
And the idea is for everybody
who's taking classes online and offline,
we can actually have an easy
way to navigate through all the lectures,
is you have to hunt for them, right?
So we're passing out a little sheet
that's got a web address on it.
Right now, this is a temporary housing for it, and
it should be good until whenever.
But when we do get a final home, we'll
have a link that'll directly go to it as well.
So this link should be good
for hopefully all eternity until we hit
horizon and all that good stuff.
Right, okay, so this is the address.
Let's see, http://www.http.com.
NewPacketTech, one word, newpackettech.com
slash resources slash suskind.
That's the address where, it's sort
of the website for the class,
or will be the website for the class.
And it's for anybody outside, inside, where
they can easily access without all the confusion,
that's taken place up till now, easily
access all of the lectures that are online.
All right, we have been discussing a simple
quantum field, and we're not finished with it.
I have to take a two-year course, and
believe me, a real course in quantum field theory
is genuinely two years of work.
It really cannot be done in one year sensibly.
I have to take that
two years of quantum field theory,
and continue to work on it.
And then sit down to a couple of lectures.
We've already taken a couple of lectures,
but I think we've had some forward motion.
I want to take the very, very simple
version of a quantum field that we've already discussed,
first of all, remind you what it is, and
discuss how it is used, again, to describe particle processes.
We've done a bit of this.
We've talked a bit about how the quantum field,
can code or codify scattering processes,
or creation and annihilation processes of particles.
But I want to go into
it in just a little more depth,
so that you can see where some of the
really interesting aspects of quantum field theory come from,
and how they influence questions,
like energy conservation, momentum conservation.
How do those things, how are they
related to these quantum fields that we've discussed?
Okay, before I do so, we
need a little bit of mathematics,
a little bit of formal mathematics, not much.
It's mathematics that we've done
before in these series of classes,
but I want to get them up on the blackboard.
The first thing is the Dirac delta function.
Alright, the Dirac delta function,
just to remind you what it is,
is a function which is the sort
of a limit of a genuine real function.
It's a function of, let's say it's coordinate,
let's for the moment just call this coordinate anything.
It could be x, it could be k.
Let's just call it y, so that we
don't prejudice whether it's something that I've called,
that I've defined previously.
The Dirac delta function is a
function which is a sort of lump.
It's concentrated someplace.
It's concentrated someplace and not other places.
But it's the limit of
an infinitely sharply concentrated function.
So we imagine that we can go to a limit
where this lump-like function is infinitely narrow.
Now I can't draw it as infinitely narrow,
so I'll draw it with finite width.
But imagine in your mind
narrowing it, narrowing it, narrowing it.
Now of course if you
narrow it without raising its height,
the area under it will decrease and decrease and decrease
to the point where there's no area left under it.
So what I want to do is
to keep the area under this function fixed
as I decrease the width.
So as I decrease the width,
I'm going to raise up the height of it
in such a way that the
product of height times width stays constant.
How constant? One. Just one.
An area of one located someplace infinitely narrow.
That's called a Dirac delta function.
If this point is y equals, let's call it a,
just to locate the particular point,
then the Dirac delta function
is delta of y minus a,
and delta of y minus a is
zero whenever y does not equal a,
over here or over here,
and equals something infinitely sharply
peaked at y equals a.
That's the Dirac delta function.
And it has the property by definition
that the area under it,
the derivative, the integral with respect to y,
is one.
So it's so narrow and so high
that the area is one,
and it's concentrated at the point
where the argument of the function
is equal to zero.
In other words, when y equals a.
That's the Dirac delta function.
Okay, now I want to show you
how the Dirac delta function emerges
from a certain integral.
An integral that we will come on many, many times.
Let's take the function
e to the i kx.
k, oops, e to the i kx.
Now, again, as we discussed last time,
we're discussing this on an interval,
which is a periodic interval,
which has total length all around it.
Equal to L.
So the distance around here
is equal to L.
I don't know if this...
Just the distance around it is equal to L.
It's periodic.
And so functions that live on this
periodic space here should be periodic.
Meaning to say they should come back to themselves
after one full loop.
Okay.
Now,
what is k?
First of all, k is one of the allowed values
of wavenumber on this.
In other words, one of the values of k
where e to the i kx is periodic.
So let's assume an allowed value there.
And let's take this function
and integrate it
over the entire cyclic x dimension here.
We could take x going from 0 to L.
Or for symmetry,
I could take it to
go from minus L over 2
to L over 2.
In other words,
instead of starting x at 0
and going to L,
I could start it at minus L over 2
and go to L over 2.
Put 0 at the center here.
Nothing special about this.
It just symmetrizes things nicely
so that the negative half and the positive half
are symmetric.
When you leave the space,
if you're marching along,
and you come to L over 2,
you pop back up at minus L over 2.
Okay.
So we're taking a function,
a periodic function,
e to the i kx,
and integrating it from minus L over 2
to L over 2.
What is the answer?
Okay, first of all,
what is the answer if k is equal to 0?
L.
This is L.
Let's write this.
Equal to L if k is equal to 0.
And what if k is not equal to 0?
Because if you take a periodic function
that oscillates
and you integrate it,
then you get 0
because it's positive
as much as it's negative.
Only for k equals 0,
in that case, of course,
this doesn't oscillate.
It's just equal to 1.
Then you get L.
Okay.
So,
now let's think of this
as a function of k.
Let's draw the k axis.
Here's the k axis.
Now, k is not just any number.
It's one of the allowed numbers.
So it's discrete.
Does anybody remember
what the allowable values of k are?
2 pi n over L.
Right?
In particular,
as L gets bigger and bigger,
the distance between neighboring values of k
gets smaller and smaller.
And eventually,
as L gets infinitely big,
these discrete intervals
shrink to 0.
Okay.
So now what's the distance?
What's the distance?
Let's put k equals 0.
k can be positive or negative, incidentally.
Let's put k equals 0 right over here.
Here's k equals 0.
Alright.
What's the interval between neighboring values of k?
2 pi over L.
That's the distance from k equals 0,
or from n equals 0
to n equals 1, for example.
2 pi over L.
Now let's take this function.
This function is a function of k, of course.
We've integra-
I'm sorry.
I've integrated it over x.
It's only a function of k.
What is it equal to?
Let's plot it on here.
It's equal to L
when k is equal to 0.
So right at k equals 0 here,
it's high and it's equal to L.
Let's, uh,
let's just give it a
slight width just for the purpose of drawing it.
Just for the purpose of drawing it,
right at k equals 0 here,
it has a height equal to L,
but at k not equal to 0,
it's 0.
That's what we concluded.
At k it's equal to L if
if k is equal to 0,
and it's equal to 0
if k is not equal to 0.
So, how high is it?
It's height L.
How wide is it?
Well, one interval,
you can't think of anything
smaller than one interval on here,
uh, it has a width 2 pi over L.
What's the area,
if I imagine giving it that much of a width,
what is the area under it?
2 pi.
So that means
that this function is 2 pi
times the delta function.
This function here is 2 pi
times delta of k.
Why delta of k?
At k equals 0,
it's not equal to 0.
At k equals anything else,
it is equal to 0.
Now, what is the meaning of this?
This is, the meaning of this is
in the limit of very, very large L.
This becomes a very, very narrow,
very, very high function
whose area is equal to 2 pi.
Okay.
We'll keep that in mind as we go along.
This is called the Dirac delta function,
and we can now say,
let's now go to the limit of very large L.
If we go to the limit of very large L,
in other words, we're making
these intervals progressively smaller and smaller,
we're really approaching the situation that
really does define the Dirac delta function,
then this integral goes all the ways
from minus infinity
to plus infinity.
So, just think of this as a formal prescription
for an integral of e to the i kx,
and the rule is, it gives delta of k,
2 pi times delta of k.
This is equal to 2 pi
times delta of k.
That's something of importance
that when you integrate over a function
of e to the i kx like this,
dx,
you get a Dirac delta function of k.
Let's see if you can guess, supposing
instead of doing the integration over x,
I did an integral over k.
Exactly the same integral,
except it's not at all the same integral,
e to the i kx,
but instead of integrating dx,
I integrate dk.
What must that be?
It's a function of x.
But it's exactly the same structure here,
except I just interchanged x and k, right?
x and k appear symmetrically here,
so if I interchange x and k,
this doesn't change,
but I've changed the integral over k,
I've changed the integral over
x to an integral over k.
So this is now some function of x,
but what is the function?
2 pi times delta of x.
So these are two little observations
that we will see happening,
we'll see their utility
occurring in a number of places.
That's the Dirac delta function.
That's our first little bit of mathematics tonight.
What the hell was that?
Next little bit of mathematics.
I taught you what a ket is.
A ket is a symbolic notation for a quantum state.
I also think I told you...
You didn't use the word ket.
I didn't. What did I use?
I did, I did, I did, I did.
And I told you it was half of a braket.
Yeah.
Yeah, okay.
It's the other half of the braket now
that we want to talk about, the bra,
otherwise known as bra.
These are just notational devices.
For our purposes, these are simply notational devices.
And the question is, when do you use the bra
and when do you use the ket?
For our purposes, we will think of kets
as initial states in a process.
If a process starting with some initial states
is described by some quantum state,
we'll describe the initial state as a ket vector.
Initial.
In.
Final states we will describe by bra vectors.
And when you put a bra
vector next to a ket vector,
you make a bracket.
This is simply a bunch of symbolic manipulation,
but at the end, what
comes out of the symbolic manipulation
are numbers.
Okay?
Numbers.
Experimental numbers.
So I'm going to teach you now some symbolic manipulations.
For every...
Let's go back to the harmonic oscillator.
For the harmonic oscillator,
we characterized the quantum
states of the harmonic oscillator
by occupation numbers, n.
The number of excitations of the harmonic oscillator.
The number of times...
The number of units of energy
that's been put into the harmonic oscillator.
We can also describe it...
That's a ket vector.
That's the ket description of a particular quantum state.
We could also write it
in terms of a bra vector.
So far I haven't told you anything.
I just told you there's two
ways to write the same thing.
You say, what's the difference between them?
Not much.
Okay?
But if we are clever
in our use of this notation,
it will help us do some bookkeeping that's interesting.
All right.
Now, first of all,
there's the notion of the inner product
between a bra vector and a ket vector.
Now, all of this is
in our past quantum mechanics classes,
and I refer you back to it.
We're going to go through it lightning-like tonight.
If I have a ket vector
n and a bra vector m,
I can put them next to each other,
and putting a ket vector in there,
and putting a ket vector next
to a bra vector in this way,
always gives a number.
The ket vectors are abstract things.
The bra vectors are abstract things.
But the product of two of them back to back,
or front to front, I'm not sure which,
in that form, is a number.
This number...
Now, m stands for some quantum state,
the nth quantum state of the oscillator,
and n stands for the nth state of the oscillator.
This number...
This is definition now...
is equal to zero
if m is not equal to n,
and it's equal to one
if m equals n.
So the bra vector and the ket vector,
for the same value of n,
have a product which is one.
It's called the inner product.
The inner product between these two.
It's one if n equals m.
It's zero if n is not equal to m.
Or, to write it, then it's zero.
Or, to write it in a unified form,
we can write it as delta nm,
whose definition is
it's zero unless n equals m,
and one if n is not equal to m.
It's kind of like the Dirac delta function.
It's a discrete form of the Dirac delta function.
All right, this is notational...
This is just notational tricks for things.
Now, let's come to creation and annihilation operators.
What I want to get at before we go further
is how creation and annihilation operators
act on bra vectors.
I've told you how they act on ket vectors,
and I have not told you
how they act on bra vectors.
Now, of course, you can say,
I haven't told you.
In fact, I haven't even told you the rules
which would allow you to deduce how they act.
But I'm going to show you how they act
and then show you why this rule
was particularly nice.
All right, so let's take creation operators first of all.
What does a creation operator do
when it acts on the
nth quantum state of an oscillator?
It multiplies it by square root of n plus one
times the n plus first state.
What about the annihilation?
The annihilation gives you square root of n
times n minus one.
So one of them raises the quantum state,
one of them lowers it,
and then lowers the quantum state,
and in each case they multiply
by the appropriate square root of n.
Now we can ask,
now we're asking for a definition.
This is not a theorem which we want to prove.
This is a definition of how creation
and annihilation operators operate
when they act on bra vectors.
So how shall we take a plus
to act on the nth bra vector?
And I'm going to tell
you now what the rule is.
The rule is that however
it acts on the nth vector,
it gives another vector, another bra vector, of course.
Let's circle that bra vector,
and now take its inner product
with the nth ket vector.
However this acts,
whatever it gives,
it gives another bra vector.
That's the rule.
When an operator acts on a ket vector,
it gives a ket vector.
When it acts on a bra vector,
it gives a bra vector.
And the notation is such
that when an operator acts on a bra vector,
you put the operator to the right
and hit it to the left
when it acts on a ket vector.
So it's a neat notation.
The rule is that you get exactly the same answer
as if you did what?
You applied a plus m.
Allow a plus to act on m
and then take the inner product with n.
See, there's two distinct operations.
However a plus should act on n,
we'd like to find out
how it should act on n,
we're going to define it
so that you get the
same answer for this bra ket
as if you allowed a plus to act on m.
Well, I've given you the rule
for how a plus acts on m,
and then take the inner product with n.
So let's see if we can figure out from this,
from this set of abstract principles
or abstract definitions,
how a plus acts on n.
Let's see.
Let's first take the bottom line here,
the bottom line, let's calculate it.
It's n,
and now a plus acts on m.
What does that give?
Square root of m plus one.
That's a number, we take it outside.
Square root of m plus one,
and then what?
m plus one.
What does this give?
This factor gives zero
unless n is equal to m plus one.
If n is the same as m plus one,
then you get the number
square root of m plus one,
which also happens to be the
square root of n, of course.
So that's one way of calculating what,
that's this over here.
But notice, it only gives an answer,
a non-zero answer,
if this is one unit higher than this.
Sorry.
Yeah.
It only gives an answer if
m is one unit lower than n.
If m is one unit lower than m,
then a plus comes along,
increases m by one unit,
and then we get a non-zero answer.
So the only way to get a non-zero answer
is if m is one unit lower than n.
Well, let's look at this over here.
Supposing that a plus acted on n to raise n.
Then we would only get an answer
if m was one unit bigger than n.
But according to this rule,
we only get a non-zero answer
if n is one...
I think, uh,
all right, let me say it accurately.
I get my...
Okay.
From this form, we see that n
has to be one unit bigger than m
to get a non-zero answer.
n must be one unit bigger than m.
All right.
If, on the other hand,
a plus increased the value of n over here,
then we would only get a non-zero answer
in the opposite situation,
where n was one unit what?
Less than m.
All right.
So this can't be the right rule
that when a plus acts to the left,
that it increases the index here.
What it must do is decrease the index here.
And in fact, that's the definition.
That's the correct definition.
When...
When a plus acts on a bra vector n,
it doesn't increase n,
it decreases n.
n minus one.
And what about the numerical factor there?
The correct numerical factor is just square root of n,
if you want to.
If you want to, you can work this out.
All right.
What if it...
What about n a minus?
What does that do?
Well, the answer is...
I've given you enough rules
that you can determine yourself what it does.
What it does is it increases n,
n plus one,
times square root of n plus one.
In other words, to make the story short,
when a plus acts on ket vectors,
it increases n
and multiplies by square root of n plus one.
A minus decreases n
and multiplies by square root of n.
When a plus and a
minus act on the bra vectors,
they just interchange.
A plus decreases n
and multiplies by square root of n.
A minus increases n
and multiplies by square root of n plus one.
All right.
That's the rule.
Just...
That's the rule
which leads to a very lovely calculus
that's useful in quantum mechanics.
So calculus meaning now tricks for computing simple things.
Let me give you an example.
Let's calculate in two distinct ways
the following quantity.
Let's take a plus, a minus.
Remember what that was?
What did that stand for?
Yes, it stands for...
It's a quantum mechanical operator
that stands for the occupation number,
the number of quanta in the state.
And let's calculate this quantity here.
A minus, I'm sorry.
A minus.
Let's calculate it in two different ways.
Now, for those who studied some quantum mechanics,
you'll know that this expression stands
for the average value
of whatever this quantity is
in the quantum state n.
But for the moment,
let's just calculate it
as an abstract exercise.
But let's calculate it two ways.
In the first way,
let's allow this operator
to act to the right.
First, a minus acts to the right.
What does a minus give
when it acts on this?
It gives square root of n
times n minus one.
We still have a plus,
which we haven't used up yet.
n.
Now, numbers come on the outside.
Numbers like square root of n,
they come on the outside.
Square root of n.
Now, what does a plus do
when it acts on n minus one?
It pushes it back up.
It pushes it back up
and multiplies by what?
Square root of n.
One integer higher than what appears here.
So that means, again,
square root of n.
That gives us two square roots of n,
which means n,
times n what?
Square root of n.
n.
a plus on n minus one
brings us back to n.
And nn, what is that?
That's just one.
So it just gives us n.
If it acts a plus, a minus
when sandwiched within the quantum state n,
just gives us the numerical number n.
What would happen if we did it
not in the opposite order,
but by acting to the left
on the bra vector?
Let's do it.
What happens when a plus
acts on n to the left?
It gives us n minus one
times the square root of n.
But we still have to act with a minus.
What does a minus do
when it acts on n minus one?
It raises you back up.
Raises you back up to n.
A minus.
And gives you another square root of n.
So you see,
with this definition,
that the creation and annihilation,
or the raising and lowering,
get interchanged when you go
to their action on bra vectors and ket vectors,
then it doesn't matter
which way you imagine these operators operate,
we'll get the same answer.
It's a useful notation.
And so when you see a thing like this,
you don't have to ask,
should you operate with this to the right
and then take the inner product with the left-hand side,
or should you operate to the left
and then take the inner product with the right-hand side?
You get the same answer.
That's the beauty of that particular definition here.
All right, that's good.
Now, what are we going
to do with all of this?
Well, of course, we're going to study quantum fields,
which are objects built out of these creation
and annihilation operators.
Yeah, let's go right there.
Let's go to the quantum fields,
go back to a simple quantum field
that we've discussed already.
And then come to the description of quantum processes,
scattering processes, creation of processes,
annihilation processes, and so forth,
how they're described by quantum fields
or how they're described
in terms of mathematical expressions
involving the quantum fields.
Why are we interested in processes like collisions
and creation and annihilation processes involving particles?
Because in the microscopic world,
that's about all we can do.
If we want to do experiments,
the only real handles we have on experiments
is colliding particles together and see what comes out
and describing those processes,
how the initial state of the particle,
of two particles, for example,
morphs into some other state
involving five, seven, nine particles,
four particles, whatever it is.
The tool for that is quantum field theory,
and we're setting up some simple algorithms
to help us with these simple examples.
All right, so let's go back to the definition
of the simplest quantum field.
The simplest quantum field,
we took it to be
a function of only one coordinate,
namely x.
There's no reason why we can't
think of x, y, and z here
and make position into a three-dimensional thing.
If we do so,
the momentum also has to be...
Oh, incidentally,
we'll work in units in
which h-bar is equal to one.
I don't think tonight the speed
of light will come into anything.
But what's the connection between momentum and k
if h-bar is equal to one?
They're the same.
Normally, you would have an h-bar over here, h-bar k.
But if h-bar is set equal to one,
k and momentum are the same thing.
Right.
So we concocted a thing which we call
the quantum field associated with the point of space x.
As I said, x could
be a three-dimensional point of space.
If it is, then k has to be three-dimensional.
If we're living in three dimensions,
then the momentum is three-dimensional,
meaning to say it has three components.
And then k will also have three components.
But other than that,
the formulas I'm going to write down
are pretty much the same in three dimensions,
whatever number of dimensions we're doing.
Psi of x was a sum
over all the allowed values of momentum.
If we're talking about the universe on a circle
or the periodic universe,
then these are the k's which are
2 pi over l times an integer.
If we're talking about an integer,
then we're talking about an infinitely big universe,
then k can be anything, any number.
Sum over k,
summation over k of the creation operator
for a particle of momentum k
times e to the minus ikx.
That now has become a quantum field.
There's a conjugate quantum field,
and now we pretty much,
if we're quantum mechanics people,
we talk about the Hermitian conjugate.
If we're classically oriented people,
we simply talk about the complex conjugate.
We can call it psi
star or psi dagger of x,
the complex conjugate,
which is a similar thing involving annihilation operators
times e to the plus ikx.
Then we call the gradient motionıs a few n cakeOS,
divided by pi over n,
which is essentially the series battery of a particle.
And this is solving for the
of the energy Lorentz sample Ivate.
I'll look at the free holiday increase
and you'll see that it's a useful definition.
Okay?
So, I'm afraid that's the situation here.
Why is this the definition?
Because this is a useful definition.
I could have put something else here,
and it would have been a useless definition.
So, it's premature to ask why this is
the definition, but it is a nice, simple expression.
It's not very complicated.
Sum over the allowable values of momentum,
creation operator times e to the minus i kx,
or the complex conjugate which has annihilation
operator times e to the plus i kx.
Now, I'm going to do
something even a little bit fancier.
I'm going to give these
psi of x's some time dependence.
So far, they don't depend on time.
The definition does not involve time.
But I'm going to introduce some time into the game.
And how do I introduce
time? Why do I introduce time?
Well, remember that there's a connection
between the momentum, the wave vector k,
and the frequency of an oscillation.
These are fields.
These are fields. Fields oscillate.
As it's written now, it doesn't
oscillate. It doesn't have any time dependence.
If this has anything to do with
a real field, waves, and so forth,
we better introduce some time into it.
Well, that's not so hard, because we remember that
for each value of k, there is a frequency.
Frequency tells us how things change with time.
Supposing I have an object, a mathematical object,
which has a certain frequency, omega.
How do I write the
function that oscillates with frequency omega?
E to the i omega t.
E to the i omega t, which also happens, of
course, to be cosine omega t plus i sine omega t.
This is a function with a definite frequency.
The frequency is omega.
Alright, now, in past lectures, I pointed out
to you that for various kinds of waves,
each k, k is a wave
vector, it's inversely related to the wavelength,
for each k, there is a frequency.
So we can say that there is, for
each k, there is an omega of k,
and each oscillation, each time we see
an e to the minus i kx,
we can put in front of it an
oscillation, in front of it or behind it,
an e to the i omega of k times t.
Now, this thing has not only
space dependence, but it has time dependence.
And moreover, it's time dependent, we
do the same thing here, of course,
e to the minus i omega of kt.
Let's erase side dagger for the
moment, we'll come back to it,
I want more room on the blackboard.
Here's an object which has
both space dependence and time dependence.
The time dependence has been arranged in such
a way that for each value of the wavelength,
or k, it oscillates with a time dependence which
is just the right time dependence for that wavelength.
This is now a function of space and time.
It truly is a quantum field
now, it varies in space and time.
Okay, I want to take an example
and show you that in the example,
there is an equation, a wave
equation, for psi of x and t.
And see if we can figure
out what the wave equation is.
See if we can find the wave
equation for psi of x and t,
knowing the connection between omega and k.
Now, I haven't told you what
the connection between omega and k is.
But, let's suppose that we're
talking about a non-relativistic particle.
In other words, I'm not talking about a photon,
I'm talking about a species of particle,
which moves with much less than the speed of light.
We're working in the approximation
in which everything is non-relativistic.
Okay, when h-bar is equal to one,
h-bar equals one,
omega has another name.
What's the other name for omega?
Energy.
Remember,
energy of a photon, or energy of a quantum,
of a single quantum, we're
talking about a single quantum now,
the energy is h-bar omega.
If h-bar is equal to one,
omega and energy are the same.
Momentum is equal to h-bar times k.
So, when h-bar is equal to one,
energy is frequency, and momentum is wave number.
Okay.
What's the connection for a slowly moving particle,
slowly means only slowly moving
compared to the speed of light,
what's the connection between energy and momentum?
Right.
Energy of a slowly moving particle
is the square of the momentum
divided by twice the mass.
This is, of course, the same thing as writing energy
is equal to one half mv squared,
and p is equal to mv.
Right.
If we solve for v
and plug it in into here,
we get this relationship here.
Okay, that also tells us now
the relation between omega and k,
k squared over two m.
Right?
So now, we really do know
the precise form of psi of x and t,
it's a sum over the allowed values of momentum,
and omega of k is not
just some arbitrary omega of k,
but it is k squared over two m.
With that proviso,
psi of x and t
solves or satisfies a differential equation,
a wave equation.
So let's see what the wave equation is.
First of all, in wave equations,
derivatives with respect to space and time
enter and are equal to each other in some form,
that's what a wave equation is,
equations for how space variation is related,
or how time variation is related to space variation.
So let's consider first the time derivative of psi.
What's the time derivative of psi?
I'm going to call it psi dot,
I'm going to call it
the time derivative of psi dot,
because this is the time derivative of psi dot,
this is the time derivative of psi dot,
and I'm going to use this to
calculate the time derivative of psi dot.
So I'm going to get
the time derivative of psi dot,
which is the sum of a plus of k,
times what?
Times i omega,
inside the summation,
i omega of k,
e to the i omega of kt.
All I've done is say every time,
this is still under the summation here,
every time I differentiate with respect to t,
it pulls down a factor of i omega.
So that's psi dot.
Now let's look at the space derivatives.
What is the space derivative?
d psi by dx.
Well, we do exactly the same thing.
Every time we differentiate with respect to x,
it pulls down a factor of minus ik.
So this is equal to the same kind of thing,
summation of minus ik,
a plus of k,
times e to the minus ik x,
e to the i,
omega of kt.
So differentiating with respect to x
always just pulls down a factor of ik.
Differentiating with respect to time
pulls down a factor of i omega.
Now there's no simple relationship
between this and this.
Why not?
Because omega is related to k squared.
If omega was simply related to k,
for example,
if omega had to be equal to k,
then we would just say
psi dot is equal to d psi dx.
For example, imagine a world,
or a kind of particle,
where the frequency is in fact equal to k.
That's a very simple situation.
In that situation,
i omega k is the same as,
apart from a minus sign,
is the same as ik,
and we would say,
i k,
that such a field satisfies a equation
that psi dot is equal,
I think,
to minus d psi by dx.
Is that clear?
All right.
But that's not the case here.
We have to have omega equals k squared.
So how can we get k squared?
Take another derivative.
Each time we differentiate,
it brings down a factor of ik.
So let's differentiate again.
That brings us minus ik squared.
What's minus ik squared?
I think that's minus k squared, right?
Minus k squared.
Minus,
with a minus sign.
But now,
k squared is 2m times omega.
So let's write that.
2m times omega.
And let's divide the left-hand side by 2m.
2m is just a number.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
I'm confused.
Is the minus sign really supposed to be there?
I thought you had minus i.
Let's see.
Let's check.
When I differentiate with respect to time,
it gave an i omega.
So that's all i omega.
Now, when I differentiate it with respect to k,
it gave it a minus ik,
and I did it twice.
So that gives minus ik squared.
What is minus ik squared?
Minus k squared.
This is minus k squared.
So yes, as far as I
can tell, the minus sign is there.
Minus sign.
OK.
There was a minus k squared,
and then I substituted for minus k squared
minus 2m omega.
And that's where this came from.
OK.
I'm more familiar with this
in the form in which
we divide both sides by 2m.
This doesn't matter, of course.
Let's divide it by 2m,
and we get 1 over 2m
times the second derivative of
psi with respect to space squared
is omega times all this stuff,
but that's clearly proportional to psi dot.
What's the relationship?
You've got an i omega there.
Here we have an i.
There's going to be an i in the formula.
We can divide by i, which is
the same as multiplying by minus i.
To make a long story short,
the right equation should be minus i psi dot,
that's the time derivative of psi,
is equal to 1 over 2m
times the second derivative of
psi with respect to x squared.
Now, do I have the sign right or not?
Of course I don't. I never get it right.
Okay.
Now is it right?
No, you had it right.
I'm not sure.
1 over 2m squared?
1 over 2m.
Not 1 over 2m squared.
Okay.
Let's see.
Is the minus sign there or not?
Let's put a minus here,
and then there's a plus here.
So it looks like it's the plus sign.
As far as I can tell, it's the plus sign.
Yeah.
Well, it's just that you have the i on
the opposite side of the equation than i do, so...
Well, of course.
That will do the trick, right.
Okay.
Does anybody know the name of that equation?
It's the Schrodinger equation.
The Schrodinger equation.
Right.
But it's not the Schrodinger equation for
the same thing as in elementary quantum mechanics.
In elementary quantum mechanics, psi
is just a function of position.
It's not an operator.
It doesn't do things.
It's just a thing whose square is a probability.
Here, it is an operator.
When it acts on states, it creates particles.
It annihilates particles.
This is an instance of the
relationship between particles and quantum fields.
Quantum fields are operators.
They happen to have the same equations
as the Schrodinger equation of elementary quantum mechanics.
They are very closely related.
But they're quantum mechanical operators.
They're observables.
You can observe them.
Under what circumstances do they behave like this?
They behave like classical fields.
In other words, you can measure them
the same way you measure the electromagnetic field.
The answer is that they behave like classical
fields when the number of quanta is very large.
When the number of quanta is large,
then the magnitudes of the fields are large,
and the quantum fluctuations are
small, the quantum uncertainties are small,
exactly like a harmonic oscillator.
A harmonic oscillator, if you look
at it, is a quantum oscillator.
It's a quantum oscillator.
If it's got a big motion, it behaves classically.
If it's only got one quantum unit
of excitation, it behaves very quantum mechanically.
So this is an example, as
I said, of a quantum field,
and it has creation and annihilation operators in it.
Nevertheless, it's a thing which satisfies an equation,
and the equation is the Schrodinger equation.
This is obviously a more advanced
notion of the Schrodinger wave form,
and it's a little bit more complex than just saying it's
a thing whose square is the probability for a given particle.
It's something a little bit different.
Okay, and as I said, it is a quantum field.
It's the simplest version of a quantum field.
How do we use it?
How do we use it to describe processes?
So I'm going to give you any...
And we've already talked about this a little bit.
What I didn't talk about, and
which I want to come to now,
is energy and momentum conservation,
and how energy and momentum conservation are codified,
or codified, whatever the right word is,
in the various dependencies of psi
and the way that we describe various processes.
I want to imagine now
describing the very, very simplest process
in which...
a particle scatters off a target.
A target, in this case, is a thing
which is so heavy that it doesn't recoil.
A particle comes and either reflects
off it or scatters off it.
In three dimensions, it could have its trajectory changed.
In other words, it could be coming in
from the left and go off straight ahead.
But what can you say?
About a particle scattering off an ordinary target,
a target that's just stuck there, it doesn't move,
stays there forever and ever.
Which of the conservation laws would you
expect to be true for that particle?
How about momentum?
And it would make no sense
whatsoever if it has any specifics.
But it isшибene to innovate in, in,
and to form a kind of aignon,
but I think the base is just...
a hotspot where a real species has 겁
And to find its real intentions in this particular training,
we have to have two levels of calm-
have two levels of calm
Don't createencias on one side and underground.
You're a physical object-
a physical object-
A person to become...
a person to become...
So it's not absorbed.
But yes, it could be reflected, bing bang.
It could be refracted, in which case
its direction of motion is changed.
In any case, the momentum of that particle
generally is not the same coming in as going out.
Of course, secretly what happens
is momentum is really conserved,
but what happens is of course the target
absorbs some of the momentum.
But let's just fix the target.
Let's imagine nailing down the target,
and the target is not part of our mathematical description,
or the motion of the target is not part
of our mathematical description.
Then in the mathematical description
of a particle scattering off a target,
the momentum of the particle is not conserved.
What about the energy?
Yeah, the energy of the particle is conserved.
If you take a tennis ball, well, a tennis ball
is a bad example because it heats up
when you throw it against the wall.
But an idealized tennis ball where you can ignore heat
and you throw it against
the wall and it bounces off.
What can you say about
the way that it bounces off?
You can't say that momentum is conserved.
The momentum has gone from that direction to that direction,
but the energy is conserved.
So how can we see, can
we see that in some simple model
of the scattering process that momentum is not conserved
and energy is conserved using these wave fields?
So we talked about this last time a little bit,
and I showed you how you could describe a process
of scattering, creation, annihilation, and so forth
using these quantum fields.
So here is a model,
here is a, space is horizontal,
time is vertical, and the
axis over here represents a target.
It's fixed in space, it neither,
and it goes on and on forever
into the past, it just sits
there, and a particle comes in.
It hits the target at
some point, and either bounces off
or goes forward or scatters into some other direction.
So we describe the initial
state by saying there's one particle
with a momentum.
Let's call it k in for initial, initial or incoming.
And then a particle goes
off, having scattered off the target.
And let's use a language now.
It's absorbed by the target and suddenly re-emitted
by the target.
Think of it, instead of just thinking of it
as bouncing off the target, let's
in the back of our mind
have a picture in which
it is absorbed, or it's absorbed,
and suddenly re-emitted by the target.
So we're annihilated by the target and then instantaneously
re-created by the target, but
possibly with a different momentum.
Let's call that final momentum k final.
Let's just call it ki and kf.
Initial and final.
And what are we interested in?
We're interested in the probability amplitude,
the quantum mechanical probability amplitude,
that the particle scatters from
momentum k initial to k final.
Now, one more ingredient.
I'm going to assume that the scattering can happen
with equal strength, equal at any time,
always at the same place.
We're going to place the target at x equals zero,
but we're going to assume
that the scattering process can occur
at any time.
We're going to place the target at x equals zero, but we're
going to assume that the scattering process can occur at any time,
whatever time that particle gets there,
it will scatter or not
scatter or do whatever it does,
but with no special dependence on the
time at which the process takes place.
That's going to be our basic assumption.
How do we describe the event of the
particle being absorbed at position x equals zero?
Well, we describe that
by means...
This should be psi dagger, shouldn't it?
I think this should be psi dagger.
It's the daggers that go with the plus signs here,
I think in my notation that I used last time.
I think that's right.
But then, you do the plus sign, so...
I don't think so.
I think a plus always went with a minus here.
I think so.
And then this one would be plus, if I remember.
Okay.
So, you describe it in the following...
By a kind of bookkeeping.
It's all bookkeeping, but it's useful bookkeeping.
You absorb the particle.
This is a piece...
This is a field which creates particles.
Let's write down the other
conjugate field which annihilates particles.
It's the complex conjugate, or psi of x and t,
which is made up out of annihilation operators,
e to the plus i kx,
e to the minus i omega of kt.
It's just the...
Every place...
Everything is conjugated.
e to the minus i kx becomes e
to the plus i kx, and so forth.
And these are to be thought
of as complex conjugates of each other,
or Hermitian conjugates of each other.
All right.
Let's imagine, first of all,
absorbing the particle at the origin.
How do we do that?
We absorb it by an opery.
Well, we start with the initial state.
The initial state has no
particles with any particular momentum
except one particle with momentum ki.
So, if we described it in terms of occupation numbers,
only...
The occupation number associated with
momentum ki would be non-zero.
We can also just label that by
saying there's one particle with momentum ki,
and be done with it.
We don't need to specify
all the particles that aren't there.
But nevertheless, it's useful to keep in mind
that when we specify the initial state,
we're specifying all of the occupation
numbers of all the various quanta,
and only one of them,
according to assumption here, is present.
So there's a one here,
and all the others are zero.
And we just label it by saying,
well, there's one particle with momentum ki.
Then, that particle is either...
is annihilated at the origin, if it's at the origin,
and let's describe that by
psi of x and t,
but x is equal to zero.
Zero and t.
Why is x equal zero?
I'm assuming that if the process happens,
it happens at the target,
and the target is at x equals zero,
but it can happen at any time.
So that's the process of
absorbing the particle at time t.
That's what this says.
But then, the particle is immediately recreated,
and then, it's annihilated.
That's why you say, why does it have to be?
It doesn't have to be.
That's the model that I'm making.
A particle absorbed and immediately re-emitted.
That's a mathematical model.
It's not necessarily a law of nature
about any particular kind of particle.
In fact, in the real world,
a photon can be absorbed by an atom
and emitted later or earlier.
So what we're talking about
here is a simple mathematical model.
In which the process happens all at an instant.
Particle absorbed and re-emitted.
And what's the emission described by?
It's described by the creation of
a particle also at point zero.
So that's psi dagger of
zero and the same time t.
But what time?
What time should I put there?
The same time.
The same time, but which time?
It will matter.
So, why one or zero?
How about let's say it can happen at any time.
Any time that the particle gets there.
Whenever the particle gets there.
That's the same as saying,
integrate this over all possible times.
In other words,
there is a process in which
the particle is absorbed at this time,
at this time, at this time, and so forth.
So let's not prejudice what time it happens
by just averaging or integrating over all possible times.
This is a mathematical expression which we can work out.
I will show you as we go along
what the implications of this integral over time are.
But the basic physics of it
is that the process could happen at any time.
No special time.
No particular time is singled out as special.
And we get rid of the
specialness of the value of time
by just integrating over all values of time.
What does this give?
This gives the final state.
Here's an initial state.
These are operators which operate on the initial state
and give some final state.
How do we calculate the probability
that the final state consists
of one and only one particle
moving with some other momentum?
If you remember your rules of quantum mechanics,
we take the inner product of this state
with the final state.
So let's say one particle with momentum k final.
This is a number.
Remember, a ket vector operator bra vector
give us some kind of number.
Is this number the probability for the scattering?
Not quite.
We have to square it.
We have to take the absolute
value of it and square it.
Now I've left out one important ingredient
in this expression.
We're going to evaluate this.
We're going to go through it,
and we're going to see what it says.
Of course, I'm purposefully,
well, not purposefully,
I would rather be able to explain all of this
in complete logical order.
But, you know, given an hour
to do all of quantum field theory,
we have to draw on things
that we've done in the past.
So in the past,
I explained that probabilities are squares of amplitudes,
and amplitudes are inner products
between initial states and final states.
Okay?
So here's the thing we want to calculate.
But I've left one thing out.
I've left out the strength of the scatterer.
The strength of the scatterer is a measure
of the strength of interaction
between the scatterer and the final state.
And the scattery.
So let me give you an example.
You could have a charged particle at the origin,
which is scattering a photon.
A photon comes in,
is absorbed by the scatterer,
and re-emitted.
What is, in that case,
what corresponds to the strength of the scatterer?
The answer is the electric charge of the charge.
The bigger the electric charge,
the more probable it is
that the electron,
that the photon will get scattered.
There is a measure of the strength of the interaction
between scatterer and scattered particle,
the strength of the coupling between them,
which has to be codified somehow.
And it is simply by a numerical number put here.
It's called the coupling constant, G.
G for what?
I don't know what G is for.
It's a measure of the strength of the coupling
or the strength of the interaction
between the scatterer
and, between the scatterer or the target
and the particle itself.
I'll give you an example.
Some examples.
The scattering of a meson
from a proton
is a strong process,
meaning to say that
if the meson is absorbed,
if the meson arrives at the location of the proton,
it has a high probability of scattering.
That's indicated by a large coupling constant.
A photon in the vicinity of a charge
also could be a proton.
A photon is also absorbed and re-emitted by a proton.
The probability for that scattering,
the probability that the photon gets redirected,
is much smaller than the probability for the meson.
And that's indicated by the coupling constant
being much smaller for the interaction
of a charged particle with a...
You think of something even smaller?
Neutrino.
Yeah, a neutrino interacting with a proton
has an even smaller constant for scattering off this.
That's what made...
Would that be valid also for an electron?
For the target being an electron or the...
Well, right now we're just making a model,
in fact, a model,
in fact, of an electron
or something like an electron scattering off a target.
So don't think of this as
being valid for any real thing.
This is a simplified model
for a number of different situations.
What about the scattering of a graviton by a nucleus?
Graviton is the analog for gravity of a photon.
Well, it can happen,
but it's an extremely small constant.
I won't even try to tell you
how a 10 to the minus 10
is some large number by comparison.
All right.
So the strength of the interaction
and the probability that this actually happens,
that the particle gets redirected,
is indicated or described
by the coefficient g, which appears here.
It's just a number,
and it's called the coupling constant.
It's called a coupling constant.
There are many coupling constants.
All right, so let's see if we can calculate this.
What are we trying to calculate?
We're trying to calculate the probability
for going from k initial to k final.
That's all.
Yeah.
Question?
Is there any logic for g being a constant
as opposed to being a function of omega or k?
That's a good question.
The answer is there is no logic to it.
No, there is logic to it,
but there are situations where it's a function of omega.
All right.
I'll show you some situations.
As I said, this is a model
of a particular kind of simple scattering.
There are more complicated kinds of scattering.
A more complicated kind would be,
and this would really be
for the case of a photon
and an atom, for example.
Photon comes in,
atom gets excited,
bzzzzzz,
and then de-excites by emitting the photon.
Okay?
Here's a little gap,
a time gap between the time the photon is absorbed
and the time it's emitted.
This happens to be equivalent
to saying that the coupling constant is omega-dependent.
Okay?
So, as I said,
we're talking about a simple model
and just trying to find what the consequences are.
There's going to be one important consequence.
And it is very general.
The rest is not so general.
But the one important consequence
that I want to get to.
So, let's just plug away.
We're going to just go straight ahead,
plugging in for psi
its value written in terms
of creation and annihilation operators,
and then use those creation and annihilation operators
to annihilate the initial particle
and recreate the final particle
and calculate the expression that's up there.
The square of it will be the probability.
So, let's do it.
Okay.
So, yeah.
Question.
If g was 1, would that probability must be 1?
If g is equal to 1,
yeah, all right.
That's a good question.
You could ask what happens
if g is much bigger than 1.
Does that mean that the
probability is much bigger than 1?
No, it doesn't.
It doesn't.
It just means that you have to go ahead
into a more complicated calculation.
This calculation that I'm doing is only correct
for very small g.
Okay.
It's correct for very small g.
What you have to do when g is larger
is extremely interesting
and will be very important to us in what follows.
The answer is you have
to do higher order perturbation theory.
Okay, but we're not doing that now.
Well, we're just doing the simplest thing.
All right.
So, let's do the simplest thing
and just plug in for psi its value.
All right.
Psi, the first psi, not the psi dagger,
but the first psi is a summation over k,
not k initial, but just k, a summation index,
A minus to absorb the initial particle of k,
e to the i kx,
e to the minus i omega sub kt,
and that acts on the initial state
which happens to have one particle of momentum ki.
Yeah?
Since the x is zero.
Thank you.
X is zero at the scatterer.
So, let's leave it out.
E to the i k0 is just one.
Okay?
Which terms in this sum will contribute?
k i.
Only when k is equal to
k i will we get anything.
Right?
Why?
Because the annihilation operators give zero
when they act on states where there are no particles.
The only particle around has momentum k i,
and so only when k is equal
to k i do we get anything.
But nevertheless, let's leave it in this form
just for the moment.
Now, what about the other operator, psi dagger?
That's also a sum over momentum.
I better use a different index
because I don't want to
use the same summation index twice
and get confused.
So, I'll call it, let's call it L.
And now we put a plus of L,
that creates the new particle with momentum L,
times e to the, well,
x is still equal to zero.
x is still equal to zero,
so we don't get anything from here.
But then we have e to
the i omega sub L times t.
What about the final state?
The final state is the state
with a particle of momentum k final.
Okay, which term, all right, first of all,
the term in the sum over k which contributes
is only when k equals k i, right?
What about the sum here over L?
What does L have to equal?
k final.
Remember that when a plus acts to the left,
it's a positive.
So, what about the final state?
When a plus acts to the left, it annihilates.
It has to find a particle to annihilate.
A plus of L only gives you something
when L is equal to k final.
So, really both of these sums collapse.
Only k equals k initial and L equals k final.
That's all there is.
What did I leave out?
G.
But I've also left out something else.
What is it?
Integral dt.
It's the integral dt,
which is the thing that I'm really interested in.
All right, so the only contributor here
is k equals k i.
What does a minus of k i do
when it acts on a state with momentum k i?
It just creates a state with no particles, right?
It annihilates the particle with momentum k i.
What about this sum?
This sum is only non-zero
when L is equal to k final.
So, we can put k final here.
And when this acts on a state with k final...
Oh, sorry.
Yeah, okay, right.
We're okay.
This is good.
All right.
What happens when A acts
on a state with k initial?
It just gives a state with no particles, right?
So, that's just no particles.
What happens when this acts on a state with
particle with momentum k final?
It just gives no particles again.
What is this number?
One.
So, that much is one.
So, all this operator nonsense
of creating and annihilating particles
all goes away,
and all we have is a number g.
That's the probability for the scattering,
or that's the amplitude for the scattering, g.
Nothing else except the number g.
So, that's the probability for the scattering,
except that we have this integral.
Not in this expression.
I think you're thinking about a relativistic problem.
No, no, no.
There was only one particle here.
Because there was only one particle...
Yeah, yeah.
There was only one particle, right.
Okay, but the important thing,
the only thing that really I'm illustrating here
is the integral over time.
And what is it?
It's an integral dt,
e to the i,
omega, let's just call it final,
minus omega initial,
this is k initial,
times t.
That's the whole upshot.
The time integration gives us an integral
over e to the i,
omega final, minus omega initial, t.
All of the operator nonsense just gives us a one.
Nothing very interesting.
The coupling constant gives us a g.
And now we have to evaluate this integral.
What is this integral?
Delta function.
This is an example of the delta function.
An integral dt of e
to the i something times t.
Let's see, was it 2 pi times the delta function,
if I remember?
Yeah.
I think it was 2 pi g
times delta of omega final minus omega initial.
Does this ring a bell?
Delta of omega final minus omega initial.
It's only non-zero
when omega final is equal to omega initial.
Omega final is equal to omega initial.
Omega initial is the final energy.
Omega initial is the initial energy.
So somehow, magically,
now notice that if we had not integrated over time,
we would not have gotten this delta function of energy.
So somehow there's a connection between the fact that
there's a conservation of energy
and the fact that it doesn't,
there's no preference for any specified time.
We could have made a model
in which the scattering only happens
if the time is within some boundaries.
Then this integral would have only gone over
some limited amount of time.
It would not have made a delta function.
So the ingredient here,
which is closely connected with energy conservation,
is time translation symmetry.
That every time is like every other time.
Yeah?
That whole thing is squared.
Does that matter?
It's amplitude.
Oh, oh, the square of the delta function.
Well...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The probability,
for the probability we have to square this.
This is the probability amplitude.
The probability itself will have the square of this,
but who cares about the square of a delta function?
The delta square of a delta function is also zero
if omega final is not equal to zero.
We have to worry about squares of delta functions,
but in any case,
this will be zero unless the initial energy
is the same as the final energy.
Let's assume the initial energy
Then this is the operative important part
of the scattering amplitude.
Let's call this by its name.
It's a scattering amplitude,
and the probability for the scattering
is proportional to 4 pi squared G squared.
Okay.
All right, the strength of the scatterer
or the probability for it to scatter
contains G squared. They always wind
up containing pi's, but the important thing
is the G squared. And which
final momenta can happen? Well, I
didn't specify anything special about
the final momentum here. This final
momentum could have been anything as long
as the energy was the same. So this
scatterer has the property that it
takes a particle and with a probability
proportional to G squared, changes its
momentum with equal probability to any
momentum with the same energy. That's it.
So this is a scatterer which can scatter
into any direction with equal probability.
Okay, any direction with equal probability. That
of course is not true of all scatterers.
This is this very simple model that scatters
with all with equal probability in all directions
and the coefficient G squared, 4 pi squared
G squared in this case, is the probability.
So this is, I've shown you many
things so far tonight. In particular, the definition
of a coupling constant.
The fact that the integration over time
is the thing which ensures energy conservation,
which is just another way of saying the
problem has time translation symmetry. There was nothing
special picked out about one time or another
time. And I've illustrated the idea of a scattering
amplitude or the amplitude, the thing which
becomes squared in order to calculate a probability.
This is a fairly generic set
of ideas, but the details can differ.
Can you always simplify these things by
redefining the position so x is zero?
Say it again, louder.
Can you always simplify this by
redefining the position so x is zero?
No.
Good question. Yes, yes, in this particular
case, yes. The question of what would happen
had you not put x equals zero here,
right? That's kind of the question. Okay, what you
would have found is there would have been
another factor. The other factor in here would
have been in the amplitude, e to
the i, k initial minus k final.
Okay.
Times the position of the scatterer. What
shall I call the position of the scatterer?
Just, let's just call it x of the scatterer, x
of the target. x of the target is a number.
x of the target is just the position of
the target. When the position of the target was
zero, this didn't occur. If the target was
moved over to position x target, then the
you would get an extra factor.
But what would happen to the probability?
It's not changing.
No change because the, when you square, meaning
to say when you multiply by the complex
conjugate, this goes away. Multiplying this by its
own complex conjugate, which is what I mean by
squaring, multiplying by its own complex conjugate, this
goes away. So this does not appear in the
probability.
Okay.
Get the same probability no matter where the target is.
But in an intermediate stage of calculation, in calculating
the amplitude, the position of the target would occur.
Okay. Yeah.
So it's a very simple model so
you could cram two years into an hour.
Yeah.
But the mathematics, unless I see it wrong, seems to
say if we said that it didn't matter where it happened,
but it happened exactly at time zero,
we'd get a different kind of probability.
We'd get a different conservation.
Yes.
Who would you guess the conservation would be?
Well, it's momentum and...
Momentum and no energy conservation.
Right.
And does that have a physical interpretation or
is this more a property than just a mathematical?
Well, of course, in the real world, if
we're studying, for example, the interaction of two particles
and we take everything into account, both particles and so
forth, the scattering can occur at any time at any place.
Right.
But you could imagine.
You can certainly imagine.
You can certainly imagine an
approximate situation where you might...
Okay, you're asking me is there ever a situation where...
Here the approximation was we just
ignored the recoil of the target.
Okay.
And therefore the momentum was not conserved.
Is there ever a situation where energy is not conserved?
And that sort of situation is what happens
when you have time dependence in the coupling,
or time dependence in the strength of interaction.
Now, yes, there certainly are situations where that can be a good approximation
to say something makes a sudden change in the system from the outside.
And when a sudden change in the
system happens, that's when the scattering takes place.
Yes, we can think of situations where that happens.
I can.
We can try to concoct one.
I can't right now.
I'm a little too fuzzy.
But, yes, we can certainly
concoct a situation where something suddenly...
Okay.
...sudden happens in such a way that it
makes the scattering possible at an instant of time.
And then energy would be completely not conserved.
Right.
Do most of the coupling
constants come from experimental data?
Yes.
Also, you just said introducing a time
dependence in the coupling constants, which started...
Well, that usually means when there's
a time dependence in the coupling constant,
that usually means there's something that you've ignored in
the system, which is either moving or time dependent,
something whose dynamics and degrees of freedom you're sort of ignoring in the
same way that you ignored the possible recoil or repositioning of the target here.
So I'll try to think of a situation
where there's an interesting violation of energy conservation,
or where the bookkeeping was such that
you threw some of the energy away.
But let's come back to it.
Yeah.
Hitting a moving target.
Right.
Hitting a moving target is an example.
Where the target...where, again, the motion of
the target is thought of as completely fixed.
Yes.
Right.
And I...
On certain scales, you have to worry
about the size of the target versus the...
Yes.
The frequency of the...the size of the wave.
Yeah.
So electron versus x-ray versus gamma versus...
Here, in this model, the target...the
size of the target was zero.
Yeah.
In this, right.
And you're absolutely right.
Something interesting happens when the target has a
certain finite size, and we can discuss that.
But let me just come back
to the question about the moving target.
If you think about it for a minute, of course,
if you have a moving target, you can't just say,
Well, I'm going to move this.
Of course, if you have a
moving target, energy is not conserved.
For example, supposing that wall was moving toward me, and I had a tennis ball,
and all of a sudden, the wall hits the ball, and the ball moves off.
The energy of the tennis ball...we're not
accounting for the energy of the moving wall.
We're not trying to worry about that.
So if the wall is moving, that corresponds to a time dependence, in this case, a
time dependence not of the coupling constant, but a time dependence of the location of the scatterer.
That would be enough to make energy not conserved.
And we could see it in the mathematical formalism.
Okay, so to reiterate, these creation and annihilation operators are the tools which
allow you to discuss transitions of particles from one state to another state.
We have not talked about...
Well, actually, we did talk about creation and annihilation.
Yeah.
Let's discuss another situation.
Oh, incidentally, supposing psi was
the field operator for an electron.
Each kind of particle has its own separate field.
Okay?
So electrons have a different field than photons.
When you put psi here, you
better specify what particle you're talking about.
Okay?
Let's think of the electron.
Psi describes electrons now.
Here was a process in which an
electron came in and an electron went out.
What happened to the total charge?
Did the total charge change?
No.
One particle came in.
One particle came out.
Now, let's imagine a different situation.
Let's imagine a situation where one electron
comes in and two electrons go out.
Okay, crazy.
I mean, it can't happen.
But let's for the moment, nevertheless, try to imagine it.
How might we describe it
by the same kind of mathematics?
One electron comes in, two electrons go out.
How do I modify this?
And here, my simple model is two
electrons go out from exactly the same point.
And exactly the same point.
We have a creation.
Yeah.
We might put another, we might square this.
In other words, psi of zero t, psi dagger of
zero t, psi dagger of zero t, psi of zero t.
Oops.
There should be a t here, right?
Yeah.
Okay.
What about...
Now this is, this of course can't
happen in nature because electric charge is conserved.
This corresponds to the annihilation of
one electron and the creation of two.
Bad idea, but nevertheless, let's write it down.
What about two electrons in and
two electrons out? Is that okay?
Well at least it doesn't violate electric
charge conservation. How would we describe that?
Another psi.
Psi, psi, psi dagger, psi dagger.
هبط
two electrons in, three electrons out
psi, psi
psi dagger, psi dagger, psi dagger
okay which ones of these are allowed
and what's the rule
i'm not deriving a rule now,
we're just going to observe a rule
same number of creation and annihilation
same number of psi's as psi daggers
this is not allowed
this is allowed
the rule is, same number of psi's as psi daggers
is there another way to express that?
does the order matter?
does the order of the operators
it's not a question of the order of the operators
it's the number of psi's
versus the number of psi daggers
when the number of psi's, alright let's
when the number of psi's
is different than the number of psi daggers
versus
when the number of psi's is the
same as the number of psi daggers
how can you diagnose
these combinations
of course it's very easy just to count
the number of psi's and psi daggers of course
but let me give you a mathematical diagnostic
that really does have a deep meaning
let's imagine
a transformation, now psi dagger does
mean the complex conjugate of psi
it is the Hermitian conjugate
in the language of quantum mechanics
but the Hermitian conjugate is
the analog of a complex conjugate
let me imagine that
i take an expression like this
just a mathematical expression like this
like this and I transform psi by
multiplying it by a phase. A phase means
an e to the i times some number, let's
call it alpha, times psi. I just, I'm just
doing now, blindly playing a game. Wherever I
see psi, I multiply it by e to
the i alpha times psi. What happens
to psi dagger? If I multiply a complex
quantity by e to the i
alpha what happens to its complex conjugate?
E to the minus i alpha, psi dagger.
What happens to objects that have an equal
number of psi and psi dagger? They stay the same.
What happens to a number of psi and a dagger?
They stay the same.
happens to objects which don't have an equal
number of psi and psi dagger? They change.
So we could characterize the allowed processes
by the ones which are described by operators
which are invariant, unchanged, by the operation
of changing the phase of the operator.
Indeed. But for the moment,
let's give it a simpler name.
Invariance under changing, under redefining the
field so that you change its phase.
Overall, you change the phase by a constant phase factor.
If the description, if the interaction expression here
is invariant, then you change the phase.
If it's invariant, then charge is conserved.
If it is non-invariant, then charge is not conserved.
What happens, supposing I had psi plus psi dagger,
what kind of thing does that correspond to, incidentally?
All right, I'll leave that to you to think about.
But is this unchanged by phase?
No.
No, no.
Isn't that the real part?
This is the real part of psi.
And if you multiply by a phase,
you change the real part of psi.
So that's not a quantity which is invariant.
Question.
If you have a target and you
have an electron impinging on a target,
you may have many second of electron emitted.
Yes.
Well, if you have, what kind of target?
Any kind.
A target full of electrons?
Yeah.
Well, sure, you can have, yes, yes, yes.
You can have that.
Yeah, right.
You say, what happens if you have an
atom and you hit the atom with an electron
and 75 electrons go off?
Well, charge is not violated, of course.
What has happened is the atom has changed.
All right.
This is a situation in which you cannot
get away with ignoring the dynamics of the target.
In the particular, the important dynamics of the
target is the change of charge of the target.
You can't, in this case, treat the target
as though it was a completely passive thing.
You've got to remember.
All right.
The target changed itself.
What's that?
Yes.
That means the target itself has
to be described by a quantum field.
All right.
And we can discuss that.
I think we've gone far enough for tonight.
All right.
So what have we found?
We found that time translation invariance,
corresponds to energy conservation.
Phase invariance, we can call this phase invariance,
corresponds to charge conservation.
And we haven't worked it out yet.
We will work it out next time,
that spatial translation invariance
corresponds to momentum conservation.
I'll show you how that works next time.
But we're making our way slowly into
how particle physics processes are described by fields.
That's our goal for the next lecture.
I don't know, maybe half a lecture on it.
And then we'll move into some of the symmetries
and some of the more interesting laws of particle physics.
Just to work it out in the math, we
could have just as easily had a process that was
psi, psi dagger, psi, psi dagger, psi, psi dagger, right?
Yes.
Yes, but it's not hard to re-
OK, right.
That's great.
I've chosen always to put all the daggers
to the left and the psi's to the right.
And I think that's a good way to put it.
I think that's a good way to put it.
And then I'll put the daggers to the right.
Remind me next time and I'll show you how
to rearrange other expressions so that they become like this.
I know what you're asking.
You're asking what would happen if instead of
this we put psi, psi dagger, psi, psi dagger.
And I will tell you next time.
But they still match.
This is allowed.
Does it mean the same thing?
No, not quite.
Not quite.
Remind me next time.
I'm going to have to do
a lot of things going into it.
But remind me absolutely next time.
What is the difference between this and this?
And I'll show you next time.
All right.
I actually left time for some questions.
If you want to ask some questions.
I've just run out of steam.
I have a question.
Well, it's not that I.
Yeah, go ahead.
Have you ever heard of a thing that.
Excuse me.
That inherits from.
That he implies charge .
Well, it's sort of trivial.
If you have as many psi as the psi
dagger, that means the interaction eats the same number
of electrons as it spits out.
All right.
Each psi annihilates an electron.
Each psi dagger creates an electron.
You know, having proved that phase invariant implies charge.
Charge concentration will get away around the.
All I did was point out.
That all of the objects with equal numbers
of size and side daggers will be invariant
under the phase operation here.
If they have different numbers of size and side daggers.
Let's take a case.
Yes.
Psi, side dagger, side dagger.
I get that.
You get it, right?
I'm not sure what the rest of the question is.
If they have equal numbers of size and
side daggers, it's phase invariant and it conserves
charge.
If it has different numbers of size and
side daggers, it's not phase invariant and it doesn't
conserve charge.
So we're just observing that when
it's phase invariant, it conserves charge.
When it's not phase invariant, it doesn't.
There are two other rules
at the same time, conservation rules.
Energy, momentum, and charge for the moment.
We haven't.
We haven't gone through momentum conservation,
although it was mentioned by somebody here.
Ask me if the process can happen at any
place instead of any time, then yes, then it conserves
momentum.
But we'll come to it.
We'll do that case.
Those are, that's Emmy Nuthers.
Yeah.
In classical mechanics, it's Nuthers' theorem.
In quantum mechanics, it's even simpler.
But.
But here, I'm sort of short-circuiting all
of that discussion by just showing you how
it works mechanically in terms of these quantum fields.
Question.
Up there you have the probability of that
first system is four pi squared G squared.
Right.
Does that mean when you empirically.
Yeah.
When you do the sine of di into the
coupling process that it must be less than one over
two pi in that particular case?
It must be less than one over something
or you have, or your model is very incomplete.
If you ask me in what
way it's incomplete, I will tell you.
In what way it's incomplete is that the
real scattering process is not described by just
a particle coming in and getting scattered out.
It's described by something more complicated.
It's a sum of amplitudes in which the
particle comes in, scatters off the target, comes in,
goes back out, comes back in, scatters
off the target twice, comes back in, scatters
off the target three times.
It's a whole infinite series.
Each one, each term has a
factor of G in front of it.
It's only when G is small
that only the first term is important.
But we'll come to that.
This is a basic theme that when the coupling
constant is small, you can get away with the
simplest minimal process.
When the coupling constant gets large, one has
to, well, let's just call it what it is.
One has to sum up
an infinite number of Feynman graphs.
Basically these pictures that I've drawn are
Feynman graphs and the vertices of the Feynman
graphs are described by these objects.
Okay.
The vertices of the Feynman diagrams tell
you the basic elements that can happen.
Particle comes in, bounces back out.
That's psi times psi dagger.
Two particles come in and bounce back out.
That's psi dagger, psi dagger, psi, psi, or whatever.
And we'll give things their proper name next time.
Yeah.
Are there any situations when the particle is small?
Are there any situations when
the coupling constant has imaginary components?
Well, yes.
What are they?
You want me to, the existence
of a theta parameter in QCD.
The existence of a theta parameter in QCD.
I'm sure that means nothing to you.
Yeah.
But it does happen that there
are complex values of coupling constants.
It usually means that time
reversal invariance has been broken.
Complex coupling constants are usually an
indication of a violation of time reversal
invariance.
That's really what it comes down to.
Now you can't see that from
what I've told you up till now.
At least if you can, you're smarter than I am.
I can see it, but only
because I know how to see it.
But it's not a problem.
It's not obvious.
But that is the case.
Complex coupling constants mean that
time reversal invariance is broken.
In other words, things don't look, if you
run the process backward as a movie going
backward, it's not a possible process.
Yes.
You said at one point also that
instead of having the scattering occur, the scattering
occurred, the outgoing particle at the same
time as the incoming particle would be before
or after.
You also mentioned before.
It's not happening.
Not now.
Yeah, no, no.
I did say that, and I sort
of regretted it the minute I said it.
But we will, we will.
Hmm?
No, this is, it's a fair question,
but it's not the time for it now.
Yeah.
Jean Franklin used to say
it lasts before you tickle it.
What's that?
Jean Franklin.
Jean Franklin would say it lasts before you tickle it.
Okay.
Yeah.
I'm probably going to say you'll get to this
at some point, but how do you turn this into
something that's relativistic?
Ah.
Again, you're jumping way ahead.
I'm trying to go slowly, and
everybody's pushing me to get ahead.
Okay.
You really want to know?
You add this and this and put a
square root of omega k in the denominator.
Okay.
Yeah.
No, no.
We're jumping ahead.
I mean.
Yeah.
Hey, you talked about charge conjugation.
Conservation.
With a phase factor.
Yeah.
But the rest mass, m, that doesn't change also.
Right.
Yeah.
change also in a non-relativistic process,
but in a relativistic process it can.
And there's nothing in basic quantum mechanics
which says that rest mass can't change.
It's a combination of quantum mechanics, or
not even quantum mechanics, even just classical
mechanics, together with an invariance principle,
and the invariance principle is Galilean invariance,
which is a non-relativistic analog of Lorentz invariance.
But yeah, it is true, in a
non-relativistic situation, total mass can't change, but it
can in relativistic scattering.
So what did you want to ask me, exactly?
Well, it's just that logically we think of
rest mass conservation in the same terms as
charge.
No, no, no, no, no, no, not at all.
Not at all.
One is absolutely true in nature, the other
is only true for very, very slow velocities.
Right?
There's nothing sacred in physics about conservation of
rest mass, and what's more, it's not true.
An electron and a positron annihilate into two photons.
There's no conservation of mass, there
is a conservation of electric charge.
So one of them is a sort of accidental.
non-relativistic fact.
The other is a deep underlying symmetry of
nature, which happens in simple case just to
correspond to this phase invariance.
Next time we'll talk about fermions, we'll talk
about what happens if you have more than
one species of particles, supposing you have
electrons and muons and quarks and so forth,
how do you describe all of this?
What's allowed, what's not allowed, what kind of processes?
And all in the language of quantum .
Yeah.
Strictly speaking, with your scatterer example you
gave us, you said it was an electron,
but I thought we only knew about bosons so far.
Ah, good point.
Good point.
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
Yeah.
This, so we have, we're talking
about a bosonic version of an electron.
Yeah.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.