Stanford University
Last time I started to tell you something about how quantum field theory gives
rise to a theory of the particle interactions through an object called the Lagrangian.
I think that was not terribly clear, so I want to go back
to it a little bit before starting to discuss the details of particle physics.
We're still thinking about quantum field theory.
The basic technique that I was alluding to last
time is called the path integral method of quantum mechanics.
And it is the...
most direct route to Feynman diagrams, to the theory
of particle interactions that are based on Feynman diagrams.
So, let me just try to briefly go through the basic ideas, which
we started to do last time, but I don't think I was sufficiently clear.
Anyway, the path integral formalism or
method in quantum mechanics due to Feynman,
is a generalization, is the quantum mechanical
version of the principle of least action.
So I just want to remind you
what the principle of least action is.
If we're talking about a particle, now I don't mean a
particle from the particle physics quantum field theory point of view,
just a classical Newtonian particle, the motion of a classical Newtonian
particle from one point of space-time to another, just very quickly,
is determined by a Lagrangian.
Okay.
Lagrangian is a function of the coordinates of
the particle, the time derivatives of the particle,
and from the Lagrangian, whatever the
Lagrangian is, one constructs the action.
And the action is an integral along
the trajectory of the particle of the Lagrangian.
For every trajectory, whether it's the true trajectory
or not the true trajectory from here to here,
by the true trajectory, I mean,
the solution of Newton's equations,
from one space-time point to another space-time point,
whether or not the trajectory is a solution,
it has an action, the integral
of the Lagrangian along the orbit.
The classical principle of least action is that the
trajectory followed by the particle through space-time minimizes the action.
Right.
From that, you can derive differential equations,
and those differential equations
are called Newton's equations,
and I will assume that you know
a little bit about this idea of action.
Now, the same idea applies to classical field theory.
And the way the idea works is
for a particle, for an ordinary particle motion,
the Lagrangian is a function along an orbit,
a function of an orbit.
For a field theory,
and of course it's an orbit which
connects some initial configuration to a final configuration,
for a field theory,
the equations of motion of a
field theory, classical equations of motion,
are also determined from a Lagrangian.
The Lagrangian is a function of whatever fields,
I'll call them generically just phi,
and not just the time derivatives of the fields,
but the space derivatives and the time derivatives.
Let's say derivative of phi with respect to x mu.
That's just a shorthand way of saying that
the Lagrangian depends on phi and derivatives of phi.
One thing which is required by the theory
of relativity is that the Lagrangian be a scalar.
That a transform under Lorentz transformations is a scalar.
But that being said,
the Lagrangian can be anything built
out of phi's and derivatives of phi.
What is the action?
Imagine we have a region of space-time,
time as usual flows upward,
space is horizontal,
and we have a region of space-time
between an initial time and a final time.
Then the action is the Lagrangian.
Then the action in this region,
the action is the action in this region,
just as the action for a particle trajectory is the
action from one end point of the trajectory to another,
here is the action in a region of
space between an initial configuration and a final configuration,
and the action is equal
to the integral over that region,
let's write it d4x, which means the
time and dx and dy and dz,
of this Lagrangian.
So it's the total integrated value
of the Lagrangian over space and time,
whereas for the particle it's just an integral over time.
Now what do you do?
What's the analog of a starting point for the particle?
A value of the field on the initial surface here.
Given not just one field, but
all the fields in the problem,
prescribing the values of the
field on the initial surface here,
and prescribing the values of the
and the values of the fields on the final surface,
you can ask, is there
a solution of the equations of,
oh, let me go back a step, forget that.
Yes, is there a solution of
whatever the equations of the theory are,
which starts with a given initial value of
the fields at time t equals zero, let's say,
and ends with the fields being
something different at some later time?
And the answer is the principle of least action again.
The equations of the theory are formulated by saying,
yes, there always does exist something in between,
which is a correct solution of the theory,
which has a given initial value of the fields here,
and a given value of the fields at the endpoint,
and the correct solution of the fields in
here is the one which minimizes this action.
The one which minimizes the action.
So the principle of least action gets extended,
to a kind of space-time principle of least action,
where the degrees of freedom in here are fields.
Okay, now let me very quickly remind you
what the quantum mechanical use of action is.
How exactly you derive the
classical principle of least action
from the quantum mechanical version
of Feynman's quantum mechanical version,
we don't really need to get into here,
you can go look it up,
and anything about Peltz,
anything about path integrals,
but for a particle,
let's come back to the particle motion for a moment.
According to Feynman,
or according to quantum mechanics,
a thing that you might
want to calculate is the amplitude.
Is there anything wrong with the
value of a field returning to itself?
No. No. No.
No more than the possibility
of the position of this thing.
So how do you go from
one space-time event to another space-time event?
Why space-time events?
We're having values of fields
here and values of fields here.
Well, integrating d4x,
so there has to be some d4 trajectory.
No, the trajectory is replaced by a history.
A history of the field
from the beginning to the end.
A history means the values
of the fields all along here.
Everywhere is in here.
Okay?
The idea of a trajectory
becomes a trajectory in field space,
which means...
We have to specify actually the
coordinates as well as the field values
to get an initial point.
To get an initial point?
Well, you're specifying the
initial boundary condition or whatever
as 4.
As field values.
Field values all along some initial surface.
You pick the initial surface.
In other words, you pick time...
It's the whole field at some cross-sectional...
It's the whole field along some cross-sectional...
Yeah.
All right?
Which is another way of saying the
whole field at a given instant of time.
And the final configuration is
the whole field at some later...
Time.
And the question is, is there a
solution of the theory, whatever the theory is,
which interpolates in between these in the same
way that a trajectory interpolates from here to here?
And the rule is, minimize the action.
That, if carried out...
We did this a number of classes ago.
But if that's carried out,
the requirement of minimizing the action...
The requirement of minimizing the action leads
to partial differential equations for the fields,
and those partial differential equations
are things like Maxwell's equations,
things like Einstein's equations, and so forth.
All right, so...
All right, let's come back
now to the quantum mechanical idea.
The quantum mechanical idea has to do with amplitudes.
Amplitudes are things out
of which you construct probabilities.
So, for example,
you can ask the question,
what is the amplitude that if
a particle is injected into the world,
however it's injected in,
at a space-time point x and t,
what is the amplitude that if I
look for it at a later time,
let's say this is at x and time t,
what's the amplitude that if
I look at a later time,
let's call it t prime,
that I will find it at
position x prime and t prime?
So it's the amplitude that if
I start a particle at this point,
close my eyes for a while,
and then turn on a detector,
which looks for the particle at a certain place,
the amplitude for finding it there.
That amplitude is a complex number
that depends on the initial point, on the final point.
It's a complex number whose
magnitude squared is the probability.
All right, that's the rule.
Square the amplitude,
or multiply it by its complex conjugate,
and that is the probability for the
particle to go from here to here.
Feynman's rule is the following.
It says take the action for any trajectory.
Take an arbitrary trajectory
and write down the expression
e to the i minus i,
the action of,
the trajectory.
We can just write it out.
It's integral of,
now we're talking about particles now,
integral of the Lagrangian dt
from one point to another point.
It's a function of, or functional of the trajectory.
And now, actually there's a
factor of h bar in here,
a factor of h bar in here.
That's where quantum mechanics comes into it.
So, sum this, or integrate it,
over all possible trajectories.
Well, in non-relativistic quantum mechanics,
you don't let them go backward in time.
But all possible trajectories,
which never loop back on themselves in time,
sum that over all the possible trajectories.
For each trajectory, it's a complex number.
Add them all up.
Now, how do you add up such a thing
in some complicated kind of integral?
But we needn't worry too much about the details
of how you actually calculate it.
That, according to Feynman,
is the amplitude for going from here to here.
It's the sum of all possible classical roots.
Classical root does not mean a solution of the equations.
It just means a possible root.
It's the sum of all possible roots,
whether or not they're solutions of the equations,
of Newton's equations,
of e to the minus i times the action,
measured in Planck's constant units.
Incidentally, Planck's constant has units of action.
So this is simply the action
in units of the Planck's constant.
The e arises because the...
because to go a little step involves the...
something very...
You have to multiply these.
Yes.
Both together.
Right. Exactly.
That's exactly right.
And the other thing here is the i.
The i is part of quantum mechanics.
What can I say?
Yeah.
That sum is the probability?
That sum is the thing whose square is the probability.
By square, I mean times its complex conjugate.
This sum could hardly be a probability
because in general it's complex.
It's got an i in it.
If you multiply it,
you get the sum of all possible roots.
If you multiply it by its complex conjugate,
that is the probability.
This is the probability amplitude.
The complex thing...
So this is Feynman's formulation of quantum mechanics.
And now it can be extended to quantum field theory.
In quantum field theory, the corresponding question...
Now we're not actually going
to formulate it this way because...
But this is a correct way to formulate it.
We're going to fudge it a little bit
and make our way through it without any rigor.
But the same idea.
You start with an arbitrary configuration of the field.
All right?
So that's some initial phi of x.
x now being just x and not t.
An initial configuration of the field.
And now you look at
some final configuration of the field.
Let's call it phi prime of x.
These are two different functions.
And you can see that the first
one is a function of the field.
And the second one is a function of the field.
And you can ask, what is the probability amplitude
that if I start the field at some value
and let the system go
and then detect the field at a later time...
Imagine you had some way of starting an initial condition
with a field being prescribed at every point of space.
Of course, that's an idealization.
You don't have a chance in
the world of doing that, really.
But you had some sort of apparatus
which allowed you to start
the field in an arbitrary configuration,
let it go,
and then you had another apparatus
which detects the values of the field at every point.
Then you can ask, what is the probability
that if you start the field in a given way
that at a later time
the field will have some value?
Again, that probability is determined
in terms of a probability amplitude.
And the probability amplitude
is...
Again, the sum over
all possible ways of interpolating
the field between initial and final,
all possible...
Exactly what I said.
All possible ways of filling in
between the initial state and the final state
with a field value at every point
of e to the minus i a,
and then you have the field action.
That's the integral d x, d
t, d x, d y, d z,
d 4 x,
of the Lagrangian,
which is a function of phi
and the derivatives of phi.
So you evaluate the Lagrangian at every point,
integrate it up.
That gives you the action for a particular...
Let's call it a trajectory.
It's not really a trajectory in any ordinary sense.
But it's a history.
Let's call it a history, better yet.
For each history,
each possible history that you can imagine,
it doesn't have to be a true history,
a real history,
for every possible history you can imagine,
there is an action.
The action is itself an integral.
But then you can sum this over all possible histories,
and that is the amplitude
to start with a field value phi
and end with a field value phi prime
between these two trajectories here.
Okay?
That's the notion of a path integral.
Yeah?
I'm not concerned that they're infinite number paths,
but the action is going to be a finite number
for each of these paths.
Well, it's a finite complex number, right.
Yeah, so how can that converge to anything?
Why is that not an infinite number?
Um...
No, there are many, many integrals.
Well, okay, you're asking...
All right, let me phrase it a little more strongly.
Adding up an infinite number of numbers,
well, that's nothing special.
I think what you're pointing out is that
each one of these numbers is not only finite,
but has a magnitude equal to one.
Or something that is not decreasing.
It has a magnitude equal to one.
All right?
It's an exponential of i times something, right?
So any number like this is
a number which on the complex plane...
You're not minimizing this sum?
Not minimizing it.
You're summing over all trajectories.
You're just summing over all of these amplitude, okay.
No.
These things do converge.
They don't...
They converge because they oscillate.
They all lie on the unit circle.
Not on the infinite circle.
On the unit circle.
And yet the integrals do converge.
That's the definition of the delta function.
For example, that's one example,
but there are many examples
where integrals like this converge.
The kind of thing that can't converge...
Well, if you have an infinite number of numbers
all of which are positive,
and you add them up,
positive and bounded away from zero,
all right, you have an infinite number of numbers,
all of them positive and bounded away from zero,
of course that's going to diverge.
Okay?
In this case, you have numbers which can cancel.
Over here is one trajectory.
Over here is another trajectory.
These are the amplitudes for different trajectories.
And this one
cancels this one.
So it's not hard for an integral...
Well, you could say if they're equally distributed
around the unit circle, then you get...
Zero.
Yeah.
In fact, most of them,
except for a small fraction of them, they are...
That's right.
They tend to cancel a lot.
The only trajectories which tend not to cancel
are the ones near the classical trajectory.
We don't have to discuss that now,
but that is the way
that you go from quantum mechanics
to classical theory,
at least in this formulation.
If you look for the particular trajectories
where you have the least cancellation,
those are the trajectories of stationary action.
The trajectories where the action is minimum.
But that's another story.
This is the quantum mechanical
path integral formulation
that much of modern science,
modern field theory,
basically all of modern field theory,
quantum field theory is based on.
All right, now I'm not
going to derive the next step.
I'm simply going to state the next step.
But I wanted to at least explain to you
what this quantity is
before I show you how in practice it's used.
Now when I say in practice,
this is a bit of an oversimplification,
but not too bad, not too bad.
The last time we talked a little bit
about how the Lagrangian is used
to calculate processes,
particles moving from one place to another,
particles interacting.
When I say calculate processes,
what did I really mean?
I really meant calculate the probability
for an initial state to go to a final state.
But there are two distinct ways
to think about relativism,
well, about quantum field theory.
One is in terms of fields
and the other is in terms of particles.
We know that there is this duality
between particles and fields.
We could ask a totally different,
apparently totally different question.
Instead of asking,
suppose you had a given field value here
and you want to know what the amplitude is
for a final field value,
we could ask,
supposing you had some incoming particles,
quanta of the field.
You express things in terms of field quanta
rather than in terms of
classical field configurations.
Supposing I told you that the field initially
was in a state which was described
by a particular collection of incoming particles.
Incidentally, when I say the field,
I may mean a collection of fields.
All right?
So I tell you not the
value of the field along here,
but rather the particle content coming in.
And I tell you what
the particle content is going out.
And I ask you, what's the probability
that you went from one particle content
to another particle content?
It's a question of,
a similar kind of question,
but expressed in terms of the particle representation
of quantum field theory,
rather than the classical field configuration.
And the answer, not surprisingly,
involves exactly this same object.
Okay?
We talked about it a little bit.
I think what I told you last time,
not incorrect, but it was
a little small piece of it.
I said what you do is you took one,
I'll just remind you of something I said,
and then I'm going to say it again,
but in a more correct way.
You take one plus the Lagrangian,
remember what we did.
We said let's divide up in space-time
into lots of little cells.
It's hard to give meaning to objects like this,
like this path integral directly.
The way to give meaning to it
is to divide up space into lots of little cells,
and instead of thinking about continuous functions
or even discontinuous functions,
think about a value of the field
in each one of these cells.
All right.
That makes it more concrete.
And then in the end,
you let the size of the cells go to zero.
So let's not let the size
of the cells go to zero.
Let's keep them finite like this.
What I told you is that you take the quantity
one plus the Lagrangian in each cell,
in the ith cell, called L sub i.
That's the value of the Lagrangian in each cell,
and you multiply it for all the cells.
Remember I said that?
If you don't, it doesn't matter
because we're going to say it again
the right way this time.
All right.
And then we did something with this
to try to calculate,
and I tried to show you
that there are pieces in here
which describe the propagation of particles,
the collisions of particles.
We're going to go back over it again
because it really is central.
All right.
First of all, I missed being tired.
I was not terribly clear.
It's really one minus i
times the Lagrangian in each cell.
Okay?
Now one minus i,
one plus a small,
this is, for the moment, imagine,
this is a small quantity.
I shouldn't, actually it's not one
plus the Lagrangian.
It's one plus the action in each cell.
Now the action in each cell
is the Lagrangian times the
space time volume in each cell.
All right.
Space time volume is delta x, delta y, delta z
times delta t for each cell.
Let's call that a small number.
Let's just call it the space time volume.
Let's call it a to the fourth,
where a is a small number.
All right.
So each little cell is small,
so the action in each cell is itself small,
because the cell is small.
Now one minus or one plus a small quantity,
let's call it one plus epsilon,
is an approximation to e to the epsilon.
e to the epsilon is,
this is approximately equal for small epsilon.
But the exact formula is a power series in epsilon.
It's one plus epsilon plus epsilon squared over two
plus epsilon cubed over, what comes next?
Three factorial, which is six.
Three times two times one.
And so forth and so on.
So one plus epsilon is approximately for small things
equal to e to the epsilon.
But in fact, it's more efficient and correct
to really write something different
than what I wrote over here,
namely this thing.
Let's think about what this thing is.
ありがとうございました
In fact, don't you have
to put an h-bar in the...
I'll probably wind up setting h-bar
equal to one as usual, but, right.
Okay, what is this object?
Alright, um...
This exponential here,
what's in here,
we're going to imagine replacing
not by an integral, but by a sum.
The integral over space and time here,
just imagine that we've replaced it
by the sum...
And what is it a sum of?
It's the sum of the
action in every little cell, right?
Each, when I replace the
sum of the integral by a sum, up in here,
when I replace the integral by a sum up in here,
what I'm really doing is just adding up
the action in all these little cells.
Now, the thing about a
exponential
is that the exponential of a sum
is the product of exponentials.
e to the a plus b is e
to the a times e to the b.
So this can also be written
as another way, in another way,
you forget the summation here for a minute.
That's summing over paths.
Before we do that summing over histories,
what this object is,
it's an exponential of a sum,
so it's also the product
of e to the minus i over h-bar,
a in the first cell,
e to the minus i over h-bar,
action in the second cell, a is action,
a in the third cell,
and it's exactly this kind of product,
product over all the cells,
not of one minus i times the action,
but of e to the minus i times the action.
They're close to each other.
It actually wouldn't matter which we used,
but in practice, but...
Okay, so let's now...
consider...
Question?
Okay.
All right, so now having this form here,
let's go back to what...
Let's forget particles for a minute and think about fields
and re-express the path integral idea.
So here we have a region of spacetime
that's been chopped up into tiny little cells.
Okay?
So what's the idea of an initial condition?
Enough.
All right, what's the idea of an initial condition?
The idea of an initial condition is to
start on the first row of cells here
and give the value of the
fields at every point in there.
That's an initial condition.
That's the analog of an initial condition.
A final condition is to specify
the fields in the last row.
So the question then is, what is the probability amplitude
that if a field is specified in
a certain way on the first row
and the field is specified in the last row,
what's the probability to go from one to another?
Or the amplitude, the amplitude that
if you start it a certain way
and let the system run, you will
later find it in the final state,
and the final state now means the
field in each one of these cells here.
Answer?
You take...
e to the minus i times the
sum of the action in all the cells,
but we now realize that this is simply
the product of e to the minus i
of the action in each cell.
We multiply together the action in all of these cells...
For a given history.
For a given history, which means a
given value of the fields in each cell.
And...
We multiply them all together.
We compute the exponential of the action,
and then we sum it over all
ways of populating the cells with fields.
All possible histories means all
possible values of the fields
that could be in every cell,
with the exception of the
first row and the last row.
The first row and the last row
are fixed by the initial and final conditions.
All right?
In other words, by the...
Oh, by the initial and final conditions.
The initial and final conditions.
We don't look at the field in the interior.
We simply start the system and then detect it.
And the rule is sum over all
possible field configurations that could exist in between.
So that has reduced this idea to a discrete form
in which we see that what we have here
is this infinite product.
So this product over actions.
All right.
Now let's try to formulate some ideas about particles.
Instead of asking the question,
what if we start with a given field configuration,
what if we start with a given particle configuration
and end with a given particle configuration?
What is the amplitude to
go from one to the other?
So I'll tell you how you think about it.
We're not going to derive this.
We've talked about it a good deal.
We've talked about the idea as a good deal.
We've talked about the fact that fields
are made up of creation and annihilation operators.
And what we're multiplying together
here is functions of the fields.
Functions of the fields and therefore functions...
Yeah?
I read somewhere that someone thinks that
field quanta are not necessarily identified with particles.
You're right.
You would disagree with that?
Well, I'm not sure who and what was the context.
But you wrote field theory.
No, I'm not sure who said
it and what the context was.
Well, give me a little more to go on.
The question was somebody said something.
My grandmother probably said it.
The fields quanta in quantum
field theory are not necessarily identifiable
as a particle.
The only thing I can think of
is that he was talking about quarks.
And of course, in some sense, quarks are particles.
But in some other sense, they're never detectable as
particles because they can never escape from one another.
That's the only thing I can think of.
So quarks are the quanta of the quark
field, but they're never directly detected as separate quarks.
They're never well separated from other quarks.
That's the only thing I can think
of that he might be speaking about.
Well, I guess during unitary evolution,
it doesn't necessarily boil down to observables.
And so you may not have
particles that are identifiable at intermediate states.
I don't know what the...
If you accept the idea
of a quark as a particle,
then you're not going to be able to identify it.
It's true that there's not a one-to-one correspondence necessarily between
the fields in a theory and the particles in the theory.
That's an idea which is true as long
as the coupling constants in the theory are small.
Okay, so there is
not necessarily a one-to-one correspondence.
Yeah, I mean, it is true.
There are field theories that...
that for one reason or another,
you wouldn't describe their
quanta as conventional particles.
But, you know, at some level,
it's just the difference between words.
If you define particle to mean
quanta, then there's no difference between them.
They're indivisible.
They carry energy and so forth.
So for my money, I would call them particles.
But...
But, yeah.
Can you talk about some of the histories?
Is there some limitation on
what histories you can talk about?
Do they have to be
sort of continuous in some sense?
No.
No, in fact, they don't have to be continuous.
First of all, of course, the idea of continuity on
a discrete space like this doesn't quite mean very much.
The field in the neighboring cell is just
going to be a different value of the field.
The rule is...
The rule is divide the space into cells.
And in actual practice, this is
the way quantum field theory is defined.
You divide the theory into cells.
You sum over all possible ways of...
of populating the cells with values of the fields.
All possible ways.
No restriction to things which are approximately continuous.
And in fact, quantum
fields are not approximately continuous.
They jiggle a great deal.
And you sum over all
the possible values of the fields.
And that gives you your...
So, in principle, for each field and each derivative, you can
assign it all possible values from minus and from minus plus.
Well, you don't assign the
derivatives separately from the fields.
The derivatives, of course, are
related to differences of the fields.
And you can't assign the differences
of the fields in neighboring boxes.
So you populate with field values.
And then derivatives are replaced by...
Yeah.
And you can use...
There are different rules that you might adopt.
You might define the derivative here to be
the difference of the field here and here.
Right.
Yeah.
That's a minor detail.
But in any event,
you might take the real line up
and break it up into small intervals,
but you'd still have a sum over a countable
number of possible values of the field for each field.
And if there were two fields,
then you'd be doing that over...
Yep.
By the field here, I mean all of the fields.
Right.
So you would give a value to each
possible field in the theory at each initial step.
It's a really nasty-looking computation.
Absolutely.
These are complex functions.
They're analytic functions, so...
Well, they're analytic functions of...
But the relationships between the values of the field
have to conform to what you learn in complex variables.
No, no.
Complex variables is about the theory of analytic functions.
Analytic functions are extremely smooth.
They're the smoothest functions you can think of.
These functions do not have to be smooth.
They're complex-valued, but they're not analytic functions.
The field itself is analytic.
The field as functions of position?
Definitely not.
They're, on the average, highly discontinuous, but...
If I were to do the...
Hm?
If I were to do the computation on the...
If I were to do the computation on
the computer, how do I know, you know...
That it will converge and do all the right things?
Yeah, I mean, how many
different fields I have to consider...
How many different...
Different assignments I have to consider.
Okay.
So, of course, this by now is
a major industry called lattice gauge theory,
or lattice quantum field theory.
Lattice because it divides the world into a lattice.
And this has been studied to death,
how to do these integrals in practice.
By now, it is a very effective tool, but it
took, you know, some 30 years to develop the computing technology.
I was involved in it in the
very, very beginning, the very, very beginning.
I wasn't involved in the computer technology of it.
I was involved in it in the very beginning,
but setting up the rules for lattice gauge theory.
Okay?
So there was a history.
The first part of it was setting up the
rules for it, and that took about three weeks,
and then something like 30 years to
develop the technology to compute these things.
And you're right.
I mean, you know, how do you
know when you've sampled enough of the space?
Okay?
So there are...
And a lot of the wisdom
of it came from statistical research.
Okay?
And you know, you have statistical mechanics
where you do very much the same thing.
You calculate partition functions or
probability distributions for this checkerboard here,
not a quantum field theory.
It could be a real crystal lattice, and
you might be summing over configurations of whether
there is or isn't an electron at each site.
So a lot of the methodology came from...
The quantitative study of statistical mechanics systems.
We have the same question.
How do you know when you've sampled enough?
And this is not the subject of tonight's
lecture, so the answer is the experts know.
Or they think they know.
And they get good answers.
They get good answers which agree with experiments.
So it seems to work.
Okay.
So let's go back and remember that quantum
fields are a shorthand for creation and annihilation operators.
And if we're talking about, let's say, the product of
some fields in this box times the fields in this box,
that can represent the annihilation
of a particle in this box
and the creation of a particle in a neighboring box.
So we might just represent it by
a particle moving from one box to another.
What kind of things in the action here actually do
correspond to a particle moving from one box to another?
So let me tell you.
There are things in the action here which,
strictly speaking, are not associated with one box,
but with a pair of boxes.
Namely, the derivative terms.
The derivative terms, I was a little bit hasty here when
I said you multiply all these things together, one for each box,
as a little bit of a cheat because there are
terms in the Lagrangian which are associated with pairs of boxes.
So really you can think of it as summing
over the boxes and summing over neighboring pairs of boxes.
But that's a detail.
Which terms involve pairs of boxes?
The terms which involve pairs of boxes are the
ones that are associated with the annihilation of a particle.
The terms which involve pairs of boxes are things
like the derivative of phi with respect to t squared.
The derivative of phi on a lattice
becomes the difference of phi in neighboring boxes.
So in here, this derivative of phi with
respect to t might really be written as
phi at point t.
So phi at point x, well, phi at point t
and x minus phi at point neighboring time and x.
Do we actually have second derivatives?
No second derivatives. These are first derivatives.
I mean, would we?
Never.
Okay.
Never. Bad idea.
Does real damage.
Now, what about derivatives
with respect to spatial coordinates?
Same thing.
It corresponds to the...
to the difference of two neighboring points in space.
And then the instruction is to take
one half of the square of the derivative.
Well, one half of the square
of the derivative will have in it...
I just want to focus now on the terms
which multiply phi times phi at a neighboring point.
Let me just focus on those.
There's also terms in here which
multiply by phi by the same...
by the value of the same point.
But in particular, there are terms in
this Lagrangian which multiply phi at one point
times phi at a neighboring point.
Every time you lay down...
a term like this,
represents the motion of a particle from here to here.
You can think of it that way.
Okay, let's...
let's take...
let's concentrate on these terms.
Let's forget the interactions in the Lagrangian.
These are simply...
these are called the kinetic terms,
the quadratic terms in the Lagrangian.
They're things which are easy to deal with,
and they do correspond to motion of
the particle from one point to another.
Let's look at this.
And let's include only those.
Let's...
We don't even need to write it in this form.
Let's just write it as e to the minus
i times the sum over all pairs of boxes,
over all neighboring pairs of boxes.
I said over all boxes, but
it's clear that's not quite right.
We want to think of it
as sums over neighboring pairs of boxes,
of things like phi in one point,
or things like phi in one box,
times phi in a neighboring box.
So I'll use the notation x in x prime
to represent neighbors on the lattice.
That's what goes into the action.
Well that's what goes into the exponential of the action.
There are some coefficients in front of it, of course,
but that's of secondary importance.
And now we can expand out this exponential.
Let's see what's there. There's 1 minus i times
the sum of phi of x, phi of x prime
And then things like, let's see, what's the next term?
i times i is minus 1,
so it looks like it's minus
summation of phi of x, phi of x prime
squared
times another factor of the sum of
phi of x, phi of x prime
Or this could be phi of x
prime, x double prime, x triple prime
x double prime and x triple prime
are one pair of neighbors
This is another pair of neighbors, and I think I
left out a factor. There should be a two factorial downstairs
I'm simply expanding out the exponential here
And what's the next one? Well, it has three powers
of the sum, four powers of the sum and so forth
Okay, let's look at each term here
the first term has
something which involves a sum over the lattice of
An annihilation of a particle at one point
and a creation of a particle at another point
at a neighboring point
the next term
Oh
incidentally
The rule that I'm going to tell you again. I'm in the business
of telling you some rules now. I'm going to tell you some rules now
the amplitude of the
Particle is going to be the same as
the amplitude of the particle at one point
So if you're going to have an
operation to put a particle into the system
The rule is you've got to close
off. You must not have a dangling
endpoint a
dangling endpoint
Can only dangle like that if you've got an
operation to put a particle into the system a
dangling endpoint for example
We're going to have diagrams which have particles going
from one point to another if they end like this
They're illegal unless there's an
instruction to put a particle
In at this point and to
take a particle out at that point
So endpoints like this
We will simply rule out as things
unless they correspond to a
Specific instruction to put a particle in at this point
and take it out since we're only putting particles in
In the initial state and taking
them out in the final state
The only endpoints would be allowed
on the top and the bottom
Okay, so let's let's take a particular term here
Phi of x and Phi of x'
These are neighboring points on the lattice and they correspond
to a motion of a particle from one place to another
As a sum of terms that could be
a term for a particle from here to here
A term for a particle from here to here
But none of these will contribute
Unless of course there would be one situation
In which they would be in
a finite space and then I can't...
they would contribute, that would be, of course, if
this layered structure here was only two layers high,
and we put in a particle over here
and took one out at the neighboring point.
Then there would be a contribution to the amplitude
of that coming from this term in the product,
phi of x times phi of neighboring x.
That would contribute, and it would contribute
to the amplitude, basically the factor minus i.
It would tell you that the amplitude to go from
one point to another was simply minus i, this coefficient here.
Okay, but that's not very good if this...
How do we get from here to here?
Okay, from here to here.
How do we get a particle from here to here and calculate the amplitude
that if we put in a particle over here, that will detect it over here?
For that, we have to find in this sum of products here,
we have to have a term which will leave no dangling ends.
Okay, let's just take this term here.
This has a particle moving from x to x prime,
and then another particle moving from x to x prime.
So we have x double prime to x triple prime.
Are you saying the second term contributes only
when the initial and final state are adjacent?
This term here, yeah.
Yeah, that's right.
This notation means
neighboring particles, neighboring boxes.
Here we have one neighboring box, and
here we have two other neighboring boxes.
Yeah.
So, for that we have the five x prime.
The first term is 5x 5x prime.
Yeah.
And the second term is 5 double prime.
Yeah, it just means pick two
neighboring and sum over all possibilities.
Sum, this is a sum over all neighboring pairs.
So it doesn't have to be adjacent to the first?
No, no, no, no.
In general not, but it can be.
In fact, this could even be the
same pair, but it doesn't have to be.
Yeah.
Sum over all of them.
All right, so what does this one do?
It moves a particle from x to x prime, and this
one moves a particle from x double prime to x triple prime.
All right.
So one of them moves
a particle from here to here.
This is x prime to x double,
to x, from x to x prime.
And then the other one moves
a particle from here to here.
That's x double prime and x triple prime, let's say.
Obviously there's going to be dangling ends.
Unless,
well, let's take this case here
where we only have three layers.
If we only have three layers, the only way to avoid dangling
ends is to have the first particle connected to the second particle,
sorry, the first box connected to the neighboring
box, and then this box connected to this box.
There won't be any dangling ends except for the dangling
ends which correspond to the initial particle and the final particle.
So if this was only three layers thick, we would find a
contribution here, namely where x prime is the same as x double prime,
that transports the particle from the initial position to the intermediate
position, and then from the intermediate position to the final position.
All right.
So,
let's look at this.
Okay.
What would be the amplitude then associated
with a particle going from here to here?
At least corresponding to this term, it would be
a one over two factorial and a minus sign.
That would be it.
You read off the coefficients, and
the coefficients tell you the amplitude.
Thus far, we don't have a
way to get from here to here.
Not with two factorials, but with two factorials.
Okay.
Not with two steps, anyway.
Two steps can...
However, if this was only two layers thick, we would have now
a way to get from here to here, to go across the diagonal.
How do we go across the diagonal?
We go again to this second order term here,
the term which has a two factorial in it,
and we find the term which
takes us from x to x.
From x to x prime, and then from x prime...
From x to x prime,
and then from x prime to...
From here to here, and then here to here.
What's that?
There are other paths.
There are other...
Other paths to get to this angle.
Yeah.
There's another path where you jump from
here first to here, and then up.
I don't think there's any other besides that.
Yeah.
Not with two...
Oh, not with just two terms.
Right.
Okay.
But now, there was no reason
to stop here with only two terms.
Let's go on.
We can have three terms.
Three terms would correspond to going
from one box to an adjacent box.
Well, it would correspond to three distinct steps.
And if those three distinct steps were
to connect it together in a row,
or to connect it together into a chain,
in other words, in this sum of products,
we found the term which took us...
Here, we could come right back again.
That would contribute together with the
direct jump from here to here,
would contribute to the amplitude to
go from this point to this point.
So you see, built into this prescription is
something like the original particle path integral idea.
The amplitude to get from here to here is the
sum over the amplitude to go from here to here,
and the amplitude to go through
another root, also this one back here.
And eventually, if you expand this out to arbitrary order,
there will be a term in there for every possible
root that you can take to go from any initial configuration
to any final configuration of that particle.
Okay.
So, first of all, just thinking
about a single particle moving in spacetime,
this field Lagrangian contains information
about the amplitudes to go from...
Now, let's take an arbitrary...
to go from any point to any other point.
What you do is you add up
all of the possible ways of going there,
and what is the coefficient
for each way of going there?
You read it off the coefficient that
multiplies that particular term in this sum.
1 over 2 factorial, 1 over 3 factorial.
Some of them have i's,
some of them don't have i's.
Remember that i squared is minus 1, so some of
them have i's and some of them don't have i's.
And so in general, the amplitude to go
from one point will be a complex number.
But they can also go back and forth.
That's what's new. That's one
of the things that's new here,
that they can propagate up and
down, and that's a feature of relativity.
Even the same two cells.
What's that?
Even the same two cells thousands of times.
Oh, indeed.
But you can go backwards.
Yeah.
All right.
Let's talk about going backward in time.
You could think of, here's
one that goes backward in time.
You can think of this as either allowing a
new rule where particles can go backward in time,
or you can follow time forward and say what really
happened here is the particle moved from here to here,
and then a particle pair,
particle and antiparticle in fact,
were created,
the particle half of it going to here,
and the antiparticle combining together
with the original particle to annihilate.
Think of it either way.
But the rule now allows trajectories which go backward.
Let's come back to this term here.
In this form of relation, since
you have n factorials in the denominator,
does this mean that you sort
of have convergence in the nulls?
Does it help the convergence?
Well, the n factorials certainly help the convergence,
but they're not enough to make it converge.
But the expansion of e to the i something,
of course, this is just an expansion
of e to the i something or other,
so of course it converges.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
But the sum over configurations doesn't have to converge.
Yeah.
This part converges.
And this is going to be
some finite number of total configurations considered.
Yeah.
Okay.
Let's, let me, all right, now let's
go on to a slightly different problem.
We studied the particle moving from one point to another.
Now let's suppose we put in two particles,
and we want to know what
the probability for the two particles
to go to two other particles.
In other words, we want to start,
and I'm going to take the case where
there are only two layers for a moment.
There's the case with only two layers for a moment.
And I want to know the probability
that if I start a particle over here,
it will get to here.
No, if I start two particles,
one over here and one over here,
that they'll get to here.
Okay.
Well, come back to this term.
Now remember what this term did for me before.
Before, it allowed me to hop three units.
But that same term allows two
particles each to go one unit.
Look at it.
This can create a particle.
This can annihilate it.
This can create a different particle and annihilate it.
This corresponds to a graph
where you start a particle in here,
and it goes to here.
That's this factor.
And the other factor, instead of
taking the particle that's already there
and moving it over here,
it just takes a totally new
particle and moves it to here.
Okay.
So this same factor, this same term,
contributes both to the motion of a single particle,
three boxes,
and it contributes to two particles each moving one box.
Did I say that right?
More or less.
Three boxes, one, two, two boxes.
Yeah.
So there's a lot in here besides just
motion of a particle from one place to another.
It has information in it
about any number of starting particles
going to any other number of final particles.
Now, in fact, particle number doesn't change
as long as we just take this into account.
Why not?
Because every starting, every dangling endpoint here,
well, let's see.
Yeah, it has to end somewhere.
Well, if you start and
end with different numbers of particles,
then obviously something has to happen.
Well, that would mean there has
to be a dangling in somewheres.
Supposing I wanted to, I mean, I can't,
how would you get from one particle to two particles?
What if I start with electron and positron,
I could end up with no particles?
Well, okay, that would be something,
that would be something, that
would just be something like this.
Two particles.
Let's put another layer in here.
Yeah.
Yes.
That's true.
That would correspond to an electron and a positron,
for example, annihilating each other.
The only problem with it is it doesn't change.
The only problem with it is it doesn't conserve energy.
So in fact, when you added up all these amplitudes,
you would get zero, but, but, but,
So you have to,
Yeah, but, yeah, but under certain circumstances,
if there was an electromagnetic
field to soak up the energy,
yes, you're right, it would, it would,
it would have information in it
about an electron and a positron annihilating.
Right, so there's just a lot in here.
There's a lot in here.
But not everything.
Not everything.
To find out the other things
that are implicit in the field theory,
there are other terms in the Lagrangian.
Now what you put in
the Lagrangian is determined by experiments,
and it's really just a way
of codifying the results of experiments.
But what else can you have in Lagrangian?
We had the derivative terms.
Let's say,
phi dot squared
minus the derivative of phi with respect to
x squared and y squared and z squared,
all that kind of stuff.
That was the stuff that I wrote down as
phi at one point times phi at another point,
at a neighboring point.
Then there are possibly other things that
just involve phi and not its derivative.
So for example, you could have things like phi squared.
Remember what the coefficient is?
One half here.
That's a convention.
Remember what the coefficient of phi squared is?
The square of the mass of the particle.
We should divide by two.
That's again a convention.
And if we included this term here,
what that would do,
it doesn't move a particle from one place to another.
It
absorbs a particle at one point
and emits it from the same point.
From the same point.
So it would correspond to graphical constructions
where we would add a new rule.
If a particle enters a region here,
from one box to another,
one of the terms that can act
is this mass squared term.
It would simply
take the particle and do nothing to it.
It would leave it in the same spot.
Then another term could come and move it,
but it would weigh that particular path
with a factor of m squared.
Every time this term acts,
it weighs the path with another
factor of m squared in the amplitude.
So there would be terms where no m squares act,
where only these derivative terms act.
In other words, where in expanding this product out,
we only had the derivative terms.
That would be the theory of massless particles.
The theory of massive particles
would have a new rule that
one of the possible things
that can happen at every step
is you may or may not
just weigh that path at
that point with an m squared.
Alright, so the mass term is another rule
for how you evaluate these paths.
These path integrals.
Another rule.
We don't have to get into detail.
The main point is that
the mass of a particle is codified
by another term in the Lagrangian,
which is m squared phi squared,
which weighs paths
in such a way that it knows about their mass.
Alright, but more interesting
is the more complicated terms.
Things like phi squared.
Let's put a g.
Sorry, phi cubed.
Phi cubed
can do a number of things.
It can annihilate one particle
and create two particles.
It can annihilate two particles
and create one particle.
It can create three particles.
It can annihilate three particles.
Alright, so that's a new kind of thing
that can happen on this checkerboard here.
In expanding out
the action,
expanding out the exponential,
there might be additional terms here,
for example, g phi cubed.
When we expand out,
we can have not only
these products which take a particle
from one point to another,
but also processes where particles
are created and annihilated
in threes.
Either two in, one out,
two out, one in,
or three in or three out.
What that looks like on here
is, for example,
supposing we have
several of
these quadratic terms
which move particles
in one cubic term.
What can that look like?
Well, what it can do
is it can take a particle
moving it from here to here,
and suddenly in that box
we put a phi cubed.
In that box
it can absorb one particle
and emit two more.
Now the next thing that could happen
is the two particles
could move
to other boxes.
But basically what it does
is it takes a particle,
absorbs it, and creates two.
And those two particles can be on their way.
And this would then
contribute to a process
where one particle came in,
two particles went out.
Okay?
In fact, you can make
very, very complicated things.
You can make things of...
Let's go back to the one particle
going from one place to another.
One particle going
from one place to another...
Let me stop drawing checkerboards.
Let's just imagine the checkerboard there.
One particle
going from one place to another
can go directly,
just a bunch of small hops,
a bunch of these hops.
But also something else can happen.
On the way,
at some point,
the cubic term
could act.
If the cubic term can act,
it can take that one particle coming in
and split it.
Split it into two.
And then
both particles
move along until
another cubic term,
something quadratic in the cubic term,
something with two cubic terms in it,
can create
an extra particle
and reabsorb it.
So in fact,
the actual amplitude
to go from one point to another
by one particle
is not just the sum
of simple trajectories
going from one point to another
through the space-time,
but is more complicated.
It has infinitely more complicated.
It has processes
where the particle
splits and rejoins.
In other words,
where the particle emits a second particle
which is then reabsorbed.
An example of this would be an electron
moving along and emitting a photon
and reabsorbing it.
Part of the amplitude
for an electron to go from one place to another
is through the process
of emission and absorption of a photon.
It can get wildly more complicated.
Of course, we have to add all of these up.
The rule is add up
the amplitude for every particle
to go from the initial state
to the final state.
You could have
several of these splitting and joinings.
things jumping across
the gap
between particles.
And this can get
arbitrarily complicated
from the point of view
of electrons and photons.
Things like this could happen.
And this could happen
in the form of a quantum
process.
An electron goes through,
a photon emitted,
another photon emitted,
but even worse,
the photon can break up
into an electron and a positron.
But then the electron and positron
can exchange a photon between them.
All of these processes
come out of expanding out
the action like this
and finding the individual terms
which do all of these things.
If you want the amplitude
for any one of these processes,
you just go back
to what appears here,
find the term that you're looking for,
and find the coefficient
in front of it.
It may or may not have an i,
depending on whether it's an even power
or an odd power,
and it will have some factorials
and so forth.
That will give you the amplitude
for a specific process.
But then the full amplitude
is a horrendously complicated sum
of all of these things.
Right, so you may have certain things
that happen in multiple of those histories.
In what?
In multiple of those histories
you may have similar terms
which then the overall amplitude
for that process would be
actually from all the different histories.
Yeah, from all the different histories
going from the initial to the final.
So there are two ways to think about field theory.
One is to think about fields
and think about histories
as initial values of the fields,
final values of the fields,
and you sum over all the values
of the fields in between.
And the other is this particle way
to think about it,
where the field is replaced
by a distribution of quanta.
And again, amplitudes
for initial configurations,
which means an initial particular
set of particles,
and a final set of particles.
The basic processes,
the basic underlying processes
are governed by this Lagrangian.
That is the most important thing.
Anytime you have
more than two fields interacting,
you have an interesting interaction
process where particles can split
and join and so forth.
What would happen if you had
phi to the fourth here?
Which is a perfectly good interaction.
That would be some place
where a particle, for example,
could come in and break up
into three other particles.
You know, one to the third,
two to absorb the initial state,
three to emit the final state.
Or it could be a scattering
in which two particles
come along, collide,
and two go off.
Anything that looks like a vertex
of four particles all together,
two in and two out,
or three in, one out,
or so forth,
or just four out,
or four in,
they're all governed
by this term.
And so forth and so on.
Let's see, how are we doing?
So that's the spontaneous arrival
of four particles at the final state?
Yeah, except once again
it would violate energy conservation.
So if you really worked it out
and added up the amplitude
from every position
where this could happen,
every space-time position
where it could happen,
you could have a very good
interaction process
with the four particles.
You would find out
that it doesn't happen.
In other words, they all add up to zero.
So processes which violate energy
typically all add up to zero
in these things,
energy or momentum.
So the conservation of energy
falls out of doing the calculation
and the conservation of momentum
is the same thing?
Yes.
So the conservation of energy
falls out of doing the calculation
and the conservation of momentum
is the same thing?
Yeah, we did some examples.
I showed you how integrating the vertex
over all time conserves energy,
how integrating it over all space
conserves momentum.
Same thing is true here.
Integrating the position
of these vertices and the endpoints
of these things over all possible positions
in space and time
will
simply
add up to zero unless energy
and momentum is conserved.
But apart from the conservation laws,
everything that
you can draw down will happen
with some probability.
Now,
how could it possibly be
that you add up this humongous thing
and the answer doesn't come out
infinite?
Well, the answer
is that there are
coefficients here.
There are coefficients here.
These are called coupling constants
particularly the coefficients
for the higher powers here.
We could call this G3,
we could call this G4.
And the rule is
in a diagram, in a Feynman diagram
like this, every time
you have a vertex, let's say
with three particles coming together,
the amplitude
contains a factor
of G, G3
in this case.
So the more complicated the diagram gets,
the more power
of G that it has.
Each vertex
gives you a power of G.
If G is a small number,
then
each successive power
of G gives you
a smaller and smaller contribution
and you have a chance
that the thing might be able to converge.
The technical
question of whether it really converges
or not is a very difficult one,
but you can see that you have a chance
if G is a small number.
If these coupling constants
are small numbers,
then the simpler the process is,
in other words,
the fewer number of vertices,
the bigger the contribution,
and the larger the number of vertices,
the more complicated
the smaller the contribution,
and you have a chance at any rate
at some sort of convergence
to an answer.
If the coupling constants are large,
it means these series
do not converge,
and if they don't converge,
it doesn't mean that the theory is wrong,
it just means you've chosen
a naive prescription
for trying to work with it.
But in practice,
most of the quantum field theory,
most of the things we do with quantum field theory
are based on the assumption
of small coupling constants.
And under those circumstances,
it's possible to evaluate these,
not just evaluate them,
but add them up
and find out that
the one with four vertices
is much smaller than
the one with two vertices.
So that's the name of the game.
Can we do color theory in the same way?
Yeah, we're going to talk about color theory.
Now the next step is to write down
the list of all particles
and to write down
either
in the form of Lagrangians
or in the form of Feynman rules.
The Feynman rules
and the Lagrangians
have the same information in them.
Three identical particles
coming together,
let's say three bosons,
that's phi cubed.
Particles going from one point to another,
those are the kinetic terms,
the quadratic
terms here.
So the
Feynman type rules
are the following.
And the Lagrangian
are the same thing.
And you can either
describe the world
by specifying all the vertices,
incidentally,
the lines between one point and another
are called propagators.
The place where
more than one particle, more than two particles
come together, those are called vertices.
Vertices and propagators.
But as I said, they're just simply
another shorthand way of
describing a Lagrangian.
This is a shorthand way of describing the graphs.
So we would have stated
all of particle physics
in a kind of dumb way
by simply writing down
the list of all particles,
writing or constructing
or even just expressing
a quantum field for each particle,
and then writing down
a Lagrangian
for all those particles
would contain all of the interactions
or we can write down
all of the particles in the graph.
And simply specify
what all the possible vertices are.
Either way,
they come to the same thing.
They're kind of a complete list
of everything that can happen.
Once you know everything that can happen,
you can start thinking about
calculating amplitudes for particles
to go from one place to another.
Particles to collide.
Particles to collide and scatter.
Here's particles colliding and scattering.
Two electrons colliding and scattering.
Just put them together.
And you can see
that by a photon jumping
from one place to another.
Again, Lagrangian tells you
how to calculate the amplitude
for each of these.
And as I said,
it contains all the information,
including symmetries,
including conservation laws.
So I think it's probably...
Should we write down
the list of all elementary particles?
So when you write down
a Feynman diagram,
the bottom is the initial configuration
and the top is the...
That's right.
The bottom is the initial configuration
of particles.
The top is the final configuration
And as I said,
it is the kind of complementary way
to think about field theory,
quantum field theory,
complementary to the field description
where you would start
with a given field configuration
and end with a given field configuration.
So the complementarity
between particles and fields
is very much like the complementarity
between momentum and position.
These are two different ways
to describe the same reality.
And there are uncertainty relations
between them.
If you know with precision
the number of particles,
then you know that there's uncertainty
in the values of fields.
If you know the values of fields,
then there's uncertainty
in the number of particles.
So there are complementary ways
to describe the same thing.
And the Lagrangian is useful
in both contexts.
Question.
The coupling constants,
are those predicted by theory
or are they determined?
Sometimes under certain circumstances
there are symmetries
which relate coupling constants.
So this or that coupling constant
for this process might,
for instance, be related
to another coupling constant
for a different process.
So some of them are related
to each other by symmetries.
But their values in general
simply come from experiment.
Simply come from experiment.
Much of this,
if you really go and learn
about quantum field theory,
has its beauty.
It does have elegance and beauty
in its properties.
Now when we start writing down
the list of facts,
what particles there are,
what their masses are,
what their coupling constants are,
it's just a mess.
It's just a very ugly mess
with very little coherence
except the coherence
that comes from symmetries.
Symmetries tell you relationships
between different kinds of particles
and their processes.
And not so much.
It is a large number
of random facts
about a somewhat unmotivated
collection of different kinds
of particles.
But still you're pretty confident
of the coupling constants because
Once you measure them, you measure them.
If you change it a little bit,
then you get wrong answers.
Oh, absolutely.
Let's do it this way.
You have too many particles,
which means too many fields,
too many for any aesthetic sense.
You have a lot of them,
a hundred of them or something.
A lot of coupling constants,
which are just more or less
numbers pulled out of an experiment.
And a lot of masses,
which range all over the map.
A few relationships between them,
but once you know them,
you can start to understand
what they are.
Once you know them,
that's it.
You can calculate with great precision
anything about those particles
and anything about those particles,
anything about quarks, electrons,
photons and so forth,
means atomic physics,
particle physics,
nuclear physics,
chemistry,
and maybe it means biology.
So the amount of input that goes in
is perhaps bigger than you might like,
but the amount of output
is huge.
Question, for electrons, for example,
how many G sub n's would be?
G2, G3, G4,
would these be calculated?
How many G's are there?
For electrons and photons?
In electrodynamics?
One. The electric charge.
The electric charge...
Hmm?
Well, in a sense,
the electric charge is a kind of G3.
The electric charge is a kind
of G3.
The electric charge is the coefficient
in the amplitude
representing an electron
coming in, an electron
going out, and a photon being emitted.
Alright?
In terms of symbols,
this diagram
would be represented
by an electron
going out,
an electron coming in,
and the field operator for a photon,
which is A. I'm not writing down
the details. There are some
direct matrices,
but then the numerical
coefficient in front of it
is the electric charge.
In certain units, certain dimensionless
definition.
Alright, now the only processes
in quantum electrodynamics
are the emission and absorption of photons
from electrons.
That's all there is.
...electron collision with a photon...
Well, if there are...
Electron collision with a...
Yeah. Electron collision with a photon
is just...the simplest
process would be
photon absorbed...
I meant to say proton.
Oh. Well, protons are not usually
considered a part of
quantum electrodynamics.
Now, you can think...
When you do quantum electrodynamics,
you are doing atomic physics.
You think of the proton as a point
infinitely massive
and you don't think of it as something
described by quantum field theory.
You just think of it as a nailed down
heavy particle which never moves.
Until you open up
the theory of protons and neutrons.
I mean, but...
Alright, so the scattering by a photon,
a photon by an electron,
this is the first diagram.
But the electron is moving
at almost the speed of light
relative to the proton?
Proton, yes.
But we're...right.
Yeah, that's right.
Let's draw some diagrams
just to get some feel
for what kind of things
we have to add up.
This is the lowest order diagram
that goes into
the scattering of a photon
by an electron.
There are two powers of the electric charge.
So there's an E squared.
But this is the amplitude.
The amplitude gets squared
to find the probability
or the cross section.
Cross section is another way of speaking
about the probability for the scattering.
Alright, so that means
that the whole process,
the probability,
is proportional to the electric charge
to the fourth.
The
electric charge,
at least in suitable,
with a suitable definition,
is a small quantity.
The square of the electric charge,
again with a suitable definition,
is about one, well that's the number
of the electron.
So this is proportional
to the square of the fine structure constant.
So scattering in quantum
electrodynamics
is an unlikely process.
A photon comes in
and strikes an electron.
What is the probability
that it goes right through it
versus the probability
that it really scatters it?
The probability that it really scatters it
is governed by this
E to the fourth, and it's a very small number.
Now,
we have to add all the processes
that we can find,
add them up to form a real amplitude.
Incidentally, there's another one here
which looks like this,
where
the final photon is
emitted before
the initial photon is absorbed.
That's another process.
We have to add them all.
But then we start adding
more complicated things.
Let's focus on here.
We can add another photon.
In many ways.
This is not the only way.
We could have it go from here to here,
from here to here. Many photons.
But how many powers of electric charge
does this have?
This has four powers
of electric charge in the amplitude
and eight in the probability.
So this is even weaker.
But then we can do
even more complicated things.
We can put an electron-positron
pair in here.
Each time we complicate it,
we add two more powers
of electric charge.
So in quantum electrodynamics,
the expansion is typically
an expansion in powers of the square
of the electric charge.
Every time you add another
complicating structure
to a Feynman diagram,
it's two powers of electric charge
and it means it's about a hundred,
a couple of hundred times
smaller in amplitude
than the previous one.
So if you add them up,
it looks like it converges.
Because the more and more complicated
they get, the weaker
the probability from that
particular configuration.
Incidentally,
you don't square this
and add it to the square
of this and add it to the square
of this to find the probability.
You add them up
and then you square.
That's the rule.
Add and then square.
That means there's cross terms
between them in calculating
the probability.
These are called interference terms.
So that's the structure
of quantum field theory.
That's what we do with it.
The next issue,
as I said,
we're now at the stage
where we can really start to sensibly
talk about particle physics.
We can name all the particles.
We can specify their masses.
Those are the parameters
that we've spoken of.
And we can write down
the Lagrangians governing them
partly from theory,
partly from experiment,
and discuss their symmetries.
The symmetries can be discussed
by looking at the Lagrangian.
We'll do that.
And we can write down
the standard model of particle physics
and discuss some of its properties.
So I think we're
off to
the next session.
I think we're set now
to move ahead
and really discuss
the world of genuine real particles
and what can be discovered
in the world of them.
Instead of that M squared,
you could have the Higgs field
and then that would be a
quadratic.
That's right.
We're going to discuss that.
That's exactly it.
Where was the...
Yeah.
Where is that extension?
Oh, they're here.
X and X prime could stand for two different times.
That's how we managed to move vertically.
Alright.
Which is the term that corresponds
to the particle just standing
where it's meant to be at?
There's also some terms...
There are various terms.
There are terms where the particle just stands still.
When we wrote down
phi of X
minus phi of X prime
squared,
that did have
terms in it like phi of X squared
and phi of X prime squared.
Those are terms where the particle stands still.
The cross terms
are the ones where it moves.
So there are terms where the particle stands still
both from this and from the mass term.
Right.
Yeah.
Okay.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.