Stanford University.
All right,
so last quarter we studied classical mechanics.
And classical mechanics is fairly intuitive.
The basic ideas are things that you can visualize.
You can picture in your head motion of particles,
motion of objects.
It gets a little hard when you start
thinking of ten particles all at the same time.
But nevertheless,
the whole thing is based on
concepts that are drawn from pretty much the everyday world.
Of course,
it gets more and more abstract as you go along.
The crazy French,
who were obsessed with elegance,
kept making it more and
more and more mathematically elegant.
Lagrangians,
Poisson brackets,
blah blah blah.
Turned out all to be tremendously important.
The abstractions,
though,
are not all that difficult to understand.
And the basic concept is the concept of updating.
Well,
before that,
the concept of a space of states.
What is the state of a system?
Even before that,
the concept of a system.
A closed,
isolated system that doesn't interact with anything,
and whose motion and whose evolution,
whose history,
you wish to predict.
Classical mechanics is predictive.
It's deterministic.
And the first concept,
as I said,
after the concept of a system,
is the concept of the state of a system.
Systems can have a collection of different states.
We talked about some very simple examples
the first day of the quarter last time.
I just described for you the most
elementary simple systems consisting of nothing more,
for example,
than a coin.
Heads and tails.
The only states of the system.
The only states of the system are heads and tails.
They form a mathematical set.
The states.
Two of them for heads and tails.
Two points.
One space.
Two states.
And we can draw them as dots.
This one stands for heads.
This one stands for tails.
And you know,
it's easy to picture in your head.
From there,
we talked about equations of motion.
Equations of motion,
or laws of evolution for the simple,
very simple,
system of a couple of points,
heads,
tails,
we formulated some very,
very simple possible laws of motion.
The simplest being nothing happens.
If you start with heads,
you stay heads,
heads,
heads.
If you start with tails.
You stay tails,
tails,
tails.
Tails,
tails,
tails.
that was a very simple law of motion
more complicated law of motion
if you begin with heads you go to tails
if you begin with tails you go to heads
and just oscillate back and forth
the basic idea is the idea of updating
if you know everything there is to know
about a system at an instant of time
then classical mechanic everything that
there is to know essentially means
everything that's needed in order to predict the future
if you know everything that needs to be known
then classical mechanics consists of a set of equations
which tells you how to update the state
given its value at any given time
how to go from one time to the next
that basic idea for example
well I don't think I
need to describe the examples again
we described them at length last time
and that's extremely intuitive
in going from these very simple discrete examples
to a world of continuous motion
indeed we have to abstract
we have to replace the idea
of a small number of states
a small finite number of configurations
by an infinite number of states
for example the motion of a particle along a line
we have to label the states
by the points along a line
as well as their velocities
and so it does get more complicated
but nevertheless classical physics consists of equations
which tell you how to update
the state at any given time
and it's completely deterministic
and as I said easy to visualize
or at least by comparison easy to visualize
because it makes use of concepts from the ordinary world
which your brain is rather hardwired
to be able to understand
now I always give a little sermon at this point
and I'm going to give it again
probably you've heard it a dozen times
about the way one has to think about physics
beyond classical physics
when you move past classical physics
I don't think it can be said enough
and it's so rarely said
that I think I will say it again
and it's that once physics moves past the realm
of parameters that has to do with ordinary experience
either objects which are so small
that they're far beyond what ordinary physics is about
or velocities which are so fast
that they're far beyond ordinary velocities
whenever we move out of the range of parameters
that we're familiar with from ordinary experience
we inevitably run into things that we cannot visualize
nobody can visualize the motion of an electron
it's just not wired for it
nobody can visualize four dimensional space
or four dimensional space time
let alone ten or eleven dimensions
it's not the way physics is done
I often read some of the
stuff that goes back and forth
between some people
I suspect people in this class
about trying to explain to themselves
to each other
or to ask questions of each other
about certain abstract physical questions
and I notice very much
that a lot of the mistakes
a lot of the confusion
happens because of trying to visualize things
using the old fashioned or standard intuitions
that you're hardwired for
you may think that physicists
good physicists are especially good
at visualizing these things
they're not
I cannot visualize five,
six,
seven dimensions
any better than you can
but I know how to use abstract mathematics
to describe it
there's no substitute
there really is no substitute
for the process of abstracting
and using mathematics
to describe the things which are beyond your ability
to directly visualize
the example that I always give
and I'm going to do it again tonight
I'm going to really focus on it
and realize that you're not
going to understand quantum mechanics
by trying to visualize it as some
funny form of classical mechanics
it won't work
you'll always get it wrong
but just the idea of visualizing
space of dimensions different than three dimensions
in particular I always used to say
okay,
how many people here can visualize five dimensions
and everybody would say
no,
we can't
of course there were a few fakers
a few clowns in the class
who would say,
yeah,
I can do it,
I can do it
but they couldn't
and they knew they couldn't
they can't visualize five dimensions
but then I began to realize also
you've probably heard this before
that it's equally hard
to directly visualize two dimensions
and so I would say to the class
okay,
how many people now can visualize two dimensions
and almost everybody would raise their hands
and I would say
no,
you're wrong
close your eyes,
try to visualize two dimensions
and they would,
they'd say,
okay,
I see it
I see two-dimensional curved space
what they're seeing is not two-dimensional curved space
what they're seeing is a two-dimensional surface
embedded in three dimensions
even try to see one-dimensional space
one-dimensional abstract,
one-dimensional space
is just a line
you cannot see that line in your head
without seeing it as a line drawn in a plane
and the plane you can't see without seeing it
as embedded in three dimensions
what's going on?
why can't you?
I hate to tell you this
but you're prisoners of your own neural architecture
your neural architecture was built for three dimensions
alright,
how do you get around it?
well,
you don't get around it by training yourself
to see four or five,
six dimensions
you get around it by training yourself
to think abstractly about it
okay,
if three-dimensional space is a point x,
y,
and z
then four-dimensional space is x,
y,
z,
and w
and you learn to manipulate the symbols
now that's not to say that after a while
you don't start to gain a
new kind of intuition for things
you do
but the intuition is not the process of
physical visualization of the same kind
as when you visualize a plane
or a wave as a wave in the ocean
so I warn you about that
and I will tell you quantum mechanics
is about as abstract as anything can be
well,
perhaps things are even getting a little more abstract now
but again,
quantum mechanics is about things that
your evolutionarily developed neural structure
is not prepared to deal with directly
how do you deal with it?
abstract mathematics again
and relativity,
it's also true of relativity
it's worse than quantum mechanics
okay,
let's uh
let's begin
with quantum mechanics at the very very
simplest most primitive question you can ask
what is the state
well,
I think we can ask the most primitive question
is what is a system?
now I don't think I can answer it
it's uh,
it's a sort of
undefinable,
you start with the idea of a system
uh,
and I don't think I will
try to give it a definition
but in particular a closed system
a closed system is one which at least temporarily
is not in interaction with anything else
it's isolated
it is not interacting with anything else
and so it can be described
by itself
as a lonesome entity with nothing else involved
um,
in classical mechanics
or let's
it's even,
it's not even a question of classical mechanics
it's a question of classical logic
the logic,
the whole logic of quantum mechanics
is different than the logic of classical mechanics
the logic of classical mechanics
again,
begins of course with a system
which I won't try to describe
but the next step is the space of states
the collection of possible states of a system
if the system is a discrete system
like a coin or a die
die,
you know,
the six-faced die
it can have six states
of course a real die
a real genuine die in three-dimensional space
of course can be in all sorts of orientations
it has infinitely many states
but what I mean by a die
now is I mean an abstract mathematical die
which,
whose states just consist of one of six numbers
the space of states
is a set
one,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six
this is the space of states of a die
this is the space of states of a coin
now again,
an abstract coin
which only has two states,
heads or tails
this would be heads,
this would be tails
the abstract space of a point particle
moving along a line
what is that?
anybody know what that is?
what's the abstract space
of a particle
moving along a line?
well,
I'll remind you that the term is phase space
the space consists of the set
of possible positions of the particles
and the possible momenta
the possible velocities
and so,
for a particle moving on a line
the possible states of the system
form a plane
and the plane
has a position
sometimes called q
a momentum,
sometimes called p
and every point on that plane is a possible
state of the point particle moving along the line
but it's a set
in this case it's a continuously infinite set
of two dimensions
in this case it just consists of two points
in this case it consists of sets
six points
and we can now start building
some logical concepts for classical physics
for example
concepts such as or and and
what do they mean?
or and and are concepts
which apply to collections of states
let's
consider a proposition
proposition such and such
the proposition could be
that the die
is located
has a value which is even
is even valued
okay
that's a subset of the space of states
in fact it consists of three
of them if I'm not mistaken
three odd one,
three and five,
yes
and another proposition would be the die is odd
no,
did I say odd?
odd,
even,
whatever the other possibility is
that's another non-overlapping set of configurations
let's take another case
let's take two propositions
one of which again is that the die is odd
and the other proposition is that the die
is less than or equal to three
alright so let's see
is one,
three,
five
is two,
four,
six
and less than or equal to three
is this set over here
so now they're overlapping sets
and we can ask for concepts like and and or
for example the proposition
that it is odd
that the die is both
less than or equal to three
and odd
is the intersection of these two subsets
one and three is odd and
less than or equal to three
so there's a concept of and
and
that's
in this subset and in this subset
the mathematical
concept
is the intersection of two sets
or the sets which satisfies both things
and that's the concept of and
given two propositions
each proposition
is a collection of states
the concept of and
is intersection
what about the concept of or?
or becomes the concept of union
what set of states here either
is less than or equal to three
or odd
it's the inclusive or incidentally
inclusive or means it can be both
alright that's not the intersection of the two sets
it's the union of the two sets
the union meaning everything in both sets
everything in here
is
either less than or equal to three
or it is odd
inclusively
with both being allowed
so the inclusive or
translates into the union
and the
concept of and
is the intersection of sets
that's the logic of classical reasoning to a large extent
here's a concept
two sets
are completely non-overlapping
this one and that one
that simply means the and statement is false
there are no states in there
for which both things are true
so there's a whole logic
that is connected
with the space of states being a set
and it's the logic of set theory
we're not going to do the logic of set theory
but
it's important for me to tell you right now
that the logic of set theory is not
the same as the logic of set theory
the logic of quantum mechanics is different
it is not based on the idea that
the state of a system is a set
the state of a system is something entirely different
and only in certain limits
only in certain limits where systems behave classically
does whatever a space of states of quantum mechanics
whatever it is
does it approximately reduce to
the concept of a mathematical set
in fact just to tell you what it is
it's a vector space
and we'll talk about that
alright
but before we do,
before we start to
talk about the abstract mathematics of vector spaces
and spaces of states of quantum systems
let's talk about experiments
and describe the simplest
possible system in quantum mechanics
it's the coin
of quantum mechanics
the system with two states
heads and tails
we have to completely erase
the blackboard and start over again
so we have some system
and whenever we measure that system
whenever we measure something or other about that system
namely the analog
of whether it's heads or tails
we either get heads or tails
alright,
let's give that a mathematical notation
I'm not going to call it a coin
I'm going to call it a qubit
a qubit is a system which can have two states
and q stands for quantum
the analog for classical physics is called a c-bit
classical bit
and it's simply the idea of a coin
heads or tails
we're going to see that a
qubit is a much more interesting
well,
complicated for sure
but a much richer idea
even though it only has in some sense two states
okay,
so the qubit
the qubit,
when it's measured
we're going to talk about measuring in a moment
is either heads or tails
but let's look at it in a different way
so let's describe it another way
let's give it a degree of freedom
a mathematical degree of freedom
and I'm going to call
that mathematical degree of freedom sigma
sigma is a traditional name
for a
for the degree of freedom describing a qubit
and sigma can either take on the value one
or it can take on the value minus one
it's one
when the qubit is heads
and it's minus one when the qubit is tails
and there's no more content in it
other than heads and tails
but it allows us to start
being able to write equations for something
we can also describe this another way
by a picture
I'm going to describe sigma equals one
by an arrow pointing up
and sigma equals minus one by an arrow pointing down
no implication here of anything geometric for the moment
just a notation
a notation
three different notations
heads or tails
sigma equals one or sigma equals minus one
and arrow pointing up and arrow pointing down
okay now let's imagine an experiment
an experiment involves more than just a system
it involves a second system
and the second system is called the apparatus
in classical mechanics we never
bother thinking too much about
the details
unless we happen to be experimental physicists
and really going to go into
the laboratory and do an experiment
we sort of don't worry very much about
at least in a deep sense
we think the system can
be described completely without ever worrying
about how you detect it,
how you measure it or anything else
but in quantum mechanics
one cannot get away ignoring the concept of anything else
and that's why we call it an apparatus
so let's introduce an apparatus
and I'll tell you what an apparatus
we're going to make a mathematically abstract apparatus
I'm not going to tell you how it works
it's a black box
we're going to call it A
A for apparatus
it's a box and it has a little window
here's the window
it also
it really is a box,
it's like a carton
it's like the carton you
get in the mail which says
this side up
you want it to stand upright
here's a little window
by a window I mean a little screen
and numbers appear on that screen
and it has some sort of detector
on the end of a wire
that senses the qubit
and it senses whether the qubit
is plus one or minus one
so you start with your qubit
and you don't know what state it's in
the experiment is to determine what state it's in
so the qubit begins in the unknown
not the unknown state but unknown
we don't know whether it's one or minus one
and we're going to do an experiment
the experiment
as I said I'm not going
to tell you how the detector works
it's not important for us
it's only important that detectors do exist
and we will talk later about the process of detection
but not for now
so it has a sensor over here
bring the sensor over to the qubit
and what does it do?
a number lights up in here
either plus one
oh first of all let's start
before we do the detection
the apparatus is in the neutral state
the blank state
no number there at all
so let's just call that
the blank configuration of the apparatus
we take the apparatus over
close enough to the qubit to interact with it
and if it's a good faithful apparatus
it will then register a number here
and that number will either be plus one
or minus one
plus one or minus one
depending on which way
whether it was heads or tails
that's the act of measurement
now you may or may not
be there to look at the apparatus
this is a secondary
the apparatus has detected and recorded
what has gone on here
so that's something that
in classical mechanics of course we do the same thing
there's nothing particularly quantum mechanical about this
but we tend never to think about it
in formulating the basic principles of classical mechanics
okay so that's an experiment
that measures the state of
or measures whether sigma is plus one or minus one
but we can also think of it as another way
we can think of it
not so much as a measurement
but as a preparation
a preparation of the system
here's the idea
supposing we in fact do
measure sigma to be plus one
supposing that's the outcome of the experiment
then we can erase the one that it wasn't
and start over
and then say let's back off
reset the apparatus
reset it means start it over in the blank state
and then redo the experiment again
let's say we do it fast enough
so that there wasn't much
time for anything else to happen
what happens?
what happens is
that the detector records again
and if it's a good detector
and the system hasn't had
a chance to change very much
it will simply record the same number again
it will confirm the previous experiment
this is important
that experiments can be confirmed
again
no difference between classical and
quantum mechanics in this respect
we just emphasize it in quantum mechanics
experiments can be confirmed
we can then do it again
and again and again and again
and we will continue to get the same
answer that we got in the first place
so we can say it a little bit differently
the first experiment instead of saying
that it
determined
whether it was heads or tails
we can say it prepared it in a state
which was in this case heads
after the first detection
it's now known to be heads
it has been prepared in the state heads
we can do the experiment
over and over and over again
and always get the same answer
alright so
a device that measures
is also a device that prepares a state
a system in a given state
of course the same thing would be true
had the device
determined in the first round
that sigma was minus one
then it would continue to detect the same thing
of course there can be bad detectors
not all detectors are well made
and not all detectors work the
way you want them to work
in which case
it just wasn't a good detector
it didn't do what you wanted it to do
what does heads and tails have to do with anything?
at this point
what's the purpose of having a heads and a tails?
there's just two possibilities
you want to know
you want to know what it actually has
to do with a head and a tail?
there's just two possibilities
I just used that for familiarity
there's nothing there
there's nothing there that can
be done with heads and tails
okay
now we're going to do something new
we're going to do a new experiment
first we're going to start with a preparation
the preparation determined
that the spin was
or a spin,
I call it a spin
I'm giving away
it is a spin
the qubit is in the state plus one
all right
so the qubit
in the other notation
is an arrow pointing up
we've prepared it
we now know
we can do it a few times to check
but once we check it
we now know
that this qubit is up
and if we continue to do it
we will continue to get the same answer
but now we're going to do something funny
after we've determined or prepared the qubit
we're now going to take the detector
and turn it over
a
I don't know
this side up
we've turned the detector over
and now we're going to probe
the qubit again
and what do we learn in this case
we discover
that instead of getting plus one
we get minus one
by turning the detector over
we get the opposite answer
what is this telling us
what is this telling us about the nature
of this system
what it's telling us
oh and of course
then if we take our upside down detector
and continue to do the experiment over and over
we'll continue to get minus one
because what happens if after we do it 35 times
we determine
we turn the detector back upright
then we get plus one
what we are learning
is that whatever this system is
this particular qubit
has a sense of directionality to it
that when I drew it as up
versus down
there really was
a sense
in which orientation is being distinguished
by turning the detector upside down
I interchange up and down
well that's what I normally mean by up and down
turn it over
look at it upside down
and it changes the sign of the qubit
that's an indication that the qubit is up
and the qubit has some directionality
in space
spatial directionality associated with it
now not all qubits do
have spatial directionality associated with them
but by doing this experiment
we discovered that whatever this qubit is
it really does have a sense of orientation
an upness and a downness to it in space
so that's a piece of interesting information
we might begin to suspect
that it's a vector
we might begin to suspect that it's a vector
since it has a directionality in space
it's a vector
when it's pointing up
it's different than when it's pointing down
we can make
well,
yes
so that's the basic idea of
a qubit which also happens
to have a sense of directionality
it's like this
like this pin
and our detector when we measure it
either measures it up or measures it down
but now we're going to do something
else
here's what we might believe
given that the detector has an orientation to it
and it does have an orientation to it
there's a right side up
and a wrong side up
in fact in the detector
we might even think
that there's something
which is itself an orientation
something built into the detector
which has an orientation in it
and
you know what we might think?
we might think that this detector
is detecting the value
of the component of a vector
along the direction
of
the detector itself
so
when the detector is right side up
and it detects this thing here
it's detecting the component
of
some vector
in the plus direction
when you turn the detector over
it's measuring the component
of the same object
except with respect to an axis
which has been flipped
so you might start to think
this thing is a vector,
this qubit
so now we do something
let's do something else now
let's turn the detector on its side
we have initially
determined that the qubit
was up
we've definitely made sure it's up
we've done it a thousand times
with the right side up detector
and we know for sure it's up
it's not down
and now we detect
take the sideways detector
A,
this side up over here
with its internal arrow
pointing in this direction over here
and
what should we expect
ordinarily
ordinarily we would say well
if this thing
is going to measure
now not the vertical
component of some vector
but the horizontal component of some vector
we know that that vector
was pointing upward by the initial preparation
what should you get here
well what's the component
of this vector along the horizontal axis
zero
so the answer is
we should get zero
if this were classical physics
and this were a classical little vector
that's exactly what we would get
so we go and do the experiment
probe it
and we get
not zero but either one
or minus one again
which one do we get
one or minus one
one and minus one sort of seem to be
symmetrically located
relative to the axis of the detector
so I say
oh I got one
let's do this experiment
a whole bunch of times
let's go back
get us a new qubit
throw this qubit away we're finished with it
make sure that it's pointing up
and do the same experiment again
well we might get
plus one again
but again we might get minus one
we do it many many times
exactly the same experiment
with the qubit
known to be pointing up
and we measure what we
like to think was the horizontal component of it
and we always get
plus one or minus one
randomly
but in such a way that
if you do it a great
many times
then the average value
is zero
as many plus ones
as minus ones
so you do it a great many times
and you find every single one of them
is either plus one or minus one
but on the average
it adds up to zero
you said you threw the qubit away
what if you kept the qubit
and looked at it again
well if you reoriented it
and made sure it was up again
then it wouldn't matter whether it
was a new qubit or not
if you look at the same qubit
with the sideways
and you look at it
ok good question
so let's go back
good question
we started with a qubit known to be up
we made a detection
and we got plus one
the implication of that
is the qubit
is lying in the horizontal direction
somehow
somehow we've detected
a plus one
but a plus one relative
to a new axis
not the original axis but a new axis
supposing we now
take that same qubit
don't modify it
but do the same experiment
over and over and over again
we will always get the same plus one
once
that qubit has registered plus one
and we don't disturb it
do the experiment again and again
we will continue to get plus one
in other words we will confirm
the experiment
the difference between the two
actions that you
projected
from going from top side
to bottom side
is 180 degrees
whereas the other is only 90 degrees
when I turn the detector by 90 degrees
I no longer have
definiteness about the answer
the answer is random
but only the first time
once I do it
and I determine
whether the horizontal component
is plus one or minus one
then it's determined
and if I do the same horizontal experiment
over and over again
I will continue to get the same answer
ok
well then I could come back
and say ok
now having done that
and been pretty sure
that the horizontal component of it
is in the plus direction
I can come back and turn
my detector again
guess what will happen
I will find a random
result
half the times plus,
half the times minus
but again
once it's determined
and I do it over and over and over again
it stays the same
this is probably not important
but on your sideways
detector
your arrows are I think going the wrong way
how so
they point from A
oh oh
maybe this was an A here
ok
side
oh my face
alright yes
you're right
yes
that's interesting ok
so therefore
after having done this experiment
and found out
that I get a plus one
I do it over and over and over
a few times
I get a plus one each time
let's say then I take the detector
and turn it around by 180 degrees
minus one
but what happens if I only turn it
by 90 degrees
random
alright but what
random means
a particular kind of randomness
equal probability
for up and down
alright equal probability
for plus
for plus one or minus one
and that means that if I were to
do the same experiment
the whole thing over and over
perhaps with a whole bunch of different qubits
I have a whole
I have a whole reservoir of qubits over here
lots of them I don't even know what direction
there are they're in
whatever they're doing
and I take them one at a time
I subject them to the first experiment
if I get up
I keep them
if I get down I throw them in the trash
at the end of the day
what I've gotten myself
is a whole bunch of qubits
known to be pointing up
now I take one of them
and subject it to the sideways experiment
I may get one or I may get
minus one
I record what I got
throw it away
go to the next one
do the same experiment
I may get plus one,
minus one
record what I get
take this whole collection
a large collection of them
and do the sideways experiment for all of them
what will be the average result?
zero
I will have
as many plus ones as minus ones
and so the average will be zero
let's write that
in this case here by saying
that the average value
we need a symbol for the average value
but after this experiment
here we will discover that the
average value
of the x
of the horizontal component
of the qubit here
is zero
classically
if we would have created a little vector
in the up direction
and we measure the horizontal component
we simply get zero
in the real world
in the real world of quantum mechanics
we always get plus or minus one
but in such a way that the average
is zero
is that true even if you don't throw away
the ones that were measured to be minus one?
actually it's still true
that's correct
the answer is yes
in your description
either the detector or the qubit
seems to have some type of memory to it
some type of
yeah that's right
we're assuming
that the qubit is a number
that
that the
law of motion
of the qubit is that nothing happens
to it so it remembers when you
detect it and then you
detect it again instantly after
it hasn't changed
right that's correct
now later on we're going to
consider possibilities where
during the intervening time between
measurements some interesting thing may happen
but at the moment we're supposing nothing
interesting happens in between
it's the analog of the classical coin
whose law of physics
was just nothing happens
we don't talk about collapsing a
wave function
that's of course what's going on but
but no let's not talk about that yet
let's talk
about the operational
things that
we might
do to discover
the laws of quantum mechanics
and then
then we'll put some words on them
such as collapse of the wave packet
okay
so things are funny
in some average
sense
the horizontal component
of something is zero
but in each individual
instance
you only get plus one or minus one
now let's go a little further
let's
oh incidentally the same thing
would be true if instead of
turning the detector this way
we turned it this way
so that the internal vector
was pointing outward would still be
true same thing
okay now let's do a little different
experiment
same setup
to begin with but instead of
rotating the detector
by 90 degrees
let's rotate it by 45 degrees
in fact any
angle
let's not do 45 degrees
let's rotate
it by an arbitrary angle
so that
the internal detector
orientation
is now characterized by
some angle theta
relative to the vertical
so
it's been rotated by angle theta
and do the same experiment
now we take
the first qubit
subject it now to the
um
uh
to the detector
oriented at angle theta
what do we get
plus one or minus one
do it again what do we get
what do we get do it again
plus one or minus one never anything in
between but
in this case the average
value
of the
experimental value
of what comes
out here
is not equal to zero
it's equal
to what do you expect it to be equal to
cosine of theta
cosine of the angle
exactly like
the x component of a vector
would be or exactly like
yes exactly like
the component of this
vector along the
detector axis the
component of this vector along the
detector axis
would be smaller
by amount cosine theta
classically
quantum mechanically
we simply get plus one minus one
plus one plus one minus one plus plus plus
whatever
in such a way as to
average
to the cosine of the angle
as
the detector gets more and more
upright cosine theta
gets closer and closer to one
and that just means
it gets closer and closer
to the value to the
to the answer
if the detector were perfectly upright
now and then
you might get
a minus sign
but mostly plus signs
and as soon as the detector gets perfectly
right side up all plus ones
what about
when the detector is almost
upside down
well then you get mostly minus ones
but here and there a few plus ones
and so
it seems that the average
values
of sigma
are behaving as if sigma
was the component of a
vector
this is
something you know really different
this is because you prepared these
as ups
if you just took
raw qubits
you'd get
you'd get zero
right
the theta is only because you started with
the ups
yes
why do we need a collection of qubits
why do we need what
a collection of qubits since nothing is happening
to the qubit why can't you
take the same one again and again
no
if you take the same one and do it over
and over again with the same detector
you'll just get the same answer over and over
you'll just confirm
the previous
measurement
so if you take one qubit
known to be up because you made it
you know that it's up
and you subject it to this
angularly distorted
angularly rotated experiment
you'll either get plus one or minus one
but if you do it the second time
you'll just get the same
answer you got the first time
you won't learn
anything new
incidentally if that weren't the case
there would be no way to confirm
that the answer that you got
the first time was in any sense the right answer
the only way that you confirm
that the answer is right is by checking it
and one way to check it
is just
you know if I close my eyes
and I look at you when I see you
upright and then I close my eyes
again and look at you again
I've confirmed that the first time you were upright
but the other one
is also prepared in the same state
say that again
the other one is also prepared in the up state
this one here,
second one
yeah
what I'm saying is if
you only have one of them
then you do the experiment
you either get plus one or minus one
and then if you do the same experiment
again on the same one
over and over
you just get plus one
but if you have a sequence of them
and you do the experiment
with a sequence of them
all having been prepared the same way
then you'll get a
statistical distribution
so if you turn off the detector
and turn it on again
will it still have memory of the same unit?
switch it off?
that's what I mean by measuring it again
switch the detector off and turn it back on
so does the detector seem to store memory?
the detector has an orientation to it
and
and when I say
how does it know you changed
or did not change the unit?
change the qubit
say it again
how does it know you changed
or did not change the qubit?
change the qubit
no,
it knows that you didn't change the detector
but when you switch the qubit
and now it's reset
but if you don't switch the qubit
it gives you the same reading
and so does it tell us
it knows
it gives the same answer
there was only one qubit
isn't it that the detector isn't
remembering anything
it's just the qubit has changed?
some are sitting upside down
some on the right side are sitting right side up
if I randomy open my eyes as a student
50 percent are standing
right side up or not
close my eyes
look at another student
but if i open my eyes
and then close them
and look at the same student
it would look the same way
how do my eyes know
that the student
was looking at another student
The answer is I just looked at the same student.
Okay?
So,
the whole thing is not that weird that we can't keep
track and remember which of these things that we're looking at.
Yeah?
So basically we can think of it as the
act of observing causes you to prepare that particular qubit.
So once you observe that one,
you prepared it.
Yeah.
So now you're always going to get that answer.
Until you intervene by...
Something else.
If you change qubits but leave
the measuring apparatus in the same position,
you'll still get plus one?
Okay.
So what do I do next?
Well,
you're not going to change
the orientation of the measuring device,
but you just measure a sequence of different qubits.
Are they always going to be up,
you know,
plus one or minus one?
It depends.
It depends on how they were prepared.
Okay.
Somebody might have given you a sequence
of qubits which happened to be up,
down,
up,
down.
You might have gotten them from someplace.
You got them from a,
you know,
from a qubit store where they weren't,
where they didn't have good quality control.
But if all of these qubits were prepared the same
way and identical way and then you send them through here,
they will continue to be identical.
Right.
Okay.
So what this is telling us is there's something
funny about the notion of the state of a system.
It's not as clear cut and not as
simple as the state of either a coin,
which is either heads or tails,
or a little vector which
has components in different directions.
But,
for example,
when you measure the component along an axis
perpendicular to the known direction of the vector,
you're going to get a little vector.
You get zero,
not so.
So there's something intrinsically different.
And the difference does trace to the big difference between the notion
of a state in quantum mechanics and a state in classical mechanics.
Can I say one point?
You had here everything up plus one.
And then one by one you turn it
and some were plus one and some minus one.
And that,
each one you bring up,
that which was minus one,
you bring up.
Then it becomes minus one back on the original.
If you do the experiment,
say again.
If you bring one down and let's
say that it's minus one down here.
Okay.
Then you turn the apparatus up again and now
you said it will be minus one from now on.
No,
no,
not if you turn the apparatus.
What's it turn the apparatus?
If you turn the apparatus,
I thought you said if you turn your apparatus up,
if it had measured minus when it was turned,
that it would stay minus
when you turn the apparatus up.
When you turn the apparatus,
then you get a statistical distribution.
Okay.
When you turn the apparatus.
Once you have the qubit
that comes out of this apparatus,
let's say it was plus one.
Let's say it came out plus one.
And now you take that qubit over here.
And you turn the apparatus back up.
And it's up again.
Then you're going to get a random plus or minus.
Then it will be random
when you turn it back up.
Yeah.
So in that way then.
Every time you turn it,
it will be random.
So it ends up then
with a random bunch of qubits.
You'll end up with a random bunch of qubits.
Yeah.
Now it depends on the angle.
If the angle is not too large,
if the angle is small,
then mostly you'll get pluses.
Right.
Mostly you'll get pluses.
And you'll get minuses.
Okay.
You've postulated a two-state system and then a detector,
but what would be the difference
in logic they say in your signal or as
a variable because your detector is a two-state system
which is – it seems
like you get the same output?
Say it again.
You've postulated a two-state system,
plus and minus one.
Yes.
but then you have a detector
that always produces plus and minus one
if you postulated a variable to start with
your detector seems like it
would still give you what you're
Your detector would still be what?
It seems like you're really saying
your detector is a two state system
that you can orient and
it doesn't seem to imply that
Yeah,
right
No,
no,
you're absolutely right that at some point
we have to come back to this
and say the detector is
a system and it has states
and understand the combined system as a
quantum system composed out of two quantum systems
but let's not do that yet,
let's divide the world into detectors and systems
and then come back later and say
look,
a detector really is a system and we
have to be able to describe it quantum mechanically
also as a system and to understand the
entire thing as the interplay between two quantum systems
but that would take some steps before we get there
What if we change the axis of rotation,
does it matter?
You mean if we rotate this way instead of,
yeah,
no,
it doesn't matter
I mean if we do one rotation
using one axis and then different axes
Yeah,
right
You're right in guessing that the
whole story is much more complex
but still,
the story is more complex but
not inconsistent with what I said
so don't try to guess too far ahead,
don't try to guess too far ahead
Let's take the simple version of it first
and then we'll eventually come to
a much more rich understanding of it
So for now is it correct to think of the
detector as something that could potentially return a continuous value
from plus one to minus one,
but the system will only be,
the qubit will only be in the first two states?
For now,
yes,
right,
if you like you may think of,
yes,
for now we may think
of the detector as a thing
which can be oriented in any
direction and when we measure it,
it behaves like a classical system
Yeah
Eventually we'll have to reconcile that with
the idea that detectors themselves are quantum systems
and have to respect the
same laws as the systems themselves
Okay
Okay,
now let's
I leave you with that to ponder now
and we're going to separate from
this for a while and discuss mathematics
We're going to discuss the mathematics of the state
space or the space of states of a quantum system
and as I said,
it's not a set,
it is not a set in the same
sense that the set of configurations of a die
is a set of six configurations
It's more complicated
Alright,
but we need some mathematics
We need some mathematics,
we need some abstract mathematics
and the mathematics,
as I said,
is not the mathematics of set theory,
it's the mathematics of vector spaces
Now,
let's just discuss the word vector for a moment
You're familiar,
of course,
with the idea of a vector
A vector is an arrow pointing
in a certain direction in ordinary space
and that's one concept of a vector
but there's a more abstract
notion of a mathematical vector space
and mathematical vector spaces can encompass many,
many kinds of mathematical objects
which are not necessarily pointers along an axis in space
I generally,
when we get to this point,
I generally make a new name
a non-conventional name that nobody
else that I know of uses
for the notion of an ordinary vector in ordinary space
In other words,
a thing pointing in ordinary space
I call it a pointer to distinguish it
from the abstract mathematical concept of a vector
We're going to talk now about
the abstract mathematical concept of a vector
Don't think of it as pointing in three-dimensional space
ordinary three-dimensional space
We'll discuss in what space it points
Alright,
so let's talk about vector spaces
A vector space is a collection of mathematical objects
just like numbers are a collection of mathematical objects
and numbers,
just the real number axis for example,
is a vector space
It's a special case of a vector space
It's a one-dimensional vector space
Complex numbers are two-dimensional vector spaces
We're going to be talking about vector spaces of,
for the moment,
unknown numbers
and one-dimensionality
and we're just going to write down a mathematical notation
for an object in the vector space
and as I said,
vector space is now just a name
for a collection of mathematical objects
Completely abstract
A is a vector
and that's the notation for an abstract vector
It's Dirac's notation
and it consists of a number
It consists of a vertical line
a crooked line
and a letter in between
and that stands for the vector A
whatever the vector A is
What can you do with vectors?
Well,
you can add them
I'm not going to tell you how to add them
I'm just going to tell
you that given any two vectors
A and B
you can form their sum
and their sum is another vector
Let's call that other vector
the vector C
So a vector space consists of a collection of objects
which can be added
Numbers
I'm sorry,
I'm just confused
Vector versus vector space
Vector space is a collection of vectors
Right
The same distinction between number and numbers
Numbers are all in numbers
Number is a specific number
Okay
So as I said
Numbers are a special case of this
You can add them
You can do something else with numbers
You can multiply them by other numbers
Well,
eventually we'll talk about multiplying vectors
but not yet
What we can do is multiply vectors by numbers
Ordinary numbers or complex numbers
and we're going to be thinking about complex numbers
I hope everybody is comfortable with complex numbers
If not,
you gotta quickly get up to speed on complex numbers
But we don't need to know too much
You need to know that a complex number
is a combination of a real number
and an imaginary number
and how to multiply,
add complex numbers
and you need the notion of complex conjugate
How many people here are familiar
with the concept of complex conjugate?
Most people,
right?
Almost everybody
So I'm not going to go in it now
But basically for every complex number
there is another complex number
which is complex conjugate
It's a mapping between numbers
and their complex conjugates
That's an important notion
Keep it in mind
because it's going to come back
But for the moment
Ordinary vectors
Let's go back to,
you know,
pointers
Pointers in space
Ordinary pointers
you can multiply by ordinary numbers
positive or negative
A pointer which is of
a certain length in that direction
if you multiply it by two
it's just twice as long in the same direction
Multiply it by minus one
it just becomes in the same direction
except in the opposite,
you know,
in the opposite direction
So,
yes,
you can multiply vectors by numbers
and in a complex vector space
we're now going to talk about complex vector spaces
you can multiply vectors by complex numbers
Now do not try to picture this in your head
as any kind of pointer in some direction
Just accept we're now
talking about a mathematical abstraction
where a vector
any given vector
can be multiplied by any complex number
I'm going to use
Let's see,
what shall I use for complex number?
In my notes I used C
but I don't want to use C
Z
Z is a standard notation for
you know,
x plus i y is equal to z
So you can take any complex number
sorry,
any vector
multiply it by any complex number
and it is still some
I'm not going to try to draw it for you
Stop trying to think about drawing vectors
If there is a vector
and there's a complex number
you can multiply them
and it gives you some new vector
Let's call it
Well,
let's call it A prime
So you can multiply vectors
by numbers
complex numbers
And that's about it
That's all there really is to a vector space
Any set of objects
for which you can do this
is a vector space
I'll give you some examples of vector spaces
If A's and B's are comp-
A's
If A's and B's are just real numbers
then you can add them to make new real numbers
But you cannot multiply them by complex numbers
and still expect to get real numbers
Okay
You can multiply them by real numbers
and get other real numbers
So the real numbers are a real vector space
How about the complex numbers?
Are the complex numbers a complex vector space?
Yes
You can add them
and get new kind of numbers
and get other complex numbers
Any two complex numbers you can add
And any complex number you can multiply
by another complex number
and get back a complex number
So the complex numbers
are the simplest example
of a complex vector space
Okay
Let me give you another example
of a complex vector space
This one's incredibly complicated
but still pretty easy to write down
Take any function of a variable
Let's call it psi of x
Now x is a function of x
It may be an ordinary real variable
A function on a line
But it's a complex function on a line
It has a real and imaginary part
Complex function on a line
Can you add two functions and get another function?
Certainly
So
Functions,
just functions
are things you can add
to get other functions
Can you multiply a complex function
by a complex number
and get a complex function?
Yes
Take any complex function
multiply it by a complex number
you get another complex function
So functions form a vector space
Now that's a complicated idea
and I don't want to get that complicated yet
So let's erase that from the blackboard
I'll give you another vector space
Another complex vector space
Let's just make some symbols
A bracket
and put in entries
two entries into the bracket
And the two entries are themselves complex numbers
Alpha 1 and Alpha 2
Alpha equals a complex number
Both Alpha 1 and Alpha 2
And Alpha 1 and Alpha 2 can be anything
The collection of such symbols
is also a complex vector space
Here's the rule
Supposing you have two of them
Here's one
And here's another one
Beta 1,
Beta 2
And you add them
What does that mean?
Definition
The definition of the sum
of two
These are called columns
The sum of two columns like that
is just to add the entries
Alpha 1 plus Beta 1
Alpha 2 plus Beta 2
So given any two abstract symbols
in which the entries are filled in with complex numbers
Any two of them
Alpha and Beta
We can add them and get a third one
So
Column vectors like this
Little columns of two entries like this
satisfy the first rule
And the second rule
Is that if you want to take a column
And multiply it by a complex number
All you do
Is multiply each entry
By the complex number
You multiply each entry separately
And then you construct something
Which is just Z times that
So just pairs of complex numbers like this
Form a vector space
It's a very abstract concept
But not very hard
How about triples of them?
Sure
So any length of column like that
Now what you don't want to do
Is add a column of
two to a column of three
You don't have a rule for that
Alright
So columns of different length
Form different vector spaces
Completely different abstract vector spaces
Any question about the meaning
And this is not hard
But it is abstract
Are those the only two requirements for vector space?
Yeah,
well I think it's also important
that there be a zero vector
Zero vector is the unique vector
Which when you add it to any other vector
Gives back the same vector
Right?
I didn't feel like writing it down but
Closure requirement
The general closure requirement
That the result be closed under
Under what?
A particular space
Closed under addition?
I think,
right
And closed under multiplication?
Which I think you've illustrated
Yeah,
yeah,
that's right
Is this the same as vectorizing?
This is the same as matrices
Is it what?
Matrix
Yeah
This is a
Usually the term matrices
In this class in any case
Will be reserved for square matrices
Square matrices are collections of numbers
Which form square arrays
As many rows as columns
But the general notion of a matrix can have
Different numbers of rows and columns
And the vector would be a matrix
With only one column
In this case two rows
So yes,
this would be a special case of a matrix
But,
you know,
in many contexts
One reserves the term matrix
For a square matrix
And I will use it that way
I will use the term
matrix to mean a square matrix
So I didn't want to use it
I didn't want to use that terminology
Okay,
are you thoroughly saturated with abstract mathematics?
This should be straightforward for you
Okay,
now we introduce another abstraction
Another abstraction
Basically
It's the abstraction of
A comp-
Given a complex vector space
The complex conjugate of the vector space
Is sort of
The space of complex conjugate vectors
Just like you can have for any number
A complex conjugate
Any complex number
There's a complex conjugate to go with it
So in that sense
The complex number system
Has a
A
A dual version
Which is the complex conjugates of the original numbers
So do the complex conjugate vector spaces
And roughly speaking
The complex conjugate vector space
Or the dual vector space
Usually called a dual
Is roughly speaking
The complex conjugates of the original vectors
We'll make that more precise as we go along
But what it is
Is a separate vector space
Whose elements
Are in one to one correspondence
With the elements of the original vector space
So if there is a vector A
In the original space
Let's write it this way
Then there is
A vector in the dual
It's called the dual vector space
As I said it is
more or less the complex conjugate
And it's written this way
It's just written as a backward Dirac symbol
We'll learn to call these things bra vectors
And these things ket vectors
But no,
this is the ket vector
This is the bra vector
But for the moment
They're just symbols
An example
If the vector space is
just the space of complex numbers
Then the dual vector space
Is just the space of complex conjugates of those numbers
So there's a one to one correspondence
Between vectors and their complex conjugates
Let's
Write down first some postulates about
The complex conjugate vector space
And then test it out
By seeing if we can find a concrete
Representation of the notion
Write down some abstract postulates
And then check
Just as we did here
We said here's a concrete representation
Of the notions that we wrote down over here
Let's write down the abstract postulates
About the dual vector space
So first of all
For any vector
There is a dual vector
And they're in one to one correspondence
Next
If you take two vectors
And you add them together
Then
The dual of the sum
Is just the sum of the duals
So if you take a vector which is made up
Out of the sum of two other vectors
Then
It's reflection
In the dual space
Is just the sum of the individual dual vectors
These are postulates
These are postulates if you like
But they're not so obscure
The third assumption
Is that if you take any vector
And multiply it by a complex conjugate
Sorry,
by a complex number
Then
Its reflection in the dual space
Now,
anybody want to guess?
Of course it involves the dual vector to A
But not multiplication by Z
But multiplication by the complex conjugate of Z
Z star
Z star is the complex conjugate of Z
This is the first assumption
This would be true of complex numbers
If you take a complex number
And multiply it by another complex number
Then the complex conjugate of the whole thing
Is the product of complex conjugates
That's all this is saying
So we think of the
Dual vector space
As basically just the complex conjugate vector space
In some sense
Okay,
let's see if we can
make any sense out of this
In terms of
In terms of these column vectors
Here
Good question
Yeah
Is A plus B the same as B plus A?
Yes,
yes
A plus B is the same as B plus A
Good question
Yes,
when you add vectors
And you can see that from here
I should have
Alright,
I'm sorry
Somebody asked me
Are there any other rules
about the definition of vector spaces
And indeed there are
Among other ones
That may be all there is
That it doesn't matter which order you add them in
Yes
So you can see that here
The sum of two vectors
Is just given by numerically adding the complex numbers here
And of course numerical addition of complex numbers
Doesn't matter which way you order them
Good
So that's a good point
Okay
Okay,
so let's come back now
To
Let's put this up on top
And come back to this concrete
Non-abstract representation
Of the complex vector space
Here we have a vector
This object is representing
The vector A
The one that I erased with beta
That's representing the vector B
But right now I don't need the vector B
Okay
What about the object
If this object represents A
Then what is the object which represents
The dual vector
The corresponding dual vector
And the answer is
It's the same pair of numbers
Except they're complex conjugates
The same pair of numbers
Not quite
They're complex conjugates
Alpha one star and alpha two star
But just to keep track
That we're talking about
Of the different vector space
We write it in row form
Not as a column but as a row
This is just a trick to remember
That this object belongs to the dual vector space
This object belongs to the original vector space
And that they're different
Alright
So the dual vector space image
Of alpha one and alpha two
Is alpha one star alpha two star
That's the
That's the dual vector
And then you can check
You can check
With this definition
Are the postulates
Namely that if you add two vectors
And then take the dual
That whether or not you get the sum of duals
And you can check
Whether when you multiply this by a complex number
And then take its dual
Whether it just multiplies by the complex conjugate number
The answer is yes
So just laying out a
pair of complex numbers like this
Makes a vector space
And the dual vector space
is the same pair of numbers
Except complex conjugated
And laid out in a row
Laid out in a row just to remember
That it's not the same creature
Doesn't live in the same space of things
And that's the idea of
A complex vector space
As I said,
again,
very abstract and very easy
Final concept
Well,
it's not the final concept
But A
The n plus first concept
I'm not sure what n is
How many people find this hard?
It's not very hard
How many people find it familiar?
Quite a lot of people find it familiar
That's good
Those who don't find it
familiar apparently didn't find it hard
That's also good
The product of two vectors
The inner product of two vectors
It's the analog of the dot product for pointers
The analog of the dot product for pointers
The inner product between two vectors is strictly speaking
The inner product between a vector and a vector
And the dual of a vector
Given two vectors
Let's call them A and B
One does not form the product of A with B
The inner product
Instead,
one takes B
And constructs its image in the dual vector space
And then takes the product of the
vector A with the dual vector B
In Dirac's language
You take a ket vector
And you multiply it by a bra vector
And when you do so
You make a bra ket
Or a bracket
The bracket
The bracket of course is this thing over here
And the two together
I think this one is called the ket
And this one is called the bra
So it's a bra ket
So the inner product of two vectors
Is really a product of a vector
And the dual of a vector
Now is it the same
As multiplying
The bra vector A with the ket vector B
Question
Is it the same to multiply
The bra B with the ket A
Or the bra A with the ket B
And the answer is no
The answer is no
It is not the same operation
But in fact they're closely related
The axiom
We're still talking about axioms now
The axiom is that these two are related by
Complex conjugation
I complex conjugated A
To go from the
From the ket vector to the bra vector
I complex conjugated B
To go from the bra vector to the ket vector
So if this is the product of A
Roughly speaking times B star
This is the product of B star times A
This is the complex conjugate of this
So another postulate
Another axiom of complex vector spaces
Is that the inner product of A with B
Is the complex conjugate of the inner product of B
With A star
So what that means
In normal vector space language or whatever
Nothing to do with quantum mechanics per se
I mean there the inner product is just
All the vectors are in the same vector space
In an ordinary vector space
Right
But so this is still called an inner product
Even though it's kind of the special thing
With the complex conjugate
The usual vector spaces that you think about
Are real vector spaces
And for a real vector space
For a real number
There's no difference between the number
And its complex conjugate
So the real vector space satisfies the same postulates
Except that the complex conjugation
Is completely a trivial operation
But I mean you could have a vector space
Where you take the inner product
Of two complex vectors
And it doesn't involve any conjugation
You just multiply them component wise
And take the sum
Yes you could
You could invent such things
Then of course the inner
product of a vector with itself
Would not be real
That's okay
Who cares
So you could invent such things
Turns out not to be terribly useful
In the context of quantum mechanics
So you know it's largely a question of what's useful
And what's useful
Winds up being this concept
Right
But yes you could do
You could certainly define such a thing
It's not a commonly defined thing
Doesn't seem to have a lot of use
Now
This structure occurs over and over
In all kinds of places
Not only quantum mechanics
I mean this complex vector spaces
Are very,
very common things in mathematics
And
Okay,
let's check now
Let's see if we can
Postulate a construction
For the inner product
Of
the dual vector beta,
remember when you complex conjugate,
when you take times the original vector alpha.
This is supposed to be now,
I guess I called it BA.
BA.
And I haven't written down the notation
for B and the notation for A.
Column vector for A,
row vector for B,
complex conjugated.
I will tell you now what the rule is.
Again,
we're making up rules which
will satisfy those postulates up there.
And it's a very simple construction.
It's just beta one star times alpha
one plus beta two star times alpha two.
In other words,
you take the first entry of the dual vector
times the first entry of the vector with alpha.
Add it to the second entry times the second entry.
So it's actually just a
generalization of multiplying beta times alpha.
But it's also a generalization of the dot product.
If you remember about dot products of ordinary vectors,
you simply take the sums
of the products of the components.
If you have two pointers and they're labeled by components,
both of them,
then the dot product is just the
sums of the products of the components.
Does that satisfy the rules up here?
Uh,
what are we?
Where are the rules?
I think I must have erased the rule,
huh?
I did erase the rule.
The rule was,
um...
I lost it.
Okay.
What happens if you interchange alpha and beta?
Or A and B?
Then this becomes alpha one star alpha
two star times beta one beta two,
if I interchange them.
And that's equal to alpha one star
beta one plus alpha two star beta two.
And that's just the complex conjugate of this.
It really is the complex conjugate.
So interchanging alpha and beta,
or A and B,
really does interchange the value of
the product and its complex conjugate.
That's the notion of a complex vector space
and an inner product on the complex vector space.
Now,
let's just take a couple
of special cases of inner products.
What about the inner product of a vector with itself?
Or a vector with its image in the dual space?
Let's take the inner product of A with A.
What do I know about that?
Well,
first of all,
let's,
uh,
let's...
I'm setting B equal to A.
Okay.
That tells me that the inner product of a
vector with itself is equal to its own complex conjugate.
I just substituted for B,
A,
the inner product of a vector with
itself is equal to its own complex conjugate.
What kind of number is
equal to its own complex conjugate?
A real number.
So the inner product of a
vector with itself is always real.
That's pretty obvious just from here.
If I take alpha and multiply it by its image,
I get alpha star alpha
plus alpha two star alpha two.
Each one of these is real.
Not only is it real,
it's also something else.
Positive.
Alpha star alpha,
a number times a number.
Alpha times its own complex conjugate is always positive.
So it's real and positive.
The inner product of a vector
with itself is real and positive.
And it's considered to be the
square of the length of the vector.
The square root of the inner product of a
vector with itself defines the length of the vector.
So complex vectors have real lengths.
Real and positive lengths.
Also,
the square of the,
both the square and the length
itself are defined to be positive.
So that's not too obscure.
Every complex vector has a length,
which is the square root of the
sums of the squares of its components.
But squares now mean multiply by complex conjugate.
Next notion,
an important notion.
The notion of orthogonality of vectors.
The notion of orthogonality of vectors is,
as we'll see,
is a very important one.
I'll give some examples in a few minutes.
The notion of orthogonality between two vectors is
exactly the same as it is for ordinary vectors.
That the inner product,
read dot product if you like,
the inner product is zero.
If the inner product of two vectors is zero,
they are said to be orthogonal.
That defines,
or perpendicular.
Okay,
so two vectors are orthogonal if
the inner product between them is zero.
Let's see if we can make up some orthogonal vectors.
It's very easy.
Oh,
oh,
oh.
What about reading,
what about if I take
the inner product the opposite order?
It's just a complex conjugate of zero.
But the complex conjugate of zero is zero.
So,
saying that two vectors are orthogonal,
it doesn't matter which order you put them in.
The notion of orthogonality doesn't depend on order,
although the general idea of inner product does.
Alright,
so now we have the notion of orthogonal vectors.
In a real vector space,
how do you define the
dimensionality of the real vector space?
Well,
give me a definition of the dimensionality.
There are many definitions,
of course,
but anybody have one?
Number of vectors.
Number of entries in the vector.
Yeah,
but let's work in a more abstract way without,
yes,
that's of course correct.
The number of orthogonal vectors.
The maximal number of orthogonal vectors
that you can find in the space.
Okay,
so if the vector space is two-dimensional,
ordinary two-dimensional vector space,
there are two mutually orthogonal vectors,
you cannot find a third vector
which is orthogonal to both of them.
So the maximal number of mutually orthogonal vectors.
In three dimensions,
where's my...
I've got three mutually orthogonal vectors.
Of course,
there are many sets of three mutually orthogonal vectors,
but given three,
I cannot find a fourth one.
So a three-dimensional vector space has a
maximal number of three mutually orthogonal vectors.
And the same is true,
or the same definition,
it's definition,
is true for a complex vector space.
The maximal number of orthogonal vectors that you can
find is equal to the dimensionality of the space.
It does correspond to the number of entries here,
the number of components.
It is the same,
and you can prove that.
It's a little exercise.
Prove that the number of components of the vector
is the same as the number of mutually orthogonal vectors.
But let's just talk,
let's just...
Are there any mutually orthogonal vectors we can write down?
Sure,
loads and loads of them.
But a very simple case would be one,
zero.
Now,
one and zero,
are one and zero complex numbers?
Well,
yeah,
real numbers are special cases of complex numbers.
So a real complex number can be real.
Here's one,
and here's another one.
Zero,
one.
This one has a one in the first place,
it has a zero in the first place.
This one has a zero,
and you get the idea.
The inner product is zero times one,
plus one times zero.
Okay,
so the two vectors,
or let's just write it in terms of column vectors.
One,
zero,
and zero,
one.
One,
zero,
and zero,
one are orthogonal vectors.
The inner product of this one with
the dual of this one is zero.
That's because one times zero,
plus zero times one,
is a zero.
So there are plenty of orthogonal vectors around.
But,
in two dimensions,
and this is two dimensions,
once you've found two of them,
you cannot find a third.
So there's a little exercise.
Prove that there can be no vector which
is both orthogonal to this and orthogonal to that.
That's not hard to do.
It's very easy to do.
Hm?
Oh,
yeah.
Yeah,
zero,
zero is always orthogonal to everything.
Right,
yeah.
Yeah.
Right,
so one should be careful and say,
the maximal number of non-zero orthogonal,
mutually orthogonal vectors.
Good point.
Right.
Okay,
that's a mathematical interlude for tonight.
Complex vector spaces.
And the next time we will
discuss how the space of states,
and what it means for the space of states
of these simple qubits to be two-dimensional vector spaces.
Very,
very different than saying that they
consist of points in a set.
The space of states is in fact a vector space.
And then try to make contact
with the mathematics of vector spaces,
and the strange things that are happening,
or that seem to be happening here with these,
these,
these funny properties of measurements.
That's where we want to go.
So we've done some physics,
some experimental physics on this blackboard up there,
and we've done some abstract mathematics over here,
and next time we want to connect them,
and show what the,
what the abstract mathematics,
how it represents,
or how it can be used
to represent this unusual kind of,
logic of qubits.
If we're looking strictly at the patterns,
is it going to be
meaningful to define the multiplication operations,
or will we create a two by two matrix?
Which would be beta one star alpha one,
beta two star alpha one?
You're asking...
I,
I...
Yes.
The answer is yes.
Yes,
absolutely.
We'll construct inner products,
outer products,
all sorts of products.
Yeah.
That's right.
The outer product of two vectors is a matrix.
matrix.
Yeah.
And of course,
how do you represent it?
Just,
well,
the outer product
of two vectors is represented this way.
It is a matrix,
but we'll come to that.
All the postulates apply to a vector space of functions,
for example,
as well.
It is less obvious than...
Yeah.
A vector space of functions
can be thought of as column
vectors,
but where the entries are continuous.
So we have alpha.
Alpha is the function,
and
alpha of the first entry,
alpha of the second entry,
instead of that,
we have a continuous
family of alphas.
Alpha evaluated at point x1,
alpha evaluated at point x2,
alpha evaluated
at point x3.
And so,
you know,
you can see that the,
the,
the green gracep Chipabay left side
says that our function is zero.
Right?
Okay,
but
what everybody is saying is that the,
the,
the entry of x2,
x1,
is a function of one
or a very small group of variables,
and that's a number that's
going to rain down and down
and around,
and that Que tea,
this is going to stay at
the same value as x2 and doesn't
complex vector spaces.
The inner product,
we will discuss that.
Back on the upper left board
where you have that apparatus
turned at angle theta,
if you consider the sequence
of inputs going to outputs,
the proportion of minus ones to ones
would be given by cosine theta.
Is there anything interesting
about the distribution
of the minus ones within the ones?
What does it mean?
Well,
like higher order statistics maybe.
Still what does it mean?
Oh,
oh,
oh.
They're just completely random.
Completely random.
Yeah,
just completely random variables.
You're talking about the relationship
between the different
replications.
A whole bunch of spins
and you subject them all to the same.
And the question is,
I think you're asking
whether there are correlations
between them.
No?
No.
They're completely independent,
uncorrelated variables.
So still with the qubit experiment there,
does it make sense to say that when you,
when you're measuring the qubit,
you're affecting it,
so you're actually preparing it in a new state?
Yes,
yes,
yes.
That's exactly right.
That's why the first time does something
and the second time it just keeps it.
And that's a big difference
between classical mechanics
and quantum mechanics.
In classical mechanics,
you can measure something
sufficiently gently
to not affect it,
to not disturb it.
In quantum mechanics,
whenever you measure something,
you always disturb it.
So this is an example
of how measuring something
disturbs it
and puts it into a new state.
And I'd say that's a good point.
Yes.
Okay.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.