Stanford University.
So let's begin.
I'm going to review very quickly,
I hope quickly.
We described a simple system consisting of one qubit.
I'm going to change my terminology a little bit.
I'm going to start calling that qubit a spin.
Don't worry about what it has
to do with spinning at the moment.
Of course,
more important is that it's a little pointer.
Now I use the term pointer.
I began to use the word pointer
to refer to vectors in three-dimensional space.
While I was writing,
I realized that that's an
awfully awkward and unfamiliar terminology.
And I decided to replace it with another term,
the standard term,
three vectors.
Vectors in three-dimensional space.
I may sometimes use the term pointer,
but I think I'm more
likely to use the term pointer.
I'm more likely to speak of three vectors.
And a three vector means a vector in real space.
The more general concept,
when I simply say vector,
more likely I'm speaking about the
abstract notion of a vector space
and the elements of a vector space.
Just to warn you and keep the language clear.
Now we talked about this qubit,
which has now become a spin.
It has some of the character of
being a little three vector in space.
There is some sense or other
in which it points in a direction.
And that we can confirm by an experiment.
As was said before,
once we start thinking about quantum mechanics,
we really do have to think
about systems and their connection with apparati.
Is that a core word?
Apparati?
I'm not sure.
Apparatuses?
I'm not sure what the plural of apparatus.
Anybody know the plural of apparatus?
Apparatus.
Just apparatus?
Okay.
Just apparatus.
We do have to think
about the connection with their apparatuses.
That measure them.
And we don't get away with just ignoring it.
What's the difference?
First of all,
I'll tell you what the basic difference is
in classical physics and in quantum mechanics.
In classical physics,
measurements can be arbitrarily gentle.
Arbitrarily gentle means that you can find out
anything that you want about a system in principle
by interacting with it with something that changes
anything about it by an arbitrarily small amount.
For example,
you want to locate the location
of a particle in classical physics.
How do you do it?
You shine some light on it.
You shine some light on it,
and you make an image.
Of course,
you have to use light which is small
enough wavelength that it can resolve the object.
This is true,
but there's no limit to how weak a
light signal can be at a given wavelength.
You can make the light signal as weak as you
like so that it carries as little energy as you like.
As little momentum as you like.
Let it interact with the thing you're interested in.
Form an image,
and then after that image has been formed,
it can be magnified.
Not magnified in the sense of making it bigger,
but what's the right word for amplified?
It can be amplified.
And so the experiment itself can be arbitrarily gentle and still
find out anything you might want to know about the system.
The result of that is an experiment can always
be done which has no effect whatever on future experiments,
on subsequent experiments done,
for example,
right afterwards.
That's classical physics.
Quantum physics is not like that.
Quantum physics is such
that experiments inevitably change systems.
Any experiment to measure
something will change something else.
It's almost as though the experiment to measure coins
was such that every time I looked at the coin,
the coin jumped up in
the air and randomly flipped itself.
We know that doesn't happen,
and we can measure the state
of the coin gently without changing it.
Quantum mechanics,
not so clear.
Well,
it is clear.
It's clear that that cannot be done.
Okay,
but let's,
we're going to talk a little bit.
Before we move on to more about vector space,
and operators,
and the mathematics of quantum theory,
I want to talk a little
more about the logic of it,
and what way logic in quantum mechanics
is different than logic in classical physics.
Let's go back to our spin and our apparatus.
The spin is a,
I'll draw it as a little arrow.
Whether it truly corresponds to anything that looks
like a classical arrow or not is irrelevant.
We have to draw it on a blackboard,
and anything I draw on the blackboard will be classical.
Just because ink and pens are classical,
or approximately classical.
And an apparatus.
The apparatus is a window that has
a number that comes out of it.
The number appears in the window,
tells you the result of the experiment.
And it also happens to have a direction
in it which tells you which side is up.
How to orient it.
In fact,
it might have a whole set of three axes
that tell you how to orient it.
But that's not important.
Just the up axis is what's important.
And when the apparatus is pointing up,
the only,
in fact no matter what
direction the apparatus is pointing in,
when it interacts with the spin,
it produces a number in the window,
and that number in the window
is either plus one or minus one.
No matter what direction the apparatus is pointing in,
and no matter what has happened to the spin beforehand.
When the apparatus is pointing up,
we will say that what it has
measured is the z component of spin.
Let's put some axes in here.
Z up,
x to the right,
and y out of the blackboard.
And when the apparatus is pointing up,
we'll say that it produces an experimental number
which measures the z component of the spin.
Now is that particularly interesting to
think of it as having a directionality?
When we say it's a z component of the spin,
we're imagining that this object here
has a sense of directionality to it.
How can we test if it has a direction,
a sense of directionality to it?
Well,
we can prepare the spin
in a state of what we think is pointing up
by simply letting it interact with the apparatus.
And when the apparatus appears with
a plus one sign in it,
we'll say,
uh-huh,
the spin is up.
If we do it again with the same apparatus
pointing in the same direction with the same spin,
we'll get up again,
and up again,
and up again.
In that sense,
quantum mechanics allows for reproducible experiments.
If you measure the same thing several
times in a row with the same apparatus,
you will get the same answer over and over.
So things are not that weird.
And that's awfully important,
because we have to have some
concept of reproducibility of experimental results
in order to make any sense out of things.
So this is a good thing.
When you measure something,
and you measure it again and again and again,
you get the same answer.
Yeah?
So how does that fit
in with what you just said?
We're going to come to it.
Well,
I didn't say that experiments are necessarily so ungentle
that when you measure anything,
you affect everything.
The answer is you affect some things.
In this case,
when you measure something,
you don't affect that same thing.
If you measure it again,
the same thing again,
you'll get the same answer.
Okay,
now,
you could then say,
all right,
now that I have detected that the spin is up,
let me turn the apparatus completely over and point down.
If this were a thermometer measuring the temperature,
I don't think we would expect
it to measure minus the temperature
if we turned it over,
right?
No.
Not if it was any kind of decent thermometer.
So we would therefore then say that the
temperature does not have a sense of orientation.
Certainly not in this sense.
On the other hand,
if this is a true spin,
and we turn the apparatus over,
if initially the apparatus told us
that the spin was plus one,
after we've turned it over and do the experiment again,
it will register minus one.
So it seems to indicate that
there is a sense of directionality.
And of course,
yeah.
The same thing is true no matter
what direction we hold the apparatus in.
If we hold the apparatus in the horizontal direction,
and come along and detect a
spin that we know nothing about,
we have not yet made a measurement on it.
Maybe somebody else has made a measurement on it.
Maybe some agent unavailable to us,
who some secret person has done something to that spin,
but we don't care,
we don't know about it.
We come in with our
detector and we make a measurement.
What will we measure?
Again,
we will measure plus one or minus one.
And if we're beginning to think of this
thing as having a sense of direction to it,
we might say that what we're measuring
now is this x component of the spin.
Whereas previously,
we were measuring the z component of the spin.
Let's give them names.
The sigma z,
which is the component of
the spin along the vertical axis.
At the moment yet,
I'm not asking you to
think that this notion of component
is the same as the
notion of component in classical physics.
It's just a name for the moment.
And sigma z,
whenever it's measured,
is plus or minus one.
The same thing happens when we
turn the apparatus on its side,
and we measure the same procedure.
We measure something that we can now call sigma x.
And sigma x is always plus or minus one.
And the same thing if we turn
the apparatus around so that it's facing frontward.
In fact,
no matter what direction we orient the apparatus,
it always gives us plus or minus one.
This would be a little bit strange,
more than a little bit,
if this object really were a classical vector,
a little vector,
perhaps a vector of unit length.
If it were a vector of unit length,
and this detector were really measuring the
component of spin along its own axis,
there is no way that it
would just give plus or minus one.
Components of vectors,
even if the vector is
required to have exactly unit length,
here's a vector with exactly unit length,
a pointer,
a three vector,
a vector of exactly unit length.
If we turn it and do other things with it,
the x component or the z component can
be any number between minus one and one.
So this is a funny vector
if it's a vector at all.
But still it does seem
to have a sense of orientation.
The results of experiments do seem
to change when you rotate detectors.
In particular,
if you begin by orienting
the spin along the z axis,
in the up direction,
let's call this up,
that means sigma z is equal to plus one,
and then rotate the apparatus,
detect it again,
you won't necessarily get plus one.
In fact,
you may get plus one or you
may get minus one with equal probability.
You could do the experiment
over and over and over again.
Half the times you would
get sigma x equals plus one,
half the times you would
get sigma x equals minus one,
even though you knew sigma z
was exactly plus one in each case.
So something's funny,
but what is true is that the
average value of sigma x will be one,
sorry,
will be zero if the initial starting point was
a spin that was up along the z axis.
Same for the y axis.
If the initial value of the spin was
prepared to be up along the z axis,
and you rotate the apparatus into the y orientation,
again,
you'll have equal probability.
And so the average value
of sigma y will be zero.
You can even go beyond that.
You can say,
let's start with the apparatus,
not vertical,
but let's start with the apparatus along the x direction.
Use it to prepare the spin.
So that it's known to be
pointing horizontal along the x direction,
in other words,
sigma x is equal to plus one,
and then do a y or z experiment.
Always,
we will get random but
equal probabilities for up and down.
Or plus and minus one.
You go a little bit further.
Now of course,
I am quoting what would be the results
of experiments on spins.
I've never done such an experiment.
I don't think I could.
But I have no doubt that if
I had the skill to do it,
this is what would happen.
What?
Suppose we start out and we
have not prepared the spin at all.
Doesn't matter.
Okay,
go ahead.
So it could be up or
down or x or y or z.
We don't know what it's past.
We don't know what it is.
Right.
And we set it up so that the
apparatus is on its side along the x axis.
Okay.
And we do lots of measurements.
What's going on?
Well,
we first do one measurement before we do anything else.
Yeah,
let me come back for a second.
Let me come back a second.
Okay.
You're right.
We want to do a lot of experiments
and a lot of measurements and quantum mechanics.
There are two distinct ways
we could do lots of experiments.
It really doesn't matter which,
which we do.
We could imagine having a log of,
a large number of identical spins prepared at the beginning,
however they were prepared.
And we can do experiments
on a large number of them.
Or we can do repeated experiments on the same spin.
To a large extent it
doesn't matter which we're talking about.
And I'll tell you when it matters.
But at the moment all
we're talking about is one spin.
You said start the apparatus horizontal,
stick the spin into it,
and detect what you get.
What you get will either
be plus one or minus one.
Okay?
You could then take the spin out of there.
Give it to your friend
who does some magic with spins.
You don't know what it is.
You don't know what the hell he does with it.
He flips it around,
juggles it,
puts it in his pocket,
takes it out,
and gives it back to you,
and tells you to do it again.
Again,
you'll get plus one or minus one.
It may be that he did nothing,
in which case the second time you'll get
the same answer you got the first time.
Or it may have been that he turned it over,
in which case you'll get the opposite answer.
But whatever you get,
it will be plus one or minus one.
Okay.
Then if you do a repeated experiment
knowing that nothing else was
done to the spin in between,
you'll get the same answer
if you do the same experiment.
Okay?
That's,
uh...
Good.
Okay,
so let's be a little more general.
Let's suppose that we orient the
axis of the detector in any direction.
So let's make a notation for a direction.
A unit three vector.
A unit three vector...
Unit vectors in three-dimensional space
are always indicated by putting a
little hat on top of the symbol.
So this is a unit vector along a particular axis.
We start with our detector
along the axis M,
not horizontal,
not vertical,
not in or out,
but just catty-cornered in some...
some complicated way.
There's M.
And...
uh...
We start with the spin.
Let's start with the spin
previously having been oriented or prepared
along a different axis,
the N axis.
How do we do that?
Well,
I should have gone a little slower.
We start with the detector along the N axis.
Do an experiment and discover that along the N axis
the spin comes up plus one.
Then we rotate the apparatus into the M direction,
and we do another experiment on the same spin.
It will either come up plus one
or minus one along the M axis,
never in between,
but the average value of the
spin along the M axis here
will not be one.
It will not be minus one.
What will it be?
It will be the cosine of
the angle between M and N.
In other words,
the component of M along N.
How do we write that?
Let's write that.
Let's write a formula for that.
The symbol for averages in quantum mechanics
are a pair of angular brackets like this.
This one is called a bra,
this one is called a ket,
and the whole thing makes a braket,
which is British law.
British for bracket.
Okay?
The average value of sigma M,
knowing that it was originally
oriented along the N direction
and measured along the M direction,
is the cosine of the angle between N and M,
which can also be written as
N dot M,
the ordinary dot product of the vectors,
or just the component of N along M.
The spin was oriented in the N direction,
you measured it along the M direction,
and the answer is plus or minus one,
but on the average,
it's what a classical physicist might have expected
if he measured the component of a spin
which is oriented in one
direction along some other direction.
This is exactly the component of M along N.
Alright,
so,
if you do the experiment many,
many times
and collect averages,
it seems,
in fact,
that the average quantities do behave like vectors,
or like three vectors.
But the individual experiments are very resistant
to giving any answer other than plus or minus one.
Okay,
so this now...
The apparatus doesn't know how to give any answer
other than plus or minus one.
It doesn't know how to give any.
You might try to build another apparatus that does better,
but it won't do better.
Make sure I understand the setup here.
The setup is that you prepare the...
The spin along the N axis.
And then you measure it along the M axis.
Right.
And you get a random answer,
but random biased.
Biased in such a way that the...
that the average is N dot M.
That,
for example,
would mean
that if N and M were the same direction,
that you didn't rotate it at all,
what is N dot M in that case?
One.
Alright.
And that would just be an indication
that you got the same answer if N was up,
and you did the experiment,
you'd get it up and up and up
over and over and over again.
Okay.
Quick question.
Wouldn't it be more...
I want to be very rigorous here.
Wouldn't it be more accurate to say
the expected value would be N times N
rather than the average?
No.
My friend Murray Gilman loves to say
the expected value.
It is not the expected value.
Why not?
If I gave you a probability distribution
which looked like this,
what would be the expected value
that you would have?
The least expected value
would be the one right in the middle,
but the average value would be
the one right in the middle.
Okay?
Expected values and average values
are very different in general.
And this is the average value.
The average,
if you average the quantity
that you get in the standard sense of averaging,
standard average,
it's also called the expectation value.
But again,
that's a misnomer.
It's not the value that you expect necessarily.
I just want to make
sure I'm thinking about this right.
The spin,
the only thing we know about the spin
is that when we measure,
we get plus one or minus one.
Right.
Really that tall...
Well,
that's all we know
until we start doing a lot of experiments.
The constant z component of this and that,
that all has to do with results from the apparatus.
That's right.
It has nothing to do with the thing,
I mean,
at least not in order.
Well,
there are different experiments
that you can do on the spin.
The results of those experiments can be used,
or the particular experiment you do
can be used to label
what it is that you measured.
I guess what...
I guess the point I'm trying to make is
at one point you were drawing a spin
and it's having an arrow either up or down,
and that seemed to be sort of prejudiced.
It's either plus one or minus one,
whatever that means,
we don't know.
There's no geometric meaning to it.
Yeah,
that's right.
There's no geometric meaning to it,
obviously,
to begin with.
But we did discover that by turning this thing over,
we always get the opposite sign.
Well,
that's starting to tell us there's some difference
between the apparatus up and the apparatus down.
It's not like a thermometer measuring temperature.
There's some notion there that it's different
to be up and down.
And then if we turn it on its side,
we find out that in
some sense it really does behave
on the average like a vector.
On the average.
But it is what it is.
But that vector changes depending on how it's been prepared.
In other words,
when you prepare it,
you may have something with an x component
if you've got the apparatus one way,
but if you prepare it with the apparatus another way,
it may have a z component.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
Okay.
But it is what it is,
and I've told you the facts.
The facts are,
if you first prepare
by putting your apparatus along one direction,
and then measure with your apparatus
along the other direction,
the average value of the
result will be n dot m,
but every single event will be
a plus one or a minus one.
Nothing left to say.
Say it anyway.
But something slightly different is that if n and m
are along the same direction or opposite direction,
then it isn't just an average.
It repeats itself.
Yeah.
Whereas if it's any of the others,
it's an average.
Yeah.
Right.
It's still an average,
but it's different.
Right.
But if a number,
or a result,
can only be plus or minus one,
and the average is plus one,
it means every event was plus one.
Okay.
Right.
Let's talk about logic a little bit.
Our problem with quantum mechanics
is that logic,
the logic of quantum systems,
is different
than the logic of classical systems.
But our brains are classical systems
and incapable of thinking in quantum logic.
Nevertheless,
we can get a glimmering
of what quantum logic is like
by thinking about these experiments.
We could either talk about the calculus of propositions
or the nature of the states of a system.
The space of states of a system.
Let's start with the space of states of a system.
The space of states of a system,
and think classically for a moment,
they're a set.
And they're a set of possible states.
Here they are.
Heads,
tails,
six,
five,
four,
three,
two,
one for the die.
Particle on a line
would have an infinite number of possible states,
but the states form a set of some type.
A proposition,
about the states of the system,
is basically a subset.
It's a subset of states
for which the proposition is true.
Okay?
So,
for the die,
my proposition is the die shows an even face.
That's a proposition,
and it's true for half the states of the die,
and so it corresponds to a subset,
two,
four,
and six.
There's the contradiction.
The victory statement,
the not statement,
not the die shows an even face,
which is obviously equivalent to the statement
the die shows an odd face.
And so,
in classical logic,
the not of a statement,
the not means the contradiction of the statement,
if this is the statement,
meaning to say it's true for
all the subset of states in here,
the not statement is the statement,
and the not is the complement,
or the collection of things which are not in there.
Okay,
let's go to our spin.
Proposition.
The spin is up along the z-axis.
What's the not of that?
The not of that is if
we measure the spin along the z-axis,
we get something else other than one.
The only other possibility is minus one,
so spin equal minus one along the z-axis,
is the not statement of the
spin is up along the z-axis.
So,
logic makes some sense,
but we begin to find very peculiar differences
when we start talking about the operations of combining
propositions through the use of and and or.
And and or are different in quantum mechanics
than they are in classical mechanics.
I want to lay that out.
It's so interesting and so rarely explained
that I sort of like to explain it.
Yeah?
I may be digging in what's not there,
and if I am,
just correct me.
In the classical example,
like with guys,
the universal set is finite
in terms of the number of elements in it.
Number of states in it.
And the inverse of that.
And then you jump to the quantum example,
and it seems like that would be infinite
because it's all the possible times.
Does that make a difference?
The all possible what?
All the possible experiments that
you could do is not limited.
Yeah,
okay.
You're getting at something important,
which we're going to get to.
It's clear that in some sense,
the number of states of this spin is finite.
It's just up or down if
we measure it along the z-axis.
On the other hand,
it also looks like we can take
and tilt our apparatus in any direction
and prepare the state in any oriented along any direction.
So it looks like there's an infinite ambiguity
in the state of a system.
This is the whole point of trying to understand
the states of systems,
to understand the connection
between the continuously different direction
that the electron could point in
and the fact that any time
we measure it along a given axis,
it's only up or down.
But we'll come to it.
It's a good question,
but we'll come to it.
Okay,
let's talk about calculus of propositions.
If I give you two propositions,
A and B,
I can form two combinations of them,
A or B,
and A and B.
Let's just see what that means in terms of sets.
If we have two propositions,
this one is A,
this one is B,
then A and B,
means the set of states
which belong both to A and to B.
So it's the intersection
of the set A and the set B,
called logically the intersection
or set theoretically the intersection,
is basically the AND operation.
This point is in A and it's in B.
Okay,
that's straightforward.
And given any two propositions,
you can always form the,
oh,
and,
or another way to say it,
the right way to say it,
is this is the set of points in here
for which the proposition A and B is true.
A and B is true in here
and it is true nowhere else.
Okay,
what about,
what about these two subsets?
A and B.
A and B is still a proposition,
but it's always false.
There is no,
there is no state for
which A and B is true.
All right,
so there are A's and B's
that you can put together.
I mean,
my friend Sanjay over here is,
weighs 600 pounds,
and my friend,
that's not a good one.
There are combinations for which A and B
is always false,
obviously.
All right.
In particular,
if you take A and not A,
it's always false.
All right,
but still,
the definition of A and B
is the intersection,
and it's true
for all the states in the intersection.
OR is a little more complicated,
or at least there are two versions of OR.
There is the exclusive OR,
and the inclusive OR.
In the English language,
we usually,
when we use the word OR,
we usually mean the exclusive OR.
When we say that,
I am Jewish and I am Catholic,
I ordinarily mean that I can't be both.
All right,
that I can't be both.
And so the usual OR
is the exclusive OR,
the one you normally think about.
But in logic,
the term OR
is the inclusive OR.
It means A,
it's true if A is true,
it's true if B is true,
and it's true if both of them are true.
It's the inclusive OR.
So,
I can
correctly say
I am a physicist
and I am a father.
That's true.
But I can also say I am a physicist
or I am a father,
and it is also true.
Why?
Because both of them are true.
So that's the inclusive OR.
Inclusive OR
corresponds to the union of two sets.
If I have A and I have B,
then the inclusive OR
is everything in both sets
or either set.
Okay,
anything,
not in both sets,
anything in either set or in both sets.
The exclusive OR
would correspond to things in one set,
or in two sets.
But not the other set.
The exclusive OR includes
we will always,
whenever I speak of the OR,
I always mean the inclusive OR.
Okay,
so that's AND and OR.
What else can you say about them?
Not very much.
What?
Plus or minus sign up.
Yeah,
we're going to now use that concept
to try to formulate a
set of AND and OR statements
about the spin
and then ask how would you verify them.
How would you verify them?
How would you verify them
and does it mean anything to verify them?
Okay,
so let's take the two propositions,
A and B,
to be
sigma z
is equal to plus one
plus one
and sigma x,
this is A
and this is B.
Sigma x is equal to plus one.
They're both propositions.
We would know how to check either one of them.
If we wanted to check sigma A,
so the first A,
we would turn our apparatus vertically upward
and measure the spin.
We would check it.
It's either true or false.
If we wanted to find out
if B was true or false,
we would turn the apparatus on its side.
In classical logic,
if there are two propositions,
you can form the combination A or B.
Let's start with A or B.
So we'll take A or B.
And let's think about checking its truth value.
Is it true or is it not?
Alright,
so we'll design an experiment to try to...
Oh,
and let's go back a step.
Let's imagine the hidden ghost in the works.
Has previously,
unknown to us,
has originally oriented the spin upward along the z-axis.
He knows,
we don't.
As far as we know,
we know nothing.
But the ghost in the works
has oriented the spin vertically upward.
Just to...
And it doesn't...
This doesn't matter,
but we could start that way.
So the spin is upward.
And let's check whether A or B is true.
How do we begin?
Let's begin by...
By measuring the spin along the z-axis.
We put our detector,
or our apparatus,
in the vertical direction.
And we measure.
What do we get?
We get plus one.
We get plus one because the ghost in the
works has made it a point to begin with.
We don't have to go any further.
A or B is true.
A or B includes the possibility
that both A and B are true,
but all it requires to be true
is that one of them is true.
And we've just discovered that A is true.
So A or B is definitely true.
But now let's do the experiment in another way,
in an order which would not
matter if we were doing classical physics.
And the reason it doesn't
matter when we do classical physics
is when we do an experiment that has no
necessary effect on the outcome of a later experiment,
if the experiment is gentle enough.
So let's do the experiment in the opposite order.
Instead of first finding out whether A is true,
let's first ask if B is true.
And then we'll come back
and ask if A is true.
Alright,
secretly the spin is pointing up in the Z direction.
So the ghost knows that.
But we don't.
And so we come along knowing nothing about the spin
and say,
why should I measure A first?
Let's first measure B.
Let's first measure A.
Let's measure the X component of the spin.
And what do we get?
We get either plus one or minus one.
We get plus one or minus one.
With a 50% probability.
So there's a 50% probability that B is plus one.
But if B is not plus one,
it doesn't mean that A or B is wrong.
We still have the chance that when we measure A,
it'll be plus one.
Okay.
But the problem is that in
measuring B the first time around,
we orient,
we prepare B along the X axis.
Whatever we get,
whether it's this way or this way,
we have prepared that spin along the X axis.
What will the next experiment give when
we measure it along the Z axis?
50% probability of being up,
and 50% probability of down.
That means we have a 25% probability of finding
both that sigma X was equal to minus one
and sigma Z is equal to minus one.
We have a 50% probability in the first
experiment that sigma X was not equal to one.
And then in the next experiment,
we have another 50% probability on top of that.
That sigma Z was not equal to one.
So we have a net probability of one
quarter that both A and B were false.
When we did the experiment in one order.
When we do the experiment in the other order,
it is certain that A or B is right.
Why?
Because A is right.
So,
what is true in classical physics,
that the idea of A or B is symmetrical,
symmetrical between A and B,
the idea of the or statement,
A or B,
if A or B is true,
then B or A is true.
And we find that in quantum mechanics,
the concept of A or B at best
can only be defined in a
way that depends on the order
in which you determine A or B.
I would say that the
two propositions are incompletely specified
in the quantum mechanical case,
because you have to give the order,
right?
It isn't like the particle has a certain X spin,
independent of how you handle it,
right?
Would you say that's right?
Yeah,
I would.
But,
I would also say that any attempt
to think of a logic of experiments
will be different than quantum mechanics.
What is the hierarchy between A and B?
Why,
the what?
Hierarchy.
What hierarchy?
In other words,
A and B,
if you measure A,
then you're certain of B,
if you measure B,
then you aren't certain of A,
but you're certain of B.
No,
no,
let's go back.
I said the ghost in
the woodwork has made the spin
to be pointing up along the Z axis.
That's a,
we don't know that,
but it's true.
Okay?
Then,
if we're going to do the same thing
if we measure sigma Z first,
under those circumstances,
we will surely find that A or B is true.
But if we measure under the same circumstances,
the same degree of lack of presence of knowledge,
we measure B first,
we find out that there's a
25% chance that A or B,
this composite statement here,
is false.
So,
a question,
the operation A or B,
the result is now going to be a probability,
it's going to be 0.25 instead of 0.1.
Well,
not only that,
but you have to specify
which order you determine A and B.
Right.
So that's in itself an element of something new
that the OR statement does not unify two statements
into a symmetrical,
in a symmetrical way.
Question?
I'm confused when we,
the thing has been prepared so that it's up,
we don't know if it's been prepared.
No.
We then...
That doesn't,
that didn't matter.
Just to simplify the story,
I said that.
It wouldn't have mattered to her.
But we then do the experiment,
we do B,
because by turning the machine,
the apparatus on its side,
and I thought what you'd said is,
if we now do this multiple times,
we'll get an average.
Yeah,
but we're not doing it,
we're trying to find out...
But you're saying we're going to prepare,
what you're saying is when we do that first measurement
on its side,
we're preparing the spin again.
And that would say then,
then from then on,
we should always get plus one if we prepare it.
Plus one for sigma X,
but then if we do sigma Z,
we'll get a random answer.
Measuring one,
the random answer...
So we're going to get a,
we're going to get a,
we're going to get a random answer for...
Sigma Z.
The first measurement of sigma X.
Yeah.
Yes.
Think about it.
I can't stop the class to...
Okay.
Question.
If we have a measurement
device to measure two different particles,
and...
Why have you gotten,
why have you jumped to two particles?
I was just wondering,
the act of measurement,
does it inductively spread backwards?
What?
I don't know.
That was all review.
All right,
the next thing which I was going to review,
but I'm not going to because it took too long,
is vector spaces.
I'll just remind you real quickly,
vector spaces are sets of elements.
You can add elements.
This is not something you would do with sets.
You can add two sets,
of course,
to make a bigger set,
but there's no natural single element,
which is the sum of two elements.
So the elements of set theory,
namely the basic individual objects,
are not things that you
can add and make new elements.
The space of states of a
quantum system is a linear vector space,
and that means given any two states,
you can add them in
some sense and make another state.
And that's what we're going to explore.
This logic,
this peculiar logic,
and this peculiar distortion of logic,
turns out to be the logic of vector spaces.
It's a logic which is embedded
in the structure of vector spaces
in a very neat and tidy way,
and that's why,
ultimately,
why vector spaces are important.
Okay,
so let's just remember vectors
are things that you can add,
if there are two vectors,
A and B,
you can add them,
you can multiply them by complex numbers.
Every vector has a dual vector,
which is kind of its complex conjugate.
If we call these objects ket vectors,
because they are the second half of a bra ket,
then the ket,
the bra vectors,
which are in one-to-one correspondence,
which are,
for every ket vector,
there is a bra vector,
but its status is that of a complex conjugate,
so there's two dual vector spaces,
and you can take inner products of vectors,
a bra vector with a ket vector.
So,
the bra vector and the
ket vector can be combined together,
it gives a complex number.
The inner product is a complex number,
and it satisfies that it
is equal to the complex conjugate,
complex conjugate of the opposite order.
So when you take a complex
vector in a complex vector space,
and you take the inner product,
if you interchange the two vectors,
then that's equivalent to complex conjugation.
That's pretty much what you need to know.
That allows you to define,
given the idea of an inner product,
that allows you to define the
notion of the length of a vector.
We usually don't think about the length of a vector,
we usually think about the square
of the length of the vector.
And the square of the length of a vector,
let's say the vector is a,
is the inner product with its own conjugate,
or with its own dual.
Usually we say it's the inner product with itself,
but that's a sort of slight abuse of fact,
of terminology.
And this is always real.
The reason it's always real,
is because if we interchange A and A,
we just get back to the same thing,
but this tells us that the
inner product of A and A
is its own complex conjugate.
Being its own complex conjugate,
it's real.
It's also positive,
that's easy to prove.
And it can be thought of as
the square of the length of a vector.
It's analogous to,
closely analogous to,
the dot product of a three vector with itself.
If A and B were three vectors,
then we wouldn't distinguish the bra and the ket,
but we would write that
A dot B is the dot product between two vectors,
analogous to this.
And we would also write that A dot A
was the square of the length of A.
Okay?
So,
the inner product of a vector with itself
can be thought of as the
square of the length of the vector.
And finally,
there is the notion of orthogonality.
Two vectors are orthogonal
when their inner product is zero.
Orthogonal.
Same definition as for dot product.
When the dot product between two vectors is zero,
those vectors are orthogonal.
Those are the definitions that
we need for a vector space.
The other definition is the
definition of the dimensionality of the vector space.
How many dimensions does a vector space have?
And the way to decide that
is by asking what's the maximum number of orthogonal vectors
that you can find in the vector space.
For ordinary vectors,
let's say in two,
three,
four dimensions,
this is obvious.
In two dimensions,
I can pick a vector.
Just pick any vector.
Make it a unit vector just by shrinking its length
until it's of unit length.
And then I look around and
I see if I can find
another orthogonal vector to it.
Yeah,
in fact I can find two.
One point's this way and one point's that way,
but that's not an important distinction.
We find one other direction,
or one other vector,
apart from a numerical multiple.
Apart from a numerical multiple,
there is one other vector which is orthogonal to it.
And so there are two mutually,
the maximum number of mutually orthogonal vectors
that you can find is two.
If you go to three directions,
you can find a third one,
but no more.
Try to find a fourth one,
and you run out of directions.
So,
three dimensional space has three
mutually orthogonal vectors.
Four dimensional space has four,
and so forth.
And the same thing is true of complex vector spaces.
We described a version of complex vector spaces
which were just column vectors.
Alpha one,
alpha two,
alpha three,
dot dot dot.
And they're duals,
which were row vectors,
which were made up out of the complex conjugate variables.
And so once we have a vector,
we can start looking for orthogonal vectors to it.
Vectors which are perpendicular in this sense.
Find another one,
then look for a third one,
look for a fourth one.
However many you find,
you'll eventually run out of directions.
That's the dimensionality of the space.
For the special case
in which there are only two entries here,
it's a two dimensional vector space.
You can only find two mutually orthogonal vectors.
You can find many pairs of mutually orthogonal vectors.
Now just in real space,
there's these,
point them in any direction,
but once you find two of them,
there won't be another one.
Okay,
so we have the idea of mutually orthogonal vectors.
And now we have to state what is the connection
between a vector space and the space of a vector.
The space of possible states of a quantum system.
The quantum system that we're going to deal with
is still this very primitive and simple single spin.
Until we get the handle on that,
we won't want to move to more complicated things.
Is there any description that the orthogonal vectors
have to be perpendicular to each other?
That's what orthogonal means.
Well,
suppose you have a cube,
and then you sort of tilt it like a parallelogram.
It's still three dimensional,
but the coordinate systems are not perpendicular.
One of them is not.
Perpendicular and orthogonal are synonymous terms.
It is the long term,
but it has a wide angle.
You know what I'm saying?
Perpendicular and orthogonal both mean right angle.
You're confused by something,
and I don't know what it is.
I'm confused by the one.
Yeah,
yeah,
I know you are.
But...
Perpendicular,
orthogonal,
right angles,
they mean all the same things.
I think you think about linearly independent
versus being fully orthogonal.
But if you have a set of linearly independent vectors,
you can extract an orthogonal set out of them.
This is true.
He's not confused.
This is right.
Linearly independent is different than orthogonal.
Orthogonal is linearly independent,
but linearly independent is less strong than orthogonal.
These two vectors like that,
they're linearly independent,
but they're not orthogonal.
Those are orthogonal.
Okay,
let's...
We'll come back.
All right.
The states of a quantum system,
this is a postulate,
form a vector space,
form a complex vector space.
In fact,
the space of the simple system,
we've been discussing,
form a two-dimensional vector space.
Let's write down some vectors.
We know some states.
We know,
for example,
that there is a state
that can be prepared in which
the spin is pointing upward along the z-axis.
We characterize the state by the experiment
that we did to get it in that state.
That experiment...
had the apparatus vertically upward,
and it created a state of the system
which either could have been down or up,
but let's say it's up.
We can label that state in a number of ways.
We can call it up.
We can call it down.
We can call it plus.
We can call it...
Well,
up and down are the same as plus and minus.
We could draw them with little arrows up and down.
What other ways could we...
We could write it as sigma z equals plus one,
and sigma z equals minus one.
They all mean the same thing.
Up,
down,
plus,
minus,
sigma z equals plus one,
sigma z equals minus one,
all the same thing.
All right?
So there are two states that we know about
that we can access by putting the...
or we can prepare by turning our apparatus upward
along the z-axis.
Let's give them names.
These states are vectors in a vector space
according to hypotheses.
And they can be called,
let's say,
up and down.
If it is true that
the vector space is as simple
as just a two-dimensional vector space,
then that means that any vector in that space
can be written as some linear combination
of up and down.
In other words,
every vector
in a two-dimensional space
can be written in terms of two basis vectors,
up and down.
So that's enough to write any state whatever.
Up,
down.
All right,
what about,
though,
the state which is made
by tilting our apparatus along the x-axis?
We get something different.
It's not the same thing.
It's not up,
because up means up along the z-axis.
It's not down,
because down means down along the z-axis.
And we know they're different
because we know the results of experiments
on these two different kinds of states
will in general be different.
So,
we can call those states...
I tend to call them left and right.
There's up and down.
There's right and left.
Those are two other states.
We could draw them this way if we liked.
They also correspond to sigma x equals one
and sigma x equals minus one.
And we could label them if we liked.
Let's label them right and left.
Finally,
we know that if we were to turn our apparatus
so that the apparatus was pointing along the y-axis,
we could access two more states.
I think we call those in and out,
into the blackboard and out of the blackboard.
And so,
there's in and out.
Into the blackboard and out of the blackboard.
And they correspond to sigma
y equals plus or minus one.
We could label them in and out.
All of the logic that I've described to you
and all of the experimental results,
as we will see,
we will not see it immediately,
it took some time to understand all of this,
it is all summarized by a few statements,
but the first of which is
that the space of all states
of that simple system is two-dimensional,
has only two independent states,
which means that these other things can be written
in terms of up and down.
Okay,
so let's go to general linear combinations
of up and down and ask what they mean.
Let's take a vector,
I guess we can call it A,
which is of the form a coefficient,
a complex coefficient alpha one times up,
plus another complex,
another,
I suppose we should call this alpha up.
Alpha up.
Alpha down times down.
The alphas are complex numbers.
In complex vector spaces,
you multiply,
they could be real numbers,
but in general,
they will be complex numbers.
Let us suppose we knew what that meant,
what kind of state this was,
where it came from.
It's a new beast,
it's not up,
it's not down,
somewhere in between.
Next postulate.
The next postulate is that if
we were to measure up and down,
if somebody prepared us an electron
or a spin in this state
and we measured up and down,
we would find probabilities for up and down,
and those probabilities would be
probability for up
is the square of the magnitude of the force.
So if we were to measure up and down,
we would have the magnitude of this coefficient
and probability for down
is equal to alpha star down,
alpha down.
In other words,
it's basically the square of the coefficient
or the square of the component
of A in the directions up and down.
These alphas,
they're essentially the components
of a general vector along the two axes,
up and down.
There's something that I failed to tell you.
It's also a postulate.
There are many,
many postulates,
but you'll see they fit together in a neat package.
There are probably fewer postulates than I'm saying.
I'll bet we can reduce it down to four postulates,
four axioms.
But rather than try to axiomatize it,
we'll just...
do it a little more informally.
What's the relation between up and down?
Are they the negative of each other?
No,
they're orthogonal.
Now,
that's a postulate.
The basic postulate is when things
are measurably different.
When two states are such that you can cleanly
tell the difference between them by an experiment,
they are orthogonal.
Orthogonality literally means they are
sufficiently different that you can,
with a single experiment,
or maybe a few experiments,
tell the difference between them uniquely.
I'll tell you what it
corresponds to in terms of sets.
You might say that two sets are orthogonal
if they don't share any elements.
This is not a standard terminology.
But you might say it anyway.
They're orthogonal if they don't share any elements.
That means they're distinctly different.
There's no chance that an experiment
will confuse the two of them.
An experiment will...
a nice experiment to distinguish them
will not lead to any ambiguity.
The same is true of up and down.
Up is distinctly different than down.
If you measure up,
you'll measure up again and again and again.
And the version of that in quantum mechanics,
or the implication of that in quantum mechanics,
for the vectors,
is that things that correspond to physically
unambiguous different situations
are orthogonal to each other.
So up and down are orthogonal to each other.
What if we have a combination of up and down
with some coefficients?
Then there's a probability to be up
and a probability to be down.
And the probabilities are given by
alpha star alpha,
and alpha star alpha down.
Again,
that's a postulate,
but we'll see in a moment what that corresponds to.
Well,
what's the relation between
the probability for up and the probability for down?
The answer is that if we add them,
we get one.
And therefore,
alpha star alpha plus beta star beta
is equal to one.
Any reasonable state of the system
which has total probability one
over all the different things that can happen
should satisfy that the sum of the probabilities,
of the distinct probabilities,
should add up to one.
And so that says that
alpha star alpha
plus beta star,
not beta,
alpha up up plus
alpha down star alpha down,
did I use beta before?
No,
okay.
Should equal one.
But that's equivalent
to the statement that the
inner product of A with itself
is equal to one.
When we think about...
Prove this.
Prove that alpha star alpha
summed over
up and down
is equal to the inner product of A with itself.
It does follow from the postulates.
It does follow from the postulates
and the assumption
that U and D are perpendicular unit vectors.
U and D are perpendicular unit vectors.
Make that assumption.
They're orthogonal to each other.
They're unit vectors.
If they're not unit vectors,
you can change them until they are unit vectors.
And then you can prove
that the inner product of A with itself,
of a vector with itself,
is just the sums of the squares
or the conjugates times itself.
Okay.
So that's a little thing to prove.
But what does that say?
That says that a physical state
corresponds to a vector in
the vector space of unit length.
A unit vector.
The unit standing for the fact
that the total probability is one.
All right,
so states...
Not only equal vectors in a vector space,
but they're unit vectors.
The other term for unit vectors is normalized vectors.
Normalized vectors.
Normalized is another word for unit.
So all physical states,
all states are what you can do to that...
Electrons,
spin,
or anything else,
correspond to unit vectors.
And given any such unit vector,
the probabilities associated with it
are alpha star alpha up
and alpha star alpha down.
So that is a bit of information.
But wait a minute.
What happened to these other vectors,
right and left?
What happened to right and left?
Right and left seem like different states.
But according to the postulate,
right and left must be linear combinations
of up and down.
That's not too surprising,
because if you prepare right or left
and then measure up or down,
you get plus one or minus one.
That's all there is.
Plus one or minus one.
So it's not too surprising
that whatever right or left is,
it's somehow a combination of up and down.
And that statement is buried
in the properties of vectors.
So let's look at the state left.
No,
let's look at the state right.
What do we know about it?
Well,
we know that it must be a combination,
alpha up,
up,
plus alpha down,
down.
We can also write that in
the form of a column vector,
alpha up and alpha down.
Number one.
Number two,
supposing an electron is created
pointing along the right direction,
the x-axis.
What are the probabilities for
it to be up and down?
You remember?
Half.
That means that alpha up star alpha up
must equal a half,
and alpha star down alpha down
must equal a half.
Okay.
Let's make a guess.
The simplest guess would be to put
one over square root of two
and one over square root of two here.
Alpha up is one over square root of two.
If alpha up is one over square root of two,
what's alpha star alpha?
One half.
Okay.
This one's also one half.
Now we could put some other things.
What ambiguity is there?
We could put a minus sign here,
or we could put a
complex coefficient in front of here
without changing the magnitude of it.
We'll come back to that.
We'll come back to what that means.
We'll come back to what that ambiguity means.
But let's take this as a working hypothesis
for what the state right is.
That leaves us with the state left.
What do we know about left?
Well,
right and left are physically distinguishable
by a single experiment.
You can orient your apparatus
along the x direction,
measure sigma x,
and determine unambiguously
whether it corresponds to right or left.
What does that mean about the vectors right and left?
It means they're orthogonal.
Orthogonal and physically measurably distinct
are the same things.
So that tells us that left,
right
should be equal to zero.
Incidentally,
we have assumed that
up,
right,
left,
and left are the same.
Down is equal to zero.
Up,
down,
orthogonal.
By symmetry,
basically.
There's nothing different about the x-axis
than the z-axis.
So if the two vectors up and down are orthogonal,
it stands to reason that the two vectors
left and right must be orthogonal.
Here's right.
Is there a vector that's orthogonal to it?
Yeah.
There is a vector which is orthogonal to it.
What is it?
One over square root of two up
minus one over square root of two down.
Now it's ambiguous whether you put
the minus sign here or here.
Either way will work.
And we'll find out that there's no physical difference
between those two possibilities.
We'll find out later that there's no physics
in the overall sign of a vector.
So here's one which is orthogonal.
How do we check that this is orthogonal to that?
Well,
let's write the row,
let's write the,
here's the column vector
describing right.
Let's write down the row vector,
no,
that's not the column vector.
Here's the column vector.
The column vector describing right is
one over square root of two,
one over square root of two.
That's these two.
What is the row vector describing left?
If we want to take the inner product,
we want to combine the
row vector with the column vector.
So the row vector describing this guy over here
is one over square root of two
minus one over square root of two.
And to take the inner product between them,
you take the product of the first coefficient
times the first coefficient
plus the product of the second one
times the second one.
Standard rule for taking the inner product
between a column vector and a row vector,
you match the first component with the first component,
multiply them.
Second component with the second component,
And go right down through all the components
and add them up.
Okay,
so what's the answer?
One half,
sorry,
one over square root of two
times one over square root of two,
that's a half,
minus one over square root of two
times one over square root of two.
This inner product is zero.
So we found a second vector
which corresponds to right and left,
a candidate,
if you like,
for right and left.
And what's more,
you'll notice that this vector also has the property
that the probability for it to be up and down
is equal to a half
for each one.
Why?
Because the square of this is one half
and the square of the magnitude
of this one is one half.
So we have a nice symmetrical relationship
between left-right and left-left.
between right-right and up-and-down.
Incidentally,
it's kind of interesting,
supposing,
um,
where's my eraser?
Under your paper.
Yeah.
It's kind of interesting.
I've written right and left
in terms of up and down.
I could,
of course,
write up and down
in terms of right and left.
Let's see what we get.
If we add these two equations,
the downs will cancel,
and we'll just get up.
We'll get 2 over square root.
We'll get square root of 2.
That's 2 over the square root of 2 times up
equals right plus left,
and then divide by square root of 2.
And we'll find that down
is equal to right minus left
over square root of 2.
So you see there's a complete reciprocal relationship
between them.
Um,
if we began our experiments
with our apparatus along the x direction,
we might have started,
we might have started with left and right
and come to the conclusion that up and down
are combinations of left and right.
Okay,
that leaves in and out.
What about in and out?
Is there a third pair of vectors,
in and out,
which stand in the middle of the vector,
and in the same relationship
to right and left,
and to left,
to right and left and to up and down
as they stand to each other?
Is there a third combination
which has,
uh,
which is symmetrically defined?
All right,
let's put it up here.
We have up and down,
and they're orthogonal to each other.
We have right and left,
right,
which is equal to one over square root of two.
We can write it as up plus down,
and left,
same thing,
one over square root of two,
times up minus down.
We also have right left equal to zero.
Moreover,
we have something that I'm not going to write,
but I'll say it anyway.
If you start in right,
and you say,
what's the probability for up and down?
It's one half.
If you start with left,
then ask what's the probability for up and down.
It's one half.
What happens if you start with up and down?
What's the probability for right and left?
Well,
it's also one half.
We know that's one half
from the physics of the situation,
but it's also true that
when I rewrite up and down,
in terms of right and left,
the coefficients are also one over square root of two.
So they're nice and symmetrically related to each other.
All right,
so that leaves us with the last possibility,
or the last perpendicular direction,
in and out.
Okay,
so let's try to guess.
It's going to have an up,
and it's going to have
a down,
plus a down.
But there's going to be some coefficients here.
We don't know what those coefficients are yet.
What do we know about the coefficients?
They're complex in general.
In general,
they're complex.
Their modules,
well,
square has to be one half.
The square has to,
the magnitude of this square has to be one half.
We also know that the coefficients here
have to be such that in and out
are perpendicular to each other.
And we also should find that
if we rewrite in and out
in terms of left and right,
the coefficients should also have modulus one half,
just by symmetry.
Turns out that's enough to determine them completely.
I'm not going to prove it.
That's a homework assignment.
It's a nice homework assignment.
Let's see what the requirements are.
The requirements are that in out equals zero,
that both in or out,
when written in terms of up or down,
should have coefficients
whose magnitude is a half,
squared magnitude is a half,
and also when written in terms of left and right,
the same corresponding coefficients here
should have magnitude plus or minus a half.
That is enough to determine
the coefficients in terms of up and down
with a small ambiguity which is not interesting.
I'll tell you later what that ambiguity is.
It has no physics in it.
First of all,
it's the overall sign of the vectors.
That has no physics in it,
as we'll see.
We'll find out.
What is the solution?
The solution is one here and i here
with a square root of two.
We have to put a
one over square root of two
and a one over square root of two.
Out is the same thing
minus i over square root of two down.
Let's write it in terms of column and row vectors.
Should that be an i over square root of two
on the n vector?
Let's say a one at least.
Well,
I have i there.
Is that what you're asking?
I actually had it right.
It was one times i.
Good.
We can write these in terms of column vectors.
Let's write the various column vectors.
Up.
What would you write for up?
Well,
we could write one zero.
Up is just up with no down component.
Down is just zero one.
A one in the down place
and a zero in the up place.
What about right?
That's equal to 1 over square of two
1 over square of two.
Left,
that's equal to
one over square root of two
minus one over square root of two.
And now let's put in,
in is one over square root of two,
i over square root of 2 and write,
sorry,
out is equal to 1 over square root
of 2 minus i over square root of 2.
First question,
is this orthogonal to this?
How do we check?
We take this times the complex conjugate of
this plus this times the complex conjugate of this.
That's the rule for calculating inner products.
We could construct the row vectors,
we don't need to.
Oh,
let's,
no,
we don't need to.
Remember that the row
vectors have complex conjugate entries.
Alright,
but it's easy enough to do just the inner product.
The inner product is the sum of the products.
Of the entries.
Times that complex conjugate.
Alright,
so one of these has to be complex conjugated.
What's the product of this with its complex conjugate?
One half times one,
it's just one half.
So this one times this
one gives you a one half.
And how about this times the complex conjugate of this?
Minus one half.
Minus i over two,
what's the complex conjugate of
i over square root of two?
Minus i over square root of two.
So we have to multiply minus i over square root
of two times another minus i over square root of two,
which gives us minus a half.
i times i is minus one.
So that gives us minus a half.
And if we add them up,
we get zero.
So yes,
these two are orthogonal to each other.
The,
the magnitude of the coefficients here,
the square of the magnitude of the
coefficients are each equal to a half,
which proves that if you're
in the in-state or the out-state,
the probability of being up or down is one half.
How about the probability of being left or right?
How might you figure that out?
Why isn't i times pi equals i squared?
Say it again.
i times i is equal to i squared.
Definition of i is that it's
the square root of minus one.
So i times i is always minus one.
So i is not in.
i is not,
oh sorry,
this,
uh,
this i is not in,
no.
This,
okay.
i
and out
right
and left.
Up.
Up can stay the way it is,
and down.
And now go back throughout all
of the pages and change it.
Not important.
Actually,
we could have changed it more easily.
Just change this i to capital i,
but that would be a bad,
that would be bad form,
bad form.
Okay.
Is there anything about this coordinate system that,
that could imply a left or right-handed coordinate system,
like,
like a cross y equals a?
Very,
very good question.
The answer is yes,
but we'll come to it.
Yes,
that's a very,
very good question.
Um,
what is it that's in here
that is telling us that
it's a right-handed coordinate system
rather than a left-handed coordinate system?
And I didn't want to go there yet.
We'll come to it.
We'll come to it when we explore the Pauli matrices.
But,
uh,
for the moment,
we're just,
uh,
we're doing,
we're sort of getting there.
We're guessing away,
bumbling through,
trying to find vectors
which describe,
uh,
various states of the system.
Okay.
This is my proposal,
if you like.
My best guess at the moment
for what the states up,
down,
those,
those are
base,
that's the,
you start with those.
In terms of those,
what right and left are
and what in and out are.
Now,
what you could do,
we saw that you could rewrite
up and down
in terms of left and right.
I showed you how to do that.
And that means you could write
i and o
in terms of left and right.
You could check what the coefficients are.
I hesitate to do it
because I'm sure I'll bumble it.
On the other hand,
I'm tempted to do it
because I'm sure I'll get it right.
I'll take one shot at it.
One shot,
and if it doesn't work out...
Okay.
Up is left plus right.
Down is left minus right.
With a square root of two.
So,
let's see if we can
figure out what in is first.
Let's just do in.
In is one over the square root of two
times up.
What did I say up was?
Up I said was left plus...
is
left plus right
but with another one over the square root of two.
So that gives me a one half.
That's left over two
plus right over two.
That's scary.
And then plus i
over square root of two
times down.
Anybody remember what down was?
Left minus right over the square root of two.
So that gives me another...
That will give me
left
right
over another square root of two
minus left
over another square root of two.
Alright.
So the whole thing looks like...
alright.
That's the term as two one halfs.
The second term.
No,
just go back.
That one right there.
You got half and then you got two.
Yeah.
And this can just be a one half
with a square root of two
and a square root of...
and that's gone away,
right?
Do I have it right?
Good.
Okay,
so what do we get?
We get a coefficient times left.
Alright,
so here we are.
I is equal to one half
minus I...
one minus I over two,
is that right?
One minus I over two times left
plus...
I think it's one plus I over two times right?
You mean like O instead of I there?
Here?
Are we doing I or O?
I think we're doing I.
But I'm not sure.
It doesn't matter.
I think we were doing this one.
Up is left plus right
and down is left minus right
with the same I.
So I think that's right.
Okay.
Now,
what's the magnitude
of the two coefficients here
then times their complex conjugates?
Let's check that.
I don't see any square
roots of two in this thing.
Do you see any square roots of two in here?
You might have expected some square roots of two,
huh?
Nevertheless,
I maintain that if you
take this times its complex conjugates,
I hope to God it's true,
I maintain that if you
take this times its complex conjugate,
you will get one half.
Let's check it.
It's one minus I times one plus I
over two times two is four.
One minus I times one plus I,
oh praise the Lord,
is two.
It's two over four
which is equal to one half.
In other words,
this coefficient here,
although it doesn't contain any explicit square root of two,
it times its complex conjugate
is equal to one over two.
So the magnitude
of this complex number here
is one over the square root of two.
It's written in a form
that you don't see any explicit
one over square roots of two,
but
the magnitude of this is
one over square root of two
and so is the magnitude of this.
The implication of this is that
if you started in the state I
into the blackboard
and instead of measuring up or down
you measured left or right
the probability would be a half.
Alright?
So we found
three mutually related
they're not orthogonal to each other
up and down are not orthogonal to left and right
and that's a half.
So we found
up and down are not orthogonal to left and right
and they're orthogonal to each other
but they're not orthogonal in the vertical direction
but
each one
if expanded
in any of the others
would have coefficients whose magnitude
was one over the square root of two.
So they're symmetrically related
in that sense
and
what this means
in effect
is that if you start with any one of them
and measure the other component
if you start with up or down
and measure sigma x or sigma y
you'll get
probability a half.
No matter what you start with
any one of these three combinations
any one of these six combinations
and measure a perpendicular combination
you'll always get probability
plus or minus a half.
Now I've put in here some
some postulate about
what probabilities are without telling you
but
I think we're coming along pretty well
we have some mathematics here
which is telling us
that these three
collections of pairs of vectors
are nicely symmetrically
related to each other
and
that
well that's the most important fact
yes
we have
yeah
yes Kevin
no no we don't have to
this is a thought
I'm sorry
three sets of
three bases
yeah
three bases at angles with respect to each other
and so why three?
that's a good question
the question is could we find
oh excellent question
could we find another
double
let's call it
big and little
no we already used little
fat and skinny
yeah
can we find another
pair
such that fat is orthogonal
to skinny
and the inner
product that's what it
actually came down to or that the
expansion coefficients
of each one
in terms of the other
kind of bases are always
equal to one over square root of two or always
one half in magnitude
the answer is no
there is no third
or no fourth combination
that's in the same relationship
now that's not obvious
that's not the
it is the fact that we
live in a three dimensional world
it's exactly
the fact that we live in a three dimensional world
right
it's exactly the fact
it's the statement that the three dimensions
of space can be represented
in two dimensions
in two dimensional
vector space terms
alright let me tell you something else
which is true
if I give you a
column vector
let's say a column vector
alpha one alpha two
or just the coefficients
of expansion
alpha up and alpha down
if you like
the question is
how much freedom
is there in the space
is there in the alphas
such that it doesn't change
the physical nature of the state
how much freedom
does every combination of
alpha up and alpha down
correspond to a different state
the answer is no
first of all
the total probability
has to add up to one
so that's one constraint right there
alpha up star alpha up
plus alpha down star
alpha down
is equal to one
there's another fact
that we have not got to yet
but we will find
that every physically observable
quantity
always associated
with a state
always involves an alpha
times a complex conjugate alpha
we will find that
we'll find that it's
we won't put it in
it will emerge as one of the
consequences of the postulates
so what it says
is that if you multiply
both of the alphas here
by the same
phase factor
does everybody know what a phase factor is
a phase factor is
a complex number of the form
e to the i theta
of unit length
it doesn't change the magnitude
of either coefficient here
that if we multiply
every entry
by the same phase factor
it doesn't affect anything
that means
that if I were to just
give you two complex numbers here
there are two redundant
pieces of information
that really don't have anything to do
with the physical character of the state
the first is the overall magnitude
because the overall magnitude
should always be such
that the sums of the squares of these
add up to one
so that means there's one
call it a constraint if you like
and a redundancy
the redundancy is that
if you multiply both entries
by the same phase factor
here it also doesn't
change the state
so then you could ask
how many independent
variables are there
which characterize the state of the system
of this system
how many of them are there
well let's count
there are two independent
variables if we don't worry
about either of these constraints here
how many things does it take to characterize
two complex numbers
four
four real numbers
right but now one of them
doesn't count
because we have to
satisfy the constraint that the total
length of this is equal to one
one of them doesn't count
but also another one doesn't count
because the overall phase
if we were to multiply everything by the
same phase factor here it also doesn't count
doesn't change the nature of the state
so two of those
four parameters
are irrelevant
to the physical character of the state
how many does that leave over
two
two real numbers
how many numbers does it take
to characterize the direction
of a unit vector
two
what are they called
longitude and latitude
or what are they called
or something like that
just the direction of a vector
can be characterized by two angles
these two
pairs of numbers
are the same
the fact that
that it takes two real
parameters to describe
a two component
vector like this
is closely related to the
fact that it takes two real angles
to describe
the direction of a
three vector in ordinary
three dimensional space
if we would have
added
more components here it would have been more
complicated
so yes there is a deep connection between the
fact very deep connection
between the fact
that we only find three independent
combinations like this
where are they
three independent combinations and that fat and
skinny never
we can't find
fat and skinny basically they won't be there
not without increasing the dimensionality
of the vector space
that is in fact very deeply connected
to three dimensions of space
yeah
if space was nine dimensional
or something like that
we would not be able to represent
the directions of a
little arrow in it quantum mechanically
by two components vectors
we would need more components
yeah
it seems like just physically
you would take three
because two to specify the direction
and then you've got to say whether it's plus one
or minus one
no no no the plus one
plus one and minus one are
inherited the basis
yeah
so how does this scale up if you had
three complex
numbers in the vector space
you mean if you wanted to study some higher
dimensional space oh god we have to figure it out
I don't know the question is how many directions
how many parameters are there to
yeah it's more complicated
that one I'm not going to try now
right
I didn't
I got to tell you
I got really scared when I realized
that we weren't going to get any
square roots of two by doing this
the experiments you've described
agree with this math
and this math is based on
or correlates with
there being two different
dimensions
there being three space
it is yes although what you say is true
if you said there's nine dimensions
would this experiment still agree with
there would be a version of it
it would be more complicated
and you couldn't describe
the spin of a particle by just a thing
with two components like this
it would take more components
what kind of apparatus would you use
spinner theory
yeah
similar things
don't try to
look this is enough
for now understanding
this
if we went to four
dimensional space we would need
four component objects but
but it grows
three to four would be
you said the states
correspond
what about the other
what about negative vectors are they
of any interest here at all
well of course if you add two
unit vectors you can get a non-unit vector
you can
but then the rule for the
states of a system are divided through
divided through by an overall factor until it's normalized
they have the same significance
as probability distributions
which don't sum up to one
you can always go back
and say if somehow
somewhere along the line
I got some answers for probabilities that
added up to something greater than one
well I would just divide through by the total probability
to define normalized probability distributions
so
in intermediate steps of calculations
there might well be
the presence of vectors
which are not normalized
but at the end of the day
the states of the system are normalized vectors
normalized vectors
and
I've got
vectors describing
different orientations of the spin
but we haven't been very rigorous about it
and there's been no
I have made no pretense
of really a mathematical
clear derivation of these things
sort of seat of the pants
guessing to a large extent
the next time we will make some
rigorous postulates
about what these things really mean
and
their relationship
these things
and these things
and what the relationship between them is
the vectors
and the things that you measure
these are the states
but these are the things you measure about them
and the question is what's the connection
between them
okay any more questions about this
are these lectures
tracking the
content in the sequence
of those in the web
I imagine they are but I don't remember
but there's only one way that
I know how to think about
quantum mechanics so I bet they are
and
you know if you're sitting
through this for the third time
that's your problem
believe me I'm sitting through it
through the
now
is that phase factor that we can ignore
yes the answer is yes
is that phase factor
are you doing anything with that
well
mostly
we'll be saying look
it doesn't matter
alright it doesn't matter
the okay
so let's talk about the mathematics of ignoring
something
yeah that's right
yeah
yeah that's
that's true
but
let's just talk about the mathematics
of ignoring things for a minute
alright a point
is zero dimensional right
a circle is one dimensional
there's one parameter
an angle on it but supposing
I tell you that there's no significance
to where you are on that circle
there's no significance whatever
all points on that circle
are equivalent to every other point
then you might say well for all
interesting questions
the circle is just a point
if you can ignore
where you are on the circle
then
there's only one point on the circle
you're either on the circle
if you're on the circle you're on the circle
there's one point
you can say the same thing
about
let's see another example
what's another example?
well let's take this example
if you have a
well what is a complex number?
a complex number is a point on
the plane but if for some
reason the angle
of where you are on the plane doesn't
matter then the only thing that's interesting
is the distance
but now supposing you have two complex
numbers and all I tell you
is that when you have two complex numbers
the thing which doesn't matter
is the sum of their
phases
the sum of their phases,
the sum of their
angles then
there is still one angle left
over which may be important
the difference of the angles
so if I have two complex numbers
and I
tell you for reasons that I haven't specified
yet that the overall
phase which can just be thought of as the
sum of the phase angles
if the sum of the phase angles for whatever
reason plays no role in the
physics of the situation
there is still the difference of angles there
that's exactly
what the case is,
the sum of the angles
the complex
numbers that go into these
entries here is of no physical significance
we counted up
four real parameters
for two complex
numbers,
the overall
magnitude of it doesn't count
because we divide that out
that removes one of them
and then the sum of the angles doesn't
count for whatever reason
that removes another one,
that leaves
you with two
real numbers
and that's in correspondence
with the two real numbers that
it takes to pick a direction
in space
so
there's a lot of subtlety
but nothing very difficult,
the mathematics
is really easy
mathematics of quantum mechanics is
easier than the mathematics of classical
physics
two by two matrices
is very simple
mathematics is
easier,
it's unfamiliar
yeah
there's something that's always been
vaguely unsettling
which I think is at the heart of all this
the idea that the up and down
are along a single axis
one pointing this way and one pointing that way
but they're orthogonal somehow
well
orthogonal doesn't mean perpendicular
in three dimensional space
it means physically distinguishable
it means unambiguously
distinguishable
left and right are not physically
distinguishable uniquely from up and down
why?
because if you have a thing oriented along
left
and you measure up or down you might get up
so you
think of
I have to think of
two orthogonal axes as being two independent
you could vary independently
yes,
that's right
so here you can vary independently
the probability for up
and down
of course they have to add up to one
right,
they have to add up to one
but ignoring
the question of whether they add up to one
you have the freedom
to independently vary
the coefficient in terms of
u and the coefficient in terms of
d
now the fact that they
have to add up to one is another fact
yeah
don't confuse
orthogonality in the space of states
with orthogonality
in
in three dimensional space
the analog idea
in phase space
um
or in
the configuration space of a classical system
orthogonal
space
the orthogonality of two probability distributions
let's think of
let's suppose you have
phase space
or the configuration space of some classical system
here's the phase space
x and p
and I give you a probability distribution
a simple probability distribution might be
zero everywheres except in some patch
where the probability is uniform
okay
the analog of
orthogonality
between of two distinct
probability distributions
is that they don't overlap
that they're non-overlapping
that there's no ambiguity
and
that's the analog of orthogonality
up and down
don't overlap
if you're up you're not down
and if you're down you're not up
right
so
now if you think about
there is a situation
in which orthogonality
is the same in space
and in the space of states
it's the polarization of photons
the polarization
of photons is a little bit different
and I didn't want to get into it
because it's more complicated
um
but
right
it would have been better if there was a different
word for perpendicularity and
space and orthogonality
in the space of states
different concepts
it's very much what's going on here
that being oriented
along right
um
yeah
can I do an experiment
which can distinguish
between a spin pointing up
and a spin pointing down
yes
you can bring your apparatus over to it
detect it
and if it's up it'll point one
if it's down it'll point minus one
or it'll give a minus one
can you use that apparatus
to tell you uniquely the difference
between a spin pointing along the x-axis
and a spin pointing along the z-axis
what would you do
to tell the difference
well
what would you measure
no matter what you measure
it's not going to uniquely tell you the difference
if you measure sigma
z and you get plus one
that doesn't tell you anything
about sigma x
it doesn't
you could have gotten sigma z equals plus one
because
it was pointing along the z-axis
and you got it with certainty one
or
it was pointing along the x-axis
and with probability a half you got it pointing up
there's no way to tell
there's no way to tell by a single
well defined experiment
whether the spin was pointing
let's say up
or r
what if you measure if
a photon comes off or not
with one experiment
either a photon will or won't come off
and from that you cannot tell uniquely
whether it was
a
no
you can't tell from that
it's exactly the same as measuring the spin
if you get up
in your measurement
it does not tell you whether it was initially up
or it was initially sideways
and with probability a half you got up
okay
so there's no unique single experiment
you can do to distinguish
this from this
there is an experiment that you can do
to distinguish this from this
that's what makes
up and down orthogonal
but down and left not orthogonal
they overlap
they overlap and in fact
the probability that
if you are in left that you measure down
when you measure sigma z
that's a measure of the overlap
between them
alright
the overlap which means
in technical language that they are not orthogonal
so
back back to the hierarchy thing
originally you said
we didn't know that it was programmed
up z
but if we measured up z
and got up we didn't have to measure anything else
if the
what we're trying to do is confirm
the proposition
the spin is up or
the x
the z component of spin is up or
the x component of spin is up
we want to confirm
that's a single proposition it's not two propositions
it's a single proposition
the spin is up or
the spin is up along z
or it's up along x
that's a single proposition
if the first detection
measures the spin up along the z axis
we're finished
alright
and since the setup
was setup beforehand
we know that in that case we would get
the right answer
ok
would it be fair to
summarize that point as saying that
propositions are not commutative
uh
yeah
I mean
actually propositions technically correspond
to projection operators
and projection operators are not commutative
好
That it would be proper to summarize.
I don't know if that summarizes everything about it,
but that certainly summarizes part of that point.
Depends on which order you,
yeah.
So you've cautioned us about trying to visualize,
okay?
So is the sigma along
the z-axis or along the x-axis,
isn't that a visualization that?
It is,
it is,
it is.
That would explain why it doesn't make sense
where you measure it.
Well,
yeah,
yeah.
And then you measure n and it's an extra.
Yeah,
yeah,
no,
it is,
it is a visualization.
Do keep in mind,
though,
this interesting fact
that on the average,
the spins,
if you measure many of them,
many,
many of them,
the average values do behave
like components of a linear system.
So you can't measure them in a single little vector.
In particular,
if you take a large number of these spins
and you make sure that they're all pointing upward,
and then you measure some oblique component of them,
with your apparatus being tilted,
then the average that you get for the oblique component
will just be the projection of the upright vector,
onto the oblique direction,
exactly as if you were
measuring the component of a vector.
So the upshot is,
if you have a large number of them,
in many cases,
you can visualize with classical physics.
After all,
that's what classical physics is.
Classical physics is,
to a large extent,
the approximation of systems which consist of many,
many parts,
which all behave,
simultaneously,
the same way.
I'll try one more question.
Is there any,
looking at the properties
of the model you described,
is there any relation between that
and the notion of gauging variance?
I suppose.
I suppose there is.
You'd have to be more specific than that.
Gauge invariance does have to
do with these phase factors here.
That's why I was referring to them.
Yeah,
it does have to do with them,
but,
but we can't get into that right now.
Actually,
one thing that I find myself getting confused about,
but I think I see it now,
is that,
we're calling it measurement,
and the tendency is
to think of a measurement in the classical sense,
like here comes,
say,
a particle,
and we're going to measure
some property,
but it's not like that,
because we can't really say what the value was
before we did the measurement.
We can only say what it
is after we did the measurement.
But then,
once we measure it,
we can measure it again,
and the same thing again,
and there will be consistency.
I mean,
we put it in a certain state,
and we know what that state is.
And if we do the same exact preparation
over and over and over again,
then we get this distribution.
Yeah,
yeah.
That's right.
You can't always think that a system has a property,
and it's just your job
to find out what it is.
Yeah.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.