Stanford University
Okay,
let's go on.
In fact,
let's forget for the moment the spin system.
We'll come back to it for sure.
Probably tonight,
in fact definitely tonight.
But let's remind ourselves of,
I think I wrote down four
principles of quantum mechanics last time.
And I want to write them down again
and then move on to a fifth principle.
In fact,
they're not all independent.
It's easier for me to explain them one at a
time than to try to derive from the minimal absolute.
Minimal number of them.
And I don't think there's
any particular advantage in doing that.
So we'll just write down all
the principles that I wrote down.
The first one is that observables,
observables are the things that you measure.
They could be called measurables.
And if I had,
if it was up to me,
I would have called them measurables.
But they were called observables.
Observables are represented.
And I'll just use the equal sign to indicate.
Observables are represented by Hermitian operators.
I'll use the symbol L
for the moment for Hermitian operator.
Not all operators,
not all linear operators are Hermitian.
And it will not always be the case that
the symbol L will stand for a Hermitian operator.
But right now,
L stands for a Hermitian operator,
any Hermitian operator.
Every observable is identified with a Hermitian operator.
Now the question of whether every
Hermitian operator is a Hermitian operator,
is a thing which can be measured,
is a generally hard question.
You have to,
you know,
what can and can't be measured depends
on what kind of materials you have available,
all kinds of things.
Generally,
the abstract rule that,
or the folk rule,
let's call it,
is that any Hermitian operator
is identified with an observable,
and someday somebody will figure out how to measure it.
Okay.
But the other way that any
observable is identified with a Hermitian operator,
that's for sure,
the eigenvalues of a Hermitian operator,
let's call them lambdas.
Lambda is the eigenvalue of L.
The eigenvalues represent the possible numerical values
that L can exhibit when it's measured.
Okay.
So eigenvalues,
eigenvalues of L,
which equal lambda,
no,
they represent the possible observed,
or the possible outcome of experiment,
possible outcome,
of an experiment to measure L,
of L measurement.
Okay,
I think we had a
third one along the line here.
Yeah.
Physically distinguishable states.
Now let's just see
what physically distinguishable states mean.
Certainly,
up and down are physically distinguishable.
And the meaning of saying two states are
physically distinguishable is that there exists a measurement
of some kind that you can do that can tell
you the difference between an up state and a down state.
In other words,
somebody hands you a spin from out of their pocket,
and they say,
I created this spin,
I prepared it in a state
which is either up or down.
Can you do an experiment to
unambiguously tell me which one it is?
Yes.
You tilt your apparatus until
it's pointing along the z-axis,
and you make the measurement.
If the state was up,
you will get plus one.
If the state is down,
you will get minus one.
No ambiguity.
The same is true for left and right.
Different measurement,
different thing that you would measure.
You would measure the x component,
and you would tilt your apparatus,
along the x-axis,
but same deal.
On the other hand,
supposing somebody,
that same person,
came along and said,
Here,
I'm going to give you a spin.
Here it is.
And that spin,
I either prepared up or I prepared it right.
I am not going to tell
you which way I prepared it.
I'm not going to tell you which way
I tilted my apparatus when I did the preparation.
I'm just going to tell you,
it's either left,
sorry,
it's either up or right.
Can you do an experiment which
will uniquely tell you the difference?
The answer is no.
For example,
supposing you decide to measure the spin along the z-axis.
Well,
if it's up,
you'll get plus one.
If it's right,
with 50% probability,
you'll get plus one.
So you can't be sure whether you,
uh,
whether you,
whether you were up or right.
What if you were oriented at 45 degrees?
Still,
you would have a probability for,
yeah,
yeah.
Yeah,
it would not be unambiguous.
Right,
okay.
So,
the next postulate.
Excuse me.
In your last statement,
that's assuming it was prepared along the z-axis.
If it had been prepared along the x-axis,
then if you measured the x-axis first,
you'd get this.
If you measure the x-axis first,
you'll find something out,
but,
uh,
you could have found out exactly the
same answer if it was along the z-axis.
In either case,
there is some probability of getting the
same answer whether it was up or right.
There's no experiment you can do which unambiguously will,
uh,
will determine which it was.
Alright,
so that leads to the notion,
I'm not going to try to
give a more precise definition of it,
that leads to the
notion of physically distinguishable states
by which is meant that there exists
an experiment or a set of experiments
that can unambiguously determine which of
the two states you're talking about.
The next postulate is that
physically distinct or physically distinguishable states
are represented by orthogonal vectors.
Okay,
so physically distinct...
Distinct,
distinguishable,
same thing.
A little easier to write distinct.
Physically distinct states
imply orthogonality.
Alright,
I said that observables are Hermitian operators.
I could have just said linear operators.
Let's leave it at linear operators for the moment.
But let's add a postulate
that the result of every experiment,
every simple primitive experiment,
is a real number.
If it's a real number,
if it's a complex number,
it really means that two things,
two independent things,
were measured.
The actual results that come out of your apparatus,
that come out of your,
um,
uh,
you know,
well,
the needles on your apparatus,
they're real numbers.
So,
I'll add that as a postulate,
the results of experiments are always real numbers,
and therefore,
the eigenvalues of observables,
are real numbers.
Now,
that does not prove that the operators are Hermitian.
Not enough.
The other added thing is that the various eigenvectors
with different eigenvalues,
physically distinguishable states,
are orthogonal.
Okay,
that's this third postulate.
And that tells you that observables are Hermitian operators.
It's the Hermitian operators
whose eigenvalues are real numbers,
whose eigenvalues are always real,
and whose eigenvectors are orthogonal.
That's necessary and sufficient.
Uh,
so,
this one,
as I said,
they're not all completely,
uh,
independent of each other.
One,
let's,
one,
two,
three,
and let's write number four now.
I forgot what four is.
Oh.
Um,
yeah,
what was four?
Yeah.
Ah,
the probability,
the probability principle.
Okay.
The probability principle,
it's also called Born's Rule.
Max Born.
Born's Rule,
let's just call it Born Rule.
But it's a rule
for probabilities.
So far,
none of this has much content.
The added content,
well,
no,
it has content,
but the real bite here is,
uh,
for the prediction of probabilities
for various experiments.
And the Born Rule is the
rule for how to calculate probabilities.
The Born Rule says,
if you,
if your system has been prepared in state A,
all right,
system in A,
and you measure L,
the observable L,
now I'm using interchangeably
the physical idea of the observable
with the operator,
which right now is L.
It represents it.
I'm not going to make a special language
where the operator will always be called the operator
and the observable with L same,
they come in pairs.
All right,
so if you,
if the system has been prepared in state A,
and you measure L,
you measure L,
the outcome is going to be one of the eigenvalues.
So the only question you can ask is,
what is the probability
that you get the answer,
lambda?
Okay,
one of the specific eigenvalues.
The answer is,
the probability,
the probability that you get result lambda,
that's the probability that you get
out of the various eigenvalues that you get lambda,
is equal to the square of the inner product
of the state vector that the system was in,
with the eigenvector
corresponding to normalized eigenvector,
all vectors are normalized now,
the inner product of A with lambda squared.
A with lambda,
the inner product,
sometimes incidentally the inner
product is called the overlap,
it's a measure,
if we said that
orthogonality is complete distinguishability,
unique and complete distinguishability,
then a lack of orthogonality represents to some extent
the inability to make the
clear distinction between two states.
Yeah,
all right,
so this is,
this is,
yeah,
question.
Well,
I'm surprised to see lambda represented as a vector
because it's a value.
No,
no,
all right,
the notation is,
every eigenvalue is associated with an eigenvector.
I'll just write E vector.
And the notation is that the vector labeled by lambda
is the eigenvector associated with the eigenvalue lambda.
That's a good point,
I mean,
you know,
the problem with trying to be a purist about this,
about notations,
is that notations get very complicated.
And they get so complicated that they're difficult to read,
there are too many indices,
there's too many different letters you have to use.
So,
yeah,
sometimes we use a slightly,
excuse the word,
bastardized notation,
where we conflate a symbol for a vector
with a symbol in this case for an eigenvalue.
Good.
Okay,
yes,
that's the probability principle,
or Born's Rule.
And let's just look at it for a minute.
You might say,
why the square?
Why the square of the absolute value?
Well,
in general,
these overlaps are neither positive,
not even real in general.
Overlaps between two vectors are not necessarily real.
In fact,
in general,
they're not.
We're talking about a complex vector space,
and if the components of the vectors are complex,
in general,
the inner product will not even be real,
let alone positive.
On the other hand,
the square of the,
or the absolute value of the square,
the square of the absolute value of the inner product,
that is real.
It's not only real,
it's also positive.
So this has a chance
to be a candidate for probability,
whereas the inner product itself doesn't.
The inner product itself is called a probability amplitude.
So a probability amplitude is a thing that you square
in the sense of absolute value to compute a probability.
Needless to say,
the justification for these principles,
in the end,
is experiment.
On the other hand,
you could ask,
how much can I bend
them and still make physical sense
out of the predictions?
The answer is nobody has ever found a way
to change the rules of quantum mechanics
and still preserve,
a reasonable,
reasonably logical structure.
So you'll eventually get familiar with these principles.
Yeah?
Which of these principles took
you from several possible outcomes
to one actual outcome?
Well,
okay.
If A is an eigenvector of L,
if it is,
if the starting state of the system happens to be
an eigenvector of L,
then it will only have an infinite number
of eigenvectors.
So it's not going to
be a product of one eigenvector.
Right.
So that's,
again,
these are good questions.
If you say L ket lambda equals lambda ket lambda,
it kind of shows you.
Yeah.
That's right.
Excuse me.
Is it,
what if lambda is an eigenvalue
for multiple eigenvectors all at once?
Yeah.
Still,
the rule is the same.
But what you have to do,
you have to do is,
Right.
Okay.
I'll give you two answers.
The first answer is,
don't worry about the case where
the eigenvalues may be the same,
because it's very special.
But that's not good enough.
Let me,
let me,
let me say what the right answer is.
The right answer is if you want the probability
for a given value of lambda,
and there's more than one eigenvector
with the same value of lambda,
then you add them.
You simply add the sums of the squares of the,
just probability addition.
So the questions tonight are really good.
Yeah.
And what about the case where
A has overlap with several different eigenvectors?
Yeah,
yeah.
Then you,
then you,
then you take the sums of the squares of them.
You take the sums of the squares.
If there are several different eigenvectors,
all with the same eigenvalue,
first of all,
you make them perpendicular to each other.
You can always make them perpendicular to each other.
Different eigenvalues.
No,
no.
Even if they were the same eigenvalue,
there's a,
the theorem,
okay,
let's go back to the theorem.
The theorem says that the
eigenvectors with different eigenvalues are orthogonal.
It doesn't tell you anything about
the eigenvectors for the same eigenvalue.
All right,
so supposing you have two
eigenvectors with the same eigenvalue,
then it's also true that any
linear combination of those two eigenvectors
is also an eigenvector with the same eigenvalue.
For example,
let's suppose lambda,
lambda one and lambda two,
now these are not two different values of lambda.
These are the same value
of lambda but two different eigenvectors.
Maybe we should write it like this.
Lambda one and lambda two.
Two different eigenvectors,
both exhibiting the same eigenvalue.
Then you can take any,
what that means is that
L on lambda one equals lambda times lambda one.
L on lambda two equals lambda,
lambda two.
Multiply this by any complex number alpha.
This one by any complex number beta.
And add the two equations.
What you find is that L on the linear combination
the linear sum alpha lambda one plus beta lambda two
is equal,
on this side now you have lambda,
times the same thing as in the bracket here.
In other words,
if you have two eigenvectors with the same eigenvalue,
you can add them with arbitrary coefficients,
and they remain eigenvectors.
Now given two distinct vectors,
given two distinct vectors,
and all the possible linear combinations of them,
you can always find perpendicular combinations.
You got this one,
you got this one.
Now we can always add them or subtract them
with coefficients to make them perpendicular.
So the rest of the theorem is
that if the two eigenvalues are the same,
you have the freedom to
choose two eigenvectors which are perpendicular.
Which are orthogonal.
Alright,
and the end of the day,
to summarize the theorem,
is that given a Hermitian operator,
its eigenvectors can be chosen
so that they form a basis.
So that they're orthonormal,
perpendicular to each other,
and normalized.
Okay,
so where were we?
That was an interruption,
but I don't remember where I was.
That's the problem with interruptions.
We just finished Born's Rule.
You were just talking about Born's Rule.
Yes,
I was talking about Born's Rule.
Right,
oh,
good,
okay.
So now,
if you happen to have several eigenvectors,
let's say lambda one and lambda two,
both with the same eigenvalue,
then you construct the overlap
of the state vector with lambda one,
you construct the overlap
of the state vector with lambda two,
you square this one,
and you add them.
In other words,
you simply add the probabilities
for the two possible ways
that you could get the same lambda.
Just a sum of probabilities.
Thank you,
Sanjay.
You're already too late.
I already got Oreos.
But my wife would say,
this is probably healthier than Oreos.
Yeah,
it is.
Go ahead.
What?
You're going to eat the Oreos?
You're going to hurt their feelings.
Excuse me.
Okay.
I have a question.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
Loud and clear.
Could we say also that
the reason why those things are squared,
regardless of whether they're complex or not,
is so that the total probability adds to one,
right?
Yes.
Mm-hmm.
Right.
We know it's the sums of the squares
of these things which add up to one
for normalized states,
for normalized vectors.
That's right.
I'm not sure which one implies the sum,
but I'm not sure which one implies which,
but clearly they fit together very nicely.
Good.
Okay.
Is it possible to get an unambiguous result
from an unprepared experiment?
I'm not sure what an unprepared experiment means,
but I think what you're asking is,
supposing somebody gives you a spin,
and they don't tell you anything
about how they prepared it.
They just said,
here it is.
I give it to you.
I tell you nothing.
Then it is not possible
to find an experiment
which has an unambiguous answer.
All right.
Another good point.
Okay.
Now,
now we need to,
we need to come
to a new idea and a new question.
In classical mechanics,
all of this,
this whole story here
was summarized
when I showed you a heads and a tails,
and I said those are the two possible states
of a simple system.
I didn't,
we didn't talk about measuring it.
You know,
it was all sort of obvious,
and we didn't have to,
because we know that measuring is,
it doesn't do very much to a system.
You measure,
but you,
that doesn't change the system in any way.
Here we come to a much more complicated story,
but the story up till now
is really the quantum mechanical analog
of just specifying
that you have a collection of states.
The next question we asked
was how do states change with time?
That we called in the classical case
dynamical laws of motion,
or dynamical laws of nature
or whatever,
the rule for how a state changes.
If you remember,
there were some examples.
The coin,
a simple example would be,
put the coin down,
and the rule is nothing happens.
It just stays the same way.
Well,
that's pretty trivial.
Another possible law is
in each interval of time,
and we have a stroboscopic time
that we can imagine,
and in each interval of time,
it flips.
Heads,
tails,
heads,
tails.
That's a perfectly good law.
We talked about the concept,
the same concept in the context of a die
with six faces,
or any number of faces,
including continuous infinity.
Same basic idea.
The laws of physics are updating
from instant to instant
of a configuration.
And they tell you how the configuration changes.
And if you have good laws
in classical physics,
they're deterministic.
They tell you how the state changes.
But also another rule,
and the other rule we called reversibility.
Reversibility was basically just the idea
that states don't run into each other.
That states which are distinguishable,
namely different,
heads and tails are distinguishable,
are two states which are different,
will evolve mathematically
and stay different.
All right?
That was the idea of reversibility.
And what it comes down to
is exactly that,
that if you know the state at any instant,
you not only will know what comes next,
but you will also know what came before,
because there's no chance
that states run together,
and two different states
giving you the same outcome,
then you wouldn't be able to tell
where you came from.
So reversibility is the idea.
We also called it information conservation.
And I suspect I referred to it
as the minus first law.
Minus first because it comes before everything else.
Quantum mechanics also has a rule of
both reversibility and information conservation.
You can call it the minus first law.
But it comes down to the same thing.
States which are distinguishable,
in the sense that I said,
that there exists an experiment
that uniquely distinguishes them,
stay.
Distinguishable.
Alright,
so now we want to talk about
how states evolve with time.
We're going to come back
and discuss this in the context of the spin.
It's the simplest system of quantum mechanics,
and it's a good idea to
get it all down for that.
But let's talk about it more generally.
Okay.
Here's the postulate.
The postulate is
that if you have a system
at time,
at some specific time,
let's call it a time zero.
And I'm going to start changing
my notation for states.
Instead of calling them A and B,
I'm going to start using a notation
which is more or less a standard notation
in quantum mechanics.
Call them psi.
Psi is a Greek letter.
And psi is a commonly used letter
to represent the state of a system.
Now the states of systems
do change with time.
So you have to think of these,
these vectors,
as being functions of time.
They evolve.
So let's put that in here
in the following way.
Psi of t,
this simply represents
a state which changes with time.
Which state?
Could be any state.
It's not the same after a certain time
as it was to begin with,
but we're following one specific state
of a system that's been prepared
and then allowed to evolve
by whatever means things evolve.
Alright,
the postulate is
that psi of t
can be obtained
from psi of zero,
this means time zero,
by an operation on psi of zero.
A unique,
definite operation
which is governed by the laws,
by the quantum mechanical laws
for that system.
So we have to do something to the vector.
It doesn't stay the same.
So let's represent what we do
by the operation of some kind of operator.
Now incidentally,
we didn't have to start with time zero.
We could have started with time
something else.
So,
we can say that
psi of t
is the time of evolution
from the initial state
to the final state.
Not necessarily final,
but the state at some time.
The basic postulate,
two basic postulates.
The first is that U is a linear operator.
That U is a linear operator
and the same U
for any state.
Whatever the initial state is,
you put that here
and you hit it with the same U,
the same operator.
In other words,
there is a,
this is called the time development operator.
It's a linear operator
and it evolves the state
from one instant to another.
You could try to ask
what would happen if you made a more
general hypothesis.
For example,
you might have the hypothesis
that U depends on the initial state.
Or you might have the hypothesis
that U is an operation
but not a linear operator,
some other kind of operation.
You can try it.
You'll very shortly run into big troubles
with all kinds of things.
It's been tried,
I guarantee you.
It's been tried and repeatedly,
every so often,
some physicist will try to invent something
and then some other person will come along
and say,
look,
that has troubles with locality
or it has troubles with causality
or it has troubles with probability analysis.
It's a very complex interpretation.
And you're free to try.
I've given up trying.
I actually never tried.
Right,
okay.
So U is a linear operator
with all the rules for linear operators.
But one other thing,
and that's this idea of
conservation of information
or conservation of distinguishability.
That if you have two states,
two different states of the same system
and you evolve them,
let's call phi of t,
capital phi,
that's given by the same U of t,
the same operator,
times phi at time zero.
Then,
if phi,
to begin with,
is orthogonal to psi,
in other words,
if they're physically distinguishable
to begin with,
then they will remain orthogonal
for all time.
Yes.
Is there anything to the fact
that you used uppercase letters
on the left and lowercase?
Say it again.
The Greek letters are uppercase
on the left and lowercase
on the right.
Is that just a...
I guess I'm sloppy.
No.
Right.
All right,
so
orthogonality breeds orthogonality.
Physically distinct states evolve
to physically distinct states.
Distinguishability remains intact.
It's the immediate analog
of the minus first law
of classical mechanics.
So let's see if we can find out
what it says.
Oh,
incidentally,
it's very easy to prove from that,
well,
what does it say?
It says that if psi and phi
were initially orthogonal,
then they would be
orthogonal.
I'm...
All right.
No.
If they were initially orthogonal,
if,
then...
Don't ask me to make capital letters.
It's much quicker to make
the lowercase ones,
but I mean capital here.
I mean uppercase.
Then this is true,
and it remains true for all time.
It's an easy exercise.
I will leave it to you
to prove that if orthogonality
is preserved,
that you can say a stronger thing.
It's implied by this.
You can say if you take
any two vectors,
which may or may not be orthogonal,
the inner product between them
stays constant with time.
There's a nice little trick.
You take any two vectors,
you expand them in basis vectors,
and then you assume that the basis vectors
remain orthogonal with time.
Then you can prove that the inner products
of any two vectors
is time independent.
So it follows from the orthogonality,
the evolution of orthogonality,
that the inner product between two states
remains the same.
The overlap between them remains the same.
There's a sense in which the overlap
between two states
is of course a measure of their similarity,
and what it says is the degree of similarity
remains the same.
Okay,
let's see if we can figure out
what that means for u.
What it says,
let's rewrite this
by plugging in for phi
of t and psi of t
the product u times phi and u times psi.
But before we do,
we have to remember
that we have to flip this equation,
oops,
chocolate pie.
Is this chocolate?
Yeah,
it is chocolate.
We have to flip it from a ket vector
to a bra vector equation.
Okay,
so let's do so.
This is psi of t equals psi of zero.
Not times u,
but times what?
u dagger,
the Hermitian conjugate.
Not the complex,
it's related to the complex conjugate,
but the Hermitian conjugate.
All right,
so now we plug this into this equation here,
and what it says,
let's write it out,
do a little bit of erasure.
For arbitrage,
they don't have to be orthogonal.
Whatever they are,
they have some inner product.
That's equal to psi of zero,
u dagger of t,
u of t,
phi of zero.
All I've done is plug in.
For phi,
u of t.
For psi,
u dagger of t.
Now,
the product u dagger times u
is another operator.
What is the product of two operators?
We didn't talk about this,
but the product of two
operators is a very simple concept.
You take a linear operator,
and you apply it to a vector,
and then you take the result,
and you apply another operator to it.
The process of repeatedly applying two operators
gives you an operation,
which is called the product of the two operators.
So that's what this is.
First you hit phi with u,
and then you hit the result with u dagger.
And what this says is
that for any phi and psi,
any phi and psi at all,
that when you plug in here,
u dagger and u,
the product of u dagger and u,
you get something,
which is exactly the same as had you not
evolved the state.
The inner product stays the same.
Whoops,
I think I made a mistake.
One of these should be phi,
right?
Alright,
so that's the principle of
conservation of overlap,
if you like.
What is the principle of conservation of overlap?
Well,
here's a theorem.
We don't need to...
This is,
again,
very,
very easily proved
by going to a basis.
Very easily proved.
That if the matrix elements,
this is called the matrix elements,
or the product,
like this.
If...
this equation is true
for any pair of vectors,
in other words,
I'll write the theorem in general.
If you have an operator,
let's call it k,
or u dagger u,
and for any pair of vectors,
psi...
psi k phi
is equal to psi phi,
for any pair of vectors,
whatever,
it follows that k is the unit operator.
The unit operator is the operator
which does nothing,
just gives you back
the same vector.
So it follows,
then,
that u dagger times u must be the unit operator.
That's the content of conservation of overlap.
u dagger of t,
for any t,
times u of t
is equal to the unit operator,
meaning the operator which does nothing.
Just gives you back the same vector.
Question?
Can you then say that one
is the inverse of the other?
In matrix algebra?
Yes,
you can.
Indeed.
Alright.
Let's examine this a little bit now.
In particular,
let's examine it
for very,
very small time.
For very small time,
in other words,
where you only evolve the system
by a tiny little incremental time,
let's call the incremental time epsilon.
Alright?
Let's write that u of epsilon,
now first of all,
what is u of zero?
No time evolution at all.
Just one.
Just the unit operator.
So for very small epsilon,
u must be itself close to the unit operator.
Plus a small deviation,
presumably of order epsilon,
and that will be right.
It will be of order epsilon,
so there will be something of order epsilon
times another operator here.
I'm going to make use of freedom
and,
that I have,
and I'm going to
put a minus sign here.
We're going to put an operator over here.
This minus sign has no content yet,
unless I know what the operator is over here.
The minus sign,
it just absorbs into the definition.
And I'm also going to put an i here.
Again,
there's no content yet,
because I haven't told you anything about h.
h is some operator.
Epsilon times h is just an operator,
and i epsilon h is just an operator.
So I have not really said anything other than,
for small epsilon,
the operator u is close to the identity.
How close?
Of order epsilon.
And then there may be additional things,
of order epsilon squared,
epsilon cubed,
but we're going to drop them
and study this equation.
Oh,
I should,
we should name,
we should give a name to this equation here.
More specifically,
we should give a name to operators
which satisfy this rule.
u dagger times u is equal to one,
or,
as was said,
that u dagger,
the Hermitian conjugate of u,
is the inverse of u.
Such operators are called unitary.
u is a unitary operator.
So this is,
again,
this is a restatement
of the principle of conservation of overlap.
Let's now apply this equation,
this condition,
to u of epsilon,
and see what we find out about h.
Okay,
so let's bring it over to this blackboard.
u of epsilon,
is equal to one minus i epsilon h.
Now let's do it over here.
Alright,
what about u dagger?
u dagger is the Hermitian conjugate.
The Hermitian conjugate of one is just one,
but then we have the complex conjugate,
plus i epsilon,
and then we have to Hermitian conjugate h.
Okay?
Alright,
so here is u dagger,
and here is u.
And now let's multiply them together,
and set the result equal to one,
to order epsilon.
To order epsilon.
Okay?
So,
what do we have?
We have u dagger is one
plus i epsilon times h dagger,
times one minus i epsilon h.
That has to equal one.
And now just expand it out,
to order epsilon,
one plus i epsilon h dagger minus h,
equals one.
As I said,
that's just to the approximation
that epsilon is so small
that its square can be completely ignored,
compared to order epsilon.
Alright?
So,
the ones cancel.
And basically what we find,
is that h dagger minus h,
has to be zero.
We cancelled out the ones,
we get zero on the right hand side.
And so to order epsilon,
h has to equal h dagger.
This is the condition,
that h be Hermitian.
Now I didn't call it h for Hermitian.
I called it h for something else.
I called it h for Hamiltonian.
Okay?
What it has to do
with the Hamiltonian of classical mechanics,
will eventually become clear.
The Hamiltonian for classical mechanics,
also enters in,
to the equations for how systems evolve
from one instant to the next.
But,
of course,
that's not a good enough
reason to call this the Hamiltonian.
We want to see that it enters the equations,
in a way very,
very similar to the way,
the Hamiltonian enters into classical mechanics.
And it does.
It is also the thing which,
it's Hermitian,
right?
That means,
that it's an observable,
or it could be an observable.
It's a Hermitian operator.
It could be an observable.
And it is an observable.
It's the Hamiltonian.
It's the energy.
Hamiltonian and energy of the Hamiltonian.
They're the same.
This is what the energy of a system is.
It's the Hamiltonian,
which generates the evolution of state vectors,
according to this rule here.
Yeah?
That could be any Hermitian operator.
It could be any Hermitian operator at the moment.
Now,
what determines what Hermitian operator you put there?
Well,
it can't be,
yes,
it could be any Hermitian operator,
associated with the system you're studying.
Right,
right.
If we're studying a system of one spin,
we want to make it up out of operators
that are associated with the spin.
So,
yes,
it can be any operator,
but it's either experiment or some,
it's the same things which govern
why you choose one Hamiltonian or Lagrangian
in classical mechanics.
Either experiment,
some prejudice about the way things work,
some symmetry principle,
whatever you have
that might give you a
clue as to what H is.
At the end of the day,
you may have to resort to experiment to find out,
but whatever it is.
Okay,
so,
that's,
right,
so now let's rewrite our equation.
Let's rewrite,
question?
Yeah?
So,
when you do the expansion like that,
normally then H is a constant,
right?
That's what,
you know what I mean when
you do that first order expansion?
So it'd be,
it's H of 0?
Well,
H is an operator.
I mean,
it's not a function of time
in that case,
right?
Okay.
Or not a function of epsilon.
The situation with
a possible explicit time dependence of H
is the same as in classical physics.
In classical physics,
H can depend on time.
For example,
if you have a particle moving in a magnetic field,
and the strength of the magnets
is being varied with time by changing the current
through the electromagnet,
then the Hamiltonian for the
particle moving in a magnetic field
is time dependent.
Okay?
Otherwise,
if you have the,
if the parameters of the
problem are not varying with time,
then you say the Hamiltonian is not time dependent.
It's exactly the same.
Exactly.
You know when you do an expansion like that,
you'd be using,
say,
H of 0.
Yeah,
yeah,
no,
that's right.
That's right.
In principle,
H could be a function of time.
Let's take the case where it's not,
and what that corresponds to
is the situation where the parameters of the problem
are not time dependent.
Where in classical physics,
we called it time translation invariance.
Remember in classical physics,
time translation invariance,
which means like every time is
the same as every other time.
Okay?
You do the experiment,
the same experiment at a later time,
will have the same output
as the identical experiment at an earlier time.
The statement of that principle,
time translation invariance,
is that H does not have explicit dependence on time.
It's just an operator which doesn't depend on time.
As I said,
you can imagine situations where
you're ramping up the current
in an electromagnet,
or the universe is expanding,
or God knows what,
there's some explicit time dependence,
then H can be time dependent.
Now,
do you remember what happens to energy conservation
if the Hamiltonian is time dependent?
Down the drain.
Right.
Same thing here.
If the Hamiltonian is time dependent,
and we haven't yet seen why
there might be a conservation of energy,
we'll come to that,
but,
alright.
Okay,
so let's come back then to this equation,
over here.
What happens at the long times?
What happens to what?
This is all for the small,
epsilon time.
Sorry,
what?
Say it again?
This is for the small,
infinitesimal small.
Yes.
Yeah,
we'll come to that.
Basically,
you just multiply them together.
Right,
we'll come to that.
Okay.
Or you can think of it another way.
After you've updated by a small amount of time,
you just do it again,
and again,
and again.
Alright?
You just do it repeatedly,
but we can use this to derive a differential equation
for the way the state changes with time.
Let's do that.
Okay,
so let's look at the state of the system
at a time epsilon,
and this time epsilon could be
thought of as a time epsilon right,
right after some arbitrary time,
which I'm going to call zero,
but it doesn't matter.
Psi of epsilon is equal
to one minus i h epsilon,
minus i h epsilon times psi,
let's say,
at time zero.
Or another way to say
it is that psi of epsilon,
minus psi of zero,
this is the small incremental change in the state vector,
that's equal to minus i
epsilon operation by h on psi.
Now as I said,
this zero here doesn't have to be zero.
It could be any time as long as
epsilon is epsilon units after the starting time.
Okay,
let's divide this equation by epsilon.
You're allowed to do this because
you can multiply vectors by numbers,
so we're just multiplying both sides by one over epsilon,
one over epsilon times this whole thing.
Okay,
what's this thing on the left hand side?
One over epsilon times the difference of two things,
which are by,
which,
at two slightly different times.
That's just the time derivative of this vector.
We haven't talked very much
about taking derivatives of vectors,
but it's clear you can do that.
You can take the difference between two vectors,
that's perfectly well defined.
They will be close to
each other if epsilon is small.
If you divide by the small epsilon,
you'll get something which on
the right hand side is just
the time derivative
of psi.
The time derivative of psi equals minus i h psi.
At any given time,
it doesn't,
as I said,
it doesn't have to be at time zero.
At any given time,
if you want to find out
how the state of the system
changes over an incremental time interval,
this is your,
this is your equation.
Completely analogous to the
way you update classical systems,
but because,
because knowing the state vector is
not the same as knowing the values
of the experimental outputs of experiments,
you can know the state and
still there can be ambiguity or uncertainty
in the value of an experiment.
This tells you how states change,
but it doesn't tell you
how the results of experiments change.
The experiments,
the results of experiments are still statistical,
but with a continuously updated state vector.
Okay,
this is,
this equation has a name.
The name of this equation is
the generalized time dependent Schrödinger equation.
This is the general form,
this is the Schrödinger equation.
Specific versions,
what Schrödinger wrote down was a very specific version,
and this is the general version of this.
We're going to come to that later in the course,
but this is the general idea.
The rate of,
all right,
I don't need to say it again.
This is what it is,
but of course in order to use it,
you have to know what h is.
Question?
Yeah.
So all of this is dependent
on the reversibility of the system,
is that right?
Yes.
So,
I guess,
Or the conservation of,
of inner products,
yeah.
Right,
so I guess stepping back,
how does that match the fact that if
you take an up vector and a down vector,
and you measure them along the horizontal axis,
they can sort of both end up,
you know,
in sort of what I
just don't want to be in,
in multiple states.
Okay,
that's a good question.
You have to remember when you do that,
you're intervening with an apparatus.
In order to follow the system,
under those circumstances,
you have to include the
apparatus as part of the system.
You cannot interact with the system
and not include the things which
are interacting with it in the system.
Classically,
it's not such a bad sin,
but quantum mechanically,
if something interacts with the system strongly enough to,
to affect it,
well,
strongly enough to measure it,
you have to include it as part of the system.
Now,
this is the way a system evolves
if it's isolated and completely
not in contact with anything else.
We will have to come
back to ask how it evolves,
what happens when you put it
in contact with a measuring apparatus.
We'll have to have a
model for how measurements take place.
But this is the way the system behaves
if nobody disturbs it during the course of the evolution
from time zero to time t.
Okay.
We'll have to come back to that.
It's an important question.
Oh boy.
Yeah.
Really just two assumptions.
Well,
maybe three.
First is that time evolution takes
place by a linear operator called U.
And that operator is independent of
the state that it's acting on.
Okay?
With me?
Okay.
That's the first statement.
The next statement is that
inner products are conserved with time.
And that tells you that U is unitary.
Okay?
From that,
we went over to here
and discovered that the small little incremental change
is governed by a Hermitian operator.
Okay?
So,
we get to the idea of a Hamiltonian.
And then we just rewrote that and said,
look,
the small little incremental change could be thought of as
1 over epsilon times the
time derivative of the state vector.
Okay?
So,
this is the Schrodinger equation.
How do you solve the problem
if there's a long time interval,
not a short time interval?
You basically solve this equation.
And we'll talk about how you solve this equation.
We'll do so for lots of examples.
But,
um,
okay.
All right.
To go on and explain what
this has to do with classical mechanics,
or what it has to do
with the corresponding concepts in classical mechanics,
we need a couple of ideas about how
you relate classical ideas to quantum mechanical ideas.
We need the idea of what is
called the expectation value of an observable.
It's a bad name.
It's a bad name because the expectation value as defined
may have very little to do with
what you expect the experiment to give.
This doesn't have much to do with quantum mechanics.
It's just an issue of probability theory.
I think we've talked about this before,
but I'll just remind you.
If you have a probability
distribution which looks like this,
then the least likely answer that you
could possibly get is right over here.
It's also the expectation value.
So it's a poorly chosen terminology.
The right terminology should sometimes,
some,
fancy people.
I won't name Murray Gell-Mann,
but some fancy people like
to call it the expected value.
Well,
it's even less the expected value
than it is the expectation value.
It's the average value.
It's the average value,
and the average value of something can be a value
which the thing can't even take on,
a possible value that it couldn't even have,
the average value.
For example,
if you assign heads plus one and tails minus one,
and you flip the coin,
what's the average?
Zero.
Zero,
but you can't get zero.
So it's got nothing to do
with the expected value of an experiment.
But nevertheless,
it's called the expectation value,
and we will call it the expectation value.
But it's the average value.
Let's talk about the average value of an observable
given a particular state.
All right,
so our state is A.
I said I was going to change the psi,
but sometimes I will,
sometimes I won't.
Could we go back to
the expectation value for a second?
Yeah.
I think I just have
to clear my head of statistics,
but when I look at that picture you draw,
I see it's a frequency distribution.
Yeah.
So to me,
the middle is not the average.
It really is the expected value.
It's the value that's going to occur,
and it's going to occur most frequently.
No,
no,
definitely not.
This one here,
it never occurs.
Never,
ever,
ever.
Let's even make it worse.
Okay,
what are the x and y values,
what are the x and y axes represented?
P is the probability,
x is some variable,
something that you measure.
This could be the probability for finding a particle
at different locations,
okay?
All right.
It could be that for some particular,
state,
the probability,
let's make it symmetric about the origin just to,
it could be that the
probability distribution looks like this.
I meant to make this symmetric,
and it's really very,
very zero
in a neighborhood of the origin here.
There's no sense in which x equals zero
is expected.
You can do the experiment forever and ever and ever,
and you will never get x equals zero.
You'll either get an x somewhere in here or here.
So to call it the expected or the expectation value
is sort of a misnomer.
It is the average value defining averages
in a very particular way.
Now,
for many,
many smooth probability distributions,
in particular,
probability distributions
that don't have big holes in them,
something like this,
let's say,
it can very often be the case,
it very often is the case,
that the probability,
that the average value
is the most likely value to get.
So it's just,
they call it the mode,
the most likely value.
What's the peak?
The peak there is the most likely value.
Yes,
by definition,
the top of the peak is.
And in many,
many cases,
if you have nice,
simple probability,
Gaussian probability,
you know,
bell-shaped curves and so forth,
then the expectation value or the average value
is usually quite close to the average
and peak value and so forth.
They're all usually close to each other.
But certainly there can be violent exceptions.
The coin or the spin,
which can only be plus one and minus one
and never zero,
the expectation value and the average value
are quite different.
Okay,
but that's just a little sermon
and gave me a chance
to badmouth my friend Murray Gell-Mann.
Question.
Yeah.
If you take a spin where the apparatus
is perpendicular to the spin,
probably 50% of you make it very unlucky
you hit a million ups in a row.
Yeah.
The average would be up,
but that's not accurate.
Yeah,
well,
okay,
it depends on what you mean by average.
There's a notion of average which is strictly mathematical,
and we're going to write it down in a minute.
There is an unwritten law,
which I think it's safe to say nobody really understands,
but it's the law of large numbers,
that if you do a thing enough times,
how many times?
I don't know.
If you do a thing enough times,
you do an experiment enough times,
the average gotten by averaging
the results of your experiment
will be equal to the average defined mathematically
to within what?
To within the margin of error.
What is the margin of error?
There's a specific number.
Does it really mean that every time you do it,
the answer will come out within the margin of error?
No.
All right.
So we're assuming standard probability theory
that if you do a
thing plus this extra little ingredient,
this extra physical assumption,
I don't even know what to call it,
that if you repeat an experiment enough times,
the average of your data will be the mathematical average.
Can anybody prove that?
No.
That's a law of large numbers.
No,
no,
no.
There's nothing you can do to prove it.
The reason you can't prove
it is because sooner or later,
somewhere in the multiverse,
somewhere there's going to be an exception to it.
No matter how many times,
if you do it a zillion times,
a zillion is a number,
incidentally.
It's not infinity.
A zillion is one with a
logarithm of a zillion zeros after it
or something like that.
Right.
If you do an experiment,
and there's enough repetitions of it,
eventually somewhere,
someplace,
there's going to be a violation of it.
This is closely connected to
the second law of thermodynamics.
You know,
there was a principle.
The second law of thermodynamics
says that an entropy never decreases.
Boltzmann was never able to prove that,
and he finally realized that the right law is
the entropy probably never decreases,
except when it does.
Which is rarely,
So I'm not going to
try to give you an explanation
of why probability theory works.
This is,
to me,
very puzzling,
but we will assume probability theory works.
The statement that it works
is the same as the statement
that the average of your data will be,
for a big enough experiment,
will be the mathematical average.
All right,
so let's talk,
well,
let's come over to this
side here first and just say,
supposing we have a collection of,
we have a probability distribution for some variable,
let's say for lambda,
lambda,
one of the eigenvalues,
we're going to measure an eigenvalue of L.
Supposing we have a probability for lambda,
there it is right there,
the thing I called prob of lambda,
probability for lambda,
and lambda can take on
a whole bunch of different values,
lambda sub i,
let's call them.
So this becomes the probability for lambda sub i,
then the average,
the definition of the average,
is the sum over i
of lambda i times the probability for lambda i.
That's the definition of the average,
and we'll represent the average by the symbol,
the bracket symbol.
Why it's labeled by the bracket symbol we'll come to.
Okay.
But that's the definition,
standard probability theory definition
of the average of a quantity.
The quantity times the probability that
the quantity takes on that particular value,
summed over i,
and as I said,
that's standard definition of average.
Okay.
What is the average
in a state A
of the observable lambda?
So let's say that A
is expanded
in a basis.
Which basis?
The basis of eigenvectors of L.
Alright?
Remember,
L is a Hermitian operator,
it's eigenvectors form a basis,
you can expand vectors in an orthonormal basis.
So let's write this in the form
alpha sub i,
sum over i,
lambda sub i.
Remember that the lambdas are an orthonormal basis.
What is the probability
lambda
in the state i?
Probability
for lambda i
is equal to alpha star i,
alpha i.
Alright?
I maintain,
oh this is the probability,
and the average
of lambda,
let's call it the average of lambda,
is the sum over i,
lambda sub i,
alpha i star alpha i.
All I've done is plug in.
Let me prove
that this is the same thing
as taking the vector a,
the bra vector a,
and sandwiching between the bra vector a
and the ket vector a,
the operator L.
The operator L is the operator L,
is the operator whose eigenvalues are lambda.
Let's see if we can prove that.
It's actually quite easy.
All we do is say,
let's just plug in,
let's come to another blackboard,
plug in,
and
let's see if we can prove that.
Alright,
so let's calculate this
creature over here.
A,
is this summation,
and let's use also that the bra vector a
is the summation over i
of lambda sub i,
alpha star i.
Alright,
so we make a sandwich.
The sandwich is the sum over i and j.
Why?
There are two sums,
one for the bra and one for the ket.
Lambda sub j
alpha star j.
This is the bra vector a,
and then we put L there,
and then we put the ket vector,
alpha i,
lambda i.
It's pure plug-in-ology.
Now,
what is L when it acts on lambda sub i?
Lambda sub i is the function of L,
and the lambda sub i's are the eigenvectors of L.
So,
when L acts on lambda sub i,
we still have sum i j,
lambda j,
alpha star j,
alpha i,
and now L hits lambda i,
and it gives us lambda sub i
times lambda i.
Now all this junk in here
is just a number,
for each i and j.
For each i and j,
this is just a number.
So,
that means we are called upon
to take the inner product of
lambda i with lambda j.
What is that?
Right,
it's one or zero,
depending on whether i equals j or not.
Given that,
this sum,
the double sum,
collapses to a single sum,
in which lambda i and lambda j are identified,
and this just becomes sum on i,
lambda i,
well,
okay,
let's cut through some of the steps.
If j is not equal to i,
you get nothing.
If j is equal to i,
the inner product is just one.
So,
this just becomes
the sum over i,
alpha star i,
alpha i,
lambda i,
which is exactly
what we have over here,
over here.
So,
we've proved this relationship here,
that the average
of any observable
is just the sandwich,
the braquette,
the braquette.
بركة
made out of sandwiching L,
the observable,
between a bracket,
between a bra and a ket
That's the same bra and ket,
the bra and ket associated
with the state of the system
That's where this notation of bracket comes from
Okay,
that's a good thing to know,
that if you want the average of a quantity
just sandwich it between the bracket,
the bra ket representing the state
Any questions about that?
Okay,
now I'm going to tell
you what we're going to do
What we're going to do is
we're going to try to find equations
governing the time evolution of these average values
The idea is that under suitable,
reasonable circumstances
if the probability distributions are nicely shaped,
if they have a sort of nice bell-shaped curve
that by calculating the time evolution of averages
you're doing something pretty close to what
classical physics would instruct you to do
about calculating the equations of motion
uh...
of the classical system
the way averages tend to evolve in time
as I said,
under suitable circumstances
follows equations which look very very
much like the corresponding classical equations
Alright,
so our next goal is
to try to find the rules
for the time evolution of these average values,
expectation values
and that's not so hard
We have all the equipment we need to do that
and let's see if we can do it
Alright,
so at any given time
at any given time
the average of lambda is given by
psi of t,
that's the state vector at time t
the operator l representing the observable
times psi of t
In other words,
I just plugged in for a
the actual time dependent state of the system
this is the average of
l as a function of time
I don't know,
what should we call it?
Let's call it uh...
okay,
it's the average of l as a function of time
again,
this is a kind of a wrong notation
it's not the average of l of t
it's the average of l as a function of time
as a function of time
Can you put the t outside the bracket?
We could
We could put the t outside the bracket
That's non-standard
Sub t
But why don't we just go with standard notation
Standard notation and remember
Well,
okay,
I'm not going to do it
I'm going to just call it average of l
as a function of time
Okay,
It is a function of time
That's the main thing,
it's a function of time
We could do something else
We could call it l bar
Another notation for average is to
put a bar on top of something
That's another notation for average
Standard notation
And we could just call it l bar of t
It means the average as a function of time
Let's do it that way
What we would like to do with this
We'd like to find equations of motion for it
In other words,
we'd like to find out
how it changes with time
Differentiating it with respect to time
I want to take this quantity
and differentiate it with respect to time
So
Let's call it l dot
Now we have bars with dots on top of them
l dot of t
is the time derivative of this
Now l of t,
that's just some fixed operator
It's some fixed definite operator
All of the time dependence
is in the state vectors
The state vectors change with time
The operator changes with time
The operators,
those are fixed
Those are definite operators
So let's see if we can
take the time derivative
of this here thing
The time derivatives
act on the psi of t's
When you take the time derivative
of a product,
and this can be a product of
vectors,
it can be a product of numbers
it can be a product of functions
well,
functions
The rule is always the same
It's the time derivative of one
times the other,
plus the time derivative
of the other times the one
That's very general
So,
this is going to equal then
d psi by dt
the bra vector
l
psi
plus
psi l
d psi dt
Oops,
I erased a very important
equation or else I buried it
under the
blackboard,
let me write it over here
d psi
dt
is equal to
minus i h
psi
That's what we're going to
stick in over here
So we begin to see that the
Hamiltonian is going to tell us something
about how average values change with
time
The Hamiltonian of classical physics
tells us how the corresponding
quantities change with time
The Hamiltonian of quantum mechanics
will tell us how the averages change with time
We're going to also need
the bra version of this
So let's write the bra version of this
The bra version of it is
d by dt
of the bra vector
psi of t
is equal
plus i
psi h
h is her mission
and so we don't have to her mission
conjugate it
it is her mission
but we do have to change the sign of i
when we go from bra to kets
Okay,
so now we're just going to plug in
Let's just plug in
and we'll get l dot
Yeah
l dot
Okay,
let's do this one first over here
This one is going to be plus
psi and there's a minus sign
minus sign from here
minus i
psi
l
h
psi
That's what we get from here
How about the other one?
The other one is plus i
times the expectation value
We have psi here,
psi here
i
times h
l
minus l
h
psi
How about h l minus l h
Is it zero?
Why not?
h l
Who cares which way we order from?
Well,
operators
don't necessarily commute
Commute means
that you can
freely interchange the order of them
In general,
this is true of matrices
Products of matrices
don't necessarily commute
Sometimes they do
And in particular
an operator commutes with itself
l times l minus l times l
That's okay
You can do it there
l times l minus l times l is zero
Okay?
So is h times h minus h times h
But in general
l times h is not equal to h times l
It may be
But typically not
What is this animal called?
h times l minus l times h
It's called the commutator
of the two
Okay,
so this is the definition
Given to operators
Well,
they could be just h and l
The combination
h l minus l l
h is written
with a square bracket
h comma l
And it's called
the commutator
Commuting has something to do with
passing freely between each other
Exactly what it has to do with
taking the subway in New York
I don't know
But it's called
the commutator
And so what we have here
is the equation
that the average
of l
at any given time
Sorry,
the average of the time
The time derivative
of the average
is equal
to psi
commutator h l
psi
But this object over here
is just the expectation value
of commutator of h with l
So we can think of this
as an equation
relating the time derivative
of a certain average
to the average of another quantity
I did
Is it plus i?
It's plus i
I did
Or we can write it like this
We can write
l dot of t is equal to i
Well,
average
times
average of the commutator
h l
And I'll indicate that by
a bar on top of it
So we have
equations of motion now
for averages in terms of averages
If the probability
distributions for everything
are nice and peaked
Then we really can just say
that the averages are approximately
nice and peaked
so that the averages are close
to the highest point on the curve
and the curve is reasonably narrow
so there isn't an enormous amount of uncertainty
Then this basically says
that the time derivative
of
the classical
or the time derivative
of the approximate l of t
is equal to the approximate
average of commutator of h with l
And so one writes
this of course is not quite right
but right anyway
l dot
is equal to i times commutator h l
Now this has to be taken
with a little grain of salt
What it means
is an equation among averages
It means an equation among averages
but it's often just written in this form
l dot is equal to h times l
Okay
Now before we do this
before we finish
I want to remind you
of a classical mechanics
equation of motion
It's the equations of motion
represented in terms of
Poisson brackets
Do you remember Poisson brackets?
Fish brackets?
What were the Poisson equations
of motion?
Anybody remember?
And if you
Right
d by d t
exactly,
of a classical function
and this could be a classical function
of q's and p's
In classical mechanics we have q's and p's
l incidentally
is a standard notation for angular momentum
This could be the angular momentum
but right now I'm just using it
to represent any observable
d by d t
of l is equal to
a certain Poisson bracket
and the Poisson bracket
is the Poisson bracket
of l
with the Hamiltonian
Remember that?
Probably some of you don't
but I'll advise you to go
and look at the Hamiltonian
and look it up
It's in the
next to last
lecture of the
classical mechanics
on Poisson brackets
and
I will not go through it here
I just wanted to remind you of it
and I want you to notice the similarity
Where is it?
Did we erase it?
I think I erased it
The similarity of this with
d l by d t
the average value
is i
minus i or plus i?
I lost track
plus i?
i times
the commutator
of h with l
Now incidentally,
okay
let's just point out one thing
Poisson brackets
have the property
that if you interchange
the two expressions
what happens to the Poisson bracket?
It just changes sign
So do commutators
h l minus l h
if you interchange the order
of them change sign
So we can also write this as
minus
l with h
commutator of l with h
It's a remarkable
similarity and it suggests
that
we
identify the Poisson
bracket
with
minus i times the commutator
Now I've left out
a discussion of something
I just realized it just now
and I've completely forgotten about it
What happened to h bar?
We've been working
in units in which
h bar is one
I've been working in units
in which h bar,
Planck's constant
is one.
The question is
if we were to reinstate Planck's constant
and make it not equal to one
where would it go in these equations?
and
what's that?
Yes,
it goes in Schrodinger's equation
that's correct,
but how
do we trace it?
Let's see
how do we trace it?
Here's the equation here
I told you that h
has the significance of the Hamiltonian
and therefore it has units of energy
So let's look at this equation
The psi
cancels out on both sides as far as
units go.
The units of
this psi are the same
as the units of this psi
and so
the right hand side of the equation
apart from the psi's has units of an energy
The left hand side of the equation
has units of inverse time
Inverse time
and energy don't have
the same units
Inverse time is inverse seconds
and energy is joules
or whatever
So we have an equation here which doesn't make
good dimensional sense
We need
a constant in here
and the constant
we have to put a constant in here
Let's see,
where does the constant go?
Does it go on the right hand
side or the left hand side?
Where does
Planck's constant go?
Right hand side
or left hand side?
What?
If it goes in one
place in one thing,
then it goes in the inverse
in the other place.
Okay
So here's
all you have to know is that Planck's
constant has units of energy times time
Planck's constant
has units of energy times time
So let's see
So energy times time,
so we want to put Planck's
constant here
Energy times time over time is equal
to energy.
That's where
Planck's constant goes into these equations
And I apologize for having completely
forgotten about it
But that's where it goes
And
if we follow it
through the equations,
no doubt
it appears over here
Uh
I think
it appears in the
denominator here
Yeah
You see,
I got everything right
except where I have h,
I should have
h over h bar
Right
We can rewrite this this way,
h over h bar
So in all of my
equations,
wherever we wrote
h,
the Hamiltonian
we really should have,
if we want
to keep the units straight,
h
over Planck's constant,
and that goes straight
through to here.
So really
the right equation
including the constants
is the L D T
is one
is one over
h bar here
One over Planck's
constant
Planck's constant is a small number
So this
looks like it's very big
But on the other hand,
this is L times
h minus h times L
In classical physics,
that would be
zero
So whatever this is
classically it's zero
and quantum mechanically it must
be a small correction to the classical
physics,
to the extent that quantum
mechanics is a small correction to classical
physics,
and so the
commutator is itself something
which is typically small and of order n
h bar,
so that allows us then
to guess
to guess an identification
between
commutators and Poisson
brackets.
Now
I'm
this is non-intuitive
at the moment,
it's just a
just looking at two equations
and saying look,
if there's going to be any connection
between quantum mechanics and classical mechanics
then
there must be a connection
between the Poisson bracket
and between the Poisson
bracket and the commutator
namely,
Poisson bracket
must be equal
to minus i over
h bar
times commutator
or
it's usually written the other way
commutator is
i h bar
times Poisson bracket
Commutator is a small
thing,
because there's an h bar
there.
Poisson
bracket in classical physics is not a
small thing,
it's some number,
I mean it's some
characteristic quantity which is not
neither small nor big
and in the same units,
the units
that you do classical physics,
the standard
units,
meters,
seconds
whatever
commutators are very small
that's because they're almost zero
a times b minus b times a
is almost zero.
Okay
No,
I don't think so
I think i
we had a minus i on this side
minus i over h bar
multiply by h bar
and now multiply both sides by
i and use that minus i
times plus i is one
yeah
right,
it was Dirac who
recognized this connection
and built his quantum mechanics
out of it,
he built his quantum mechanics
out of making an identification
of Poisson brackets
with commutators
but of course the foundations
of the subject
quantum mechanics
is a
consistent subject without having
to make any reference to classical physics
the right way to think about things
is that quantum mechanics comes before
classical mechanics,
commutators
before Poisson brackets
you have to derive classical physics
as an approximation to
quantum mechanics
so here we see some formal similarities
at this point here
we have no idea why this
commutator should have
features in common with the Poisson bracket
before we go
let me just say,
let me write down
some of the features of commutators
and Poisson brackets to remind you
are
and again
all of this should be at this stage
should be a little mysterious
what is this funny connection between Poisson brackets
but
let's pursue it anyway
okay
let me remind you about
Poisson brackets
first of all if I have two
quantities
I'll call them A and B now
or maybe A and B I use for
let's just call them L and H
they don't have to be the Hamiltonian
and anything special they're just L and H
alright the first thing is
the Poisson bracket
of L with H
is equal to minus
the Poisson bracket of H with L
okay
the commutator of L
with H
is minus the commutator
of H with L
so that's
a parallelism that we can begin with
now let's take some other
let's take some other properties of
Poisson brackets
there's a lot of properties
of Poisson brackets but let me just
write one or two more
if I have
two operators
or two not operators
but two quantities
let's call them L and M
okay
L times M
is itself a classical
quantity and I can compute
its Poisson bracket
with H
does anybody remember the answer
I'll remind you
I'll tell you
go look it up
this is important
it's L
it's the Poisson bracket of L with H
times M
plus
L
times the Poisson bracket
of M with H
and
I'm going to
now in classical physics
the order of multiplication
doesn't matter
so you can bring the M
on the left or the right it doesn't matter
you can bring the L on
the left or right it doesn't matter
but this is
the relationship
for the product of two variables
the Poisson bracket
go back to the next to the last lecture
and
check this out this was one of the defining
not one of the defining
one of the properties of Poisson brackets
you can do the same
you can ask the same question over here
supposing you have
L M
and you take its commutator with H
what do you get
this is an exercise
all you do is you write
that this is equal to
L M H
minus H L M
and now
you start just juggling
and adding some terms
and eventually you'll discover that this is
the same as this
same relationship
that this is equal to
L times the commutator of M with H
plus
L
commutator of L with H
times M
the way to do this
is just write
L M H minus H L M
and then write it down
you'll find out these guys here
this is L M H
minus L H M
plus L H M
minus H L M
four terms here
two will cancel in pairs
and you'll just get this back
it's a one step thing
it's a really easy thing
ok,
so you begin to see
some pattern
that Poisson brackets
and
commutators must somehow be closely
related
the last
thing I'm going to show you tonight
is about energy
conservation
now,
we're not going to
consider the most
general concept of energy conservation
we're simply going to
ask is the average
of the energy conserved with
time
we have not even really
gotten to what it would mean
for energy itself to be
conserved in any deeper way
but we can ask
we have all the ingredients now
which will allow us
to ask how the average
of
here's how the average
of any quantity changes with time
no
here it is over here
we can now specifically ask
how the average of the energy changes with time
let's do it
the energy
I claim is the Hamiltonian
ok,
or it's definition
if you like,
what is energy?
it's Hamiltonian,
so let's check
and ask whether energy is conserved
if energy is the Hamiltonian
this equation would read
the time derivative of the average
of the Hamiltonian
is equal to
minus i over h bar
times
the commutator of the Hamiltonian
with itself
the Hamiltonian with itself
it's h times h minus h times h
h times h is the same as h times h
quantum mechanics is not that weird
you know,
it's weird
but h times h is
the same as h times h
so this is zero
whatever the Hamiltonian is
its average
its average,
its expectation value
with time is always 0
and so it's conserved in that sense
at minimum in that sense
there's a stronger sense in which it's conserved
and we'll come to it
but
even this weaker sense is kind of interesting
and it tells us we're
on some kind of right track
to be able to compare quantum mechanics
and classical mechanics
ok,
I'm going to stop now
and take a few questions
and yeah
I'm going to stop now
ok
and the fact that you've given the bar notation
and the probability
here?
x bar is the sample mean
and you use the probability
probably,
I just mean the average
I mean the average defined
ah
defined as summation of
probability of lambda times lambda
ok
so
I don't know
what's the standard symbol in statistics
for an average in this sense?
a bar
sometimes they write
they do what?
the first moment of the distribution
you knew they would use it sometimes
yeah
ok
lambda
yeah,
ok
um
I'm used to just
calling it
lambda
hmm
e brackets of lambda
e bracket of lambda
and that stands for what?
the average expected value
expected value even though it's not the expected value
you don't expect to get it
yeah,
ok
um
you've never seen the expected
the average value of the bar on top of it?
yeah,
I mean it's normal
conditions that it means the sample mean like the average
ok
yeah
when I use the term average I will mean this
it's also called the expectation value
and I will freely interchange
the Dirac notation
for the average
with
the bar notation
ok
and if that's not
if that's not
standard according to
statistics books
too bad
so over here you wrote down the Schrodinger equation
yes
and then you wrote down
the
how did you go from the left hand equation
to the right hand equation
was that complex conjugation
or was that Hermitian conjugation
Hermitian conjugation
but
remember that H is Hermitian
we proved that
that was
that was the condition of unitarity
that H is Hermitian
how can you interchange the
order of psi and H but not d dt
and psi
where where where
on the left side equation
you got d dt and psi
d dt is the operator
this one here?
yeah
yeah the time derivative of a
bra vector is a bra vector
the time derivative of a ket
look the time derivative is just another way
of talking about differences
the difference of two bra vectors is a bra vector
the difference of two ket vectors
is a ket vector
in the limit
the difference becomes the time derivative
or the derivative
so the derivative of a
bra vector is a bra vector
the derivative of a ket vector
is a ket vector
if you want to take this
ket equation
what is the bra that goes with this ket
the bra that's dual to this ket
is the time derivative of the corresponding
bra vector
since time is not an
operator you don't have to worry
about time
just think of this as
taking the difference of two vectors
yeah
it's just the difference of two vectors
right
exactly
and
again
quantum mechanics is weird
but
taking the difference of two vectors
and replacing it by a derivative
when the difference is small
that's perfectly legitimate
you said that the form of Hamiltonian
we will choose depending on symmetry considerations
well yeah
in the derivation here
we did not put any symmetry considerations so far
no
so why is it that
we are getting energy conservation out
how come we're getting what
energy conservation out
how do we know that this is corresponding to energy
well we don't know that it's corresponding to energy
until we do a lot more
we don't know that we
can define it to be energy
the Hamiltonian but that's not satisfying
we want to see in cases where
we understand the classical physics
and we understand
what energy is
we're going to want to see that the
quantum mechanics of the same system
the classical system is an approximation
to the quantum mechanical system
physics is really quantum mechanical
under certain conditions such as
a system is heavy
basically that,
that it's heavy
that it's big
that it's large masses
then
the system behaves approximately classically
which means that the average values
move in ways
which are consistent with the classical equations of motion
we're going to want to see that
when we study such big heavy systems
that
the thing that we call
the quantum mechanical Hamiltonian
is
essentially
closely connected with the thing that we call
the classical Hamiltonian
but we'll come to that
we can't do everything all in one night
I'm just showing you similarities
and we're going to want to do better than that
whether we'll actually get to do better than that
I don't know
we can't do everything
but
that's the logic
yeah
yes
way back to the electron spin
I think when we left off the last lecture
you were going to show
what the probability is
yeah
right I had saved some time to do that
but I think I've done enough for tonight
who was it who sent in the solution to it
yeah
well done
right
so
but we'll do it
I just
I've run out of steam
right
we'll come back to that
we're going to come back to that
so how can your postulates
work without a collapsed postulate
what's that
how can your postulates work without a collapsed postulate
well we really want
we really want to derive the collapsed postulate
but the derivation is deeply connected with
something else that we haven't come to yet
and I think we're going
to come to it next time
entanglement
the measurement process is really a process of
establishing entanglement between a system and an apparatus
and until we've talked about
the entanglement process
we're not going to be able to do that
I think
until we do
we simply have to
adopt the language of collapse
but
next time
remind me about collapse
I'm close to collapse
ok
for more
please visit us at stanford.edu