Stanford University.
All right,
there was an issue that
came up the last time and
I didn't understand the question.
There was a question that kept coming up and
I didn't understand what it was
until the very end of the class.
And it was an interesting and a good question,
so
I wanna go over it because it is important.
It had to do with a spin
in a magnetic field emitting a photon.
And I maintained that if it emits a photon,
remember the way we set things up.
We said let's take the
Hamiltonian to be omega over 2,
let's say sigma z.
That has two eigenvalues,
plus omega over 2 and minus omega over 2.
So the two eigenvalues.
Okay.
Let's call it E1 for energy.
The lower of the two eigenvalues
is minus omega over 2 and
the upper one is,
let's see,
we can call this E minus and
E plus,
is plus omega over 2.
So there are two energy levels.
If we drew an energy level diagram,
energy,
we would have two eigenvalues.
It would be zero over here,
but that would not be one of them.
And then we would have one,
and
one over here,
omega over 2,
and minus omega over 2.
All right,
now what can happen under such,
under,
we are not,
we have not studied this process yet,
but let's talk about it for a moment.
Given two states like this,
it is possible for an atom or a spin or,
or a system with energy levels
like this to emit a photon.
Emit a photon and go from
the upper one to the lower one,
if it's in the upper.
If it's in the lower state,
obviously it cannot emit a photon.
It doesn't have the energy to do it.
But if it's in the upper state,
it can emit a photon.
And that photon will have the
energy difference between the upper and
lower state,
so it will have an
energy of frequency or energy omega.
Sorry,
not frequency,
it will be frequency,
but more important,
it will have energy of omega.
There's an h bar missing.
I've been setting h bar equal to zero.
No.
H bar equal one.
I've been setting h bar equal to one.
It's really h bar omega,
but I'll continue to set h bar equal to one,
because we're all grown ups and we're not,
we're not afraid of setting h bar equal to one,
right?
What?
It was zero last quarter.
It was zero last quarter,
yes.
that's correct.
Right.
Okay,
so we draw a picture of the photon,
a transition.
And a photon being emitted.
Now somebody said,
what if the spin was not pointed up or down?
What if it were pointed,
here's the z axis,
what if it were pointed,
well,
let's say this way,
along the x axis.
And then it emitted a photon.
Would it not emit a photon of half the energy,
namely omega over two?
And the answer is no,
it would not emit a
photon of energy omega over two.
Let's talk,
discuss first what would happen classically.
Classically,
if we had a rotor,
a spinning rotor and
a magnetic field that had an energy which
was the typical energy would be the co,
proportional to the cosine of the
angle between the axis of the spin.
Here's the axis of the spin.
Here's the magnetic field.
The energy of that rotating
object would depend on the orientation,
the rotation of the spin relative to the magnetic field.
The energy would be minimum down and
it would gradually increase until it were up.
All right,
that's number one.
Number two,
classically and quantum mechanically,
classically the actual value,
quantum mechanically the expectation value of the spin,
precesses around the b axis with frequency omega.
That also happens classically.
It's in the,
the classical mechanics notes
in the Poisson bracket section,
where we studied exactly that question.
It wasn't called spin,
it was called angular momentum.
The spinning top does exactly the same thing.
And that spinning top,
if it really is a little electromagnet,
a little magnetic system rotating,
it will radiate.
In the process of going around with frequency omega,
it will emit radiation.
At what frequency?
Omega.
It'll emit radiation at the,
and how much radiation will it emit?
Now it's classical,
it's not emitting photons,
it's emitting classical radiation.
And it will gradually,
as it emits radiation,
fall over until it gets
down and then no more radiation.
How much energy will it emit?
It will emit all together.
And the answer depends on
the angle that it started at.
If it starts up,
it will emit all together
an amount of energy that's proportional,
essentially omega.
If it's pointing down,
it will emit no energy.
If it's pointing horizontally,
it will emit,
let's say,
omega over two.
So there'll be a continuous possible value of emission,
of radiation,
at the same time.
frequency.
Quantum mechanically,
it can only emit a photon with whatever energy
that photon has,
and the answer is a different,
it's a related but different
answer.
If it emits,
it will emit a photon of energy omega.
On the other hand,
the
probability of whether it emits is not one necessarily.
In fact,
let's suppose
that the initial state is
some alpha up plus beta down.
If alpha and beta are
equal,
that corresponds to being oriented along the x-axis.
If alpha is 1 and beta
is 0,
that's pointing up.
If alpha is 0 and beta is 1,
that's pointing down.
An up
electron,
or an up electron,
is a positive.
If alpha is 0,
that's pointing up.
If alpha is 1,
that's pointing down.
An up electron,
or an
up spin,
will emit a photon of omega omega,
of frequency omega,
of energy omega.
So if there was just the up state,
yes indeed,
it would emit omega.
If it was the
down state,
it emits nothing.
If it starts in the superposition of states,
then
with probability alpha star alpha,
it emits,
and with probability beta star
beta,
it doesn't emit.
What is the average energy
given that there's a probability alpha star
alpha that emits with a photon of
frequency omega,
energy omega,
and beta star beta that emits nothing?
What is
the average energy?
And the average energy is the same as the classical
energy.
The average energy is the same as the classical energy,
but each individual
event emits a photon of either,
either emits no photon or emits a photon of
energy omega.
Okay,
so this was a,
who asked the question?
Somebody here asked the
question.
Yeah,
is that,
yeah,
okay.
So that's the,
that's the upshot.
And it's
sort of internal consistency of quantum mechanics.
Now of course to really,
yeah.
If the electron will,
will emit a photon when it goes down in energy,
presumably it could
absorb a photon.
Yes,
yes.
That's correct.
How precise would,
would that photon have to be to omega?
That depends on the lifetime of the state.
And which in turn depends on how strongly
coupled the,
depends,
it depends on the magnitude of the dipole moment.
The stronger the dipole
moment,
the magnetic dipole moment,
the faster it will emit.
The faster it emits,
in other
words,
the shorter the lifetime of the excited state will be.
It's the inverse lifetime which sets the
scale of exactly what you're asking the,
the,
the precision with
which you have to be at exactly.
There's a spread in the energy levels.
The spread in the energy
levels or an uncertainty in the energy levels.
And the uncertainty in the energy levels is inverse to
the,
um,
to the lifetime of the state.
So,
right.
So you're absolutely right.
There,
there is an
is a spread and it's governed
by the energy time uncertainty principle,
but we're not
there yet.
Okay.
Whether we get there or not,
I don't know.
Okay.
Is this phenomenon of photon emission what's
used to create an apparatus to detect
spin?
What apparatus?
To create an apparatus that detects spin of an electron.
You could.
Do you mean for photons that you can do it?
That's one way to do it.
I decided not to think about that
as an apparatus because they didn't like it.
It didn't satisfy the rule that
if you measure a component of spin,
you leave the system
with exactly that.
After thinking about it,
I decided that did not
qualify as a genuine measuring apparatus.
Yeah.
So we're going to come to measurements and
the meaning of measurements in a little while,
but—
Oh,
it's a half an hour gone already.
Okay.
If there are no more questions,
I want to move on to the subject of entanglement.
I had a few words to say
about the collapse of a wave function.
Let's just talk about for a moment
the idea of collapse of the wave function.
We talked about how quantum states evolve.
Well,
the quantum state is a system of
events that evolve according to the Schrodinger equation.
And that is the way they evolve,
but that's the way they evolve between events where somebody
or something,
a detector or an apparatus,
or just some other system,
an external system,
interacts with the original quantum system.
So we have a quantum system.
We have other things in the world,
including observers and including apparatuses,
and just
things.
If we take away all the other things,
the system might be left in some state,
and the
system will then evolve
according to the Schrodinger equation.
And then we may bring back the other things.
The other things might be an apparatus.
Where did our apparatus go?
Our apparatus is hiding,
but it could be our apparatus or something else.
But let's say it's an apparatus,
and the apparatus measures some specific thing.
Then what happens during the course of
the interaction with the apparatus is a measurement
takes place,
and the system is left in
an eigenstate corresponding to the particular
outcome.
So for example,
we might start,
let's suppose we want to measure L.
And our system,
after a while,
might be in a state,
some summation over I,
a bunch of
complex numbers,
alpha sub I,
times eigenvectors of L.
Eigenvectors of L with eigenvalue lambda
sub I.
Okay,
what's the probability for the outcome of the experiment?
The system got here by
evolving using the Schrodinger equation.
We started it out,
we evolved it with the Schrodinger equation.
Here's what we got at the end of the day.
And now we make a measurement of L.
Okay.
And we get some specific value of lambda.
Random,
we don't know what it's going to be,
but it's going to be something.
Let's say it's lambda 7.
We measure lambda 7.
Thereafter,
or right after that,
the system is in state lambda 7.
The course of the operation of measurement
is not governed by the Schrodinger equation
for the system.
It's governed by the nature of the measuring process.
And it simply tells you that you'll come
out with one of the eigenvalues as the measured
value,
and the state vector will be just one of these.
Which one?
Random.
Random,
depending on the measure.
Now that's funny,
because you might think,
look,
well,
first of all,
let's give it a
terminology.
The terminology is the wave function has collapsed.
It has collapsed around one point.
It has collapsed around one single eigenvalue.
You can't predict which one,
but all of the structure here
with all the other ones becomes
irrelevant,
and only one state pops into existence,
so to speak.
All right,
now what's wrong with this?
What's wrong with this?
There's absolutely nothing wrong with it.
It's a correct description of the measurement process.
But what is very uncertain.
And satisfying about it is,
after all,
apparatuses are just quantum systems.
Why do we have two
rules for the way systems evolve?
One the Schrodinger equation,
and one this arbitrary collapse of the wave function.
The answer is that we,
if we want to think
quantum mechanically about the whole system
of system
system plus apparatus,
that's fine.
We can do it,
and I hope we'll get to it tonight.
And then it's pure Schrodinger equation,
but we cannot separate the system into just system
and apparatus.
We have to think about the whole
quantum system as being system plus apparatus.
That raises the question immediately,
right now,
how do you combine systems together?
If you have more than one system,
it could be an electron spin and the apparatus.
We have two systems now.
Imagine we had a good quantum theory of the apparatus.
The apparatus is a physical system.
Quantum theory governs it.
How do we describe the combined
system where we take two components,
one spin,
one apparatus,
put them together,
how do we make it into a single quantum system?
And then how,
with that single quantum system,
do we describe this process of measurement?
That is a very...
It has a very interesting...
It's confused generations of physicists,
partly because Bohr was very stubborn about
this and didn't really quite have it right.
And he was a nice man.
He was a very nice man.
I'm very glad I never met him.
No,
he was a nice man,
but the thing is he
was also a very stubborn man.
And in this particular thing,
he was mostly right.
But here and there,
he was wrong.
I mean,
apparently it was very tough to
be around him when he was.
People tried to explain to him over and over again,
you have to think of the combined system
and you have to think of the combined
quantum system if you want to understand the quantum
mechanics of measurement.
And he said,
no,
he didn't believe that.
Anyway,
combined system.
We have two systems now.
Let's just not worry about what they are.
They are two systems.
Okay.
We'll get more specific in a moment,
but let's give them names.
Let's call one of the systems A,
and A does not stand,
it could stand for apparatus,
but
it doesn't have to.
It's just A,
system A.
And we'll call the space of states of system A,
S sub A.
S sub
A could stand for system A,
but now I have it to
mean the space of quantum states of
the system A.
And we have another system I'm going to call I.
It's another system I with
its own space of states I.
The system A has states which
are labeled by a basis of states.
You choose a basis of states in the system A,
and you label them A.
A can go from 1 to
whatever the number of states of system A is,
whatever the dimensionality of the space
of states A is.
And system I has states I.
Any state of system A,
if you didn't have I,
would be a superposition
of these basis states.
Any state of system I would
be a superposition of these basis states.
Okay.
How do we put the systems
together and make a single quantum system?
Well.
I'm going to tell you what the rule is.
I'll give you a cookbook rule,
but it's pretty compelling,
and it is the way real things
work.
Okay.
You build a space of states of the system A,
I,
which means A and I together,
both of
them.
That space of states is called,
mathematically,
it is what is called the tensor product.
I'll tell you what it means in detail.
But it's the tensor product of
the two space of states S A,
and this is the symbol for
tensor product,
S I.
Now what does a tensor product mean?
Well it means something very simple.
It means you construct a new space,
a new mathematical space,
whose vectors are labeled
by a value of A and a value of I.
Okay.
In other words,
you pair off the basis vectors in all possible pairings,
one from A,
one
from I,
and you construct a basis which is labeled A I.
If this,
let's suppose the dimensionality of
this space is D sub A,
and the dimensionality
of this space is D sub I.
Or D sub,
I guess it's capital A I want here.
Okay.
D sub capital A,
and D sub capital I.
In other words,
the number of orthogonal states
of each one of these separately.
Then what's the dimensionality of the tensor product?
D A times D I.
You get to pick one
from A and one from I,
like in the Chinese restaurant,
one from A
and one from I.
Okay.
And how many are there all together?
D A times D I.
That's why it's called a product,
because the dimensionality is a product.
So this is D A times D I in dimensionality.
These are the basis states for the tensor product.
Okay.
They're labeled with two indices.
Now,
you think of them as an orthonormal basis.
Orthonormal in the following sense.
If you take two such vectors,
A I and let's say B J.
Okay.
Where B is another one
of the basis vectors of A,
and J is another one of these.
What's the inner product between these?
Let's take these to be normalized vectors.
What is the inner product between them?
And the rule for a tensor product
is the inner product between this and this.
Of course,
we have to make a bra vector out
of it in order to take its inner product.
Okay.
But if we made a bra vector out of
this and took its inner product with this one,
the
rule is that the inner product is zero unless A
is equal to B and I is equal to J.
In other words,
unless they match.
Okay.
If they don't match,
these might be observably different.
For example,
if this B was the same as this A,
but I was not the same as J,
then one half
of the system here would be observable differences
associated with observable differences in the subsystem I.
So in order for them to have an overlap,
B must equal A and J must equal I,
and then they're observably the same vector.
Excuse me.
Are these arbitrary vectors A and J?
These are basis vectors.
So they're part of an orthonormal basis.
Yes,
you could pick any orthonormal basis for this
one and any orthonormal basis for this one.
But why I have a number
of these things we're talking about here?
Yeah.
Okay.
But you could pick any orthonormal basis from
this one and any orthonormal basis from this
one and put them together this
way and you'll get the same result.
It doesn't matter which basis you pick,
but let's pick a basis to be concrete.
Let's pick a basis.
If A and I are not
the same as both B and J,
the inner product is zero.
I can write an equation for that.
B,
J,
A,
I is equal to delta,
Kronecker delta,
A,
B,
Kronecker delta,
I,
J.
If I is not equal to J
or A is not equal to B,
this is zero.
It's only non-zero if I is equal
to J and A is equal to B.
So?
These vectors form a vector.
Formally,
by construction,
which means you're simply assigning values
to things now,
but in a way that is useful,
these vectors form,
by definition or by construction,
an orthonormal basis for the combined system.
And this makes sense.
Excuse me,
another question?
Mm-hmm?
And you've defined it's dependent upon the basis by...
It does.
But actually,
as I defined it,
let's put it this way.
The words depend on the basis.
The construction in the end doesn't.
The construction in the end doesn't,
and that's not hard to show.
This is,
however,
keep in mind that these basis vectors
are not all of the vectors in
the tensor product.
You can then take any
linear combination of these basis vectors,
and they're also a vector
in the tensor product.
So,
the general vector in the tensor product is
of the form sum over I and A,
alpha,
let's
call it some IA,
IA.
A general linear combination with coefficients
that depend on what's inside here,
times the
vector,
times the basis vectors.
Now,
the answer is,
if you were to have chosen another basis.
Another vector.
Another set of bases.
You would have gotten exactly the same vectors,
except they would have been written differently.
They would have just been written in
a different basis of the combined system.
Changing basis for the individual systems corresponds
to a basis change for the combined
system.
Okay,
so that's good.
And we now have the idea of a tensor product.
And I'm going to give you a concrete example now.
The concrete example is the
next most complicated quantum system.
Namely two spins.
Well,
it's debatable whether it's the next most
complicated or the next to next most
complicated.
And the reason I say that is
because two spins have four basis vectors.
You could imagine a system with only three basis vectors,
and such systems exist.
But since we're trying to learn how to combine systems,
let's take two systems and combine
them,
each of them being a spin.
So what do we have?
We have an electron nailed
down at this position over here,
and it has a spin,
which we're
going to call sigma.
And it has three components,
sigma,
x,
y,
and z.
So sigma,
x,
y,
and z.
And we have another one over here.
We need a name for it.
Now I toyed for a while
with calling this one sigma one,
this one sigma two,
but there
were too many indices.
Then I had sigma two.
Sigma one x,
sigma one y,
but they're bad.
So I decided to give this one another name.
And the Greek letter that comes after sigma is tau.
I don't know if it's the next letter.
It's the one in the English alphabet,
st,
yeah.
So the next one I think
in the Greek alphabet is tau.
And I simply call this one tau.
How many components does tau have?
Well tau is also a spin.
So it also has three components,
x,
y,
and z.
Supposing I choose for the
basis vectors for each of these,
the up and down basis vectors.
In other words,
the states in which sigma z is up or down,
and the states in which tau
z are up and down.
Then our basis vectors for sigma are up and down.
Okay.
Our basis vectors for tau are exactly the same.
Up and down.
And maybe in order to indicate that
these are vectors for the system tau,
and these
are vectors for the system sigma,
let's use a slightly different kind of bracket notation
here.
Let's use a curly bracket.
I'm going to give that up very shortly.
I just want to point out
to you that these are the two.
These are different than these.
And down.
So good.
What is the basis vectors for the combined system?
If we put the systems together,
what are the basis vectors for the combined system?
There are four of them.
Two times two is four.
And what are they?
They are states in which both spins are up.
That's one of them.
One spin.
And I'll always take the first entry here to correlate.
The first entry is the
first entry to correspond to sigma.
And the second entry to correspond to tau.
Up down.
Down up.
And down down.
That's the four basis vectors.
Each basis vector carrying two labels now.
A sigma label and a tau label.
That's the idea.
And it's a very reasonable idea.
I'm going to go back to the first one.
Yes.
Suppose these two component systems interact.
Doesn't that change things somehow?
No,
the basis vectors stay the same.
But the linear combination of basis vectors
that they're describing the system will change.
Yeah.
So any state in this space can be written as
an alpha up up times up up plus an alpha
up down up down.
Plus.
An alpha down up down.
Down up plus an alpha down down down down.
That's the most general thing we can write.
Let's call it psi.
The answer to your question is if
you started out with a particular linear combination.
Let's say for example just alpha up up up up.
Both spins up.
And you let them interact.
Then in general what will
happen is these coefficients will change.
In fact it could even happen that after a
time alpha up up might go to alpha down down.
In other words two spins up might interact in
such a way as to just wind up down.
That would not be a change
in what the basis vectors are.
It would be a change in what the alphas are.
Okay.
So.
Uh.
Okay.
So.
All right.
Now there are several questions we can ask.
Incidentally one of the criteria for doing this
correctly is that if we take the combined
system but then we only do experiments
on one of the halves of it.
The other one doing whatever it's doing
and they're well separated from each other.
Let's suppose.
They're well separated from each other and
we do experiments on only one of them.
The answers that we get should be the same
answers that we got when we didn't even think
of it as a combined system.
If we have a theory of sigma which
we've talked about now for five weeks I think.
And we know all about it.
We know how to do experiments on it.
And now we think of it as
half a system composed of sigma and tau.
But sigma and tau are
far from each other let's say.
They're not interacting with each other substantially.
And we do exactly the same experiments
that we've been talking about up till now.
We should get the same answers.
So we should put these things together in
a way which makes sure that the earlier issues,
the earlier description of
either subsystem is still correct.
Now I'm not going to bother proving that.
I think you'll get the idea
and you'll see how it works.
And the way we are
putting things together does guarantee that.
Okay.
Now we can go in two directions from here.
We can talk about the space of
states or we can talk about the observables.
And we're going to do both.
We're going to do both.
But I'll take a vote.
How many people want to
talk about the space of states?
How many want to talk about the observables?
We'll talk about the space of states first.
You knew I was going to do that.
Come on.
All right.
Yeah.
One question.
Are we allowed to pick left and right?
What's that?
Oh,
yeah,
yeah.
Sure.
There are.
Yeah.
Supposing we wanted a state which was
left for sigma and up for tau.
All right.
So this would be a state which would be prepared.
We have two apparatuses now.
I'm always uncomfortable with the word apparatuses.
I always think it should be apparati,
but I don't think that's right.
We have two apparatuses.
One.
That's right.
That we apply to sigma.
The other that we apply to tau.
And we now take our apparatus,
one apparatus,
the sigma apparatus.
We point it in the,
let's say,
the xy,
not the xy,
along the x axis.
And the other one,
and we point along the z axis.
And we wind up discovering that sigma
was along the x axis with plus 1.
And tau was along the
z axis also with plus 1.
So that means that sigma was up,
but tau was right.
How do we make a state which is...
So the answer is this.
You,
I'll tell you what you do,
but then we'll eventually have a mathematics to this.
Sigma is definitely up.
But tau is a linear superposition of up with down.
Okay.
Easy.
You just take up up plus up down.
Square root of 2.
1 over square root of 2.
You can think of this another way.
You can say,
think of it as a product.
A product of up for sigma and right for tau.
Now,
what is right?
Right is up plus down,
right?
Right.
Right is up plus down.
So this can also be written as up times,
and I'm going to put a big square bracket around
it,
up,
squiggly bracket,
plus down.
But if I want to normalize it,
I should put a square root of 2 downstairs.
Okay.
So we just think of it as a
product of sigma up and tau in the,
along the right direction.
But that's the same thing here.
We have 1 over square root of 2 up up.
That's this one.
And 1 over square root of 2 up down.
Okay.
I'm not sure if this answered your question or not.
I think it probably partly did.
Yeah.
Okay.
Right.
And,
you know,
okay.
This kind of state is called a product state.
It's a product state in which you
know exactly what's going on with sigma,
namely it's in
the up direction,
and you know exactly what's going on with tau.
It's in the right direction.
It's a product state,
and it's simply two separate
things which were prepared independently,
and here it is.
A product state is by definition a product.
Let's write the most general product state.
The most general,
but this is not a,
this is not the most general product state.
The most general product state can be written as follows.
Alpha up up plus alpha down down.
That's for sigma.
And then for tau,
let's call it beta.
Let's call the coefficients for,
for tau,
let's call them beta.
Beta up up squiggly plus beta down down.
What does this mean?
This means that sigma was prepared
in this particular linear combination here.
It might have been by holding
your detector in some funny angle.
And this one is the response to
holding the tau detector at some other angle.
Had you had only one of these,
not the other,
you would just have written this down.
Had the other one,
you would have written this down.
Together,
you write down the product.
That's the rule.
Okay,
that's the rule.
And of course,
you know,
ultimately these rules are the rules because they agree with
experiment,
but it's a pretty plausible rule.
This is a product.
We could also write it alpha
up beta up times up up.
Plus alpha up beta down up down.
Do I need to write the rest of it?
Well,
I will.
Plus alpha down beta up down up.
Plus alpha down beta down down down.
All right,
now of course,
this is of the form of a general vector,
but there's something special about this.
There's something special about the coefficients here.
The coefficients factorize into it and therefore this
is in a certain sense special to some extent.
Let's see if we can quantify how special.
Yeah?
What kind of vector product is that?
That's a tensor product.
This is an element of a tensor product and
it's the tensor product of this vector with that vector.
Okay.
It's a vector drawn in the composite system as a tensor product
of a vector describing one system and a vector describing the other system.
So strictly speaking,
the tensor product is usually used for the whole space.
But then you would say this is
a product state within the tensor product space.
And I'll just call it a
tensor product state or product state.
It's not general.
And to see how non-general it is,
we can count parameters.
Given a general system,
a general state vector,
how many parameters,
how many independent parameters does it take to describe it?
And the answer is four complex numbers.
Alpha up up,
alpha up down,
alpha down up,
alpha down down.
I am not assuming that it has this special form.
Just general four numbers.
Four complex numbers is eight real numbers.
But that's a little too much because
we should assume that the state is normalized.
So that's one constraint.
And we also know the overall phase is not important.
So when you count parameters,
you always subtract two.
One for the normalization and one for the phase.
Eight minus two is six.
Six real parameters.
Six real parameters describing a general state of two spins.
How many here?
Well,
the state describing the sigma particle,
that has two real parameters.
Four real parameters for alpha up and alpha down,
but then we subtract two.
Same thing here.
This is a normalized state,
and its overall phase doesn't matter.
This is a normalized state.
Its overall phase doesn't matter.
Altogether,
four real parameters.
It's the same four real
parameters that you might have guessed
if you just said I have two spins.
Each spin had two parameters
necessary to write down its state.
Two real parameters.
The real parameters could have been
the polarization directions of the spin.
The axis along which the spin is oriented.
Or...
So there are four parameters here,
but six parameters here.
That simply proves that not all states are product states.
In fact,
most states are not product states.
We're going to talk about
some non-product states soon enough,
but this is the notion of a product state.
And in the product state,
we can really think of separate states
for each of the particles or each of the subsystems.
But for a more general state,
you can't really divide it
into a state for one subsystem
and a state for the other subsystem.
They're entangled.
They're entangled in a more elaborate and more...
I don't know what the word is.
Entangled.
They're entangled in a more entangled way.
We're going to discuss that entanglement.
That's a very important concept,
of course.
Okay.
So that's two spins.
How many parameters?
Six versus four.
They're entangled.
Right?
We talked about product states.
And that's what we know about
the space of states of this system.
It takes six parameters to describe it.
Well,
only four parameters if it's a product state.
Product states are the ones
for which you can separately say
there's a state for one system
and a state for the other system.
End of story.
Okay.
Now let's talk about observables.
Now we come to observables.
What are the observables for this composite system?
Well,
they must be the same observables
as for the separate systems by themselves.
In other words,
sigma x,
y,
and z and tau x,
and z.
They are the things you could measure with two apparatuses
of the same kind as we
used in our experiments on one spin.
We now have two of them.
And so we have sigma x,
sigma y,
and sigma z and tau x,
tau y,
and tau z.
Let's see if we can figure
out how these operators ought to operate
on the states of the combined system.
Now you can sort of guess.
I'll spell it out,
but here's the rule.
Let's take sigma x,
and let's apply it to
a state of the sigma system.
Obviously,
it belongs with the sigma system.
If it applies to up,
it gives down.
If it applies to down,
it gives up.
You can check that.
That's the fact that sigma x is equal to 0,
1,
1.
This off-diagonal character means it takes
up to down and down to up.
This is what sigma x does
ordinarily if we only had one subsystem.
Here's what it does on the combined system.
Sigma x on any vector which
begins with up and has anything...
Let's see.
Which one was a and which one was i?
Second one was i?
Tau went with i or tau went with i?
Tau was i.
Okay.
So sigma x,
when it acts on up i,
all it sees is the up...
All it sees is the first thing here,
and it's completely passive
with respect to the second index.
In other words,
it doesn't even notice the second index.
It leaves it the same.
It doesn't change it.
But it does whatever it
should do on the first entry.
Likewise,
sigma x on down i equals up i.
You just take what it
did for the single spin space,
and you just think of the
other index as a kind of spectator
that just goes along for the ride.
Doesn't do anything.
On the other hand...
Oh,
let's do one more.
One more sigma.
Sigma z on up i.
Well,
what does sigma z do when it acts on up?
Sigma z is 1 minus 1,
0,
0.
It just gives back up with value 1.
So that's just up i.
And what about sigma z on down i?
Well,
what happens when sigma z hits down?
Minus down.
So this gives minus down i.
How about sigma y?
Well,
sigma y does something very
much the same as sigma x,
except it throws an i,
not this i,
but the numerical complex number i,
throws it around because...
What is it?
Sigma x...
This is sigma z.
Sigma x was 1 minus 1,
and sigma y was equal to minus i,
i,
0,
0.
Sigma y also flips up
to down and down to up,
but it throws in a gratuitous i here and there.
Okay,
so that's what sigma does.
Now,
how about tau?
Well,
tau does exactly the same thing,
except that the first entry becomes the spectator,
and only the second entry gets acted on.
So let's do this one.
Tau,
let's say,
x on a up.
a could be anything.
Now,
a can be up or down.
It doesn't matter.
Tau x on a up
is equal to a times down,
and tau x on a
down is equal to a up.
All right,
let's do tau z.
Tau z on a up equals a up,
and tau z on a down
is equal to minus a down.
And you can figure out the action
of the y components of the spin.
It's straightforward.
With this definition,
it's quite clear that if you're
talking about an observable associated with sigma,
that the tau degrees of freedom are completely passive.
Nothing happens to them.
The eigenvectors of the components of sigma
are simply product states of the eigenvectors
of sigma times any vector for tau.
In other words,
for example,
the eigenvector...
the eigenvectors of...
let's take sigma y.
Ordinarily,
the eigenvectors of sigma y
are 1i or 1 minus i.
I can't remember which one has
eigenvalue plus 1 or minus 1,
but one of the others.
All right.
That means...
that means the linear combination up plus i down.
That's an eigenvector of sigma y.
If you want the eigenvector of sigma y,
when we're talking about the composite system,
it's exactly the same,
except you put an alpha...
an i in here,
I guess.
An i in here and an i in here.
Same i.
So,
for example,
it could be up up plus i down up,
or up down plus i down down.
The i is a spectator.
It just goes along for the ride.
Anything which was an eigenvector for the single system
remains an eigenvector for the single system,
except you have to add in
the index for the other particle,
for the other subsystem.
And that's all there is to it.
With these definitions,
as I said,
it's pretty clear that the separate subsystems
behave independently,
quite independently,
as long as you don't let
them interact and feel each other
or do something interesting with each other,
as long as they are kept separated.
Okay.
Um...
Other questions?
Quick question.
Yeah.
Those equations sigma x acting on u
against m and sigma x acting on u...
Yeah.
Shouldn't those...
Since you have sigma x acting on an object,
shouldn't that result in a super positional state?
No.
Sigma x...
Expanded up in terms of the eigenstates of sigma x,
right?
Well,
let's just do it by matrices.
Sigma x is .
Up is .
Okay?
What happens?
This times this is 0.
This times this is 1.
So up has gone to down.
Okay?
Likewise,
if we put a 0 here and a 1 here,
this would become a 1,
0.
So it just takes one 0
and flips it to a 0,
1,
and back and forth like that.
In general,
of course,
you would be right,
but for this particular case,
it just gives you back...
I see how the 1s and 0s work out,
but I'm trying to map that into the physical situation
where you're...
You're making the measurement of the x direction
of the state that's prepared this way.
Well,
this doesn't say...
This doesn't say...
Let's see.
This doesn't say 1,
0 and 0,
1 are eigenvectors of sigma x.
Far from it.
It's about as far from
an eigenvector as you can get.
When you act with sigma x on this one,
you get a completely orthogonal state.
So this is not the rule that says...
This is not the equation that says,
that 0,
1 or 1,
0 are eigenvectors.
An eigenvector is a vector which
is kept in the same direction
by action of the operator.
This is...
As far as you can get from that,
the operator acts and gives you something orthogonal.
And that's...
Okay?
All right,
you'll have to work that out.
Up is a linear superposition of left and right.
It is.
Right.
Indeed it is.
That's correct.
That sort of connects to my question before class,
which is,
so is there any physical meaning
to applying an operator to a non-eigenvector?
Well...
What does that operation equate to?
Most of the times,
that's just an auxiliary operation
in some calculation or other.
Well,
it doesn't have any particular special physical meaning,
but in this particular case,
what it tells you is 0,
1 and 1,
are about as far from eigenvectors as you can get.
And what it tells you is
that if you measure sigma x,
in an eigenstate of sigma z,
it's as random as it can be.
Okay.
It's as random as it can be.
All right,
we're going along good.
Yeah?
So in this product rotation that you have,
what happens if I have sigma
x tau x operating on t?
Say it again.
In the product,
first equation that you have,
tau x on t gives you a t.
What happens...
Yes.
What happens if I have sigma
x and tau x operating on t?
You mean sigma x times tau x?
Okay.
We can work that out.
Let's do it.
It's a little bit late.
It's five minutes later in the notes,
but let's do it right now since we're at it.
Let's take sigma x,
tau x,
and tell me what vector you
would like to apply it to.
How about up up?
Let's do up up.
What does tau x do?
Let's see.
Tau...
I keep forgetting.
No,
this one...
The one on the left is sigma,
right?
This one's sigma,
and this one's tau,
right?
Okay.
All right,
so we start with tau.
And we hit this.
What does tau x do?
It operates on this one and leaves this one.
This one alone.
So this gives...
Do I have it wrong?
Yeah.
It operates on this one and leaves this one alone.
Right.
Okay,
so it gives sigma x.
I have not acted with that yet.
Times...
Now,
tau x flips this one.
So it's up down.
Okay,
now what does sigma x do?
It flips this one.
So it just gives down down.
Kind of boring,
but that's what it does.
Let's do it in the opposite order.
Let's take tau x times sigma x on up up.
What does it do?
It does exactly the same thing.
Sigma x hits one of these and flips them.
And it flips this one.
And then tau x comes and
hits the other one and flips it.
So when tau x times sigma x acts,
it gives exactly the same thing
as sigma x times tau x.
Commutator of sigma x with tau x equals zero.
No difference between the order of operations.
Let's try it for sigma x times tau z.
Okay,
let's do it for sigma x times
tau z and see what we get.
Oh,
I have not proved this because
I only exhibited for one particular state.
In order to argue that sigma x times
tau x equals tau x times sigma x,
you would have to show that they give
the same thing when x is equal to zero.
They're acting on any basis vector.
It's enough to show that they
give the same thing on basis vectors.
All right,
but that's pretty easy.
Not hard to do.
You can do it on any basis vector.
And you'll find out that
the order of operations doesn't matter.
In fact,
the same is true if you take sigma x times,
let's say,
tau z.
Let's do it again.
Shall I take a different vector?
Let's take some other vector.
Instead of up down,
let's take down up.
And see what it does.
And then we'll do it in the opposite order.
All right,
what does tau z do
when it hits this vector here?
It only acts on the second entry.
And it's a z component,
so it just gives plus one on an up,
right?
So this just gives sigma x times down up.
Tau z on up.
Gives up.
So that just goes right through.
And what does sigma x
do when it hits down up?
This gets to be a little bit gobbly gook.
At this point,
my tongue starts rebelling.
What does sigma x do when it hits this guy?
It just flips down to up.
So it gives up up,
right?
Let's do it in the opposite order.
So we have z sigma x on down up.
All right,
first sigma x.
That flips down to up.
So it gives us tau z times up up.
And then tau z just gives
one when it hits the up here.
So it gives the same thing again.
And you can sort of see why.
If they're acting on separate indices here,
it doesn't matter which way you order them.
This is very general.
It doesn't matter which state you take.
It doesn't matter which component you take.
Any component of sigma commutes with any component of tau.
You can check that just by knowing how they act.
All right,
so we can say sigma anything.
I'm not sure what to call the index here.
Sigma,
I don't want to call it i.
We've already used i for something.
But...
Uh...
Sigma...
M.
N.
Sigma and tau M.
For any n and m,
they commute.
The meaning of that is that
if you have two separate subsystems,
which are combined in this way,
the observables for one and the observables
for the other can be simultaneously measured.
In particular,
if you took the systems in far apart,
and you treat them as a single quantum system,
you would expect that measuring one of them
doesn't interfere with any measurement of the other one.
And that's what this says.
That measuring a sigma does not preclude measuring a tau,
and vice versa,
for any components of them.
So in that sense,
they behave like independent systems.
You can make any measurement on sigma,
and any measurement on tau.
Yeah.
So what we've got so far is we've got
these observables on each independent part of the subsystem,
on each piece of the system.
And we can think about an observable
as one part is happening in this system.
Yeah.
It's as happy as it was
before you added the other subsystem.
Are there other observables?
Yes.
Yes,
that's a good question.
Are there observables which are somehow more
intimately connected with having both of them?
The answer is yes.
For example,
sigma times tau.
Sigma times tau,
sigma x times tau x,
or sigma x times tau y,
that sort of thing are observables that somehow know
more intimately about the combination of both of them.
And they know,
in particular,
about entanglement.
You started with independent.
You just said spins in,
spins out.
Now,
how are you linking them so
that they defend all each other?
We haven't yet.
What we've done up till now is do all the ingredients
which tell you that as long as you do separate experiments,
separate operations on the two subsystems,
that they will behave exactly as they would
have had the other system not been there.
But now you can ask,
what about?
Are there more,
are there more,
in particular,
if the system is,
the combined system,
if it's in a product state,
if it's in a product state so
that each component has its own state vector,
then the quantum mechanics of each one
of them is separate from the other.
They don't interfere with each other.
They don't know about each other in any way.
That's what this prescription ensures.
So they're not entangled yet?
No,
no,
they're not entangled yet.
Not if they're product states.
Now what we found out is that
the product states are a four parameter set.
We found out also that the
full space of states has six parameters.
So there are apparently states which are not product states.
Those are the states which have,
to varying degrees,
a degree of entanglement.
I'm going to write down now the most entangled state,
and we're going to examine it a little
bit and see in what way it's odd.
Up or down?
There are many highly entangled states,
maximally entangled states.
I'm writing one,
one particular one.
Minus,
and I'm putting the minus here just because I
happen to know that it has a particular property,
which is not so important at this stage,
but let's put the minus there.
Minus,
down,
up.
One over square root of two,
of course.
One over square root of two times the whole thing.
Now,
this state is interesting.
It has the property that if you may,
well,
it has a correlation.
If you know that tau is down,
then signal must be up.
On the other hand,
if you know that tau is up,
then signal must be down.
Now,
what does that mean mathematically?
We're going to find out
exactly what that means mathematically.
This is not a product state.
There is no way that this can
be written as a product of one state.
It's a sum or a difference
in this case of two product states,
but it is not a product state.
How can we tell?
So,
let's consider...
the expectation value in a
state of the components of sigma.
Let's go back to the one subsystem,
to the one system quantum mechanics,
one spin.
And let's ask,
what do we know about that?
In particular,
I'm interested in expectation values of...
in any state.
Take a state.
And take the expectation value of all three components...
This is the average value...
I'm not multiplying or anything,
I'm just considering them individually.
Can they all be zero?
Can they all simultaneously be zero for...
for an ordinary state of...
for the ordinary two-parameter family
of states of a single system?
Should we take a vote
or should I just tell you?
The answer is no.
They cannot all be zero.
And here's the reason.
Well...
The reason is,
given any state,
there is always a direction in space,
in three-dimensional space,
a direction for which sigma in that direction,
the component of sigma in that direction,
is definite and equal to plus one.
Given any psi,
this is what I told you
in the very beginning of the lecture,
or maybe even before the lecture,
given any state,
there is some linear combination of sigmas,
which is definitely equal to plus one.
In that case,
if I find that particular combination,
nx,
you know,
dot sigma into n,
that particular linear combination,
its expectation value can't be zero,
because it's definitely up along that direction.
So the answer is,
given any state,
there is always some direction,
let's call it sigma dot n,
that depends on psi,
it depends on psi,
sigma dot n,
for which this is...
It's not only not zero,
but it's equal to plus one.
The average of sigma dot n is of course...
If sigma dot n is definite,
if it's known and there's no ambiguity about it,
then the average is just equal to
the value that it's known to be.
So there is always some n.
Alright.
For any psi,
there exists
an n
such that
this is true.
Therefore it cannot be true
that all of these can simultaneously be zero.
For a state of a single spin...
You can't measure them all simultaneously.
But if I give you a state,
I tell you the state,
then I can...
Then you can tell me
what direction of space
should you orient your detector
so that the answer comes out plus one.
Okay?
For example,
I mean,
I can just give you up.
Okay,
so what direction,
if I gave you up,
what direction should you orient your detector to?
Along the z-axis.
What if I gave you up plus down?
With square root of two.
What direction should you orient your detector to make it?
To make sure that you get plus one.
Along the x-axis,
right?
Okay.
What if I gave you up plus i down?
I don't know,
some...
Either plus y or minus y.
Okay,
I forget which one.
Given any combination,
there are enough directions
that you can find the direction
for which sigma in that direction
is definitely plus one.
And therefore,
it cannot be
that all of these expectation values
are all zero.
Why?
Because you know that sigma dot n
is equal to plus one.
And that's,
of course,
just a linear combination of these.
Okay,
so as I said,
it's impossible
if we have just a state of one spin
isolated by itself.
It's been prepared somehow.
However it's prepared,
there exists a direction
in which the spin
is definite and not equal to zero.
Okay.
Um...
What about this state?
What about this state by now?
Let's take sigma
and ask whether any of the components
of sigma
have a non-zero expectation value
in this state.
What I'm going to show,
I'll tell you the answer right now.
We're going to show that
all three components of sigma
have zero expectation value
in this state.
That means this state cannot possibly be
a product state.
A product state is one in which
each component behaves as if it were just
a state of the subsystem by itself.
This state is going to behave in a way that
no simple product state could possibly behave.
We're going to find...
And so let's do it...
Let's do it...
Um...
Okay,
let's put...
The square root of 2 here is not important.
That's not the important thing.
We have up-down minus down-up.
We're going to take the expectation value.
So that means we have to make a sandwich.
The sandwich will have up-down minus down-up.
And in the middle here,
we're going to put a sigma.
We could do the same with tau.
We get the same answer.
So let's put sigma z first.
Let's put sigma z here and see what we get.
First we act with sigma z.
And what does sigma z give when it hits up-down?
It just gives up-down,
right?
All right.
All right,
so this just gives up-down.
But what does it give when
it hits this guy over here?
It gives up-down.
So this is the minus down-up.
But there's already a minus down-up,
so there's a plus.
There's already a minus.
The minus gets killed.
That's over here.
And that's the inner product.
Let's put some bracket around it.
That's the inner product with up-down minus down-up.
Okay,
let's calculate it.
What's down-up with up-down?
Zero.
What's down-up with down-up?
One.
So we get a one.
What's down-up with up-down?
Zero.
Oh,
oh,
I got something wrong here.
What did I do here?
This should be up-down,
right?
Yeah,
up-down.
Okay,
so let's go back.
Up-down with up-down is one.
Up-down with down-up is zero.
All right.
What about down-up with up-down?
Zero.
What about down-up with down-down?
One.
One,
but there's a minus sign here.
So this is orthogonal to this.
The inner product is zero,
and it says that the expectation value
of sigma z is equal to zero.
Sigma z in this state,
not any state,
but in this state,
is zero.
Let's try sigma x.
Let's try sigma x next and see what we get.
So we have sigma x here.
All right,
let's build our sandwich again.
We have a minus sign here.
And what happens when sigma x equals up-down,
hits up-down?
It flips up to down.
Sigma x is the flipper,
and it flips the first entry here.
So it flips the first entry to
down and flips this entry to up.
We're taking the inner product with this vector over here.
So let's see.
Is there anything in common over
here with something in common here?
No.
So there's no way to get an inner product.
Down-up with down-down is zero,
et cetera,
et cetera.
Again,
this is zero.
So sigma x is equal to zero.
Expectation value.
Okay.
What about sigma y?
Let's put sigma y there.
Sigma y is also a flip-flop operator.
It flips up to down and down to up,
but with an i.
I don't remember which,
where the i goes.
It either goes here,
here,
something like that.
But whatever it does,
it flips this up to down,
so we get a down-down.
And it flips this down to up,
so we get an up-up.
Again,
no inner product.
It's zero.
So there we are.
All three components have zero expectation value.
But that's funny because we proved,
well,
we didn't prove,
but I told you that if I
take any state of a single spin,
it is never the case that
all three sigmas have zero expectation value.
What's the lesson?
The lesson is that there are states of the composite system that can
in no way ever be thought of as separate states for the two subsystems.
That's what entanglement is.
That's an example of entanglement.
Yeah.
So one thing you didn't show here,
but maybe it's obvious,
is that if you do have a product state,
then it will satisfy the same property
where one of them will be not.
Yes.
That's correct.
Isn't that straightforward to show?
Well,
if you show it for the single spin by itself,
then remember the other index
just goes along for the ride.
So however you derived it for one spin by itself,
you'll do exactly the same derivation except put a
sort of spectator index to ride along with it.
So,
yeah,
it's obvious that if it's true for one subsystem
by itself that it will be true for the composite.
What's not obvious is that it's true for one subsystem.
Okay,
so,
yeah.
So that's an exercise.
That's an exercise to show that all three
components of the expectation values cannot be zero,
and that there's always a direction in which it's maximum.
So how do you put
a system in this strange state?
Yeah,
it's a very natural state to have.
I'll tell you,
if you have two spins and the
two spins are interacting with each other,
they will have a,
in particular,
if they're little magnetic moments,
then they will have an interaction with each
other which will prefer to make them anti-align.
Now,
this is anti-aligned up-down.
This is anti-aligned down-up.
And in fact,
this combination here has the lowest energy.
This combination has the lowest energy.
It has less energy than up-down plus down-up.
So if you bring these two
spins together and you wait a while,
they'll radiate a photon eventually and come to this state.
Right?
So it's actually not at all
hard to get this kind of state.
It's rather easy to get this kind of state.
And we'll discuss that when we talk about interactions.
But it's a typical situation that this is a result.
If you take two spins,
put them together,
and let them come to equilibrium by radiating a photon.
Yeah?
You said bring a while.
How long is a while?
A long time.
What determines the length of the...
First of all,
how close you bring them together.
Second of all,
how big the magnetic dipoles of the spin are.
And that has to do with the
strength of coupling to the electromagnetic field.
So,
you know,
an ordinary laboratory situation.
In an atom,
the electrons are close enough together
that they will radiate a photon
in not too long a time
to achieve this so-called singlet state.
This is called a singlet state.
I'm not going to tell you why right now.
There are four basis vectors all together.
The reason that this one is called a singlet
is because there are three others which are the triplet.
Okay?
Can you give a feel for why up-down,
bump-down-up would have higher energy?
Yeah,
well,
not at the moment,
but eventually.
I will tell you the answer,
though.
If you think of these as little angular momenta,
and you put them in up-down,
minus-down-up,
the total angular momentum is zero.
If you put them down-up plus down-up,
the total angular momentum is one.
And energy is often proportional to angular momentum.
So,
but yeah,
we can come to that.
Eventually we'll come to that.
It's a fair question.
But let's not try to answer it right this minute.
Yeah?
If you take a general state
of two systems like we have,
is it possible to change the basis such
that one basis creates a subspace of product states
and the other is purely entangled states?
You're asking whether the notion
of entanglement is an invariant notion.
The answer is yes.
There's a very definite quantity that you can calculate,
called the entanglement entropy,
which measures the strength of entanglement,
which is not dependent on any particular basis.
Now,
I might tell you right now,
this state,
okay,
this state does have a special feature
that up-down plus down-up wouldn't have.
Supposing you took this state,
and this is a good homework assignment,
up and down,
individually for both sigma and tau,
can be rewritten in terms of left and right.
For example,
up is left plus right,
down is left minus right,
or whatever it is.
The square roots of two are there,
but you know what I mean.
Okay.
Supposing I write this state,
I plug in every place I see down,
left minus right,
and every place I see up,
left plus right.
What do I get out of this?
The answer is very simple.
I get left right minus right left.
Supposing I rewrite it in terms of in and out,
what do I get?
In out minus out in.
So,
the structure that this state has,
the nature of it,
is actually the same in every basis.
In every basis,
it looks the same,
and that would not be true for up-down plus down-up.
Down-up and up-down,
they would,
um,
uh,
okay,
they would get mixed up with other states.
There are three other states.
This is one.
There are three others.
The three others are,
well,
obviously there are three others,
and they mix up with each
other when you change the basis.
But this is not obvious.
This is not obvious at all.
All right,
let's do one last thing.
I'm not sure whether it'll
be the last thing or not.
I think it's probably the last thing for tonight.
Um,
let's ask now about one of these observables,
which is not an observable that can be identified
with either subsystem,
but which has somehow got to do with both.
All right,
and let's look at its expectation value.
A very simple example.
Let's take...
Let's take the expectation value of the product
of sigma z times tau z.
We'll do that one.
We'll do sigma x times tau x.
And maybe we'll do sigma x times tau y,
or,
sigma x.
We'll do,
we'll try some examples.
Let's take the expectation value of this.
Now,
to do this,
we again make a sandwich.
And,
uh,
all right,
so let's do it.
Up,
down,
whoops,
sorry.
Now I should put the square root of 2 in.
The reason I should put the
square root of 2 in now
is because I'm not going to get 0.
So if I really want to get the numerical number,
I want to put that square root of 2 in.
And here we have
up,
down,
minus,
up.
Also over square root of 2.
So in fact,
I can take the square root of 2's
and put them all into
a factor of 1 half here.
This is the expectation value in the singlet state.
Here we take the singlet state,
and we take sigma z times tau z.
Let's see what we get.
All right,
first of all,
when sigma z,
when tau z acts,
what does it do?
Do you remember?
I don't,
oh,
yes.
Tau z doesn't flip.
It just gives you a sign,
which is plus for this one
and minus for this one.
So we can remove the tau z
just by putting a minus sign here,
right?
Did I do that right?
Hm?
Let me see.
Tau z.
Tau z acts on down to give minus down.
It acts on up to give up.
So it has no effect on this term,
and it changes the sign of this term.
I think I did it right.
No?
Yeah,
okay.
Minus.
Now what about sigma z?
What does it do?
It flips the sign.
No,
it doesn't flip.
It gives plus on this one
and minus on this one.
So it changes the sign of this one.
Okay,
now we have to put it together.
We have up down,
up down,
with a minus sign.
It's a minus one.
We have down up with down up.
Minus one.
Cross terms give nothing.
Up down with down up gives nothing.
Down up with up down gives nothing.
There are two terms.
You get a two over two.
Two?
Hm?
Minus two over two.
Equals minus one.
What does this say?
This is kind of interesting.
Um,
the expectation value of sigma x by itself was zero.
The expectation value of tau x by itself was zero.
The expectation value of sigma x
times tau x is minus one.
Let's see if we can see why.
Look at the state here.
In this component over here,
obviously,
sorry,
this was sigma z,
sigma z.
Sigma z we were talking about.
Sigma z are opposite in both contributions here.
Sigma z times sigma z
for this piece is minus one.
Why is that?
This one's up,
this one's down.
If sigma z is plus for this one,
sigma z is minus for this one,
the product is negative.
The product is negative one for this one also.
In fact,
if you think about it,
this state is an eigenvector
of sigma z times tau z.
What's the eigenvalue?
Minus one.
So in fact,
this state is a state in
which if you measured the product,
sigma z,
tau z,
you would get minus one every single time.
So the expectation value is minus one.
Nevertheless,
the expectation value of the individual sigma x,
sorry,
sigma z's and tau z's is zero.
So this is beginning to get something wrong.
So to get some of the
flavor of what an entangled state is,
it simply doesn't behave like
you might expect two separate systems
which are just independent and have always been independent.
They behave.
Let's try,
this is undoubtedly going to get boring now,
but let's do it anyway.
This is plus minus.
We'll go back to the original sandwich.
But instead of sigma z,
let's do sigma x,
tau x.
Alright,
so sigma x times tau x,
it's easy to figure that out.
Tau x flips the second entry.
Sigma x flips the first entry.
Alright,
so this object here simply flips
both entries without changing any signs.
It flips no entry at all.
What did I say?
Yeah.
So what does it do?
It looks like it interchanges these two.
Right?
Interchanges these two,
makes this one minus and this one plus.
Now what's the inner product?
Up down with minus up down,
minus one.
Down up,
or minus down up with down up,
minus one again.
Again,
minus two over two equals minus one.
Same exact thing as...
And what would you guess about sigma y,
tau y?
There's nothing special about the y-axis,
same thing.
Also has an expectation value equal to zero.
So it's a product of expectation values.
So,
alright,
this,
again,
is telling you very clearly
this can't be a product state.
For a product state,
the expectation value of a product like this
would just be the product of expectation values.
And that's not what's going on here.
So this is a highly entangled state.
About as entangled as you can get.
Excuse me.
Will we take the product of two observables?
Sorry,
that's too...
Two operators,
essentially.
So,
how I should think of that physically?
Is that one alternate followed by another observation?
In this case,
remember,
no,
you don't think of...
Not in general,
no.
In general,
it's just another operator.
If it's Hermitian,
it's another observable.
It can be measured.
But in this case,
since all sigmas commute with all taus,
you can think about measuring them both simultaneously.
Alright?
And in fact,
if you measure them both simultaneously,
you will simply discover the obvious
fact that they are oppositely oriented.
Alright,
let's do one more.
Let's do...
Since I haven't worked it out,
and I never worked it out,
I'm going to work it out right now.
Let's do sigma x times tau z.
Let's do sigma x...
Oops,
what did I write here?
Sigma x,
tau x.
Alright.
Let's do sigma x times tau
z and see what we get.
I don't know the answer,
so let's do it.
I have a suspicion that...
No,
I have a suspicion...
Okay,
we'll find out.
What happens when tau z acts on this guy here?
Tau z just changes the sign,
right?
Tau z...
Just changes the sign.
If it's down,
you get minus one.
If it's up,
you get plus one.
You're going to flip them around,
so I flip them around.
Oh,
I flipped them around.
Yes,
you're right.
Good.
Yeah.
Okay,
so tau z sees the down
here and makes it minus down.
It sees the up here and leaves it alone.
Okay.
Now what does sigma x do?
Sigma x flips the first entry,
and so it gives minus down down minus...
Now let's see.
It flips minus up up,
right?
Now we have to take the
inner product with this guy over here.
Well,
nothing over here matches anything over here,
so we see that the
answer in this case is zero.
We see the answer is zero.
The expectation value of sigma x
times tau z or any non-equal ones,
that's equal to zero.
Okay.
What does it say?
Well,
I don't know.
The main reason I did it is
because I was curious what the answer was,
but I also did
it just as an illustration of
the machinery of calculating an expectation value.
But these ones tell you clear things.
What they tell you is
that in a very definite sense,
any given component of sigma and tau,
the x component or the
y component or the z component,
are oppositely oriented.
It's obvious here that for the z component,
they're oppositely oriented.
This is opposite to this.
So in any of the component state vectors here,
they're oppositely oriented.
But we also found something else out.
We found out that they're oppositely oriented in
the x basis or in the y basis.
Any one of the bases,
if you measure any one of the spins,
any component of the up spin,
basically it automatically tells you what the other one is.
What this is telling you is
that the other one is the same.
This is telling you,
since it's telling you that the
product is always equal to minus one,
in fact,
this is an eigenvector of the
product of any of these products,
it tells you if you measure
any component for one of them,
that you will get exactly the
opposite if you measure the other one.
It's a correlation.
It's a correlation,
it's a statistical correlation,
that if you measure one of
the components of spin of sigma,
and also the same component for the other one,
they'll be opposite.
Because it doesn't tell you much if
you measure the x component of this spin
and the y component of that spin,
that doesn't tell you much.
But it does tell you that if you
measure the same component of either of them,
they will come out opposite.
Yeah?
This is Bell's theorem,
the job number.
So,
I mean,
he's dealing with a system where
these two spins are emitted in opposite.
And it seems like it would
be an up-down kind of state.
Is that right,
or is that...
No,
the kind of states that
Bell dealt with were entangled states,
up-down minus down-up.
It's exactly what he's dealt with.
Yeah.
Will any interaction lead to a state like this?
This?
Yeah,
almost any interaction between the spins
will lead to a state like that.
Um...
Yeah,
but...
Did you say it's a statistical correlation?
Yes,
it's a statistical correlation that,
um...
Look,
at this le...
To some extent,
it's similar to a trivial observation.
You know,
the way I like to phrase it is I
have a penny and a dime in my pocket.
Alright?
I put my hand in my pocket,
I take them out,
I don't look at them.
Without looking at them,
I give one to Alice and one to Bob,
and then I tell Alice
and Bob to take off and,
you know,
go to the moon and go
to wherever you want to go.
Then it's going to be the case
that if Alice looks at her coin,
she instantly knows what Bob's coin is,
right?
She sees,
if I got a dime,
he's got a penny.
If I got a penny,
he's got a dime.
Uh...
That in itself...
is not surprising.
There's nothing,
uh...
In the past,
they were together.
Some correlation was established.
What was the correlation?
The correlation was a correlation
that if Alice has a dime,
then Bob has a penny,
and vice versa.
No other possibilities were possible.
Right?
So it was a correlation
between Alice's coin and Bob's coin.
And it was an anti-correlation.
If we called heads and
tails plus one and minus one,
then if Alice was plus one,
Bob is minus one.
But the opposite is also possible.
They don't know in advance.
And yet,
when Alice is far away
and when Bob is far away,
Alice looks at her coin,
and she instantly knows what Bob's is.
I assure you,
that does not violate the special theory of relativity.
And this kind of correlation is a...
This is called Einstein-Rosen-Podolsky correlation,
or entanglement.
This is the quantum version of
that same nickel and dime story,
penny and dime story.
Real nickels and real properties.
Yeah.
No,
there is certainly a difference.
There is certainly a difference.
But just the idea that by
looking at something at one place,
you instantly know something that you didn't know before.
And then you have a second
to go about the other place.
That's just statistical correlation.
It's a tremendously common thing in physics.
There's nothing special about it.
The question is,
what is it that's special
and different about this entanglement?
And that's where John Bell found something interesting.
He didn't find non-locality.
And we're going to talk next
time about what non-locality means in physics
and what it was exactly that John Bell found.
But I'm going to tell you right now,
it was not non-locality.
It looks like non-locality,
and the reason is because
you're trying to apply classical reasoning.
What John Bell said is you
can't apply classical reasoning to quantum systems.
That's what it came down to.
Quantum systems are quantum mechanical,
and if you try to apply classical reasoning,
you're going to find inconsistencies.
I can say it another way.
I'll tell you another way.
Here's a way to say it.
Imagine you had a computer,
and you tried to simulate on that computer
the quantum mechanics of a single spin.
Now here's the way you would simulate it.
You would be able to instruct the computer
to orient its apparatus in an arbitrary direction.
In other words,
you would put in coordinates.
You would put in coordinates for a direction.
And when you put in the coordinates for the direction,
the computer would do some calculation,
appeal to a random number generator,
and spit out a plus one or a minus one.
There would be an algorithm that would say
that if you do it over again immediately,
that you'll spit out the same number again.
And that if you do it again,
you'll spit out the same number again.
But you might then say,
all right,
now let me make it more interesting
by adding in a mathematical magnetic field,
which allows the spin to process.
What would you do?
You would solve the Schrodinger equation.
Find out what the state was
after a little bit of time.
Calculate the probabilities for up and down,
or whatever you decide to measure.
Calculate the probabilities.
Appeal to the random number generator,
and spit out a number that was statistically
exactly what you should get on the average
from quantum mechanics.
Somebody who came to this computer
and started playing with it and doing these experiments,
rotating his apparatus in different directions,
turning on magnetic fields in other directions,
weighting various amounts of time,
and then telling the computer,
measure this or that component,
would reproduce exactly quantum mechanics,
at least to the extent
that random number generators are possible.
They're not exactly possible,
but you can make pretty good random numbers.
All right.
So that would be a quantum...
That wouldn't be a quantum computer.
That would be a classical computer
simulating quantum behavior
where somebody doing a little experiment on it
could be fooled into thinking
that it was actually dealing with a single element.
So you could be doing a quantum experiment
on a single electron inside the computer
and doing a quantum experiment.
You couldn't tell the difference.
Now the question is,
could you do the same thing for two spins?
In particular,
I want to do the same thing for two spins,
and I want to do it in such a way
that one of the spins,
all of its data is located in one computer,
and all of the data for the other spin
is located in the other computer.
Now I can bring the computers together,
have wires connecting them and so forth
for a while,
do arbitrary things,
and then cut the wires and separate them.
Can I simulate
the quantum mechanics of the two-particle system
in such a way that it would appear
that one of the computers contained one particle
and the other computer contained the other particle?
Now remember,
this is a classical computer,
two classical computers.
And the answer is that the
only way you could do it
would be to have wires connecting the computers
at all times.
You could not do it unless the computers
were capable of interacting directly
at a distance.
But that does not mean that the system is non-local.
Non-local means that signals can be propagated
from one place to another.
What it's telling you is you simply can't
simulate quantum mechanics
in a local way by a classical computer.
The logic of quantum mechanics is different.
It simply does not allow itself to be faked
by a computer
unless that computer is connected
over large distances into everything in the world.
Quantum mechanics manages to do the same thing
without having wires connecting things.
However,
you could ask the question,
does that constitute what physicists call non-locality
or what Einstein would have called non-locality?
It does not.
It does not constitute in any way the ability
to send a message from one place to another.
But we're going to come to that.
We'll deal with that.
No,
it is fundamentally the inability to simulate
quantum mechanics by classical computers
unless the classical computers are hooked up
in highly non-local ways.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.