Stanford University.
Was talking about what happens during or
from beginning,
from before a measurement to after a measurement.
They were talking about what happens to
the evolution of an isolated black hole
left to itself between the time that it
was prepared and the time it was measured.
Okay,
nevertheless,
I could answer the question,
is entanglement inevitably irreversible?
If two things which are not entangled come together,
interact with each other,
do whatever they do,
and become entangled,
is it irreversible?
Not necessarily.
Anything that can happen,
the opposite can happen.
And now we're not talking about an external
apparatus measuring a system.
We're simply talking,
for example,
about two spins.
Two spins interact with each other,
come together,
go off,
and they're entangled.
What happens?
Is it possible to disentangle them by,
for example,
reflecting them,
letting them come together and interact again?
Can they become disentangled?
Yes.
Yes,
there's no rule that says entanglement is irreversible.
On the other hand,
if an entanglement happens and you take one
of the electrons off and throw it away,
then the other one is stuck there,
left being entangled with a thing that just does,
not going to come back.
Not going to come back unless,
of course,
somebody out there reflects it back in.
So yeah,
entanglement is reversible.
But as far as you're concerned,
the measurements that you do are irreversible.
That's a very peculiar situation,
and you have to think about
it to understand what it means.
We're going to move off the
question of these very simple systems,
spins,
sometimes called qubits,
tonight at some point,
but I want to just go over just very briefly,
I think I probably discussed this in class last time,
but nevertheless,
it's so important,
that I want to hammer on it.
First of all,
there was a notion of a density matrix.
If we have two systems,
Alice's system and Bob's system,
and Alice's and Bob's system
are far away from each other,
so that Alice doesn't get to
do any experiments on Bob's system,
Bob doesn't get to do any experiments on Alice's system,
but they're entangled,
either they are or they are not entangled,
they may be entangled.
Is there a description that Alice by
herself uses to describe just her subsystem?
The answer is yes,
and the working description of her
subsystem is called the density matrix.
So let me just review that very,
very quickly,
and go back over some concepts.
If the wave function of the Alice-Bob system,
the combined system of Alice and Bob,
Alice's subsystem and Bob's,
if the wave function
is called psi of A and B,
B for Bob,
A for Alice,
then Alice's density matrix is defined
to be psi star,
the complex conjugate of the wave function,
alright,
now let's say rho,
it's rho,
called the density matrix,
it's indicated by rho,
it has subscripts A and A prime,
because it's a matrix,
but it doesn't have anything to do with Bob,
so it's purely a matrix with respect to Alice's variables,
let's indicate that by calling this Alice's density matrix,
and it's given by psi star of A B,
A prime B,
I always get confused,
yeah,
A prime,
psi of A B summed over Bob's variables.
It doesn't depend on Bob's variables,
because they've been summed over.
When you sum over something,
it no longer depends on that set of variables,
so this is only a function of Alice's variables,
and it contains all possible,
all possible,
statistical information
that Alice can ever know
about her half of a system,
unless Bob comes and interacts with her system.
Of course,
if Bob comes from wherever he is,
and gives her system a shot of some sort,
that will change her density matrix,
but as long as Bob stays away from her system,
Bob's in Palo Alto,
Alice is on Alpha Centauri,
as long as Bob does
not interact directly with her system,
her density matrix doesn't change,
no matter what Bob does.
Let me give a little proof of that.
Let's take Bob's subsystem,
to not be so narrow as just to
be the little spin that he's carrying around,
and also Alice's,
let's imagine that Alice's subsystem
consists of everything in Alice's neighborhood,
everything that she can have any contact with,
and everything in Bob's system
is everything in Bob's neighborhood,
maybe even including Bob,
and now Bob is going to do something.
He's going to do something,
interact,
of course he can only interact,
interact may mean he may
turn on in a magnetic field,
he may do all sorts of things,
to change the evolution of his subsystem.
He's going to make a subsystem evolve in some way.
What are the ways which Bob
can cause his subsystem to evolve?
Many,
many ways,
but whatever they are,
they are always governed by unitary matrices.
Let's come over here and forget Alice for a minute,
and ask what Bob can do to his subsystem.
He has a wavefunction,
let's leave Alice out of the picture altogether,
just,
let's suppose that Bob has a wavefunction,
and he's going to manipulate the system somehow.
He's going to manipulate the system somehow,
and send it to a new wavefunction.
The rule is,
the new wavefunction of his subsystem
must be related to the
old wavefunction by a unitary operator.
Unitary operators are the things which govern the system,
and govern time evolution.
Go back,
remember about time evolution,
unitary operators,
and that means that
psi of b becomes replaced by sum over b,
some unitary matrix,
bb prime,
psi of b prime.
In terms of wavefunctions and matrices,
this is the description of what happens
to Bob's matrix,
sorry,
Bob's column vector,
this is basically Bob's column vector,
describing his half of the world,
or his system,
and to find out what happens to it,
no matter what he does,
even if he doesn't do anything,
but let's suppose he does something,
if he does something,
it generates a unitary evolution
of his wavefunction.
Now,
how do we describe the same thing
in the composite language?
In the composite language,
if the wavefunction is psi of a and b,
Alice's and Bob's variable,
what happens to it when Bob manipulates
his half of the world?
Exactly the same thing with Alice's variables
being just spectators,
just being passive spectators,
so psi of a and b just becomes psi of,
whoops,
let's put in there,
b prime,
this is sum of b prime,
this is a function of b,
and you sum over b prime,
okay?
That's again,
the sum over b prime
of u of b and b prime,
psi of a and b prime,
a just passed through,
Alice knew nothing whatever about this whole process,
her subsystem was not,
was not in any way influenced,
her index,
or her part of the wavefunction,
her half of the dependence of the wavefunction,
was uninfluenced by Bob's manipulation.
So let's go back and take
the manipulated wavefunction,
here's the manipulated wavefunction,
let's call it
psi manipulated,
the manipulated wavefunction
of b and a,
of a and b,
and that's this.
It's been modified
by the action of Bob's
unitary operator.
Okay,
now let's recalculate,
let's recalculate
Alice's density matrix.
After all,
Alice's density matrix contains all information
that she can ever know
about her half of the world,
and so let's see what happened to it.
Well,
we first of all have to take
the manipulated psi star,
we still have sum over b,
but now we take the manipulated psi star,
oh,
we haven't written psi star,
sorry about that,
we have to write psi star,
manipulated of,
and we want to know about it
with index a prime in b,
a prime in b,
and that we get just by complex conjugating.
This tells us how psi changes.
Let's just work out the complex conjugate.
That's the complex conjugate of
a prime,
Where is it,
a and b prime?
This is a prime in b,
just a prime in b.
But here,
since b prime is a summation variable,
we do not want to write b prime here.
b prime was the summation variable used over here.
Let's just invent another one called b double prime.
That's going to be a summation variable in a moment.
And u complex conjugate of b and b double prime.
Yeah.
u complex conjugate,
and of course there's a
sum over b double prime here.
And the only reason I called it
b double prime instead of b prime
was so as not to confuse it with b prime.
Here's one sum,
and here's a separate sum.
Alright?
Now,
here's something.
What do we know about unitary operators?
Unitary operators are operators that if we interchange b,
if we interchange the two indices,
and complex conjugate,
what happens?
That's called,
it's called the inverse operator,
or the Hermitian conjugate.
For a unit,
in general it's called the Hermitian conjugate.
Specifically for a unitary,
it becomes the inverse operator.
Now let's just call it the Hermitian conjugate.
If I
uncomplex conjugate,
and interchange these two,
sorry,
b double prime,
b double prime b,
then this becomes Hermitian conjugate.
Alright,
so this is the usual story.
If operators operate to the right on ket vectors,
the corresponding action on bra vectors is given by the,
by the Hermitian conjugate.
Alright,
so now all we have
to do is plug this in.
We plug this in for the left,
for the,
for the manipulated manners,
where h times times Sh
plus what,
plus just A prime
and all the
That's a nuisance,
too many indices for me
to be comfortable on the blackboard,
but I think this is worth doing.
Now,
what about psi?
Psi is the other half
that comes into the density matrix,
and that's u,
b,
b prime,
psi of what?
Psi of a and b prime.
Complicated little mess.
Oh,
what are we summing over?
We're summing over all the b's,
basically.
Yeah.
We're summing over this b over here.
Let's put a b summation here.
We were summing over b double prime to
get the manipulated wave for this complex conjugate,
but we also have to sum over b prime here.
Sum over all the b's in sight.
Each b is a summation variable.
By the time...
We're finished.
All right,
but now look at what we have.
It looks complicated,
but what is this thing over here?
Well,
not quite...
Yeah,
one is essentially correct,
but of course what you mean is the unit matrix.
This is the product matrix of u dagger.
This is a unitary matrix,
so u dagger is u's inverse.
b double prime b,
b b prime.
This is just the Kronecker delta.
b double prime b prime.
It just instructs you to set b double prime
equal to b prime when you do the sum,
when you do one of the two sums.
Let's say the b double prime sum.
So all of this then becomes sum over b prime.
Well,
let's see.
What have we got?
We've set b double prime.
Yeah.
We've done the sum over b.
That's done.
No sum over b.
We just did it.
And now we set b
double prime equal to b prime.
Psi star of a prime,
b prime,
psi of a and b prime.
That's it.
Now,
it doesn't matter whether we call b prime
b prime or whether we call it b,
because it's a summation variable.
So let's do that.
Let's just call it b.
And what do we have?
We have exactly,
I hope,
I pray,
the original density matrix.
So Bob,
no matter what he does,
as long as what he does
is described by a unitary matrix,
Bob will have absolutely no
effect on Alice's density matrix.
It does not matter whether they're entangled or not.
Nowheres did I specify that this was a product state.
That is what physicists call location.
Locality.
The inability of Bob to
influence any statistical prediction of Alice's
by doing a manipulation on his own degrees of freedom.
Locality is not violated.
This form of locality,
this form of locality is not violated in any way
by the phenomenon of entanglement.
That's the technical argument.
Notice that it does depend on unitarity.
So,
and what did unitarity do with?
Unitarity had to do with conservation of distinctions.
What I call the minus first law,
at least in its quantum mechanical version.
So there's a funny and interesting interplay.
Funny,
interesting interplay between
the conservation of distinctions on the one hand,
and locality.
If Bob somehow had access to changes
which were not described by unitary operators,
this would not have become the unit matrix over here,
and the final density matrix would,
Alice's final density matrix,
indeed would have been modified.
This is interesting,
the way the whole thing holds together.
This is why it's so hard to change quantum mechanics.
You want to play a little game?
Let's let Bob,
let Bob's evolution not quite be unitary,
only approximately unitary.
Well,
then immediately you start sending signals
faster than the speed of light.
How?
By instantly modifying Alice's density matrix.
So,
things hold together tightly,
and it's hard to change them.
Good,
so,
yes.
So.
Is it correct to say that if Bob's
matrix is unitary,
the evolution matrix is vector?
Yeah.
Essentially,
you can't do it if he's
not really able to touch his system.
He's not able to...
Touch it,
change it.
He's not able to change Alice's system.
He's changed his own system by
doing something,
and that doing something was
described by this unitary matrix.
Okay.
That's the part that confuses me.
If he's doing something,
isn't he going to be violating unitarity?
No.
For example,
he might be turning a magnet.
He might be turning a magnet in such a
way that it has an influence on his spin.
What is that influence?
It will change the state of the spin.
For example,
yeah.
If you have a spin in a given direction,
and it's coupled to a magnetic field,
and you turn the magnetic field,
in some way,
you'll typically change the evolution of that spin.
Okay.
So Bob can do that.
He can change a magnetic field
that's acting on a certain spin.
The result will be to
change the way the spin evolves.
That will change his own measurements of the spin,
of his spin.
If he does act
by
rotating a magnetic field,
which is mathematically described,
by some sort of evolution,
doesn't matter what,
some sort of evolution,
it's described by a unitary operator,
then,
uh,
then he does change the results of his own measurements.
For example,
he rotates the magnetic field,
but he doesn't rotate his apparatus.
The result is that he's going to
change the probability distributions of his own spin.
But he will not change any
of the probabilities of Alice's spin.
Okay.
So are you saying quantum
mechanics is always based on locality?
Locality defined by the inability
of Bob to influence Alice's measurements.
Okay.
Yeah.
Now,
the question is,
so what's the big deal?
Is that what you were going to ask?
You asked it.
I was,
um,
guessing what you were going to ask.
Why don't you ask it?
Single particle wave function,
put a photon through a beam splitter,
it goes off in two different directions.
You catch it at one detector
faster than the speed of light,
the wave function collapses.
Whoa,
whoa,
what?
You do what?
You detect a photon at one detector.
The wave function at the other detector collapses to zero,
instantaneously.
I showed you what happens.
The density matrix of the other system does not change.
Period.
Really.
You get average measurements that don't change.
What's it,
what,
what hap-
I know,
I know.
People,
look,
I'm doing my absolute best to tell it
to you as it really is and to cut
through the crap that's out there.
To cut through the crap that's out there,
because there is a huge amount of information
that's out there.
There is a pile a mile high.
And we somehow want to cut through that.
This is the mathematics of cutting through it.
Now,
nevertheless,
there were some pretty damn
smart people who are uncomfortable about
something,
something that they call nonlocality.
I mean,
you know,
Einstein was no jerk.
He was pretty smart.
And they didn't call him Einstein for nothing.
That's my favorite joke.
John Bell was pretty smart.
They didn't call him Einstein,
though.
Yeah.
So there's something going on.
There's something going on.
Yeah,
go ahead.
And this goes back to
your original comment about the question.
I want to get,
I'm reviewing last week,
so make it quick.
To me,
this is real clear,
I think.
And that is the,
your idea of locality means that the,
the,
the states don't affect each other.
In other words,
there's,
there's two things.
The density.
The information about the states.
Yeah.
And,
and it seems that in the confusing part
of quantum mechanics is that those two different
things get mixed up somehow.
Is that accurate or?
No,
it's fuzzy.
But it's true.
That cleared it up a lot.
So I will try to,
I will try to tell
you as often as I can.
I understand it.
What the concrete operational facts are.
So I told you last time,
I was a little bit tired last time,
and I'm not sure I was completely
clear.
So I won't go over it again because it's very,
very interesting.
And it really is at the
heart of all of the confusions about,
confusions,
I mean,
I must
say,
including my own internal
confusions about quantum mechanics.
When I first learned about ERP,
Einstein,
Rosen,
Podolsky,
that was the discovery.
Well,
I don't know if it was,
I don't know if it was a discovery.
I think maybe Schrodinger
said some things about entanglement.
But it was Einstein,
Rosen,
and Podolsky who really called attention to how peculiar it
was.
Basically,
what they said is we have a
very funny situation here where although we can
know everything that can possibly
be known about a composite system,
we know nothing
at all about its constituents.
That's crazy.
That violates my sense of reality.
That violates my sense of what it
means to know what a system is doing.
It violates all sorts of things.
I remember when I first heard about it,
it was actually before John Bell,
sometime in
the 60s when I was a student.
No,
I wasn't a student.
I was a young assistant professor.
And I started to think about it,
and I thought about it a lot.
I tried to figure out what it means.
I was sort of inclined
to try to think about it.
I was very inclined to think about
it in terms of simulating quantum mechanics,
and I still
am.
What are the limits?
If quantum mechanics is so very strange
and so very different than classical physics,
does it mean that you can't fool
somebody into thinking a system is quantum mechanical
if all you have,
your resources,
are entirely classical?
And the answer is yes and no.
So I know I talked about this last time,
but it really is at the center of things.
So let's go back over it quickly.
As quick as I can.
We're going to build ourselves a quantum simulator.
I think somebody built one on the site.
I came across it about an hour ago.
Who's that?
Yeah.
Does it work?
Well,
it doesn't actually simulate yet.
Not yet.
Is that picture your picture?
It was a picture of Einstein and Heisenberg,
and Einstein says,
I don't like this,
and
Heisenberg said what?
Einstein says,
I think I'm not going to like this.
Yeah.
I'm not going to like this.
Right.
He says,
how can you be so sure?
Yes.
Right.
I think that captures it.
Why go on?
But okay,
let's talk about the nature of quantum simulators.
First of all,
I just want to simulate a single spin.
I think I told you how to do it,
but let's write down the steps.
We have a computer screen.
Here's our computer screen.
On the screen,
we have a picture of a detector.
Not a detector,
an apparatus.
And the apparatus can be oriented
in any direction in three-dimensional space.
We need to do some three-dimensional graphics here.
And it has a window,
and the window shows one of three possible states.
One is called blank B.
That's the detector or the
apparatus before it's interacted with
anything.
So it can be B or
it can be plus or minus one.
B is not important.
It's just to say,
three-dimensional.
It's not important to be able to
see anything before the detector interacts with anything.
There's a button over here called M.
And the operator of the system,
of the computer game,
basically all he ever gets to do is
press M and then look at the
result of the M stands for measure.
It performs a measurement.
Now,
over here,
connected to the computer by wires,
by cables,
connected to the screen
is a computer.
And the computer stores information in its memory.
And the basic information that
it stores is two complex numbers,
alpha up and alpha down.
Those are supposed to be the components
of the wave function of the spin.
I didn't say yet that there was a spin here,
but that's what we're talking about.
Alpha up and alpha down.
The computer only can generate alphas which
satisfy alpha star alpha up plus alpha star
alpha down is equal to one.
Whenever it generates them.
And it can do something else.
It can do two other things.
It can update the alphas by
solving the Schrodinger equation for them.
There's some Hamiltonian,
for example,
it could be that the spin
is in an imaginary magnetic field,
in which case the alphas would change with time.
The computer knows how to do that.
It knows how to solve Schrodinger's equation.
Computers can solve Schrodinger's equation beautifully.
And it updates these as a function of time.
Updates them according to the rules of quantum mechanics.
One other thing,
the cables are instantaneous.
They convey information instantly.
So we'll have one more element.
The other element will be a random number generator.
Let me just say some words about random number generators.
Random number generators sounds
like we're introducing quantum mechanics.
No,
we don't need quantum mechanics.
You can simulate to a very,
very high degree of confidence
a sequence of random numbers or random number generator
purely out of classical considerations.
You know how to do it.
You take the digits of pi or whatever
and you make something that looks
would fool anybody,
including a sophisticated scientist.
A sophisticated mathematician into believing
that you were generating a set of random numbers.
So there's a random number generator inside the computer.
Alright,
the operator starts by initializing the system.
And initializing the system simply means
starting out some orientation for the detector,
for the apparatus,
doesn't matter what.
And setting the alphas to some initial values.
He can plug in what he wants to plug,
initial values to b,
or the computer just sets them
according to whatever rule it likes.
Then the system runs for a period of time,
an indeterminate period of time,
updating the alphas
until the operator decides to press m.
A certain amount of time has elapsed,
the operator decides how much time,
and presses m.
At that point,
the random number generator
generates a plus one or a minus one,
but with probability alpha star alpha up,
that it's plus one,
sorry,
alpha up,
alpha up star,
that it's plus one,
or else alpha star alpha down,
that it's minus one.
Remember,
the sum of these two alpha star alphas
add up to one.
So,
armed with the random number generator,
the computer sends a signal
with a probability,
of the appropriate probability,
to the detector,
and the detector detects,
or registers,
what the computer sent it.
Okay?
That's one measurement.
Now,
as soon as that happens,
the computer re-initializes the alphas.
How does it re-initialize the alphas?
If the detector detected plus one,
then it sends back a message.
It doesn't really need to send back a message.
After all,
this message got from here to here.
All right?
So,
the computer over here knows
whether it got plus one or minus one.
If the detector saw plus one,
then it sets alpha u back to one,
and sends alpha d to zero.
In other words,
it does what we call
collapsing the wave function.
According to the result,
or according to the outcome of the measurement,
it re-initializes the alphas.
So,
whatever was measured,
you start with probability one
for the outcome,
and probability zero for the,
what shall we call it,
the anti-outcome.
And then it runs again.
Solves the Schrodinger equation,
does it again.
The operator makes a ramp,
makes whatever decision he likes.
I mean,
what makes him decide
to pressure,
to press M?
He's an experimental physicist.
What makes experimental physicists
do what they do?
I don't really know.
But he does what experimental physicists do.
Now and then he presses M,
and does the whole operation over again.
Oh,
sorry.
Before he does,
he may decide to run
and rotate the apparatus.
Now,
the computer in here knows
what the orientation of the apparatus is.
So when it calculates,
it not only calculates the updated alphas,
but it also calculates
the probabilities for the rotated detector
to detect whatever it's going to detect.
That's all algebra and a little bit of,
that's purely algebra.
The computer makes the kind of calculations
that you did,
or presumably did,
makes the kind of calculations
to calculate what the probability would be
that if the detector was rotated
in some arbitrary direction,
then what's the probability
that it will get up or down?
Now,
who is it that decides
to rotate the computer?
Well,
it's the operator again,
the experimentalist.
The experimentalist not only can press M,
but he can also reorient the detector
anytime he wants.
This is about as much
as an experimental physicist can do
with that spin.
Rotate the apparatus,
measure.
Rotate the apparatus again,
All right?
And what's the result of the outcome of this?
The outcome of this is indistinguishable
from what the experimental physicist
examining the spin would see.
So we've simulated quantum mechanics.
All right,
now we want to know
whether we can simulate quantum mechanics
of two spins,
one on Alice's side of the world over here,
and one on Bob's side of the world.
Yeah?
I don't understand the purpose of the button M
in our,
in other words,
when he decided to push it,
some amount of time is involved.
Yeah.
Has that affected anything going on in the computer?
Yeah,
the computer has been updating all this time.
Right,
but when we talked about our basic model
of how spin works,
time did not come into it at all.
We did talk about Hamiltonians.
We talked about Hamiltonians
and how Hamiltonians update the state of a system.
You're right,
we didn't discuss how a,
we didn't discuss much about Hamiltonians for spins.
Yes,
we did.
I believe I described a spin and a magnetic field
and how the average spin precesses.
We did.
But if we didn't have the magnetic field,
because that's how we started
out talking about all this stuff,
right?
Then time is not,
should not be a factor.
Okay,
I understand.
Right.
Now there's no real magnetic field.
There's just an imaginary magnetic field
that the computer knows about.
And where does that come into it?
It comes into the solution,
the nature of the exact Schrodinger equation.
Okay.
Now,
we do this over here
and precisely the same thing over here,
except instead of alphas,
we have betas.
Beta stands for Bob.
Exactly the same setup,
replicated twice.
Bob does his measurement.
Alice does her measurements.
They're perfectly happy.
Each one says,
I have a spin.
It's quantum mechanical.
They don't talk to each other.
And each one says,
my spin is in a state.
The language that we would describe this by,
quantum mechanically,
is they have simulated a product state.
A product state in which Bob's,
sorry,
Alice's wave function
is this,
and Bob's wave function is this,
and the combined system is in a product state.
Supposing now we want to simulate a any state,
a more complete description that includes entangled states.
Well,
we can do it this way.
Let's start with a way
that's sort of guaranteed to work.
We take the computer and
we put it in the middle,
a single computer.
We can think of the single computer,
if we like,
as a pair of computers,
connected by wires,
but just by the fact
that they're communicating with each other
and interacting with each other,
really makes them a single computer.
And in that single computer,
we now store four complex numbers.
The four complex numbers that we store in there are
alpha up,
up,
down,
alpha down,
up,
down.
These complex numbers here
are not necessarily
products.
In fact,
let's assume they're not products.
In other words,
that this is not a product state.
Let's assume it's a highly entangled state.
Even a highly entangled state is
described by four complex numbers like this.
That's what's in the computer.
And what does the computer do with it?
It evolves the Schrodinger equation.
First of all,
we initialize.
Same deal.
We initialize.
We start with some alphas.
The alphas,
are allowed to run according
to whatever Schrodinger equation describes them.
And at the end,
either Bob or Alice or both,
without knowing what the other one is doing,
press,
or as the case may be,
don't press their measurement buttons.
Once the measurement button has been pressed,
an instantaneous signal goes back to the computer.
The computer grinds out its random number generator,
and whichever side was measured
sends a signal to the detector
with appropriate probability,
either plus one or minus one,
and then reinitializes itself,
reinitializes itself in a way that doesn't touch,
for example,
if Alice does the experiment,
then it doesn't touch Bob's end of things.
If Bob does the experiment,
the computer reinitializes itself.
And then Bob re-normalizes his half of the wave function,
which is another way of saying it
throws away the piece that you didn't measure.
Throws away the pieces you didn't measure,
and re-normalizes the wave function so
that the total probability is one.
Exactly the same thing,
there's no real difference with a single system.
You can simulate it,
and you can simulate it
in a way which would describe
all the possible things that Alice and Bob could measure,
whether or not the system was entangled.
Where do we get in trouble?
We get in trouble if after initializing,
we try to separate the computers and break the wires.
For example,
here's what we might do.
Given these alphas,
we might put them into both computers.
Take the set of alphas that we generated,
put this one into this computer,
and put this one into this computer,
now since the computers are not
going to talk to each other,
they have to have separate random number generators.
The random number generators will not talk to each other.
Each one contains the full entangled state,
and then we go through the same operation.
What's going to happen?
The computer is simply going to forget.
For example,
for a highly entangled state,
let's say the entangled state is this one,
and the singlet state,
then the right answer would be that
if Bob and Alice both measure,
they should get opposite values for any spin.
If they measure the x component of spin,
they should get opposite values.
If they measure y components of spin,
But,
if when we separate them,
they have separate random number generators,
and the random number generators don't talk to each other,
then guess what's going to happen?
There's going to be no correlation of any kind
between what Bob measures and what Alice measures.
Nope.
Bob may measure plus,
and Alice may also measure plus,
because their random number generators
are not connected to each other.
And so even though both computers may
know about the full state of the system,
if the random number generators don't talk to each other,
then the results of the experiment
will not contain the correlation.
The correlation that Bob and Alice
could later come together and report,
Bob would say,
my first experiments are a plus.
If things were working right,
then Alice should say,
my first experiments are a minus.
And so forth and so on.
That correlation will not be there
once you try to separate the computers.
Are the random numbers correlated
if you don't separate the computers?
You can have a single random number generator
that sends out signals to both computers.
If it sends out a
signal plus one to this computer,
it sends out a signal minus one to that computer.
So all you need is a single random number generator,
but it has to be
able to talk to both computers.
So there's got to be wires in the world.
There's got to be wires in the world
connecting this side and this side,
if for no other reason,
then they can both connect
to the same random number generator.
You've got four alphas there,
but it sounds like you just
described that the alphas are independent.
Now you've got to think about it.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Well,
that's sort of right.
Once you've separated them,
then what happens next,
after some measurements are made,
doesn't preserve the relationship between them.
They become disconnected from each other.
Yeah,
so think about it a little bit.
I mean,
even better,
try to simulate it.
This is,
this,
I've never tried,
but I don't think it should be that hard
if you can do a little bit of computer programming.
I've simulated much harder things than that
when my son was a little kid.
We had this thing called BASIC.
Anybody remember BASIC?
Yeah.
And he and I designed a basketball game,
and it had friction,
and it had,
oh,
it was really,
much harder than this.
So that was my last experience ever programming anything.
Can I say a quick scenario?
I think you'll learn a
lot by trying to simulate this.
Okay,
you have a detector called a cell phone,
and I get a signal from Alice or Bob
about some random event.
It could be a spin.
Let's suppose we're,
Will you please speak concretely?
We get a signal from Bob of some random event.
What does it mean?
Can you please be exact?
I will be very precise.
Very exact.
I'm getting two text messages,
one from A,
one from B,
okay?
And they can have a
value of one or a zero,
each of them.
Okay?
And I get a million of these things,
and I notice the distribution that
the A signal is about a
50% chance of being one or zero,
same with the B signal.
Okay?
It could be from a spin.
Yes,
yes,
okay,
go ahead.
Now,
when I look at the correlation,
it turns out that whether it's A or B,
the other one is the same.
In other words,
it's correlated,
a correlation of one.
That's in the real world of entangled states.
Right.
Now,
this could be,
we don't know where it's coming from.
I'm just getting information.
So I get an information to,
A comes through,
I don't look at it,
B comes through,
I know it's a 50-50 chance,
I don't look at it,
but as soon as I look at A,
I know what B is,
so the wave function completely changes.
Now,
the example I'm using is not a state,
I'm just,
Bob and Alice are sexting twins.
One's a boy,
one's a girl.
You gotta hurry up,
because I gotta get on to particles.
So there is nothing magical about that.
There is nothing weird about that.
If it's correlated like that,
it's very probable they're identical twins
instead of fraternal twins.
So what am I missing?
What is the correlation between the two?
What is weird about that?
If you don't find it weird,
good.
What's weird is that you can't simulate it classically
without having a central processor connected by wires.
That's what's weird about it.
So don't those wires that connect the two distant computers
represent non-locality?
Oh,
okay.
Now we ask.
All right,
the last one.
those wires are there.
For goodness sakes,
surely Bob can send a message
through the wires to Alice.
That takes no time at all,
because they're instantaneous.
Yeah.
True enough,
if this were a real computer setup.
But if Bob is restricted to only do the things
which quantum mechanics allows him to do,
if he is restricted by the rules of quantum mechanics,
then we find that,
we find out,
amazingly,
that Bob can never send a message
through the wires that violates locality.
Why?
Because all Bob can do is manipulate his own system
with unitary operators.
And so that's what's curious here.
Does that mean that the
world is filled up with wires
that we can't see?
I don't think that's the message.
I think the right message,
but of course here you can hear,
there's room for debate,
what the right message of all of this is.
The message I take away from it is basically
quantum mechanics cannot be simulated by a classical system.
The logic is too different.
The structures of the two theories are too different.
And I don't take away the message
that the world is full of wires,
that if only we could access them,
we could send messages back and forth.
Other people do.
But I think at least if
we know how to do quantum mechanics,
we'll agree on the facts,
we may disagree on basically
whether there are or are not wires there.
Are there really wires there or
are there really not wires there?
Well,
perhaps the culprit is the word really.
But this is,
oh,
there is one other element to it,
which is quite interesting.
We've made an assumption that Bob and Alice get
to kind of randomly make decisions
about when to press the button,
about what orientations,
about what to decide to measure.
Bob sits here and says,
okay,
northwest,
southeast,
or whatever,
makes these random decisions according
to the principle of free will,
so to speak.
That's fine as long as Alice and Bob
are outside the system and not part of it.
We don't need to ask the question
of consciousness and the question of free will.
We'll just admit that Alice and Bob can
make random decisions about when to measure various things.
It's obviously a pretty good approximation.
But once we take Alice and
Bob and put them into the system
so that they are governed by the laws of physics,
then things get a little bit touchy.
What do we mean by saying
that Alice can decide to do this,
or Bob can decide to do that?
And that,
I think,
is where the possible loopholes in
all of this can come from.
That,
uh,
now,
I don't want to get
too deep into heavy philosophical discussions
of all sorts of
psychological and questions of consciousness.
I don't know the answers.
That's it.
I don't know the answers beyond what I've told you.
Uh,
I'm certain of two things about it.
I am certain that there are a lot
of people who think they do know the answers,
and I'm also certain that they don't.
That's it.
I have a question.
Yeah.
Um,
actually,
not a question,
a comment.
Uh,
if you Google for Quantum Randy Challenge,
you'll find a blog entry that
has the setup for this simulation.
Really?
Yeah.
For the entangled case?
It doesn't have the...
It doesn't solve it.
It says,
if you can...
Here's a program.
Yeah.
Your challenge is to put...
Fill in this blank place.
I see.
And if you can,
he'll give you a million dollars.
Hey,
okay.
Well,
actually,
he won't give you a million dollars.
Somebody in Sweden will give you a million dollars.
Yeah.
Okay,
that's very interesting.
so I'm not the first one to...
Well,
I bet I was the first
one to think about it this way,
but I've been telling this to people for 50 years.
Hmm?
No.
I don't know.
I probably wasn't.
I think maybe Bohr thought about it this way.
Who knows?
It doesn't matter.
Um,
let's,
uh...
We could spend the rest of eternity talking about spins.
They're so...
Why?
Because they really are interesting.
But,
uh,
you know,
we want to get to something else.
We want to get to particles.
We want to get to more complex systems.
The most complex system we've discussed is two spins,
four-dimensional,
and...
Well,
Hilbert space.
Uh,
we've gotten about to the point where in classical physics
we got through the first lecture.
The first lecture was about these simple,
discrete systems,
and then we rather immediately moved on to continuous motion
of things like particles
moving continuously with an infinite,
and not just an infinite,
but a continuously infinite range of possibilities.
That's where we have to go now.
Now,
fortunately,
we've set up so much of the apparatus
of quantum mechanics,
and we've got a lot of things going on.
So we can do it fairly quickly.
There's a little bit of
subtlety about replacing sums by integrals.
That's about it.
That's about the nature of the subtlety.
Sums and integrals.
We've expressed the general principles of quantum mechanics,
and then exhibited it in a
variety of simple spin system examples.
Now we'll plunge right in.
We'll go back to the first lecture.
We'll plunge right in to quantum gravity.
No.
We'll plunge right in to the problem of
a single particle moving on a one-dimensional axis.
We'll take the axis to be infinite,
although that's mostly because I don't
have time to be more careful.
If we want to get anywhere else,
we're going to have to...
it's much,
much more
slightly less mathematically rigorous.
All right and in order to be rigorous,
you really have to contain a system
in a finite volume and so forth,
but we don't need to do that.
So we have a line,
an infinite line.
Along an infinite line,
one particle can exist.
We won't do two particles yet.
One particle can exist in one dimension.
That line is a galaxy.
is labeled by a coordinate x,
let me not write down the coordinate x,
but also the
states of the particle,
the states of the particle are also labeled by the
position of a particle.
Now here we are departing from classical logic.
In
classical logic,
the states of a particle are
labeled by a position and a momentum.
If we were talking about the states of a spin,
we would say the state of a spin is
described by all of the co- or maybe
at least two of the components of spin,
but
we can't do that in quantum mechanics.
We can't specify two components
simultaneously.
Same in classical mechanics,
specifying,
as you,
I'm sure you
know,
specifying the position and the momentum is too much,
and we'll see how
that works.
We'll see how that works,
but for the moment let's
take it as a postulate that
a complete description of the state of a particle,
and you can't get any more out,
is,
for example,
to know that it's located at a position x,
and if it's located at
position x,
we'll describe that by a ket vector.
The ket vector x,
that's the state
of a particle when it's located at position x.
Now of course we can consider
more complicated,
more
complicated,
complicated states,
linear superpositions of these.
In quantum mechanics we are
always allowed to make linear superpositions,
and so the space of
states is bigger than just the
space of particles located at definite positions.
Let's call the general state psi.
This is the general state of a particle,
doesn't
mean anything now,
it's just an abstract symbol,
and it's a vector in some vector space.
The vector space now has a continuously infinite
number of basis vectors.
Now strictly speaking that's a mathematically bad thing,
but we're
going to play that game.
If you want to understand more
deeply the mathematics of quantum mechanics,
you go and you learn about Hilbert space,
but we're not going to do that tonight.
So the general state of a particle is called psi.
Remember what the wave function of a system is.
The wave function of a system,
in a particular
basis is the projection of
a state onto the basis vectors,
and we call that psi of A.
Now we come to a particle,
the basis of states are the position states,
and what is the wave
function?
The wave function is the inner product,
the inner product of the particle.
And the
inner product of the state
vector with the eigenvectors of position,
and that's called
psi of x.
That's the wave function.
That's the classical,
not classical but that's the standard quantum
mechanical wave function of a particle.
It plays the same role as in the simple systems
we've discussed,
the inner product of the state vector with A.
Now we can say a little more.
What is the basic function,
and is it greater than
the class of the state vector?
In this context,
the probability that the system,
whatever it is,
exhibits property
A is given by this thing squared.
In fact,
it's given by psi star of A,
psi of A.
That's the probability that the system is,
that the outcome of an experiment to determine
whether the system was,
had property A,
that's the probability.
Likewise,
in exact parallel,
the probability to find the particle
at X is equal to psi
star of X times psi of X.
I really haven't done anything that we haven't done before.
Now in quantum mechanics,
like in any other sensible statistical theory,
the sum of all
probabilities should add up to one.
So the sum of psi star
of psi should add up to one.
But when probabilities refer to a continuous variable,
we don't talk about the probability
that the particle is located exactly at point X.
That's too sharp.
The probability that a thing is located
exactly at any given X is zero.
We talk about the probability that
it's located within a range of X.
Or better yet,
we talk about the density of probability.
We talk about the probability density.
And we integrate this over a little range
of X to find the probability that you're in
that range of X.
We do something like that here.
If we want to know not whether
the system is definitely specified at A,
but we want
to know whether it's at a range of A,
we sum over them.
But here we sort of have to do it.
Total probability equal to one.
That's the condition.
That the integral of psi star of X,
psi of X,
dx,
is equal to one.
Total probability of the system
has to add up to one.
And as I said,
the only new thing here is that
we have to replace sums by integrals.
And that does make mathematical subtlety
that we have to worry about,
but it's sort
of in the mathematical deepening.
OK,
what about the inner product between two state vectors,
one at X and one at X prime?
Well,
here we go back,
for inspiration,
right back to this case.
OK.
And let's make sure that we get a better idea.
0 if a is not equal to a prime
and 1 if a is equal to a prime.
And we're not going to be able
to quite get away with that here.
We're not going to quite be able
to get away with the statement that
x prime is equal to 0 or 1.
We are going to say that if
x is not equal to x prime,
then it's 0.
But we're not going to say
that when it's equal to x prime,
that it's 1.
That would not leave us anywhere.
What we're going to say is that it's
a function which vanishes unless x equals x prime,
but has area 1 under it.
We'll see how that works out.
We'll see what that does for us.
In a moment.
What it really comes down
to is a different normalization here.
But again,
the basic idea that states are orthogonal
if x is not equal to x prime,
that we will retain.
But the numerical value of what we
get when x is equal to x prime,
we're going to take to be slightly different.
And in fact,
we're going to invent a function,
not we are,
Dirac did,
the Dirac delta function.
x minus...
x minus x prime.
The Dirac delta function is
not a real mathematical function,
although by now I think
mathematicians have defined it to death
so that it is a real mathematical entity.
But for our purposes,
we can think of it in a very simple way.
It's a function which is 0...
Well,
let's take delta of x.
Not delta of x minus x prime.
This is basically delta of x minus 0.
x prime 0.
The function delta of x.
It's a function which is 0
unless x is equal to 0.
That's the same as saying this thing is
0 unless x is equal to x prime.
So if this is x,
it's 0 everywheres except x equals x prime.
And at x equals x prime,
it's a very high narrow spike.
How high and narrow?
High enough and narrow enough,
that the area under it is one unit.
That means if it's approximated by
a narrow interval of size epsilon,
that it has height 1 over epsilon.
And then you imagine a limit
where you take epsilon smaller and smaller,
1 over epsilon higher and higher,
always keeping the area under it equal to 1.
That's the Dirac delta function.
Dirac delta function,
0 everywheres except when x equals x prime.
So here's the area under x prime.
And the Dirac delta function is infinite in
some sense when x is equal to x prime,
but in such a way that the
area under it is equal to 1.
Okay?
All right,
now let's use this to further elaborate on
what the meaning of psi of x is.
I'm going to guess,
and then we're going to check.
I'm going to guess that the meaning
of psi of x is the following.
That if I want to write a general state vector,
psi,
that I can think of it
as a sum over the basis vectors.
But not a sum,
an integral.
Of course an integral,
because the basis vectors are continuous.
The x of some coefficients,
some coefficients,
well let's,
no,
let's write it this way.
Psi is equal to an integral
dx of some set of coefficients.
I'm going to guess what they are.
I'm going to guess that they're psi of x.
Times the,
times the,
the state,
the quantum state where the particle is located at x,
but then we're going to
add them up for different x's.
It's exactly the same thing that we did,
for ordinary quantum systems,
except this was replaced by a sum.
Alright,
now I've given you two
distinct definitions of psi of x.
One is that it's the inner product
of the state vector with the eigenvector x.
I'll call it the eigenvector of x.
The other is that it's the expansion coefficients
in writing psi as a sum over vectors.
Now,
if you're a little bit uncomfortable with the idea of,
of a continuous basis of vectors that you integrate over,
you're in good company.
The mathematics of this is,
um,
as I said,
by now it is,
been made rigorous,
but it's,
it's,
um,
it took pages and pages and pages and pages
and books and books and
books on something called distribution theory
to make sense out of this with precision,
but it's pretty intuitive.
It's pretty intuitive,
and we'll,
we'll stick with that.
Alright,
so let's calculate,
or let's put a prime here.
This is a sum,
an integral.
It doesn't matter,
it doesn't matter what you call the integration variable.
Let's call it x prime.
And now let's calculate the
inner product of x with psi.
As I said,
there were two different definitions of psi of x.
Let's check that they're the same.
So,
here we have it.
Integral dx prime.
Psi of x prime.
Inner product of x with x prime.
What's the inner product of x with x prime?
I think I wrote it someplace.
Where is it?
I think I erased it.
That's equal to the integral of the x prime,
psi of x prime,
delta of x minus x prime.
Okay,
what is that?
Alright.
First of all,
delta is a function which is zero
everywhere except at x equals x prime.
So that means that in doing this integral here,
you'll only get a contribution when
x prime is equal to x.
That means the answer is going to come
out to be proportional to psi of x.
Furthermore,
the area under this delta function is exactly one.
If we imagine that this delta function is a p,
pinched narrower and narrower high spike,
so that the area under it is one,
then this integral would tend to psi of x.
The rule is,
if you have an integral
over a delta function like this,
it simply picks out the value of
the integration variable where the delta function vanishes.
Sorry,
where the argument of the delta function vanishes.
Where x minus x prime vanishes.
That's where the function is not zero.
And the integral of a function with a delta function just
gives you the value of the function at the point x.
That's a rule.
We might as well write that down.
Let's write that down as a rule.
Integral delta of x minus x prime,
f of x prime is
always equal to f of x.
It picks out the value x prime equal to x.
That's part of the definition of the delta function.
Okay,
so it's just equal to psi of x.
And we find consistency that the thing
that we called psi of x over here
is the same as the thing that
we called psi of x over here.
All of this has its
exact parallel for the ordinary systems.
Top integral on the bottom board,
yeah.
So I'm looking at psi of x prime times,
the ket vector x prime.
Adding them up,
superposing.
I'm trying to figure out which are the basis vectors.
These are the basis vectors.
Let's compare that with
psi is equal to sum over a,
a prime,
let's call it a prime.
Psi of a prime,
a prime.
Okay?
If we use the fact that
a and a prime are orthogonal
and do exactly the same
thing except replacing sums by integrals,
we will also find that the psi that appears here
is the same as the inner
product of psi with the basis vectors.
So I've really done nothing that we haven't done before.
I appreciate it's a little,
possibly a little unfamiliar.
But all it is,
is,
same thing we've done before.
So the psi of x prime sort of plays
the same role as the alphas and some other?
The x prime plays the same
role as the a prime here.
Yeah.
The psi plays the same role as the psi.
The sum is replaced by the integral.
Sum over a prime is replaced by integral,
the x prime.
And otherwise it's exactly the same.
Okay?
Now let's calculate
the inner product.
One quick question.
It may be nitpicking or something,
but
on the left hand side where you have the
Dirac's formula,
lower right hand corner,
you've got a vertical line between the axis.
Over here in the middle formula,
there's no vertical line.
Thank you.
Okay.
Good?
Because it could have been a line or a column.
I got you,
got you,
got you.
Right?
Nope.
Absolutely.
How about the inner product of two vectors?
Well,
the inner product of two vectors is some inner product.
But one way of calculating the inner product,
let's go back to ordinary quantum mechanics,
ordinary means for the discrete systems.
Here,
we don't need this right now.
How do we calculate the inner product?
Let's take it.
Inner product of psi with phi.
We first write psi and phi
as sums over the basis vectors.
So this is equal to sum
over two sets of basis vectors,
a prime and a,
psi star of a prime times a prime.
That's the bra vector.
We complex conjugate,
of course,
when we deal with bra vectors.
That's the psi half of it.
And then the phi half of it is the
sum over a of phi of a times a.
Phi of a being the coefficients of the phi vector,
psi star being the coefficients of the psi bra vector.
All right.
Now,
phi of a is just a number.
Psi star of a is just a number.
And the inner product of a prime
with a is just the Kronecker delta.
So all of this adds up to
sum of psi star of a prime,
phi of a,
and then a Kronecker delta of a and a prime,
which is exactly the instruction to
set a equal to a prime.
Now,
I think you've seen that before.
This is simply the rule about row vectors.
If psi star of a
is represented by a row vector,
psi star of a1,
blah,
and phi is represented by a column vector,
then this is just the
rule to take this times this,
plus this times this,
plus this times that.
So this is the common garden
variety quantum mechanical in a product.
أنا
كن...
don't need to go through the same exercise here.
We can immediately write down what the
result is going to be just by analogy.
It's almost not even an analogy,
it's just replacing wherever we see a's put x's,
and wherever we see some put integral.
The inner product of two state vectors
for a particle on a line is integral
dx psi star of x phi of x.
It satisfies incidentally one of
the basic rules of inner products.
What happens to an inner product
if you interchange the two vectors?
What's the relation between
the inner product psi phi
and the inner product phi psi?
Complex conjugation.
Now what would happen in here
if you interchange psi with phi?
You'd wind up writing phi star here and psi here.
That again would be the complex conjugate.
And for exactly the same reasons.
Alright,
so this is equal to this.
For both discrete systems and for these continuous systems.
Inner products.
The inner product of a vector with
itself is the norm of the vector.
And just as in previous examples,
you normalize the vector to
one to express the fact that
total probability adds up to one.
So,
that's the problem.
Not much difference.
Just a difference of notation.
And I think what gets to be confusing
about it is you know both of these things.
You know about these simple row vectors and column vectors.
And you know about functions.
But you're not used to thinking of functions as vectors.
Or maybe you are.
If you are,
good.
But if you're not used to using functions as vectors.
F of x's or functions as psi of x's.
Then you have to get used to it.
But it's not.
But functions are vectors in a vector space.
You can add them.
You can multiply them by complex constants.
And you can add them.
You can multiply them by numbers.
And so they satisfy the axioms of a vector space.
Space of functions is a vector space.
Now,
sometimes you may want.
Yeah.
In more classical mathematics,
would you put as the limits of integration minus and
plus infinity?
You would.
Which incidentally says something.
It says that we shouldn't be
thinking about functions which grow at infinity,
for example.
We should be only thinking
about functions which are square integrable.
Now we're going to have to modify that.
Square integral means you square them.
This is called squaring them.
That the integral exists.
Functions which grow at infinity won't do that.
Now those are crazy.
Because it would say that all of the.
If you had functions which grew at infinity,
where would the probability be?
The probability would be all located off at infinity.
And that's not what we want.
We want to be talking about probability
distributions which have a total finite probability under
them.
So.
That means we should take perhaps with a grain
of salt the idea that we can write down
any function.
But for the moment we're going to
be a little bit loose about that.
Okay.
I think I'll slow down here for a few
minutes and let you digest that and ask for questions.
Yeah.
Can I go back to entanglement?
Yeah,
go ahead.
I didn't want to,
I meant about this but okay.
Maybe this is quick.
It seems like just about everything must
be entangled with something almost all the time.
Oh,
yeah.
Yeah.
You're entangled with all sorts
of things in the environment.
And we haven't talked about
the importance of a complex environment.
Uh.
It's not so important in the very foundations of it.
the subject,
but it is important to why we
see the world the way we are,
that we're constantly
being bombarded and getting entangled with things.
Has a theory of distribution been useful for physicists,
or is it just …
Oh,
boy.
Certainly.
Okay,
so it's not just some … it
didn't just clean up the Dirac delta function,
is it?
Oh,
you mean,
has it … well,
oh,
I see what you mean.
You mean,
has it done
anything else besides clean up the … I don't know.
I don't know.
I think it's made rigorous a set
of concepts that physicists use all the time.
Has it really
changed?
No,
no.
The theory of distributions … yeah,
I'll tell you what it did for physicists.
えっと
made them have to argue less with mathematicians
it was one of the many
examples where mathematicians got dragged screaming and
kicking by physicists
of course the opposite also happens but
it was an example where mathematicians
at first looked at this thing
and said what are you
crazy that doesn't make any sense
it's non-rigorous and
and in time
they came to peace with it
through defining it in their own way
but no i i don't
think the mathematical structure of it
has influenced physics as much as you might have expected
unfortunately because there are big problems
of confusion related to it in
quantum field theory and it hasn't
presented
all those problems
okay
okay next place we want to go is observables
we want to talk about observables
and give some examples of observables
observables are linear operators
what are linear operators acting on a space of functions
they're operations on the state on
a function that gives another function
if you have a linear operator let's call it m
for some reason i've saved l to stand for observables
and i've used previously m for a general
linear operator so let's continue to do so
whatever m is it's a machine
and thought of as an abstract operator in a space
it takes a state vector into another state vector
psi prime let's say
or a vector in the vector space
but it also can be thought of
as a thing which acts on wave functions
every state has a wave function that describes it
and the machine
oh that's why that was why we
called it m yes i remember now
we called it m for machine
the machine can also be
thought of as acting on a
wave function to give another wave function
so let's think of it that way uh...
let's think of it in concrete terms
as an action that we do on
a wave function to produce another wave function
now it's linear
linear means that when it acts on the sum of
two functions it gives back the sum of the results
it means that if it acts on a function which
is a numerical product a numerical multiple of some function
it gives back the same numerical uh...
multiple
all the ideas of what a linear operator are
continue to be exactly the same
let's talk about some linear op- oh oh
okay that's that's the notion of a linear operator
now what about a hermitian linear operator
i'll tell you the definition of
hermitian we've we've talked about it before
but i'm going to give it
to you in a condensed form
the condensed form
is also true
for all of the vector spaces we've studied
and you may recognize it
uh...
if not go back and prove
that it follows from the previous definitions
a hermitian operator
hermitian for operators is roughly
speaking the analog of real
as opposed to complex
okay here's what's true about hermitian operators
if you have a hermitian operator
which i will now call L
right
then it has the property that if you
take if you act on a wave function psi
or state vector psi
and take its inner product with phi
that that is equal to
psi L phi but not quite
what do i have to do with it
complex conjugate it
now if L were not let's go back a
step supposing L was not hermitian would this be right
not quite
what would we have to do
we'd have to put a dagger here
in other words we'd have
to roughly speaking complex conjugate L
okay
if L is hermitian
then the rule for that
is that it's matrix elements
it's when sandwiched
when sandwiched in opposite order
you don't have to complex conjugate L
because it's already
the analog of real
this is the condition that an operator is hermitian
that's important because hermitian operators
are the class of observables
okay
so let's work out one or
two hermitian operators while we're at it
i guess we may need this so
let's work out a couple
first of all one of the simplest things
that i can do to a wave function
i don't know what's there
there are many simple things i can do to it
but a very simple thing
is to multiply it by x
an even simpler thing would be
to multiply it by a simple number
but let's take slightly more
complicated and multiply it by x
multiplying by x gives back a function
so this is at minimum an operation on a function
is it linear
sure it is
if x multiplies psi of x
let's say plus phi of x
it gives x psi of
x plus x phi of x
in other words when it acts on a
sum it gives the sum of the results
if it acts on a numerical multiple of a psi
it gives back the numerical multiple
so it's a linear operator
question is it hermitian
is it a hermitian operator
okay so let's check
here's what we have to take
we have to take
psi
in a product
of
x times phi
that's this one
oh sorry i think i wanted
to do it the other way
phi x psi the top
phi x psi
and
and ask whether this is true or not
we'll check in a minute
and x is a real number right?
no x is not a
number x is a function x
we've multiplied one function by another function
that takes functions to functions
x is not a number
it's a variable
any given value of it is a number
but
it's a machine that takes the function psi of x
and replaces it by x psi of x
alright so let's calculate
the wave function
of
the ket vector
is x psi of x
the wave function of the bra vector
is phi star of x
the inner product is
let's put some brackets around it
bracket
this is a ket vector inside the red bracket
and this is a bra vector
and the rule for taking the inner product
whoops i think i interchanged star and not star
but the rule for taking the inner product
is to integrate
so let's get rid of the bracket here
and just integrate dx
oops sorry dx
alright that's in this order
what about this order
this order over here the inner product without the star
without the star there's a star here
the thing we're going to compare it with
is the same thing
except with psi star
x phi of x
well look at it
is this integral the complex conjugate of this
yes it is
the complex conjugate of phi star
is phi
the complex conjugate of psi is psi star
and what about x
x is its own complex conjugate
so what about this
so yes indeed
x is an operator which satisfies
the basic rule of Hermitian operator
that if you interchange the psi and the phi
it complex conjugates
alright if yeah
what observable does x correspond to
position
it is the position
is the delta function a
eigenvector of position
well maybe we'll come to that next time
I think I won't yes it is
but we'll come back to that
x is an observable
what does it correspond to
it corresponds to position of a particle
we will prove that by showing that the eigenvectors x
that the vectors x are eigenvectors of that operator
but not right now we'll do that the next time
it's easy it's trivial
stupid question
so
am I correct in assuming that
when you write x up there
it's implied that that is really f of x
the x is a function of x
so it is
x is an n f of x
yes it's implied that that
x is a function of x
it has a whole bunch of different values
it has a whole bunch that's right
it itself is a function
which is multiplying another function
alright
so it's an operation on
a function which gives another function
yeah
that's exactly right
let's take another operation or operator
differentiation
if I differentiate a function I get a function
that's the first test of whether it's an operator
if I differentiate the sum of two
functions I get the sum of derivatives
if I differentiate a numerical multiple of a function
I get the numerical multiple of the derivative
it's a linear function
is it a Hermitian operator
so here we have to
here we have to get ourselves a fresh blackboard
and check once and for all whether it's
well check whether it's Hermitian
okay
what happened what is
let's call a derivative operation
let's call it capital D
D
on psi
gives us some psi prime
what about wave functions
D when it acts on psi of x
by definition now
this is the definition of how D acts
it simply gives D psi by D x
I may sometimes lapse into calling
this partial derivative with respect to x
that's fine
doesn't matter
there's only one x
so it just differentiates
it creates a new function
it's a linear operator
is it Hermitian
okay so let's write down the two sides
of the Hermitian condition here
and see if they're the same
that's all there is to it
the left side is integral
phi star of x
times the operation
D on psi
which is just D psi by D x
what's the other way of doing it
or the right hand side
the other way of doing it is
integral
psi star
not doing the same thing
doing something different
psi star of x
D phi by D x
and the question is
whether this is the complex conjugate of this
so let's write equals with a question mark
we don't know
complex conjugate
so let's do this integral over here
first of all the thing in the bracket here
is just equal
to integral
psi of x
D phi star
by D x
just complex conjugate
the complex conjugate of a product
is just a product of complex conjugates
so the thing in the bracket
is psi of x D phi star by D x
and we're asking whether this is equal to this
they look similar
this has a psi
this has a phi star
but unfortunately this one has psi differentiated
and this one has a phi star
and this one has a psi
you know what I mean
psi and phi
how do you go from this to this
integration by parts
and integrate like this assuming
what are we assuming when we
say we can integrate by parts
we're assuming that far away the integral
the functions go to zero
that the end point contributions from integration by parts
don't give us anything
well of course the functions
must go to zero far away
because the integral of the total thing must be one
so we can integrate by parts
everybody know what integrating by parts is
if not find out fast
it's simply a rule
I'll tell you what the rule is
you can shift the derivative from one
if you have a product
D x
this is D x here
if you have a product
psi of x times the
derivative of phi star of x
then you can simply shift
the derivative from one function to the other
but it's at a cost
the cost
a minus sign right
good
so this is equal
to minus
the integral
phi star of x
D psi by D x
whoops
we're in bad shape
this is integral phi star D psi
D x
this is minus the integral of
phi star D psi D x
they are not equal
in fact worse than that
they're absolutely the opposite of each other
the opposite in the sense
of the negative of each other
can we fix it
well no we can't fix this
but we can redefine an operator which is her mission
the redefined operator which is her mission
is not derivative
it is minus r
the minus sign doesn't matter
you can put i or minus i
D by D x
so let's go through it again
and check whether now it's her mission
this is the new thing that we're going to call
and we're going to give it a different name
I'm not going to call
it D because it's not derivative
it's minus i times the derivative
anybody have a good suggestion
for what I might call this
P brilliant
P
P for
momentum
alright
and if I really wanted it
to be momentum with units of momentum
what else would I put there
where
right or left
right
well you can put it on the
left but then you better put it downstairs
alright but we're not going to worry about h bar
we're going to use our usual convention of equations
ignoring h bar for the moment
P is minus i D by D x
let's see what happens
over here we have to replace
this by an i over here
minus i thank you
minus i
what about this one
we've complex conjugated everything
we better change the sign
because the complex conjugate of minus i is plus i
and so
let's do it this way
minus i
and we should get plus i here
if it's Hermitian
why
because in the process of taking the complex conjugate
every i gets converted to a minus i
and every minus i gets converted to a plus i
is it true now
yeah
why
because this is equal to minus this
that's what we proved over here
okay
so if we stick an i here
because i changes sign in the complex conjugate
this little operation here
tells us
that minus i D by
D x is a Hermitian operator
it's a little odd isn't it
that minus i D by D x
should somehow be a real thing
should represent a real thing
and that D by D x should not
but
let's check something out
let's check something out right now
let's just
we're going to finish up in a moment
we haven't talked about expectation values yet tonight
but I think you can
guess how to think about them
expectation values in the state psi
of an observable L
are just the sandwich composed of
psi on both sides and L in the middle
so let's take the expectation value of momentum
it's integral
psi star of x
psi of x
and then according to the rule here
p is minus i D by D x
P is minus i D by D x
is this real or imaginary?
you're wrong
it's real
so let's prove that it's real
I hope it's real
god I hope it's real
okay
alright
so let's integrate by parts
this is equal
first of all let's take out the minus i
minus i integral psi star of
x D psi by D x
now let's look at this again
so let's integrate that by parts
this is equal to
minus i
and then we can switch the derivative
we can switch the derivative to the starred variable
integral
D psi star
by D x
times psi of x
but then
in doing the integration by parts
we have to change the sign
so here we have a little theorem
the integral of this thing here with a minus i
is the integral of this
thing here with a plus i
what's the complex conjugate of this whole thing?
the complex conjugate it
you replace it with this
you replace psi star by psi
well psi is over here
you replace D psi by D x
by D psi star by D x
and you replace minus i by plus i
this over here is the complex conjugate of this
can everybody see that or shall I explain it further?
let's put a minus i out here
and write that this is equal
to D psi by D x
this just gives us D psi by D x
minus i D psi by D x
this is clearly the complex
the integral
are complex conjugates of each other
D psi by D x
is the complex conjugate of this
that one is the complex conjugate of this
and i and minus i
are complex conjugates of each other
so given that this is the complex conjugate of this
and they're equal to each other
what do you say about a thing
which is equal to its own complex conjugate?
it's real
so we prove a rather startling fact
that the integral of psi star of x
minus i D psi by D x is real
no,
yes i did yeah,
right
and again it's because when you integrate by parts
you pick up an extra minus sign
so instead of this thing being minus its complex conjugate
it's plus its complex conjugate
okay,
so what did we learn?
we learned that this is a Hermitian operator
it's a Hermitian operator and therefore
an observable in quantum mechanics
the next time we'll explore something like that
a little more.
We'll discuss what this has to do with Fourier transforms.
We'll
discuss questions about what the
probability for finding the particle at
different locations are,
but then we'll also talk about what the probability for
having different momentum are.
And then we'll move to the Schrodinger equation.
We'll move to the evolution of the wave function.
This after all now is
really,
in the classic sense of the word,
a wave function,
and we'll think about
how it evolves with time.
Oh,
one other thing we could do it tonight.
I
think we're probably at the point of diminishing returns.
Are you exhausted?
We could do one more thing.
Let me do one more thing for you.
Let's calculate an
interesting quantity.
And why it's an interesting quantity
we'll come to in a moment.
So let's take a
quantity which seems very dull,
but which is interesting,
and calculate it.
It's the
commutator of x with p.
Take any wave function,
whatever it is,
psi of x,
anyone,
and we're going to do
two things with it.
We're first going to multiply it by x,
and then we're going to
multiply it by minus i d by,
or operate with minus i d by dx.
Alright?
This can be
called px operating on psi.
This is p,
this is x in the order first x,
then p.
Then we're going to calculate it the other way.
xp,
and then we're going to calculate it by psi.
on psi.
What is that?
Let's,
on the other half of the blackboard over here,
we're going to write x
times minus i d by dx,
psi of x,
and see what we get.
In fact,
what we're going to do is we're
going to compute the commutator,
which means we're going to calculate
this one with a plus sign,
we're going to calculate this one with a
plus sign and this one with a minus sign.
So this one with a minus sign,
but before we subtract them,
let's just calculate them.
All right,
this is just minus i,
and now the derivative of a product.
The derivative of a
product.
This derivative here now has to act on the
whole result of x acting on psi of x.
x acting on psi of
x gives a new wave function,
and then p acts on it.
So,
what do you get when you hit the product?
You get two terms.
The first term is the derivative of x times psi,
derivative of x is just 1,
so the first term is just psi of x,
and the second term is
plus x d psi by dx.
Everybody agree with that?
Okay.
The derivative hit x and left psi,
and
and then the derivative hits i and left x.
That's this side over here.
Now what about this side over here?
Here,
the d by dx doesn't act on x,
it just acts this way.
It just acts on psi of x and gives
us minus i d by dx psi of x.
x minus i x d psi by dx.
Now let's subtract them.
Let's take this one with
minus and this one with plus.
This corresponds to taking the commutator of
x with p acting on psi of x.
Commutator of x with p is another
operator and it acts on psi of x.
What do we get when we subtract?
Let's see,
this one now has to come
with a plus sign since we're subtracting.
Since we're subtracting,
we have to change sign here.
And this term cancels.
Yeah.
This term cancels,
goes away,
and all we're left with is psi of x.
That's all we're left with.
This term cancels.
And we're just left with,
what is it,
i psi of x?
i psi of x.
All right,
so here's what we found.
For any psi of x whatever,
for any psi of x,
the commutator of x with p
acting on psi of x just gives,
is it plus i?
I think it's plus i psi of x.
Now,
if an operator acting on any wave form,
gives another operator,
if the operator x p acting on any wave function
is the same as i acting on that same wave function,
for any wave function whatever,
it follows that this operator is equal to this operator.
Another way of saying it
is if x p minus i,
put it all in a big bracket,
when it hits any wave function at all,
gives zero,
then it means that this is zero.
There's only one operator which gives
zero when it acts on every state,
on every vector.
Okay,
there's no vector which escapes when this thing hits it.
All right,
the implication is that this thing is zero.
There's only one operator which annihilates,
which kills every vector,
and it's a zero.
So.
x p minus i.
x p minus,
or commutator x p is equal to i.
If I put back the h bars,
there would be an h bar here.
Yeah,
i h bar.
We've seen things like this before.
You may have to go back to your classical mechanics,
we've seen things before like this.
We've seen Poisson brackets,
which had similar relationships.
The Poisson bracket of x
with p is equal to 1.
Earlier in this course,
we discussed the potential relationship,
we had reason to discuss why commutators,
it had to do with Schrodinger's equation,
go back.
But we discussed this.
We discussed the relationship,
that there might be a relationship between commutators
and Poisson brackets,
and in particular,
the relation involved this i h bar.
Okay.
This is actually where Dirac
began his discussion of quantum mechanics.
He said there must be something analogous
to a Poisson bracket in quantum mechanics.
And the only thing you could think
of which had the right algebraic structure,
was anti-symmetric,
it had a certain mathematical structure,
was the commutator.
And he postulated that commutators and
Poisson brackets were related with each other,
through
an i h bar,
and then proceeded to go exactly
backwards from the way that we went.
He said,
if this is the Poisson bracket,
then this must be the commutator,
and so there
must be an operator p
whose commutator with x is i,
and he went back through the operation,
and discovered that p was
analogous to the i h bar.
And so he said,
what does this mean?
So what we found is that the
commutator is minus i d by dx.
So he went in the opposite direction.
We discovered p by just playing a game,
said,
let's see,
how about this operator d by dx?
What does it do?
What we found is that it was not Hermitian.
We had to multiply it
by i to make it Hermitian.
We explored it a little bit,
found out some interesting properties of it,
but the most
interesting property is that its commutator
is equal to i h bar,
which,
uh,
I think it's
It suggests that it's connected with the Poisson bracket,
the classical Poisson bracket being
one.
Of course,
the upshot of it is,
and of course we need to
do a lot more to convince ourselves
that the operator minus i d by
dx really behaves like quantum mechanical momentum.
We can't just say,
well,
it looks like a Poisson bracket,
it must be the quantum mechanical
momentum.
We have to show that wave packets move.
They move with velocities that are governed by this,
that the thing,
that it's conserved,
that it has all the properties of momentum,
but we will.
There must be some connection between
this abstract operator minus i derivative mass.
And what?
And the idea of mass.
Well,
we would like to show that
in some way that it is.
Well,
we would like to show that
in some way that it is.
That it's the mass times the velocity.
So what we'll try,
what we'll eventually show is that
if you have a wave packet,
in other
words a psi of x,
which is a concentrated distribution like this,
that that wave packet
moves along the x-axis with a velocity which
is given by the expectation value of this
momentum operator divided by the mass.
That's what we would like to show.
That the velocity with which the mass moves
along the x-axis is the velocity with which
this wave packet propagates along the axis.
That velocity,
you can call it the group velocity,
it's usually called the group velocity,
the
velocity that the group of waves moves along
times the mass of the particle is equal to
the expectation value of the momentum.
Once we do that,
then I think we're,
and that it's conserved,
that'll take us a long way
to calling it momentum.
I'm sorry.
At some point we have to say
quantum mechanics is more fundamental than classical mechanics.
And the definition of momentum should be
through quantum mechanics and then we should show
it behaves in a certain way
when particles are heavy and so forth.
Okay.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.