Stanford University
I gather you people had
a lot of fun with entanglement.
It's a good subject.
I mean,
it really is
absolutely the heart of quantum mechanics.
But of course,
yeah,
I mean,
I would say up till now,
we have really studied the foundations of quantum mechanics
in very,
very simple systems,
and the foundations have been laid out,
they've been exposed,
you know what they are,
and really the only thing left to
do now is to study some examples.
Yeah?
So in classical mechanics,
we started with a very small number of empirical
observations by Newton,
and sort of everything else was obtained by mathematics,
sort of,
more or less.
More or less.
So what's the equivalent in the case of quantum mechanics?
What are the sort of basic atomic empirical observations?
You mean historically?
Well,
the minimal set that you need.
I would say the minimum set is what we described
when we talked about an apparatus which you could rotate,
a spin,
and a window in the
apparatus that was zero and one.
That's logically the simplest thing you can do.
It's of course not the way quantum mechanics was discovered.
But just as analyzing the experimental data that you
would get by taking an electron or a spin,
orienting your detector,
pressing the M button,
the measure button,
and getting a one or minus one on the screen,
doing this over and over and over again,
accumulating statistics,
is the simplest thing you can do.
And you have to do that for each physical property,
like momentum,
like spin,
and so on?
Yes.
Right.
A quick question on the system you
described with the singlet and the triplet,
and the photon going off.
You said if you capture the
photon quickly and reflect it back,
is that simply because you only have a
system with just the singlet and the triplet,
or can any other photon also cause disentanglement?
No.
That's a good question.
Well,
you don't have a photon out there.
You have a photon or you don't have a photon.
The radiation field itself is
not in a state of positive...
Whether or not you have a photon out there could
also be thought of as a zero or a one.
The radiation state itself,
the radiation system itself,
could be modeled by having another degree of freedom,
and the other degree of freedom could
also have a zero or a one.
Zero would mean no photon present.
One would mean a photon present.
Okay?
So,
what happens...
Let's suppose we start with a singlet and a triplet,
superposed in this way,
with no photons.
Alright?
So to express the fact that there are no photons,
we have to put another degree of freedom in here,
and we have to say,
this is a tensor product
with a state of the
radiation field which has no photons.
That's the way...
Keep in mind,
this here represents the two electrons,
either in the singlet state or the triplet state,
and this represents the state of the radiation field.
Now,
if you wait for a little while,
and while the electrons are entangled here,
they are not entangled with the radiation field.
This is a simple product
of a vacuum of photons,
no photons,
and a particular state of the electron pair.
In fact,
I said this was entangled.
This is not entangled.
This combination was just up-down.
Alright,
now you let it evolve for a while.
What happens is the singlet
stays the singlet,
and it does not emit a photon,
but the triplet,
what happens to it,
it becomes the singlet,
and emits a photon.
So what happens to this state,
it evolves into the linear combination
of singlet,
times no photon and one photon.
In other words,
it's a singlet electron,
it's a singlet state of the electron pair,
but a linear superposition,
quantum linear superposition,
of no photon and one photon.
That seems a little bit strange,
but it's an important idea
that you can not only superpose states of a particle,
you can superpose
the number of particles.
No particle and one particle
can be quantum,
any two states can be superposed.
So,
the state of a system of a vacuum,
empty space,
that's a state with no photons,
a state with one photon,
is a state with one photon,
and you can add them.
That's what's happening here.
You would eventually come to the state,
which is singlet,
times,
no photon,
plus one photon.
This state now,
is it entangled between the,
are the electrons entangled with the radiation field?
No,
because it's pure product.
But are the electrons entangled with each other?
Yeah,
because it's a singlet state.
Only the singlet state.
Only the singlet state appears here,
and the singlet state is an entangled state.
So the electrons are entangled with each other,
but they're not entangled with the radiation field.
On the other hand,
the radiation field is left in a superposition of states
of having a photon and not having a photon.
So what do we start with?
We started with a
unentangled state of the electrons,
totally unentangled with the radiation field.
I say this is unentangled
with the electrons,
because that's what we started with,
UD,
and no photon.
We started with unentangled,
completely everything unentangled,
waited for a photon to be emitted.
When the photon was emitted,
the singlet,
the triplet state became the singlet state,
but it emitted a photon,
and the result was an entangled state of the electrons,
but unentangled with the radiation field.
Okay.
It's a pretty tricky set of ideas.
You haven't brought anything external in,
like a magnetic field,
so that,
what's causing the...
No,
no,
no.
In order to,
no,
there's nothing external here.
So what causes the triplet to emit the photon
is the interaction with the other electron,
which is why they're not entangled.
Right.
Right,
the interaction between the two electrons,
roughly speaking,
each electron is in the magnetic field of another electron,
but what they want to do is maximally anti-align,
or better yet,
they want to minimize or make maximally negative
the value of sigma dot tau.
That's the,
so they emit a photon to do that.
All right,
the last time we started to move on
to the problem of proton,
we were talking about the particle motion.
Forget particle spin.
Of course,
real particles may have both position and spin.
But let's concentrate for today on
questions
relating to the position of particles.
The simplest example we can think of
is a particle moving on a one-dimensional axis,
x.
There it is.
Before we study that,
I wanted to do a little mathematical interlude
that'll take at most 10 minutes,
maybe less,
having to do with Fourier analysis,
Fourier transforms,
and its relationship to a,
you know,
to the Dirac delta function.
So let's take a blackboard
and do some mathematics on it.
The function e to the i p x,
let's take p to be a number.
p is a number now,
it's not a variable.
e to the i p x.
That's a combination of sine and cosine functions,
and therefore it has a wave-like character,
and we call it a plane wave.
We call it a plane wave.
Just simple waves,
cosines and sines,
a combination of cosine p dot x and sine p,
i sine p dot x.
And you can think of it as a wave.
Of course it's not moving,
just writing e to the i p x
doesn't give it any time dependence,
so it doesn't move,
but it's wave-like.
Okay.
A very wide class of functions,
and certainly all the functions
we will be interested in,
can be written as sums of plane waves,
or integrals,
better yet,
integrals of plane waves.
And decomposing a function,
in this case a function of x,
let's call it psi of x,
decomposing it into plane waves
is called Fourier analysis.
Now most of you know that.
In fact,
most of you,
or some of you in any case,
know about Fourier analysis,
but we're going to spell it out now.
Every function,
every function that we will be interested in,
in fact,
it's probably true
that that excludes almost all functions,
but we also exclude almost all functions
when we say that they're continuous,
when we say that they're differentiable,
when we say that we can express them
in any meaningful,
sensible form,
we exclude almost all functions.
But if we take our functions
to be reasonably continuous,
and I won't try to be very,
very precise,
continuous and not to blow up at infinity,
in other words,
to fall to zero
at minus infinity,
at plus infinity,
almost all functions,
all functions we will be interested in
can be expanded in waves in this way.
Now expanded means they can be written
as integrals over p.
What is p?
p tells you how fast the wave oscillates.
This is some moderate value of p.
If I increase p,
I create a wave with a very short wavelength.
Decrease p,
I'm talking about a wave
with a very long wavelength.
So this is just saying we can
decompose a function
into waves of different wavelengths.
Each wavelength has an amplitude,
an amount of that wave that's in there,
and we'll call that psi twiddle of p
times e to the i p x.
Psi twiddle of p is
just the amplitude of the wave.
The amplitude that the wave of type p
has strength psi of p
in the function psi of x.
Fourier's theorem
is a theorem which tells you
how to reconstruct
psi twiddle of p.
I'm going to,
just for definition,
this is purely for definition,
I'm going to put a one
over square root of two pi here.
That's a convention.
We could have absorbed it into
psi twiddle of p.
Psi twiddle is complex?
Psi twiddle typically is complex
and so will psi of x be complex.
That's a good question.
Both of them I intend
for the moment to be complex.
Now it may happen that one of these is real
and the other one is complex.
That can happen,
but at the moment
we're just interested in arbitrary complex functions.
That's right.
Alright,
the question is how do you reconstruct
psi twiddle of p from psi of x?
And I'm going to leave it as something
you can look up if you don't know it.
It's the basic theorem of Fourier analysis
that psi twiddle of p
and notice that psi of x
is an integral over p.
Psi twiddle of p is going
to be an integral over x.
dx over square root of two pi.
Times
psi of x
and the natural thing would be to write here
e to the i p x,
but it's not.
It's e to the minus i p x.
Two pi,
thank you.
That's the basic theorem of Fourier analysis
that if psi of x is the Fourier transform
of psi twiddle of p,
defined in this way,
then psi twiddle of p
is a Fourier transform of psi of x.
Very much the same pattern,
except that you put
e to the minus i p x there.
We will need that theorem.
So if you don't know that theorem,
it's a very important theorem in quantum mechanics.
And it expresses a kind of reciprocal relationship
between x and p.
Which of course ultimately are
going to be position and momentum.
Okay,
that's one little mathematical interlude that we will need.
The other has to do with the delta function.
And then we're going to combine them together.
For a mathematician,
the definition,
we have an intuitive definition of a delta function.
It's a high narrow function.
It's so narrow,
that its width is essentially zero.
And so high that the area under it is one.
Okay.
We can call that a representation of a delta function.
A definition of the delta function,
of course the delta function is not a real function.
It's infinite somewheres,
but you know,
that's an anal attitude about the delta function.
It took years for physicists incidentally
to convince mathematicians that delta functions were okay.
But mathematicians didn't like them for a very good reason.
Their functions,
you can't square them though.
If you square them,
there's still zero everywhere except at the same point.
But instead of having a height
big enough to make the area one,
they have a height which is the square of that.
And so they themselves are not,
are worse objects.
But they got over it.
I mean,
they got over it.
And I'm told now by some of my mathematician friends
that it's okay to write a delta function.
Okay.
Properties of a delta function.
The first thing,
and the way a mathematician would think about it,
is it's an operation that
you can do on a function.
In particular,
you can integrate,
any function of x,
any reasonable function of x,
with a delta function,
delta of x minus x prime.
Oh,
no,
let's go a step,
let's even go,
let's not even do that yet.
Let's take delta of x minus x prime
times f of x.
First property of the delta function
is that this is equal to,
f of x prime,
times delta of x minus x prime.
Why would that be true?
That certainly wouldn't be true
for a general function delta.
The reason it's true is because delta is only non-zero
when x is equal to x prime.
So it's no big deal.
Delta of x minus x prime is only non-zero
when x equals x prime,
and therefore it doesn't matter whether
you put x or x prime
when multiplying it by x.
It's just a function.
So that's property number one.
Now property number two,
that pretty much follows from that,
no,
not yet.
Property one,
next property two.
Integral of delta of x minus x prime
is always equal to one.
That's just a statement that the area
under this bump is equal to one.
And it doesn't matter where you put it.
You put it over here,
or you put it over here,
or you put it over here.
The area is always equal to one.
And so the integral of
delta of x minus x prime,
let's say from minus infinity to infinity,
is always equal to one.
And the last property,
which follows from these two,
is that the integral
of delta of x minus x prime,
f of x,
is equal to f of x prime.
Now,
you see it in two ways.
One is that you can say,
look,
the delta function is only non-zero
when x is equal to x prime,
and so it picks out the
value x prime in f of x.
Or you can just say,
use property,
where is it,
property number one,
to rewrite this in the form f of x prime
integral delta of x minus x prime,
dx.
Why am I allowed to
bring the f of x prime
on the outside?
Because it doesn't depend on x.
It's just...
x prime itself is a constant.
Hm?
It's a fixed value.
From the point of view of...
Yeah,
that's right.
That's right.
So I just bring it on the outside,
and then I say the integral
under the delta function is one,
and so I just get f of x prime.
All right,
so those are
the obvious properties of the delta function,
which you might use
to axiomatize what a delta function is.
Okay.
Now I'm going to prove
a theorem
which provides a representation
of the delta function,
an important representation
of the delta function.
Let's...
I think we can erase this for the moment.
Did I want to erase that?
I probably didn't.
Integral f of x delta of x minus x prime
is equal to f of x prime.
Now,
this actually is a function
of the delta function.
This is the way the mathematicians define it.
As an operation that you do on a function
that gives the value of the function
at some point.
And this is enough to define
the delta function.
It's not enough to define the delta function
if there's only one function f.
If this is true for every function f,
there's only one function,
only one delta here
that will fill that function.
And this is the delta function.
Okay.
So this can be taken
as the defining function
if for all f this is true,
then this is the delta function.
What's that?
Yeah,
dx.
Good.
Okay.
Now what I want to do
is I want to take
the two top equations
and put them together.
Here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to write that
psi of x is equal to this thing,
but then I'm going to plug in
for this thing
the second equation
and re-express psi of x
back in terms of the function
psi of x itself.
And let's see what we get.
Either we'll get something
completely trivially stupid,
or we'll get something completely trivially stupid,
or we will learn something.
And the fact is we will learn something.
So let's take psi of x and write it.
Psi of x is equal,
I'm just going to write down,
integral dp over square root of 2 pi
e to the i px.
And now I'm going to shove in
the second equation
for psi twiddle of p.
And that is,
let's put a bracket around it,
dx,
integral,
let's call,
let's,
yeah,
hold on a second.
Let's call it psi of x prime.
And to make it psi of x prime,
all we have to do is put a prime here.
I've just changed the name of the variable
on the left side.
And to do so,
of course,
I have to change the name of the variable
on the right hand side.
All right.
I don't want to confuse x and x prime.
Now the second equation for psi twiddle of p,
that I can leave as it is
and just write that it's integral dx
over square root of 2 pi
psi of x
e to the minus i px.
So I've just plugged in psi twiddle of p.
Now integrals,
are generally insensitive to which order
you do the integrals,
particularly if they're integrations
from minus infinity to infinity,
as they are here,
both of them.
If they're well defined
and they converge and everything,
then it doesn't matter which order
you do the integrations.
So let's start
let's isolate some things.
Let's put here integral dp over 2 pi
oh,
over 2 pi.
We now have a single factor of 2 pi.
One coming from here,
one coming from here.
Let's isolate e to the i p
x prime minus x from here.
We have e to the i px prime,
e to the minus i px.
That's e to the i px minus x prime.
And then,
we still haven't written down psi of x,
so let's write down psi of x.
And now interchange the order of integration
of x and p and write this as integral dx.
Integral dx.
That's equal to psi of x prime.
So look what we have.
We have a relationship between
psi of x and psi of x prime.
We have a way of writing psi of x prime
in terms of psi of x.
But what is it?
But look what stands here.
Take this whole thing here.
This is an integral over p.
It's true.
But all it is is some
function of x prime minus x,
right?
Let's give it a name.
Let's call it the capital delta function.
Let's call this the capital delta function.
And write this dx capital
delta of x prime minus x.
This whole mess here,
including the 2 pi and everything else,
after integration over p times psi of x
equals psi of x prime.
What does it tell you about this capital delta function?
It's just a good old delta function.
So we've proved an interesting relationship
and one that is at the heart of
many,
many things in quantum mechanics.
Here it is.
The integral dp over 2 pi
e to the i p of x prime.
So the integral dp over 2 pi
e to the i p of x prime
is equal to delta of x minus x prime.
In other words,
a kind of screwball way of writing the delta function
by itself expressing it as a Fourier transform
or a sum of plane waves.
We can also write this in another way.
We can write,
we're not writing the same thing,
I'm writing a different thing.
But just by interchanging x and p,
by interchanging x and p,
I can write another equation,
dx over 2 pi e to the
i x of p minus p prime
equals delta of p minus p prime.
This is,
these two are identical.
I've just changed the name of
x to p and p to x.
If this equation is true,
this equation is true
because they're exactly the same equation
except that I've interchanged the name
x with p and p with x.
So this is an important,
as I said,
fact about delta functions.
These are the basic methods of the delta function.
These are the mathematical facts that we need.
This here is not important.
We've got it on the blackboard over there.
Oh,
if you don't like the
way I got the second one
from the first one by just interchanging p and x,
you can go back to these equations
and instead of eliminating psi twiddle of p,
eliminate psi of x by substituting
in psi of x from here
and you'll get,
you know,
you just interchange p and x.
Good.
All right,
so now we have what we need.
Yeah?
On the left-hand side,
underneath the board that you just wrote down,
you wrote x prime minus x,
but then on the right board
you wrote x minus x prime.
Does that imply a factor?
Actually,
it doesn't matter.
It's a good question.
It doesn't matter,
and the reason is
delta of x minus x prime is unchanged
if you interchange x and x prime.
It's a symmetric function of its argument.
If you interchange delta of x minus x prime
is the same as delta of x prime minus x.
So you can check that.
So the answer is it doesn't matter.
But you're probably right.
Probably if I did the derivation systematically,
I might have gotten x prime minus x here,
but then in the end it doesn't matter.
Okay,
so let's add...
this equation over here.
Integral dp over 2 pi e to the i p,
either x minus x prime or x prime minus x,
doesn't matter,
is equal to delta of x minus x prime,
and integral dx over 2 pi e to
the i p minus p prime times x,
times x,
is equal to delta of p minus p prime.
All right,
now let's come back to the world of physics,
the world of quantum mechanics,
a particle on a line.
If we were doing classical physics,
we would describe the particle on the line,
the state of a particle on the line,
by a point in phase space,
and phase space consists of a value
of x and a value of p.
One of each.
For a one-dimensional particle,
just one.
One x and one p.
What about quantum mechanics?
How do we describe the
state of a quantum mechanical particle?
Well,
you can try to make some guesses.
Not how do you describe the state,
but how do we describe an orthonormal basis of states?
That always is the question.
When you start a new system,
you ask what defines the space of states,
and one way of defining the space of states
is to provide an orthogonal normalized basis of states.
And all states that are orthogonal,
then,
are linear superpositions of that basis.
Alright,
there are various possibilities.
You might wonder,
maybe the states can be represented
by the position of a particle,
x.
You might think maybe they can be represented
by the momentum of a particle.
Or you might wonder,
might the states be represented as a pair,
an x and a p,
or a p and a p?
This is large,
after all,
in classical physics,
it takes an x and a
p to describe the position of the,
the state of a particle.
What is it in quantum mechanics?
And the answer is in quantum mechanics,
that x and p are too much information.
In the same way that,
for the spin,
knowing sigma x and sigma y,
or sigma z and sigma y,
or whatever,
is too much information.
You can't know both of them simultaneously.
The same,
of course,
is true in quantum mechanics.
It's actually more familiar.
It's called,
of course,
the Heisenberg uncertainty principle,
but you can't know both.
So it's one or the other.
Classical physics,
a particle has an x and a p.
In some sense,
in quantum mechanics,
a particle has an x or a p.
Meaning to say,
you don't try to describe it by both,
you describe it by one or the other.
And we'll see what the relationship is in a moment.
So we suppose that there is an eigenvector
of an observable position
for every value of the observable position.
This vector represents
a state in which the
position of the particle is definite
and at position x.
So it's an eigenvector of something
which we'll think of as an observable x.
We'll understand a little more mathematically in a moment.
And,
like any good basis,
the point of a basis
is to write any wave function,
psi,
or any state vector,
as a superposition,
a sum of the basis vectors.
Since the basis vectors form
a continuous range of possibilities,
we write it as an integral dx,
replacing the sum,
and then eigenvector x
times something which depends on x.
This is completely analogous to
what we've done in the past,
where we've taken an arbitrary vector
and expanded it in terms of eigenvectors of something.
And these are the coefficients here,
and we call these things the wave function.
We call these things the wave function.
And in fact,
they are given by
the inner product of the eigenvector x
with the state psi.
That is psi of x.
This is fully analogous
to what we studied in simpler systems.
Wave function is the projection of the state
onto a state of definite x,
that's psi of x.
And secondly,
psi star of x times psi of x
is the probability
that the particle be found at position x.
Now,
strictly speaking,
we talked about it last time,
you have to think of it as a probability density,
a probability per unit x,
or probability per unit interval in x.
But you know how to take that into account.
All right,
so that's,
this is the basic framework of quantum mechanics
just being repeated,
except for a continuous variable.
The inner product between two vectors,
x and x prime,
is zero unless x equals x prime.
And if these were continuous,
if these were standard discrete variables,
we would say,
zero unless x equals x prime,
one if x equals x prime.
We would write
Kronica delta x x prime.
But x,
that's not helpful for continuous variables.
For continuous variables,
we write the delta function.
The delta function,
the Dirac delta function.
It's the continuum analog
of the Kronica delta.
We have bra vectors and ket vectors.
If a ket vector is
described by a psi of x,
a bra vector,
of course,
would be described in a similar way
in terms of psi star.
So,
ket's psi of x,
wave functions,
bra's psi star of x.
Usual thing,
nothing new here.
Finally,
the inner product,
not finally,
but the inner product,
not between x and x prime,
but between two arbitrary states,
let's call them
psi and phi.
Each one of which
can be expanded
by use of a wave function.
Phi is described by a wave function phi of x.
The bra vector psi,
can you tell the difference between my
psi's and my phi's when I say it?
Yeah,
okay.
This is Greek phi,
this is Greek psi.
But I never say psi,
I say psi.
I think the Greeks do also,
anybody know?
So is this really just a bunch of sci-fi?
Somebody must have thought of that.
Write that down.
Keep that.
Good.
Okay,
and this one is described by
psi star of x.
And if you expand them both
appropriately in eigenvectors of x,
bra vectors and ket vectors,
and then use the inner product rule here
for the eigenvectors of x,
you will get,
of course,
that the inner product is the integral,
the x.
It follows by simply expanding,
psi expanding,
phi,
and using this inner product here.
But it's also hardly surprising.
It's the same kind of formula
that we would have previously
for discrete systems.
And last but...
Question.
So position and momentum is too much information.
So we're asserting really that
it's just the position that gives us
a complete basis,
and pretty much anything else
is going to be too much information,
not just momentum.
So redundant.
Yeah.
Pretty much anything else.
Now,
the only reason I'm hesitating
is because we could imagine a particle
moving in two dimensions.
In that case,
it's not clear yet
whether we can know the x coordinate
of the position and the y coordinate
of momentum,
for example.
And the answer is you can.
So...
But if our system was just a particle
in one dimension,
that's it.
X and...
Right.
So that's a good point.
So does that mean that momentum then
can essentially be expanded,
can be treated as a psi?
So that means that momentum
can be treated as a psi,
and hence be expanded by an integral
involving x.
Is that right?
Yes.
The Fourier transform's a four.
Right.
Okay.
Let's...
Oh,
one last thing.
The probability density is psi star psi,
not psi star phi,
psi star psi.
And if I integrate psi star psi
with respect to x,
that would be the inner product
of psi with itself,
and that should be equal to one
on the basis that the total probability
should be one.
In other words,
nothing new again.
Physical states should be normalized.
Normalized so that...
So that integral psi star psi
is equal to one.
Okay.
Now...
Next.
Last time,
we talked about
some observables.
The position and the momentum.
So let's review a little bit about that.
Let's invent an operator.
Now,
capital X here...
Maybe I should...
How can I indicate that it's a capital X?
Um...
Let's put an extra line in.
That makes it a capital X
and therefore an operator
as opposed to just a number,
an eigenvalue.
This is the operator or the observable
which...
Whose eigenvalues
are the positions of the particles,
the observables.
Okay.
The observable values.
Um...
Let's talk about the action,
the action of psi...
Of X
when it hits a vector.
That's what operators do.
They hit vectors and they make new vectors.
Alright.
I'm going to tell you what the action is
by telling you
how it behaves in terms of wave functions.
Instead of telling you how
psi acts on an abstract vector,
I'm going to tell you what happens
when the operator X
hits a wave function.
Wave functions and state vectors
can be thought of as
one being a representation of the other.
When X hits psi of X,
what it does
is just multiply
psi of X by X.
In other words,
it gives you another function.
That's the nature of operators.
They act on functions to give other functions.
They act on vectors to give other vectors.
If functions are representations
or constructions which represent those vectors,
then whatever linear operators are,
they should be such
that they do something to the wave function.
And this is what X does to the wave function.
It simply multiplies it by X.
It gives you a new function,
which is not the same function,
it's a different function,
but that's the nature of it.
Now let's prove something.
Let's prove that the eigenvectors
and the eigenvalues
of this operator
are what we expect them to be.
You of course do expect them to be something.
You may not realize at this moment
that you expect them to be something,
but as soon as I show you what they are,
you will say,
oh yes,
we expected that.
Okay,
so,
what is likely to be the eigenvector
of capital X?
Well,
it should be a state
where the particle is localized
at position X.
In particular,
let's talk about the particle being
localized at point X-naught.
What would we expect the eigenvector to be?
It should be a function
which is zero everywhere except at X-naught.
Right?
That's what we would expect.
It should be concentrated at X-naught.
And so,
let's try the function delta of X minus X-naught.
X-naught is just a parameter here now.
It's a function of X,
but it's a function of X which represents
the particle at position X-naught.
And let's ask the question,
when you operate
with the operator X
on this wave function,
what do you get?
Well,
the answer is,
you just multiply it by little x.
But now we go back to one of the properties
of the delta function,
and we're going to look at
namely,
that when you multiply it by any function of X,
you can replace it by a function of X-prime.
So,
or in this case,
X-naught.
This is also equal to X-naught
times delta of X minus X-naught.
But what is this equation?
This is exactly the equation
for an eigenvector
and eigenvalue
of the operator X.
The operator X
hits the wave function
and the operator X
and gives a number
times the same wave function.
Operator hits wave function,
gives number times wave function.
It's clear that this is an eigenvector
of the operator
with eigenvalue X-naught.
Alright,
so now we can make a list
of eigenvectors of various
observables.
We're starting our list.
Eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
The eigenvector associated with
a particle localized at point X-naught,
that is equal
to the delta function
of X minus X-naught.
Exactly as you expected,
right?
Good.
Okay.
I'm sure you did.
And that finishes up X.
What about P?
What about momentum?
Again,
momentum
being an observable function
you can observe it.
If it hits you in the side of the head,
you feel it.
You recoil.
That is what momentum is.
Momentum means the same thing
quantum mechanics does in classical mechanics.
It's conserved.
And so if you absorb something with some momentum,
you recoil.
Alright,
what is the momentum operator?
The momentum operator,
and we will
the justification for this will come a little later.
We did talk about it,
but I want to go back over it.
Momentum is called P.
The operator momentum.
The operator momentum
is equal to
there's no point beating around the bush,
let's say what it's equal to.
It is equal to minus
I
and I'm going to put in some units here.
So,
I'm going to put in some units here.
Later on,
we will set h-bar equal to one.
It's just a choice of units,
but for the moment,
let's keep h-bar there.
Times
the derivative operator.
D.
The thing I called D last time,
or the operator D.
Last time we studied
whether capital D was hermitian or not.
And we found that it was not.
But,
if we multiplied it by I,
either with a plus or minus sign,
it doesn't matter.
If we multiply it by
an I,
then it becomes
hermitian.
We worked that out last time.
If you remember that little
trick with the integration by parts.
We found that D was not hermitian,
but I times D is.
So this is the definition
of the momentum operator.
Or it's
a bunch of symbols.
So far.
But,
what does P do
when it acts on a wave function?
It just gives
minus I h-bar
times d psi by dx.
So it is also an operator.
It's also an operation.
It's an operator,
it's a linear operator,
and it is a hermitian linear operator.
P.
So that's what it takes
to qualify as an observable
in quantum mechanics.
At this point,
since psi is only a function
of one variable,
it doesn't matter whether
I use partial derivatives
or just ordinary derivatives.
Let's call them ordinary derivatives.
d psi by dx.
Next question,
what is the eigenvectors
of the momentum?
The eigenvectors of the momentum
satisfy P on psi,
or minus I h-bar,
d psi by dx,
equal some eigenvalue,
some observable value
or some possible outcome
of an experiment.
Let's call it P naught
times psi.
This,
of course,
P naught is a number.
It's the eigenvalue.
We can,
let's just,
if we get rid of this,
if we get rid of the minus I here,
it becomes a plus I on this side,
and we can divide by h-bar.
Alright,
so this is just the equation
for an exponential,
derivative being proportional
to the same function,
and the solution for psi.
It's unique
apart from a multiplicative constant.
Psi,
this is the eigenvector
of the momentum
as a function of x,
and let's label it by P naught.
Alright,
just to label the fact
that it's the eigenvector
for momentum P naught.
It's a function of x,
and what is it?
It's e to the i
P naught x.
Question?
Over h-bar.
Oh,
thank you.
Over h-bar.
Alright,
I'm just going to keep the h-bar
around for about 10 more seconds.
I just want to point out
that this is a wave-like
thing.
This is a wave-like
It has sines and cosines.
And it has a wavelength.
The wavelength is the distance
that you have to move
so that the thing in the exponent changes
by 2 pi.
In other words,
if we call the wavelength lambda,
P naught over h-bar
times lambda equals
2 pi.
That's the definition of the wavelength.
How far do you have to move
so that the sines and cosines
return to themselves?
Or that the wavelength
is 2
pi h-bar
divided by P naught.
P naught being the momentum
of the particle.
So,
here we see the first
example of the relationship
between momentum
and wavelength.
Larger the momentum,
the smaller the wavelength.
Of course,
we have not yet justified
the choice of the terminology
momentum for this thing.
But we can keep
in mind that later on we're
going to want to come back
and see that this P really
does behave like momentum.
But so far
it's just an abstract
observable.
We don't know what it means yet.
Okay,
so here we are.
Lambda is equal to this.
And now that
I have demonstrated that,
let's get
rid of h-bar because I will forget
about it anyway.
Let's get rid of h-bar.
Get rid of this formula here.
And see,
this is the
Now it's not clear yet that I've normalized
this correctly.
It's not clear yet that this is normalized
to 1.
Let's take the inner product
between two
momentum states.
This here is a
representation of the momentum state
P-naught.
Or
let's just call it P.
Get rid of the naught.
It's not serving any real purpose here.
P.
But think of P as just P.
Let's take the
inner product of two
momentum states.
P-prime and P.
What is our formula for
inner products?
Here it is,
right over here.
No,
here it is,
over here.
One psi-star
and one phi.
So that means
the inner product is the integral
of
e to the minus
i P-prime x.
That's the wave function of P-prime
or the
complex conjugate of it.
And then the wave function for
e to the minus i P-prime x.
e to the i P-prime x dx.
Or equivalently,
integral e to the i
P-prime x dx.
Now if we've done things right,
since P is supposed to be
an observable,
a Hermitian operator,
and the eigenvectors of
Hermitian operators
should be orthogonal,
then the
then this should be zero if
P is not equal to P-prime.
It's pretty clear that it is zero
if P is not equal to P-prime,
and for the following reason.
The real and imaginary parts
of e to the i P-prime x
are cosines and sines.
If P is not equal to P-prime,
these are cosines and sines
of P-prime x.
Cosines and sines
are as positive as they are negative.
If you integrate them
over a large interval,
you'll get zero.
As long as you pick up
an integer number of wavelengths,
and that's important here.
So as long as P
is not equal to P-prime,
this integral just oscillates itself to zero.
Okay?
Equally positive
and equally negative
for both the real and imaginary parts.
So it is true,
P-prime is not equal to,
the inner product is equal to zero
if P is not equal to P-prime.
What about if P is equal to P-prime?
This is integral
from minus infinity to infinity.
Without looking at the other blackboard,
what can we say about this
for P equal to P-prime?
It's going to be infinite,
right?
The integral of one integrated over all space is infinite.
So in fact,
it's looking,
it's smelling like it is the delta function.
It's smelling like it is the delta function.
Infinite when P is equal to P-prime
and zero otherwise.
It's a good thing.
But we don't know what the actual
numerical coefficient is.
But yes we do.
Up here we have
uh,
integral,
where is,
that's this one over here.
Integral of the x
over 2 pi
is delta of P minus P-prime.
The upshot of this
is just that in order
for this to be normalized,
so its inner product is a real delta function,
you have to divide by
the square root of 2 pi.
Yeah,
square root of 2 pi.
Big deal.
Square root of 2 pi,
this is the wave function
for a particle of momentum
uh,
2 pi here,
a particle of momentum P.
We now know
what the wave functions of particles of momentum P are.
What the wave functions of particles of momentum P are.
Question?
Yeah.
When you were talking about
two different P and P-prime,
you talked about taking the integral
from minus infinity to infinity
of some oscillating function,
and you said this is zero.
And I'm just trying to
think in my head,
normally
when you do an integral,
you
how do you justify that zero?
I can see a sort of
average zero,
but I'm not really sure how to justify it.
Yeah,
I knew somebody was going to ask.
Yeah.
The answer is that you really justify
it by
starting with a theory on a
finite interval.
You're asking,
I think,
questions about
convergence of the integral.
Integral doesn't really converge.
So you really have
to go back to some
earlier starting point,
which,
had I started,
if I were teaching
quantum mechanics in a
graduate class or something,
I would have
started by thinking
of a theory on a finite interval,
or
even better,
on a finite periodic
interval,
worked
it out,
and then taken carefully the
limit as you let things get,
go
to infinity.
And then,
everything could be justified with rigor.
We don't have the time,
and so I don't
do that.
But,
of course...
You're talking about the Fourier transform itself,
right?
Yeah.
It's not really quantum mechanics,
because I was
just thinking about the...
It's a fact about the
Fourier transform,
but I did
cheat.
I did
At some point,
I interchanged
an x integration with a
p integration,
and one of
those integrations didn't converge.
I did basically the same
cheat that I did here.
But,
you know,
I wouldn't
cheat you if I didn't
know that the steps can be filled
in,
and if I didn't know that
if you go and find yourself a book on Fourier
transforms,
you won't be able to fill the steps in yourself.
So,
I haven't really cheated.
What I've done was just a little bit of a
short,
a short cut.
All right.
Now,
we've talked about the wave functions
of particles with momentum
p,
but now I want to talk about
a different concept,
the wave
function in the momentum
basis.
So far,
all of these wave functions have
been thought of as
functions of x.
p here is just a parameter.
It's the momentum of the particle,
but the wave function
is a function of x.
Oh,
incidentally,
notice something.
Notice something important.
The wave functions
of particles with definite
momentum oscillate
endlessly forever and ever,
and they're absolutely
unlocalized.
They're as delocalized as they can be.
In particular,
psi star psi of x
is uniformly spread
out over the entire
real axis.
In no sense is the
position
of the wave function
well defined.
It's as uncertain as it could be.
On the other hand,
the momentum
is very precise.
This is an eigenvector
of the momentum operator.
If this were the wave function of a particle
and you measured its momentum,
it would be p.
If you measured its position,
it would be random all over the axis.
Very much,
well,
much worse than,
but very much like the
sigma x and the sigma z
representations
where one may be definite
and at the cost of the other one
being as indefinite as possible.
In that case,
it's just one and minus one.
Here,
it's much worse.
So,
when a particle
is localized
in momentum,
it's completely
delocalized in position.
We want to be able to say,
I would like to do the reciprocal
thing also.
I'd like to say that the
momentum is
the probability
amplitude
for finding different
momenta.
So,
let's see if we can construct that.
For that,
I think we're finished over here.
All right.
We defined,
in general,
we define a wave function
by taking the state vector
and projecting it onto eigenvectors
of various observables
and that gives us the wave function
in the basis associated with
that observable.
If I project it
onto
an eigenstate of x,
that gives me the wave function
psi of x.
If instead,
I project it onto a
state of definite momentum,
that gives me something that I can call
the wave function in the
momentum basis.
It's not a function of x,
so it doesn't
look like a wave in space.
Doesn't look like a wave in space,
but it's called
the wave function.
And it's a function of momentum.
What is it?
Let's give it a name.
Let's call it psi twiddle
of p.
I use the twiddle notation
just to
remind you
that it's a different thing,
a different animal from the
x wave function.
How do we calculate this?
Let's suppose we know
the x
representation of the state vector,
psi of x.
How do we calculate this?
Well,
we take the inner
product of the
state vector,
psi,
with the vector p.
But we know what that is.
That's the integral
dx.
I think I've
lost it.
I don't mean,
yeah.
Only the equation.
What was it?
Psi phi
equals integral
psi star of x
phi of x.
The x.
Okay?
So,
I want the inner product
between p.
Well,
I know the wave function of p
in the position basis.
It's just,
what is it?
It's e to the minus
i px
over the square root of 2 pi,
if I remember right.
That's what we
wrote down
for psi sub p of x.
That's this guy over here.
And then we have to multiply that by
psi of x
and integrate.
But that's exactly equal to
psi twiddle of p
with the same notation that I used
for Fourier transforms.
In other words,
the momentum
state wave function,
psi twiddle of p,
is exactly
the Fourier transform
of the position space wave function.
That's the upshot.
Momentum
and position are related
in the same way that
ordinary variables,
positions
and Fourier
variables are related.
Okay,
so here we have,
let's just call
it psi twiddle of p.
And if you know,
what this says is,
if
you know the wave function and the position basis,
you know everything.
That's enough.
In fact,
you can recover
the wave function in the momentum
basis,
and also
the probability
to find the particle with different momenta.
After all,
what is the prob-
I've abused the notation.
This shouldn't be a capital psi here.
This should be a small psi.
It's a wave function.
And of course
the probability
to measure a given value of momentum
is just
psi twiddle
star of p
times psi
twiddle of p.
So,
what do you do?
In some way
or another,
you know
what the wave function of
a particle is,
psi of x.
But you're not interested in
measuring x.
You're interested
in measuring p.
How do you
determine the various probabilities
for measuring different p?
You take that x wave function
you subject it to Fourier transform
you find
the Fourier transform of it
and its square
is the probability for different momentum.
This is extremely
similar to going from the
sigma z basis to the sigma x basis.
Go through
it and see if you can
find the similarities between the two.
So,
if you wanted to take a
position operator in the momentum space
it would be i h bar partial partial
p.
Right.
Remember p
was equal to
minus i d by dx
and you apply this
to a position space wave function
you apply it to a position space
wave function
to find out how it acts.
So,
you can see
x
not quite parallel
not minus i d by dp
but plus i d by dp
The minus sign difference
has a great deal to do with this
minus sign here.
But you can work it out.
This is the first time
that I've seen an explanation
for a Heisenberg pair
of quantum mechanics.
Position versus momentum.
And I assume that a similar relationship
would apply to other Heisenberg pairs
like time and energy.
Time and energy
is a funny one.
Time is not usually regarded as
an operator in quantum mechanics.
It's not usually regarded that.
Although you could.
Um
you know,
you do measure time
you look at your watch.
The hand of your watch
is an observable.
And so in that sense
clock readings can be thought of as observables.
There's something a little bit
funny about them and I don't
want to get into it now
but um,
but
usually in quantum mechanics
time is just considered
the parameter by which states evolve.
But it is true.
If you have a clock,
for example
and you're interested in making
an extremely
accurate observation
of a clock,
it will be at the cost
of a lack of
precision in the energy
of the clock.
So yeah,
it is.
What Heisenberg pairs are there that
I might not be aware of?
Electric and magnetic field.
Almost anything you can think of
will have a
conjugate variable.
Electric and magnetic field
um
uh
Temperature and pressure.
What's that?
No,
temperature and pressure are statistical
mechanical variables,
they're not quantum mechanical
variables.
What's that?
Angular momentum.
Yeah,
well,
okay.
Angular momentum and angle.
If angular
momentum and an axially
symmetric system
the angular momentum
and the angular orientation would be
another one,
yeah.
Okay.
And there are lots of others.
Usually,
for example,
if you have some field
typically the field
and its time
derivative
are
conjugate variables.
So there's all kinds of
uh
Any other questions?
Yes.
Just like when we went from
discrete states
observables with discrete states
to continuous,
there's a kind of subtle
change in representation
in the following sense that
in that case,
the discrete states,
the operators
operated on the kets.
The wave function was just an expansion.
Yeah,
yeah,
but we could,
right.
But we could also,
remember we
also represent the operators
as matrices
and the kets as
columns.
But a column is just
a list of values
of
an amplitude as a
function of
where it's lying,
how high,
you know,
as a function
of an eigenvalue.
So it's
really is the same thing.
Um,
this is closely
related to the representation of
operators as matrices.
Just a concrete
concrete action
in a particular basis.
When you write column vectors,
you write them
in particular basis.
Right.
Alright,
last remark
last remark about uncertainty
is
the uncertainty principle
for this particular example
here,
I'm not going to
derive the uncertainty principle,
not today,
we may get to it,
but it really
is a very simple thing.
It is simply the statement
that,
uh,
that
this,
that,
it's a statement
about Fourier transforms,
first of all.
And it transcends
quantum mechanics,
it's not only quantum mechanics,
anytime you have a pair of quantities
which are related by Fourier
in a,
uh,
a transform
in this way,
it's generally the case
that the narrower
one
Fourier pair
half of the Fourier pair is,
the broader the other one is.
In other words,
the narrower
the range of
P,
the broader
psi of x will be
and vice versa.
So I don't want to go into
a mathematical
statement about,
um,
about the uncertainty principle
here,
but whatever it is,
it really just does have to do
with the character of Fourier
pairs,
x and p in this case.
We'll come back
to it,
I think.
What I wanted to get onto
was the Hamiltonians
for particles.
Just the simplest possible Hamiltonians
for particles,
and how
they govern the quantum mechanical
evolution.
Remember what the Hamiltonian
is?
The Hamiltonian is the thing
which first of all
enters into the
Schrodinger equation,
and which also governs
the time evolution of the state vector.
The Hamiltonian is
to be identified with the
classical idea of energy,
just as it is
in classical mechanics.
If you go back,
we
I
discussed this earlier,
but let's
go on.
The starting point was the idea
of the unitary evolution of
state vectors,
that state vectors
evolve by unitary transformation.
And then we said,
well,
what happens if you make a tiny little
change in time,
that should correspond to some
sort of differential change
in the state vector.
And we found out that that
differential change was governed
by a Hermitian operator
called the Hamiltonian.
So if you
have forgotten
the details of that,
go back to it now.
Not right now,
but
you'll remember the equation.
The equation
for the evolution of a
state vector
is I
let's put our h-bars in for the
moment,
take them out again in a little while.
d psi by dt
the way the
state vector,
we can write this in terms of
state vectors.
The state vector
is generally a function of time.
The state changes with time.
You can take the difference
between vectors,
and you can
differentiate vectors with respect to time.
If a vector happens to be time dependent,
you can differentiate it.
I d psi by dt
is equal
to the Hamiltonian operator
acting on psi.
That's the time dependent Schrodinger equation.
We worked at,
I think
we worked out an example
for a spin processing in a
magnetic field,
where we
just used for the Hamiltonian
one of the components of the spin.
Here is the general form of the
Schrodinger equation,
the time dependent
Schrodinger equation.
Let's try out some simple Hamiltonians.
See what kind of things we learned from them.
Tonight I think we'll just study one or two.
Then we'll go on
afterwards.
The very simplest Hamiltonian
that I can write down,
which is quite illustrative,
and nobody ever writes it down,
but I'm going to write it down anyway.
The Hamiltonian
is H.
Now H is an operator.
Not just an operator,
it's a Hermitian operator.
H doesn't stand for Hermitian,
it stands for Hamiltonian,
but never mind.
We're going to try H
is equal
to a number
constant,
C for constant,
times the momentum.
So,
it's a perfectly good thing.
Let's see what it does.
Let's see what kind of thing we learned from it.
Is this a
reasonable Hamiltonian for a particle?
Yeah,
actually it is.
And we'll find out in
a moment what kind of particle.
But it's not the usual thing.
What do we usually write for a
non-relativistic particle?
P squared over 2m,
huh?
Momentum squared over twice the mass.
We'll come back to that.
But this is simpler.
This is simpler and worth exploring first
to see how the apparatus works.
Everything here should be capitalized,
everything,
because they're all operators.
Okay,
but how
is this represented in terms of wave
functions?
In terms of wave
functions,
and we would
wave functions,
psi of x,
wave functions in the x basis,
in the momentum basis.
Wave functions in the x basis are just
projections onto the x eigenvectors
and we can do that inside these equations
here.
What this reads
then is I h bar
d psi of x
by dt
This is the way
the wave function changes
is equal
Now h is
c times p,
so let's put the c there,
and p is minus
I h bar d by dx
So there's a minus
and a minus.
An I,
an h bar,
and a d by dx
psi of x
Okay,
what have I done?
I've rewritten this equation
in terms of wave functions,
in other words,
a concrete
representation,
psi of x,
d psi of x by dt,
and I've
used here the assumption
that the Hamiltonian is just equal to
c times the momentum
and the momentum
is I minus I h bar
d by dx
Well this is a very
and of course psi is
not only a function of x
what is a psi a function of?
Time
It's a function of time because in general
a state vector changes with time,
that's all
Okay,
we can,
let's cancel out
the I h bars
and I just get
d psi
by dt
is equal to
minus c
times d psi by dx
d psi by dt
plus
d psi by dx
with a c
is equal to zero
That's a pretty simple equation
In fact it's
so simple that I know
not only what a
solution is
I know all of the solutions of this equation
Anybody know what the solutions of this equation are?
The general solution?
A function of
x minus c t
Any function
Let's leave it this way
Any function of x minus c t
Any function which is a function of
x minus c t
In other words it doesn't depend on
x and t separately
It only depends on the combination
x minus c t will solve this equation
If I differentiate
with respect to t
that will be minus c
times the derivative with respect to x
and that's all this equation says
Any function of this form
will solve the Schrodinger equation
Okay
So let's think about a function of this form
What does it do?
What does it look like?
You can start at t equals zero
cross out t here
with any function
psi of x
Of course we don't want to take
any function
I want my functions to be such
that the total probability is equal to one
So the integral of
psi star psi should be
finite equal to one
They shouldn't blow up
or they should fall to zero
nicely so that we can integrate them
But they can do whatever you like
Some sort of lump
that can oscillate
may or may not oscillate
rather general
And now we let t run
We let time go forward
What happens to this
solution?
What happens to the solution
is it stays exactly the same shape
except every feature of it
moves with a velocity c
The features of it
move to the right
with uniform velocity c
That's what this function is
It's just a function
which just moves rigidly
without changing its shape
And of course it's a complex function
So it has a real part to it
and not an imaginary part
But both of them maintain exactly the same shape
And they just slide down the axis
uniformly
with a velocity c
Now I chose c for a reason
because it's the speed of light
Is this a photon?
Well this is not really
the correct description of photons
but it's pretty close to the right
description of neutrinos
There are at least neutrinos
which move with the speed of light
Real neutrinos probably move a little slower
than the speed of light
but unmeasurably so
So this would be a darn good
description
of one dimensional neutrinos
except
that we would have to add another possibility
that they can all
These are pure right moving neutrinos
They're pure right moving neutrinos
and they do have a funny thing
that the energy
can be,
we're going to come back to this
not this quarter I think
but the energy can be both positive and negative
p is a thing which can be
positive or negative
So this particle has the property
that it can have positive or negative energy
but that's not important
What's important here is the picture of the wave function
moving down the axis with uniform velocity
The whole probability distribution
is the wave function
rigidly moves down the axis
What happens to the expectation value of x?
It moves the same way
So the expectation value of x moves with velocity ct
and
that's the quantum mechanics of the simple system
I would just
point out
that if we compare
this with the classical mechanics
of exactly the same system
Hamiltonian is equal to
cp
How do we compare the
How do we do the classical physics?
We use Hamilton's equations
So here
It was mainly for this reason right here
that we did all quarter of classical mechanics
last quarter
Not just for this one but
for all sorts of things like this
Hamilton's equations
Let's look at Hamilton's equations
Hamilton's equations are the
h by dp
equals x dot
and
the h by dx
equals minus p dot
The h by dt is just equal to c
right?
The h by dx
that's equal to zero
So what this says
classically
is that the momentum is conserved
Now we'll come back to the conservation of momentum
in quantum mechanics
But it also says that the position of the particle
moves with velocity c
In quantum mechanics
the whole probability distribution
in this case
this is a very very simple case
sort of engineered just to have a simple answer
the whole probability distribution
moves with
but in particular
the expectation value of x
moves with velocity c
So the expectation value
of the position behaves
according to the classical equations of motion
Now
that's
as I said this is a very easy example
which is
a little too simple to be perfectly general
but
but it does illustrate the
So this would be the Schrodinger equation
for this
very very simple Hamiltonian
ok
I think we're
about
alright let's go a little more
a little more
What about a
and of course this would make this a relativistic particle
this would not be a non-relativistic particle
this is a guy who
moves with the speed of light
so
yeah
I mean without using the
c just using some other numbers
other stuff speed of light
would this be the
correct Hamiltonian for
any particle moving in free space
No any particle which is always
constrained to move with the same velocity
so right
right so for example
um
you know just as photons
are the quanta
of the electromagnetic field
sound waves and crystals
also have quanta
and those sound waves are called phonons
and at least at low energies
those phonons move with a uniform velocity
the uniform velocity being
the speed of sound
so if you had one dimensional phonons
you would describe
them in a similar way
but couldn't you just do that
just throw an electron in free space
and it would follow that
uh
no electrons don't generally move with the speed of light
I'm just saying at any speed
no no no no
you see this
this law of physics
for this particular kind of particle
says that no matter how you throw it
whatever momentum you throw it with
it's always going to move the same way
right
he said replace the c with the v
with the what
with velocity v
velocity v means momentum
but pv is the same as p squared over 2m
not quite
it's p squared over m
but that's close to the
right that's close
right
of course there was one thing
for a relativistic particle of course
p is not v over m
but you're on the right track
yeah
I was just imagining that any particle has a
wave function for its position
right and if it's moving in space
that wave function is just moving
no no no
you see that's not quite right
um
only for this very
very simple situation
does the wave function move
with this rigid behavior
and maintain its shape
not true
more generally
if you take a non relativistic electron
we're going to work out its equation in two minutes
uh
the shape of its wave function
is not maintained
it sort of wobbles and does things
and sort of gradually falls apart
and disperses
uh diffuses disperses
whatever you want to call it
so um
right
I picked this one just because it's easy to solve
but um
but it doesn't represent
uh
the most general kind of motion of a particle
alright so let's
let's talk about let's take a guess
let's take a guess
for a non relativistic particle
um I think I already
earlier showed you
that the
equations of motion for expectation
values
quantum mechanically
are very closely related
to the corresponding equations of motion
classically
Hamilton's equations
or Poisson bracket form of them
um
so you can
imagine
that if you want to represent
the quantum mechanics of a system
which is
which whose classical physics you know
you basically use the same Hamiltonian
now we will come back to that
we'll come back to that and justify it better
but the natural Hamiltonian to guess
for a non relativistic particle
is just a good old
p squared over two m
so if you want to represent
the quantum mechanics of a system
this is not a particle with a force on it
this is a particle with no force on it
a free particle
the energy the kinetic energy
t is equal to
one half mass
times velocity squared
momentum is m times v
and we can
rewrite the kinetic energy
if that's all there is let's call it h
as p squared
over two m
so that's the Hamiltonian
for a classical particle
notice
this Hamiltonian has a funny feature
particles can only move to the right
there was no
left moving motion
they all only move to the right
uh
and
that's a funny thing
the asymmetry between
left and right
has to do with the fact that p goes to
minus p when you invert left and right
the Hamiltonian changes
sign when you this this Hamiltonian
that's a funny thing
the energy of a particle
with negative momentum
is negative
energy of a particle with positive momentum
is positive that's a little bit weird
okay
non ordinary
non relativistic particle
its energy is independent of which way it's moving
and that's ensured by the fact
that the energy is proportional to p squared
not p
alright so let's start with the energy
being p squared over two m
and work out
the Schrodinger equation for it
now we will be working out the genuine Schrodinger
well the original version of the Schrodinger equation
for a free particle
now we just write h is
equal to p squared over two m
h is also
i
d by dt
now
let's put h bar in
just to
as Schrodinger would have done it
on psi
that's the left hand side
thought of as an operator
operating on an
sorry
that's i h bar d by dt
and the right hand side
of the equation
is just h acting on psi
but h is p squared over two m
so let's write that
as one over two m
and then what is p
whatever p is we have to square it
but let's write down where p is first
minus h bar i
i h bar
derivative with respect to x
but we have to square it
it's p squared
squaring it just means multiplying it by itself
so let's square this
i h bar squared
and then the square of the first derivative
is the second derivative
means you just apply it twice
times psi
or on psi of x
that's it
that's the Schrodinger equation
for a
ordinary non relativistic particle
moving on a one dimensional line
let's leave the h bars
i h bar d psi by dt
and then
we have
i h bar d psi by dt
which is equal to
minus h bar squared
minus comes from minus i squared
over two m
d second psi
by dx squared
this is a kind of wave equation
incidentally
this is also a wave equation
this is a wave equation
and psi is a wave function
psi is also a wave function
this is the Schrodinger equation
for a particular function
for an ordinary non relativistic particle
it has the property
that waves of different wavelength
move with different velocities
I'm getting a little tired
so we're going to quit soon
but waves of different
ah
wavelength
move with different velocities
because of that
the wave function
does not maintain its shape
and in fact
it can't be maintained
it tends to fall apart
and
ah
spread
wave function spreads out
with time unlike
this very simple case over here
in this case no matter what the wavelength
no matter what the momentum is
they all move with the same velocity
not so here
different momentum move with different velocities
and so a wave with a given shape
different parts of it will move with different velocity
different wavelengths
in it will move with different velocities
and it will
fall apart
we'll study it a little in more detail
we'll study its
behavior
but I think I'm
for more
please visit us at
stanford.edu