This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
I almost always begin with the same sermon.
About, especially when teaching
about quantum mechanics or relativity.
The sermon is always the same.
It's the fact that we as animals have
inherited through the process of evolution certain intuitive
ways of thinking about the physical world.
And if you don't believe it, you
think that maybe ordinary animals are not physicists,
you watch a lion chasing an antelope.
And you notice that that lion, the
minute that the antelope, that the relative velocity
between the antelope and the lion
changes sign, the lion just stops dead.
Somehow he did some calculation, or she, it's
usually a she, the lion, did some calculation,
some physics calculation involving some
very complicated concepts of velocity, direction,
all kinds of complicated computations like that.
And most of the million years, they're
speaking about the human body in the future.
Have you ever heard?
How butchering a
animal,
because they talk about other things.
Most interesting ones are the overall change.
Where is the displacement?
did he have components? Did
he know about sines and cosines?
Yes, somehow he did know about sines and cosines
These are things which were inherited
biological in origin
and they are the basis of our intuitions about physics
our intuitive picture of the world
Much of physics has to do with
those things, in fact, all of modern physics
everything in modern physics
has to do with those things
which are beyond the intuitions
that we were able to get
from the ordinary world
has to do with
with ranges of parameters which are
way outside the range of parameters
that humans or animals ever experienced
For example, it's not too surprising that
human beings didn't know how to deal
with velocities approaching the speed of light
that they got the wrong
ideas about how to add velocities
when nobody in 1900 had ever, probably had never moved
faster than 50 or 60 or 100 miles an hour
Well, they probably did when they were falling off cliffs
but they didn't live to talk about it
maybe they got up to 200 miles an hour, maybe
but nobody ever had experienced anything like
the velocities approaching the speed of light
and so it was not surprising that their intuitions
that their way of thinking
about adding velocities and so forth
the theory of relativity
was, and how you synchronize clocks, all that stuff
all that good stuff that Einstein did
that it was outside the framework
of their ability to think about
through intuitive pictures, through intuitive mathematics
They had to invent new mathematics
The new mathematics was abstract
meaning to say you couldn't visualize it
four-dimensional space-time
I can't visualize four dimensions
I've learned tricks to visualize it
So physicists to some extent rewire themselves
or people who learn physics
do a process of rewiring themselves
to some extent to develop intuitions
to be able to deal
with these new ranges of parameters
but still, they're foreign, they're alien, they're peculiar
even to me
Quantum mechanics deals with a range of phenomena
which is also outside the experience of ordinary humans
for which evolution simply didn't
provide you the means to visualize
Evolution did not provide you
the means to visualize an electron
to visualize the motion of an electron
to visualize the uncertainty principle
When you think of a particle moving
What is a particle?
A particle is a thing with a position
At every instant of time it has a position
If at every instant of time it
has a position, it has a trajectory
If it has a trajectory, you
can calculate the velocity along that trajectory
just by knowing the separation between
points and what the time interval is
you can calculate the velocity
and that's the intuitive way of doing it
The intuitive picture of a particle
and where does it come from?
It comes from thinking about
rocks, throwing rocks, shooting arrows
all kinds of things that human beings normally do
So we never developed the need
It would have been very bizarre
if our brains had been wired
to understand the uncertainty principle
Why would Darwin have given us the...
Incidentally
If you prefer to think of
the intelligent designer, go right ahead
I prefer to think about Darwin
But why would either of
Darwin's ideas or the intelligent designer
have provided us with the
ability to understand the uncertainty principle
when it's never anything that's
part of our ordinary experience?
The answer is it didn't
And so quantum mechanics for that
reason appears extremely weird to us
Physicists, as I said, rewired themselves
and developed ways of thinking about it which are intuitive
But still, quantum mechanics is much, much more unintuitive
incidentally, than the special theory of relativity
And what we're going to try to do here
is expose some of the weirdness of quantum mechanics
The weirdness of the logic of quantum mechanics
The weirdness of how quantum information works
This is not a class
A conventional class in quantum mechanics
A conventional class in quantum mechanics would
stress such things as the Schrodinger equation
and waves
and how particles sometimes behave like waves and so forth
We may or may not
get to a bit of that
But that's not the important subject
that we're going to concentrate on
What we're going to concentrate on
is the basic logic of quantum mechanics
The basic logic of quantum information theory
Physics is information
When you say something about
a physical system, you're saying something...
You're giving some information about it
You give the information in various forms
Usually in the form of numbers
In classical physics, you often give...
I will give you some examples, but...
you usually give it in the form of real numbers
the position, the velocity, a set of real numbers
in quantum mechanics, sometimes you use
real numbers, but very, very often
you give discrete information
discrete information such as yes or no
or up or down
or male or female
well that's probably not such a good example
the difference is between, yeah that's probably not
I think I'll withdraw that, heads or tails
heads or tails, do I have a coin?
no
a Gedanken coin
thought coin, head, tail, head, tail
when I flip the coin
head, that's a piece of information
it could be tail
it's a two valued system
either yes or no
up or down, heads or tails
or sometimes
they're logically all the same of course
they're logically all the same, whether
we're talking about heads or tails
up or down
or whatever it is, they're logically the same
and they're simply decisions which
have two possible, or questions
which have two possible answers
and a bit of information
which has two possible answers is called a bit
it's called a bit
and it can either be a classical bit
or a quantum bit
all real bits in nature are quantum bits
obviously since nature is made out of quantum mechanics
but sometimes the quantum aspects
of it don't manifest themselves
in an ordinary computer
the quantum aspects of the bit
don't really manifest themselves for
reasons that we'll come to
and it's just called a classical bit
a classical bit of information
this head, the coin flip
yes or no
the quantum bit
is the quantum analog
of the flipped coin
the yes or no type question
but it is much, much more subtle
and the first thing we're
going to want to explore is
what is a quantum bit
now, but before we do that
let's talk about classical bits
classical bits can be described
either by writing down a zero
or a one
these are, we could also use one and minus one
or we could use five and fifteen
doesn't matter
but zero and one is a convenient notation
of the two possible values
zero could stand for heads
one could stand for tails and so forth
so we're thinking about this
we're thinking about some physical system
when we're thinking about information
we're thinking about a physical system
such as a coin
and this is the information contained in that coin
either a zero or a one
there's a notation
this seems like a ridiculous and redundant notation
its importance will only become clear
when we start to think about quantum bits
but we're going to use the Dirac notation
the Dirac notation
describes the state of a bit
not whether it's California or Oregon
but the configuration of the bit
and it's usually labeled
with a notation zero
or one
or whatever other information
whatever other way you decide to think about the bit
these are the two states
that a bit can have
either a zero or one
and it's represented
I don't know if I drew that well
let's draw it again
zero
or one
these are the two states of a bit
all of this extra junk here
is excess
you don't need it
it doesn't tell you anything
it just says that you're putting it inside a bracket
incidentally
this pointy bracketed object over here
the thing that contains the information on the inside
is called a ket
it's called a ket
because it's the second half of something
which we will later learn is a bra ket
or a bracket
there's another half
that we haven't exposed yet
now what about multi bits
supposing you have more than one bit
and we're talking now classical physics
so far we're not talking about anything quantum mechanical
supposing we have several coins
and I line them up
I label them so we know which one is which
in fact just in order to not confuse coins
let's make sure they're different coins
penny, nickel, dime, quarter, half dollar, silver dollar
so we have a bunch of coins
we can't confuse them
and we can lay out some information
by saying head, tail, tail, head, head, tail
that would be some information about a collection of bits
how would you label that?
well you would label it with
a string of zeros and ones
so for example
let's take zero always to stand for head
it's easy to remember
zero stands for head
and one stands for tail for obvious reasons
right, so my string of coins
head, head, tail, head, tail, head
I would label zero for head
zero for another head
one, zero, one, one for example
that's a configuration of one,
two, three, four, five, six coins
alright
let's say it was six coins
that's a configuration of a multi-bit system
in this case six bits
again
for reasons that add absolutely nothing to this description
we're going to stick it inside a ket
stick it inside a ket which
is just a kind of notation
it might be a good idea
to put some commas between these
but maybe not, maybe it's just
best to leave it that way
that's a specification
it could be the specification of
the bits of information inside a computer
it could be just a series
of heads or tails or so forth
but before we do anything else with this
let's ask a very simple question
how many possible configurations
how many possible states are there
of, well let's start with one bit
if there's only one bit
then there are only two states
what if there are two bits
well then you can have up, up
up, down, down, up, down, down
four, two times two
so for two bits we have two squared
what if we have a hundred bits?
the answer is
two to the one hundredth power
two times two times two times two a hundred times
so if you have an in-bit system
the number of possible classical configurations
is just two to the n
let's write that down, let's put a notation in
let's write the number of states
the number of states, n sub s
the number of states
of a system of little n bits
is two to the n
let's suppose we
oh let's invert that first of all
let's invert, little n is what?
little n is the number of bits
big N is the number of states
so if the number of bits
is four
then the number of states is two to the four
which is sixteen and so forth
we can invert this
and we can write
if we knew the number of states of a system
then we can take the logarithm of this equation
log to the base two is particularly convenient
if we take the log to the base two
of the number of states
which is equal to the number of bits
you can generalize this
not every system has as its number of states
two to a power
supposing I have a state, a system
a die
you know, the things you use in Las Vegas
to throw away your money with
it's got six
possibilities, one through six
that is not two to any particular power
it's just six
but we can still generalize this definition
of the number of bits of information
in fact, the number of bits of information
that a system can contain
is by definition
the logarithm to the base two
of the number of states
which for the die
would be log
to the base two
of six
what is log to the base two of six?
is it an integer?
no, it's some stupid irrational number
I don't even know, what is
it, how big is it about
two to the two to the two is four
two to the three is eight
two to the two point five
three seven nine eight six fourteen
or whatever
so
the amount of information
which is always the logarithm
of the number of states does
not have to be an integer
but we're going to be considering systems
which are made up out of
some number
of bits, each of which has two states
so for the simplicity we're
going to be talking about systems
the number of states is always two to a power
that's just for simplicity
there's nothing special about it
but almost every system can be represented that way
or approximately represented that way
let me give you an example
supposing we have
some question
of physics
which has as its answer
a real number
but we're only interested in that
real number to a certain approximation
the temperature, the temperature in the room
I'm interested in the temperature in the room to
to a certain number of significant figures
I can represent the temperature
or any other number for that matter
by writing it as a number in base two
what's the temperature in this room incidentally
it's about three hundred degrees
from absolute zero
so it's three hundred
I can write three hundred
not as three hundred
which is, what does three hundred mean
three hundred, you know what it means
it means three times ten to the two
plus nothing times ten to the one
plus zero times ten to the zero
but we write it to things in base two
I don't know what three
hundred looks like in base two
somebody can figure it out
base two, everybody know arithmetic in base two?
anybody not know arithmetic in base two?
okay, so everybody knows arithmetic in base two
we write out any number that we like
as a series of zeros and ones
one, zero, zero, one, zero, one, zero, zero, one
that's some number to the
some particular integer, it's an integer
so if I'm interested in the temperature
and I'm not interested in
being too careful to define fractions
I want to know whether it's seventy two degrees
or seventy three degrees
I don't care about seventy
two point four oh six nine
I can write it as an integer
and that integer
can be represented
as a sum of bits
not a sum of bits,
but as a collection of bits
every number, every single number
if you're willing to truncate
the number of decimal places
approximate that number
and say I'm interested in that number
only to thirty five decimal places or whatever
or to thirty five places to base two
that number simply is
both is represented by
and represents a collection of bits
so any time, and incidentally
if you want to have a
finer grain description of the temperature
than integers in centigrade
you just use a more refined notion of degree
you go down to ask how many degrees is it
but not in centigrade units
but in units of ten
to the minus a hundredth centigrade
again, you can give it as an integer
and integers can always be represented
as sequences of zeros and ones
so almost any information in physics
can be represented in terms of bits
in particular
the measurement of
quantities
such as temperature for example
let me give you another example
this is a more complicated example of the same thing
supposing I'm interested in a field
a field means a thing which can vary throughout space
alright
well the temperature can vary throughout space
the temperature is a field
it varies throughout space
it's not one of the more interesting fields
from the point of view of fundamental
fundamental particle physics or anything
but that certainly is a field
it varies from place to place
and how can we represent that
can we represent that in terms of bits
yes if we're willing to tolerate certain approximations
and we're always willing to
tolerate some degree of approximation
what we do
is we break up the room
into a lot of little tiny cells
I won't try to draw three-dimensional lines
I'm going to try to draw a three-dimensional room
in my notes I drew a three-dimensional room
it took me about a half an
hour to put in all the lines
just a two-dimensional room
and here's what we do
we first of all order the cells
we make the cells small enough
so that the temperature doesn't vary very much
from cell to cell
so we might fill this room with several billion cells
label the cells
this is the first cell
two, one, two, three, four, five, six
I don't know, up to a thousand
thousand and one, thousand and two,
thousand and three, thousand and four
and we can label all of the cells
and list them
once we've listed them
we can write the temperature of the first cell
there's the temperature of the first cell
I'm putting a little comma in
just to distinguish between cells
then we can write the temperature of the second cell
and the temperature of the next cell
zero, zero, one, one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine
I've kept nine decimal places in the basis
in arithmetic in base two
one, one, zero, one, however, until I'm finished
then I go to the next cell
do the same thing
temperature there is one, one, zero, one, zero, zero
and so forth
eventually all I have
is a list of zeros and ones
this long list of zeros and ones
if somebody knows how to use it
is equivalent to knowing the temperature
at every point in the room
the same is true of the electric field
the magnetic field
anything which varies from place to place
so
almost everything that I can think of in physics
can be represented
in terms of bits
so if you know everything about how bits work
you basically know everything about how physics works
of course
you may not know what the rules are
for manipulating these things
but this is the basic
setup of physics
information
in the form of a series of questions
each of which can be answered yes or no
now of course
you may want to refine your description
to refine your description
you may want to add
more decimal places to the temperature
to the specification of temperature
and you might want to
make your lattice finer
that's just making a better approximation
so the right thing to say is that most
physical systems that we know about
as far as I know all physical systems
can be represented
at least approximately
and perhaps to always increasing approximation
by a series of bits
that's why we get to use computers to do physics
if this weren't true we couldn't use a computer
we couldn't use a digital computer
in any case to do physics
we'd have to use analog computers or something
okay so that's
let me give you another example
another example of how you might
use bits to represent another
these are all so far classic
systems as I said
I don't want to redraw the lattice
but I do want to get
rid of this top row here
since I've already mutilated it
here's a lattice
and what I'm interested in is the motion of particles
this lattice is just an artificial imposed lattice
that I've imposed on the room here
just so that I've divided the room into mathematical cells
and what I'm interested in is the motion of particles
moving around in this room
at any given instant
I can ask the question
let's take a very simple case
let's take the case
where a particle
where you can't squeeze more than one particle
into one of these cells
we can imagine that
the cells are about as big as a particle
in which case you can't squeeze in more than one
then every cell either has a particle
or it doesn't have a particle
we can label the cells
that have particles with an x
we can
label the cells that don't have a particle
with nothing
or better yet
we can label the cells that have a particle
with a one
and the ones that have no particle with a zero
in that case
this becomes a specification
of where the particles are
in the lattice
it's no longer the temperature
but the same long sequence
of zeros and ones
now the number of zeros and ones
would just be equal to the
number of cells in the lattice
what would this number mean?
it would mean that in the first cell
there's a particle
in the second cell there's no particle
in the third cell there's no particle
in the fourth cell there's a particle
in the fifth cell no particle
in the sixth cell particle
and so forth and so on
and so given such a string of numbers
you are given a specification
of where the particles are in this room
in that way
again
motion of particles
motion of fields
temperature
just about anything in physics
can be represented in terms of bits
any questions?
right, a bit is by definition
a question about a system
which has only two possible answers
which you can always take to be yes or no
used to be a game
20 questions
didn't you?
I think it's a bit
where somebody would think of a category
and then you would stand there and ask
yes no questions
until you tried to figure out what the category
what the category was
so that was
using the idea of bits
yes question
oh I just arbitrarily said supposing
we are interested in the temperature
to a certain degree of accuracy
right
so I'm interested in the temperature to accuracy
but now I'm not speaking about temperature
I'm just giving another example
these are just examples intended to show you
something which is more or less clear
otherwise we could not use computers to
to simulate physical problems
classical physical problems
yes
right
but you need
for the general real number
you need an infinite number of bits
right
any rational number
can be represented by a finite number of bits
and the rule
well
that's not quite true
you have to
you have to remember to repeat them but
if it's rational it's going to repeat after some point
yeah if it's rational it's
going to repeat after some point
right
so
but if it's an irrational number then
you need an infinite string of bits
but in general we will allow infinite strings of bits
although not in a genuine computer
well so far remember we're doing classical physics
all right so far no quantum mechanics
so I will come
let's see where
yes we were going to
come to that very very shortly
well let me tell you how very quickly
an electron
first of all we're not talking about motion yet
we're talking about configuration
configuration means
the state of a system
at a given instant of time
okay
so
the presence of an electron
at a given instant of time
let's suppose the nucleus is
known to be right over here
and we're not going to ask about the nucleus
the nucleus just sits there
it's a lump on the
all right so
we could say at instant number one
we're going to have a state of the system
and as 32
what's the youtubers
an electron
right
and an electron
relative to the project
is known to be
not
level
in a
poly
progressively
like
ization
Starting with this configuration, we move, and
let's use this symbol here to indicate
that at the next, we could, we've broken
up space into a lot of little individual cells.
We could also break up time, I
thought I had my watch but I don't.
We could also break up our watch into
a digital watch which digitizes time, just again as
either a convenience or an approximation, and
we could say if at digital time number
one the electron was, or the system was
described by one electron located at this location,
then what happens next?
Next it moves to some new configuration.
In this case it might move over one
place, one, two, three, four, five, six, it moves
over to the other.
One to the sixth place, one, two,
three, four, five, six, and so forth.
So the motion of a system is described
by a rule of updating, of updating information,
how you update it from one instant to the next.
Alright, so physics basically consists of two,
a physical system consists of two things.
It consists of a collection.
It consists of a collection of possible states
which can be labeled by a collection of bits,
and it consists of a time evolution which
is an updating which tells you how to take
one collection of bits and replace it by
another collection of bits at a slightly later instant
of time.
I don't know if that answers the question.
To actually work out an orbital
motion, it's a little bit more complicated.
It's a little bit more complicated.
But the motion orbiting around here gets
confusing because when you jump from one
layer to the next, if this is one and this
is a hundred, then a hundred and one is over
here.
So you don't jump from a
hundred to a hundred and one.
You might jump from a hundred to
over here, which would be two hundred.
So it can be complicated, the updating procedure.
It can look complicated, but nevertheless,
it's an updating procedure that just updates
your...
your state of knowledge at each instant of time.
That's classical physics.
Now there are some rules, and
we're going to come to them.
But before we do, let's define the space of states.
This is...
And I want to emphasize,
we are still doing classical physics.
There is nothing quantum mechanical even
though we're talking about discretizing systems and
making out of them systems of individual bits.
It's just a matter of time.
So far, we are dealing with
what should be called classical bits.
C bits, I think they're
called, as opposed to Q bits.
Q bit is a quantum bit.
These are classical bits so far.
Okay.
So let's take all of the configurations
and just abstractly, in a purely abstract way,
we take all of the configurations.
Incidentally, what are they?
This is about 10 by 10.
This is roughly a 10 by 10 lattice.
This 10 by 10 lattice has 100 sites.
How many states does it have?
I'm not talking about one particle now.
I'm talking about any number of
particles can be on this lattice.
How many different configurations are there?
Two to the hundred.
A very, very, very big number.
Two to the hundredth power.
That's how many different ways we can...
Arrange zeros and ones on this lattice
or specify whether there's particles in various
positions.
A very large number of possible states.
But let's just abstractly think about all
these states and just draw them as points.
If there are 10 to the hundred, I have
to draw 10 to the hundred points, which I'm not
about to do.
These are the various states.
These are not the lattice points.
For example, for one bit, if I had only
one bit, then the space of states would consist
of only two points, up and down,
and I would just draw two points.
This would be the space of
states of a simple one-bit system.
Now let's ask...
What are the possible laws?
The laws of motion because we're ah sevent
percent of the time that some states are
a set, some states are a set.
It's the laws are, it's a law.
We've been talking about laws all the time.
We've been talking about mottoing.
Here's one motto.
For instance, if I say!
Oh, yes!
you know that there is
at one point a set action!
You might be talking about one way or the other.
So, that's what that components are for
that, boost, power, power, crust, incompetence to
increase, change, we talk about moved with
putting the first, the second, the final.
Another one
Pivotal
In the beginning, when we were depending
on the thinking, which is very simple –you
meaniny?
This is the muzzle.
This red portion.
A muzzle.
This red part.
moment. This could stand for heads, this could
stand for tails. If we start with heads, if
I had a coin we would do it.
Here's heads and tails. Heads, tails. One possibility is
very simple. If you start with heads, it
stays heads. Nothing happens. If you start with
tails, it stays tails. Nothing happens. That's a
law of updating. It's not a very interesting
law of updating. How would you draw that?
Well, here's how we'll draw it. Heads goes
to heads. We'll make an arrow. If we start
with heads, it stays heads. If we start with
tails, it stays tails. So we draw an arrow
from what you start with to what you end with.
What's another possible law of updating?
It's a law of updating.
Here's a law of updating. If it's tails,
it becomes heads. Then it becomes tails. Then
it becomes heads. Then it becomes tails. That's
a little more, not very much, but a little
more interesting, a slightly more interesting
system. It just flip-flops back and forth.
How would we draw that? We would
draw that again. Heads, tails, heads, tails, tails,
tails. If you start with heads, you go to
tails. If you start with tails, you go to
heads.
So the law of updating in this case
is just described by such a diagram, basically. A
diagram which tells you if you start at a
given state, what it will be in the next instant
of time. Is that clear? So this is one
way of describing the laws of physics. Write down
all the states. Keep in mind what they
stand for, of course. Remember that in this case,
one stands for heads, one stands for tails,
or whatever it happens to stand for. If it's
male, female, this could be an interesting
case of... That would be an interesting...
This would be a very interesting law of motion
in that case. I don't think I want to... I
don't think I want to explore that any
further. If this were my undergraduate class, I would
never have brought that up.
This is more likely... This is the more
likely law of updating for sexuality. Female, male.
So you see, simple laws sometimes apply.
Sometimes they're a little more complicated. Can you
think of an interesting system that flip-flops
like this? Offhand, I can't think of anything.
It's obvious that it applies. It's a little
bit more complicated. It's a little bit more
complicated. It applies to a lot
of things, but offhand, I can't...
No, no, no. Right, right, right, right. But
this is... Yes. But if you just have... You're
not intervening. I don't want you to intervene. This
is the system by itself. If you had some
peculiar light switch by itself, it went back
and forth and back and forth and back and
forth in a regular way, but that's...
Day and night. Day and night. You know, this is...
Which?
Well, there's a lot of states to the
pendulum in between, but yes, you've got the idea.
It's hard to think of a simple example, but I
bet by the time we all go home and we came
back next week, every one of us would have
an example of a... We could call this the
flip-flop. This is the flip-flop motion. This
is the un-motion. Well, we can extend this.
If we know what the space of configurations
is and we lay them all out, either abstractly
in our mind or actually just write them
on the blackboard, then the motion of the system
can be represented by a series of arrows, where
I'm not going to be able to see the
motion of the system. I'm going to be able
to see the motion of the system. I'm going
to be getting tired, but...
And so forth and so on.
You only need two to the hundred.
Yeah. I don't know. Let's do the possible...
Let's think of some possible motions of a
two-bit system.
Okay.
So, this system simply has four states. That's
all we have to know. It has four states.
Well, here's one possible motion. If we start
with this configuration, we move to that configuration.
If we start with this configuration, we move
to that configuration, and so forth. If we
watch what actually happened with time, the
system would move from one configuration to
the next around a closed loop. Now, the closed
loop is not necessarily a closed loop in space.
It's a closed loop in the logical
space of possibilities here, logical space of configurations.
That's one possible thing that
can... Here's another one. Perfectly good.
What this is, is it's a pair of systems,
a pair of... It's a pair of systems, which
are separately undergoing flip-flops. Each one
undergoing flip-flops. This one is flipping,
and flopping.
This one is simultaneously flipping and flopping. If
we start over here, let's see what that
stands for. That stands, for example, for
both heads. It could stand for both heads.
Then we go to both tails. Then we go to
both heads, then we go to both tails. Or we could
start with one head, one tail. And do this.
That's what this is. This is a pair of systems
flipping and flopping. There are other possibilities.
So there are different laws of motion that
the system, whatever it happens to be, could
have. So when you specify a system, you not
only have to specify what the states of the
system are, but you'll have to specify how it
moves. And how it moves is a rule for jumping
from one configuration to the next.
Now, let me give you
an example of a logically-prone system.
Okay.
It's a logically perfectly sensible rule, but
which is defective from the physics point
of view. It never happens in physics.
We can do it, I think, well, let's do
it with four states. Let's see how this works.
Yeah, here it is. If you start here, you
go here. If you go here, start here, you go
here.
One, here's a second round, two, here's a second.
Two, here's a third.
Excuse me one moment. For some odd reason,
in my notes, instead of a diamond shape, I've
drawn a square. Let me go
back. There's my four states. Okay?
If you start here, you go here.
If you're over here, you go over here
and if you're over here, you go over here.
Alright so now we can
say what happens wherever you start.
If you start over here, you jump to here, you jump to
here, you jump to here, you jump to here, you jump to here,
you go here you go here you go here
you go here you go here notice you never
come back to here with this particular law.
There's something different about this law
than there is about the other examples.
And all the other examples...
Well can anybody spot what's wrong with this?
Well not what's wrong with
it, but what's different about it.
Well it doesn't consist of loops.
This is true.
You can't figure out necessarily where you came from.
You may be able to tell where you go
next, but you can't always tell where you came from.
For example, if you find yourself over here, you
don't know if you came from here or whether
you came from here.
If you're over here, you
have lost a piece of information.
This is a motion which loses information.
It loses information in the sense that
you can't tell where you came from.
There's no way to reconstruct the
past, but you can reconstruct the future.
Or construct the future.
Wherever you are, you're told where to go next.
But wherever you are, you
don't know how to get back.
If you're over here, well you know you
came from here, but then you don't know whether
to go back here or to go back here.
So this is what is called an irreversible history.
It's a history of...
Or a law which loses information.
And at the fundamental level of physics,
the fundamental level where you're really keeping
track of everything, not where you're coarse-graining
or not looking carefully, but where you're
carefully looking at every degree of freedom
of a system, classical physics never allows
the loss of information like this.
There is a unique...
Future point wherever you are, and there
is a unique past point wherever you are.
That is one of the laws...
It's not necessarily a law of logic.
It is something which is true of all
physical systems, that they are reversible in that
sense.
Yeah.
Let's say I change state twice.
All right?
And I'm over here.
1, 2 or 1, 2.
I don't know if I came from here or here.
All right.
We could give this property a name.
We give it the uniqueness of the future
point and the uniqueness of the past point.
We could invent a name for it.
We could call it unique-tarity.
Do you know what the quantum version of unique-tarity is?
No.
It has a name.
It's called unitarity.
Unitarity is a name I just made up.
Unitarity is the quantum equivalent which
tells you that you can always reconstruct
the past from the future.
The state of a quantum system, you can
either run forward uniquely or run backward uniquely,
and you'll come to some unique point in time.
It's aathletic.
It's a very unique state.
It exists.
to some unique previous state or future
state, and that's called unitarity in quantum mechanics.
But we haven't done quantum
mechanics. Nothing's quantum mechanical yet.
Is that time symmetry?
It's a kind of time reversal symmetry. It's
actually not a time reversal. Okay, so it's
not a time reversal symmetry exactly. It's
a time reversibility, I would say. This diagram
has a sense of orientation to it. If I
start something over here, it goes around this way.
It definitely does not go around this way unless
I reverse it, unless I look at it backward
in time. So it's not precisely what you
would call time reversal symmetry. A time reversal
symmetry means that you could either go
in going into the future you could go
either way but in this case you only
go one way but it's it's it's the
reversibility of the laws that that you can
find a reverse law given a law you
can find a reverse law which will
take you in the backward direction I think
that's I think that's right yes yes well
two arrows coming away from a point says
I don't know which way to go oh boy do I
go that way or do I go that way so it's
it's it's clear that that's not a law
of motion okay no branching ratios oh well
let's we're doing at the moment
we're doing quantum mechanics so I mean
classical mechanics so it gets
more complicated with branching ratios and
was it classical mechanics is
less fundamental in quantum mechanics
always is.
all real systems are quantum mechanical
the question why some of them suppress
the quantum mechanics and you don't see
it is a question which we'll try to
answer as we go along but we might
ask it at the quantum level and at the
quantum level I think we can give
a better answer but ultimately at the end
of the day it seems to be
a law that that they basically says that
forward in time and backward in time
are are I won't say equivalent to each
other but that there's no preferred
really preferred sense in which forward
in time is different than backward in
time even though it feels like there is
this this this is this is the question
that took 20 years to answer and the
answer is in my opinion no it is not possible to answer that question
but I'm going to ask you a question that's not possible to answer in time.
but it was one of the great questions
of physics that took a long time to answer
and I'm not going to get into it now
but it might be an interesting thing for us
to explore toward the end after
we've talked about quantum mechanics we we
have to talk about quantum mechanics
before that makes sense that question
yeah I think they're all Newtonian in
a sense in the sense Newtonian to me
simply means that there's a difference between
the two and the other and that's
a definite state for a system
that evolves with time according to a
definite law of deterministic
deterministic that's that that's the
right word yeah but I think you
can think of more complicated situations you
just could start drawing some diagrams
yourself and and see what makes sense
what what's reversible what's not reversible
and but yes you're right that
is true it loses the information as to where
you came from the system yep we mean
it's not a part of the system the
system started here it went to here it went
to here it went to here it went there
anymore you won't find that point ever
again right right but the main point is
you've lost the distinction between the
two possible starting points whereas in
all the other situations you have a
different starting point and you have the
point that's going to be the starting point
and you have the point that's going to be
different starting point and you have
the point that's going to be
happening all the time all the time
but for that particular reason of predicted
if you know where you are and you
know how many steps you made you can say
where you were well I think I think
for a long long time mr. Stephen Hawking
thought that this is the way black holes
work so not so clear I'm not so
clear okay yeah yeah good good so let's let's
talk about that um if I take a a
I don't know what's a good example but if you taking a bunch of molecules in a bath if you taken a half of a
Allison like a whole lot of mi Schedule removing water what tells you mijn in th bravery method but I don't know how you fell so
Let's take the molecules in this room, and
I start them all out in a certain configuration,
very definite configuration. I put them all up
in the left-hand corner of the room there,
and I let them go. After a while, the
room will be full of air, just like it is.
If I put them up in that corner
of the room over there and let them go,
after a while, same thing. Put it up
in that corner, after a while, same thing.
So it looks like we've lost
information. But in fact, that's not true.
If we followed every single molecule,
and we followed it in infinite detail,
with infinite precision, which we don't do, of course,
then we could reconstruct, by running everything backwards,
we can reconstruct the fact that the molecules
may have come from that corner of the room.
It's prohibitively impossible to do in practice,
but in principle, following every
single detail of every molecule.
Now, what really happens in the real world,
is we lose information because we
lose the ability to follow the details.
Not because the information gets lost, but because
we lose the ability to follow the information.
That's where the second law comes,
when you start losing the
ability to distinguish different states.
So we don't distinguish
whether, in our coarse-grained picture,
we don't distinguish the different
detail, the level of molecular detail,
and we don't distinguish the level of the molecular detail,
and so it looks like
different configurations become the same configuration,
but that's only because we
simply don't look carefully enough.
It's because we're lazy.
Do you need an infinite number of bits to...
Ah, ah, ah. You mean
in the real room, like this.
No, because of quantum mechanics.
Because of quantum mechanics, no.
But if it were not for
quantum mechanics, yes, you would need
an infinite number of bits.
Now, what does that mean?
That means that you have to
specify a bunch of real numbers,
precisely, with infinite, with tremendous precision.
You have to precisely prescribe
the locations and also the velocities,
but in particular the locations of every single molecule,
with a tremendous amount of precision.
And the longer that you want to track
the system, the more precision that you need.
So ultimately, to track a system for a long time,
you need to specify with infinite precision
the exact positions of every point, of every molecule.
That means you have to
give a set of real numbers.
A set of real numbers involves, as
you say, an infinite number of bits.
So the answer is for a
collection of real particles moving around
that you really try to follow classically,
depending on how long you want to track them,
depending on how long you want to follow it,
you would need more and more bits to describe it.
Oh, yes, yes, yes, that's right.
If the room were really sealed, let's idealize this room
so that nothing can get
into or out of the room,
all particles bounce off, reflect
off the walls of the room,
so that it's an entirely sealed up room,
then the room can be
described discretely, because of quantum mechanics,
at least up to some energy.
If we know that the energy isn't arbitrarily high,
then we can describe it
by a discrete collection of variables
that has no exit.
So let's say...
Yeah, so we could...
So to make such a thing,
we could just reverse all the arrows.
Here is an example.
It doesn't actually have no exit,
it just makes it back to itself.
No, this one has no exit.
No, it just exits to itself.
Well, then if I want it to
exit to itself, I have to do this.
Yes, that's what I'm just saying.
We could do that, but as
I drew it, it had no exit.
Huh?
But let's think about what it means.
Let's...
I'm not too interested in what here.
The question is what happens when you're over here.
All right?
When you're over here, you have two ways
to go, and you don't know which way to go,
so it's not deterministic.
It doesn't know whether to
go this way or this way.
It might go half the times
this way, half the times this way.
You might need some statistical rule.
50% of the time or 30%
of the time it goes this way,
Sorry, 70% of the time with random statistics.
That would be non-deterministic.
So it seems that the real laws of nature
are both deterministic
and backward in time.
That's the implication of not having loose ends
floating around like this.
That they're deterministic either way,
so that wherever you are,
you can either trace forward uniquely
or backward uniquely.
And that is all of classical physics in a nutshell.
You're now taking a complete course in classical physics.
There's nothing that the world can't do
and that does not fit that pattern
at least to an arbitrarily high degree of approximation.
Let's take a seven-minute break.
Well, I was going to jump to quantum mechanics,
but before I do,
I want to do a little bit of mathematics,
elementary mathematics.
Most of you know it,
but nevertheless, let's lay it out.
Matrices and vectors.
I'm going to give you a little
bit of a tour of the world.
I'm going to, at the moment,
I'm not going to mathematically define a vector
in any sort of sensible, you know,
even approximately rigorous way or abstract way.
I'm just going to tell you.
A vector is a sequence of numbers,
a finite number of numbers,
and it's a vector.
It's called a finite sequence of numbers.
And you can represent it in a variety of ways,
but I'll give you two ways
to represent a sequence of numbers.
The first way is to write them one after another.
Let's just give them names.
I don't want to call them...
My numbers now, I...
At the moment, I mean real numbers
as opposed to complex numbers.
I don't mean zeros and ones.
I mean arbitrary sets of real numbers.
They could be zeros and ones.
Zeros and ones are fine,
but just general numbers.
So I just lay them out.
What should we call them?
Components.
Hmm?
Yeah, they're called components,
but I want a letter for them.
A? A?
A is good.
A1, A2, A3, A4,
and just put something around them
to surround them so that we know.
This would be a four-dimensional vector.
Why four-dimensional?
Because it has four components.
Don't try to visualize vectors now.
There's no value at all for our present purposes
in trying to visualize these as pointing in space
or anything like that.
They're just lists of numbers.
Okay?
Lists of...
That's one way.
Okay?
There's another way that we can list
the same set of numbers.
Put them in a column.
A1, A2, A3, A4.
Same information in them.
I mean, I'm not talking about information
in the abstract sense that I used before.
Same thing.
Sometimes it's useful to write it this way.
Sometimes it's useful to write it that way.
You'll find out as we move along.
When it's written in this form,
it's called a row vector.
it's called a column vector.
What we're actually talking about now is notations,
neat notations for doing certain
arithmetical operations involving collections of numbers.
But isn't one of those the dagger of the other?
When we get the complex numbers,
we will then use complex numbers.
Use complex conjugate notation, yes.
But for the moment, let them just be real numbers.
Okay?
Now, there's another concept now called a matrix.
And think of a matrix as the following way.
A matrix is a thing which acts on a vector
to give another vector.
All right?
So it's a kind of machine.
You put the vector into the machine
and out pops another vector.
According to a particular rule.
Oh, sorry.
Before we do that, before we do that,
let's imagine a particular column vector
and another different row vector.
Different row vector has different entries.
Not the same set of numerical entries,
but a different set of numerical entries.
So let's call them B.
B1, B2, B3, B4.
These could be 6.01, 5.97, 3.04,
and A1 could be 7.8, A2.
None of them, they could be the same
or they might not be the same,
the A's and the B's.
This is some particular row vector
and some particular column vector.
There's a notion of multiplying
a row vector by a column vector.
And the notion of multiplying a row vector
by a column vector is as simple as this.
It's a following simple operation.
You take the first entry,
oh, incidentally,
the dimensionality of the row vector
and the dimensionality of the column vector
should be the same.
That means that they should have
the same number of entries.
Not necessarily four.
It could be five, six, seven.
In which case they would be
five-dimensional vector spaces,
six-dimensional vector spaces.
This extends to any number
of entries into the columns and rows.
But the rows and the columns should have
the same number of entries.
Alright.
There's the notion of the product
of a row vector and a column vector.
It's called the inner product.
And it's very simply constructed.
You take the first entry of the row
and multiply it by the first entry of the column.
You add to that the second entry
times the second entry
plus the third entry
times the third entry
plus the fourth entry
times the fourth entry.
So the product of these two,
which you could just write as B next to A,
that product, the inner product,
is B1A1 plus B2A2
plus B3A3 plus B4A4.
It's a number.
It's not itself.
The product of these two vectors,
the inner product,
is not another vector.
It's not a matrix.
It is just a number.
The numerical value is just gotten
by adding up the column,
sorry, the row times the column
in just this form.
B1A1 plus B2A2 plus B3A3
plus B4A4.
Is that clear?
Don't ask me why.
That's definition.
Is this what you call
the dot product?
Yeah.
If we were talking about ordinary vectors in space,
it would be the dot product.
Yeah.
More abstractly,
for abstract vector spaces,
it's called the inner product.
But yes, it is the same as the dot product
for three-dimensional ordinary vectors in space
where these would be the components of the vector.
Yeah.
Okay.
Now there's the concept of a matrix.
And a matrix, as I said,
is an operation that you can do on a vector
to give a new vector.
All right?
But it's not any old operation.
There are particular family of operations
that are characterized by matrices.
A matrix is represented
by a square array of numbers.
Let's call the answer,
entries M.
All right?
So in the first place,
we put M11
to indicate that it's in the first row
and the first column.
Then M12.
Then M13.
Then M14.
Okay?
M...
What should I call this one?
It's in the second row
of the first column.
This is in the second row,
second column.
Second row, third column.
Next one.
M31.
M32.
M33.
M34.
And M41.
M42.
M43.
M44.
Now, as I said,
I've chosen four dimensions
just arbitrarily.
Four is about as many as,
as big as I want to handle
on the backboard.
And it's big enough to be
a little abstract
so that it's general enough
to see what's going on.
All right.
That's what a matrix is.
That's all it is.
Now, you can think of it,
you can think of it,
you can think of each column
as a column vector
whose components are labeled
by the first entry here.
Okay?
Each one of these can be thought of
as a column vector
where the first entry
labels the column entry.
Or you can think of it
as a collection of row vectors
where it's the second entry
which labels the component.
Either way,
you can think of it both ways
at the same time.
A collection of column vectors,
or a collection of row vectors.
But all together,
it forms a matrix.
Now, matrices can multiply vectors.
So let's put a vector over here.
A1, A2,
I should line them up more carefully.
A1, A2, A3, A4.
And when you have a matrix,
you can think of it as,
let's say,
a column vector.
And when you,
I don't know,
I've done a reasonable job
of keeping rows and columns
underneath and next to each other.
But if you like,
draw some imaginary lines
to separate them into rows and columns.
All right, this matrix
acts on this vector
to give a new vector.
What is the new vector?
And here's the rule.
I've made the vector wide,
which is going to be
a fairly complicated expression.
But it is just another vector.
It's another single,
it's another column.
It's a column
which I've had to draw wide
in order to be able to fit in
everything I want to write down.
Here's what you do.
If you want to find the first entry
into this column,
sorry, into this row,
into this row,
you take the first row
and you multiply it by the column.
And you get the inner product
of the first row with a column here.
So what is that?
That's M11 times A1
plus M12 times A2
plus M13 times A3
plus M14 times A4.
In other words, you take all of this
and you multiply it by this
according to the inner product rule.
And that gives you the first row.
M11, A1
plus M12, A2
plus M13, A3
plus M14, A4.
Now you want the second entry
into this new vector over here.
Done exactly the same way,
except you go to the second row.
And you take the second row
and multiply it by the column.
That's going to give you M...
I'm only going to do two of these.
The rest you can do yourself.
M21
M21, again times A1
plus M22 times A2
plus M23, A3
plus M24 times A4.
And the other two entries you can figure out.
You get them by multiplying the next row
by the column,
and finally the third row by the column.
That gives you a new vector.
It's a way of processing a vector
to produce a new vector.
I will give you some examples
as we go along.
It's a rule of multiplication
which is very useful.
The reason it's defined is because it's useful.
And we're going to see
how it's useful by using it.
Let me give you an example
of how a matrix...
how the idea of a matrix
can represent the time evolution
of the configuration of a system.
Supposing, again, we have our configuration.
Let's take a look at the configuration space.
Let's label them.
The first configuration,
the second configuration,
the third configuration,
the fourth and the fifth configuration.
These are not points of space.
These are configurations of a system
which has five distinct states.
And let's take a very, very simple
law of evolution.
The first one,
you start here,
you go to here.
If you start here,
you go here.
And what do I do if I'm here?
Go back.
No, no, that one,
that's no good.
That's disallowed, I think.
Is that disallowed?
I think that's disallowed.
that's disallowed? Yeah, that's disallowed
because
if you find this... yeah, that's not reversible
that's not reversible
that's not what I wanted to hear. What I
wanted to hear is that you go back to here
so this is just a
one goes to two, two goes to three, three goes
to four, four goes to five, five goes back to one
it's a cycle
here's another way to represent the same thing
we can
represent the state of the system
by a column vector
and the column vector
we simply insert a one someplace
if I want to represent the first state over here
I put a one
and then a bunch of zeros
one, two, three, four, five
this simply represents
the first state
what about the second state?
the second state I'll represent by zero
one
zero zero zero
the third state
by
zero
one
and so forth
so the states of the system can be represented
by a column, but a particular kind
of column, a column with all zeros
and a one someplace
where is the one?
namely whichever state you're focusing on
if you're focusing on the fifth state
put the one in the fifth entry here
now
what is this rule of evolution
the rule of evolution says that
if you have a one someplace
then the next instant of time the one moves down
so if you start here
the one moves down to here
and the next instant it moves down to here
next instant it moves down to here
next instant it moves down to
here, then where does it go?
go? Up to the top. Right. So there's
a procedure that you do on this column to
tell you where the system goes in the
next instant of time. That process can be
represented by a matrix. So let me
show you the matrix that represents that. The
matrix is an operation on a vector which
you can think of in this case as the
updating operation. The operation which updates
the vector. So here it is, let's
see we put 0 1 0 0. This is
five-dimensional so I need five. 0 0 1 0 0
0 0 0 1 0 0 0.
I'm sorry, I'm gonna make this four-dimensional.
I'mma call it, I'm just gonna call it,
I'm just gonna call it zero zero zero. Now
I'm getting sick of it, I don't like five dimensions.
Five is too many for me.
One, zero, zero, zero.
Let's try it out.
Let's try it out on this vector right over here.
This represents the third state.
What happens if we act with this matrix
on the third state? Let's just try it out.
Let's see what we get.
Well, the first entry, up on the top,
is gotten by taking the top vector
and multiplying by the column.
Zero times zero, plus one times zero,
plus zero times one, plus zero times zero.
What's the answer?
Zero.
Next place, zero times zero, zero times zero, one time...
One time...
Whoops, whoops, whoops!
I did it better.
Okay.
Instead of going down, it's gonna go up.
It's okay.
Up and down, we just turn the whole thing over.
Would you prefer...
Let's just...
Let's get it right.
Zero, zero, zero, zero.
One time.
Zero.
Where did I have it before?
I had it over here?
Yeah.
One, one, one, one, and then up here?
One.
Okay.
So let's start over again.
What's up on the top?
Zero times zero.
Zero times one.
One, one times zero.
We're still okay.
Zero.
Next one.
7, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11,
12, 13, 14, 15, 16, and 19.
1, 0, one, zero.
But now in the last place, I have 0 times 0,
0 times 0, 1 times 1, and 0 times 0, so 1.
The column has moved down one step.
Now you can check for yourself. Here's your homework.
Check that any place that you put this 1, it will
move down by one step until it gets to the bottom.
And then it will recycle
and go up to the top.
So that's a little thing to check.
In fact, you can put in any numbers here.
Only 0s and 1s may make sense, but we
could put in any number, A, B, C, D.
Okay.
And what will come out over here is everybody will move down a
step, A, B, C, but then D will move up to the top.
So if you put a 1 in any one of the places,
it will slide down one unit and then reappear at the top.
The point is that the evolution of systems can
be represented by matrices, matrices of a particular kind,
and a bunch of, in classical physics, in this
kind of classical physics, there are always just 1s here.
Quantum mechanics is more complicated and
more difficult, but in classical physics,
but sprinklings of 0s and 1s so as to
make the, each state shift into the next one.
Okay.
That's an example of the
use of matrices in classical physics.
So far, no quantum mechanics, just pure classical physics.
There is an interesting, well, all right,
this will do for the time being.
We'll come back to it.
So that's an example of
matrix algebra, matrices multiplying vectors.
What about matrices multiplying matrices?
Why might we want to do that?
Why might we want to multiply matrices by matrices?
Well, here's the idea.
Supposing we wanted to upgrade or update a second time.
To update a second time, what we would do would be
to apply the same matrix to the resultant that we got.
In other words, let's write it this way.
Let's write it abstractly.
We have a matrix M,
which we multiply by a vector.
We multiply by a vector V
to get a new vector V prime.
Okay.
That's just abstract notation for writing a matrix
and a vector and getting a new vector.
That's updating the vector V to a new vector.
Let's update it again.
Let's go one more interval of time.
How do we do that?
Well, what we do is we write
M times V prime equals V double prime.
Okay.
So, we would do the same updating trick,
except now update V prime instead of V.
And we would get V double prime.
V double prime being the state of
the system after two units of time.
But we could also write that by
realizing that V prime is M times V.
We could write this as M times M
times V is equal to V double prime.
This just means we apply the matrix twice.
Okay.
We can also think of it as squaring
the matrix M and then multiplying it by V.
So, how do you square a matrix?
Or how do you multiply one matrix by another matrix?
This is what you would do
if you would want to update twice.
Once with one matrix and then once
with another matrix or the same matrix.
How do you multiply matrices?
And the answer is basically the same kind of rule.
I will do it now for 2 by 2 matrices
because it's getting too complicated even for 4 by 4 matrices.
For a 2 by 2 matrix,
we have M11, M12, M21, M22.
Let's call it some other matrix N.
N11, N12, N21, N22.
The result of multiplying a
matrix by a matrix is this.
Multiplying a matrix by a matrix is another matrix.
It's another matrix.
And we do it in a very similar manner.
Supposing we want the entry here.
We get the entry by taking the first
row and multiplying it by the first column.
M11 times N11 plus M12 times N21.
Same kind of inner product.
And we put it over here.
Now supposing we want the next entry.
For the next entry, we take the first row because
after all we're interested in the first row up here.
We take the first row but multiply
it by the second column over here.
So what would be over here would
be M11 times N12 plus M12 times N22.
I'm not going to write it all out.
Now we can move down to the bottom.
The bottom, if we wanted this entry, we would take
the bottom row and multiply it by the first column.
If we want the last entry over here, we would
take the bottom row and multiply it by the last column.
So we multiply matrices by the same kind
of pattern that we multiplied matrices times vectors.
We can simply think of it as multiplying
this matrix by this vector, putting it over here.
Multiply this matrix by this vector, put it over here.
So there's a notion of multiplying matrices.
And what multiplying matrices does is
it gives you a new matrix
which updates you to the next matrix.
Which updates you not by one interval of
time, but updates you by two intervals of time.
If you wanted to short circuit the problem of updating,
and you wanted to update the state
of a system five units of time,
what you would do is
multiply the matrix together five times.
You do it in sequence.
First, the first, times the next.
The result times the next one.
Times the result.
Times the next one.
And you can work out what the matrix is,
which would take you from the state
of a system at an instant of time
to a state of the system five instants later.
So matrix multiplication, multiplying matrices by matrices,
is also an important concept.
One last example of matrix algebra.
Involves row vectors.
Supposing you have a row vector,
and you want to multiply it by a matrix.
The rule is you write the row matrix first,
B1, B2, B3, B4,
and then you write the matrix.
M11, M12, M13, and so forth.
M14, dot dot dot, dot dot
dot dot, dot dot dot dot.
You're tired of writing Ms.
Well, what's the result going to be?
The result is going to be,
a row vector.
And here's the way you get
the entries of the row vector.
The first entry of the row vector,
you get by taking the original row vector,
and multiplying it by the first column vector over here.
That product,
that product,
is the first entry.
Then you take the original row,
and multiply it by the second column.
That gives you the second entry.
Then you take the original row,
and you multiply it by the third column.
That gives you the third
entry over here, and so forth.
You see the pattern, it's
always multiplying rows by columns,
and putting them, putting the result in the right place,
in the right row and column.
In this case,
a row vector times a matrix is another row vector.
A row, a matrix times a column vector is another,
here it is,
a matrix times a column vector is another column vector.
And a matrix times a matrix is another matrix.
Um, get familiar with that.
Work out some examples.
Work out some examples of your own devising,
just put some numbers in,
multiply row vectors times matrices,
matrices times column vectors,
and matrices times matrices,
and get the experience of
working out how these things work.
Do it for two by two,
for three by three matrices,
and you'll get familiar with it,
because we will use it
over and over and over again.
In fact, that's the primary mathematical operation
of quantum mechanics,
is multiplying rows and columns,
and columns times matrices.
If you know how to do that,
and you're familiar with it,
and you can read off the answers easily,
you've got all of the
basic mathematics of quantum mechanics.
It would help to have a little bit of,
uh,
calculus to go with it,
but, uh,
the basic new thing is matrix multiplication,
and column vectors and row vectors.
So please,
uh,
practice with it a little bit.
I should have made up
some examples for you to do,
but, um,
you can make up your own.
They're very straightforward.
Okay, uh,
uh,
we're getting close to nine o'clock.
Are there any questions?
Next time we're going to start talking about qubits,
quantum bits,
and how quantum bits are very different than classical bits.
Question?
Yes?
What's your name?
My name?
Leonard Susskind.
Or Susskind.
You, uh,
if you like,
uh,
you know,
polishing the apple for the professor,
you can call me Leonardo.
I like that very much.
Well, you mean,
say it the other way.
What restriction does reversibility place on him?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
That it have an inverse.
Okay.
Right.
Well, that's the...
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But I mean in a more,
if, if I were,
uh,
in a more abstract sense,
the answer is that it should have an inverse.
That the matrix should have an inverse.
The inverse, of course,
is the thing that takes you back.
Not all matrices have inverses.
So,
uh,
and you want,
you know what an inverse is.
Yeah.
Okay.
Good.
And I will,
we'll,
if you don't,
we'll come to it.
Any other question?
Yes.
That, that is a good question.
Yeah.
Uh,
the final exam is buying me lunch.
Right.
That's a lot of lunches out there, boy.
Every,
look,
nobody asks me about grading the class.
Nobody,
I mean,
a lot of you have been here before,
so you know my policies.
My policies are you're here to learn physics.
There is nobody here who is,
uh,
here for a degree or,
if you are,
then I'll,
I'll be glad to give you
a numerical grade if you need one.
In fact,
everybody needs a numerical grade.
I know that there's an enormous difference in
the level of preparation of different people here.
Uh,
and to compare,
to compare you in an exam setting wouldn't make
sense because I do know that there's an enormous difference.
I know that everybody here is here because you want to be here
and you want to learn physics and not because you have to be here.
Uh,
so,
uh,
my policy is,
to either not grade the course at all or if
somebody needs a grade in order for some particular purpose,
uh,
to,
to give a D minus.
Lowest possible grade.
Lowest possible passing grade.
All right.
So,
it is,
it's,
I didn't tell you what it's for yet.
I gave you,
that's right,
I gave you an example of how you can use
it to implement the idea of updating a vector from one,
uh,
from one instrument to another.
It's one example and,
but I haven't told you yet why we're doing this.
I
often spend,
I often spend an hour
talking about qualitative aspects of physics.
In this case it was how
do you abstractly think about deterministic physics,
uh,
abstractly in terms of bits and so forth,
and then spend,
uh,
some time doing some,
mathematics which really I won't tell you
what it's for until the next time.
But I want to make sure since I'm going
to start doing some quantum mechanics the next time,
I want to make sure that everybody will recognize the little
algebraic little bit of manipulations that we'll do and have the,
have the,
uh,
the mathematics for the next time.
So it's really for the next time that,
uh,
that I set this up.
Yeah?
Do you promise to tell us next time what?
I think,
I think you will see.
I think it will be clear.
Uh,
right.
I think it will be clear.
Yes,
I do promise to tell you why.
Yeah.
Do you have a problem with that?
No.
Sure.
Is that quantum junkies,
uh,
is that what it's called?
That,
that,