This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
I want to start talking about quantum mechanics now.
We haven't talked about quantum mechanics.
We've talked about classical physics in a
world where what we can call the state
space, the space of states, is discrete.
We've talked about hopping around from one
state to another and how information is counted
in bits, how with time you can jump
from one state to another, and so forth.
That's all classical physics, or
it's physics based on classical logic.
Classical logic means that the space state...
is a Boolean space, so that
everybody know what a Boolean space is.
If not, all it means is a bunch of
points in some space, and that each point represents
a state, and all of the logic
is classical logic, classical logic that Aristotle would
have understood, that Newton would have understood,
and so forth, whereas quantum mechanics makes
use of an entirely new kind of logic,
which is in a very basic way different.
To illustrate...
I'm sorry.
To illustrate it, I'd like to start with
the basic idea, first of all, of a single
quantum bit, a qubit.
We talked about the classical bit,
which is just the heads-tails type distinction.
Here we can...
I have my prop already.
This end is different than this end.
If I point it up, that's one state.
If I point it down, that's another state.
That's the two states.
That's the two-state system, and
that's all there is to it.
Nothing in between.
Assume nothing in between.
That's the basic classical bit, either
up or down, with nothing in between.
And of course, you can have many bits.
Ooh, that's fun.
You can have many bits, two
bits, three bits, four bits, whatever.
And pretty much all of physics...
Anything in physics...
Anything in physics can be represented or
at least approximated by a system of classical
bits, anything in classical physics.
Quantum physics, the concept of
a bit is very, very different.
The concept of a bit of information.
And that's what we want to talk about today.
The basic, simplest example is the spin of an electron.
Now, we don't have to know
very much about what spin means.
Whether it's spinning or not, this is not very important.
What is important is that every
electron has associated with it a vector.
Now we're going to get into big trouble because
there are two things that I'm going to wind
up calling vectors.
One of them is abstract vector spaces, which
we're going to come to in a little while.
And the other is vectors in ordinary space.
A vector...
This I took with me just
to illustrate the idea of a vector.
You know what a vector is.
It's a vector.
It's an object in ordinary space.
It's an object with a length and a direction.
And I put a nail in the end here to
indicate the arrow so that you'll know which way it's
pointing.
It's not pointing at me.
It's pointing up in the corner of the room there.
That's your naive elementary physics concept of
a vector, a thing in ordinary space that
has a direction.
Of course, it also has components.
For example, this vector here has
a component in the horizontal direction.
It has a component in the vertical direction.
But altogether, it's pointing in this other direction.
So that's one concept of a vector, a
pointer in space with a length and a direction.
Now there's another thing we're going to
call vectors, which is a more abstract concept.
And it's not necessarily, in general, will
not be referring to things in space.
It's an abstract mathematics.
I just wish there was a different word for it.
We're going to be talking about vector spaces.
I think sometimes when I teach quantum mechanics, I make
up a new word for one or the other of
them.
Call it a schmecter or something.
I don't know.
But it never really works.
So we have to keep in mind that when
I use the word vector, sometimes maybe I should
just make a new word.
Some people say arrow for the old guy.
Yeah.
That's a good idea.
Let's just call this vector.
Let's just call this an arrow.
You know how long I will last
before I start calling it a vector?
Not very long.
Right.
Now the spin of an electron is an arrow.
I was going to say vector.
I can't help it.
No, I cannot.
I can't do it.
I'm going to call it a vector.
I can't help myself.
Let's call it a spatial vector.
How about a spatial vector?
A spatial vector means one in ordinary space.
So if my fist is the electron over
here, the electron has attached to it a mathematical
vector.
It's not a rod like this,
but it's a sense of directionality.
Really what it is is a direction of twist.
But just think of it as every electron has
attached to it a vector which can point, you
might think, in any direction in space.
In fact, in some sense,
it can point in any direction.
It can point in any direction.
It can point in any direction in space.
And in fact, that vector can
also be thought of as a magnet.
It can be thought of as a bar
magnet with a north pole and a south pole.
So here's the north pole with a nail.
The south pole is over here.
Every electron is a little magnet.
And the amount, the strength of the magnet,
which is measured in some units, which I forget
what they're called, strength of
magnet units, is some particular number.
So that means all electrons, their space
vectors that go with them, it's called the
magnetic moment.
The magnetic moments are all the same length.
They may point in different directions,
but they're all the same length.
And we can simply imagine that they are objects
all of the same length, or a common length,
but different directions.
Now, let's talk about ordinary classical magnets.
And I want to talk about the concept
of preparing a state and detecting a state.
We're still thinking very classically for the moment.
Everything I explained here
was completely with classical logic.
So here's our electron.
And it has attached to it an arrow
with a north pole and a south pole.
And let's say I want to prepare.
Let's say I want to prepare that
electron in a configuration where its magnetic moment,
its little vector, is pointing this north
there that doesn't stand for its direction.
It stands for the north pole of the magnet.
I want to have the north pole, I
want the magnet to be pointed vertically upward.
I want to prepare it that way.
How do I do it?
OK.
What you do is you
simply create a large magnetic moment.
And you're going to do that.
So let's say you create a magnetic field.
For example, you put a, you create a magnet.
This is not a very good pen.
You create a magnet.
You can do it as an electromagnet if you like.
Turn on some current to make an electromagnet with
a north pole over here, a south pole over here.
And the electron is supposed
to be in the magnetic field.
What will happen to that little bar magnet?
Well, what actually will happen to the little
bar magnet, if you know anything about how
bar magnets move in magnetic fields, is it will precess.
It will not just jump up into
a right position, not unless there's some friction.
Instead what it will do is it
will precess like this around the magnetic field.
Everything imagine is in a vacuum, so
there's no friction or anything like that.
The electron will precess around like this.
That's what a little bar magnet would do.
But sooner or later it will
get rid of that precessional energy.
Anybody know how it gets rid of the precessional energy?
It radiates some radiation.
It radiates a little bit of electromagnetic
radiation, or a lot, depending on the circumstances,
on the size of the magnetic field and so forth.
It will radiate away its energy
and come into the best energetic field.
Magnetic configuration, which is pointing straight up,
where the north pole of the magnet
is pointing toward the south pole, where the
north pole of the electron is pointing toward
the south pole of the
magnet, only which part I've drawn.
So that's the preparation.
If we do it with a very, very
big magnetic field, it will radiate that energy quickly,
and very quickly come to equilibrium.
And then it will radiate to equilibrium with
the north pole of the electron pointing vertically
upward.
If you like, if we don't want to get,
I was going to use the word entangled, but embroiled
with the question of where the electron is,
just imagine in your head that I hold the
electron absolutely fixed in position, so that
the only thing that can do anything interesting
is the direction of the magnetic field.
Okay.
So after a small amount
of time, that electron will be...
Pointing in the up direction.
We could, if we liked, we could prepare
the electron in a different configuration by rotating
the magnetic poles to something like
this, south-north, we could prepare the electron
initially so that it's pointing in that direction.
So we start with an electron pointing in some direction.
And then we can start to
prepare the electron in a different direction.
So we start with an electron pointing in some direction.
Okay.
Now we want to measure, we want to do a
measurement to find out which direction, this is a second
kind of experiment, it's the detection.
What first was the preparation, and then we
do some things to the electron, whatever it
is, and next we want to find out,
we want to detect which direction the electron is
pointing in.
Is it pointing in that direction?
Is it pointing in some other direction?
Mainly we could ask what's its
angle relative to the magnetic field.
And to answer that question, we do exactly the
same thing that we did to detect it, to
prepare the electron.
We stick it into the large magnetic field
and wait for it to radiate some radiation.
Alright.
Now if this, if all of physics were
classical, and this were really a perfectly classical
setup.
Well...
If we had a classical compass here
instead of a quantum mechanical electron, then the,
again, the electron would eventually point its
way itself up, but one measure of the
angle would be how much radiation it emitted.
For example, if it was almost perfectly upward
to begin with, if it were almost perfectly
upward, then it only has a little bit of radiation.
It's not going to radiate much.
It's going to radiate a little bit.
It's going to radiate a little bit of extra energy.
Perfectly upward has the minimum energy.
When the North Pole is pointing toward the South Pole.
That's the minimum energy of that little pointer here.
Rotate it away a little bit.
You give it a little bit of magnetic energy,
and of course, after you've put it into the,
after you've let it come to rest again, it
does so by giving off that little bit of energy.
Alright.
If you were to go to a more extreme situation.
Where you point it the other way.
If you pointed the electron in some horizontally,
then by the time it got vertical, it would
emit even more energy.
Finally, if you pointed it straight down,
it would emit the maximum amount of energy
in the form of radiation.
And so you could measure at least the
angle relative to the magnetic field by measuring
how much radiation comes out.
Alright.
And the answer would be a nice
continuous function of the angle of the electron.
So that when the, so when the
electron was pointing up, no energy comes out.
This is angle horizontally.
Energy emitted if the angle is
zero, that's when it's pointing straight up.
No energy.
If the angle is downward.
Right.
So you would measure the maximum energy, and then
as you turn it over all the ways, back
to zero energy and so forth.
So you would measure then, the same way
that you prepare, you measure the spin, the spin
direction of the electron by letting it emit a photon.
By letting it emit some radiation, excuse me.
And counting up the amount of the radiation.
Now I've told you completely the
wrong story for a real electron.
This is not the way it works.
This is not the way it works for any electron.
Alright.
So you would measure the maximum energy, and
then as you turn it over all the ways,
this is what happens.
This is the way it works for a genuine electron.
Something else happens, and I'll
tell you now what it is.
And it's very weird.
It really does illustrate the
weirdness of the quantum world.
First of all, no matter which way you create
the electron in here, I won't even try to
give a classical picture.
If I try to give a
classical picture, I will prejudice the story.
You do something to the electron,
and you put it over here.
Whatever you do to the electron, one thing
you could do to the electron is initially
prepare it in some funny angle.
But whatever you do to the electron, you put
it over here, you turn on the magnetic field,
and one of two things happens.
Only two things can happen.
One is it emits no photon.
Okay.
No electromagnetic radiation.
The other is that it emits one quantum,
one photon of electromagnetic radiation of a very
particular frequency.
It's the particular frequency that corresponds to
the energy of jumping from down to up.
Whatever that energy is, you can emit a
photon of just exactly that energy, and no other
energy.
Okay.
So there seems to be, it's almost as
if the electron had only two possible configurations.
You jumble it up, you don't know what you've done
to it, you stick it in here, and it seems
there's only two things that can happen.
One is that it behaves as if it were
pointing up, in which case it gives off no photon.
The other is that it behaves
as if it were pointing downward.
Okay.
So it's almost as if the
electron had only two possible configurations.
The other is that it behaves
as if it were pointing downward.
Okay.
So it's almost as if it were pointing
up, in which case it gives off no photon.
And gives off the photon.
And those are the only two
things that happen, that can happen.
Alright.
But depending on, now that seems a little weird.
Why?
Because supposing you prepared the electron by
putting it into a magnetic field that would
have the effect of freezing it into a direction,
let's say at 45 degrees, or even better, at
90 degrees relative.
In other words, 90 degrees.
In other words, horizontal.
Then we would think to ourselves, well that
electron is now pointing in some other direction.
Now when I stick it into the vertical
field, you would think that the response would be
something different than if it
were just plain up or down.
But no.
The response is always just one of two responses.
Either it does give off a photon or it doesn't.
And always of the same energy.
So it seems that in some sense,
there are only two states for the electron.
Either it's pointing up or it's pointing down.
But wait a minute.
What about if you put the electron into
a magnetic field pointing in yet a different
direction?
Then you're going to find that there are
only two states for the electron, either pointing
this way or pointing that way.
Something's very confusing.
How many states does the electron actually have?
Is it only up or down?
Or can you make it point in some other direction?
And if you do make it point in some
other direction, how come when you stick it into
the up-down detector here, the detector that
detects the direction in the up-down direction,
that you only get two possibilities?
How come there isn't a
continuum of possibilities in between?
That's the puzzle, or that's one of the
puzzles of quantum mechanics, that it behaves as if
there are only two states.
There are only two states, up
or down, when you measure it.
But you can nevertheless prepare that electron
pointing in any direction by using a magnetic
field in the appropriate direction.
Now, the one thing, though, that is true
is if you started with the electron pointing
upward, let's suppose we created the electron
pointing upward by putting it in this very
strong position.
So, let's say we have a strong magnetic field.
We'll shut off the magnetic field for
a while, and then turn it back on.
The answer is, we will get no photon.
The electron is pointing up.
Supposing we first create the electron in
some other direction, pointing along the 45-degree
axis here, and then we do the vertical experiment.
We turn on the vertical magnetic field.
We will either discover the electron pointing
in the opposite direction, or we will either
discover the electron pointing in the opposite direction.
We will either discover that it's up
or down, but with a probability distribution.
It will not be definitely up or definitely down.
We can do this experiment repeatedly, over
and over and over, many, many times identically.
Sometimes we will find a photon emitted.
Sometimes we won't.
The more the electron was initially
pointing vertically upward, the less the probability
is that we will emit that single photon.
So, we'll have to make sure that we're
not going to get any more than one electron.
The maximum probability for emitting that photon
will be if we were originally pointing
down.
Somewhere in between, the probability will be
half for a photon to be emitted.
In fact, that's exactly the case if
the original electron were prepared horizontally, by a
horizontal setup, and then put into the vertical
field, there will be a probability of a half
that it emits the photon.
And a half that it doesn't emit the photon.
So, there's something extraordinary going on here.
In some sense, it seems there are only two configurations.
Every time you measure that electron, you
will either find it's up or it's down.
Nothing else.
Nothing in between.
But there are situations where it will
be probabilistically, if you do the same thing
many, many times, you'll
find there's a probability distribution.
And it's that probability distribution
that will determine the probability distribution.
And it's that probability distribution which has
some memory of which way you originally
created the photon.
So a quantum bit is a confusing thing.
It looks like it has only two states, up or
down, but then you can make it point in some
other direction, so that it
looks like there's other states possible.
Again, when you measure it, you find only two possibilities.
It's a confusing entity, a quantum bit.
So, what's the probability?
Well, it's a quantum bit.
It's a quantum bit.
Any questions so far?
Yeah?
This magnet is a large size.
Say it again?
Not the magnet that's attached to an electron, is it?
Right.
The magnet that creates the field.
Oh, yeah.
Is a large object.
Yeah.
If one would try to test and create a
field to interact with, would it be possible to
do it with small objects, like other electrons?
Oh.
Like, what would it be?
That's when we're going to start
to talk about entanglement between electrons.
But let's do it one at a time,
and then we'll come to the two-electron system.
The two-electron system is the one
that's really interesting, because that's where entanglement
starts to happen.
So let's not try that one yet.
Little steps for little feet.
Yeah, question.
Yes.
To get this probability distribution, you have to do this.
Yeah.
Do you have to do the whole experiment
over and over again, prepare it, and then measure?
If you want to get it experimentally.
Or can you prepare it
once, and then turn it back?
Well, there's no way that with one
experiment that you can accumulate a probability distribution.
But can you prepare it once?
Prepare it this way.
Measure, turn the field off, measure
again, turn the field off, measure again.
Or do you have to
prepare it each time in between?
No, you have to prepare
it again each time in between.
Okay.
Right.
Yes, yes, yes.
You can prepare a lot of electrons at once.
But I think the question goes something like this.
Supposing you prepared it this way, and then measured it.
And then measure the same one
again, and then measure the same one.
No.
Once you discovered this was up the first
time, it will be up every time afterwards.
And so what you'll discover in the
second experiment, the third experiment, the fourth
experiment, no photon.
So what you'll discover will be
that it's still up until then.
So you just have to do the same
thing over and over again, and then measure.
Really nice.
You have to do the same
thing about all the other ones.
And then you've just got to measure
this way again and then measure it.
Or maybe measure it once.
No.
Once you discovered this was up the first
time, it will be up every time afterwards
And so what you will discover in the
second experiment, the third experiment, fourth experiment, no photon
So once the experiment has fixed
it to be up, that's it
It has no memory anymore of this
On the other hand, as... yeah?
Preparing means waiting to see what happens and
then when it's... if it emits, you assume that's...
Right, right
So you're just doing that again
That's what I'm calling... that's one way of...
That's one way of preparing an
electron, yeah, it's the usual way, yeah
You're talking about an electron by
itself, not an electron in an atom
I'm talking about an electron by
itself, not in an atom, yeah
Well, I'm talking about an electron perhaps which
is in some potential which nails its position down
So that it wouldn't...
We don't have to worry about it moving
We're just concentrating now purely
on the spin of the electron
So imagine driving a nail through the heart
of the electron and nailing it to the blackboard
It still has the ability for its spin to move
Is the magnetic field of one electron constant?
Is the electron field... say it again
The magnetic field constant for one electron
Is it...
Constant in time
Oh, constant...
Well, okay, so here's what we're imagining
Imagine I want to do an experiment
So I take an electron which is there originally
I don't know how I got
it there, any way I like
Without the magnetic field being there
Now I want to measure that electron
So I very quickly turn
on a very large magnetic field
How do you do that?
If it's an electromagnet, it's
very easy, you flip a switch
And all of a sudden there's a large electric field...
Sorry, magnetic field pointing upward
And if that electric...
If that magnetic field is large enough
It will very quickly cause the electron to radiate
Okay, so I would say, no, we want to be
thinking about turning on the field to do the measurement
Or to do the preparation
Yeah
In the single-electron series, is
it possible to prepare facing south
And then put it into the magnetic field system?
Put it on the switch and then...
The outcome is facing north
That's right
If you start...
If you start turning over the whole device
You start with south in the bottom
Where south belongs
And north in the top where north belongs
Then the electron will point down eventually
Now you remove the magnetic field
Okay, you remove the magnetic field
Or suddenly reverse...
Just turn off the magnet
And reverse the polarity
You can do that by
reversing the current in the electromagnet
So that suddenly the south pole is on
top and the north pole is on the bottom
The electron was down
In a very short amount of time,
it'll flip up and give off a photon
Was that the question?
The probability of that is one?
And then...
The probability of that is one, yeah
The probability that it will
give off... Yes, in that circumstance...
give off a photon is one
If on the other hand, this weren't perfectly aligned
And you were at some cattywampus angle
Then the probability would be less than one
And it's those probabilities
which constitute the experimental...
Yeah
So it must put energy into the electron in order
for it to keep emitting in all these experiments, right?
So somehow it must get like charged up or...
No, it doesn't get electrically charged
It has electric charge
Turning...
Now, turning on...
Turning on the electric current going through these magnets
You'll have to do a little more...
You'll have to put a little more energy
into the magnet because the electron is there
In other words, originally...
The energy comes from the energy that
you used to turn on the magnetic field
One more
In the case of the electron, actually...
What's the importance of 29?
So, the longer you turn this
magnet, the faster it emits a photon
Are we supposed to assume that's
instantaneous or what happens in that transition?
Well, the point...
Yeah, I mean, that's...
The language is probably wrong
Here's what I can tell you
If you make the magnetic field sufficiently large
The electron will very quickly emit in a photon
Now, the correct answer in general...
Is that the photon will be emitted at
a more or less random time in the planet
One more interesting thing, if you
try and go for it for real...
in the same way that a radioactive atom will decay
It decays with a half-life
So if you put the electron into
the magnetic field in the wrong direction
it will, with a certain half-life, decay
Decay means give off a photon
and write itself in the other direction
But if you make the magnetic field large enough
that half-life will be very short
and so it will very suddenly flip
Okay?
No, but I'm talking not about
when it gives off the electron
but when it gives off the photon
but during the transition,
when it's transitioning from the...
One of the things we've learned in quantum mechanics
is to ask questions only if
we know how to make the measurement
If you can tell me in detail how to measure
when the electron emits its photon
then we can try to answer it
I would say that's one of these questions
that you're not supposed to answer
There's a thing called the energy-time uncertainty principle
And if you know the energy of the electron
you're uncertain about the time
But let's come to uncertainty principles later
It's a good question
But if you have like a million electrons
you can measure the intensity of the light
Yes, you can measure the
intensity of the light given off
but any given photon would
be emitted at a random time
Well, if you know how many electrons there are
and what the intensity of the light was
you can sort of count the books
Yes, but you can't say when any given photon
or when any given electron decayed
Right
Okay, let's...
Well, what you've got to know is that
the more energy you put into the system
the more quickly it will lift the dead
The bigger you make the magnetic field
the more energy you put
in, the more quickly it will...
Right, absolutely
Absolutely
More quickly in the sense of a smaller half-life
Right
Okay, so first of all we're dealing with a theory
that only has prob... that has a probabilistic description
And we will see ultimately
that there is really prob...
There's probably no way around the fact
that the description has to be probabilistic
at least at some level
The mathematics of the state space
of the concept of a state
The state is different in quantum mechanics
It's clearly different
If this were... clearly different
It's a system with only two states
you think
But then again it seems to be
able to be oriented in any direction
The mathematics of quantum mechanics
and the states are...
And in particular the states of a quantum bit
are not the mathematics of a set of two points
They're not the Boolean mathematics
of a set of two points
The thing which describes...
The mathematics describes a quantum state
is a vector space
Now I use vector in a different sense
It is no longer an arrow in ordinary space
It is a mathematical abstract...
vector space
whose character you'll come to understand
if you persist and...
and persist at it a little bit
you will begin to understand
what this vector space is
and how it characterizes the possible configurations
or the possible states of an electron
and how it can be consistent with this fact here
Okay
I'm going to spend a little bit of time now
just doing some abstract mathematics
and then we'll seek to interpret it
and to interpret the state of the electron
I'm going to tell you
what a linear vector space is
what a vector space is
A vector space is a collection of objects
and here are the rules for an abstract vector space
As I said, do not confuse this
with the pointer that...
that is a vector in ordinary space
This is just an abstract, complete, abstract
mathematical abstract
an abstract, completely abstract concept
First of all, a vector is an object
and we'll label it
like that
It's an object with a set of rules
It's a collection of objects
with a rule
First of all, a rule
that any vector
can be multiplied
by a constant
to get a new vector
This gives a new vector
We could call it...
Let's call it A prime
So there's a concept of multiplication by a constant
Now, first of all, let me tell you
that the constants we're going to be talking about
are complex numbers, not real numbers
Anybody here not familiar with
the concept of a complex number?
If so, raise your hand and be humiliated
Okay
All right, now
If you really don't know what a complex number...
It may be that you
know it, but by another word
Now, if you really don't know about complex numbers
look them up
because you're going to need them
All right, a complex...
Remember this number i
i is the square root of minus one
Now, minus one has no number that's...
that's... that's... that's... who's...
There's no number, ordinary number
whose square...
whose square is minus one
So there is no square root of minus one
Any number times itself is always positive, right?
Three times three is nine
Minus three times minus three is also nine
But mathematicians many, many, many years ago
invented the abstract idea of an imaginary number
They called it imaginary
and said
Let it be that i
squared is equal to minus one
Invent a new number
Okay, we know how to use those numbers
I'm not going to...
I'm not going to spend any time at it
Whoever raised their hand
Are they familiar with i equals
the square root of minus one?
Yes
All right
Now
Let's look at complex numbers
Complex numbers are what happens if you take two...
two real numbers, ordinary numbers
Let's call it
a and b
different a
plus i b
In other words
If you add a real number
to an imaginary number
you get a complex number
That's the whole definition of a complex number
You can multiply complex numbers
So you have to remember
You use the ordinary rules of arithmetic
except you have to remember
that i squared is minus one
So for example
If you're going to...
Well, as an exercise you can square this
What's the square of a plus i b?
I won't tell you
You can work it out
All right
So that's a complex number
Often character
Often written as z
Sometimes z
You can use any letter that you like
But it's a complex number with both
a real part and an imaginary part
Another concept is the complex conjugate
This is very important
You'll need it
All right
And it's very simple
It's a minus i b
is the complex conjugate of z
So if you take a real...
If you take a complex number
and you change the sign of the imaginary part
That's called the complex conjugate of the number
The complex conjugate of the complex conjugate
gives you back the original number
These are important mathematical concepts
They're very elementary
Let me give you an example
Supposing you multiply z star by z
What is that?
That's...
Or z times z star
It doesn't matter
Either way
It's a plus i b times a minus i b
Let's see what we get
Just ordinary multiplication
We open up the brackets here
We get a times a
Which is a squared
We get a times i b with a minus sign
Minus i a b
Plus i a b
From this one times this one
And then
What about i b times i b?
What does i b times i b give?
Minus b squared
But there's a minus sign here already
So it's minus i b times i b
i times i times b
And so that gives plus b squared
All together we get a squared plus b squared
These pieces cancel
So that's an example of using
I mean that's an example
We're not using it for anything
It's just an example of a definition
And then using the definition of complex arithmetic
To calculate what z star z is
Notice that z star z is always real
And it's always positive
It's always real and positive
a squared, a and b are real numbers
a squared and b squared are both positive
So z star z is
a real number and it's positive
It's thought of more or less
as the magnitude of the complex number
Alright, so first of all
For the kind of vector spaces
we're going to be thinking about
They're called complex vector spaces
And one of the rules of one of the operations
That exists in the complex vector space
Is multiplication by a complex number
Now, a complex number includes real numbers incidentally
So you can, c could be two
Or it could be i
Or it could be two plus i
Or anything like that
There's a notion, if there's a vector
You may multiply it by a constant
And you get a new vector
That's the first operation
And there's only one other
operation that's of interest to us
It's adding vectors
There's a rule for adding vectors
Or assume there's a rule for adding vectors
So if I have two vectors, a and b
I can construct a vector called a plus b
And that's some new vector
Which I guess we can call c
But c is a different c than appears here
This c stood for constant
This c just stands for a new vector
Which is a plus b
So every pair of vectors, you can add them
And I'm going to show you
I'm going to show you some less abstract examples
But, first of all
The simplest example of a vector space like this
Is just the complex numbers themselves
The ordinary complex numbers
Allow you to multiply any
complex number by another complex number
And particularly a complex number
A particular, a constant, particular complex number
And it allows you to add complex numbers
So just complex numbers by themselves are a vector space
A complex vector space
That's the simplest example
But, let me show you another example
And the other example is
something we talked about last time
Which we called column vectors
Just represent an abstract quantity
By a set of components
All the components are themselves complex numbers
So, for every vector
Really what that vector is standing for
I write equal signs, I probably shouldn't write equals
Mathematicians would have a stroke if I wrote equals there
But, let's do that
So, the first one is
The first one is represented by a column vector
The column vector has entries
And it's just a table of numbers
But, it's a table of complex numbers
Right?
It's a table of complex numbers
Supposing you want to multiply that column vector here
By a constant
The rule is very simple
Multiply every entry by that constant
So, let's say that column A
Is represented by
C A1, C A2, C A3
We just multiply all the components by the same number
That's multiplication by a constant
How do we add two vectors together?
Let's suppose we have two vectors, A and B
A is represented by the column
Whose entries are A1, A2, A3
whose entries are A1, A2, A3
A is represented by the column
B is represented by B1, B2, B3
Where these are
A's and B's are just numbers
And when we add them
We just get a third column vector
Whose entries are A1 plus B1
A2 plus B2
A3 plus B3
So, column vectors are an example of a vector space
And they are the basic example
That we will use over and over again
As I said, mathematicians would have a stroke
If I called the columns vectors
They would say the columns represent vectors
And you would call these the components
Or a set of components of a vector
Okay, that's the idea of an abstract vector space
The very strange thing is that
the states of a quantum system
In particular, a quantum bit
Oh, incidentally
You're not restricted to three
This is a particular case
This is a three-dimensional vector space
We could have a two-dimensional vector space
That's actually going to be more
interesting to us for the moment
A two-dimensional vector space just has two entries
That's the next simplest thing, if you like
To the numbers
The next simplest vector space
is a two-dimensional vector space
Then there's a three-dimensional vector space
And a four-dimensional vector space
And so forth
And they all make sense
Okay
That's
And you'll get used to this
Sooner or later you'll start thinking
in terms of abstract vector spaces
If you pursue this subject
There's no way to learn
quantum mechanics honestly and correctly
Without going through this mathematics
So it's absolutely essential
Now
If we were talking about the simplest vector space
Just complex numbers
Then every complex number has its complex conjugate
That means
That there is a second vector space
Which is the space of the complex conjugate numbers
That the concept of complex conjugation
Is an important concept
And it also exists
For other vector spaces
All you have to do basically
Is write the complex conjugate of the entries
But
A rule
When you're writing the complex conjugate of a vector
I want to write the
complex conjugate of the vector A
You draw it the other way
This way
That stands for the complex conjugate
Of the vector A
And furthermore
You represent it
By a row vector
The components of the row vector
Are the complex conjugates
A1 star
A2 star
So whenever you see a row vector
Always think of it
As the complex conjugate
Of the corresponding
Column vector
If I tell you there's
A row vector A
Which is in correspondence
With a column vector A
Always remember that there's a complex conjugation operation
Okay
This is the basic idea of a complex vector space
Written out in components
Everybody happy with that?
Anybody?
There's no asterisk at the A
In that
No
Usually
That's right
The notation does not
Put a star over here
But you remember
That the star is implicit
In turning the symbol backward
Now I'll remind you
This symbol is called a ket
No this symbol is called a bra
Do I have it right?
I don't
I never
One of them's a bra
One of them's a ket
But it doesn't matter
It's completely symmetric between the two
Remember that the complex conjugate of a complex conjugate
Is the original thing
So that's
That's
The notion of a complex vector space
And finally
Not finally
But
We want to put the pieces together
You can multiply
Two vectors
The product
Is called
We've discussed this before
I realize
I'm not getting senile
I know I've talked about this before
But we need
We really need to do it right now
There's the concept of the inner product
Of the inner product
Of the inner product of two vectors
The inner product of two vectors
The easiest way for me to describe it
Is in terms of components
I don't want to spend a lot of time
Giving you the most abstract definition
Are there any mathematicians in the audience?
Plug your ears
Just plug them up
And
Right
Alright
The
Actually
I'm going to
Actually mathematicians also use components
But
I think
Anyway
The next
Concept
Is the concept of the product of two vectors
But it's always
It's the inner product of the two vectors
And the concept is
Really
The product of a vector
With the complex conjugate of another vector
It's very much
Like
Multiplying a complex number
By the complex
By the complex number
By the complex conjugate of another number
Could be the same number
Could be another number
So I'm going to give you the rule
The rule I'm going to tell you
In terms of components
Okay
Here's the rule
If I want
The inner product
Between the vector b
And the vector a
And it's written like that
It's got a bra ket
That's a bracket
Okay
That's where the term bra ket came from
And it's written like that
It's got a bra ket
That's where the term ket came from
Half a bracket is a bra
The other half of the vector is a ket
And again I forget which one is which
This is the ket right?
Correct
Yeah that's the ket
This one's the bra
Okay good
Good
The rule is
You take the two vectors
The b vector
Is a row vector
And you write b1 star
b2 star
That's the representation of the b vector
And the representation of the a vector
Is a1 a2
You do not star it
And the inner product between them
This product is gotten
By multiplying the first component
Of b
With the first component of a
b1 star a1
Plus b2 star a2
First row with first
Sorry
First entry here
With first entry here
Plus second entry here
Second entry here
Supposing for example
Okay everybody
That's the basic concept of the inner product
It's just like multiplying two numbers together
Except we get a term
For each entry
The one entry and the two entry
For example
If we take the inner
product of a vector with itself
Let's take a with a
The inner product of a vector with itself
Has the form a1 a2
A1 star a1
Plus a2 star a2
Notice one thing about this
A number times its complex conjugate is
First of all positive
And second of all real
Well it couldn't hardly be positive if it weren't real
It's a positive number
So the sum
So the inner product
Of a complex vector with itself
Is always a real positive number
It can be thought of
As a kind of size of a vector
It's actually the square of the size of a vector
If you like
You can think of it as the
square of the size of a vector
The length of the vector
It measures the magnitude of the vector
So this operation
Of inner product
Is absolutely essential as we'll see
To the interpretation
And it's complex vectors like this
Which represent the states of a quantum bit
Let me just digress
Let me stop doing mathematics for a minute
And talk about the quantum bit again
The quantum bit
Could be pointing straight up
We could invent a symbol
For the state
For the configuration
Of the electron pointing up
Let's call it
We could either call it up
Or we could call it
A little vector up
Or we could just call it plus
I think I'll just call it plus
To indicate that it's pointing upward
Or we can have an electron which is pointing down
Now remember
When we go to measure the electron
We either find that it's up or down
And nothing in between
And that we can identify
With the vector minus
Just an abstract notation
This stands for the state of an electron pointing up
This stands for the state of an electron pointing down
Now in classical physics
We would never under any circumstances
Think of adding these two vectors
Or multiplying them by numbers
We would just say
This means electron up
This means electron down
In quantum physics
The general state of an electron
Or an electron spin
Is a vector in a vector space
Which we could write
A plus
Times plus
Plus A minus
Times minus
In other words
It's a two dimensional vector space
We could also represent it
By A plus
A minus
And here's the rule
The rule
So there are some coefficients
That we can add them together with
And here's the meaning of those coefficients
Or at least the partial meaning of those coefficients
A plus star
A plus
Is the probability
That we find the electron up
Remember it's positive
It's positive
And it's real
A star times A
Is positive and it's real
And it's the magnitude
Of the
Or it's the square of the magnitude
Of the coefficient
Of the up configuration
And then there's the down configuration
The probability of finding the electron down
Is A minus
Times A star minus
That's the probability to find it down
That's the interpretation
Or that's part of the interpretation
Just to give you some orientation
Where we're going
The quantum state
Of that electron
Which when we measure it
We find with a probabilistic distribution
Is either up or down
And nothing in between
That's represented by saying the electron
When it's pointing in some function
When it's pointing in some funny angle
Is given by a complex vector
Complex vector space
Which can either be represented abstractly like this
It can be represented concretely
As a column vector
And
The square or magnitude
Of the square of the entries here
Are simply the probabilities
To find it up or down
Now presumably probabilities add to one
So one of the rules about quantum mechanics
Is that the vectors that represent
That we have a vector space of some kind
An abstract vector space
But the vectors which actually represent
The physical states of a system
Are
The word is normalized
Normalized means
That the sum of the probabilities is one
So A plus star
A plus
Plus A minus star
A minus
Should be set equal to one
This is like considering
Only vectors of unit length
That doesn't mean
That in the vector space itself
There aren't other vectors
Of other magnitude
There are
But the physical states of a quantum system
Have to be normalized
Which is the same thing as setting the sums
Of the probabilities to one
So normalized vectors in a vector space
Represent the states of a quantum system
Now that's a very abstract concept
Why do we get driven to such very abstract concepts?
Why can't we visualize this the same way
We visualize classical physics?
Well it's because
We don't have the wiring
And we have to rewire ourselves
To learn to think about
the quantum states of a system
Being an abstract vector space
Once you get this idea
Of an abstract vector space
And how
It fits together with the states of a system
Then you're flying
And you can understand all of quantum mechanics
So any questions about this?
The entries
The coefficients
Or equivalently the components of the vector
When you square them
Or better yet
When you multiply them by their own complex conjugate
Give you the probabilities
For the two possibilities
Yeah
So the expression of a quantum represents a quantum state
That represents a quantum state if a star a
If a
In fact we can say it this way
The inner product of a with itself
That's given by a plus star a plus
Plus a minus star a minus
That should be one
So legitimate quantum states
Should have inner product with themselves
Which is equal to one
And that's just a statement
That's just a statement that the sums of the probabilities
Of all the probabilities should add up to one
Where is your
Or what looks like a column
vector a plus and a minus
Oh plus and minus are now just to indicate
That one of them corresponds to spin up
And the other corresponds to spin down
And we could have called them
We could have given them different names
I could have called them a up and a down
Or I could have called
them a one and a two
So they don't have any relationship with
the ket plus and the ket minus
They do have
They are the coefficients of the
ket plus and the ket minus
Okay so let's go back a step
What about the ket plus
How should we represent that
Well in a good basis it's one zero
In some basis let's
At the moment I don't want to discuss the
The ambiguity in basis vectors
We'll come to that
But for the moment we have a basis
Don't worry if you don't know what I'm talking about
This vector will be represented by one zero
Okay
It'll be represented by a one in the upper place
And a zero in the lower place
What about the minus ket
The minus ket is represented
by a zero and a one
Okay
This is just some arbitrary correspondence
Now then if I multiply this by a plus
The numerical constant a plus
Then we have to multiply this by a plus
We don't have to multiply zero by a plus
Because zero times anything is zero
If we multiply this by a minus
Then this becomes a minus here
And if we add them together
A plus times the plus ket
Plus a minus times the minus ket
We just add these together
And we get
Adding them
Gives us a plus a minus
Okay
Does that answer the question that was asked
Yeah
Okay
So yes we certainly
The plus and minus ket
Is represented by a plus and a minus
And the minus ket is represented by a plus
So we can use this notation
Instead of one and two
Here I used one and two
They're just labels
One and two is just a label
To label the two entries
I could have used up and down
I could have used Joe and Pete
I could have used anything I want
To label them
Here I'm using plus and minus
The two possibilities
For the orientation of the electron
Of the electron or of the quantum bit
Plus and minus
Good
Okay
So now we have a
A basic concept of a vector space
The inner product
Question
Does minus ket plus make sense
Say it again louder
Sorry
Say it louder I couldn't hear you
Does minus ket plus make sense
The minus ket
Minus one minus plus
No the minus ket is not
minus one times the plus ket
No no no no no no
I know that it also makes sense
I know that they're different
but does that also make sense
Oh yes
You're asking whether
The
Whether this object makes sense
Yes
You're allowed to take any vector
and multiply it by any complex number
In particular a complex number is minus one
In fact
But your interpretation was that
But this is not
It is not the same as minus
Right
This has a
Okay let's make that clear
The minus here does not mean
that it's minus the plus vector
It's just a label
No more than A2
No more than A3
A2 means twice A1
Yeah
You said the probability of this
thing in a state is the
The A plus dot plus
A plus right
So minus plus ket and ket both represent states
where you have probability one in the plus states
Yes that's correct
That's correct
Oh no
The minus ket is probability one in the minus state
Wait wait
This ket here has probability one in the plus state
So if we don't minus
sign we also have probably one
Which one which one there
If we remove the minus we also have
That's right
Both of these
That's right absolutely absolutely we're going to come to
that very good very good very good very good
You're pointing out something that I was
about to come to in a moment
I'll tell it to you right now
Well okay if I multiply it
by any complex number of magnitude one
That's right that's correct that's correct
So physically we would not
distinguish this state from this state
I won't write equals because in
the mathematical vector space they're not equal
But they represent the same physics
However however when I add them A plus
and minus A minus are not the same
That is a different state alright that is
a different state with a minus sign here
But we'll come to that we'll come to that it
was something I was going to talk about but not yet
I want you to digest just the idea that the
components of the state of the equation are not the same
Components of these abstract vectors
when squared correspond to probabilities
Does it make physical sense to change the minus
ket to a bra and multiply those two together
Yes
So let's let's tell me I think you're asking
whether it makes sense to take the ket vector plus
And consider
What I'll call its conjugate
which is the bra vector plus
In this case the there's no change because the
Well except that you were writing as a row
Right
What about the inner product
The components don't change
That's right in this case in this case right
Because one is a real number
we don't have the complex conjugated
Okay so here's a
Little exercise
What's the inner product of the plus vector with itself
One
One because it's just multiplying one zero times one zero
One times one is one
So this is one
What about minus minus
Also equal to one
What about
The inner product of
Plus with minus
Let's just check that for those who don't
see it so quickly let's just check it
The plus
Bra
Is one zero
The minus ket
Is zero one
All right so when we multiply them together we get
one times zero plus zero times one which is altogether zero
All right
What about minus plus
Also zero
What's the word for two
vectors whose inner product is zero
Orthogonal
They're
Called orthogonal vectors
So the two vectors representing the two distinct
states of the electron one up and one down
Are two orthogonal vectors
In a
Linear vector space of states
Okay that's the basic setup
Uh
And the coefficients that appear there
Their squared magnitudes
Are the probabilities of the constant homeostasis
for the two configurations, the
probability for up and for down.
Now, as you can see, there are more
possible physical states than just up and down.
There are all the linear combinations.
It's the linear combinations of them
that correspond to the electron point
having been prepared in different directions.
So in other words, an arbitrary combination like this,
with an A plus and an A minus there,
when this is not 1 and 0 or 0
and 1, correspond when you consider all the possible complex
numbers to the different directions that
you might have prepared the electron.
But still, all there is is up and
down and the probabilities for up and down.
So a state, for example,
let me give you an example.
A vector, let's write 1 in both slots.
That's not allowed.
Why isn't that allowed?
Probability doesn't add to 1.
So the probability would add to 2 here.
1 squared plus 1 squared is 2.
We have to divide it by square root of 2.
Now each of the probabilities is a
half, and they add up to 1.
What about parentheses or something?
Parentheses where?
What doesn't make sense inside of a cat.
You're right.
I meant to write the column.
That's a state.
So you have an equal probability, namely
probability a half to find the electron up,
and now this one has probability
a half to find the electron down.
There are more states than just up and down.
And in fact, this one corresponds to what
you would create if you created the electron
pointing in the horizontal direction.
If with a magnetic field in
the horizontal direction, you froze the electron.
Let's take a break.
If you put the electron into place
with a magnetic field in the horizontal direction,
in the horizontal plane, one of
the possibilities would be this state here,
which would have half a probability of being
up and half a probability of being down.
Half the probability of up and half the
probability of being down actually corresponds to some
configuration where the electron is
lying somewhere in the horizontal plane.
So we have plenty of vectors around with
all kinds of complex numbers out of which we
can build, and we'll see that we can do
this, we can build the space of electrons which
in some sense are pointing in any direction,
but whenever we measure them, all we get is
up or down with probabilities
that are governed by these coefficients.
Let's take a break for seven
minutes, seven minutes and thirty seconds.
All right.
Now more than one person is probably a
little bit confused about the two notions of vectors.
One is having to do with directionality in
ordinary space, and one having to do with
this abstract concept and this notion of components
of vectors labeling up state and down state.
The question is what's the connection between
the notion of directionality in the horizontal
plane space and these vectors here.
Now what I want to say first
of all is they are not simply related.
They are related but not simply related.
For example, how many components does
a vector have, an ordinary vector?
Three.
And they're real numbers, right?
X, Y, and Z.
They're all real numbers.
These vectors have two
components and they're complex numbers.
That means how many real numbers does
it take to describe one of them?
Four.
All right.
So they're not the same thing.
But there must be some connection.
We're not going to do that connection just yet.
But we will come to it.
Next concept, which we already went into a
little last time, is the concept of a matrix.
Question.
How do you know what vector
space describes other deeper quantum galaxies?
Okay.
It's an experimental question, in a sense.
From the fact that there are only two possible
answers to the way that when you do this experiment
on the electron, you either get that
it's up or down and nothing in between.
Okay.
That tells you that there are two possibilities
and it tells you that you should be dealing
with a two-dimensional vector space.
All two-dimensional complex vector
spaces are mathematically the same.
So they're all the same.
A two-dimensional complex vector space
is a two-dimensional complex vector space.
There's not more than one of them mathematically.
So...
So you count up the number of possibilities.
Somebody asked me before if I had to spin
one particle instead of a spin a half particle,
which is what an electron is,
how many components would there be?
Then there would be three.
But it's an experimental question.
How many possibilities are there?
How many states are there?
How many distinct possibilities are there?
And in the case of the electron spin, in
the case of the spin of the electron, there are
two possibilities.
One is that the electron is a two-dimensional vector space.
And so it's a two-dimensional vector space.
And they're all the same.
There's no distinction between
different two-dimensional vector spaces.
Other than the fact that we
could consider real or complex vector spaces.
Okay.
Let's move on to the concept, to the
abstract concept of a linear operator or the concrete
of a matrix.
Let me tell you where we're going.
We've talked about states, but we haven't
talked about the things that you actually
measure.
The things that you measure or that
you can measure are called the observables.
The observables of a system are the things
that you can measure and get answers for.
Position of an electron is an observable.
But we're not doing anything as complicated as that.
If we were to label the up and the down
state as plus and minus, we could invent an observable
which would have two possible values.
It could either be plus, plus one or minus one.
And it would be an observable that we could measure.
If the electron's up, we will
assign it the number plus one.
If it's down, we'll assign it the number minus one.
Also called an observable.
Anything that we can measure that has a numerical value.
Numerical value means a real number.
Anything that we can measure that when
the measurement is recorded, it gives rise to
a number, a numerical number, is called an observable.
So as I said, in the case of the
electron spin, if we measure the, whether it's up or
down, we could assign up the number
plus one and down the number minus one.
And in that way have an observable
which, whose numerical value when we measure it
is either plus one or minus one.
Let me talk about, before
talking about observables and quantum mechanics,
let's talk about observables for a
minute in classical mechanics, in classical theory.
In classical theory, the states of a system,
are just a set of
states which we represented by points.
How many do we have?
One, two, three, four, five, six.
These could be the six possibilities for
throwing a dice, a die, a single die.
The one, two, three, four, five, six. This is it.
And we could assign
some numbers to each one of these states.
So we could call, we could label
this one one, two, three, four, five, six.
We throw the die and we
look at it. That's the measurement.
We throw the die and we look
at it and we get an answer.
The answer is either one,
two, three, four, five, or six.
That measurement is the measurement of an observable,
and it's an observable which has six possible answers.
There are other observables that we could concoct.
For example, we could concoct
an observable which is zero everywheres,
except at one value.
One, zero, zero, zero, zero.
Zero.
Now, this means that if we flip the die,
and we get a one,
we assign the number one to the observable.
If we get any other number, we
assign the value zero to the observable.
So there are many different ways to do this.
So there are many observables that you can make,
and basically they correspond to
any functions of these points.
Any functions of these points
assign any function to the points.
Function of points means assign any numbers
you like to these points, real numbers.
And then when you flip the die,
and you see what comes up,
you say the value of the
observable is whatever the numerical value
of that observable was when you flipped the die.
There are many, many observables that you can think about
in this simple system.
But they're all rather trivial.
I mean, they just correspond to
the basic question of whether the die
is one, two, three, four, five, or six.
Interesting just not because...
Yes, it is interesting to define the observable
as a function of which state we're talking about.
F sub n.
n here represents which of these states we're talking about,
and f is a function which could
be any number for each of these states.
That's called an observable.
When you flip a die,
you look at what you get,
and you assign the number f to the particular state.
F sub 1, f sub 2, through f sub 6.
That's called an observable.
And it's a sort of overkill
concept in this classical situation here,
but let's continue.
Now, let us suppose that for one reason or another,
in classical physics,
we haven't been very careful in doing our classical physics,
measurements and so forth,
and we don't know exactly
what state the system is in.
All we know is some probabilities.
For example, we may have a loaded die,
a loaded die which is an unfair die,
like the kind dirty gamblers use,
and you flip it,
and it lands on the table.
There may be a probability distribution
for different values of the one,
two, three, four, five, or six.
Let's label that p sub n also.
That's the probability,
the a priori probability, let's say,
that when you flip the die,
you get the nth state.
Then, what is the average
if you flip the die many, many times,
and each time you measure f,
you flip it many, many times,
you measure f,
what is the average value of f, f sub n?
There are many, many, many identical experiments.
The answer, anybody know?
Well, the answer for the average value of f,
we're assuming, of course,
that the sum of the p sub n's is one.
In other words, the sum of the probabilities of one.
The average value of f is
the sum over all the possibilities
of the probability for the nth configuration
times the value that the
function has in the nth configuration.
So what you do is
you add up all the configurations
weighted according to their probability.
Weight them according to their probability.
For example,
if all the probabilities are equal,
then you just add up the f sub n's.
If they're all equal, incidentally,
they're not one, they're one over n,
because they're one over the number,
one over six in this case.
But this is the average over many, many,
let's take an example.
Let's do a coin, a simple coin,
up or down, heads or tails.
Let's say there's the probability for heads,
and we're going to call heads plus.
There's the probability for heads, which is p plus.
There's the probability for tails, which is p minus.
If we have heads,
we assign the number plus one.
If we have tails, we assign the number minus one.
What is the probability for that observable,
which is either plus one or minus one?
It's p plus,
the probability for plus,
minus the probability for minus.
Because every time you get a minus,
you give it a value minus one.
In other words, every time you get a tail,
you give it a minus one.
Every time you get a head,
you give it a plus one.
The average is p plus minus p minus.
The difference between the probability of head and tail
is the average of the headsness or the tailsness.
So this basic formula here,
which is just the most elementary
formula of probability of the notion of an average,
that you average over all the possibilities,
weighing it with the value
of the quantity of the observable,
whose average you're taking,
and you weigh it according to the probability
of that particular configuration.
And that's the average value
of an experiment which consists
of many, many repeated experiments.
What's that?
Expected value, sometimes called the expected value,
sometimes called the expectation value,
sometimes called the average value.
And that's what we're going to be interested in.
We're going to be interested in the average values
of things that we can measure,
the average values of observables.
Now, what I haven't told you
is how you represent observables in quantum mechanics.
And the representation of observables
in quantum mechanics is more intricate and complicated
than just saying we assign to each state
a numerical value that we call
the observable value in that state.
It's a more complicated concept
and a more tricky concept,
the notion of an observable,
or measurable,
measurable quantity.
And it's related, not related, but is,
well, related, related to
the concept of a linear operator
or a matrix.
For our purposes, they're the same thing.
Again, the mathematicians will object to me saying
a matrix is a linear operator.
I don't know, do you object?
Anybody object to my saying
a matrix is a linear operator?
There is a question over there.
What?
Somebody had the same thing.
Can I just, in this example,
if f of plus is one
and f of minus is minus one,
the expectation value, though, is zero?
If the probabilities are equal.
Yeah, yeah.
Let's say the probability is equal.
My point is that it's,
the expectation value ends up being
a number that is,
that the underlying system is never in that state.
Oh, that's true.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, right.
That's why people don't like calling it
the expected value because
it is the,
it is a value which is very definitely not expected.
So I,
everybody used to call it the expectation value.
Now, that's a little,
that's a little weaker than saying the expected value.
Then my friend Murray Gelman started calling it
the expected value.
Well, it ain't, as you point out,
It's worse than that because you have to divide by,
you really have to divide by n.
That's a problem.
No, no, the sums of
the p's add up to one.
Assuming the sums of the p's add up to one.
Okay.
But when you think of it as dividing by
the overall sample size.
Yeah.
In this case it's one.
Yeah, that's what it means.
The p is a half and a half.
That means that you end up with the typical person
having two and a half kids or whatever.
No.
That would be shortening.
Right, so it's not the,
it's not really the expected.
You know, you have to guess how many kids
you're gonna have.
You probably wouldn't guess two and a half.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
It's a payoff.
In the gambling you can actually line up with zero.
I mean, it's a, so it's a value you get.
It just doesn't correspond to the point.
Right.
But it is the average value.
It's by definition the average value.
Okay.
So that's right.
So if, I'm glad you pointed that out,
that if p plus and
p minus were both a half,
then the average value would be zero,
but zero is not a possible answer.
So the average value is not the expected value.
There is no expected value in this case.
But it tells you something.
If you get something at zero in your average value,
it tells you that there's a
lot of divergence in the simple state.
Say it again?
It tells you that there's a lot of divergence.
Divergence?
There's a lot of,
there's a lot of divergence.
The variance is too wide, huh?
Well, if I take a coin and I flip it,
a fair coin and I flip it,
I think I will get half the
times heads and half the times tails.
You said something about,
did you say something about temperature?
Variance.
I mean, in the case of coin tossing,
of course it tells you that it's a 50-50% chance.
Yeah.
Yeah, it tells you,
it tells you you're basically completely ignorant.
If you're completely ignorant, there's a 50-50 chance.
And if you do the experiment
over and over with a fair coin
and you average the result,
the average had better be zero because it can't be,
it can't be positive and it can't
be negative because it's an equal balance.
On the other hand,
if you have an unfair coin,
let's say three quarters of
the time it comes up heads
and one quarter of the times it comes up tails,
then the average is what?
It's three quarters minus one quarter,
which is a half.
All right?
So if you have this unfair coin,
which three quarters of the time comes up heads,
one quarter comes up tails,
then the average is a half.
All right?
Again, doesn't mean that you can measure a half.
It just means that that's the average value.
Okay?
Average values are important.
Let me give you one observable,
one kind of observable,
which is special.
Supposing I take this special class of observables,
which is one at one state,
f is one for one state over here
and zero for all the others.
What's the average value of it?
Just the probability.
Right.
So if I had an observable,
which I invented,
which was one at one
place and zero every place else,
then there would be only one term in the sum,
because f is zero for all the others,
and for the one case where it's not zero,
we just get p.
So if you knew the rules for calculating averages,
you would also know the rules for calculating,
for all possible observables,
you would also immediately know
the rules for calculating probabilities.
Now the way to say it is,
if you know how to calculate
the average value of any observable,
you can reconstruct from it the probability distribution,
the probabilities for that observable,
probabilities for the different possibilities.
So that raises the question now,
what is the mathematical representation of observables?
And that is matrices.
Matrices or linear operators.
So let's talk again a little bit about matrices and,
where am I?
I don't know where I am.
Let's talk about observables,
or let's talk about matrices first.
A matrix is a thing that
you can multiply a vector with,
or act on a vector with.
It does something to a vector.
It's an operation on a vector.
But it's not just any old operation on the vector.
It's a linear operation.
I'm not going to explain that,
because we won't need to explain it.
But whatever it is,
call it M,
M for matrix,
and in the abstract notation,
it's a thing,
it's an object,
which you multiply a vector by,
and you get a new vector.
For example, one simple example is
just multiplying by a complex number.
Multiplying by a complex number is a operator.
It's a very simple operator.
You just multiply the vector,
and you get the number 2.
The number 2 just takes
every vector and doubles its size.
Okay?
But the general operators that we're going to consider
are ones which are represented by matrices.
So if we have our vector A,
which we represent by a column vector,
and I'm only going to write two-dimensional column vectors,
but you'll immediately deduce what to do
if you have a few more in your mind.
So let's do a few more entries here.
We can multiply it by a matrix,
and a matrix is a square array of numbers,
M11, M12, M21, M22.
And in general, these numbers are all complex numbers.
In general, they're all complex numbers.
The A's and the M's in a complex vector space
can all be complex numbers.
And the rule for matrix multiplication,
which I showed us last time,
for multiplying a matrix by a vector,
is just,
if you want the top entry,
which you can think of as the top row,
you take the top row,
and you multiply it by the vector.
You take the inner product of
the top row with the vector,
which will be M11A1
plus M12A2,
and then down here,
M21A1 plus M22A2.
So it's another vector.
I had to draw it pretty wide
because I was adding some numbers here,
but it's just a vector.
It's a column vector with one column,
and it's constructed by taking this row
times the column,
and this row times the column,
and those are the two entries.
That's it.
That's all that matrices are.
Let me give you a couple of examples,
a couple of simple examples
from a very ordinary vector space.
A very ordinary vector space
is just the pointers or the arrows
that you can draw on the blackboard.
You can multiply a vector by,
in this case, a real number.
You can double it, you can triple it,
you can multiply it by minus one,
and you can add two vectors.
So vectors that you draw on the blackboard
are a vector space.
Let me give you, and they have,
what are their components?
Their components are the x component,
here's x, here's y,
and the vector has an x component
and a y component.
So we represent this vector
by its x component and its y component,
and we could write it in the form
x component of vector,
y component of the vector.
Of course, now I'm only doing
two dimensions,
so I'm going to do
a two-dimensional space.
These would be real numbers
on the blackboard.
They wouldn't be complex numbers,
and this would be a two-real-dimensional vector space.
Now, let's think about some operations.
The first interesting operation,
which is the most easy,
is to stretch the vector space.
For example, multiply every vector by two.
Okay?
Multiply every vector by two
will sort of magnify the whole space
by a factor of two.
Any vector will get stretched out
to twice its original length.
That's all that happens.
Here's the matrix
that represents that operation.
It's just the diagonal matrix 2, 2.
Diagonal means that its entries
are along the diagonal.
There are two diagonals in the matrix.
This is called the principal diagonal,
I think, if I remember.
The other one is called
the unprincipled diagonal.
I don't know what it's called.
I don't know.
What?
Degenerate.
The good diagonal and the bad diagonal.
This one is the bad diagonal.
All right.
Let's just calculate what we get.
In the upper entry,
we get 2 times vx plus 0.
So the upper entry just becomes 2vx.
The lower entry,
we get 2 times vy.
So, as advertised,
this is the operator,
which simply doubles the length of every vector.
All right.
Very easy.
Here's a more,
almost a similar thing.
But supposing I just wanted to
double the y component.
What would that do to the vector space?
It would take every vector
and stretch out its y component
by a factor of 2
without stretching out its x component.
So it would be a stretch in the y direction
by a factor of 2,
but no stretch in the y direction
but in the x direction.
How would we represent that?
Okay.
Again, a diagonal with a 1 here
in the x place, in the xx,
and the yy place, the factor 2.
Let's check it.
1 times vx gives us vx.
2 times vy gives us twice vy.
So that's a stretching of the vector space
in the y direction.
Likewise, we could put the 2 here,
and the 1 here.
And the 1 here,
that would be a stretching of the vector space
which stretches it out in this direction.
One or two more.
These are very easy examples.
So far, they've only involved diagonal matrices.
Let me give you another one.
The matrix which corresponds to
rotating every vector by 90 degrees.
Take any vector
and rotate it by 90 degrees.
In other words, this is the operation
which rotates the plane by 90 degrees.
I'll tell you what it is,
and then we'll check and
see if we can see why.
It's off-diagonal.
Or...
1 minus 1, excuse me.
Oh, let's do this one first.
Let's do what this is.
Before I do the rotation,
let's do this.
Let's see what this does.
This takes 0 times vx,
1 times vy.
It interchanges vy and vx.
Anybody see geometrically what that corresponds to?
A reflection.
It's a reflection of the vector space
about this diagonal.
Takes every vector
and reflects it about that diagonal.
Just flips it about that diagonal.
That's this matrix.
Here's another matrix
where you put a minus 1 down here.
What does this give?
This gives vy minus vx.
vy minus vx.
It interchanges the x and y,
but then throws in a
minus sign for one of them.
That is an operation.
I'm going to leave it to you to prove
because we don't have time,
but I'm going to tell you what this does.
It rotates the vector space by 90 degrees.
Oh, does it go the other way?
It's an easy way to see all this.
Well, you know it.
It's going to rotate the other direction.
It negated it, so...
Yeah.
You negated the...
The y component.
It rotates every vector by 90 degrees.
Just the y component.
What's that?
Rotating it around the x axis.
The y component.
The x component is going into minus...
Right.
So where's the x?
The vector pointing in the x direction
is going into minus the vector pointing in the y.
So which way is it?
So what's it doing?
It's rotating by 90 degrees.
No, but 180 degrees.
Clockwise.
Oh, clock...
Rotating clockwise.
Yeah.
That's what I drew here.
It rotates the vector by 90 degrees.
So you see, what matrices correspond
to is they correspond to a...
Transformations of the vector space.
Stretchings, rotations, more complicated kinds of things.
Another example would be a shear.
A shear...
This is interesting to try to work out
the matrix that corresponds to a shear motion.
Let me tell you what a shear motion is.
A shear motion ish.
What a shear motion ish.
A shear motion takes every...
Well, it...
Oh, boy.
Slides stuff this way.
Okay?
So it slides you to the right by
an amount proportional to how high you are.
It takes every point and shifts it to the
right by an amount proportional to how high you are.
Okay?
to how high you are. There's a
matrix that describes that motion. Deforms the plane,
tilts this axis over, is what it does. I'm
not going to write that one out. I'll see
if you can find it the next time I'll
tell you what the answer is for a shear motion.
But in general, matrices correspond to
transformations, special transformations. Not all transformations
are represented as matrices. These are
the linear transformations, to be specific. But
these are the ones we're going to be interested
in. And we're going to be interested in a
special class of them. Now this is very abstract,
and for the moment you will not see why. This
is just definition. But I've got to give
you some mathematics and then intersperse it with
some physics. I'm going to give you the mathematics
today, and next time I'm going to show you
what the point is. There's a notion of
a Hermitian matrix. The notion of a Hermitian matrix
corresponds to the notion of a real number.
It's a kind of concept of reality versus imaginary,
but it doesn't mean that the entries are all real.
What it means, is that if you take an
element of the matrix, Mij. That's some element of
the matrix. It could be some big matrix, I
don't know how big it is, and it's somewhere
over here. And then there's Mji. Mji is
the reflected matrix element. If this is M12,
it would be over here.
then M21 would be over here.
M35 might be over here.
M53 would be over here.
So interchanging rows and columns
is a kind of reflection of
the matrix about the diagonal here.
A Hermitian matrix is one that, if you reflect it,
complex conjugates.
In other words, Mij is equal to Mji star.
If this matrix was just a number,
let's just take a case of numbers.
And I tell you I have a number
which is equal to its own complex conjugate.
What does that tell you about the number?
That it's real.
That it has no imaginary part.
Now, for a matrix, that's not what it says.
It doesn't say that the entries are real,
but it's a kind of reality property.
Let me give you some examples
of matrices.
One which is Hermitian.
Does everybody know how to spell Hermitian?
H-E-R-M-I-T-I-A-N
A-E-S-H-U-N
Hermitian.
H-E-R-M-I-T-I-A-N
Okay.
Some people respond to it.
Would you mind writing it up for us?
Yeah.
No, I wouldn't mind.
I don't know.
When you say some people write it
with an E, it's kind of weird.
E-A-N.
E-A-N?
In England, of course.
It's a real place.
What?
Hermite ends with E.
Yeah.
Hermite is a kind of little bug.
It eats.
That might be polynomial.
Yeah.
Right.
That's right.
It eats polynomials.
Okay.
In other words, when you flip
it, you get the complex conjugate.
Here's some examples.
Oh, oh.
That says one thing.
It says the diagonal elements are real.
Because M11.
What does it say?
It says,
M11 is M star 11.
If you flip the rows and columns
on the diagonal, you get the same answer.
For example, I equals 1, J equals 1.
M11 equals M11 star.
So first of all, it
says the diagonal elements are real.
Real numbers here.
Seven and three.
But then it says that
the off-diagonal elements are complex conjugates.
So here's a matrix, for example, that is not Hermitian.
Four and two.
That's not Hermitian because two is
not the complex conjugate of four.
All right?
This is Hermitian.
Four is the complex conjugate of four.
So if a matrix is real
and it's Hermitian, it's also symmetric.
But here's another one which is Hermitian.
Hermitian.
Four plus I.
And four minus I.
Four plus I is the
complex conjugate of four minus I.
So this is the notion of a Hermitian matrix.
And now I'm going to tell you
that we're going to find next time,
or we're going to postulate next time,
that Hermitian matrices are
the quantum version of observables.
The classical version of observables,
functions,
of the state points.
The quantum version of an observable,
a Hermitian operator,
which means a Hermitian matrix for the moment.
That's where we're going.
Yeah?
What you'd like to do is you'd
like to kick this vector with that matrix
and it's the state of the electron system.
And, well, some of the probabilities is one.
Some?
Is this?
It's not so that we can kick it or...
This is...
No.
When you kick an electron,
you want to kick it with a unitary operator,
not with a Hermitian operator.
What's that?
You come to it.
Okay.
I'll tell you this.
What a unitary operator is,
is one which doesn't change the length of any vector,
which is what I think what you were asking about.
Yeah, one of the vectors.
Right.
A Hermitian operator does not have that property in general.
So a unitary matrix is
one which doesn't change the length,
and it's the result of an operation
that you actually do to the electron.
You kick it, you hit
it, you do something to it.
I'll tell you very quickly now.
Well, no, I won't bother telling you
because we'll get into it next time.
Matrices, or more generally, linear operators,
are the basic quantum concept of the observable,
the thing that you can measure.
And we're going to then discuss
what kind of...
What kind of matrices correspond to the z component,
the up-down component of the spin?
What kind correspond to the x component of the spin?
What kind correspond to the y component?
What kind of observable, what kind of matrix
corresponds to the component of the spin
along some arbitrary direction?
And so we're going to see then
that there's a connection between
these vectors, matrices, and so forth,
and real directions of space,
but that's going to take some time.
It'll take some space,
and we're going to go through some,
a little more pieces.
Without all of this,
there's no way that you can understand honestly
what entanglement is,
what Bell's inequalities mean,
what the basic setup of quantum mechanics is.
So it's more...
If I had my way,
I would love to be able to teach this
without all this mathematics,
but I can't.
There's no way.
So you want it honestly,
you want it correctly,
you want the basic ingredients
that go into quantum mechanics.
We have to go through,
we have to go through this bit of mathematics.
Once we're through it,
our mission operators, vectors, and so forth,
then the rest is kind of smooth sailing.
It's relatively easy stuff,
but so far we've had to spend more time
on mathematics than I might have liked.
Good.
Okay.
The preceding program is copyrighted
by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.