This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
We won't get to Bell's theorem, but that's okay.
We can do that next week.
I hope we get to entanglement.
All right, but we were in the midst of still,
entanglement has to do with what happens,
the simplest case of it is when
you have two electrons with their spins.
Forget the fact that electrons can move around,
just worry about their spins.
Entanglement is what happens when
you have more than one system
and the kind of interesting quantum states
that can be made for
systems which have parts to them,
more than one part.
We're still struggling through trying to understand
the simplest quantum system,
the one bit or the one quantum bit system,
the spin, the two-state system.
And I wanted to finish that
up because it will come in
in a very central way, all
of the things we are talking about,
about the simple spin system.
Last time we talked about what happens if you're interested
in the component of spin along some axis,
which is neither three, two, or one,
but along some arbitrary axis.
And the arbitrary axis can
be represented by a unit vector,
a unit pointer,
a unit pointer that has components
n1, n2, n3, incidentally,
okay, so here's my coordinates in space,
I guess I've called this one
one, this one two, this one three,
and this one three.
And I may lapse every now and then
into calling one, x, two, y, and three, z.
So keep in mind that's, I've tried not to,
I've tried to keep a consistent notation in my notes,
but I do have that habit
of sometimes going back and forth
from one, two, and three to x, y, and z.
And then if you have an ordinary,
vector in space, not this unit vector in particular,
but some other vector, yes?
Is that a right-handed coordinate system?
Is that right-handed or not?
I intended it to be right-handed, but I can, x,
I think so, but I almost, my shoulder is broken,
and I don't think I can do it.
It doesn't matter.
One, two, and, I mean, it does matter,
but is it right-handed or isn't it?
No?
It's left-handed.
It's left-handed, okay.
So then we have to
have y going into the board.
All right, then we have to
have y going into the board, but...
Although you could have just relabeled y,
and y and z, and z could have gone out.
Yeah, yeah, indeed.
But my broken shoulder is limiting my orientation.
All right, now, if you have some physical vector,
thing that you can measure, in particular,
a thing that we've represented as having components sigma,
sigma x or sigma 1, sigma 2, and sigma 3,
this is supposed to be some physically measurable
little magnetic moment or spin vector.
It has components along the 1, 2, and 3 axes.
We can call them sigma
1, sigma 2, and sigma 3,
and we have called them sigma
1, sigma 2, and sigma 3.
Those are observable quantities,
and we represent them by matrices.
But for the moment, forget that they're matrices.
If we're interested in the component of sigma
along the arbitrary axis n,
then what we're interested in is
the dot product of sigma with n.
And to indicate a unit vector,
it's conventional to put a
little hat on top of it.
If it's a unit vector,
then let's just write down a couple of equations.
n1 squared plus n2 squared plus
n3 squared is equal to 1.
Okay, that's the definition of a unit vector.
And sigma dot n, this
is the ordinary space dot product,
not the inner product of
two abstract vectors representing states,
but just the ordinary dot
product in space of a vector
that we can measure
whose components are measurable quantities.
And the unit vector n, then this is by definition
n1 sigma 1 plus n2
sigma 2 plus n3 sigma 3.
But now, each of the sigmas is itself a matrix.
The n's are just numbers.
The direction cosines of some direction is what they are.
The direction cosines of some direction.
But the sigmas are matrices,
and so this whole thing is itself matrices or operators,
if I want to be really technically correct,
linear operators.
But let's just think of them as matrices.
And then remembering what's,
let's write down what the matrix is.
Okay, so sigma 3,
remember what sigma 3 is,
it's the matrix with a 1 and a minus 1.
So that means we would multiply it by n3
and put n3 here and minus n3 here.
Sigma 1 has a 1,
and a 1 over here,
so we would put an n1 over here,
and an n1 over here.
And then sigma 2 has a minus i,
and a plus i.
So we would write plus i,
and let me make this bigger.
n1 plus i n2.
And then down here it would be n1,
no sorry, minus i n2.
And here it would be n1 minus,
plus i n2.
And then minus n3 over here.
Notice that it's Hermitian.
The diagonal elements are real,
the off-diagonal elements are
complex conjugates of each other,
that makes it Hermitian.
And I'm going to just make a little notation,
I may or may not use it very much,
but it's a standard notation,
to write that n1 minus i n2
is equal to n minus,
and n1 plus i n2
is equal to n plus.
Just definition.
Okay.
Let me write another interesting simple equation.
If you multiply n plus,
oh, then we can just
write that this is equal to,
and simplify the expression,
n3 n minus n plus minus n3.
That's the matrix sigma dot n,
and it's supposed to be an observable,
something we can measure.
We measure it by putting the electron,
or suddenly turning on a large magnetic field,
oriented along the n-axis,
and then checking whether it
does or doesn't emit a photon.
If it doesn't emit a photon,
then it has
positive component of sigma dot n.
Okay.
Now, one thing that we checked last time,
I believe we checked last time,
was that for any n,
sigma dot n squared
is equal to one.
You can check that
either by multiplying this matrix by itself,
and then using the fact
that n1 squared plus n2 squared
plus n squared 3 squared equals one,
or you can check it
from the fact that each one of the,
well, you can check it
from properties of the sigma matrices,
from the sigma matrices themselves.
I think I, did I work that out last time?
Yeah.
And it follows from the fact
that any one of the sigmas
times any one of the other sigmas
is equal to minus
sigma j sigma i,
for i not equal to j.
So sigma 1 sigma 2
is minus sigma 2 sigma 1,
and you can check that easily
that the square is equal to one.
Now, I'm not going to prove this right now,
it's a very, very,
I can't prove every single
little detail of everything we do,
because it would take forever.
So, here and there,
if I say something that you don't know,
usually it's,
it usually means it's something that takes
about a half a line to prove,
and you can prove it.
Think of it as a homework assignment.
Okay, so if sigma dot
n squared is equal to one,
well, if a number squared is equal to one,
that means that the number
is either plus or minus one.
Right?
If a matrix squared is equal to one,
it means its eigenvalues are all plus or minus one.
Okay.
So sigma dot n, in fact, has two,
for any n, has two eigenvalues,
one plus one and one equal to minus one,
as you might expect,
corresponding to the two possibilities
that when you measure the spin along that axis,
you either get plus or minus.
So, for sigma dot n squared is equal to one,
that's one fact.
Another little algebraic fact,
which is kind of neat,
if you multiply these,
I don't know if it's neat,
it's true, that's all.
If it's n plus times n minus,
that's equal to n one squared plus n two squared.
Oh, notice that n plus and n minus
are complex conjugates of each other.
So n plus n minus,
oops, n plus n minus,
is equal to n one squared plus n two squared.
Now this is a true statement.
All right, let me add to this,
all right, let me add to this,
n plus n minus is equal to
n one squared plus n three squared,
and then subtract n three squared.
I haven't changed it.
And now I see that n plus n minus
is equal to one minus n three squared.
One minus, one minus,
I don't want to square the whole thing,
I only want to square the n three.
That's a, that's a useful little algebraic fact
that if you do the homework,
I'll write a little sign for you,
you will use over and over again.
But it's, it's, it's not anything deep,
it's just a little algebraic fact.
Okay, here is the question,
ultimately the question I want to ask is the following.
Supposing I orient the spin,
I prepare a spin by putting
it in a large magnetic field,
waiting for it to decay or not decay,
and then I force it into a particular,
along a particular axis.
Supposing I force it to be along the n axis.
Then I measure the component of
the spin along a different axis.
Let's call it the m axis.
Here's the m axis over here.
What's the probability that if I make the spin
with a spin along the n axis,
I measure it along the m axis,
I will find that it's plus along the m axis,
and of course the opposite probability
that it's minus along the m axis.
This is the central kind of question
that quantum mechanics deals with.
For the simple spin, electron spin,
this is about the only interesting question
that you can ask.
Question?
Okay.
You could also of course ask,
supposing you oriented along the m axis
and measured on the n axis.
By symmetry it's pretty clear
that they should be equal to each other.
And furthermore,
you might even expect
that the rotational symmetry of the world
should mean that the answer only depends
on the angle between n and m.
That would be a nice thing to discover,
and in fact it's true.
The answer only depends on the angle between them.
That's going to be part of your homework assignment.
But how do you do it?
Okay.
So we have to go back then
to the basic probability postulate
about quantum mechanics.
That what we first do
is calculate the eigenvectors
of sigma dot n
and the eigenvectors of sigma dot m.
Now, we first find the eigenvector
of sigma dot n that corresponds
to spin pointing definitely along this axis.
And then we take the inner product
with the eigenvector of sigma dot m
corresponding to spin pointing along this direction.
So we could write this out.
Let's make a notation.
Okay.
Question? No. Yes.
Yeah, you just told us that
sigma 1, 2, and 3 are spin operators.
Does quantum mechanics tell us that,
or did some experiments tell us that?
Well, it's no single experiment.
It's the whole accumulated, I mean,
um, how to say this?
There was a whole lot of data about this.
You could do this experiment
over and over and over again,
and eventually you would discover
that the probabilities,
that there are probabilities,
that's an experimental fact,
that the probabilities are given by the formulas
we're going to write down.
That was something that was deduced by guessing.
It was guessing. It was brilliant guessing.
Um, but, uh,
and who guessed it?
It wasn't any single person.
It was a buildup from the work of,
first of all, starting with Einstein,
who was the first to realize that quantum theory
involved probabilities,
and then Born,
and then Heisenberg,
and then Dirac.
So there was a series of steps
in which all of this was eventually discovered.
Now, nobody, nobody has ever understood
what the hell Heisenberg was thinking
when he invented matrix mechanics.
Nobody understands what the mystical experience
or what he was smoking or what,
but, uh, but, uh, he did.
And, uh, I think you simply have to take
quantum mechanics as data,
by
the mechanics of a big questions.
Okay, so, what
we're talking about now,
what I'll introduce,
certainly to this.
call it the vector, the eigenvector of
sigma dot n with eigenvalue plus 1.
What does it satisfy? It satisfies
that sigma dot n equals 1.
If you apply sigma dot n to
it, you just get the same vector back.
This whole elaborate thing here is just
a statement that I'm talking about the eigenvector
of sigma dot n with eigenvalue plus 1. If
I apply sigma dot n to such an eigenvector,
I just get 1 times the same vector.
That's the eigenvector corresponding to a state.
We could call it...
We can call it an eigenstate. The
word eigenstate is also used all the time.
This is the eigenstate of sigma dot n such
that sigma dot n, if you measure it, is definitely
equal to plus 1.
We can do the same for sigma dot m.
Sigma dot m on the state sigma dot
m equals plus 1 also equals sigma dot m.
This equal here is not an equals.
It's just part of the notation.
This is the notation labeling the vector.
I could have used a simpler notation.
What do we have to do?
The first step is to construct these vectors to find out
what the eigenvectors of sigma dot n are and sigma dot m.
Then when you've done that, you
construct what is called the probability amplitude.
The first step is the probability amplitude.
That's the inner product.
That's the Cry偵ás type of neighbourhood.
And over here, this girls
is equal to sigma dot m.
Alright?
So now we pulled that out, and this
is what you would get that it's trivial.
See dí's equalár between the prepared state and
the final outcome whose probability you're interested in.
Sigma dot m equals 1.
This is the probability amplitude that if you
create an electron with its spin along the n-axis,
Not the probability, this is the probability amplitude.
To get the probability, this is a
complex number in general, you square it.
You multiply it by its complex conjugate, which
is labeled by two bars and a square.
The absolute value of it squared.
That's the probability, we can call that the
probability that, I don't want to write all
this out.
It's the probability that if sigma dot n is
equal to one, and then you measure sigma dot
m, you'll get one, as opposed to minus one.
That's the kind of thing that quantum mechanics calculates.
That's exactly what quantum mechanics
does in every single case.
It asks a question, what is the probability
that you'll get a certain outcome about a
particular variable, given that you've prepared the
state in some way, perhaps involving some
other variable.
One notation in probability is that you use
the given as a subscript, and then what you
test for is the .
Okay, so we could then write the probability
that if sigma dot n equals one, then sigma
dot m equals one.
The probability in general will be less than one.
So let's think of some cases.
If n and m are equal,
then obviously the probability is one.
If n and m are opposite directions, then
that's just a question, what's the probability if
the spin is up, then it's down?
Well, that must be zero, so we should find that.
What about at 90 degrees?
A half.
Anywhere in the plane, if m is in the
plane perpendicular to n, we would expect to get
the probability being a half.
And that's true.
But how do we justify it?
How do we actually calculate it?
So I'm going to take you through the
calculation of the eigenvectors, but then you are going
to go home and take their inner product,
I'll take their inner product, but then you'll
square it and boil it and cook
it and stamp on it and cry.
It's an ugly little calculation.
It's not a pleasant one.
No, it's not a pleasant one.
Okay.
It's not very hard.
It took me about 15 minutes.
But I used a lot of tricks, which means it
took me a lot longer than it will take you
without any tricks.
Okay, so let's find the eigenvector.
Now first of all, when you start looking
for eigenvectors, we're going to try to solve
the problem.
Sigma dot n, where is it?
It's n3 minus n3 and minus n plus.
That's sigma dot n.
And we're going to look for a vector,
alpha beta, such that we get alpha beta back.
Now in the first round, I'm not
going to worry about normalizing the vector.
Later on, we can normalize the vector.
Normalizing it means multiplying it by some constant
so that the sums of the squares add
up to 1.
But for the moment, let's not worry about that.
And if I don't normalize the vector, also
another thing, I don't think I've ever mentioned
it.
All of the physical quantities in
quantum mechanics are insensitive to multiplying the
vectors, any one of the vectors, by a phase.
A phase means a complex number of magnitude 1.
And the reason is because all of
the physical quantities, you always count them.
You always complex conjugate them and square it.
And the complex conjugate are of, and a number
whose magnitude is 1, a number like e to the
i theta, it will not enter
into any probability that you ever calculate.
So if you take a vector and you multiply it
by the number e to the i theta, you have changed
nothing about its properties.
Because you always wind up multiplying a quantity.
A quantity by its complex conjugate.
So that's something to keep in mind,
that you should normalize the vector, but multiplying
both the top and the bottom here by the
same e to the i theta doesn't change anything.
All right, but the upshot of that is
we can arbitrarily, for example, choose alpha to
be 1.
If we don't care about normalizing the vector
and we don't care about its phase, then there's
no loss of generality.
And just choosing alpha to
be 1, and I'll do it.
And then later we'll come back and normalize it.
So what happens if we choose alpha, let's choose
alpha to be 1, and then I'm going to
call the lower entry here z.
And I want to get back 1z.
The question is, what does z have to be?
What is the numerical value of z?
All right, so let's read it off.
Let's work out the equation.
Let's take the top component.
That's n3 times 1 plus n minus times z.
n3 times 1 plus n minus times z.
That has to be equal to 1.
That's reading off the top component of the
left-hand side and setting it equal to the
top component of the right-hand side.
Now, you can do the same with the bottom component.
You get exactly the same equation.
You get exactly the same equation for z.
OK, so I won't even bother.
We obviously have enough equations here to find z.
We don't need to write the second equation.
So let's just solve it.
We can subtract n3.
We get n minus z is equal to
1 minus n3, and then divide by n minus.
And we have found...
We've now found an eigenvector of z.
So we can write the second equation.
OK.
So we have the eigenvector of sigma dot n.
And here it is.
I'll write it out now.
It's equal to 1 minus n3 over n minus.
Now, it's not normalized.
It's not normalized.
To normalize it, we have
to multiply it by some number.
Let's just call it c.
We have to multiply it something so that this...
So that the sums of
the squares add up to 1.
All right.
Now, what do we actually have
to do to be more precise?
We have to make the inner product of
this vector with itself be equal to 1.
Let's see what the inner product
of the vector with itself is.
So let's first write the
row vector, the corresponding row vector.
1, 1 minus n3.
Now, shall I write n minus down here?
Conjugate.
And the conjugate is n plus.
OK.
That's the row vector.
And if I multiply this by the column
vector, 1, 1 minus n3 over n minus,
then what I'll get is 1
times 1 plus 1 minus n3.
Squared over n plus n minus.
Did I do that right?
Which is 1 minus n3.
Which is what?
1 minus n3 squared.
Yeah.
Let's work it out.
Let's multiply 1 by n.
1 minus n plus n minus.
So this becomes n plus n minus plus 1.
When I square this out, I'll get
1 plus n3 squared minus twice n3.
Is that right?
Am I doing this right?
And then we have to divide
that by n plus n minus.
I'm just going to take
you a little ways into this.
I'm going to take you
a little ways into this calculation.
Now, what is n plus n minus?
That's, where did we have it?
n plus n minus is 1 minus n3 squared.
And so plus n3 squared, this just gives us
The n3 squares cancel.
The 1's add, and you get 2
minus twice n3 over n plus n minus.
Is that right?
I think that's right.
You can simplify it a little bit further.
Yeah.
This is 1 minus n3 squared downstairs.
I'm not going to do all the algebra.
I'm just going to take you a little ways.
Hm?
對
Yeah, so this is, first
of all, there's a 2 outside
then there's a 1 minus n3 in the numerator
and then in the denominator, that's 1 minus n3 squared
It's 1 minus n3 squared, which is
1 minus n3 times 1 plus n3
Right
So we take
1 minus n3 times 1 plus
n3, and don't worry if you don't
if you're not following, because I'm going
to make you do it over for homework
Alright, and then we cancel out the 1 minus n3
We get an answer, the answer
is 2 divided by 1 plus n3
What was that? That was the
inner product of the vector with itself
And we didn't get 1, that's bad,
that's bad, we haven't normalized the vector
What do we have to do
to the vector to normalize it?
We have to multiply it, not by the square root
of this, but by the square root of 1 over this
We want to kill, we want to
cancel this 2 divided by 1 plus n3
And so we have to multiply the vector, the eigenvector
by the inverse square root
So here is the normalized eigenvector
and the homework, of course, is to check this and
to check that it is the normalized eigenvector over 2
times 1 minus n3 over n minus
That's the normalized eigenvector corresponding to
measuring the spin along the n-axis
The same thing is true along the m-axis
except wherever you see n, you put m
Let's rewrite this, let's actually put
the square roots on the inside
A square root of 1
plus n3 minus n3 over n
n3 over 2, and then 1 minus n3,
this looks too complicated, this is more complicated
than it really has to be, but
1 plus n3 square root divided by 2.
That's the normalized eigenvector.
Now what about the other half of the calculation?
The other half of the calculation is the
other vector, the eigenvector of sigma dot m.
And that's easy.
All we have to do is
replace n by m and complex conjugate.
So the appropriate row vector looks very similar, square
root of 1 plus m3, and then in the
second entry, 1 minus m3.
Now instead of m minus, we'll put
m plus, because it's complex conjugated, and then
square root of 1 plus m3 over 2.
What do we do with this mess?
We take the inner product.
The inner product, I'm not going to do it.
I'm going to tell you what the answer is.
We multiply this one by this
one, oh, this is 2, right?
Nobody told me 2.
We multiply this one by this one,
and we add this one times this one.
It looks like an unholy mess, and it is.
Okay?
But.
If you use...
Okay.
If you use the law of algebra, and you
just go through it, brute force, it will take you
10 minutes.
If you use all the
tricks, it'll take you 15 minutes.
So and you just use, you use over and over
again the fact that n plus n minus is 1 minus
n3 squared.
You fiddle it.
I'm going to tell you what the answer is.
Not for this.
Not for this in itself.
But we have to do one more thing with this.
What's the next thing we have to do with it?
What's that?
It has to be 0.
Why does it have to be 0?
They're orthogonal.
Why?
This is m, this is n.
What?
There's nothing orthogonal about them.
If this were n, this would be
a vector times its... what are you saying?
If m and n were the
same, the inner product would be 1.
That's what we took care of to make sure of.
No, no, no, they're not orthogonal.
Okay.
What do we want to do with them?
What we want to do with it, that's... okay.
Square it.
Take it times its complex conjugate.
It times its complex conjugate.
So we take this inner product.
We multiply it out.
It's a big mess, but it's
just a mess of n's and m's.
And we take the whole thing when we get
it and we multiply it by its complex conjugate.
And we multiply it by its complex conjugate.
And you sit and you calculate and you
calculate and you calculate and you... you can even
try to throw it onto a computer and
see what you get using Mathematica or something or
whatever you like, however you like to do it.
But the answer is incredibly simple.
I have yet to be able to find
a one-line way to prove, to demonstrate the answer.
I always have to do
it, go through the whole thing.
I am absolutely convinced that there's a
one-line argument, but I can never find it.
Anyway, the answer is 1 plus n1 m1
plus n2 m2 plus n3 m3 divided by 2.
Or 1 plus n dot m.
Over 2.
That's the whole answer.
After you're finished.
It has n's and m's, all
of the components, all over the place.
And it simply boils down eventually to this expression.
Now what is n dot m?
Anybody know what n dot m is?
It's the cosine of the angle between them.
It's the cosine, let's call this theta nm.
The angle between the n-axis and the m-axis.
And so this is just 1 plus
cosine of theta nm divided by 2.
Now, first of all, one interesting thing about it is
that it only depends on the angle between n and m.
That means you would get the same
result if you rotated the whole experiment.
Okay?
That's an interesting fact.
And it's an important fact, of course.
It's what has to do with rotational invariance of physics.
That the axes didn't matter.
That if you rotated the whole
experiment, you would get the same answer.
It's also symmetric in n and m, since
it only depends on the angle between them.
And the angle between them, it doesn't matter
whether you write n first or m first.
It's exactly the same answer
if you interchange n and m.
That's interesting.
But let's see what it gives for various situations.
First of all, supposing n and
m are in the same direction.
If n and m are in
the same direction, then theta is 0.
Alright?
The angle is 0.
And cosine of 0 is 1.
1 plus 1 is 2.
2 divided by 2 is 1.
So, the first thing it says
is that if you prepare the electron,
pointing along the n-axis,
and then you measure it along the n-axis,
you will definitely find it up.
You made it up, you measure
it, and you find it up.
That's a good thing.
What about if n and
m are opposite to each other?
Not perpendicular, but opposite.
In other words, then theta is 180 degrees,
cosine of 180 degrees is minus 1.
1 plus minus 1 is 0.
Okay?
So, the first thing it says is that
if you prepare the electron along the n-axis,
and then look and ask whether
its spin is along the minus n-axis,
you get 0 probability.
In other words, if it's pointing that
way, it's definitely not pointing that way.
That's a good thing.
What if theta is 90 degrees?
And it doesn't matter.
Notice, it doesn't matter if n is fixed.
m can be anywhere in space.
In space, as long as its angle is
fixed, so it could be on a cone.
But in any case, if theta
is 90 degrees, what do you get?
Cosine of 90 degrees is 0, huh?
Cosine of 90 degrees is 0,
and so you just get 1
half, which is what we expected.
But now we actually know the interpolating formula,
the formula that's good for any angle.
And this is the most
primitive but basic quantum mechanical calculation.
that quantum mechanics does.
So notice, I mean, think this is a remarkable achievement.
We have some strange theory in
where whenever we measure the spin
along any given axis, it's either
plus or minus and nothing in between.
And yet, there's something about this
system which doesn't care about the axes.
You can orient the spin along any
axis and measure it along any other axis,
and instead of getting fractional answers,
you get fractional probabilities for the result.
And this is the fractional probability.
Okay, are there any questions up till now?
Well, we could plot this function,
incidentally, as a function of angle.
At 180 degrees, it goes to 0.
At 0 degrees, it's 1.
And it looks like, whoops,
I'll put 180 degrees over here.
It just looks like that.
So we know the answer now to
any question that you can meaningfully ask
about a single quantum bit.
How do we know that it's the same electron?
Well, we just have one electron.
But how do we know that?
We observe it somehow, which means it's interact with it,
but we do not .
Well, we build us a
cavity and put some sealed walls
that prevent anything from going in and going out,
and we do find that that electron stays in there.
We can measure the electric charge
by measuring the outgoing electric flux.
We find it doesn't change.
So, yeah, we can measure the electric charge, for example.
And...
What's that?
If it doesn't matter,
the glowing electrons instead of the
one that results should match the...
If we do the same thing
to every one of the electrons,
is that what you mean?
Yeah.
That's right.
And in practice, we can
either do one of two things.
You don't measure a probability.
In order to measure a probability,
you have to do an experiment repeatedly.
Okay?
You have to do the
same experiment over and over again.
You can do it in one of two ways.
You can take the same
electron and continuously repeat the experiment.
So you put your big magnetic field along the n-axis,
line up that electron, and
then measure it along the m-axis.
Then when you're finished, you put back
your big electric field along the n-axis,
line it up again, and do the experiment
over and over and over and over again.
You can do that, or you can
get yourself a whole bunch of electrons,
and do a million identical experiments
doing one experiment on each electron.
You should get, and you do get, the same answer.
Okay?
You do get the same answer for the probability.
In the case that you have a million electrons,
the probability simply means the ratio
of the number of ups and downs
within the margin of error, of course.
There's always margins of error.
You're saying that the million electrons
are all covered in one experiment?
Well, you could...
You can do an experiment in
which you take a million electrons,
line them all up along the n-axis, okay?
Okay, you fellows, line up along the n-axis,
put a big magnetic field on each one,
and then measure each one's spin along the m-axis.
Some will be plus, some will be minus.
Okay?
But the ratio of the number of pluses and
minuses will measure the probability for plus and minus.
Actually, they just all have to have the same thing.
The same...
They don't have to have
the same thing all lined up.
Okay, but if you really want to...
Yeah, right.
But that's indeed so.
But yes, that's true.
But let's be a little bit purist about it and
say we do the same repeated experiment over and over.
But yes, you're right.
Yeah?
If you use one electron, how many times can
you repeat it and it can always emit photons?
Wait, say it again?
How many photons can an electron emit?
Endless numbers.
It's the energy fed in
by turning on the magnetic field.
Okay?
When you turn on that magnetic field,
if the spin is in the wrong direction,
you have to do a little more work to turn
on the magnetic field than if it's in the right direction.
And it's that energy which
is effectively the photon that's emitted.
So there's no limit to the number
of times you can do this experiment.
Now you had defined the same thing.
You said sigma in terms of the three sigma matrices.
Yes.
And one of the side effects of this
was that you went from having nice clean eigenvectors
to really ugly looking eigenvectors.
Yeah.
And also, ugliness is in the
eye of the beholder, of course.
So I mean, yeah, I mean it is.
One of these days I'm going to find a
trick for this calculation so that it's not so ugly.
But yeah.
The question is, is this a general
characteristic of that type of matrix operator?
And would it help to define the basis of one?
Yeah.
Let me put it this way.
There's another way to prove that the
answer only depends on the angle between them.
But that will take us into unitary matrices and things.
And we'll get into that.
We will get into that.
And symmetries and interesting things
that we haven't gotten to yet.
But I could do just a simple example.
I could, for example, take n to be up.
Supposing I took n to be up.
Let's see what we get if
we take n to be up.
Okay.
So if n is up, m doesn't,
the m eigenvector stays the same, right?
m is just some arbitrary direction.
All right.
So let's take the n eigenvector to be up.
Then this is just 1, 0.
Okay.
Now the answer is easy.
It's just this times this.
Plus this times this, but that's 0.
All right.
So the probability amplitude, the thing that you square, is
just the square root of 1 plus m3 over 2.
We square it.
And what do we get?
We get 1 plus m3 over 2.
But m3 is just the cosine of the
angle of m with the third axis, right?
That's what m3 is.
m3 is a direction cosine.
In this case, the direction cosine of m.
And so it actually is just cosine of that angle.
So if we're willing to pick particular directions,
and in particular if some of the directions
are along the axis, one of the axes,
then it's usually very simple.
But it's still not a unit matrix.
Which is not a unit matrix?
Well, that, because it's...
First of all, I don't see any matrix here.
This was not a matrix.
This was absolute value squared.
It means times its complex conjugate.
So you can set the coordinates any direction you want?
Wait, wait, wait.
Yes.
Yeah.
One of the matrices was just sigma3, by itself,
which has eigenvectors and .
Alright, so I chose this eigenvector.
Alright?
In particular, we should check
that that really is the eigenvector.
Supposing m3 is plus 1.
Supposing it's plus 1.
Okay?
n3 being plus 1 just means that
n is along the third axis pointing up.
Alright?
1 plus n3 would be 2.
2 divided by 2 is 1.
So this just becomes 1.
That's gone.
1 is up here.
But 1 minus n3, that would be 0.
Right?
If n3 is 1, this would be 0.
So in fact, for the special case where
n3, where we're in, is along the third axis,
the eigenvector would be 0.
The eigenvector is just 1, 0.
And it's the eigenvector then of just plain old sigma3.
Okay?
Good.
So...
But you can always choose the coordinates however you want.
Well, no, no, no.
You're right.
But there was nothing from the start that
guaranteed that we were going to be able to
find a, um, find rotational invariance in the problem.
So one of the things
we proved by doing this calculation,
is that the answer is rotationally invariant.
If we had independent reason to
believe that the answer was rotationally invariant,
then we'd just pick an axis.
I know I'm cheating, but all
the mathematics you did was rotationally invariant.
So you did the dot product and the eigenvector.
Well, I just picked this
crazy set of 3 sigma matrices.
Where did I get them from?
Yeah.
Once you've done that, you already
know what you're going to be.
Right.
But we're talking about...
We're touching on the question of symmetries
now, namely the symmetry of a system under
rotation.
And there's a whole subject of symmetry and
quantum mechanics which we will come to, which
is interesting on its own.
And I prefer to defer that discussion about
picking axes until we have a language to speak
about it in.
At the moment, let's just take it as a
boon, as a gift from one of our professors.
Yeah.
And it's a gift from God that the answer
came out to be only dependent on the angle
between the N and M.
May I ask you a question?
Yeah.
So we're observing this probability...
Whoops.
Ay-yi-yi.
I'm going to get in big trouble.
So we're observing the probabilities and the gift
of God that it only depends on the angle.
Yeah.
And from the physical perspective, how do we explain that?
Well, the answer is, well, the answer
is that the angle is a given.
The angle is a given.
So you could totally explain why it's a given angle.
I'll tell you, let's wait a little while.
Let's wait a little while.
But is the question of symmetries
and how symmetries work in quantum mechanics.
And it's a step that I don't want to do
right now because I do want to get to entanglement
and getting entangled in...
They're good questions.
They're very good questions.
But I would prefer just to say at
this point, it's just luck, luck of a draw.
We picked the right matrices.
All right, first of all, when you...
I'll just get something to munch on.
Eh, leave it.
No, no.
Let me just get the cookie out of the way.
That's the most important thing.
Yeah, another important idea that we've sort of mentioned
but never really focused on
is when you measure a thing,
you get an answer, but then you
leave the system in some new state.
In other words, when you measure
something, you go into the system,
you interact with it, and
you change its state in general.
In particular, if you measure a
particular quantity and you get an answer,
that answer corresponds to some eigenvalue,
you leave the system in an eigenvector with that eigenvalue.
So, if you...
If you measure the spin
along the m-axis to be up,
you leave the system in the state
where the spin along the m-axis is up.
You started with the state along the n-axis.
You measured it by putting
it into this large magnetic field,
and you leave it in the state
corresponding to the measurement that you've made.
So that's an important idea that
not only is it a measurement,
but it's a kind of filter which...
like a polarizer that polarizes photons.
You measure the polarization of a
photon by sending it through a polarizer,
but at the same time you also leave it
in the state of polarization corresponding to that polarizer.
Same idea here,
that the electron is left in an
eigenstate of whatever it is you measured,
corresponding to the value that you measured.
Okay.
Let's see.
Oh, there's another interesting theorem.
No, let's...
Yeah.
Can you measure...
Can you do a single measurement,
or simultaneously two measurements,
that measured both sigma 1 and sigma 2 simultaneously?
Can you do a measurement which measures both of them,
and doesn't screw up somehow?
And the answer is no.
And the answer is very simple.
The reason is very simple.
The eigenvectors...
If you measure sigma 1 and you get an answer,
and you measure sigma 2 and you get an answer,
remember, the rule is that you leave the
system in an eigenstate corresponding to that measurement.
Okay?
Okay.
You've got your A.
Just carry on.
All right.
Now, the problem is, there are no eigenvectors
in common between sigma n and sigma m.
They have different eigenvectors.
They are not in common.
Therefore, you cannot measure them both simultaneously,
because you cannot leave them in a state which is
both an eigenvector of sigma dot n and sigma dot m.
They just are no...
There are no eigenvectors which they share.
All right?
So, no, it is not possible to measure them.
But an interesting question is, what is the condition,
the mathematical condition,
that you can measure two quantities simultaneously?
And the answer is that they
had better have all the same eigenvectors,
that the eigenvectors of one of them had better be
exactly the same as the eigenvectors of the other one.
Because if you measure them and you get an answer,
then the answer has to be an eigenvalue,
and the eigenvalues correspond to distinct eigenvectors.
And the only way that you
can ever measure two quantities simultaneously,
and be sure that you get answers,
is if they share all the same eigenvectors.
What was that?
If two matrices share all the
same eigenvectors, they have a property.
The property is they commute.
Okay?
Now, this is again something I do
want to get to where I'm going tonight.
But let me write that
as a theorem on the blackboard.
You can attempt to measure it, but...
What's that?
You can measure and get the right answer,
or they don't disturb one another.
You can do the measurement, but...
Well, how would you measure
sigma x and sigma y simultaneously?
You could do the physical experiment.
How?
Remember, you measure sigma x by putting it
into a large magnetic field along the x-axis.
You measure sigma y by putting it
into a large magnetic field along the y-axis.
Well, you can put it into a magnetic field
which is both along the x-axis and the y-axis,
but then you'll be measuring, you know,
you'll be measuring not sigma x or sigma y,
but sigma along a 45-degree angle.
You'll be measuring something different.
So, the answer is you'll never think
of a way of even measuring it.
But that's good because the mathematics
says you shouldn't be able to.
All right, the condition, if I have
two matrices that they have all common eigenvectors,
I'm going to write the condition and either
look up the proof of it, prove it yourself.
It really is a one-liner.
This really is a one,
well, maybe two lines at most.
But if two matrices, A and
B, have all the same eigenvectors,
let's call them alpha sub i.
These are the various eigenvectors.
No, that's not what I want to write.
Lambda i.
This is the ith eigenvector.
Wow.
Alpha i.
Yeah.
And another matrix has exactly the same eigenvectors,
but perhaps different eigenvalues.
Let's call them mu.
Mu i times alpha i.
In other words, the same set of
alphas are the eigenvectors of both matrices.
Then you can measure
them simultaneously, the two quantities,
if they have the same eigenvectors.
And under those circumstances,
there's a theorem that's a one-liner, as I said.
It says that A times B
is equal to B times A.
Or, in mathematical terminology, well,
or A minus B, A B
minus B A is equal to zero.
Remember, the order that you multiply matrices is important.
When you multiply matrices, it's important.
If the matrices commute,
that means it doesn't matter
which order you write them in,
then all of the eigenvectors are
simultaneous eigenvectors of the two operators.
That's a theorem.
Necessary and sufficient condition for all
of the eigenvectors to be the same
are that the matrices commute.
Commute means you can interchange the order.
Another way of writing the same thing,
the mathematical notation for A B minus B A,
is to just write them in a bracket.
Not a bracket, a commutator.
This is called the commutator, and
it means A B minus B A.
If two operators commute,
you can measure them simultaneously,
because they have exactly the same eigenvectors.
That's a theorem, and as I said,
it really is a one- or two-line theorem.
You know how A acts on,
just multiplied by a number,
and then you know how B acts,
it also multiplies by a number,
and so you can easily figure out
what the product of A and B is
on any vector, on any eigenvector,
and from that you can conclude,
you can make your conclusion.
So I don't want to
go through the proof of that,
because it would take us astray,
but I do want to get to...
Okay.
There is one more theorem,
another theorem about the simple spin,
and it's a very interesting theorem,
and an important theorem.
This one is really quite important.
It's a theorem about the single spin.
What it says is that no
matter what state you write down,
what vector, in other words,
any vector you write down, alpha, beta,
with presumably alpha star,
plus beta star, beta equals one,
assume that,
so that's normalized,
no matter what state you write down,
there is always some direction of space,
such that if the electron is in this state,
then the spin along that direction is definitely plus.
In other words, any vector that you write down
is an eigenvector of some sigma dot n.
Given an alpha and beta,
you can find a direction in space
such that this is an eigenvector.
Let's write it alpha beta equals alpha beta.
Any alpha or beta.
In this case, the problem is not finding the eigenvector.
Given an n, you can look for an eigenvector.
This is the reverse problem.
Given the state of an electron,
can you find the direction along
which that electron is definitely up?
And the answer is yes.
And the simplest way to prove it is to count,
think of this as equations,
alpha and beta are fixed numbers,
fixed complex numbers.
This is an equation for
the components n1, n2, and n3.
The simplest way to prove it is
simply to count the number of equations
and the number of variables that you have.
The number of equations is the
same as the number of variables.
Basically, there are two equations,
one for the top component
and one for the bottom component.
How many components of n are there?
Three.
Yes?
I think sigma dot n
is up there on the board,
and it's got n3 and n plots.
So there are two variables.
Yeah, no, there's only two variables.
There's two variables, two real variables,
because nx squared plus ny squared
plus nz squared is equal to one.
In other words, n is a unit vector,
and so the number of variables that
it takes to describe it are two angles,
longitude and latitude, on a sphere.
So there are two variables,
there are two equations, two unknowns,
and the number of unknowns and
the number of equations is the same.
You can check that.
And so there's always an n.
There is always an n given any vector.
So what that says is that
if you take it a lot...
Here's the way you might do the experiment.
You've made an electron in some definite state,
but you're not sure what direction it corresponds to.
You're not sure.
You did something with the electron,
and you weren't clear.
Somebody...
All you know is somebody
put a magnetic field on it
and lined it up along some direction.
Oh, I don't even know what they did.
Whatever they did.
They did something, and they
left the electron in some state,
and we would like to find
out if there is a definite direction
along which the spin is up.
So here's what we do.
We, first of all, make a whole
bunch of replicas of the same experiment.
So we have a whole bunch of replicas
of electrons, all identically prepared.
All identically prepared.
Now we measure...
Now we use the...
And how many of them?
A hundred zillion of them.
We're going to use the first hundred million
to find out which direction the spin is pointing.
And then we'll check all the rest of them
and check and make sure that they
really are all pointing in the same direction.
So what you can do is
you can measure the spin of
the first one along some arbitrary axis.
You can measure the first
hundred of them along that axis.
If they all point up along that axis,
it sounds like there's a good
bet that they're up along that axis.
And then you measure all the rest of them,
and you find them all up.
But you might find that
if you measure along the z-axis,
you'll find some up and some down.
Okay?
If you measure the first hundred of them,
and you find some up and some down,
change direction a little bit.
Change the direction of your magnet a little bit,
and check another hundred of them.
If you still find there
are some up and some down,
change the direction of the magnet again.
Keep changing the direction of the magnet
until you find the direction
where all hundred or all thousand test electrons
are definitely up.
Then, when you've found that,
you will find that all
the rest of them are up.
Okay?
A thousand may not be a big enough number.
You may have to use ten thousand.
But that's the idea.
There is, for any state of an electron,
no matter how you prepare it,
if you prepare it carefully,
there will be a direction
along which it is definitely pointing in that direction.
Yeah?
The n has two degrees of freedom.
No.
But l and beta are complex.
Right.
Good.
Very good.
So it sounds like there are four.
It sounds like there are four.
But you have that normalization.
Right.
We have the normalization,
but we also have the freedom to change the phase.
We also have the freedom to change the phase.
So there's no...
The phase drops out of the equation also.
Don't you need a eigenvalue?
One.
One?
Well, we're looking for a direction.
Such that the eigenvalue is one.
We're searching for some direction
that the eigenvalue is one.
And this gentleman over here
asked exactly the right question.
He started counting variables.
How many equations are there?
Well, there's as many equations as
there are components of alpha and beta.
Okay?
There are four complex components.
This equation reduces it down to three.
But then the fact that the
overall phase of the wave function,
that you can...
That...
That doesn't matter in this equation either.
In other words, multiplying it by both sides,
by e to the i theta doesn't matter.
And so really there are only two degrees of freedom
in writing down a complex vector for an electron.
Two degrees of freedom.
Two variables here.
Two independent interesting variables here.
Two of them here.
And so the number of equations is
the same as the number of unknowns.
But there's a theta in it, physical meaning there.
The theta...
The overall phase of the wave function does not have...
Or this is called a wave function.
The overall phase of the state
vector does not have a physical significance.
Why not?
Because whenever you calculate any physical probability,
you always wind up multiplying it by its complex conjugate.
When you multiply by a
complex conjugate, the phase goes away.
Okay?
So the answer is,
there are two variables,
two physically interesting variables,
that go into defining the state of an electron.
And they're in one-to-one correspondence
with the two physical variables
that define a directionality in space.
So you can make a correspondence between the components here
and directions of space.
Alright.
That's true of single electrons.
Everything I said.
Now, I am going to continue because...
Well, let's see.
No, we can take a five-minute break.
Let's try to get to entanglement today.
To get to entanglement, we have to think about...
I'll tell you something.
I went to a school, a middle school,
and I taught a bunch of ten-year-olds
about string theory and extra dimensions and all that stuff.
It was kind of interesting.
Teaching them was very much like teaching you guys.
It's...
No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
It was.
They're unafraid to ask questions.
They're boisterous.
They're fun to teach.
It's the people in the middle, the undergraduates,
who are just terrified of asking a question.
Just no fun to teach.
One kid asked me a brilliant question.
He said, the neutrinos, there's all these neutrinos around.
Are those the things that give me headaches?
But, you know, it really has the same feel.
We're going to begin now studying pairs of electrons
to get to the basic idea of entanglement.
All we need is two electrons.
But just before we do that,
I want to make a table.
A table of the action of the sigma matrices.
I just want to write sigma...
Sigma one on up.
What does sigma one on up give?
Sigma one is the matrix which interchanges up and down.
It's off diagonal, and it means that it interchanges.
It takes up to down.
Sigma one on down equals up.
Sigma two...
What does sigma two do on up?
Well, sigma two and sigma one are very similar,
except there's an i in there and a minus sign.
So actually, what sigma two on up does...
Anybody know?
Well, it gives you down again,
but it gives you down with
an i in front of it.
And sigma two on down
gives you minus i times up.
You can check that just from the matrices.
And finally, sigma three.
What does sigma three do when it hits up?
It just goes up.
Up is an eigenvector of sigma three,
with eigenvalue plus one.
So it just goes up.
And sigma three on down gives minus down,
because it's an eigenvector with minus sign.
This is an abstract representation of the sigma matrices.
Well, it's not abstract.
It's concrete.
But it has the same
content that the matrix structure has.
Now let's come to pair of electrons.
And when I speak of pair of electrons,
once again, I'm not concerned with their position.
I imagine that they're nailed down.
They've been nailed to the wall.
And the only thing that's
free to vary is the spin,
spin of the electron,
the little magnetic moment that it carries.
And now we have two of them.
We have two of them,
and we're interested in the space of states,
the possible configurations of two spins.
Now again, I can measure the spins.
For example, I can measure the spin of a magnet.
I can measure the spins,
for example, along the third axis,
and use the measurements along the
third axis of the two spins.
And I could choose the same axis.
Just for simplicity, I will choose
to measure them along the same axis
and label them very similar to
the way I label the single electron.
But now we need two labels.
So for example, here's a fact we
can write down all of the states.
Let me write down all the possibilities.
We have in the first entry
here will correspond to the first electron,
and the second entry will correspond to the second electron.
So this means electron number one is up,
and electron number two is up.
We will never get confused about which electron is which.
One of the electrons is
nailed to the blackboard over here.
The other one is nailed over here.
And we call this one, and we call this two.
So there'll be no confusion.
There'll be no confusion about which electron is which.
This is electron one up, electron two up.
And then there's a state
in which electron one is down,
and electron two is up.
And then there's another one
in which electron one is up,
but electron two is down.
And then the last one, down, down.
That's all there is.
Those are all the possibilities that we can get.
Four possibilities, two times two.
These are
the four possible states of two spins.
And so we're evidently dealing, obviously,
with a four-dimensional vector space now,
with four basis vectors,
and two sets of quantities, two sets of observables.
Now, the two sets of observables are,
of course, the spins of the two electrons.
How am I going to label
the two spins of the electrons?
I can't call them sigma one and sigma two,
because I've already used sigma one
and sigma two for something else.
For the two components of the spin of one electron.
So I need another name.
The first one I will continue to call sigma.
The second one I'm simply going to give another name.
Tau follows sigma in some alphabet or other.
So we're going to label the first electron spin
and just call it sigma.
It has three components, same as it had before.
Sigma one, sigma two, and sigma three.
And the other one I'm just going to label tau.
And it also has three components,
tau one, tau two, and tau three.
How do the spin operators for the two electrons,
how do they operate and what
do they do to these vectors?
Let me teach you now how you think about...
First, let's take the first electron.
What does the spin operator, sigma
one, sigma two, and sigma three,
do to these four state vectors?
How does it act on these four state vectors?
And here's the answer.
If you're interested in the first
spin, the one on the left here,
you simply turn a blind eye to the second one.
You don't look at it. It's passive.
The operator sigma, which refers to the first spin,
has no action on the second electron.
It does nothing to it.
So when sigma acts,
it may or may not flip
the spin of the first electron,
but it leaves the second one completely unchanged.
That's the rule.
Now, this rule, of course, is an empirical rule,
but it sounds reasonable
that the spin of the first electron
should only act on the first electron,
on the coordinate of the first electron.
So, for example, let's do one or two examples.
What does sigma one do
when it acts on the state up-down,
just as an arbitrary example?
Well, you just turn a blind eye to down,
and in fact, when I
say you turn a blind eye,
I mean we will not change
the down for the second electron,
but we'll do to the first electron
exactly the same thing
that sigma one did on the first electron.
What did it do? It flipped it down.
So, turning a blind eye to the second electron,
sigma one makes down,
makes the first electron down.
It has done nothing,
the second electron is completely passive,
sigma one does that.
Let's do another example,
let's do sigma one on down-down.
Well, again, it does nothing to the second electron,
and it flips the first electron up.
Up-down.
Okay, so you see what I mean by saying
the second electron is passive.
Now let's ask about what tau does.
Tau are the operators associated with the second electron.
They also do something to the state vectors.
This time, you turn a
blind eye to the first electron,
and allow the operator to act exactly the same way,
except substitute sigma for tau,
exactly the same way,
but as it applies on the,
oh, before I do that, let
me do one more case of sigma.
What about sigma three on,
let's take an arbitrary case, up-up-down.
What does this give?
Well, sigma three on up leaves up,
with a plus one.
So it does nothing.
Up, and the second one is passive,
which just stays the way it is.
What about sigma three on down-down?
Well, you look over here on this chart,
sigma three takes down to down,
but with a minus sign.
So it gives you minus down-down.
In other words, the second electron
just goes along for the ride.
What about the taus?
The taus,
act on the second electron,
and the first electron goes along for the ride.
So let's do one or two cases.
Let's take tau two,
and act on up-down.
Alright, so to see what it does,
we go over to the chart,
we're acting on the second electron being down,
so we go over to sigma two on down,
and it gives us minus i times up.
So, this just gives us,
minus i times up up.
The first electron has been passive,
nothing has happened to it.
The second electron has responded
exactly the same way to tau,
to tau two,
as dictated by this chart here.
That's a set of definitions.
That's a set of definitions
of what sigma and tau do.
If you know what sigma and tau
do to all of the various vectors,
to all the independent vectors,
then you also know what they
do to any linear combination of them.
So this is a complete specification
of how sigma one,
sorry, how sigma and tau,
all components of them,
act on any vector.
Yeah?
Why is the minus i outside of the cap?
You did that on the left,
on the left,
and it sort of slipped by,
but now it's got significant implications
because the minus i is affecting both the electrons.
Electrons.
What happens to the minus i inside?
Well, multiplying a vector by an i,
it doesn't matter where you put it,
it doesn't make,
there's no meaning to putting it inside the vector.
You can multiply a vector by a constant,
but the constant,
that's a notational notation,
standard notation to leave the constant
on the outside of the vector.
To put it another way,
the inside of the cap is just a label?
Yeah, it's a label, right.
Right, that's right.
It's a label.
It's just a labeling configuration.
It doesn't make any sense to
multiply the label by a number.
So it goes on the outside.
But you are,
yeah, I mean,
you wouldn't be able to tell from this equation alone,
from this equation alone,
whether this i was because
of this up or that up.
But if you look at all the various possibilities,
you know, here's this tau 2,
let's write all the various
things that tau 2 can do.
Let's first do up up.
So tau 2,
let's see,
that the,
we have to see tau 2
on up gives i times down.
So that's i times down,
plus i times down,
and so forth.
We can go through the list of them.
The point is we know what sigma and
tau do to every one of the vectors.
And so we know completely what
the nature of the vector is.
We know completely what the nature of these operators are.
We don't have to bother writing down matrices.
We know what they do.
That's enough for us for now.
We could invent matrices describing them,
but it's unnecessary for the moment.
Maybe later we'll do it.
So is that i or rotation?
No, it's just multiplication by i.
It's not physically,
it's just multiplication of the vector by the number i.
It doesn't represent any rotation in real space,
if that's what you're asking.
It does not represent the rotation in real space.
It's just the action of these matrices.
That's all.
The matrices do.
And they just do the
same as they would have done
had the other label not been there.
That's...
Now, how many...
Over here, this gentleman over here remarked before
about the number of variables that it takes to specify
the state of an electron.
And the answer was two.
The answer was two independent real variables
that are important in specifying the state of an electron.
How many do you think
it takes to specify two electrons?
That's what you'd think, wouldn't you?
But let's go through the counting.
There's a four-dimensional vector space.
You can...
Where are they all?
Up, up, down, up, up, down, down, down.
What states can you build?
You can multiply each one
of these by a complex number
and add them all together.
That's the most general state of two electrons
that you can write down.
The linear combination of arbitrary...
with arbitrary coefficients
subject to the constraint that the sums of the squares
are equal to one.
And that the phase doesn't matter.
Now how many are there?
What's the counting now?
Six.
Eight.
Four complex numbers.
Yeah, we have to remove two. Right.
Right.
Four complex numbers.
That's eight variables, eight real variables.
Remove two. That gives you six.
Right. Something's going on here.
There seem to be more possibilities
than you might have guessed
had you said each electron
itself can be in some state.
If each electron was in some state,
each electron requires two variables
to define its physical state,
you might have guessed the answer was four.
Okay?
It seems that the space
of states must somehow be richer.
It must contain things which are...
which cannot be described simply
as each electron having its own state.
Because there are just too many variables.
Just too many possibilities.
Instead of four, there are six.
So six variables.
Six independent real numbers
characterizing the state of a two-electron system.
All right.
This is entanglement.
But first let me tell you what corresponds
to a pair of electrons,
each with its own state,
each with its own state
that you would recognize as...
Supposing the state of the...
electron number one...
Well, supposing we put the electron number one
in the state alpha up
plus beta down.
And let me put a one here
to indicate that this is electron one.
So, let's say that this is electron one.
That's electron one.
That's the state of electron one.
And now what about electron two?
Electron two, I'm going to write alpha two
times up
plus beta two
times down.
I'm not going to write...
It's state of two.
State of two.
Now, neither of these are really two-electron states.
Two-electron states have to have two indices.
What...
If electron one is in this state
and electron two is in this state,
then the two-electron state
you write down the following way.
You write it as a product.
Alpha one up...
And then I'll tell you what to do with it.
Alpha one up plus beta one down
times...
Let's put a bracket.
Alpha two up
plus beta two down.
And then read off from this the following object.
Alpha one alpha two
times both electrons up.
Up, up.
Plus alpha one beta two
times the first electron up, the second electron down.
Then beta one alpha two...
Beta one times alpha two times down up.
And then finally, plus beta one beta two
down, down.
This two-electron state...
This two-electron state, which was obtained
by combining two one-electron states,
corresponds...
corresponds to a state in which each electron
has comfortably been placed in its own state
sort of independently.
That's what this is.
If you were, for example, to take such a state,
you would find
that there is a state,
there is some direction
in which sigma one is definitely up.
Remember, for any electron state
that you can make with an alpha and a beta,
there is always some direction
in which sigma is...
sigma dot n is up.
This state has that property.
With the same...
Just using alpha one and
beta one in the same way,
you'll find a direction in space
such that sigma one
is definitely positive.
It'll be the same direction
as you would have gotten
by just looking at the one-electron system by itself.
Same thing for the two-electron,
for the second electron.
There exists some direction,
a different direction in general,
a different direction
in which the second electron
is also pointing along the positive axis.
You can check
that if these two states
have the property
that this one is definitely up,
this one is definitely along the n-axis,
and this one is definitely along the m-axis,
then you can check
that the thing that you've composed in this way
has the same property
with respect to the more complicated
two-electron system.
Remember, sigma one only acts on the ups...
Sorry, on the first electron.
Sigma... tau... sorry.
Sigma acts on the first electron.
Tau acts on the second electron.
And you can check
that this two-electron state
has all the properties you would expect
if you simply had two distinct electrons
that had been prepared completely separately,
never talking to each other independently.
Not necessarily in the same state,
two different states.
For example,
if you just put electron one
in magnetic field pointing this way
and electron two
in magnetic field pointing this way,
and let them come to rest
and let them give off their photon
or not give off their photon,
then that's what this kind of state is.
That's what a product state would be.
It's called a product state.
It's a simple product state.
And it always has
a pair of directions
along which
each electron is polarized.
That's the word.
To say that the electron
is definitely up along some axis
is to say it's polarized along that axis.
Now I'm going to construct for you
a state
which obviously doesn't have that property,
which does not have the property
that there's some direction
along which the spin is up.
And it is an entangled state.
It's one that does not have the property
that you can think of it
as two separate electrons
which have been prepared independently,
each one with its own state.
Somehow the electrons are more intricately entangled.
The state of the electrons
are more intimately entangled.
Here's a state.
It's very simple.
One electron is up.
The other electron is down.
And you add to that
the first electron down
and the second electron up.
Of course, you'll have to put
a one over square root of two
to normalize it.
And you'll have to put
a one over square root of two down.
But that one over square root of two
is not going to play any role
in what I say.
Here's a state.
And this state has the property.
If you think about what this state means,
it has the following property.
That if you measure electron number two
and find it's down,
then electron number one must be up.
And if you find electron number two up,
then electron number one is down.
This state has a funny property
that if you know that it's in this state,
if you happen to know that it's in this state,
the combined system,
then you would learn something
about the second electron
by measuring the first electron.
This state has the property
that if you measure
the second electron to be down,
then the first electron is up.
And if you measure the second electron to be up,
the second one is down.
Now the first one is down.
You know what I mean.
I'm getting tongue-tied.
It's getting too late.
Let me prove something to you.
Let me prove that every one of the sigma matrices
as well as the tau matrices
has average value zero
in this state.
Remember how to calculate the average value?
You sandwich the operator that you're interested
between the state and its...
the same state on one side and the other.
Okay?
Supposing it were true.
Supposing the expectation value
of all three of the sigmas was zero.
Then it will also be true
that the expectation value
of any sigma dot n will be zero.
If the expectation value of sigma dot n is zero,
that means that there's a half a probability
for it to be up along that direction
and a half a probability for it to be down.
So if all of the expectation values
of all three sigmas are equal to zero,
then there can be no direction
along which sigma is definitely up
because along any direction
the probabilities are a half a half.
So let's see if we can prove that.
Let's take the three sigmas and check.
First of all, we have to
make a bra vector out of this.
All of the coefficients are real
so there's no complex conjugation.
The one over square root of two
is not going to play any interesting role here.
It doesn't do anything.
Let's make the corresponding bra vector.
The corresponding bra vector
also is the sum of two terms.
And it's up down plus down up.
And now let's pick a sigma.
Let's start with sigma one.
Sigma one and then same state
except the ket version of it,
up down plus down up.
Okay, now we know how sigma one acts.
What does sigma one do?
It acts on the first entry here
and it changes, it intertwines up and down.
That's all it does.
It changes up to down in the first entry
and down to up.
So sigma one on this state here
is the sum of two terms.
Up goes to down, down down.
And takes this down and makes it up.
The other side here, I've done nothing.
Up down plus down up.
What's the inner product of up down with down down?
Well, I didn't tell you that.
Well, I didn't tell you.
But the answer is zero.
They correspond to physically different situations
where one electron, which was up over here,
is down over here.
That always means they're orthogonal.
Different labels always correspond to orthogonality.
Up down, up up, down down, and down up
are all mutually orthogonal to each other.
That's an assumption.
But it goes together with the idea
that these are
measurable, distinctly different configurations.
So, we have an up down
and a down up over here.
But no up down and no down up over here.
So these must be orthogonal.
Everything here is orthogonal to everything here.
And the inner product is just plain zero.
You'll only get something if there's something common
between the left, between the
bra vector and the ket vector.
That's the only way you can get something non-zero.
That's the expectation value of sigma one.
What about the expectation value of sigma two?
Well, sigma two does about the
same thing that sigma one does,
except it throws in some i's and some minus signs.
But still, there's up down here and down up.
Over here, there's only down down and up up.
So it's still orthogonal.
This is still orthogonal to this.
The expectation value of sigma two is zero.
We found the expectation value of
sigma one is equal to zero.
The expectation value of sigma two is equal to zero.
The only one left is sigma three.
So let's check sigma three.
What does sigma three do on this?
Well, keeps it up. Does nothing.
What does it do to this one?
Minus sign.
So sigma three just multiplies this one by minus.
Now let's look at the inner product.
What's the inner product of up down with up down?
One.
What's the inner product of up down with down up?
They're different situations.
Zero.
Down up with up down?
And up down, sorry, down up with down up?
There's one, but there's a minus sign.
So we found all three
expectation values are equal to zero.
We've encountered a situation which is impossible
if every electron had its own state
in the same sense that it
would happen in the same way.
So, let's say that it would have a state
as if there was just a one electron system.
For any one electron system, there is always some
axis such that sigma dot n is equal to one.
That the expectation value of sigma
dot n is equal to one.
And incidentally, in any eigenvector of a
quantity, the expectation value is just that eigenvalue.
So there's always some direction that
sigma dot n is equal to one.
But if all three components
of sigma have zero expectation value,
then every sigma dot n
expectation value is equal to zero.
So, in every single direction in space, the probability is
a half a half to find the electron up or down.
This is something new.
When we concentrated on single electrons
and prepared them in magnetic fields,
no matter how we prepared it with a magnetic field,
we found directions where the electron
spin was pointing in that direction.
Now when we have two electrons, in this interesting state,
where measuring one tells you something about the other,
we find something new.
We find that there is
no direction, or in every direction,
the expectation value of sigma is equal to zero.
Equivalently, any direction that you measure the spin along,
you'll find 50-50 probability that it's either up or down.
There'll be no bias toward upness
or downness along any axis whatever.
Which is quite different than you might have expected
if you just had independent
electrons, prepared them with magnetic fields.
This is something new.
Something that cannot be if the only possible states were
the ones that were like just having two independent electrons prepared.
It's called an entangled state.
And as I said, the one way
you can read off that it's entangled
is from the fact that if you
measure one, you learn something about the other.
Okay.
Now, how odd a phenomenon is this?
We're going to dwell on this at length,
but this is our
first experience seeing quantum entanglement.
I'm a little confused though.
You're trying to make, I guess
what I'd call a direct measurement,
or the first one gives...
Nonsense, it's a contradictory thing.
But you started off by saying, well another way to
do this is to measure the spin of the second one.
And then you could say something
about the spin of the first one.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, two separate things.
Making spin, trying to measure the spin of the
second one, it's a separate thing for you and me.
Let's for a minute forget the statement about
measuring one and learning something about the other.
Let's forget that for a minute.
So we found the system that no matter what
direction you put the magnetic field on electron one,
forget electron two,
no matter what direction
you impose the magnetic field,
you'll always find 50-50 probability.
This is something that would not have happened
had you created the electrons
independently by their own magnetic field.
There's another question, how do
you create electrons in this state?
In this state over here.
And we'll come to that.
But for the moment, apparently in the mathematics,
there are a collection of state vectors,
or a collection of quantum states,
which have properties that know,
well, that are odd.
Now they do have the property, we're going to come
to this in a moment, we'll come back to it.
Supposing you measure electron one
and find it in some state,
do you learn anything about electron two?
The answer will be yes.
It will be just as
you might expect, as I said,
if you measure electron two up,
you will find electron one down.
How odd is this from
a simple probability point of view?
Well, in some sense, it's not that odd.
In some sense.
Supposing I have, you know, a penny and a dime.
Okay?
And I take the penny and the dime,
well, let's suppose for the moment that the
penny and the dime are exactly the same size,
so I can't tell the difference with my hand.
And I take them and I shake them up,
and without looking, I grab one and I
grab the other and I take them far apart.
Guess what?
If I look at this one and I find it's
a dime, I instantly know this one is a penny.
Likewise, if I look at this one and I find
it's a penny, I instantly know this one's a dime.
Without any lag, without any time lag.
So that's a classical version of entangled probabilities.
It's not all that odd.
Uh...
Question?
Or at least at first
sight, it doesn't seem terribly odd.
The difference...
Well, I think we'll come to
it next time, what the difference is.
There is a difference, and we'll come to it.
But just from a simple probabilistic point of view,
let's say just measuring the
upness and downness of electrons,
at first sight, it seems no odder
than the situation where I have
a penny and a dime.
I shake them up and I don't look, and
I ask about the probabilities when I take them apart.
You know what? First of all,
there'll be 50-50 probability that it's
up or down, either one of them,
no matter which one I look at,
if I only look at one of them.
But if I look at one, then
I instantly know what the other one does.
Only if you're sure that you
have a penny and a dime.
Only if I'm sure that I
had a penny and a dime. Exactly.
And the corresponding thing is true here.
Only if I'm sure that I've
prepared the two-electron system in this state.
When you make the sigma-3 measurement, you're
measuring for both of them being up.
Is that what you're saying?
When you make a sigma measurement on both of them,
No, no, when you make a
sigma measurement on both of them, yeah.
Of this pair, of this pair.
And the probability that they both will be
up is zero. Is that what you're saying?
That is true.
Is that what you mean?
It is true that the probability of
both of them is up to zero.
Right, because essentially they're all pointing,
classically you would say that they're...
Yeah, I can tell you something else.
You can define the new observable quantity.
The product of the two sigmas,
well, that's not a good example.
This is not the right state.
Okay, well, that's, yes, but what you're saying,
Oh.
Um...
No, what I'm going to say is wrong.
But you... What is it that
you said? You said that the, uh...
You're not just measuring one of them and
finding the other one is in the opposite direction.
You're measuring both in one measurement and finding that...
If you measure... Right, right.
If you measure both in one
measurement, you will find they're opposite.
But you could say you don't
have to measure them both simultaneously.
You could measure one of them over
here, and then your friend down there,
it doesn't even have to be you, your
friend down there can measure the other one.
And then you can communicate, and then you can come
together and talk about what you discovered and so forth.
You can be sure that if you discovered a penny,
you can be sure that when your friend
comes over and tells you what she discovered,
that it will be a dime, unless something intervened.
It seems to me it's like you had the
penny and the dime in the amount of a rod,
so that when one of them is
heads up, the other one is heads down,
and you didn't see this rod,
but no matter how you shook it,
you would never get two heads
or two tails, because they're connected.
Well, there are ways to shake
it that you might disturb it, but...
But I mean, one of them would
be up, I mean, because they're welded together.
Well, in the classical case, you just
started with a penny and a dime,
so you just know that there's
always a penny and a dime.
Unless, of course, an alchemist takes the
penny and comes in with a dime.
I'm sorry, there's something going on here that nobody...
That was in the Hamiltonian system.
Yeah, exactly. Right.
I was taught the law of large
numbers to find probabilities and statistical analysis.
And I was wondering what there is about this
that the law of large numbers is not used for.
No, no, we're using the laws
of large numbers in many cases.
We're using the laws of large
numbers, but at the moment I'm not.
But in many cases, when I
say the expectation value of something,
the expectation value is something that you only measure
by doing many, many repeated experiments and gathering data.
But in this very simple case of the penny
and the dime, I need only do one experiment.
If I do one experiment and I find that penny,
I know that the other person will find the dime.
Now, you may want to do this over
and over again. You may want to collect data.
You may want to do the same experiment
over and over and check that it really works.
That every time I find
a penny, she finds a dime.
Every time I find a dime, she finds a penny.
So we would perhaps like to do
this experiment over and over and over again
and check that statistically this
correlation, it's called a correlation,
that this correlation exists between what
she measures and what I measure.
It would be necessary to
do it over and over again
and collect statistics about it.
But what we should find is
that every single time we do it,
there will be, we could call it an anti-correlation between
what one person sees and what the other person sees.
Okay?
So entanglement of probabilities is not that odd a thing.
It just means you know something about the combined system
and that that something doesn't get
disturbed perhaps as you separate the things.
The odd thing is you could separate the two
people, one with a penny and one with a dime,
take her off to Alpha Centauri where it takes
four years to get information from one to the other.
Nevertheless, the instant I look at my penny,
I know what my friend out there will find.
She doesn't. She doesn't. But I do.
You're not saying that that setup
is what we should be thinking about?
At a classical level, that's
what you should be thinking about.
But we're going to find, we're going
to find, that's what Bell's theorem is about.
Bell's theorem is about the difference
between the situation that I just described
and the corresponding quantum system.
Yeah, but we know how to make it.
Yeah.
Let me put a minus sign in here.
It won't change anything.
Nothing will change.
We'll put minus signs here, but
then it'll have exactly the same effect.
Okay.
It's a better state.
Okay, here's how you make it.
Remember that each electron is itself a magnet.
First of all, I'll tell
you what this state corresponds to.
It corresponds to the magnets being oppositely oriented,
but without any preference to the other.
So, this is what it's supposed to be.
So, this is the moment for which direction, all right?
So, whichever way one magnet is pointing, the
other one is pointing in the opposite direction.
And that naturally happens if
you bring two electrons together.
Because bringing one electron into
the field of the other electron,
they naturally, one electron wants
to respond to the other electron
and make its magnetic moment in the opposite direction.
So, if you brought the
electrons together in some wrong configuration,
they would emit a photon
and jump to an opposite configuration.
So, all you have to do is bring
the two electrons together, leave them for a while.
A photon either will or won't be emitted, and
after a while, they will be in this state.
They'll be in this state because the
two magnets will try to anti-align each other,
but there's no particular preference for them
to anti-align this way, this way, this way.
And so, you'll have something.
You'll have something which is the same in every direction,
but no matter what direction you measure the spin,
you'll find that the other
one is in the opposite direction.
So, the preparation here is just to have two electrons.
Is what?
Just to have two electrons in practice.
Yeah, really, that's right.
And just bring them together
and leave them for a while.
And they'll go into this so-called singlet state.
This is the singlet state of two electrons, yeah.
So, it's the same as the Pauli's exclusion principle?
No, no, no.
At the moment, there's no exclusion principle.
We don't have to think about the exclusion principle
for the reason that we've definitely put
the electrons at different places in space.
If they're in different places in space, then
there's no issue about the Pauli exclusion principle.
Yeah, yeah, if you bring them so that they're wave-fo...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
...nailed down and we know where they are,
you don't have to bring
them on top of each other.
You just have to bring them
close enough that their magnetic fields interact,
can feel each other.
And then, if the electrons are parallel,
that's like having two magnets which are parallel,
the north poles repel each other,
and it has more energy than if they're anti-parallel.
And so, what'll happen is it'll emit
a photon and somehow come out with opposite...
Yeah.
...polarization.
And this is what will happen to those two electrons.
So it's really just using one electron
as the magnet which polarizes the other electron.
Yeah.
So in an electron beam,
you have a pair of electrons.
Yeah, a pair of electrons.
And this is the pair of electrons in the muons.
Say it again.
In one electron beam, a
pair of electrons in the muons.
Electron beam, oh, oh, oh, oh.
Well, if you have an electron...
Do I have a pair of electrons in there?
You have to...
All right, if the electrons
are far apart from each other,
and in an electron beam, the electrons are very far...
No, no, they're very far apart.
Oh, yes.
Electrons...
An electron beam is a very, very dilute thing.
Okay?
Believe me, electrons are very, very far apart
by comparison with the length scales inside an electron.
Imagine they cross over on an electron beam.
They cross over.
You mean they hit each other?
No.
They cross over.
Right.
If you have two beams of electrons, then something...
A single exchange.
Oh.
They still don't get all that close to each other.
They still...
Well, an electron and a single beam, to a
good approximation, they don't interact with each other very much.
There is some Coulomb repulsion between them,
but there's very little spin-spin interaction between them.
They're too far apart.
It's too dilute.
What's that?
What should be the distance for the interaction?
Ah, okay.
The magnetic moment has units of length.
The magnetic moment is the magnetic
charge times the distance between them.
Okay?
So the magnetic moment has units of length, and that's the
length which sets the scale about how close the electrons should be.
So in other words, they should
be within that...roughly within that distance.
And then in a fairly rapid time...
Look, it's a question of time scales.
No matter how far apart the electrons are, they will
eventually settle down to their ground state, which was the opposite...
Eventually they will.
It's a question of how long you're willing
to wait for the photon to get emitted.
So if the electrons are far apart, then the difference between the energy of two parallel ones
and two anti-parallel ones is so tiny that the photon that's emitted is such a long wavelength photon,
it's a very, very, very long
time for that process to happen.
So in a typical electron beam, there just isn't enough time
for the electron magnetic moments to feel each other very much.
Now, of course, if the electrons collide, then,
in fact, you do make states like this typically.
So that does happen.
So what should be the distance between
two electrons in such a way that they...
10 to the minus 11 centimeters or something like that.
Yeah?
Yeah.
Why does that state have a minus sign
in it instead of a plus sign in it?
Oh, we'll have to do that.
We'll have to...
Yeah, that's by no means obvious.
That's far from obvious.
Right.
I will tell you...
But I'll tell you the answer anyway.
I'll tell you the answer anyway.
No, I won't.
I'll tell you the answer next time.
Time to go.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.