This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Let's go on from where we were.
We were talking about how systems change with time.
I want to go back over that since
partly I don't remember where we were exactly.
But second of all, it's always
worth going over last week's material.
It does not mean I don't have to
make new notes. I always throw away my notes
to make absolutely sure that I don't use the
same notes twice. That's a very bad thing to do.
Okay, but I do like to go over the material
that we studied last week and just make sure everybody
has it solidly. All right, so the state
of a system is described by a ket vector,
and we call it psi. Now up till now we've
just thought of a psi as a thing which doesn't depend
on time. In fact, we haven't even talked about
time. We did last week, but before last week we
didn't even talk about time. We just
looked at the interrelationship between quantum states,
observables, measurements, and other things. So
we're going to go over that.
Okay, so here we have a system of time.
Now we want to know the interrelationship between
time and space, right? So we had time
and space and that sort of thing. Now we
want to ask how the quantum state changes with time.
So we want to put a time argument in there.
It's simply a vector which moves around in the vector
space with time. Roll is that it moves
around under the influence of a linear operator.
And so we can write that psi
of t is some unit, some linear operator,
zero. That's about the most general thing
that we could write down. So far I
haven't told you what u is, but it's
the most general thing that I could write
down under the assumption that
state vectors change linearly. Now that's
something that, as I've emphasized many times,
I cannot give you a proof of.
It's basically a postulate, but it's
a postulate that's rooted in an experiment,
plus the fact that anybody who ever
tries to change it and do something
different always winds up in
some conceptual problems. Energy isn't
conserved or something else, something
bad. Probability isn't well-defined or
whatever. So we'll take it as a postulate
that the way systems change with time is
through linear operators. Linear
operators just mean basically matrices,
but matrices which are now time dependent.
We can apply the same rule or
a
rule or a
rule or the analogous or the
related rule, actually the complex conjugate rule,
to how bra vectors change with time. So
here's some other bra vector, and this is
basically the complex conjugate of some ket
vector, and so we have to complex
conjugate on the right-hand side, phi of zero,
but then instead of u we have to
write the conjugate. U of t is the conjugate of
t, and then we have to write the conjugate of t.
Remember what dagger means? From the point of
view of matrices, it means you do two operations.
You complex conjugate all the elements, and you
reflect them. You transpose them about the diagonal.
So these two rules are basically the same rule,
one of them just the complex conjugate of the other.
Now the assumption about how systems change, you can express it
in various ways. You can just express it as probability conservation.
If the total probability is equal to one, which it's supposed
to be, then it should remain that way for all time.
What is the total probability? The total probability is the inner
product of the vector with itself, of the state vector with itself.
And so we always write that physical real state vectors satisfy psi psi
equals one, and we're not going to allow that to change with time.
So that means that for all time, psi dagger psi, or
psi conjugate psi, taking the inner product, should be unchanged with time.
It's not hard to prove from that that the inner
product of any two vectors has to be time independent.
It's rather easy to prove. I'm going
to... I'll tell you how you do it.
How would you do it for ordinary vectors?
How would you prove for ordinary vectors that if the length of every
vector stays fixed, then the inner product between any pair of vectors stays fixed?
And the way you do it is you take any
pair of vectors, and you look at the difference of them.
There's the difference of the two vectors.
Now if the assumption is that the
length of every vector stays invariant, stays unchanged,
when you do some operation,
some linear operation in particular,
that means the sides of each one of
these triangles shouldn't change under the corresponding operation.
If the sides of the triangle don't change, that means the angle between
these two vectors, as well as the length of these two vectors, doesn't change,
and therefore the inner product, or
the dot product between them, doesn't change.
So from the assumption that the length
of every vector doesn't change with time,
the inner product with itself, it's also possible to prove that
the inner product between any pair of them doesn't change with time.
If that's true, we can now
write down a more general statement
that phi of t, inner product with psi of t,
is exactly equal to phi at time zero,
times psi at time zero.
If the inner product doesn't change.
Okay, now plug in that phi of t and
psi of t are related by this object called u,
and so that becomes phi of zero,
u dagger of t, u of t,
u of t because that's what you
do to psi, times psi of zero.
So now we have a simple rule.
That phi of zero, that u dagger
u, sandwiched between any pair of vectors whatever,
is just equal to the inner product of
the same pair of vectors without u dagger u.
That's a simple elementary theorem that if the
inner product of the matrix element of an operator
is equal to the inner product for all vectors,
then you can immediately conclude that u
dagger u is just the unit operator.
So the only way to make this happen
is if u dagger u, for every vector,
I mean the point is this is
true for every vector in the vector space,
the only way that can be true is if
u dagger u, u dagger u is equal to one.
An operator with that product,
a linear operator with that product,
is called unitary.
It's the analog, it's the
analog for numbers, for complex numbers,
of a complex number having
unit length in the complex plane.
It's the analog of a number having
the form e to the i theta.
e to the i theta times its
own complex conjugate is equal to one.
That's not what a unitary operator
is, but it's the analog of that.
That the operator times its permission
conjugate is equal to the unit operator.
Okay.
Then we, I think we derived this last time,
I think we derived much of what I'm
going to say today, but let's do it anyway.
Supposing now, to get an idea
of how, of what u is,
supposing instead of allowing time to
evolve for a large amount of time,
but let's just allow it
to evolve for a long time,
for a very short amount of time.
Now this is something that
one is always doing in physics,
studying how things change with respect to some parameter
by chopping up the change into little infinitesimal pieces,
and then studying how things change under an infinitesimal,
under a very small change,
and then building up big changes by superimposing,
or what's the right word, juxtaposing lots of small changes.
So, take the time interval,
chop it up into a lot of small changes,
into little pieces,
and instead of asking what u
is for a finite amount of time,
ask what u would be for
a very, very small time interval,
and then we'll try to build up what
u should be for a large time interval.
If we know how a system
changes over every small time interval,
then it should be possible to build
up how it changes over long time intervals.
This is exactly, of course,
the same logic as Newtonian mechanics,
where you study the motion of a system
by breaking up the time interval into little tiny segments,
and then deriving differential equations.
So it's not a new idea,
so we're going to take
the time t to be small.
t equals epsilon,
that just means it's small,
and the assumption is that epsilon is small enough
that epsilon squared can be ignored.
Standard small parameter,
approximation,
epsilon is small and epsilon squared is much smaller,
so we ignore it.
Alright, now, if the time was equal to zero,
but t equals zero,
then u must just be one.
Why is that?
Times zero amount of time
shouldn't change the system at all.
If the system evolves for no
time at all, it shouldn't change,
and obviously u should then just be the unit operator.
The small correction,
the small correction should be proportional to epsilon.
I'm going to write minus,
and now this is completely arbitrary,
I'm only putting in these factors here
because I know that eventually I'm going to want to,
I'm going to want to put them in.
Minus i,
now the important factor is epsilon,
a small change in time should
lead to a small change in u,
times an object which we'll call h,
and now I'm going to put
in all the factors that really belong
that would be there in the textbook.
In the textbook, there would be an h bar,
Planck's constant.
Now, this is entirely conventional,
meaning to say that there's no
content in putting the i here,
or the epsilon, or the h bar.
It could all be absorbed into h,
and then change the name
of h and call it w.
So, there's no content,
none whatever,
in putting this i and this epsilon
and this h bar into the expression.
It's just that for purposes of comparison with other things,
with other things that
were already pre-established by history,
basically by history,
it's more, it's got less to do with
physics than it has to do with history,
we put in these factors.
The epsilon, of course, really belongs there.
That you cannot get rid of
because it's just telling you that the time is now.
The time interval is small.
But other than that,
everything else is a pure convention.
Okay, but let's, using this convention,
let's see what u dagger u equals 1 says.
So, we have to multiply, first
of all, what is u dagger?
u dagger is 1 plus i epsilon h dagger
divided by, what is h bar?
h bar is Planck's constant, of course.
Anybody know what Planck's constant is?
6.6 into minus 27,
37,000 seconds.
Why is it such a ridiculous number?
Historical.
But what the, yeah, I know,
but why, what insane person
chose it to be such a,
what history would make it so small,
so ridiculous and...
Planck was spinning curves.
Planck was what?
Planck was spinning the thermodynamic curves.
Yeah, but why did the number come out so ridiculous?
Ridiculously small.
I was hoping you would tell us.
Okay, okay.
Let's ask you another question.
Why is the speed of light so big?
No, yeah, why is, is that a good one?
Why is Avogadro's number so big?
Because we're big.
Hmm?
Yeah.
It's because chemists wanted a unit
that they could manipulate with their hands, okay?
They had little beakers and other
things that they put fluids into,
and gases,
and how big were the containers?
They were big enough to hold in your hand,
they were big enough to tip over,
to do things with,
and so it was natural that the natural unit
of measure of substance,
in this particular case gases,
should be the amount of
gas that's held in a container
about as big as a human being.
Okay, maybe 50 times smaller than a human being,
but that's all.
Well, so the question then
is a question not of physics,
but nothing to do with physics.
It has to do with human biology.
Why does it take 10 to the 27th atoms,
or something that's more than that,
10 to the 30th atoms or whatever,
to make a human being?
The answer is that with many fewer atoms than that,
you couldn't make complicated enough circuitry and so forth
to make an intelligent thing that can ask questions.
So it's the people-thropic principle
that if you weren't this big,
you simply couldn't ask the question,
so you better be that big.
That's the reason that Planck's constant is small.
It's the reason that the electron mass is so small.
And so it really doesn't mean anything fundamental
from the point of view of physics.
It's just a choice of units,
and it's a choice of units which goes back historically
to a time when people didn't know about macroscopic physics,
and so they worked with large, large numbers of electrons
and large, large numbers of atoms
because they themselves were large.
Okay, so H-bar is just there because we're big.
H is there because you've got to put something there.
The dagger is there because you
have to take the Hermitian conjugate.
The epsilon is there because we're talking about
a small deviation from t equals zero.
And the i is there because
it will save me writing i's later on.
Okay, you'll see in a
moment why the i is there.
All right, so what does U dagger U equal?
We have to say U dagger U equal to one,
so that's one plus i epsilon H dagger over H-bar
times one minus i epsilon H divided by H-bar.
That's U dagger U.
And then we ignore everything of order epsilon squared,
and so the only thing that
appears is one plus i epsilon H
bar H dagger over H-bar.
That's this term, and the other term is minus
almost the same thing, H.
The only difference between them
is one has an H dagger
and the other has an H.
But our rule is that that
has to be equal to one.
All right, so that being equal to one
says I can cancel out
the one on the left-hand side
and set the result equal to zero.
Another way to write the same thing, simpler,
is just that H dagger equals H.
That's the condition that U be unitary,
that H be Hermitian.
Hermitian means equal to its complex conjugate.
Now, we've already argued,
and you've accepted it so there's nothing new,
that I'm going to write this.
That observables, the things that
you measure in the laboratory,
correspond to Hermitian operators.
Hermitian operators are observables,
our observables are Hermitian operators.
So, whatever this object is, H,
it's an observable.
According to the formal definition
in quantum mechanics of observables,
it's a Hermitian operator.
It must correspond to something that you can measure.
Moreover, it's got to be something very general.
Precisely what its form is may not be general,
precisely what operator,
but every system has one of these.
Otherwise, it couldn't change with time.
So, the existence of some kind of thing called H
is very, very general.
All systems have them.
H is, of course, the Hamiltonian.
The Hamiltonian means the energy.
Thought of as an operator,
it's called the Hamiltonian.
Thought of as a quantity that you measure,
it's called the energy.
Sort of a redundant notation.
We call it H, we could also call it E,
for energy.
It's the same thing.
We usually reserve the label E
for the eigenvalues, for the things you actually measure,
and H is the operator.
Okay, now you can ask me,
why is that the energy?
Well,
what other definitions so far do you have?
What do you have of energy?
Anybody got any other definition of energy?
See, it's classical.
It's classical physics,
which gives you energy.
Okay, what's the definition of classical physics?
P squared over two.
Hmm?
P squared over two, yeah.
Oh, we're not, at the moment,
no, that's not the definition of energy.
That's most certainly not,
that is the energy of a non-relativistic free particle,
but it's certainly not the general definition of energy.
... to do work.
... changing of the energy.
... four seconds over distance.
... work back.
Yeah, we could work at it from that end,
but to work at it from that end,
we would have to work,
that's a very special situation
where you have non-relativistic objects,
we have non-relativistic forces,
the structure of energy,
would that help you?
Would that help you understand, for example,
the energy stored in the electromagnetic field,
saying that it's mass times velocity,
or mass times velocity squared, or whatever?
No.
There's some much more general concept,
there's some much more general concept,
and one way of characterizing it
is that it's conserved.
That's the single most important thing about it,
that it doesn't change with time,
and that for certain familiar systems,
it takes a certain form.
For certain familiar systems,
Add that to the statement that the whole shebang,
all kinds of energies,
don't change with time,
the sum of them,
and that's what energy is.
So the most important thing that,
if we're just taking an abstract system,
and we don't know how to relate it
to any particular non-relativistic classical system,
the first thing we would look for
in a definition of energy,
would be that it's conserved,
that it doesn't change with time.
We'll come back to it.
We'll come back to it today.
Why is this object an
object that doesn't change with time?
In what sense doesn't it change with time?
We'll come back to it.
Okay, so now we have an object
which will give it its name,
it's called the Hamiltonian,
and we now know that the evolution of the system
for a small amount of time
is characterized by this expression here.
Okay, let's see if we can make
a differential equation
for the change of a system with time.
Why a differential equation?
Well, if we know how a system changes
over very small time intervals,
it's natural to think of a differential equation
evolving it from one instant to the next.
So instead of looking at psi,
let's look at the time derivative of psi,
d by dt of psi.
Well, that's equal, essentially by definition,
psi of epsilon minus psi of zero.
Incidentally, any time could be taken
to be the zero of time.
There's nothing special about zero.
It's just a small shift of time.
t equals epsilon.
The starting point was arbitrary.
The important thing is that we change
the time by a little bit.
So we change the time by a little bit,
and now we have to divide by epsilon,
and that's the derivative,
the time derivative of the state vector.
Okay, we have what psi of epsilon is.
Where is psi of epsilon?
Yeah, psi of epsilon is gotten by applying
one minus ih over h bar.
Psi of zero is just gotten
by applying one.
So what is this here?
This is one minus,
and now one minus iepsilon h over h bar.
Did I get that right?
No, I didn't.
Psi of epsilon is this
minus psi of zero.
That just cancels out,
the second term just cancels out the one.
So the difference in the numerator
is nothing but i minus iepsilon h over h bar
times psi of zero.
That's the difference between
psi of epsilon and psi of zero.
Now divide it by epsilon.
That just cancels out the epsilon.
And that's it.
That's another way to think about h.
It's basically apart from this
factor of i over h bar,
it's the operator which tells you how psi changes
differentially with time.
How it changes the time derivative of it.
d by dt of psi is equal to this.
Now that's great.
That tells you how psi changes with time
from instant to instant.
It tells you the small change
over any small lapse of time.
So you can't just say,
oh, it's a differential equation.
Or basically, it's a differential equation
for the state vector psi.
This equation has a name.
It's called the Schrodinger equation.
You're probably not used to seeing it in that form.
Anybody have a favorite form for the Schrodinger equation
that we want to compare this with?
I like to spell it with the R first.
What's that?
I like to spell it R-O instead of O-R.
Schrodinger.
We've got Schrodinger.
H-R-O with an umlaut.
Yeah, umlaut.
Or E.
Yeah.
It's close enough.
It's within an H bar.
And that's it.
That's all of quantum mechanics in a nutshell.
If somebody tells you what psi is at time zero,
you evolve it using the Schrodinger equation.
You find it at a later time.
You know the state at a later time.
You make some measurements,
and psi gives you the
probabilities for all the measurements.
That's it.
That's the whole story.
There's nothing else but that in quantum mechanics.
This tells you how things change.
We already figured out, if you know the state vector,
how to calculate expectation values
and probabilities and so forth.
And that's it.
Okay, but we don't want to just stop there.
Okay.
Let's try to solve this for some simple situations.
Let's see, first of all,
you know, there is another definition of energy
that I'm sure you've seen before.
It doesn't come from classical physics.
It comes from Einstein and the photon.
Anybody know what I'm thinking of?
Hm?
Yeah, what's the formula?
E equals h nu, right?
E equals h nu.
Or h bar omega.
Omega, nu is frequency in cycles per second.
Omega is frequency in radians per second.
H bar is the thing that goes with omega.
The other Planck's constant, h,
is the thing which goes with frequency.
Frequency times the old Planck's constant
is equal to angular frequency
times the new Planck's constant.
Okay, you all know that.
So, let's see if we can understand
why this h here
might have something to do with this energy here.
Okay, let's see if we can figure that out.
Let's solve the Schrodinger equation.
But what I want to do is,
since h is a Hermitian operator,
it certainly has eigenvectors.
In fact, every Hermitian operator
has a complete set of eigenvectors.
So there's some basis, some basis of states,
some orthonormal basis of states,
which are the eigenvectors of h.
Let's imagine working in that basis.
Okay?
And let's pick one of the eigenvectors
with eigenvalue e.
e is the eigenvalue, so h on psi
is equal to e times psi.
Now, what happens if you start
with an eigenvector of h?
Well, I assert that it will
stay an eigenvector of h with time,
because if you want to do that,
you'll wait a little bit of time.
You'll be adding in, basically d by dt means,
just what are you adding in?
What are you adding into psi?
You're adding in i epsilon h times psi.
But since h times psi is proportional to psi itself,
what you're adding in, in a little time interval,
is just something proportional to the original vector
that you started with,
if psi is an eigenvector of the Hamiltonian.
So if psi is an eigenvector of the Hamiltonian,
it will stay an eigenvector
of the Hamiltonian for all time,
because the little things that you add in
are pointing in the same direction.
And if you add an eigenvector,
if you add, you know, you're just multiplying
the eigenvector by a number.
So let's look for a solution of the equation
of the form, it's always the same,
psi now is by definition,
this is, let me put a little e here,
to indicate that it is the eigenvector with energy e.
Let's look for a solution of the form
psi sub e of t
is equal to, or just psi of t,
is equal to psi sub e of zero,
in fact that's redundant, we don't even need that,
just some eigenvector of the energy,
times a function of time.
Let's see if we can solve the equation that way.
Okay, what is d by dt of psi
if psi is just f
of t times a constant vector?
Well, if this is a constant vector,
you just differentiate the f of t.
So the left hand side
is, let's call it f dot,
f dot means d by dt of f.
Standard notation, a dot over something means
you're differentiating with respect to time.
Alright, so f dot times psi,
that's d by dt,
and that's equal to minus i h over h bar
times psi of zero, psi e.
But h on psi e
is just e times psi e.
Did I leave something out?
What did I leave out?
Minus i e over h bar, so, hm?
Oh, I'm sorry, f of t, yes, good.
f, f of t, very good.
Okay, this suggests, or not suggests,
it says that we can find the solution
if we just find the solution of the equation
f dot is equal to minus
i e over h bar times f.
f of t, the time derivative of f,
is just proportional to f itself.
Alright, now,
this is not such a difficult differential equation.
It says the derivative is proportional
to the thing itself.
We know how to solve an equation like that.
Solution to an equation like that is exponentials.
If you have an equation
that says d f by dt
is equal to some constant,
and all of this is a constant over here,
a constant times f,
then the solution to that equation
is f is equal to e to the c t.
If you differentiate an exponential,
it just pulls down the coefficient of the time
in the exponential.
So the solution of any equation of the form
that the derivative is proportional to the thing itself
is an exponential, and now we can read off
what the solution is.
Here's the constant.
f is equal to e to the
minus i e over h bar times t.
It could be a constant times that,
but apart from a constant,
the solution of f is this.
We've now solved the Schrodinger equation.
The Schrodinger equation, the solution,
the time dependence of the Schrodinger equation
for an eigenvector of the Hamiltonian
is just to multiply by e to
the minus i e over h bar t
times psi of zero.
Well, what is this here?
e to the minus i e over h bar,
that's a combination of sine,
or we call it cosine,
cosine of i e over
h bar t plus i sine,
i e over h bar t,
so what is this?
Frequency.
Frequency, omega.
So what do we see?
We see that f is e
to the minus i omega t,
where omega is equal to e over h bar.
Now, suppose I hadn't told
you that e was the energy.
Supposing I hadn't told you before that h
is the Hamiltonian and that e is the energy,
at this point, we might look at this and say,
ooh, I've seen that equation before,
e equals h bar omega,
this left-hand side must be the energy.
From a quantum point of view
and from the point of view
of Einstein and photons and Planck and all that stuff,
we would recognize the left-hand side as the energy.
Not so clear that this has
anything to do with the energy
from Einstein, but it's not so clear.
It's not so clear that this is the energy
from Newtonian mechanics and so forth.
But in order to study that relationship,
we would have to be talking about systems
which have a natural, non-relativistic
mechanical interpretation, and we're not at this point.
So this is as close as
we can get to a derivation of,
for an explanation of why we call e the energy.
It is the thing that Einstein would have recognized
as the,
energy in this equation.
We have the cosine and the sine.
Yeah.
Should that be a minus sign?
And do you want, you
don't have i's inside the sine?
No.
You don't want the i's inside the sine?
No, I don't. Thank you.
Right. Cosine e over h bar t
minus i sine e over h bar.
Right. But omega is equal to e over h bar.
When you wrote the,
when you wrote down the equation for h,
you sprinkled in some values like the h bar.
You also sprinkled in the i there,
and said it all came out.
That's because, that's because, well,
I sprinkled in the i,
so that the solution would be a Hermitian operator.
Now, had I not sprinkled in the i,
I would have found h dagger equals minus h.
And I would have said,
okay, that's an anti-Hermitian operator.
That's, that's called an anti-Hermitian operator.
But I know what to do with that.
If I take an anti-Hermitian operator
and I multiply it by i,
it becomes a Hermitian operator.
So there was no content in it.
I just put it there because I wanted to give,
I wanted to define the thing
which would be Hermitian at the end.
In other words, this,
foresight or hindsight, I'm not sure which, but,
I knew the answer.
And when you got down here, then,
e is going to be a real,
yeah, yeah, yeah.
And the reason it has to
be real is because the unitarity.
We don't want the length of
the vector to change with time.
You see, now we see it coming out
that the length of the vector doesn't change with time.
And that was ensured by having e being real.
So, um,
I put all those factors there so that I
wouldn't have to deal with them in the end.
But, uh,
That makes me think, uh,
that equation, e equals h bar omega,
came from studying electromagnetic waves?
Yeah.
Well, it comes from studying any kind of oscillating system.
Is there some principle that says
that the frequency of the electromagnetic wave
is the same as the frequency of the quantum?
No, no.
Um, no, no.
That's next term.
Right.
We, right.
Is there a principle?
Of course there is.
But, uh,
but, uh,
nothing up until this point.
No.
The point, the point being that e equals
h bar omega is a more general thing
than just, uh, photons and electromagnetic radiation.
There's a more general interpretation of it,
and photons being one special case of it.
Okay, let's see.
Um,
Oh.
Supposing we have a vector which is
a sum of eigenvectors of the Hamiltonian
with different eigenvalues.
In general, the different
eigenvectors will have different eigenvalues
corresponding to the different values
that the energy can have.
Or that, uh, that it can be measured.
Supposing we take,
multiplying a vector by a phase
like this is not very interesting.
It doesn't change it in an interesting way.
It just multiplies it by a phase.
And we know that phases
are not important in quantum mechanics.
But supposing we have a vector
which is some superposition of energy eigenstates.
Now, the Hamiltonian is a, is a Hermitian operator.
It has a complete family, a complete basis of eigenvectors.
So, in principle,
any vector, any state of
the system can be expanded linearly
in eigenvectors of the Hamiltonian.
So let's do so.
Uh,
We start with the sum of n.
n simply labels the different eigenvalues
of, uh,
let's just write
some coefficient alpha n times psi n.
Where psi n is the nth eigenvector of the Hamiltonian.
Okay?
What happens to that with time?
Well, the point is that since
the evolution is with a linear operator,
we can figure out what happens
to each psi and add them up.
That's what, that's the nature of linear operators.
That's the nature of linear operators,
that you can bring them past the coefficients here
and just figure out what they do to individual
vectors and just add it up in the end.
So what happens to this?
This evolves into,
this evolves into,
summation of n,
alpha n,
but now we just have to
figure out what psi n does.
But we figured out already what, uh,
what each eigenvector of the energy does.
It just gets multiplied by e to the i,
e sub n minus i, minus i,
e sub n over h bar t,
times psi n.
Each one of the eigenvectors
is evolving with a different frequency.
This is quite different than an overall phase.
Each phase of each component here is evolving differently.
But that's the general solution of the Schrodinger equation.
Each eigenvector of the energy
just evolves with its own frequency.
The high energy ones evolve very fast.
The frequency goes around very fast.
The low energy states evolve slowly.
But if you break the, uh,
the system up into eigenvectors of the energy,
then the solution of any quantum mechanics problem
is just to write down, uh,
that each vector...
Yeah?
Uh, what you said,
I mean, I could,
even classical mechanically,
Fourier series is saying the same thing.
Well, this is a Fourier series in time.
Yeah?
So I was saying even heat conduction,
the higher frequencies evolve with
higher,
faster and smaller frequencies.
It's not...
Normally you would do a Laplace transformation
for heat conduction,
but you could also do a Fourier tran...
Yeah, both make sense.
So I was just generally saying,
is there anything unique about this compared to...
Is there anything unique about it?
Because you are saying it
from a Schrodinger equation perspective.
So...
Yeah.
Well, I'm not sure,
I'm not sure exactly how to take the question.
Um,
there's probably lots of situations
where high frequency corresponds to,
uh, to high energy,
but, uh, quantum mechanics being...
Usually it does trace back to somehow,
one way or another,
to the quantum mechanics,
but, uh,
I think we have to
look at it case by case.
I, I...
It's a little too loose a question right now.
Um...
Yeah.
I wanted to do an example,
but before I do the example...
Okay, that's, that's,
that's all basic,
easy stuff.
In fact, everything is easy in quantum mechanics.
What about observables?
Observables, not the,
not the Hamiltonian itself,
but other observables,
other quantities that we can measure.
How do they change with time?
Okay.
Now what do I mean by
how do they change with time?
For the moment,
let's ask how they're in the moment.
Let's ask how their expectation values change with time.
The expectation value,
the average value,
it's not,
the average value of a,
uh, of an,
of a observable,
let's call the observable A.
The average value of A
is psi A psi.
Now, it's the sis which change with time,
not the As.
The As are some very definite set of values.
They're not just a set of matrices
that describe very, very particular observables.
It's the states which change with time.
I've given you the rule for
how the states change with time.
And that will allow us to
figure out how the expectation value
of observables change with time.
It's only the states which change.
So let's figure it out.
Let's just ask,
what's the time derivative?
Well, first of all, let's call this A average.
A average.
And now I'm interested in the time derivative.
I want to understand the time derivative,
how the average of A changes with time.
All right, we have a product of three things here.
A state on the left,
a state on the right,
and a bunch of,
um, coefficients corresponding to the
matrix A in the middle.
How do we differentiate it with respect to time?
It's just the product of three things.
Two of them are time dependent,
the size,
and the A is not time dependent.
So we just treat it
as a product of three things.
Product of three things,
how do you differentiate a product?
Well, it's a sum of terms.
In each term,
you differentiate one of the factors,
and you add them all up.
So, this then is equal to
psi dot A psi
plus psi A psi.
And then you add the two things together,
and you get the result of the matrix A.
So, you have A psi dot.
No, I don't have to bother differentiating A.
That's a fixed matrix corresponding
to some very, very definite observable.
And I fix it once and for all.
I say I'm studying some particular component of a spin,
or whatever it happens to be,
and I'm not changing it with time.
The average only changes
because the state of the system changes.
Do you have a suggestion?
Use the Schrodinger equation.
Use the Schrodinger equation for psi dot.
So, what is this one?
Let's look at this factor here,
this term,
psi A.
And now for psi dot,
I put in minus I
H over H bar times psi.
Do I have that right?
Yeah.
That's this term here.
What about this term?
For this term,
I put in psi.
But now the time derivative of the bra vector
gets a plus I.
I have to complex conjugate.
So that gives me a
plus I H over H bar
times A times psi.
Notice two differences in the two terms.
In one case,
I have a minus I.
In the other case,
I have a plus I.
That's because I've complex conjugated.
When I study the time derivative of psi,
it's the complex conjugate of
the time derivative of psi dagger.
The other difference is the order
of operation of A and H
is different in the two terms.
Here I have H A.
Here I have A H.
Okay?
Those are the two differences.
H A minus A H.
The factor I over H bar can be taken out.
It's just I over H bar.
I over H bar.
Times psi H A minus A H.
That's the time derivative
of the expectation value of A.
A bar dot, let's call it.
We have a name for the
product for H A minus A H.
We've seen it before.
We talked about that?
Yeah, we talked about commutators, didn't we?
We didn't.
Yes, we did.
Sure we did.
Sorry, Dave.
But it doesn't matter because we could.
Actually, I did.
I proved the theorem for
you that said that two operators
will have the same
simultaneous eigenvectors if they commute.
I do remember proving that.
But it doesn't matter because it's just a definition.
A H, take two operators.
Let's call them A and B for a moment.
The combination A B minus B A.
In classical mathematics, if A and B are not equal,
if A and B are numbers,
this difference is always zero, obviously.
But they're not numbers.
They're linear operators or matrices.
And we know that matrices don't generally commute,
that you can't interchange the order when you multiply them.
And so this object, A B minus B A,
is called the commutator of A and B,
and it's written just a
little square bracket with a comma.
A B minus B A equals bracket, or not bracket,
let's not call it bracket,
let's not confuse it with bras and kets,
but commutator symbol.
Commutator symbol is the square bracket here.
All right, so now we've derived a fundamental identity
that the time derivative of any observable A,
let's rewrite it now, A
dot is I over H bar,
A bar dot is I over
H bar times, now what is this?
This is the average of H A minus A H.
So it's the average of
the commutator of H and A.
So the time derivative of the average of an operator
is related to the average
of the commutator with the Hamiltonian.
That is a fundamental significance
of the Hamiltonian in physics,
that if we want the time derivative of something,
or the time derivative of an average value,
that it is just equal to the
average of the commutator with the Hamiltonian.
Very simple.
And where did it come from?
Oh, because it's sandwiched between psi.
Who asked me?
Anything that's sandwiched between psi
like this is an expectation value.
Anything at all, if I want its expectation value,
I sandwich it between psi.
So in particular, the commutator is itself an operator,
and I can ask, what is
the expectation value of the commutator?
And I've just written it as bar on top.
So the time derivative of the average of an operator
is the average of the commutator of H with A.
Now, the first application of this,
let's do one simple application.
I'm going to do two applications of this.
I'll do one before we take a break,
and then one after we take a break.
Question?
Okay.
What is the time derivative of
the average of the Hamiltonian itself?
Let's suppose now we didn't know what the Hamiltonian was.
We had no idea what it stood for.
It's some observable.
We know that because it's Hermitian,
but we don't know what its meaning
is in the broader context of things.
So what is the time derivative
of the average of the Hamiltonian?
Zero.
Zero, because the commutator of
anything with itself is always zero.
I mean, the mathematics of quantum mechanics
is not so bizarre that
HH is not equal to HH.
That bizarre it's not.
HH is equal to HH.
Okay?
So if I plug in for A, H itself,
I find out that the expectation value of the Hamiltonian
doesn't change with time.
Sounds like there's a conservation law.
And there is.
The conservation law is the law of the Hamiltonian.
The conservation law is the conservation of H.
Every system has an H.
Every system has a conservation law.
What more likely thing is there than the energy?
And it is the energy.
ご視聴ありがとうございました
Okay, so Hamilton.
Question?
Would there be a physical interpretation for the
set of all matrices that communicate with H?
Yeah.
Well, it's the set of all things.
Yes.
Good.
It's the set of all things which are conserved.
And would that go beyond energy?
That depends on the details of the system.
For example, if we have a particle moving in free
space with no forces on it, then the momentum is conserved.
So, okay.
But if there's a force on the
system, then the momentum is not conserved.
So it depends on the details of
the system, whether there are other conserved quantities.
But yes, I mean, it's a good question.
There is the collection of all
things which commute with the Hamiltonian,
and that collection is the set of conserved quantities,
the set of things which are conserved for
the particular system that you might be thinking about.
Let's take a break.
One other point that I forgot to mention.
We're going to do an example in a minute.
We're going to take all this abstract stuff and
work it out in the very, very simplest case,
namely a spin in a magnetic field, the
simplest system that we know how to deal with.
But we'll do it in a minute.
But let me get all of the abstract.
I'm going to take all of the abstract things out,
and then we'll do it in detail, a concrete example.
The Hamiltonian H is a Hermitian operator.
That means it has a
complete family of eigenvalues and eigenvectors.
And if you work in the basis
of states described by the eigenvectors of H,
then H is a diagonal matrix.
All right?
Every H is a diagonal matrix.
Every H is a diagonal matrix
in the basis of eigenvectors of H.
That's trivial.
All right?
That's nothing new there.
And so in the energy eigenbasis, let's call it,
in the basis of states which are energy eigenvectors,
the Hamiltonian is just a diagonal matrix,
E1, E2, E3, E4, and so forth,
with zeros everywhere else.
Now, we also saw what happened.
Where is it?
We also saw what happened to
an individual eigenvector as time evolves.
As time evolves, each eigenvector gets
multiplied by E to the minus IEH,
E over H bar T.
That immediately tells us in the same basis,
the basis of the same eigenvectors,
it tells us what you are.
It tells us what you are.
You is a matrix whose entries are just these exponentials.
Each eigenvector gets multiplied by this rotating phase,
by this exponential,
and the different eigenvectors don't get mixed up.
Each one just gets multiplied.
And so it tells us that
the matrix in the same basis,
in the same basis,
is just E to the minus IEH,
E to the minus IE1 over H bar T,
E to the minus IE2 over H bar T,
and so forth,
everything else being zero.
The fact that the other elements are zero
means that the eigenvectors don't
get mixed up with each other,
that they don't rotate into each other.
Each one simply gets a phase,
and so it's a diagonal matrix that looks like this.
The way this is usually written is just to say,
well, these are matrix representations of linear operators.
In terms of abstract operators,
what one writes is that U is equal to
E to the I minus IH over H bar T.
You can interpret that just in terms of the eigenvalues,
and you can interpret this
that the element is equal to E to
the I minus IH over H bar T,
and you can interpret that
just in terms of the eigenvalues,
that the element is equal to E to
the I minus IH over H bar T,
but the elements of U are simply the exponentials,
with a T here, appropriate T here,
of the elements of H.
That's a notation, if you like.
Yeah?
I have two different systems,
and I bring them together,
so I'm going to treat them as a single system.
Yeah.
But the U-champ energy components that
happen to be at the same frequency,
how do I interpret that relative to the fact
that each eigenvector really is representative of the other?
Oh, it may be.
It can be that there
are eigenvectors with the same frequency.
Okay, so I just changed the coefficient.
I just changed that eigenvectors.
When I bring the two together,
the value is the same.
Well, how does it change
when I bring the two together?
I don't quite see that.
I'm not sure what question you're asking.
So I have a Hamiltonian for each of two systems,
and I bring them together and create a single system
with a bigger Hamiltonian.
Right.
If the energies in each of
the two systems have the same frequency,
when I bring the two Hamiltonians together,
does that mean there's going to
be some overlap in the two mechanisms?
There's system A with Hamiltonian A
and system B with Hamiltonian B.
They both happen to have a frequency element that's common.
When I bring them together...
Remember, the frequencies of the combined system
are the sums of the frequencies of the two systems.
Yeah.
Well, no, it's not because it's linear.
This is a separate postulate, if you like,
that non-interacting, separated systems,
which are non-interacting with each other,
have Hamiltonians, which are the
sum of the two Hamiltonians.
Now, we could justify that,
but since you asked me the question,
the answer is that the energy eigenvalues
are the sums of the eigenvalues of the separate system.
Now, that's not surprising.
Energies add.
Of course, if they're interacting, that's not quite true.
If they're interacting, that may not be quite true,
that the energies quite add.
But if they're non-interacting, and
you take the combined system,
the energies are simply the sums of the two energies.
The Hamiltonians are the sums of the two Hamiltonians.
Maybe we can even do
an example if we have time.
But I'm not sure if we will or not.
All right.
The example that I want
to do, in some detail now,
is the problem of a spin in a magnetic field.
Let's work out, let's write down
all the various equations that we need.
Just a single spin now.
No entanglement for the moment.
Probably won't get to it, but...
So we have the spin matrices,
sigma 1, sigma 2, and sigma 3.
They represent the components of spin,
and they're also proportional to the spin.
So the components of the magnetic moment of the electron,
if it's an electron.
And we have a magnetic field B.
That's what we have.
B.
Magnetic field pointing in some direction.
It's a pointer.
We won't call it a
vector because we get ourselves confused.
But it is a thing that
points in a direction of space,
and it has magnitude B.
Okay.
The energy of a...
spin
in a magnetic field
is given by the product of
the spin and the magnetic field.
In fact, the dot product of the two of them.
If you have a spin pointing in some direction
and a magnetic field in some other direction,
the energy stored
is proportional to the dot product
of the spin and the magnetic field.
Or really,
it's the dot product of the magnetic moment
and the...
And the magnetic field.
Now, the magnetic moment is proportional to the spin.
If you have one,
If you have an electron spinning, the magnetic
moment is proportional to the spin, and the,
what's the coefficient that connects them?
Anybody know?
Mu.
Mu, it's called mu, right.
Magnetic moment, magnetic moment.
So the magnetic moment, which is a
little vector, is actually the spin vector times
a number.
The number is called the magnetic moment, mu,
and I think there's a factor of two here
in the definition.
Let's not, let's not write that, let's
just write, here's an interesting quantity, mu
times sigma over two, the two is
entirely conventional and it could be absorbed into
the mu.
What is it, what is this thing?
This is the thing that you
multiply by B to get the energy.
Obviously there's a little coefficient here.
That has to do with the charge on the spin.
If the spin had no charge, there would
be no electric current going around, and so it
wouldn't interact with the magnetic field at all.
So the magnitude of the electric charge of
the particle is somehow buried in mu here,
and this two here I think is just a convention.
I vaguely remember there is a two
there, I think there is a two.
In any case, the energy is sigma mu over two.
That's the energy.
The energy, the magnetic field.
So that must be the Hamiltonian.
Let's take that to be the Hamiltonian, where
now sigma is thought of as a quantum operator.
B is just a magnetic field.
It's got nothing, it's not quantum mechanical, it's
just a great big magnet is sitting there,
a ten Tesla magnet, B is ten Teslas or
whatever it is, and pointing in some definite direction,
that's providing the magnetic field.
It's just a magnet provided
by this big, heavy, stable magnet.
We don't have to think about
the quantum mechanics of the magnet.
And so it's just there.
Now let's choose B in a particular direction.
What's the most convenient direction to choose?
Let's choose B in the third direction along the z-axis.
And then the Hamiltonian has a simple form.
It's just mu over two times
the magnitude of the magnetic field.
Just B without an arrow over it.
It means the magnitude.
Times sigma three.
So this is the energy or the
Hamiltonian of a spin in a magnetic field.
Okay, what I want to calculate first is I want to calculate
the time dependence of the averages of the three components of the spin.
This is the analog of the classical mechanical question
of calculating how the spin does whatever it does.
Does it rotate?
What does it do?
Okay.
So let's begin by calculating how
the expectation values change with time.
The expectation values of sigma
one, sigma two, and sigma three.
First of all, what about sigma three?
Oh, let's write down the equation.
The equation for the evolution of
an expectation value is right here.
So let's start with sigma three.
Sigma three dot.
I won't bother writing expectation values.
I mean here the expectation value of
sigma three, the time derivative of it.
Okay.
That's equal to I over H bar times
the commutator of the Hamiltonian with sigma three.
But the Hamiltonian is just proportional to sigma three.
Okay.
So the result for a numerical factor is sigma three.
And the commutator of sigma three with itself is zero.
So first thing it tells us is that the time derivative
of the expectation value of sigma three is equal to zero.
Let's draw.
Here's the xy plane.
Here's the z axis.
Z, x, y.
And now we've discovered that the component of the
spin along the z axis doesn't change with time.
How much freedom does that
give to the motion of sigma?
Well, it means that the projection of
sigma onto the third axis doesn't change.
And it means that the angle of the
spin relative to the vertical axis doesn't change.
So whatever the spin does, the expectation value of the three
components, it must somehow move on a cone of fixed angle here.
Otherwise, the component along the z axis would change.
And the axis would change with time.
Okay.
Now what about the x component
and the y component of the spin?
That's more interesting.
This one was boring.
Basically, this was just conservation of
energy, that this is equal to zero.
That since the energy is proportional to the third component of spin, the conservation
of energy must tell us that the third component of spin doesn't change with time.
Well, the average of it.
The average of the energy shouldn't change with time.
Next, what about, let's see
which one do I do next.
Let's do sigma one dot.
Sigma one dot is i over h
bar times the commutator of sigma three.
H is, let's write down what h is.
H is mu over two times b times sigma three.
So there's a mu.
Let's, i over h bar times mu divided by two,
b times the commutator of sigma three with sigma one.
Now I'm looking at sigma one dot,
so I write sigma one instead of a.
The first entry here is still sigma three.
Anybody know what the commutator of
sigma three and sigma one is?
Zero.
i is pi two or something like that.
Okay, let's work it out.
Let's work it out.
Sigma three, alright, so we're going
to write sigma three sigma one first.
First we'll do it in
the order sigma three sigma one.
That's equal to one minus one zero zero.
Sigma three times one one zero zero.
Sigma one is here.
Sigma three is here.
What's the product?
Usual rule.
First row times first column, zero.
First row times second column, one.
Second row times first column, minus one, zero.
This looks sort of like sigma y, or sigma two.
Sigma two, except that it is lacking an i.
This would be sigma two if there was
a minus i and a plus i here.
So this is actually two i times,
sorry, it's just i times sigma two.
Okay, let's check that.
i times sigma two would be
i times minus i i zero zero.
Minus i times i is one.
Yeah, that's correct.
So that's i times sigma two.
Let's do them in the other order now.
In the other order, we have zero one
one zero times one zero zero minus one.
Okay, so now we have in, let's
see, first row times first column, zero again.
First row times second column, minus one.
Second row times first column is one.
Is that right?
Yeah, one and zero.
Now, this is the same as
this except with a minus sign.
So this is minus i sigma two.
But remember when you calculate
the commutator, you subtract these two.
So subtracting minus i sigma two
from i sigma two itself gives what?
Twice i sigma two.
So the commutator of sigma three with
sigma one is just twice i sigma two.
Let's write that down.
Sigma one dot is equal to i
over h bar, mu over two, b,
and then commutator of sigma three with
sigma one is a factor of two,
i sigma two.
Now let's gather some stuff together.
The twos cancel.
I think that's why I put the two there.
I can't remember why I put the two there,
but I think that's why I put the two there.
i times i is minus.
Now remember, these are expectation values.
They're really expectation values.
They're not operators.
We could put a little bar above them.
And being expectation values,
the components are just numbers.
So this tells me that the x
component or the one component of sigma,
the time derivative of it, is proportional to sigma two.
And let me tell you what you get.
Well, let's not belabor it.
Let's just write down the answer.
Sigma two dot.
Looks very similar.
Instead of commutator of sigma three with sigma one,
we'll have commutator of sigma three with sigma two.
And that winds up giving plus mu
b over h bar times sigma one.
So we have the time derivative of sigma
one is minus some constant times sigma two.
And the time derivative of
sigma two is plus sigma one.
Does that look familiar?
It's just a rotation.
Just a rotation.
Yeah.
Just a point rotating in a plane.
Another way to say it is
a very simple solution of this,
is to choose sigma two is equal to
cosine of mu b over h bar t.
And sigma one is plus the sine, I think,
plus the sine of mu b over h bar t.
Do I have it right or do
I need a minus sign in there somewheres?
The other way.
Oh, the other way.
Yeah.
This one should be sine?
Sine.
This one should be cosine.
All right.
Derivative of sine is cosine.
Derivative of cosine is minus sine.
And when you take the derivative,
you have to pull out the coefficient
of t when you take the time derivative.
And that gives you the mu b over h bar.
So what this is,
that means that in the xy plane,
the component of spin in the
xy plane rotates around like that.
So the motion of the
spin vector looks like a procession,
a procession about the vertical axis.
In other words, about the magnetic field.
There's nothing special about choosing the magnetic
field to be along the z axis.
We could have used any axis.
Had I done so, we would have found that
the component of the spin along the magnetic field
doesn't change with time.
That's energy conservation.
And then in the plane perpendicular to the magnetic field,
we would find it processing around
the magnetic field, just like that.
That, of course, is also the known classical solution
of the way a magnetic moment,
would rotate around a magnetic field,
would process around a magnetic field.
It's kind of a gyroscope, is what it is.
It's like a gyroscope.
Isn't there a phase factor in there?
In the solution of that sine...
Excuse me, can I go
with sine plus the phase factor?
Oh, you mean for t plus the phase factor?
Yeah, yeah, that's right.
I mean, you can put in here...
What's the solution of the equations?
The phase factor simply corresponds...
Look down on the xy plane.
There's a solution where at t equals zero,
let's see, at t equals
zero, only sigma one is non-zero.
Let's call this one and two.
So we found a solution where
the spin at time t equals zero
is along the x axis and then it rotates.
There's nothing special about t equals zero.
And the way to indicate that is to
realize that we could have started at any time
with the spin pointing along the x axis,
and then we would put in here some minus theta,
where theta would just be the phase factor
or the time at which the
spin was along the x axis.
Is that what you're talking about?
Yeah, but then I'm thinking,
in order to do quantum mechanics,
you've got to have millions of electrons,
and they're going to have separate phase factors,
so it's a lot better.
The expectation value is going to be one half.
Serious?
Since in order to do quantum mechanics,
you've got to have many electrons to get averages.
Right.
And so each one has a different phase factor.
No! No, no, no, no.
The point is we're doing some experiment.
We want to do the
same experiment with all the electrons.
All right, so what's the experiment?
The experiment starts lining up
all the electrons along some axis
and then letting it go.
So we pick an axis
to line the electron up along,
and then we let it go.
If we're doing the same experiment to all the electrons,
it means that we initially
start them all the same way.
Okay, right.
If we have a system, you're perfectly right,
if we have a system that nobody's
been careful to start exactly the same way,
but we just start them,
right, then we have a mess.
We have a density, we have a mixed state then.
But if we start all the electrons identically,
that could mean that we start, for example,
we start them all pointing along the
one axis at time t equals zero,
then they'll remain the same.
They'll remain pointing the same way.
Now of course, sigma one, sigma two,
and sigma three are quantum mechanical variables.
What does that mean?
For example, supposing we start the spins so that
we know that they're pointing along the one axis
at time t equals zero.
That would tell us that if we
measured sigma one, we would get plus one.
If we measured sigma two, we would get a
half probability for it to be up or down,
and if we measured sigma three,
we would also get a half probability.
But let's start with a
system along the sigma one axis,
and then let it go for a little time.
After a little bit of time, the
system is processed into the two direction.
That means after a little bit of
time, if we were to measure sigma two,
we would find it definitely being up,
but if we measured sigma one, we would
find it with half probability in either direction.
If we wait another half period, or
another quarter period I guess it is,
we would find the spin, if
we measured along the x axis,
we would find for sure that it was minus,
but if we measured sigma two,
again we would find it randomly distributed.
So, that's the...
that's the basic solution of the problem
of a spin in a magnetic field.
If you had two electrons that were entangled,
would that imply 180 degree phase between them, or...
I know you would... if you measured in any axis,
if one of them is up,
then the other is the opposite,
given that they're sort of out entangled.
Does that bear any...
What are we assuming about the two electrons?
You have two entangled electrons,
if you measure one up, the other one is down.
I know, but what are you
assuming about the energy of the system?
We can't say what they're going to do,
unless we have an expression for the energy.
So, one possibility is that there's no magnet around,
but each one provides the magnet for the other one.
Okay?
Alright. If that were the case,
you can work out what the energy eigenvalues are,
and what the eigenvectors are. I'll tell you the answer.
Okay?
The answer is...
Let's...
Well, we're putting them in the magnetic field,
unentangled, if I guess that's my first...
Say that again?
If you put them in a magnetic field,
a uniform magnetic field, would that unentangle them?
It might.
If you put them in a strong
magnetic field, it'll tend to line them up,
but not necessarily, no.
Um...
If this is too complicated, there's no question...
No, no, no.
We could...
It's easy to answer the question about two electrons
when they're not in a magnetic field,
but when they're providing a magnetic field for each other.
Alright?
Then, the Hamiltonian is proportional to
the dot product of sigma and tau.
Sigma 1, tau 1, plus sigma 2,
tau 2, plus sigma 3, tau 3.
Alright?
We know how the sigma 1s and
the sigma 2s and the sigma 3s
and the tau 1 and the
tau 2 and the tau 3,
we know how they act on the states.
And we can work out what the eigenvalues are.
There are two eigenvalues.
The dimensionality of the space is four.
That means that there are four
linearly independent vectors in the space.
Two times two is four.
But, you know what the term
is when there are equal eigenvalues
for an operator, for a Hamiltonian?
It's called degenerate.
So if two states have exactly the same energy,
then the energy spectrum is called degenerate.
Meaning to say that there's more than
one state with exactly the same energy.
Alright.
This Hamiltonian happens to have three degenerate states
and one state which is not degenerate with it.
Okay.
Therefore, there are two energy levels.
And I'm just going to tell you the answer.
You can work this out.
The answer is that if both spins are...
We can work in the basis of the energy spectrum.
We can work in the basis
where the spins are along the z-axis.
If both spins are up,
then you have one particular value of the energy.
Let's just call it equals e, meaning
to say that it has energy e.
If both spins are down,
you also have the same energy e.
And then there's two possibilities.
Let's call it up-down, plus or minus down-up.
One of them is the so-called singlet state.
That has a different energy.
The third...
That's the minus sign.
With the minus sign, let's call this e1, e1.
With this sign, we get energy e2.
But with this sign, down-up, we get energy e1 again.
That's something you can check.
That's why this triplet of states, up-up, down-down,
and up-down, plus down-up, is called the triplet,
and the other one is called the singlet.
So we have three different energy levels.
And once you know there are three different energy levels,
and you know what the eigenvectors are,
you can then expand any vector
that you like to start with.
Pick anything you want to start with,
which is some linear combination of these.
And then just evolve it using the...
Well, using the formula that we had on the blackboard,
which seems to be gone by now.
The formula that said you expand the states in eigenvectors,
and each eigenvector goes with
a phase that's determined by the...
What's the answer?
What's the question?
You want to write down a general state?
Pick a state. Pick a state to start with.
Well, e2, the singlet.
Oh, that'll just stay e2, but it will have...
That's right, it'll just stay that way.
Any energy eigenvector doesn't
do anything terribly interesting.
It just rotates around.
It just rotates with its own phase.
So what'll happen to it is
it will pick up a phase,
e to the i, e2 over h bar t.
But what's more interesting...
Let's see, supposing we just picked...
Isn't the magnetic field going to supply
some energy every once in a while?
At the moment, they don't have any magnetic field.
No magnetic field.
They provide...
The only thing they provide is
a magnetic field of the other one.
That's all.
Okay?
So, for example, we could start.
Let's do a problem.
Let's suppose we start the system as up-down.
That's not an eigenvector of the energy.
I don't see among these...
Where are they?
Among...
There's up-up, down-down,
and up-down minus down-up, and up-down plus down-up.
Let's actually work out what would
happen if we started with up-down.
That won't be trivial.
We start with up-down.
The first thing we do
is we expand it in eigenvectors.
Let's write down what the eigenvectors are.
Up-up, down-down,
and up-down,
plus down-up,
plus or minus down-up,
divided by the square root of 2.
Obviously, these two are not
going to come into the game.
It's these two which will come into the game.
And, in fact, I can write that
up-down is equal to up-down plus down-up.
Put a bracket around it.
Plus up-down minus down-up.
Divide this by 2 and this by 2.
Okay?
So up-down plus down-up and up-down minus down-up.
The down-ups cancel, and I just get up-down.
Everybody see that?
Okay.
All right.
Now, this here is square root of 2 times 2.
Square root of 2 times square root of 2.
Let's give these two guys names.
Up-down plus down-up and up-down minus down-up.
All right?
I have some names that I always call them.
Joe and Mary.
No.
Seymour and Theresa.
Singlet and triplet.
This one is Theresa, the triplet.
All right?
So this is triplet divided
by the square root of 2.
Up-down plus down-up divided by
square root of 2 is triplet.
Plus Seymour divided by the square root of 2.
So that's the starting point.
That's the starting point.
Now let's evolve it for some time.
There are two different energy eigenvalues.
One of them goes with the singlet.
Let's call it, let's call this E triplet E triplet.
And E singlet E triplet.
So what happens to this state as time goes on?
The triplet state picks up a factor.
Now I'm going to write down
the state after a time t.
This will become E to the i E triplet.
E to the minus i
E triplet over h bar t.
Oh boy, we got too many t's, don't we?
I better call it, I better call Theresa capital T.
Triplet will use capital T.
And what happens to this one?
This one picks up the phase E to
the minus i E singlet over h bar t.
Over h bar t.
Which of E, T and E, S is bigger?
Say it again.
Uh, that depends on whether I put a plus sign
or a minus sign in front of the whole thing.
So let's see.
If I have a plus sign, I think I
probably want, for magnets you'd want a minus sign.
The energy is typically bigger for the triplet state.
That's when they're aligned.
And when two magnets are aligned, you
have more energy than when they're anti-aligned, right?
Because they like to be anti-aligned.
The north pole likes to
sit next to the south pole.
So they want to anti-align.
That means it lowers the energy when they're anti-aligned.
And that means that the singlet
energy is less than the triplet energy.
For example, we could define the energy by saying, uh,
the singlet, you can always subtract a constant from the energy.
That won't make any difference.
We could set the singlet energy equal to zero.
Then the triplet energy would be positive.
Okay.
Nothing actually depends on that constant,
but let's just leave it there.
Well, okay, now we have, now we have the evolution
of the system in terms of the triplet and singlet state.
But if we liked, we
could go back to this representation.
After all, I mean, the up and down spins might be the
thing that we're interested in, whether they're along the third axis or not.
Uh, these are both entangled states.
I might want to write
it in terms of unentangled states.
So then I would simply put back for
the triplet state, let's see what we would get.
We would get e to the
minus i, et, t over h bar.
Now, over, all over square root of 2.
And now we would have triplet.
So that would be up down plus
down up over the square root of 2.
So that would be a 2 down here.
That would be one component.
And then the other component
would be something very similar.
e to the minus i, e singlet t divided
by h bar over the square root of 2.
That'll give me a 2 downstairs.
And I'll have up down minus down up.
What do I want to do?
What I now want to do is I want to pick off the up
down and the down off separately from the two expressions and combine them together.
I want to express this in terms of
the particular states up down and down up.
So let's see what I get.
What multiplies up down?
e to the minus i, et, t over h bar.
Plus e to the minus i, e, that's et, e
singlet t over h bar times up down over 2.
But now what about the other component?
The component with down up?
It's not quite the same factor.
In fact, it has a minus sign.
Right?
A minus sign from here.
So what we get for the down
up is different than the up down.
Down up gets multiplied by one half.
You know, what is this here?
One half this times that?
No, not quite.
The et and the es are different from each other.
Yeah, hyperbolic.
No.
Okay, I'll show you in a minute.
No, it's not hyperbolic.
It is e to the, it's obviously
got to do with signs and cosines.
What it is, is it's, I believe, e
to the, let's just leave it this way.
Let's just leave it there.
You can write it in terms of
signs and cosines, but I'm not going to.
e to the minus i, et, t over h bar.
Minus e to the minus
i, es over h bar, t.
So you see that the up and downs, the
up downs and the down ups get different coefficients.
Okay?
At time t equals zero, the coefficient of
up down and down up are the same.
At time t equals zero, is that right?
No, that's wrong.
Oh, no, no, no, sorry.
At time t equals zero, we started
with pure up down, if you remember.
Okay.
So at time t equals zero, this
one's zero at time t equals zero.
Only up down.
But then we wait a little bit.
This becomes non-zero.
This gets a little smaller than the fact.
This one was maximum at time t equals zero.
It gets a little smaller.
This one grows and grows in magnitude.
And after a little bit of time,
you have a bit of down up.
Now, this is a little bit smaller.
This is a little bit smaller than the state vector.
So that means after a little bit of
time, even though you started with pure up down,
after a little bit of time, you
will have some probability of down up.
Now, you wait for a large enough time, and
after a while, this one will cancel this one.
There's a time at which
this one cancels this one exactly.
And at that time, this one is maximum.
So it goes back and forth
between up down and down up.
Back and forth between up down and down up.
Sort of interpolating in between the two of them.
That's what would happen.
But you see the rule.
The rule is first start with
the basis that you're interested in,
which happens to be in this
case the up down unentangled basis.
Write the state that you want to start with.
Re-express it in terms of eigenvectors of the Hamiltonian.
And then take each eigenvector of the Hamiltonian,
multiply it by the right phase,
and then disentangle it back into the original basis.
And that will tell you how the
probabilities in the original basis change with time.
Let's just see if we
can simplify this a little bit.
Let's see.
I think this is e to the minus i,
e t plus e s...
No.
You know what the point is...
What's that?
No, no, no, you're wrong.
You're wrong, you're wrong.
Let me just see.
What?
Yeah, that's what I want to do.
I want to pull out the average.
Yeah.
So...
Right.
What I want to do...
The average of the energy is
e t plus e s over 2.
I think that's what I want to pull out.
So, e to the i...
e to the minus i,
e t plus e s over 2.
Let me just think a minute.
If e s had been equal to 0,
then we'd only have this phase here.
This one wouldn't change at all.
Thank you for listening.
See you next time.
All right.
See you then.
ve
That's right.
Mm?
I taught Paul the average.
purposes of what you learn.
我真的把你扣上一二三
Well, the average then, you get e to the...
This is what you mean by the average?
Yeah. Okay, so what we have,
we have e to the minus i,
e t minus e s, t, plus e
to the i, e s minus e t,
e t plus, oh boy, yeah, yeah.
Okay, this one's going to be
cosine of e t minus e s.
Divided by twice h bar, right? Times t.
And the other one looks exactly the
same, has exactly the same factor, a phase,
but then it has sine of the same thing, t.
Now this is not important.
This overall phase is not important.
An overall phase doesn't
mean anything, doesn't change anything.
When you calculate the probabilities,
the overall phase goes away.
So you might as well just drop the overall phase.
Forget it, it's not important.
Do I have this right?
Yes, I do.
Okay, notice what happens.
The probabilities only depend on the difference of energies.
That's a good thing.
They only depend on the difference of energies
The overall sum of energies doesn't make any difference.
Only the difference of energies counts.
And you can see what happens is
that there's an oscillation back and forth
between up-down and down-up
with a computable frequency here.
Have I left something out?
No.
Notice what the frequency is.
It's related to the difference of energies.
So the difference of energies
of the singlet and triplet state
tell you how things go back and
forth between the two states, up-down and down-up.
That's a good thing.
That's an example of a quantum mechanical
problem worked out to death until it's finished.
But the rules are always the same.
Expand the vectors and the eigenvectors of the Hamiltonian.
Let each one evolve with its own phase.
And then put it back together again in
whatever form you want to compute whatever probability
you want.
So it's a standard ritual.
You reduce the problem to a ritual.
Ritual is always the same.
OK.
I think we're finished for tonight.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.