This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
This quarter, we're going to learn about field theory, classical field theory.
Fields such as the electromagnetic field, gravitational field, other fields in nature,
which I won't name right now, propagate, which means they change according to rules
which give them a wave-like character moving through space.
And one of the fundamental principles
of the classical field theory is that it's a field that is a wave-like character.
One of the fundamental principles of field theory, in fact, more broadly,
nature in general, is the principle of relativity.
The principle of special relativity in this particular case.
The principle of special relativity, well, let's just call it the principle of relativity,
goes way back.
There was not an invention of Einstein's.
I'm not absolutely sure when it was first announced or articulated in the form which I'll spell it out.
I don't know whether it was Galileo or Newton or those who came after them,
but those early pioneers certainly had the right idea.
It begins with the idea of an inertial reference frame.
Now, an inertial reference frame, this is something a bit tautological.
It's an inertial reference frame.
Newton's equations, F equals m a, are satisfied in an inertial reference frame.
What is an inertial reference frame?
It's a frame of reference in which Newton's equations are satisfied.
I'm not going to explain any further what an inertial reference frame is,
except to say that the idea of an inertial reference frame is by no means unique.
A reference frame, first of all, what is a reference frame?
What does a reference frame entail?
A reference frame, first of all, entails a set of coordinate axes in ordinary space,
x, y, and z, and you know how to think about those.
But it also entails the idea that the coordinate system may be moving or not moving,
relative to whom, relative to whomever.
We sitting here, or you sitting here in this classroom here, define a frame of reference.
We can pick the vertical direction to be the z-axis,
the horizontal direction along my arms here to be the x-axis,
x plus that way, x is minus in that direction.
And which one have I left out?
I have left out the y-axis, which points toward you from me.
So there are some coordinate axes for space, x, y, and z,
and in addition to specify a...
frame of reference, one also imagines that this entire
coordinate system is moving in some way relative to you sitting there
presumably with a uniform velocity in a definite direction
If your frame of reference is an inertial frame of reference
in other words, if when you throw balls around or juggle or do whatever you're supposed to do in an inertial frame of reference
if you find yourself in an inertial frame of reference
then every other frame of reference that's moving with uniform velocity relative to you
now remember what uniform velocity means
it doesn't just mean with uniform speed
it means with uniform speed in an unchanging direction
such a frame of reference is also inertial
if it's accelerated
if it starts standing still and then suddenly picks up some speed
then it's not an inertial frame of reference
all inertial frames of reference according to Newton
and also I think also Galileo
Galileo was often credited with the idea but I never read enough of Galileo to know whether he actually had it or not
neither did I read enough of Newton
they both wrote in languages that I don't understand
what was I saying?
oh yes
right
according to both Newton and anybody else who thought about it very hard
the laws of physics are the same in all inertial reference frames
laws of physics meaning F equals ma
the forces between objects
all the things that we would normally call laws of nature or laws of physics
don't distinguish between one frame of reference and another
if you want a kind of pictorial example that I like to use a lot when I'm explaining this to children
or to grown-ups
I like to think about the laws of juggling
there are very definite procedures that you train your body to do
in order to be able to juggle balls correctly
now you can imagine yourself being
in a railroad car
moving with perfectly uniform velocity
down the x-axis
and trying to juggle
do you have to compensate for the fact that the train is moving?
in particular when you throw a ball up into the air do you have to reach over to the right to compensate for the fact that the train is moving to the left?
my left, your right?
the answer is no
you don't
the laws of juggling are the same in every reference frame
in every inertial reference frame
whatever you do in one reference frame you do exactly the same thing
and you'll succeed or fail depending on whether you're a good juggler or not
but it will not depend on whether you're moving with uniform velocity
so the laws of juggling are the same in every inertial reference frame
the laws of mechanics are the same in every inertial reference frame
the laws, Newtonian laws of gravity are the same in every inertial frame
according to Newton
what about the laws of electrical phenomena?
well, there, there was a clash
the clash had to do with Maxwell's equations
Maxwell's equations were the field equations, the field theory
that governed the electromagnetic field
and the way that it propagated and sent waves
electromagnetic waves
that we ordinarily call light
or radio waves or so forth
and the fundamental dilemma, as you all know, I'm sure you all know
the fundamental dilemma was both according to, well, here was the dilemma
Maxwell's equations said light moves with a certain velocity
if you take the various constants that appear in Maxwell's equations
and put them together in the right way
you get the velocity of waves moving with a certain velocity
moving down an axis
and that velocity comes out to be a certain number out of Maxwell's equations
you have two choices
one is to believe that Maxwell's equations are true laws of nature
as good as any other laws of nature
in which case the principle of relativity says they should be the same in every reference frame
but if it follows from Maxwell's equations that the speed of light is
three times ten to the eighth meters per second
which is about what it is
if it follows from Maxwell's equations that light moves that fast
and if Maxwell's equations are laws of physics, fundamental laws of physics
and if the laws of physics are the same in every reference frame
then the speed of light must be the same in every reference frame
but that was very hard to swallow
because if a light beam is going down that axis
and you chase it and run along with it
at let's say three quarters of the speed of light
then you ought to see that light ray moving much more slowly
than three times ten to the eighth meters per second relative to you
on the other hand, a light ray going in the other direction
since you're sort of running into it
you should see going even faster
so all these possibilities could not simultaneously be correct
that the laws of nature are the same in every reference frame
and that Maxwell's equations
are laws of physics
in the same sense that Newton's laws of physics
namely the same in every reference frame
something had to give
well, the point was of course
that they were good laws of nature
and that they were the same in every reference frame
the thing that had to give
is our concepts of velocity, space, and time
and how we measure velocity
especially velocities which are up near the surface
near the speed of light
now, I'm not going to spend the full amount of time
that I did previously on the special theory of relativity
that can be found on lectures from how long ago?
they're on the internet I believe
relativity and electromagnetism
I think that was maybe about three quarters ago
I've lost track
yeah, they're up there, they're on the net
and they're the lectures on relativity
special relativity and electromagnetic theory
we're just going to cut through it real fast
we're going to cut through the basic ideas of relativity
a little more mathematically
than I would do if I were teaching it for the first time
if I teach it the first time
I tend to teach it the way
Einstein first conceived of it
how do you measure distances?
how do you measure velocities?
how does the propagation of light influence these things?
instead I'm going to take a more mathematical view of it
and think about the properties of light
and the properties of various kinds of coordinate transformations
coordinates now consist not only of x, y, and z
but also time, t
so imagine every event in the world
is characterized by
just like every particle
would be characterized by a position
x, y, and z
every event taking place in space-time
is characterized by four coordinates
x, y, z, and t
let's suppress for the moment y and z
let's just forget them for the moment
and concentrate on x and t
that would be appropriate
if we were mainly interested in motion along one axis
let's focus on that
motion along the x-axis
let's suppose there is no motion along y and z
then we can forget y and z for the moment
momentarily
we'll come back to them
and think of
motion along x and t
and the various reference frames
that might be moving along the x-axis
alright, here's
here's time vertically
here's space horizontally
physicists always draw space horizontally
and time vertically
I found out that mathematicians are at least
certain computer scientists always draw time going horizontally
I didn't know that
and I got into an enormous argument with a quantum computer scientist
which was ultimately resolved by the fact that he had time going horizontally
and I had it going vertically
these are traditions, I guess
traditions grow up around subjects
but time is north
and x is east, I guess
or at least time is upward
I think the mathematicians are thinking of it independently
yeah, yeah, that's the point
that is the point, yes
they're thinking of time as the independent variable
and everybody knows
that it's a law of nature that the independent variable should be horizontal
alright
now, let's imagine a moving observer
moving down the x-axis with a velocity v
let's take his origin of spatial coordinates
his origin of spatial coordinates at time t equals zero
is just at the same, let's assume that
I'll be the moving observer
I move down the x-axis
I am my own origin
there's nobody who is your origin
that seat is vacant over there
so that absence of human over there
is the center of the x-coordinates in your frame
I'm the x prime coordinate over there, right?
I'm the x prime coordinates
and of course I being very egocentric
will take my x origin to be where I am
there I do, I move down the x-axis
we pass each other
our origins pass each other at t equals zero
so that means at t equals zero
your axis and my axis are the same
or your origin and my origin are the same
but then as I move down the x-axis
my coordinate
center moves to the right
it moves to the right
that's supposed to be a straight line
it's as good as I can do under the circumstances
that's a straight line
and it's moving with velocity v
which means it's x prime equals
sorry, it means x equals vt
but it's also
that's the way you describe it
in terms of your coordinates
my center
you describe by saying x equals vt
how do I describe it?
I just say x prime my coordinate x prime is zero
x prime equals zero is the same as x equals vt
alright, what's the relationship between
x prime and x and t?
well it's easy to work out
if you believe this picture
the x prime coordinate
is the distance from my origin
the x coordinate
is the distance from your origin
so one of these is x
the other is x prime
the upper one here is x prime
the lower one here is x
and the relationship between them
is that they differ by an amount vt
in particular
x is equal to x prime minus vt
or x prime is equal to x plus vt
do I have it wrong?
yes I do
x prime is x minus vt
and x is x prime plus vt
yeah I think I have it
that's correct now
alright, what about time itself?
well according to Newton
and according to Galileo
and according to everybody who came afterward
up until Einstein
time is just time is just time is just time
there was no notion that time might be a constant
that time might be different in different reference frames
Newton had the idea of a universal time
sort of God's time
God up on his cloud
ticking off with his super accurate watch
and that time was universal for everybody
no matter how they were moving
and so everybody would agree
on what
on the time of any given event
in this map of space and time here
and so the other equation that went with this
is that t prime is equal to t
let's forget the top equation here
let's just forget it
one might say that this
was the Newtonian or the Galilean
transformation properties
between x and t
your coordinates
and the coordinates that I ascribe
to a point in space time
now let's examine a light ray
moving down the
plus x axis
if it starts at the origin here
then it moves along a trajectory
which is x equals ct
c being the speed of light
now shortly I'm going to set c equal to one
we're going to work in units
in which c is equal to one
but not quite yet
incidentally
once you understand a bit of relativity
working in coordinates in which c is not equal to one
is about as stupid
as using different units for x and y
if we used yards for x
and feet for y
then we would have all kinds of funny factors
in our equations
which would be conversion factors
from x which is measured in feet
to y which is measured in yards
those factors
log scale has its uses
well I don't know
log scale I don't think we're going to do log scale
oh like compound interest
yeah
I'm not sure what you're getting at but okay
I'm just saying it is quite often
in practical circumstances
that one uses different scales
yeah sometimes
there might be a good reason
I mean
it wouldn't be totally unreasonable
for a sailor to use different units
for horizontal direction and vertical direction
hmm
I mean he's used to moving around horizontally
he might use what miles
miles versus fathoms or something
nautical miles versus fathoms
I'm not sure if this question is relevant
sure it's relevant
but when you talk about a frame of reference
do you need to specify a period of time
because obviously it goes back 15 million years
there is no
yeah
we're ignoring now
the fact that the universe began at some time
and we're imagining now
as Newton did
and as the early Einstein did
that the universe has just been here forever and ever and ever
unchanging
totally static
and space and time have properties which don't change with time
now of course that's incorrect in the real world
and at some point
we will take up the subject of cosmology
and find that's not right
but as long as we're interested in time
intervals which are not
I suspect this is what you're getting at
as long as we're interested in time intervals which are not too long
in particular time intervals over which the universe doesn't expand very much and so forth
we can mainly say the properties of space don't change over a period of time
and so everything just stays the same as it always was
is that what you're asking?
well it seems that
this assumption if it is made
at least to what you're describing
so the question is
would that eventually lead to some
the point is it doesn't lead
it doesn't lead to what I'm describing
there's room for different formulas here
this is a formula which is based on an assumption
the assumption being that time is universal
that's what Einstein found was wrong
basically what he found
is that when you're in a moving frame of reference
two different observations
will not agree
about what time
a particular event takes place
this is the culprit here
this one
and some modifications to this one
but in any case to see what's wrong
let's go to Maxwell's equations
Maxwell's equations say that light always moves with this velocity
c being some numbers in meters per second
okay
three times ten to the eighth meters per second
we will later as I said say c equals one
let's imagine a light beam moving down the x-axis
let's describe how x prime sees it
in other words you see the light move this way
to the right
how do I see the light
well let's see what I see
let's just work it out
x prime will be x
which is ct for that light ray
minus vt
which is the same as c minus vt
all this says
is that I see the light moving with a diminished velocity
a velocity c minus v
why is that because I'm moving along with the light
so naturally I see it move slowly
but slow compared to what you see it
what about the light going in the other direction
supposing it was a light beam going in the other direction
then how would you describe it
you would describe it as x equals minus ct
and if I do exactly the same thing
I will find that x prime
is equal to x
that's minus ct
minus vt
which is the same as
minus c plus v
times t
so what this says is that I will see the light moving
also in the negative direction
that's the minus sign
but I'll see it moving with an enhanced velocity
c plus v
if this were the right story
and if these were the right transformation laws
for space and time
then it could not be the case
that Maxwell's equations are
laws of physics or laws of nature
in the sense that they were true
in every reference frame
they would have to be corrected
in moving frames
just like the juggler who had to reach to the right
who didn't actually
but who thought he had to reach to the right
to collect the ball when the train is moving
the physicist interested in light beams
would have to correct things
for the motion of his reference frame
now it's an experimental fact
that this is not the case
that you don't have to correct for motion
was the famous Michelson-Morley experiment
Einstein
he just rejected
he just felt this can't be right
Maxwell's equations were much too beautiful
to be relegated to the approximate
or to the contingent on which reference frame
and so he set about
to find a framework
in which the speed of light would be the same
in every reference frame
and he basically focused on these equations
and after various very very beautiful
gedanken experiments
thought experiments about light
and about measuring and so forth
he came to a set of formulas
called the Lorentz transformations
I'm going to explain the Lorentz transformations
in a more mathematical way
not fancy mathematics
but just
we want to get right to the heart of it
and not spend three weeks doing it
the best way is to set up a mathematical problem
but before I do
let me set up a different mathematical problem
which is
for most of you
you've seen me do this before
but nonetheless
let's go through it again
the problem of rotation of coordinates
we're going to do this quickly
let's just take spatial coordinates now
for the moment
two dimensional spatial coordinates
let's forget x and t
and just concentrate on x and y
two coordinates in space
instead of events in space-time
concentrate on x and y
concentrate on a point in space
a point in space has coordinates
and we can determine those coordinates
the x and y coordinates
just by dropping perpendiculars to the x-axis and the y-axis
and we would describe this point
as the point at position
let's just call it xy
now there's nothing sacred
about horizontal and vertical
so somebody else might come along
some crazy mathematician
a really nutty one
who wants to use coordinates
which are at an angle
relative to the vertical
maybe a couple of beers
and you don't know the difference between
vertical and
what, what, what
we should give this direction a name
oblique
yeah, alright
the oblique observer
the blue observer
can blue be seen?
everybody can see blue, ok
good
the blue observer also characterizes points by coordinates
which he calls x prime and y prime
the x prime and the y prime coordinates are found
by dropping perpendiculars to the x prime and the y prime axis
so here's x prime
here's y prime
and given a point at a point in space
xy
there's a rule
there must be a rule
if you know the value of x and y
you should be able to deduce
the value of x prime and y prime
if you know
the angle between the two coordinates
between the x coordinate and the x prime coordinate
and the formula is simple
we've used it in these classes many times
I'll just remind you what it is
that's x prime is equal to
x
x times cosine
of the angle between the two frames
between the two coordinate systems
minus y times sine of the angle
and y prime is equal to
minus, plus I think
x sine of theta
plus y cosine theta
I just want to remind you about a little bit of trigonometry
all of trigonometry
is encoded
in two very simple formulas
I've used them
the signs on the signs are wrong
you're right, let's see, hold on
x prime is bigger than x for small theta
you say the signs here are wrong
yeah, so it's x
x prime is bigger than x
is it?
yeah
let's see
if you rotate it to the next
so that y prime is zero
it's further out
x prime
do I have it backwards?
yeah
I'm not convinced
no, not either
so, let's see
x prime is a little perpendicular there
no, y prime is a little
no, that's y prime
this is y prime here
right
that's y prime here
and x prime is bigger than x
so there has to be a plus sign on the second term
yeah, x prime is bigger than x, let's see
yeah, x prime is bigger than x
looks like that's probably right
probably a sign
but then this one must be negative
yeah, okay
there's an easy way to correct for it
another way to correct for it
just call this angle minus theta
that would also do the trick
because cosine of minus theta is the same as cosine of theta
and sine changes sine when you change theta to minus theta
so if instead of calling this angle theta I called it minus theta
then my previous formulas would be right
it's true
true, but it's an excuse
alright, what do we know about sine and cosine?
it's important to understand sine and cosine
everything you ever learned about trigonometry
can be codified in two very simple formulas
if you know about complex functions
you know about complex numbers
the two very simple formulas are that
cosine of theta is e to the i theta
plus e to the minus i theta over 2
and sine of theta is e to the i theta minus e to the minus i theta over 2i
those two formulas contain everything about trigonometry
you don't have to know any other formulas
other than these
for example, I will assign you the homework problem
of using these two formulas
to find cosine of the sum of two angles
but the way you would do it
is just write the sum of two angles in here
and then re-express the exponentials
in terms of cosine and sine
that's easy to do
e to the i theta is equal to cosine of theta
plus i sine theta
and e to the minus i theta is cosine of theta minus i sine theta
so work through these formulas
get familiar with them
they're extremely useful formulas
once you know them
you will never have to remember any trigonometric formulas again
the other thing to know is that
e to the i theta times e to the minus i theta is 1
e to the anything times e to the minus the same thing is 1
those things characterize all of the formulas
all trigonometric formulas
in particular
as was explained to me by Michael
a number of times
if we multiply e to the i theta times e to the minus i theta
we will get 1 on this side
but on this side we will get cosine squared of theta plus sine squared of theta
not minus sine squared but plus sine squared
cosine squared
and then minus i squared sine squared
that gives us cosine squared plus sine squared
cosine squared theta plus sine squared theta
so that's equivalent to the fact that e to the i theta times e to the minus i theta is 1
alright
now the most important fact
that again follows from the simple trigonometry
is that when you make the change of coordinates
from xy to x prime y prime
something is left unchanged
namely the distance from the origin to the point xy
that's something which is
you know you count the number of the molecules along the blackboard from here to here
and that doesn't change when I change coordinates
so the distance from the origin to the point xy
has to be the same independent of which coordinate axes we use
well let's take the square of that distance
the square of that distance we know what it is
let's call it s squared
I'm not sure why I use s
but s for distance
s for distance
s for space
I think it must be for space that I'm using it
for the spatial distance from the origin to the point xy
we know what that is
it's Pythagoras' theorem
x squared plus y squared
but as I said there's nothing special about this
about the xy axes
we also ought to be able to calculate it
as x prime squared plus y prime squared
well it's not too hard to work out
that x prime squared plus y prime squared
is x squared plus y squared
it's easy to use, do
x prime squared plus y prime squared
will have x squared cosine squared theta
it will also have x squared sine squared theta
when you add them you'll get x squared plus y squared
you know the rigmarole
so it follows from
cosine squared plus sine squared equals one
that x prime squared plus y prime squared
is equal to x squared plus y squared
work that out
make sure that you have this under control
that you understand why
from the trigonometry
not from the basic physics of it
or the basic geometry of it is clear
but
make sure that you understand that you can see that from the trigonometry
okay
one last thing about sines and cosines
if I plot
on the blackboard
for every angle
if I plot
sine or cosine
along the horizontal axis
supposing I plot cosine of theta along the horizontal axis
and sine of theta along the vertical axis
then if I plot all possible angles
they will correspond to a bunch of points
that lie on a unit circle
why on a unit circle?
because sine squared plus cosine squared equals one
so
one might call
the properties of sine and cosine
the properties of circular functions
circular
in that they're convenient
for rotating
they're convenient for describing unit circles
points on unit circles are described in terms of coordinates
which are cosines and sines of angles and so forth
it's natural to call them
circular functions
these are not the functions
that come in to the transformation
the new transformation properties
first of all
these are wrong
I don't want to use x
let's uh
x
yeah yeah
no just
wrong
Newton had it wrong
Newton or Galileo or whoever it was who postulated it
Einstein modified it
now we're going to have to make sure
that Einstein's modification
doesn't change things in situations where Newton
where Newton's equations
were good approximations
the
situations
where Einstein's modifications
are important
is when we're talking about frames of reference moving very rapidly
up near the speed of light
before the 20th century
nobody or nothing had ever moved faster than
than a hundred miles an hour probably
well of course some things did
light did
but for all practical purposes light did not move fast enough
for all practical purposes light didn't travel at all
it just when you turned on the switch
the light just went on
so light didn't travel
nothing in anybody's experience
direct experience traveled faster than a hundred or two hundred miles an hour
well I should say
nothing traveled faster than a hundred miles an hour
and lived to tell about it
so all of experience was about very slow velocities
on the scale of the speed of light
on the scale of such velocities
Newton's formulas must be correct
they work
they're very useful
Newton got away with it
so they must be good approximations
it had better be that whatever Einstein did to the equations
in particular to these two equations here
had better reduced to Newton's equations
in the appropriate limit
okay let's come back now to light
light according to the Newton formulas
doesn't always move with the speed of light
but let's try to figure out what it would mean
of a better formula
of a replacement for this
that light always moves with the speed of light
first of all let's set the speed of light equal to one
that's a choice of units
in particular it's a choice of
the relation between space units and time units
if we work in
um
light years
for distance
and years for time
then light moves one light year per year
the speed of light is one
if we use seconds and light seconds
it's also one
whatever scale we use for space
if we use for time
the time that it takes light to go that distance
one unit of space
if we use that for time units
then the speed of light is equal to one
now
from the ordinary point of view
of very slowly moving things
those are odd units
but if we were electrons
we're neutrinos
and whizzing around like photons
they would be the natural units for us
uh
speed of light equals one
so let's set the speed of light equal to one
as I said it's just a choice of units
and then a light ray
moving to the right
just moves along a trajectory x equals two
t
c is just equal to one
a light ray moving to the left
is x equals minus t
how can we
take both of these equations
and put them together
sorry, x equals minus t
can I write a single equation
which if it's satisfied
is a light ray either moving to the left or to the right
yes
here's an equation
x squared equals t squared
it has two solutions
x equals t and x equals minus t
the two square roots
well, x squared equals t squared
is equivalent to either x equals t
or x equals minus t
in other words
this equation here
is a necessary and sufficient
condition
for describing the motion of a light ray
either to the right
or to the left
supposing we found
a replacement for this equation
which had the following interesting property
that whenever
let's write it this way
x squared minus t squared equals zero
this is even better
for our purposes
x squared minus t squared equals zero
that's the necessary and sufficient condition
to describe the motion of a light ray
supposing we found
a new set of rules
a new set of transformation properties
which
had the property
that if x squared minus t squared is equal to zero
then we would find
that x prime squared minus t prime squared
is equal to zero
in other words
supposing this implied this
is equal to zero
then we would find
that x squared minus t squared is equal to zero
and vice versa
then it would follow
that what the unprimed observer
you and your seats
see as a light ray
the primed observer
me moving along
also see as a light ray
both of us agreeing
that light rays move with unit velocity
now
this doesn't work
for Newton's formula here
it just doesn't work
but it does not follow
that x prime is equal to t prime
in fact it says something quite different
okay
so
the form of these equations must be wrong
let's look for some better equations
now at this point
oh let's
in fact let's even be a little bit more ambitious
it turns out being a little bit more ambitious
actually simplifies things
let's not only say
that when x squared minus t squared is equal to zero
then x prime squared minus t prime squared is equal to zero.
Let's say something even bolder.
Let's say the relation between x t and x prime t prime is such that
x squared minus t squared is equal to x prime squared minus t prime squared.
In other words, pick any x and any t and calculate x squared minus t squared.
Then take the same point except reckoned in the primed coordinates.
In other words, we take a certain event, a light bulb goes off someplace.
You say that corresponds to x and t.
I say it corresponds to x prime and t prime.
But let's require...
Just try it out. See if we can do it.
Let's look for transformations so that x squared minus t squared
will always be equal to x prime squared minus t prime squared.
That would be enough to ensure that everybody will agree about the speed of light.
Why?
If x squared minus t squared equals x prime minus t prime squared
for all x and t and so forth,
then when x squared minus t squared equals zero,
x prime minus t prime squared will be zero.
And then if this is a light ray, so is this a light ray.
Everybody get the logic?
Okay, good.
So let's assume now...
Let's ask, can we find transformations which have this particular property?
Now, it's not so different from looking for transformations
which preserve x squared plus y squared.
So, we can find transformations which preserve x squared minus t squared
and the look of these two is very similar.
And the mathematics is quite similar.
Here are the transformations which preserve x squared plus y squared.
What are the transformations which preserve x squared minus t squared?
Well, we're going to have to find out.
So, we're going to have to find out.
What are the transformations which preserve x squared minus t squared?
Well, they are the Lorentz transformations.
They are the fundamental transformations of the special theory of relativity.
They're not this, but they're closely related,
or perhaps one should say closely analogous to these equations here.
But, we have to substitute for circular trigonometry, hyperbolic trigonometry.
So, let's go back and remember a little bit about hyperbolic functions
instead of circular trigonometry.
Instead of circular functions.
Well, I didn't want to erase that.
Alright, these are the basic rules governing circular functions.
Cosine theta is equal to this.
Sine theta is equal to this.
And the e to the i theta in terms of cosine and sine.
Alright, let's see if we have a...
Now, we do have a blank blackboard here.
Let me write...
Whoops, what did I do here?
I erased something I didn't mean to erase.
Here it is.
Okay.
.
Incidentally, does everybody see how I got this side from this side?
You just add and subtract the equations appropriately,
and you isolate e to the i theta and e to the minus i theta.
That's elementary exercise.
Alright, hyperbolic functions.
What are hyperbolic functions?
Alright, those are functions of the form hyperbolic cosine cosh.
Hyperbolic cosine...
First of all, the angle theta is replaced by cosh.
And the angle theta is replaced by a variable called omega,
which I will call omega.
Omega is called a hyperbolic angle.
It doesn't go from 0 to 2 pi and then wind around on a circle.
It goes from minus infinity to infinity.
So it's a variable that just extends over the entire real axis.
But it's defined in a manner fairly similar to cosine and sine.
Cosh omega is by definition...
You're not allowed to ask why.
This is definition.
e to the omega plus e to the minus omega over 2.
All we do is substitute for theta or for i theta, substitute omega.
And that gives you hyperbolic functions.
Likewise or similarly,
there's the hyperbolic sine.
And that's given by e to the omega minus e to the minus omega over 2.
Essentially, you throw away all i's out of that formula,
out of the top formulas.
Just throw away all i's.
The equations on the right-hand side become
e to the omega equals hyperbolic cosh.
Omega plus sinh omega.
And e to the minus omega equals cosh omega minus sinh omega.
I think that's right. Is it right?
Cosh minus sinh...
It is?
Yeah. It is right.
Okay.
Now, what about the analog of cosine squared plus sine squared equals 1?
That simply came by multiplying this one by this one.
So let's do the same operation.
Multiplying e to the omega by e to the minus omega gives 1.
And now that gives cosh squared minus sinh squared.
You see we're getting a minus.
What we want? We want that minus.
The minus is important.
We want the...
Well, somewhere under here was a formula with a minus sign.
Yeah. We want to get that minus into play here.
That's cosh omega squared...
No, not cosh, but cosh squared omega minus sinh squared omega.
So it's very similar.
Everything you want to know about hyperbolic trigonometry,
and the theory of these functions is called hyperbolic trigonometry,
everything you ever want to know is codified in these simple formulas,
these and these.
And they're more or less definitions, but they're rather useful definitions.
Now, for... Yeah, go ahead.
Is it worth mentioning that x squared plus y squared equals constant is a circle?
Yeah.
And x squared minus y squared equals constant.
Not only is it worth mentioning, I was just about to mention it.
Sorry, x squared minus y squared is what?
x squared minus y squared equals constant is hyperbolic.
Hyperbolic, yeah. Right, exactly.
So if I were to play the same game that I did here,
namely plot on the horizontal and vertical axis
the values not of cosine of theta and sine of theta,
but cosine, cosh, of omega and sinh omega,
in other words, on the x-axis now,
we're going to plot cosh omega,
and on the y-axis, sinh omega.
Then this is a hyperbola.
Not a circle, but a hyperbola.
And it's a hyperbola with asymptotes that are at 45 degrees.
You can see...
Let me show you why...
why the asymptotes are at 45 degrees.
When omega is very large...
When omega is very large,
then e to the minus omega is very small, right?
When omega is very large, e to the minus omega is very small.
And that means both cosh and sinh
are both essentially equal to e to the plus omega.
In other words, when omega gets very big,
cosh and sinh become equal to each other.
And that's this line here.
Cosh equals sinh along this line here.
So when omega gets very large,
the curve asymptotes to a curve which is at 45 degrees.
It's not hard to see that in the other direction,
when omega is very negative,
that it asymptotes to the other asymptotic line here.
So that's why it's called hyperbolic geometry.
The hyperbolic angles, the coshes, the sinhs,
play the same role relative to hyperbolas
as sines and cosines do to circles.
Any questions?
No questions.
So cosh, omega equals zero?
How would you plot that hyperbola?
Oh, cosh squared minus sinh squared equals zero?
No.
No, no.
Cosh squared minus sinh squared equals one
in the same sense that sine squared plus cosine squared.
It never equals zero.
I think you wanted to ask a different question.
I think...
Oh.
Well, sinh omega equals zero is the horizontal axis.
Cosh omega equals zero is the vertical axis.
Right, right, okay.
Well, it's the x-intercept.
Yeah.
It's the vertex.
Yeah, I was just thinking, here's one point on the graph.
Yeah.
All right.
The x-intercept there is one.
Yeah.
Because cosh of zero is one.
To see that, just plug zero in here.
One plus one divided by two is one.
At least it was yesterday.
Yeah, it still is.
Okay.
So now we're sort of starting to cook a little bit.
We're starting to see something that has that nice minus sign in it.
But what's it got to do with x and t and x prime and t prime?
We're now set up to make, let's call it a guess.
.
Well, it's a guess which is based on the extreme similarity between hyperbolas and circles, coshes and cosines and so forth.
Here's the guess I'm going to make.
And then we'll check it.
We'll see if it does the thing we want it to do.
My formula, instead of being this, we're now going to have, instead of x and y, we're going to have x and t.
Time and x.
Later on, we'll put back y and z.
We're going to have to put back y and z.
But they're very easy.
Okay.
So let's start with x prime.
X prime is the coordinate given to a point of spacetime by the moving observer, namely me.
And I'm going to guess that it's some combination of x and t.
Not too different, but not the same as, where is it?
X prime equals x minus vt.
I'm going to try.
Cosh omega x.
That's right.
X cosh omega minus t sinh omega.
Sort of in parallel with this.
I could put a plus sign here, but you can go back and forth between the plus and the minus by changing the sign of omega, just as you did here.
So let's do it this way.
X cosh omega minus t sinh omega.
And t prime.
Going to look similar, but without the extra minus sign here.
This, you know, the relation between sines, cosines, and koshes and sinhs is one of just leaving out an i.
You go from sines and cosines to koshes and sinhs by leaving out the i.
Well, if you track it through carefully, you'll find that this minus sign is the same as the minus sign.
You'll find that this minus sign was really an i squared.
It's not going to matter much.
I will just tell you.
It really came from some i squared.
And if you leave out i, i squared just becomes one squared.
There's no minus sign.
So here's the guess for the formula connecting x prime t prime with x and t.
It equals, let's see, x sinh omega.
Minus, no, minus.
Plus t cosh omega.
In this case, there are two minus signs.
In this case, there was only one minus sign.
Okay.
But let's check.
What do we want to check?
We want to check that x prime squared.
Minus t prime squared is equal to x squared minus t squared.
You're probably asking yourself, what is this omega?
What does it have to do with moving reference frames?
I'll tell you right now what omega is.
It's a stand-in for the velocity between the frames.
We're going to find the relationship between omega and the relative velocity of the reference frames in a moment.
There has to be a parameter in the Lorentz.
These are the Lorentz transformations connecting two frames of reference.
In the Lorentz transformations, there's a parameter.
It's the velocity, the relative velocity.
That parameter has been replaced by omega.
It's a kind of angle relating the two frames, a hyperbolic angle.
But we'll come back to that.
For the moment, let's prove that with this transformation law here,
that x prime squared minus t prime squared is equal to zero.
Ah, is equal to x squared minus t squared.
I'm getting to that point in the evening where I'm going to make mistakes.
All right, this is easy.
You just work it out.
You use all you have to use is that cosine squared minus sine squared is one.
You can work that out by yourself, but we can just see little pieces of it here.
x prime squared will have x squared cosh squared omega.
t prime squared will have x squared.
t prime squared will have x squared sin squared omega.
If I take the difference between them, I'll get a term with an x squared
times cosh squared minus sin squared.
But cosh squared minus sin squared is one.
All right, so we'll find a term with an x squared.
When we square, take the square of the difference between the squares of this and this.
And likewise, we'll also find the t squared.
The cross term, when you square x prime, you'll have x t cosh sin squared.
When you square t prime, you'll have x t cosh sin squared.
When you subtract them, it'll cancel.
And it's easy to check.
It's basically one-liner to show that with this transformation here,
x prime squared minus t prime squared is x squared minus t squared,
which is exactly what we're looking for.
Let me remind you why we're looking for it.
If we find the transformation for what we're looking for,
for which the left-hand side and the right-hand side are equal,
then if x squared equals t squared,
in other words, if the right-hand side is zero,
the left-hand side will also be zero,
but x squared, but x equals t,
that's the same as something moving with the speed of light.
In the x frame of reference,
if this being zero is equivalent to the left-hand side,
being zero,
it says that in both frames of reference,
the light rays move with the same velocity.
So that's the basic tool that we're using here.
x prime squared minus t prime squared is equal to x squared minus t squared.
That does follow by a couple of lines using cosh squared minus sin squared.
So,
cosh squared minus sin squared equals one.
But what I want to do,
let's take another couple of minutes,
no, let's take a break for five minutes,
and then come back,
and connect these variables,
omega,
with the velocity of the moving frame of reference.
Somebody asked me a question about the ether
and what it was that people were thinking.
Somehow Einstein never got trapped into this mode of thinking.
What were they thinking about when they were thinking about the ether?
What exactly was the Michelson-Morley experiment?
Well, I'll just spend a minute or two mentioning it.
Certainly, Maxwell understood
that his equations were not consistent.
He understood that his equations were not consistent with Newtonian relativity.
He understood that.
But his image of what was going on
is that the propagation of light
was very similar to the propagation of sound in a material
or water waves propagating on water.
And of course it is true
that if you move relative to the atmosphere,
or move relative to the substance
that sound is propagating in,
you'll see sound move with different velocities,
depending on your motion.
If you're at rest in a gas of material,
there's a natural sense in which there's a particular rest frame.
The rest frame is the frame in which, on the average,
the molecules have zero velocity.
If you're in that reference frame,
then first of all light has the same velocity that way as that way,
number one,
and it has a velocity that's determined by the properties
of the fluid that the sound is moving in.
Okay.
Maxwell more or less thought that light was the same kind of thing,
that there was a material,
and the material had a rest frame,
and that particular rest frame was the frame
in which light would move with the same velocity
to the left as to the right.
And he thought that he was working out
the mechanics or the behavior of this particular material,
and that we were pretty much at rest relative to this material,
and that's why we saw light moving the same way
to the left or the right.
One would have to say then,
that Maxwell did not believe
that his equations were a universal set of laws of physics,
but that they would change
when you moved from frame to frame.
Just happened by some luck,
we happened to be more or less at rest
relative to the ether,
to this strange material.
Of course you could do an experiment with sound.
If you're moving through the sound,
you can check that the velocity in different directions
is different.
You do,
let's not worry exactly how you do that.
That's what the Michelson-Morley experiment was.
Michelson, and Morley I suppose,
said, look, the Earth is going around in an orbit.
Maybe at one season of the year
we just happen to be at rest relative to the ether,
by accident,
and some other season,
six months later,
we're going to be moving in the opposite direction,
and we won't, well,
we won't be at rest.
Only at one point in the orbit
could we be at rest relative to the ether,
so at any other point in the orbit,
we wouldn't be.
So if we measure in November
that light moves the same in all possible directions,
then in,
what's the opposite of November?
May.
Then in May we should find that light is moving
with different velocities in different directions.
Then he tried it,
and a very fancy and sophisticated way
of measuring the relative velocity
of the light in different directions,
but he found that there was no discrepancy,
that the light traveled the same velocity
in every direction at every time of year.
There were all sorts of ways
to try to rescue the ether,
but none of them worked.
None of them worked,
and the result was
one had to somehow get into the heart
of space and time and velocity
and distance and all those things
in a much deeper way,
in a way that didn't involve the idea
of a material at rest
in some frame of reference
that propagated the light.
Okay.
Where are we?
I've forgotten where we were when we stopped.
Somebody remind me.
What's omega?
Who?
Ah.
Omega.
Yeah, what is omega?
Forgot.
I don't remember what omega is.
How omega was related to the speed of light.
Ah.
How omega is related,
not to the speed of light,
but to the velocity
of the moving reference frame.
Here we have two reference frames,
xt and x prime and t prime.
What's the relationship between them?
Well, the whole goal here
was to understand the relationship
between frames of reference
moving with relative velocity
between them.
Omega is not exactly the relative velocity,
but it is closely related to it.
Okay, let's see if we can work out the relationship.
We know enough to do it.
Let's see if we can work out the relationship
between omega and the velocity
of the moving frame.
All right.
Again, let's go back to this picture.
Here's a frame of reference moving.
Let's redraw it.
Here's my origin moving along.
Okay.
What does it mean to say
that from your perspective
my frame of reference, or my origin,
is moving with velocity v?
Well, by definition,
this is not a law now,
this is a definition,
it says that this line here
has the equation x equals vt.
That's the definition of this v here.
My origin moves relative to your origin.
It moves with a uniform constant velocity.
That's an assumption that we're talking about
two inertial frames of reference.
And you, in your frame of reference,
will write x equals vt.
That's the definition of v, if you like.
What will I call it?
I will call it x prime equals zero.
All along there, I will say
x prime is equal to zero.
It's my origin of coordinates.
Okay.
Now let's come to this
transformation law here
and see if we can spot
how to identify vt.
Well, x prime equals zero.
That's this trajectory moving
at an angle with a velocity v.
x prime equals zero is the same
as saying x cosh omega
equals t sinh omega.
x prime equals zero.
Set this side equal to zero.
And that says that
x cosh omega equals t sinh omega.
All right.
So whatever the connection
between velocity and omega is,
it must be such that
when x prime is equal to zero,
x cosh omega equals t sinh omega.
Well, let's look at that equation.
It also says that x is equal to
sinh omega over cosh omega times t.
Well, that's interesting
because it's also supposed to be
equivalent to x equals vt.
Now I know exactly how to identify
what the velocity is
as a function of omega.
The velocity of the moving transformation,
the moving coordinate system,
must just be sinh omega over cosh omega.
Okay?
That's the only way
these two equations can be the same.
x equals vt.
x equals sinh omega over cosh omega times t.
So now we know it.
We know what the relationship
between velocity and omega is.
Write it down.
The velocity of the moving frame.
Now this is not the velocity of light.
It's just the velocity of the moving frame
must just be sinh omega
over cosh omega.
Well, actually I want to invert this relationship.
I want to find sinh and cosh omega
in terms of the velocity.
I want to rewrite these Lorentz transformations.
Where are they?
I want to rewrite these Lorentz transformations
in terms of the velocity.
That's the familiar form
in which you learn about it
in elementary relativity books.
x prime is equal to something with velocities in it.
To exhibit that,
all we have to do is to find sinh and cosh omega
in terms of the velocity.
That's not very hard.
Let's work it out.
The first step is to square it.
And to write v squared is equal to
sinh omega squared
over cosh omega squared.
That was easy.
Next, I'm going to get rid of sinh omega squared
and substitute.
Where is it?
I lost it.
One is equal to cosh omega squared
minus sinh omega squared.
All right.
So wherever I see sinh omega squared,
I can substitute from here.
Namely, cosh squared omega minus one
is equal to sinh squared omega.
So here we are.
This is just equal to
cosh of omega squared
minus one
divided by cosh of omega squared.
Or,
let's multiply by,
what I want to do is solve for cosh omega
in terms of velocity.
I want to get rid of all these coshes and sinhs of omega
and rewrite it in terms of velocity.
So first multiply by cosh omega
squared.
We have cosh squared omega
times v squared
equals cosh squared omega minus one.
Or,
it looks to me like this is cosh
squared omega
times one minus v squared
equals one.
What I've done is transpose,
yeah,
cosh squared times v squared
minus cosh squared itself.
That gives you cosh squared one minus v squared
equals one.
Change the sign.
Can everybody see that the second line follows from the first?
I'll give you a second.
Put the one on the left-hand side and then put the v squared on the right-hand side.
Yeah.
It's clear.
Okay.
Finally,
we get
that cosh omega
is equal to one divided by one minus v squared,
but now I have to take the square root.
Cosh omega
divide by one minus v squared and then take the square root.
Okay.
And that gives you cosh omega.
Now, we've all seen these square roots of one minus v squared in relativity formulas.
Here's where it begins to come.
Here we begin to see it materializing.
What about sinh omega?
Let's also write down sinh omega.
Well, from here,
we see that sinh omega
is just equal to v times cosh omega.
This is easy.
Sinh omega equals v times cosh omega.
So, sinh omega is v divided by square root of one minus v squared.
Let's go back to these Lorentz transformations over here
and write them getting rid of the trigonometric functions,
the hyperbolic trigonometric functions,
and substituting good old familiar velocities.
Let's get rid of this
and substitute the good old ordinary velocities.
Okay, so we have here
x prime equals x times cosh omega
and that's divided by square root of one minus v squared.
Then there's minus t times sinh omega,
which is v over the square root of one minus v squared.
If I put the two of them together,
and combine them over the same denominator,
it's just x minus vt
divided by square root
of one minus v squared.
I think most of you have probably seen that before.
Maybe slightly different.
Let's clean it up a little bit.
x prime equals
x minus vt
divided by the square root of one minus v squared.
What about t prime?
t prime is equal to t
minus vx
over square root of one minus v squared.
t prime is equal to t times cosh,
cosh is just one over square root,
and then x times sinh,
that gives us the extra v.
In other words, the formulas are more or less symmetrical.
And those are our good old Lorentz transformations.
Now what's missing is the speed of light.
Let's put back the speed of light.
To put back the speed of light is an exercise in dimensional analysis.
There's only one possible way the speed of light can fit into these equations.
They have to be modified so that they're dimensionally correct.
First of all, one is dimensionless.
It has no dimensions, it's just one.
Velocity is not dimensionless,
unless, of course, we use dimensionless notation for it.
But if velocity is measured in meters per second,
then it's not dimensionless.
How do we make v squared dimensionless?
We divide it by the square of the speed of light.
In other words, this v squared, which is here,
which has been defined
in units in which the speed of light is one,
has to be replaced by v squared over c squared.
Likewise over here.
v squared over c squared.
Now, velocity times time does have...
Notice, first of all, the left-hand side has units of length.
The right-hand side, this is dimensionless.
x has units of length,
but so does velocity times time.
So this is okay.
This is dimensionally consistent as it is.
But over here it's not.
The left-hand side has dimensions of time.
That's all right.
1 minus v squared over c squared, that's dimensionless.
This has units of time.
But what about velocity times x?
Velocity times x does not have units of time.
In order to give it units of time,
you have to divide it by c squared.
Okay, let's check that.
Velocity is length over time
times length
divided by c squared.
That's length squared...
Oh, it's correct.
It's correct.
All right, this is probably familiar to most of you
who've seen relativity once or twice before.
These are the equations relating
two different moving coordinate systems
moving relative to the x-axis.
But you see, the deep mathematics
or the mathematical structure of it
in many ways is best reflected
by this kind of hyperbolic geometry here.
And, you know, most physicists by now
never write down the Lorentz transformations
in this form.
Much more likely to write them
Easier to manipulate.
Easier to use trigonometry
or hyperbolic trigonometry.
It's a little exercise.
It's a nice little exercise
to use the hyperbolic trigonometry
to compute the compounding
of two Lorentz transformations.
If frame two is moving relative
to frame one with velocity v,
and frame three is moving relative
to two with velocity v prime,
how is three moving relative to one?
The answer is very simple
in terms of hyperbolic angles.
You add the hyperbolic angles.
Not the velocities,
but the hyperbolic angles.
The hyperbolic angle of three moving relative to one
is the hyperbolic angle of three moving relative to two
plus two moving relative to one.
And then you use a bit of trigonometry
or hyperbolic trigonometry
to figure out how you do
the cinches and coshes
of the sum of two hyperbolic angles.
Very straightforward.
And I'll leave it as an exercise
to see if you can work that out.
Much easier than anything else.
Okay, so there we have
the Lorentz transformations.
Yeah, oh, absolutely, yes.
That's a good point.
Yeah, when we, that's right.
If we have frame one,
let's call this x1 and y1,
x2 and y2,
and finally x3,
and y3,
well, then the angle
of two, let's call,
of three relative to one,
let's call it theta one three,
is just equal to theta one two
plus theta two three.
The angle connecting frame one with frame three
is just the sum of the angle
theta one two
plus theta two three.
So in that respect,
the Lorentz transformations are much simpler
in terms of the omegas.
It's the omegas which combine together
to add when you add velocities.
Now, how different is omega
from the velocity?
Let's work in units in which
the speed of light is equal to one.
Where is our formula for velocity?
All right, let's take this formula over here.
What is sinh omega for small omega?
Let's put the c squared there.
Let's not put the c squared there.
We'll not put the c squared there.
Sinh omega is essentially omega
when omega is small,
just like sine is theta
when theta is small.
The sinh function,
the Cauch function looks like this.
The sinh function looks like this.
But it crosses the axis
with a slope of one.
For small omega,
sinh omega is proportional to omega.
For small velocity,
one minus v squared is very close to one.
If the velocity is a hundredth
of the speed of light,
then this to within one ten thousandth
is just one.
If we're talking about velocities
a millionth of the speed of light,
then this is very close to one.
And so sinh omega and velocity
are very close to each other.
Let's see what's going on here.
Thanks.
Okay, so for small velocities,
omega and velocity are the same.
The actual correct statement
is that v over c
is like omega.
The dimensionless velocity
over the speed of light
is like omega
for small omega.
And so you can see
that the velocity of light
is like omega.
And so,
for small omega,
it's like omega over c.
And small velocity.
So for small velocity,
adding velocities
and adding omegas
are the same things.
But when the velocities get large,
the right way to combine them
to find relationships
between different frames
is by adding omega
and not adding velocities.
When you add omega,
like compounding velocities
as you've got up there,
I guess you won't go
greater than forty-five degrees,
because that would be faster than light.
No, no, but omega,
no, no, you see,
the speed of light is v equals one.
That corresponds to omega equals infinity.
Yeah.
Yeah, so omega runs over
the whole range
from minus infinity to infinity,
but when it does,
v goes from
minus the speed of light
to the speed of light.
So you can add any omegas,
and it's still...
Add any omegas.
Omega, that's right.
There's no speed limit on omega.
It's just like when you draw
on that diagram,
it looks like it's greater
than forty-five degrees up there.
Where, where, where?
With the omega.
Omega is the distance
along the hyperbola.
Yeah, that's right.
Sorry, where are we?
Right there.
I guess that's theta, though, isn't it?
This is theta.
That's theta.
Yeah.
Right.
Yeah, omega is the distance
along the hyperbola.
That's right.
Omega is a kind of distance
along the hyperbola.
All right.
Now let's talk about that
a little bit.
All right.
Now that we've established
the basic mathematical structure
of the transformations,
I think we should go back
and talk about some simple
relativity phenomena
and derive them.
So, let's start with
the basic mathematical structure
of a transformation.
Oh, one thing which is important,
which I, yeah, well, let's see where,
here are my Lorentz transformations
over here.
I said we ought to, at the end,
make sure that our transformations
are not too dissimilar
from Newton's.
In particular,
when the velocities are small,
they should reduce to Newton.
That's all we really know.
That's, or at least that's all
that Newton really had a right
to assume,
that we should reduce to Newton.
But we have to,
we have to,
we have to be careful
that we don't have to
take away the velocity
of the newtons.
That's all we really know.
That's, or at least
that's all that Newton
really had a right to assume,
that when the velocities are smaller
than something or other,
that his equations should be
good approximations.
Isn't adding velocities
good enough?
Hm?
Isn't velocities
adding good enough?
In fact, you're right.
In fact, you're right,
but let's just look
at the transformations themselves.
All right.
As long as the velocity
is a small percentage
of the speed of light,
an ordinary velocity
is a small percentage
of the speed of light.
So, if you're going to
take a velocity
of light,
you're going to have
to do a lot of things.
Let's see what that means.
So, if you're going to
take a velocity
of light,
the velocity of light
is equal to the speed
of light of light.
So, what are the velocities?
Well, the velocities
are what?
A hundred miles an hour
versus 186,000 miles an hour.
What is that?
Uh...
It's small, right?
And it's doubly small
when you square it.
So, for typical
ordinary velocities,
even the velocities
of the Earth
around the sun
and so forth,
fairly large velocities
is what?
fast
that's the orbital earth around the sun
it's pretty fast but it's nowhere near three hundred thousand kilometers
per... no
three hundred thousand meters per second
three times ten to the eighth no three hundred thousand kilometers per second
sixty kilometers per second three hundred thousand kilometers per second
small fraction
and then square it
so for ordinary motions
this is so close to one
that the deviation from one is negligible so let's start with the top
equation
for the top equation this is negligible and it's just x prime equals x minus vt
the bottom equation here
you have a c squared in the denominator whenever you have a c squared in the
denominator that's a very very large thing in the denominator
this
is negligible
compared to t
so here the speed of light is also in the denominator
just forget this
and it's just t
but it's just t prime equals t
it's just t prime equals t
so in fact newton's formulas are essentially correct for slow velocities
no uh... no significant departure from newton until the velocities get up to be
some some appreciable fraction of the speed of light
uh... let's talk about
proper time
proper time and then let's uh... do a couple of uh... relativity examples
yeah
question
in the bottom equation
t prime
when x is very large would you get a difference of
yes
c
that's right
when x is exceedingly large
you get a correction
but
that correction that x has to be very large
look let's uh... let's discuss before we do anything else let's uh... let's uh...
let's talk about that a little bit uh... x minus vt
uh... one minus v squared over c squared
yeah let's
alright in my drawings i'm going to set c equal to one
so let's say that we have a c squared in the denominator and then we're going to set c equal to one
but in the equations you can leave the c there
ok this equation we understand apart from this one minus v squared over c squared in the denominator
it's just this x equals vt or x minus v x minus uh x minus vt
that's newton
let's look at this one over here
ok
let's look at the surface t prime equals zero
t prime equals zero is the set of points that i in my moving reference frame call t call time equals zero
it's what i call the set of points which are all simultaneous with the origin
t prime equals zero is just every place in space time
which has exactly the same time according to my frame of reference
and i will therefore call all those points synchronous
at the same time
what do you say about them
if t prime is equal to zero
that says that t
is equal to zero
and that's the same thing
t prime is equal to v over c squared x
now let's set c equal to one for the purpose of drawing
just for the purpose of drawing i don't want this huge number c squared
to uh to distort my drawings too much
it says that t equals v x
what does the surface t equals v x look like
it looks like this
t
equals v x
which is also x is equal to one over v t
so it's just a uniform
line like that
all of these points are at different times from your reckoning
this one's later this one's later this one's later and so forth
according to my reckoning all these points are at the same time
so we disagree on the fact that the surface t is equal to zero
so we disagree
about what's simultaneous
this was this was the hang up incidentally
this was the basic hang up that took so long to overcome
that took einstein to overcome it
the idea that simultaneity was the same in every reference frame
nobody in fact it was so obvious that nobody even thought to ask the question
is simultaneous does it mean the same thing in every reference frame
no it doesn't
in your reference frame the horizontal points are all simultaneous with respect to each other
in my reference frame what i call horizontal
what i call simultaneous you do not
okay so simultaneity had to go
let me point out one more thing about these equations
i'm not going to solve them for you
but i will tell you the solution anyway
how do you solve for x and t in terms of x prime and t prime
well think about it in the case of angles
supposing i have a relationship like
x prime is equal to x cosine theta
what is it plus y sine theta
and y prime is equal to
x minus x sine theta plus y cosine theta
and supposing i want to solve for x and y in terms of x prime and y prime
you know what the solution is
just change theta to minus theta
and write that x is equal to x prime cosine of minus theta
but what's cosine of minus theta?
right, cosine theta
plus y sine of minus theta
what's sine of minus theta?
minus sine theta
times y
and likewise for y prime
y prime is equal to minus x times sine of minus theta
so that becomes plus x sine theta
plus y cosine of minus theta which is cosine theta
you don't have to go through the business of solving the equations
you know that if one set of axes is related to the other
by rotation by angle theta
the second one is related to the first one
or vice versa
the first one is related to the second one
by the negative of the angle
if to go from one frame to another
you rotate by angle theta
and to go from the second frame back to the first
you rotate by angle minus theta
so you just write down exactly the same equations
interchange prime and unprimed
and substitute for theta minus theta
same thing for the Lorentz transformations
exactly the same thing
if you want to solve these for x and t
write down the same equations
replace primed by unprimed
and change the sine of omegas times y prime
and the sine of omegas to minus the sine of omegas
change the sine s-i-g-n of all the sinches
in other words just send omega to minus omega
and that will solve the equations in the other direction
yeah
you just change the v to minus v
yes, it's also the same as changing v to minus v
yes, the way to see that
is to go
right
what was it, what did we have?
cosh omega
v equal sine h over cosine h
yup
yup, that's right
v is sine
yes, that was correct
yeah
when you change omega to minus omega
it has the action of changing v to minus v
you can just check that from the equations
good, alright let's talk about proper time a little bit
proper time
if you're doing ordinary geometry
you can measure the length along a curve for example
and the way you do it is you take a tape measure
and you sort of tick off equal intervals
equal little separations
you can think of these separations as differential distances
ds squared, small little differential distances
and that differential distance is dx squared plus dy squared
where the x squared and the y squared are just the
the differential increments in x and y, dx and dy
this is ds
alright, so that's the way
and you add them up
you add them up, that's the way you compute distances along curves
it's quite obvious that if you take two points
the distance between those two points depends on what curve
not the same for every curve
so measured along a curve
you have to know not only the two points
but you have to know the curve
in order to say what the distance between those points are
of course the distance between
along a straight line
that's well defined
but the distance along a curve depends on the curve
in any case
ds squared equals dx squared plus dy squared
is the basic defining notion
of distance between two neighboring points
if you know the distance between any two neighboring points in a geometry
you basically know that geometry
almost essentially completely
so given this formula
for the distance between two points
you can compute if you like the distance along a curve
of course you've got to take the square root of this
and then add them up
don't add the squares
add the differential distances
alright
the important thing is here
that square root of dx squared plus dy squared
which is the distance between neighboring points
doesn't depend on your choice of axes
I could choose xy axes
I could choose x prime y prime axes
if I take a little differential displacement
dx and dy
or I just take two points
two neighboring points
don't even give them labels
and measure the distance between them
the distance between them should not depend on conventions
such as which axes I use
and so when I make rotational transformations
dx squared plus dy squared doesn't change
dx and dy may change
but the x squared plus dy squared does not change
the same thing is true
in relativity
or the analogous thing
we don't measure distances
along the paths of particles
let's say now that this curve here is the path
of a particle moving through space-time
there's a particle moving through space-time
and we want some notion
of the distance along it
the notion of distance along it
another example would just be a particle standing still
there's a particle standing still
particle standing still
is still in some sense moving in time
I wouldn't want to say
that the distance between these two points in space-time is zero
they're not the same point
I wouldn't like to say it's zero
I would like to say there's some kind of notion of distance between them
but it's quite clear that that distance is not measured with a tape measure
this point and this point are the same point of space
boom here at this point of space
and then at a later time
boom again at the same point of space
two events at the same point of space
how do I characterize in some nice way the distance
between those two events?
that occurred in the same place
you don't do it with a tape measure
alright, what do you do it with?
a clock
you take a clock
and you start it at this point
tick tick tick tick tick tick tick
a stopwatch
you press it at this point
tick tick tick tick tick
it ticks off intervals
and then you stop it at that point
and you see how much time has evolved
that's a notion of distance along a particle trajectory
it's not the distance the particle moves in space
it's a kind of distance that it's moved through space-time
and it's not zero even if the particle is moving, standing perfectly still
in fact what it is, is it's the time along the trajectory
what about a moving particle?
well you can imagine that a moving particle carries a clock with it
of course not all particles carry clocks
but we can imagine they carry clocks with them as they move
and we can start the clock over here
and end the clock over here
what is the time read off by this moving clock?
the time read off by a moving clock is much like the distance along a curve
measured by a tape measure
in particular, it should not depend
on the choice of coordinates
why not?
this is a question that has nothing to do with coordinates
I have a clock made in the standard clock factory
the standard clock factory in, I don't know where, in Switzerland someplace
makes a certain kind of clock
that clock gets carried along with a particle
and we ask how much time evolves
or how much time elapses
or how much the clock changes
between here and here
that should not depend on a choice of coordinates
it shouldn't depend on a choice of coordinates
because it's a physical question
that only involves looking at the hands of the clock
in fact we could ask it
for little intervals along the trajectory
we could ask how much time elapses
according to the clock
between here and here
well the answer again
should not depend on what coordinates you use
which Lorentz frame you use
and there's only one invariant quantity
that you can make out of the dx's and dt's
describing this point
describing these two points
there's a little interval dt
and there's a little interval dx
now we're in space and time
not ordinary space
and the quantity which is invariant
there's really only one invariant quantity
that you can make out of it
it is dt squared
minus dx squared
it's the same quantity
x squared minus t squared
for a whole
you know, for a whole interval
dt squared minus dx squared
that's the quantity which is invariant
it's the negative of what I wrote over here
x squared minus t squared
this quantity
is equal to dx prime squared
minus dt prime
sorry, dt prime squared minus dx prime squared
the same algebra goes into this
as goes into showing that
x prime squared minus t prime squared is the same
equals x squared minus t squared. Incidentally, this is the same as saying
t prime squared minus x prime squared equals t squared minus x squared.
Doesn't matter which way you write it. All right, so that suggests that
suggests that the time read off, the invariant time read off along a
trajectory between two points separated by dx and dt is just the square root of
dt squared minus dx squared.
Why the square root incidentally?
Well, you're going to integrate it d tau. Well, I can integrate the t, yeah. Well, all right,
why not just dt squared minus dx squared for the time between here and
here? Here's an answer. Supposing we go to
you,
two intervals exactly the same as the first one. We go an interval over here,
dx and dt, and then we go another dx and dt. What happens when we double the
interval to dt squared minus dx squared? It gets multiplied by four because
everything is squared. Well, I wouldn't expect a clock when it goes along, you
know, when it goes along a trajectory for twice the interval here to measure
four times the time. I expect it to measure twice the time. So for that
reason, the square root is the appropriate thing here. Okay, that's called
d tau squared. d tau squared, the proper time along the trajectory of an object.
You're right, that's just d tau. Or d tau squared being dx squared minus dt squared.
d tau squared being dx squared minus dt squared.
d tau is called the proper time. Let's go. I think we'll, let's see. d tau is called
the proper time, and it is the time read by a clock moving along a trajectory. It's
not just dt. That's the important thing. It's not just dt. dt squared minus dx squared.
Let's do one last thing. Let's just do the twin paradox in this language.
I think I've had it. I'm going to finish. You can do the twin paradox in this language.
All you have to do is to compute the proper time along two trajectories, one that goes
out with a uniform velocity, turns around and comes back with the same uniform velocity
versus a trajectory which just goes from here to there. So you have the proper time along
from one point to the same to another point along a straight line
And it's no more weird
it's no weirder really from this perspective
than saying the distance from one point to another
along two different curves
do not have to agree
The proper time along two different curves in general will not agree
What is a little bit weird
is that because of this minus sign
the proper time this way is less than the proper time this way
That's the consequence of this minus sign here
Moving with some dx
decreases the proper time
Alright, we'll do a little bit more next time
but then I want to get to the principles of field theory
and uh... and
connect some
of this with field equations for interesting wave fields
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University
Please visit us at stanford.edu