This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
All right,
let's get back to the subject at hand,
which is classical mechanics.
No,
classical field theory.
But classical field theory,
as I've emphasized several times,
is a special case of
the general rules of classical mechanics.
And that's the way it should
be thought of as an example,
maybe the prime example,
of the basic rules of classical mechanics.
So I think we have to...
review just a little bit about classical mechanics
and then apply it in the field theory context.
What I particularly want to get to tonight
is the connection between symmetries and conservation laws.
Now,
we've done that in the context of classical mechanics,
but it's especially interesting and really
takes a sort of front seat
in the subject of relativistic mechanics.
So let's go back a few steps
and review a little bit about classical mechanics.
Police action,
Lagrangian,
and conservation laws in a simple context.
I don't think we'll have to do...
Hi,
come in.
I don't think we'll have to
get too involved with Hamiltonian mechanics tonight,
although later on we'll want to.
But let's just review very quickly
the mechanics of a system of particles.
And for our purposes right now,
we could have just one particle moving in one dimension,
although everything I say could be generalized just by
putting a little index i next to some symbols.
I'll probably do that.
All right,
so we have a particle with a coordinate x.
Incidentally,
sometimes it's a coordinate x.
Sometimes I use q for coordinates.
Sometimes I use x.
I'll try to be clearer about the logic.
If I change symbols,
ask me about it if it confuses you,
but I think probably it won't too much.
Anyway,
particle is described by a coordinate x,
which depends on time.
Of course,
there could be n particles,
and they could have three-dimensional positions,
in which case we would just
put a little i downstairs to indicate,
which coordinate we were talking about.
And the object of a problem of
mechanics is to compute the orbit vertically.
As always,
we put time.
Horizontally,
we put x.
However many x coordinates we need,
but I'll just draw one.
And then the particle moves
through spacetime along some orbit,
according to the principle of least action.
And the principle of least action says,
minimize...
or at least make stationary.
I'll describe what I mean by stationary in a minute.
For our purposes,
it can mean minimize.
Minimize the action,
and the action is the integral of the Lagrangian,
which depends on the coordinates and the velocities.
x dot stands for dx dt,
integrated with respect to time.
And just to remind you,
we hold the endpoints fixed,
and we don't have to do anything else.
And require that this quantity is minimized.
Minimized with respect to what?
Whenever you say something is minimized,
you imagine that you can
explore some space of possibilities,
and then minimizing means find the possibility
which gives you the minimum value
of the action in this case.
So we're talking about exploring different trajectories.
But in particular,
let's make a little change in the trajectory.
Some small change in the trajectory.
The small change in the trajectory could
involve a change from beginning to end,
or it could just involve some small little region here
where the trajectory has changed.
And recalculate the action.
Recalculate the action as it deviates
from its value along the true trajectory,
and then require that when we
vary the trajectory a little bit,
that the action always increases.
Now,
assuming that it increases
really is basically the same
as assuming that it doesn't change.
Let me just remind you,
when you're minimizing a quantity,
for example,
supposing you're minimizing something
with respect to one variable,
only one variable now.
In this context,
we're minimizing with respect to
an infinite number of variables.
The infinite number of variables are
all the positions along the entire trajectory.
So it's a very complicated problem of minimization
where we're minimizing with respect
to an infinite number of variables.
But nevertheless,
let's examine the problem of minimizing
something with respect to one variable first.
All right,
so the same quantity,
in this case,
let's just call it,
let's call the quantity f,
and it could be f of some variable x,
and it's minimized at that point over here.
So as you well know,
the rule for finding a minimum is,
the minimum is just to differentiate x
and set it equal to zero.
Another way to say the same thing
is to require that at this point here,
that if we make a little shift of x,
a little shift of x,
then that the change in f,
the change of f,
delta f,
when we change x a little bit,
should be zero.
That's the statement,
that's the same as the
statement that the derivative is zero,
that the change is equal to zero.
Okay?
In both directions,
no matter which way you move.
If that's the case,
that the change is zero,
zero of course means only
for very,
very small excursions.
All right?
So the first order change should be equal to zero.
That's the same as saying df
by dx is equal to zero.
We could also say that the change in f
when you move x a little bit
is the derivative of f with respect to x
times delta x.
If df by dx is equal to zero,
so is delta f.
All right,
so you get the idea.
Now,
supposing you have many variables.
In particular,
let's suppose we have two variables.
So there's another variable sticking
out of the blackboard here.
And again,
we have some function which now depends on two variables,
let's say x and y.
And we're looking for some hole,
some dip in the function
where it achieves its minimum
with respect to both variations in both directions.
In fact,
we're looking for a place where
no matter what direction we move off in,
the function doesn't change
to first order.
That's,
the word for that is finding the stationary.
The stationary points of the function.
But a particular example is
finding the minimum of a function.
If we found the minimum of a function
with respect to all variations of this point,
then what we want is that the derivative,
that all the derivatives of f
with respect to x equals zero,
with respect to y equals zero.
Or,
a shorthand version for it
is that if we're right at that point
and we vary both x and y
or all of the variables,
whatever the variables are,
that the change in f,
again,
should vanish.
That's a shorthand version for saying that
all the derivatives are equal to zero.
So in the same manner,
if we're looking for the minimum of the action,
what we want to do is
we want to explore nearby trajectories.
We think we have a solution.
This is supposed to be a solution.
We want to explore nearby trajectories
and require that the change in the action is zero
when we make a small change in trajectory.
Let's just write that the variation of
L of x and x dot dt
is equal to zero
when we change the trajectory a little bit.
Now,
what does changing the trajectory a little bit mean?
It means we add to f to x of t,
we add a small change.
x of t was supposed to be the original solution.
Let's add something small.
Let's call it epsilon
times an arbitrary function of t.
What are the variables in this problem
that we're minimizing with respect to?
We're minimizing with respect to
all these variables f of t,
f of t1,
f of t2,
in fact,
f all along here.
This little bump here represents f.
So the question then is,
how does the action change
when we change x a little bit?
That's easy to work out.
Incidentally,
let's write this out.
The change in x is just
equal to epsilon times f of t.
And of course,
it also follows that the change in the velocity
is epsilon times f of t.
We just differentiate with respect to time
both sides of the equation.
If x changes by a little bit,
then the velocity associated with x changes a little bit.
And we can imagine we have any number of coordinates
and do the same thing.
It's not restricted to just one coordinate,
but let's fix on x
and see what this equation says.
All right,
so this is easy to work out.
We just write that this is
that the change in the action
is equal to the change in the Lagrangian
integrated with respect to time.
But what's the change in the Lagrangian
if we change x and x dot a little bit?
Well,
that's easy.
That's the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to x
times delta x.
But delta x is just proportional to f of t.
We can put an epsilon on the outside here.
The change of x is just f of t.
So let's put f of t there.
Epsilon times f of t,
but I left the epsilon outside.
And then the Lagrangian also depends on the velocity.
So we add plus the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to the velocity
times the change in the velocity.
Integral dt.
That's the change in the Lagrangian
when we change the trajectory a little bit
by an amount of delta of x dot.
Sorry,
it's just epsilon f dot.
Epsilon is already outside here.
Any question about this formula thus far?
It's just a simple formula
that the change in the action is gotten
by varying the Lagrangian a little bit,
by varying x,
and by varying x dot.
Now,
what's the next step?
Anybody remember?
Integration by parts.
This over here.
The f dot.
And what we're using is that if you have a
integral of the form of the product of two functions,
a times b dot,
that's equal to minus the
integral of a dot times b,
as long as you don't vary the endpoints.
As long as things are frozen at the endpoints.
Then there's no contribution from the boundary
in the integration by parts.
And so it's very easy.
Wherever you see a time derivative,
if you have a product and an integral,
this of course is dt.
If you have a product and an integral
of something times a time derivative of something else,
you can switch which one
of them carries the time derivative,
but you have to change the sign.
So that's the rule of integration by parts.
And that's what we have over here.
We have a time derivative f dot over here
times dl by dx dot.
So all we have to do then,
we can do,
not all we have to do,
but what we can do is change the sign,
put the time derivative on the other factor,
and get rid of the time derivative here.
Now,
why was that a nice thing to do?
It was a nice thing
to do because it isolates f,
by itself,
without a time derivative in both terms.
So that means we can factor out of the bracket,
not out of the integral,
but out of the square bracket here,
we can factor f.
Both terms are proportional to f.
And we have f dt,
f dt.
Now,
what do we want to be true?
We want this to be true,
that this is equal to zero,
for every possible variation
f of t.
We want to explore all neighboring trajectories,
all possible neighboring trajectories,
and require that every possible shift in the trajectory,
in other words,
every possible f,
gives the same answer
when you vary the action to first order,
namely zero.
All right?
So that means that this has to be zero
for all functions f of t.
All possible functions.
Well,
if you think about it a little while,
you realize the only way
an integral like this can be zero
for all possible f of t
is for the thing that it multiplies to be zero.
Supposing the thing that it multiplied here
was not equal to zero somewheres,
for some,
at some time.
Supposing the thing that was here
was not equal to zero at some time.
Then we could choose a function of time
that was the f of t
that was narrowly concentrated
near the place where we knew
the thing in the brackets was not equal to zero,
concentrated only in that region,
and we would get something not equal to zero.
f not equal to zero,
this thing not equal to zero,
over a small enough range,
we'll get something not equal to zero.
So the only way that an integral like this
can be zero for every possible f of t
is for the integrand,
for the thing in the bracket to be zero.
This is analogous to testing the function
in all possible directions.
All possible directions,
all possible variations,
if you require that f be stationary
with respect to all possible variations,
it tells you that all
of the derivatives equal to zero.
The analog here is that what's in here,
in the bracket,
must be zero
for all possible,
for all times,
between here and here.
That's the Euler-Lagrange equations,
that's the derivation of the Euler-Lagrange equations.
Let's write them down.
ご視聴ありがとうございました
d by dt of the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to x dot minus the Lagrangian
with respect to x.
Let's use the same symbol here.
Now the only difference,
if we have lots of coordinates,
now let's call the coordinates
q instead of x.
They might not be the Cartesian coordinates of a particle,
they might include
angles,
points along some arbitrary curve,
some more generalized kind of coordinates.
Exactly the same thing will be true,
except we'll just call the q's,
we'll call the x's
q's.
It's just a renaming.
But if there are many,
many coordinates,
well,
many or more than one,
then we'll want to put an i there.
And so for each coordinate,
x,
y,
z,
different particles,
there will be an Euler-Lagrange equation,
which is essentially
of the form of Newton's equations
for each component of the configuration space.
So we've
been through that.
I assume that you have that in your notes.
That's the derivation
of Euler-Lagrange.
And it's the basis of the Lagrangian equation.
The basic equation of Lagrangian mechanics.
Now we want to generalize that to field theory.
Field theory is a special case of this,
where the various coordinates correspond to the
values of fields at different positions of space.
We worked out an example,
which was
the string.
The string is the number
of points of a particular field.
This is the number of points of a particular
So we were going to start with this,
by dividing,
subdividing space into a lot of little segments,
or a lot of little positions,
and then instead of thinking of a continuous field,
we thought
of the value of a field at each point.
We discretized it,
we discretized the field,
and replaced it by a rather
dense collection of degrees of freedom.
We called the degrees
of freedom,
we didn't call them x,
because x now is always greater
than a number of degrees of freedom.
labels position labels um doesn't label a
location of any of a particle it
labels a location in space in other
words it labels the position that we
might be evaluating the field the
field becomes the coordinate the field becomes
the degree of freedom in other words the
cues in this problem are the fields at
the different positions we could call it Q of
I sorry Phi of I meaning Phi at the
position at the Ith position or we could call
it Phi at point X I or we can just
call it Phi of X Phi of X sort
of has the implication that we're going to a
limit where we take the points to
be so dense that this field becomes a
continuous
field and we're going to have a
continuous field and we're going to have a
continuous field and we can imagine doing
that process and if we do imagine
it then the field theory just
is a special case of classical mechanics
where the cues are just the values of
the fields at the different points now I
emphasize they are not locations of anything
in space they are the values of
fields at different points in space
but as we discussed last time
you can summarize all of this
passing from a discrete description to a
continuous description replacing sums by
integrals differences by derivatives we
can summarize all of this by saying we
have a Lagrangian which begins as a sum
over position sum of all the
kinetic energies some of all the potential
energies and
and becomes replaced by an integral the X
now as I said X now does not stand
Lagrangian is an integral the X the
integral over X replaces the sum over I
integral the X of some Lagrange
density Lagrange density means you integrated
over space to find the Lagrangian and
what does the Lagrange density depend on
in general Lagrange density will depend on
the values of the fields at each
position will depend on Phi of X it
may also depend on differences of Phi at
neighboring points yeah is there
some meaning between switching from uppercase
to lowercase oh of which the L of
which of which a Phi no none whatever
have I switched oh you you consider
this uppercase yeah oh no uppercase I
will if I do use uppercase I will
do this yeah no that's just sloppy no none
whatever good right so Phi of X right
so the sum over degrees the sum over the
degrees of freedom becomes an integral over X of a
thing which is called the Lagrange
density and in general the Lagrange
density will depend on Phi it will
depend on time derivatives of Phi just
like Lagrangians depend on Q's and Q
dots Lagrangian will depend on Phi it
will depend on Phi dot which means
the time derivative with respect to time
with respect to T the derivative with respect
to T and let me write that just
as DT Phi
that shorthand for d Phi by
dt here's some here's some equivalent notational
equivalences Phi dot equals d Phi by dt
equals dt Phi equals Phi sub T all the
same thing
Phi dot really?
d dt?
phi dt
well it's not the point of the equation
it's the partial it's the total no no it's
the partial that's what I mean by Phi dot
what if it were Omega
dot wouldn't it be the derivative?
what's Omega?
angular momentum I mean you know in general
well if a thing depends on more than
one variable and Phi depends on more than
one variable then it has a
collection of derivatives with respect to each
variable but I'm just saying usually
isn't the dot always the total derivative?
if you like.
if you want me to use
the dot as the total derivative,
no I
don't use it that way and I don't
think it's commonly used that way but let's
like if you see H dot equals
a maximum bracket or something like that
fine in fact modern physicists don't
use it that way they use
it quite often to mean derivative
with respect to T keeping everything else
fixed yeah in fact I I thought I had no great
answer because you had very good answers and that's the whole thing.
can you tell me what class didn't
it have anything to do with it?
what the balance habtantes have used to give the plate data to keep your you
got the constant kanjiA here now is not much use you other one is negative of.
when you see hvis d equals T variables you will notice that one is
positive and the second point Desktopриз watch your putting a bracket soème a formน
it's so easy to write it
that I think I want to
keep it around as a notation.
That's definition now.
Definition of phi dot,
derivative with respect to t.
And if I ever have a situation
where I want to think
about the total derivative of something,
the total derivative may mean along some orbit or something.
Then I would just write d phi by dt.
I will write d phi dt.
Since I will so rarely have to use this,
I prefer to save more complicated notation
for something I use rarely.
Okay,
these are all the same thing.
And let's put phi sub t here.
Meaning to say,
the derivative of phi with respect to t
keeping everything else fixed.
But what else can L depend on?
L can also depend,
on differences of phi between neighboring points.
So you could have in the Lagrangian,
phi appearing at each point separately.
But you could also have the derivatives of phi
appearing in the expression for the Lagrangian.
And in the Lagrangian we wrote down,
the potential energy did involve differences of phi
at two different points.
That translated into something involving
derivatives of phi,
with respect to spatial positions.
So we could have equals dx phi equals phi x.
We can also have d
phi by dy and so forth.
So what can appear here is
derivatives of phi with respect to t,
derivatives of phi with respect to x,
and derivatives of phi with respect to y,
and derivatives of phi with respect to z.
All of them can appear in the Lagrangian.
Notice it's kind of symmetric between t's,
x,
y's,
and z's.
I don't just call this derivatives
of phi with respect to the coordinates.
I can also call these derivatives phi sub mu.
Where mu runs from zero to four.
T being a general derivative.
X being x zero.
X being x one.
Y being x two.
And z being x three.
In a sort of relativistic notation.
All these things mean the same thing.
You want to change the dx and have dx for?
Where?
Yeah,
I was just about to change that.
Here.
Yeah,
exactly.
That's right.
But the integral dx,
when I was thinking about a string,
there was only one space coordinate.
When I'm thinking about a string,
I'm thinking about a field in three dimensions.
Then I want to put d three x.
All right,
now first of all,
what is kinetic energy and what is potential energy?
In the example we worked out here,
the Lagrangian had,
for example,
phi dot squared in it.
That was simply the kinetic energy
of every point oscillating up and down.
When we thought about it as a string,
phi dot squared was the kinetic energy.
So typically,
in a Lagrangian like this,
there will be a term one half phi dot squared.
That's kinetic energy.
It depends,
and kinetic energy by definition
means the things which are quadratic in the velocities.
And velocity means derivative with respect to time.
All right?
So a typical Lagrangian might
have one half phi dot squared,
and then in the example we worked out over there,
there was a minus c squared.
Why was there a minus sign here?
Anybody remember?
In the potential energy?
Because the Lagrangian is
kinetic energy minus potential energy.
All right?
And what was the potential energy?
The potential energy depended on the difference of the field
at neighboring positions.
And so there was d phi by dx squared.
And of course,
in a more general context,
we might also have minus c
squared d phi by dy squared
minus c squared d phi by dz squared.
It's good to write it explicitly,
just to keep track and to remember
that this term is kinetic energy,
and this stuff here is potential energy.
It doesn't depend on velocities.
It doesn't depend on the motion.
It does depend on the configuration,
how the phi's are oriented,
how they're dependent on space,
but not on time.
So this term here is the kinetic energy.
This is potential energy.
There could be other terms in here.
There could be things like,
things which depend on phi itself without derivatives.
It's a perfectly rational thing to put into a Lagrangian.
For example,
each one of these particles
could have an energy which depends on its height.
Not on the difference between neighboring heights,
but there could be a term in the energy
which would just depend on the height of each particle.
For example,
if the whole thing was in a gravitational field,
then we might put into
here something which depends on phi.
Not the phi by dx,
not the phi by dt,
but possibly just phi itself.
So there might also be dependence on phi.
Let's put some dependence on phi in here.
A nice simple example would be minus some constant,
I'll call it mu,
and I'll put a 2 there
for purely conventional reasons,
times phi squared.
And I choose phi squared because
phi squared,
for no specific reason
except that it makes an easy equation
when we work out the equation of motion.
It could be phi cubed,
it could be phi by itself,
it could be cosine of phi,
but something which depends on phi
and not its derivatives.
So this would be a term in the potential energy
which would depend on the coordinate
of each one of these separately,
not on the differences between them,
whereas the potential energy could also have a dependence
on the gradient of phi.
The gradient in space.
Alright,
this is the Lagrange density here.
The Lagrangian is the integral of that,
but the action,
the action is the integral
of the Lagrangian with respect to time.
So that's yet one more integral.
The action is the integral of this dt,
which means d4x.
That's the structure,
that's the general structure
of field theory,
not that specific Lagrangian,
but a Lagrange density integrated over space and time
is the starting point of most discussions of field theory.
We'll start with Lagrangian.
Now what is the condition that the theory be Lorentzian?
The condition that the theory be Lorentzian variant
is very,
very simple.
You,
of course,
first must start with some idea
of what kind of transformation properties
your field variables have.
The field variables could be scalars,
they could be vectors,
four vectors.
You have to give them a transformation property
under Lorentz transformations,
not just under rotations of space.
So the field variables could be any number of vectors,
any number of vectors,
any particular kind of,
as I said,
scalars,
vectors,
tensors,
which we haven't spoken about yet.
But in this simple case,
I'm imagining the field variable as a scalar.
We'll go on to more complicated cases with vectors,
but for the moment,
just scalars.
The field variable phi is a scalar.
The important thing is that
the Lagrange density be a scalar.
If the Lagrange density is a scalar,
it means the action doesn't depend
on which Lorentz frame you use.
So if the Lagrange density
script L here is a scalar,
you don't have to even think about whether the equations
are Lorentz invariant.
They will be.
All right,
now,
this is a Lorentz.
As I've written it here,
this is a Lorentz scalar.
It has the form phi dot squared minus c squared.
Let's set c equal to 1 for simplicity.
At least at this stage,
let's set c equal to 1.
The thing in the Lagrangian is d mu phi,
d mu phi.
Remember what this means.
This stands for the four derivatives,
time derivative and the three space derivatives,
these things here.
These stand for the same derivatives,
except with a change of sign of the time component.
All right?
So d mu phi stands for the complex of objects,
phi t,
phi x,
up to phi z.
And d super mu phi stands for the same thing,
except the time component's changing.
Then when I multiply the contravariant derivative
times the covariant derivative,
it gives me something with a time derivative squared
having the opposite sign from the space derivative.
In fact,
I think I want to
put a minus sign in here.
And a 2.
So the Lagrange density that I've written down over here
is nothing but the scalar
which is made by contracting together
the covariant components of the gradient of phi
with the contravariant components.
That makes a scalar.
And as a scalar,
it tells us the action is invariant.
And if the action is invariant,
the equations of motion will be invariant.
So it's real easy
to design relativistically invariant theories.
What's that?
Oh,
this one here?
Well,
in fact,
it does.
Since phi is a scalar,
so is phi squared.
Oh,
sorry.
Yes,
you're right.
Minus mu over 2 phi squared.
Is that mu over 4?
Or is that 2 squared,
like outside?
Thank you.
Of course,
it doesn't matter.
It's the definition of mu.
But I did intend that the
mu also had a factor of 2.
Right.
Good.
Okay.
So that's the basic setup.
Now,
the next question is,
given a Lagrangian like this,
what are the Euler-Lagrange,
what are the analogs
of the Euler-Lagrange equations?
In other words,
what are the field equations
as partial differential equations?
For the case of a coordinate
which only depends on one variable,
namely time,
the Euler-Lagrange equations were just ordinary
differential equations for the time dependence.
Now we have a problem which is
to figure out not only the dependence
of phi on time,
but also on space and time.
And so the equations are
going to be partial differential equations.
Or wave equations.
Wave equations to be specific.
So the question is,
how do you take a thing like this
and minimize it?
Let's just take this to be a special case.
Here's the general form.
L is equal to an integral d
cubed x of this kind of thing here.
The action,
let's write the action,
is the integral d4x.
Well,
you do exactly the same
thing as in the previous example.
As in the simpler case,
you say let's suppose that phi of x and t,
which I could just write as phi of x mu,
but phi of x and t,
let's suppose that's a solution.
And now let's add plus epsilon times
a function of x and t to it.
What we require is that when we
change the function of x and t,
we require that the field in this manner,
that the change in the action is equal to zero.
That's the analog of saying that the action is stationary.
In fact,
it's not the analog,
it's a statement,
that the action is stationary when
you change the orbit of the field.
Think of this as sort of the orbit,
how the field varies in space and time,
is the generalization of the orbit of a mechanical system.
And we're requiring that the action
of phi of x and t,
the action be stationary.
Well,
let's work it out.
This is not so hard to do.
If delta phi is equal to
epsilon times f of x and t,
then what is the change in,
let's call it,
phi mu?
If there's a change in phi,
what is the change in the derivative?
What is the change in the
derivative of phi with respect to x?
Very simple.
It's just equal to epsilon times the
derivative of f with respect to x mu.
So,
for example,
this stands for the complex of equations,
I don't have to write them out,
that the change in the time derivative of phi
is epsilon times the time derivative of f,
and likewise for the other components,
f of x and t.
If you change phi by a little bit,
then the change in the derivatives is
just the derivatives of the change in phi.
Okay,
so now let's calculate the change in the action.
The change in the action is
going to be the integral d4x
times the change in the Lagrangian,
when I change the field a little bit.
And what is that?
That's the derivative of the Lagrangian density
with respect to phi,
times delta phi,
that's epsilon,
epsilon on the outside,
f of x and t,
plus the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to phi mu,
phi mu,
phi t,
phi x,
phi y,
phi z,
times the change in phi mu,
which is df by dx mu.
I think I have that right.
And of course this stands for a sum.
This stands for a sum over x,
y,
and z,
or x,
y,
z,
and t,
all of them.
That's it,
that's the change in the action.
What do I want to do?
I want to set this equal to zero.
That's the condition that the action be stationary.
Now,
over here I have f of x and t,
here I have the derivatives of f.
What do I do to go from,
to get rid of this derivative on f here?
Integrate by parts.
The rule for integrating by parts,
I'm not going to work it out for you,
but the rule for multiple dimensional integrals
is exactly the same as the rule
for sum over x,
y,
and z.
You're allowed to take the derivative off here
and put it on here at
the expense of a sign change.
So this is the same thing as minus,
and now the derivative with respect to x goes here.
Let me write it out,
let me write it out a little more clearly.
Minus d by dx mu
of the derivative of the Lagrange density
with respect to phi mu
times f of x and t again.
All right,
now we're getting close to being in business.
We have f multiplying both factors here,
so I can put a bracket around here
and factor out the f.
The next step is exactly the same as it was
in the particle case.
This is supposed to be equal to zero
for all possible functions of x,
for all possible ways of changing the field
away from the solution.
In other words,
we're exploring all variations of the field
away from the solution
and requiring that the action is stationary.
This has to be zero for all f.
How is that possible?
It is only possible if the
thing in the bracket here is zero.
So,
we come to the conclusion
that for each field in the problem,
we're dealing now with a problem with only one field,
phi.
If there were several fields,
we would have a separate equation for each one,
but let's deal with the case of one field.
Our equation of motion,
our Euler-Lagrange equation of motion,
which follows from the Lagrangian,
is here it is.
Take the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to phi mu.
Differentiate it with respect to x mu.
This is in close analogy
with the derivative of the ordinary Lagrangian
with respect to q dot d by dt.
Close analogy,
but there are four terms in here,
derivative with respect to q dot.
T with respect to x,
with respect to y,
with respect to z.
And then subtract off minus the derivative of L
with respect to phi equals zero.
All right,
so now we have a kind of machine.
You feed into it a Lagrange,
a scalar Lagrange density.
And I think from now on,
I'm simply going to call L,
script L,
the Lagrangian.
It's properly called the Lagrange density,
but it's a mouthful.
For a field theory,
we'll just call it the Lagrangian.
Eh,
maybe I won't.
Maybe I'll continue to call it the Lagrange density.
But if I slip and call it the Lagrangian,
either correct me or,
well,
it doesn't,
if it's clear,
don't bother.
All right,
so this is our equation of motion.
And now let's work it out.
This is our equation of motion for a field phi.
Let's work it out.
For our favorite Lagrangian over here.
Here's a specific Lagrangian.
Let's work it out.
This here is a sum.
Okay?
So let's start,
what does it say?
It says,
the only thing we have to remember
is that the time components get the opposite sign
from the space components.
That's the main thing here.
All right,
so this says that d by dt
of partial of L
with respect to phi dot
that's the first term,
I guess,
minus
d by dx
partial of L
with respect to phi x
and likewise for y and z
minus
the derivative
with respect to phi
equals zero.
And let's work it out now.
What's the derivative of this Lagrangian
with respect to phi dot?
Just phi dot.
Okay.
One half gets eaten up by the two here.
The derivative of the thing inside the bracket
with respect to phi dot
is just phi dot.
Okay?
So our first term here becomes
dL by d phi dot
is just replaced by phi dot.
And what's d by dt
of phi dot?
Phi double dot.
Two time derivatives.
Second time derivative
with respect to t.
Or just phi tt.
We could call it phi tt.
Second time derivative of phi
with respect to t.
Now,
what about the derivative
of the Lagrangian?
I made a mistake.
This is a plus sign here.
The minus is here.
No,
there's no minus over here.
This should not be minus.
This is plus.
What's partial of L
with respect to phi x?
It's minus c squared
times phi x.
Alright,
so let's put that one in.
Minus
c squared
phi x.
What's the derivative
of phi x with respect to x?
Phi x x.
Two derivatives.
I'll write it out in longhand in a moment.
But let's...
And likewise
for y and z.
So,
there's minus c squared
phi y y.
Minus c squared phi z z.
And now let's include
this last term just for fun.
I'm going to drop it soon because
it'll come back,
but for most of
tonight I'll get rid of this.
Minus mu phi squared.
So we have to
subtract the derivative of...
Where is our equation?
We have to subtract
minus
the derivative of L
with respect to phi.
And I think that gives us
I think a plus
mu phi
plus two.
Right?
Equals zero.
Like it's equals zero.
It's equal to zero.
No,
there isn't a half.
Because each one of these things
was squared.
So when you differentiate it...
That's why the half is there.
The half is there to avoid the half
in the equation of motion.
Right.
Alright,
so let me write this out in longhand.
In longhand
it's second derivative of phi
with respect to t squared
minus c squared
plus second of phi with respect to x squared
plus second of phi
with respect to y squared
with respect to z squared
plus second of phi with respect to z squared
all equals
sorry
let's put the plus mu phi
plus mu phi
equals zero.
Okay.
I only kept the mu phi there
just to illustrate
in some generality
what it would mean
to have a term in the Lagrangian
or a piece of the Lagrangian
which depends explicitly on phi.
I'm going to drop it now.
We're going to come back to it.
Is it a minus sign?
I think it's a plus sign.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
Incidentally,
the mu phi squared term
is called the mass term
and it has a great
deal to do with the mass
of the quanta
of the field.
In fact,
it is nothing but the square of the mass
of a particle
that might be described
by this field.
There's a connection between
fields and particles through quantum mechanics.
So the electromagnetic
field,
the particles
that it describes are photons.
Photons
have no mass.
So you would not have this term for photons.
Other particles which have mass
you would have this term.
But we're going to come to that.
Why do I say it's a mass?
Well,
it's not the least bit obvious at the moment.
But let's just drop it and study the theory
without that term.
Here is the equation describing
um
it describes light.
It describes the
propagation of any massless
field.
Sorry.
It describes any field
which propagates with the speed of light.
Let's just
look at it in one dimension.
We've of course already
done this.
For example,
supposing the field
only depends on time.
Of course it depends on time.
If it's any kind of decent field,
it's going to depend on time.
But supposing it doesn't depend on all three
coordinates.
Suppose it only depends
on x and not y and z.
How can that be?
Well,
if a wave was moving down the
x-axis,
a plane wave with no variation
perfectly
uniform wave fronts
moving down the x-axis
then it would have no
dependence on the other two directions.
A uniform
infinite plane wave moving down
the axis like this would have
no dependence on y and z.
And so for that situation
the wave equation would be
d second phi by dt squared
minus c squared
d second phi
by dx squared
is equal to zero.
Alright.
There are in fact
two kinds of
solutions of this equation.
This is the
standard wave equation of
a field
which propagates with a uniform velocity
c.
And the solutions of these equations are
functions
two kinds,
two of them
any function
of x minus ct
or a function of
x plus ct
doesn't have to be the same function
take any function
let's call it f
let's not call it phi
let's write
phi
is equal to any function
of x minus ct
in fact you can add
plus another function
of x plus ct
what does this
term describe?
right
you start
at t equals zero
with some
any old function of x
and now
when you write
function of x minus ct
it just describes exactly that same
profile moving with velocity c
down the x axis
what about this one?
that just describes
the profile g
moving in the opposite direction
in the left direction
now of course
there was nothing sacred about
a wave moving along the x axis
it could have rotated it
and have it moved along any axis
or even any
catty cornered axis
but
this is the typical
kind of solutions of these wave equations
the wave shape is maintained
that's right
that would not be the case
if we added in
the mu
plus or minus
mu phi
in other words
with this extra term over here
it would not be the case then
so this is a special feature
of
what is called the massless wave equation
it's called
the massless wave equation
it corresponds to the fact
that this describes waves
that move with a particular
fixed velocity
so the whole thing just moves off
with a uniform velocity
same way a light ray would
a light beam would
question?
but if g of x is not the same
if you have the two of them
then they
they're different shapes moving
so it doesn't look like
oh yeah yeah yeah
yeah you could have sure you could have
a shape like this moving to the right
and add onto it a shape which looks like
this
moving to the left
and of course when they pass through each other
you're going to see something much more complicated
but all they're really doing is passing through each other
without doing anything very interesting
alright so
that's the general pattern
left moving waves
and right moving waves
phi is not a sufficient initial condition
what's the
say it again
phi itself is not a sufficient initial condition
that's right
what's the other part of the initial condition
time derivative of phi
yeah
for example
here's the point
another way to say it is this
supposing I just gave you the field phi
at time zero
here it would be
f of x plus g of x
how do I know
that the field phi
that some piece of it is right moving
how do I know how to divide this up into
this is just the sum of
these two is just some function
how do I know
how to divide it up into left moving parts
and right moving parts
well if I also tell
you what the time derivative is
then
knowing both the function
and the time derivative allows you to
break it up into
the two parts like that
and that's a little exercise you can do
so yes you need to know phi and phi dot
same exact story
as with
particles
or with ordinary coordinates
you need to know the coordinates and the time derivatives
to get started
in any case
for the simple wave equation without mass term
this is what you get
now notice
this equation either with or without
the mass term the equation is
linear
linear means only first powers
of phi appear
higher derivatives of phi appear
but nothing ever involving
products of phi or derivatives of phi
times phi or derivatives of phi
with other derivatives of phi
linear equation
means that the only thing that appears
in it are
first powers of phi
derivative of phi second derivative of phi
and so forth
under those circumstances you can add solutions
if you have two solutions of the equation
you can add them together
and there's still a solution
you can also multiply
the solutions by a number
and it's still a solution
so a linear equation
you can add solutions
here I've just done it
you can multiply solutions by numbers
and there's still solutions
this equation is linear
even with the mass term
what is it from the point of view
of the Lagrangian
that made the equation linear
the Lagrangian is quadratic
it involves
phi squared
derivatives of phi squared
squares of derivatives of phi
sorry
and so forth
so it only involves things to the second power
that means when you differentiate
the Lagrangian
with respect to
its various arguments
you'll only get first powers of phi
and so if the Lagrangian
is quadratic
the equation of motion
is linear
do you know a mechanics problem
that has a linear equation of motion
mechanics meaning to say
not field theory but just particle motion
harmonic oscillator
even simpler it would just be a free particle
x dot squared
okay
that's equation of motion
is just x double dot equals zero
and that's very linear
well it can't be very linear
you're either linear or you're not linear
but if you want to
have a more interesting
example involving some
potential energy
then for the potential energy
in the Lagrangian minus
some constant times x squared
so it's the quadratic
character of the Lagrangian
which in turn means the quadratic character
of the potential and kinetic energy
which make the equation linear
just to remind you the equation of a harmonic
oscillator is x double dot
equals minus kx
again only first powers
and linear equations are
particularly simple to study
okay that's
the mass part
attenuates the wave
always
the mass part attenuates the wave
well it doesn't attenuate the wave
what it does is it causes
alright I'll tell you what it does
it causes different wavelengths
you can think of any wave
as being made up of different wavelengths
alright
it causes different wavelengths to propagate with different
velocities
dispersion
the result is it causes the shape of the wave
to change
so the shape of the wave changes with time
it doesn't disperse away
it doesn't fade away
but it does cause the shape to change
and it will wobble and do things
in a more complicated kind of motion
alright
we'll solve these equations
but what I wanted to do
tonight really
was not to solve
equations of motion
but to study conservation laws
an awful lot of
field theory
quantum field theory,
elementary particle physics
the whole
works is the study of
symmetries and
the associated conservation laws
so let's take a five minute break
and then come back and immerse ourselves
in the theory of symmetries
and the associated conservation laws
two cases of the
connections between
now they're really not
two cases but I just want to
for simplicity separate them
now
one of them has to do with
energy conservation and the other
all other conservation laws
energy conservation is a little bit special
although it can be cast in the same form
as the others
what symmetry does it have to do with
excuse me
translation of
the action with respect to time
in other words if there's no special
origin of time in your problem
for example
how could you have
a problem in which there was not
time translation invariance incidentally
and you can't
yeah for example
the universe is expanding
one time is not like another time
so that would be an example
some problem
where for some bizarre reason
the force law was changing
with time
so you can certainly imagine
problems
where you don't have
time translation invariance
but most problems
in physics have time translation invariance
which means it doesn't matter
at what time you start
if you start the same way
at one time or another time
the ensuing histories will be the same
except just lagging
one behind the other by the time shift
when that happens
you have energy conservation
and I'm not going to go
back through the derivation of that
that we did in the mechanics class
and it's a little more intricate
than the other ones
so I'll just ask you to go back
and
recall
the velocities
velocities mean time derivatives
not space derivatives
but time derivatives
if the Lagrangian has a term
which is a time derivative squared
or a time derivative
of one thing
times a time derivative of another thing
in other words it's quadratic
and time derivatives
then those terms are called kinetic
so for example
in our example
the term one half
phi dot squared
is called kinetic
kinetic field energy
kinetic energy of the field
it's not kinetic energy
in the sense of something moving down
down the corridor here
it's kinetic energy in the sense
that the field is moving with respect to time
the field is changing with respect to time
so this is kinetic
t let's call it
t for the
or just k,
kinetic energy
would be that
so the things which do not depend at all on
time derivatives
are potential energy
alright so what are the potential energy
we call it u
that will have one half
in our example over there
one half
the
space derivatives
plus one half
so these constitute potential energy
if you think about it for a minute
when we worked out the problem of the
chain of springs
the space derivative terms
came from the stretching of springs
the time derivative terms
actually came from kinetic energy
of the motion of the mass points
connecting the springs
so in fact these space derivatives really do
correspond to something more like
potential energy than kinetic energy
but the potential energy which depends on
neighboring points
on the field configuration of neighboring points
but they don't depend on velocities
only on gradients
we could call these spatial gradients
alright what else did we have
in the potential energy
we also could have this
mu phi squared term
so I think it was plus
mu
phi squared
over two
then kinetic energy
minus potential energy
is the lagrange density
actually
is this the kinetic energy
strictly speaking
the kinetic energy is the integral of this
over space
it's the sum of all the kinetic energy
of all the fields of all the positions of space
In the case of a string
the full kinetic energy
is the sum of the kinetic energy
of all the moving mass points
so strictly speaking
of this.
Let me put it in blue here.
It's really the integral d3x,
and the potential
energy would be the integral also.
But sometimes we lapse into a simpler language and just
call this term the kinetic energy without the integral,
and this term the potential
energy.
And of course,
we can have more complicated expressions.
This does not exhaust all possibilities.
In fact,
there's no reason why you can't put here
phi to the fourth or phi to the tenth
power or whatever you like,
but as long as it doesn't have time derivatives,
it's part
of the potential energy.
Now,
the Lagrangian is the difference
of the two kinds of energy.
Let me put my…
I lost it.
Lagrangian is the difference,
but the energy itself,
which in Hamiltonian
mechanics becomes the Hamiltonian,
of course,
but let's not worry about that.
The full
energy is kinetic energy plus potential energy.
So it's the sum of these.
Phi dot squared
plus the gradient of phi squared.
The whole thing.
So the whole thing is the integral
of phi squared plus mu phi squared.
Notice that in
the energy in this form,
all of the terms are positive.
All the terms are positive.
Kinetic energy,
potential energy,
and even the term coming
from the mu phi squared are
all positive.
Of course,
nothing to prevent me from putting
this in with a negative sign,
but I didn't on purpose.
So the energy typically has
some kind of positivity associated with
it.
What if phi is absolutely zero?
In other words,
no field,
no waves at all.
Then the energy
is zero.
Phi is zero,
the derivative of phi is zero,
and so forth.
The energy is completely
zero.
Also,
mu phi squared is zero.
And since the expression for the energy is positive,
if phi is not zero,
then the energy is zero.
So the energy is zero.
The energy of anything which is
not just phi equals zero is positive.
So any wave or
any configuration of the field is positive,
has a positive energy,
unless the field is
just plain zero.
Plain zero is called a vacuum,
and anything with a varying phi or a non-zero
phi carries energy and is called an excited state.
Okay.
So that's energetics.
And if
you go back to the original formulation of mechanics,
in the quarter on mechanics,
you'll
discover that there's a derivation of the
fact that kinetic energy plus potential energy
is conserved if the problem is time translation invariant.
So this is our first conservation
law,
conservation of energy.
Later on,
if we explore more complicated Lagrangians,
I'll
remind you of a more general definition of the energy.
But as long as the energy
breaks up into a kinetic term,
quadratic and time derivatives,
and a potential energy term,
then kinetic plus potential is conserved.
That's a general
theorem.
We could prove it,
but I didn't want to spend
a lot of time at it,
since it really
just follows exactly the pattern.
It's not that I didn't want to do it.
It's just a little
too intricate to go over again.
Go back to your notes and
see if you can find it.
And as I said,
it's a special case of mechanics.
So you don't have to
do it over again for field
theory.
It's just a special case of mechanics energy conservation.
Now,
there are other conservation laws.
Other conservation laws follow from principles like
this.
Let me remind you in ordinary mechanics.
Supposing you have a Lagrangian,
no,
an ordinary
Lagrangian.
Okay.
which depends on some q's and some q dots.
Not just one,
but a whole family of them.
Now,
supposing the Lagrangian is unchanged
if you make certain transformations on q.
If you do something to q,
and in particular,
if you take each q sub i
and add to it a small change
which has the form f
sub i of all the q's,
this means some i-th function of all the q's,
including q sub i,
q1 through qn.
Supposing if I make such a change,
supposing it's true that the Lagrangian just doesn't change.
That's called a symmetry.
Let me give you an example,
or a couple of examples.
Kinetic energy of a free particle,
x dot squared,
over 2.
mx dot squared over 2.
Forget the a.
That's the integral.
That's the Lagrangian.
Is there a transformation that I can do
that won't change the Lagrangian?
Yes.
Just take x and add a small displacement to it.
This just corresponds to displacing
your system a little bit.
If you change x by a constant amount,
incidentally,
these q's here,
these f's,
are not supposed to depend...
on time.
No time dependence at all.
Just a constant shift of some kind of the q's.
Here's a constant shift of the x's.
It just corresponds to displacing your system a little bit.
If I shift x by a constant amount,
it does not change x dot.
It doesn't change the velocity.
The change in the velocity is zero,
because epsilon doesn't depend on time.
So,
the Lagrangian theorem is,
the Lagrangian doesn't change if
you shift x a little bit.
That's one example.
Supposing I had added something.
Supposing I had added...
Let's make it a harmonic oscillator.
kx squared over 2.
Now what happens if I shift x a little bit?
This term doesn't change,
but this term does change.
This is just a statement that
if I have a harmonic oscillator,
and I shift the coordinate a little bit,
the potential energy changes.
So,
the free particle...
has a symmetry.
Shift of x.
The harmonic oscillator does not share that symmetry.
But now let's take another problem.
Let's take a problem with
two particles connected by a spring.
Let's call the position of the first one x,
and the position of the second one y.
They don't correspond to two different axes,
they just correspond to two particles.
x and y.
What's the energy?
Kinetic energy of the first particle
is mx dot squared over 2.
Second particle,
let's call it capital M y dot squared over 2.
Now,
what about the potential energy?
The potential energy only depends on
the distance between x and y.
Alright?
Depends on how much the spring is stretched.
And so the potential energy,
which goes into the Lagrangian with a minus sign,
of course,
that's going to have a spring constant,
k over 2,
and it's going to have x minus y squared.
Okay?
Now I assert that there's a symmetry.
The symmetry is to add to x and y,
each of them the same amount.
x goes to x plus epsilon,
and y goes to y plus epsilon.
That's simply a shift of the whole thing.
Both particles shifted by the same amount.
What happens to the terms in the Lagrangian?
First of all,
what happens to x dot?
x dot doesn't change.
If you shift x by a constant amount,
No change in x dot,
no change in the kinetic energy.
Likewise for the y kinetic energy.
x changes,
and y changes,
but x minus y does not change.
You've shifted x and y by exactly the same amount,
so the separation between x and y has not changed.
Potential energy has not changed.
Again,
we have a symmetry.
It's the symmetry,
in this case,
of both particles being shifted.
Alright?
So let's think of some other symmetries.
Supposing I have a symmetry,
and I have some system of particles
interacting with various kinds of forces and so forth.
As I illustrated here,
one symmetry is to shift the position of everything.
Shift in the x direction,
shift in the y direction,
shift in the z direction.
As long as the forces are,
as long as the potential energy only depends on differences,
then again,
this will be a symmetry.
But we also have other symmetries.
Rotational symmetry.
Supposing I rotate the coordinates.
That's more complicated.
In that case,
more complicated formulas for rotating coordinates.
But nevertheless,
as long as the forces
only depend on distances between particles,
if you rotate a system,
the energy doesn't change,
neither the kinetic energy nor the potential energy.
So again,
another symmetry of the problem.
Symmetries correspond
to changes that you can make in the coordinates,
time-independent changes,
that don't change the Lagrangian.
That the Lagrangian doesn't vary
when you make such a change.
The value,
the numerical value of the Lagrangian.
Whenever you have a symmetry like that,
you also have a conservation law.
Let's prove that.
It just follows very simply from,
from Lagrange's equations.
But we need a definition.
Well,
we don't need a definition,
but we can use a definition.
The definition of the canonical momentum
conjugate to a coordinate q.
Alright.
These are the q's and the p's.
For every q,
i,
there is also a conjugate momentum,
pi.
Now,
conjugate momentum
may not look at all
like what you're ordinarily accustomed
to thinking of as momentum.
It's a mathematical definition of something
which for certain situations
looks like ordinary momentum.
But may or may not look and be familiar,
you know,
have a familiar connection with mass times velocity.
Angular momentum,
for example,
is a thing which doesn't look
all that much like ordinary velocity.
And there are lots and lots of other things
and lots of other examples
which look even less like ordinary velocities of things.
But what is the definition of p sub i?
p sub i is by definition
the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to q sub i dot.
It's the thing in the left-hand side
of Lagrange's equation.
Lagrange's equation,
or the Euler-Lagrange equation,
can also be written in another form.
They can be written in the form
d by dt of p sub i,
the time derivative of the i-th
canonical momentum
is equal to the derivative of Lagrangian
with respect to q sub i
for each i.
All right,
everybody,
this is review.
I'm taking this to be review.
The canonical momentum is dL by dq sub i dot.
Incidentally,
what is the canonical momentum
conjugate through x?
It's the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to x dot.
That's just mx dot,
mv.
So for this kind of Lagrangian,
it is just your old familiar momentum.
But more complicated situations,
it may be something else.
So this is its mathematical definition.
d by dt,
sorry,
p sub i is the thing inside the square here.
Okay,
let's prove a theorem.
Let's prove a theorem
that if there is a symmetry,
in other words,
if when you do this operation,
when you take each q
and shift it by an amount f sub i,
assume the Lagrangian doesn't change.
In other words,
assume
that delta L is equal to zero
under such a transformation,
under such a shift of the coordinates.
All right,
then I assert that there is a symmetry.
Sorry,
it is a symmetry.
Then I assert that there's a conservation law.
And it's very easy to work out.
So,
here's Lagrange's equations of motion.
Let's multiply it by delta q.
Well,
yeah.
Let's take each one of these equations
and multiply left-hand side and right-hand side
by the change in q
when you do the little symmetry operation here.
All right?
Good.
I could either write delta q
or I can write epsilon
times f sub i of q.
This whole thing being delta q.
Delta q sub i.
Let's do it also here.
You're not allowed to do something just on one side.
We have to do it on both sides.
f sub i of q.
Now.
Yeah,
now let's sum.
Now let's sum over all the i's.
What's the left-hand side?
The left-hand side is the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to q times delta q.
That's the amount the Lagrangian changes
when you do this operation.
But the assumption is that we have a symmetry.
If we have a symmetry,
then the right-hand side is more or less the same.
So we have a symmetry.
And the right-hand side is by definition zero.
The change in the Lagrangian when we shift q
times the amount we change q
under the symmetry operation.
That's assumed to be zero.
You don't prove that it's zero.
For a specific Lagrangian,
you prove that it's zero.
But for a specific Lagrangian,
let's suppose that the Lagrangian is invariant
under that operation,
then this side must be zero.
Definition of a symmetry.
On the other hand,
the right-hand side here,
these f's are supposed to be not time-dependent.
These are constant time-independent shifts.
Not a shift which depends on a time,
but a shift which is completely independent of time.
Then the time derivative of f is zero,
and we can write that
this is the sum of i
d by dt of p sub
i f sub i of q.
In other words,
you take the i-th canonical momenta
and multiply it by the amount
that you shift the i-th q
i-th q
by this.
That's equal to zero.
That's what this says.
Well,
this is fantastic.
That says we have a conservation law.
The conservation law is the
approximation of p sub i f sub i of q.
You take each shift,
you take the shift of the i-th coordinate,
f sub i,
I think I dropped epsilon out of this somewheres,
but epsilon multiplied both sides.
Yeah.
It just went along with f.
All right.
We can drop it.
If something is equal to zero,
it's equal to zero with
or without the epsilon multiplying it.
This quantity is conserved.
Is conserved.
Let's work out an example or two.
Well,
here's an example right here.
Let's...
First of all,
delta x is equal to epsilon.
Delta y is equal to epsilon.
That's the common shift of both coordinates.
All right.
Well,
that says that fx...
That just says that fx is equal
to one and fy is equal to one.
x just shifts by amount epsilon.
The f is zero,
is one.
All right.
What about the canonical momentum?
The canonical momentum conjugate to x is equal to one.
That's mx dot.
The canonical momentum conjugate to y,
that's py,
is capital M y dot.
What's the conserved quantity?
The conserved quantity is the sum of p
times the shift of each of the coordinates.
The shift of each of the
coordinates is just by one unit.
I mean,
you can drop the epsilon.
The epsilon is just there to
remind you that we're talking about
a small shift.
All right.
So what's the conserved quantity?
It's just px plus py.
The total ordinary linear momentum.
But it's only conserved because
the potential energy doesn't change
when you make a shift.
Yeah.
So the px and the py aren't independently conserved?
No,
they're not.
certainly not.
Just think about the motion of
this two-particle system with a spring.
The two particles are going like this.
The x component of this momentum is not conserved.
Yeah.
It's basically the center of
mass momentum which is conserved.
Okay.
If there was no spring,
the two would be independently conserved.
All right.
Because of the spring,
only one combination is conserved.
And you find that combination by finding the symmetry.
Okay.
All right.
Let's apply this idea to classical field theory.
Let's write down our Lagrangian
and search for various symmetries.
Yeah.
That's a simple case of Noether's theorem.
That's exactly what it is.
Noether's theorem is a little bit more complex.
It's a little more general,
but this is a simple case of it.
All right.
The first thing we have to do is we
have to understand what we mean by coordinates and
momenta,
the conjugate momenta to the coordinates.
In a field theory,
the fields are the coordinates.
They're not the coordinates x,
y,
and z.
They're the analogs of mechanical degrees of freedom,
the q's.
So,
the coordinates are the fields,
and they're indexed by x
instead of being indexed by i.
What corresponds to the canonical momentum?
The canonical momentum over here is the derivative of
the Lagrangian with respect to q sub i dot.
Well,
and we call that p,
sometimes pi.
I think I prefer to call it pi now.
Pi sub i is equal to this.
The reason I'm using pi is for whatever reason,
it is conventional in field theory
to call the canonical momenta pi's.
I can't help the fact that there
are changes of convention as we go along.
These were established long ago.
But p and pi,
same symbol.
This is just a Greek p.
So,
the canonical momentum,
dl by dq dot,
what does that become?
It becomes the derivative of the
Lagrange density with respect to phi dot.
It's that thing that was somewheres in our...
Well,
let's see,
where is our Euler-Lagrange equation?
Here it is.
Well,
one of these terms is d by dt
of partial of L with respect to phi dot.
Partial of L with respect to phi
dot is the canonical momentum conjugate to phi.
It's usually called pi sub phi.
And there's one at each point of space.
At each point of space,
there's a field phi.
And at each point of space,
there's the canonical conjugate to that.
The canonical momentum conjugate to that field.
So,
both sides are functions of position.
What do we do instead of summing over i when we want to
write some expression that in mechanics would be a sum over the coordinates?
We integrate over x.
So,
phi is a function of x.
Pi is a function of x.
And otherwise,
beyond that,
it's just straight mechanics.
Let's see if we can find some symmetries
and conserved quantities associated with our simple field theories.
We have some...
Let's take the simplest field theory that we've written.
Down.
Whew,
I'm getting tired.
I have a feeling I'm probably reaching your
point of exhaustion as well as my own.
Yeah?
No,
no.
I think today's lecture was fairly heavy duty.
I'm not sure whether you've reached saturation.
Somebody speak.
Yes.
Hmm?
I can go on.
It's up to you,
man.
It's up to you.
All right.
I will go on a little bit,
but I will review it next time.
So,
you can tune out now if you like.
And I'll try to...
Yeah.
All right.
Let's take our favorite Lagrangians.
Simple one.
Phi dot squared minus derivative of
phi with respect to x squared.
And we could put y
squared and z squared there too,
but just leave it like this for the moment.
Simple.
I've set the speed of light equal to one.
It doesn't matter.
Let's put the speed of light in.
Can anybody spot asymmetry of this Lagrangian?
Strictly speaking,
the Lagrangian is the integral dx of this.
dx four,
I guess.
Well,
d3x.
But this is the simple case for one-dimensional string.
But I just don't feel like writing the remaining terms.
So,
let's take this case,
but there's no difference in the...
Can you spot any symmetry?
Translation of what?
Which?
There's translation of the x-axis,
indeed,
but that's...
Yes,
we're going to do that one.
There's a little simpler one.
It's translation of phi.
Supposing I take phi of x,
and everywhere's shifted by the same amount.
Phi of x plus epsilon.
This is a uniform shift of phi everywhere's.
Why is this symmetry?
Well,
supposing I shift phi,
what happens to phi dot?
Nothing.
Because I'm assuming that epsilon here is constant.
What happens to d phi by dx?
Epsilon is a constant,
remember.
It's just a number.
Nothing happens.
So,
this Lagrangian doesn't change when you shift phi.
That means that there must be a conserved quantity.
What is that conserved quantity?
It is...
Let's...
The sum over all...
Let's write the general formula and then make it specific.
It's the sum over all the degrees
of freedom of the canonical momentum times...
Let's just...
Times f sub i of q.
But what is f sub i in this case?
It's just one,
right?
Everybody's been shifted by the same amount.
So,
the corresponding f that would multiply here is just one.
f equals one.
Everywhere's.
Everybody's been shifted by the same amount.
And so,
the answer for the conserved quantity is the integral.
Sum becomes integral.
dx.
The canonical momentum conjugate to phi.
Times f sub i.
So,
it's just the integral of phi sub phi.
But what is phi sub phi?
It's the derivative of Lagrangian with respect to phi dot.
So,
we've discovered a conservation law.
The integral dx of phi dot of x is conserved.
Now,
what does that say?
Well,
it says what it says.
That the integral dx of
phi dot of x is conserved.
So,
what does that say?
Well,
it says that,
for example,
if you started the string.
Let's think of it as a string.
And we start the string at time
t equals zero with some arbitrary shape.
And some arbitrary velocity.
Moving in some way.
So that at every point on the axis,
there is a phi dot.
Then the integral of phi dot won't change with time.
What will happen?
This phi dot,
which is going up over here,
might get pulled back down.
We know the string wiggles.
So,
this upward phi dot might get pulled back down.
But at the same time,
this downward phi dot would get pulled back up.
And the net integrated value of
phi dot would not change with time.
That's what we've proved.
Okay,
so that's a conservation law.
Incidentally,
it doesn't mean that the
integral of phi dot is zero.
It means the integral of phi dot doesn't change.
For example,
we could start out with
the string absolutely stretched straight.
But with some part of it
between here and here moving upward.
And every place else stationary.
The integral of phi dot is positive.
Why?
Because phi dot is positive everywhere.
It's not zero.
And what will happen?
With time,
the integral,
the field will move in various ways.
But the integral of the velocity
of the field will stay the same.
So,
that's a conservation law.
Yeah?
If the initial velocity is zero,
but the string is stretched from its neutral position.
Right.
What happens then?
It looks like it's starting at zero velocity.
Yeah.
The integral,
oh,
I know what you're worried about.
You're worried about what happens if the
string is pinned down at its ends.
Yeah.
Okay.
The pinning down of the string breaks the symmetry.
It breaks the symmetry.
One way of thinking about the pinning down of the ends is to imagine that there's
a huge force which is confining the ends of the string to stay at the same position.
All right.
In that case,
the energy would change if you lift the string.
So,
the energy would change.
If you lifted the whole string up or down.
So,
we're talking about translations of the phi coordinate.
it's the pinning down which breaks the symmetry
of phi goes to phi plus a constant.
If we were talking about an infinite string,
we need to be talking,
I should have said,
we need to be talking about an
infinite string which is not pinned down anywhere.
That Lagrangian doesn't apply to the finite string.
Okay.
Well,
there's something that breaks the
symmetry for the finite string,
namely the pinning down condition.
There is another situation.
Here,
let me invent a different kind of
string which really does have the symmetry.
Let's imagine here we have a pole
over here and a pole over here.
There's a ring over here.
There's a ring over here that
can slide up and down the pole.
And the string is stretched between these two.
Okay.
All right.
Now.
Now,
you can shift.
You can shift the whole
string without any cost in energy.
You can't shift the whole string
if the ends are pinned down.
But if the ends are
free to slide up and down,
then there's a symmetry which is the
symmetry of translation of the whole string.
Phi goes to phi plus a constant.
In that circumstance,
the integral of phi dot would be conserved.
And you know what the integral
of phi dot would be for this?
Remember what phi is.
It's just the vertical coordinate of the string.
It would just be the whole ordinary
momentum of the string moving up and down.
So if you give the whole thing a push up,
it will just continue to go up.
That's what it says.
So you have to be careful and
make sure that you really have the symmetry.
And you would not have the symmetry if
the ends of the string were pinned down.
But you do have the symmetry if the
ends of the string are free to move.
Do you know the term dip?
Do you know Dirichlet and Neumann boundary conditions?
Yeah,
okay.
So for Dirichlet boundary conditions,
that means the string pinned down.
You don't have the symmetry.
For Neumann conditions,
you do.
All right,
but this was just an example.
And it's not a terribly interesting symmetry.
In particular,
if we had the term in
the Lagrangian plus mu over 2.
There should be a one-half multiplying this.
Mu phi squared.
Minus mu phi squared.
Then we no longer have the symmetry because phi
squared will not be invariant when you shift phi.
If you shift phi,
phi squared is not invariant.
It changes.
So if we have this mu phi squared term,
we no longer have the symmetry.
So this is not a very robust symmetry.
It's just a particular case
which is very easy to illustrate.
Phi goes to phi plus a constant.
And as I said,
it corresponds to a sort of uniform center of mass
motion of the whole string vertically along the phi axis.
But an ordinary field in infinite space,
an ordinary field phi in infinite space,
if it doesn't have this mass term,
where is it?
If it doesn't have the term
that I call the mass term here.
Then it will also have a similar symmetry.
Phi goes to phi plus a constant.
Alright,
next time,
I think we're finished for today.
Next time,
we have to study spatial momentum.
Ordinary momentum.
The stuff that when it hits you,
knocks you on your...
Not field momentum,
but the kind of momentum that
really hits you when a pulse of...
When a high energy pulse of radiation hits you,
it gives you a push.
And that's a different kind
of momentum than this field momentum.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.