This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
That's one,
it's not one definition of momentum,
it's one example of momentum.
And it's the one that most people are familiar with,
all right?
Now,
you go to Lagrangian mechanics,
and you remember that the Lagrangian
of a particle moving in space
has a term which is the
mass times the velocity squared over two.
And you notice that the momentum
is the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to the velocity.
That happens to equal the momentum,
the same momentum.
But now we have some new concept of momentum,
namely,
the derivative of Lagrangian
with respect to the time
derivative of a particular coordinate.
Let's call it q dot.
Now,
if that coordinate happens not to
be the linear position of a particle,
the position of a particle in Cartesian coordinates,
then it may well be that this object
is not mass times the velocity squared over two.
It's mass times velocity.
An example would be angular momentum,
for example,
where if we have a particle moving in space,
and it has a term in the Lagrangian which,
for example,
could be m over two
times r squared times the angular velocity squared,
then there's a momentum which you
would get by differentiating the Lagrangian
with respect to theta dot.
And that's,
I'm sorry,
m r squared theta dot.
And that would be angular momentum.
It's not linear momentum.
Okay,
so any time you have a
system which is described by a Lagrangian,
and in that Lagrangian
appears time derivatives of variables,
you have now a generalized notion of momentum,
which is the derivative of the Lagrangian.
And that's called,
also called,
p.
You could call it,
you could give it a name,
you could call it p sub q,
meaning to say the momentum
that's gotten by differentiating the Lagrangian
with respect to the velocity
associated with the coordinate q,
but that's a mouthful,
so we just call it the q momentum,
or better yet,
the momentum conjugate to q,
the momentum canonically conjugate to q.
It's getting long,
it's getting as bad as the original thing,
yeah.
The definition for canonically conjugate momentum appears
to be asymmetrical with respect to time,
in that there's no momentum that's
canonically conjugate with respect to time,
just the spatial coordinates.
Right.
So is that true?
Yes and no.
There is a very useful sense in which,
yeah,
what you're saying is right,
of course,
time in mechanics is dealt with differently than space,
or at least in mechanics.
In mechanics,
spatial position are the degrees of freedom of the system,
time is the independent parameter that just unfolds,
so to speak,
and everything depends on
time through parametric dependence.
Now,
it wouldn't make any sense to differentiate the Lagrangian
with respect to the time derivative of the time.
What on earth does that mean?
It doesn't mean anything.
The derivative of the time derivative,
the derivative of time with
respect to time is just one,
so it doesn't make any sense at all.
However,
when you're looking at conservation laws,
a simple example would be a particle,
we did this last time,
in fact,
we talked about two particles interacting by a spring,
but just to remind you,
if you have a Lagrangian,
for example,
m x dot squared over two,
which happens to have a symmetry,
this is a third definition now of momentum.
First one is just m times v.
Second one is partial of
L with respect to q dot.
Now,
the third one,
which is not really usually called moment,
well,
it is a form,
it's not considered a definition of momentum,
it's a theorem about conserved quantities.
Conserved quantities include things like momentum,
so momentum is a special case
of a conserved quantity under certain conditions.
What is the conditions under
which momentum is a conserved quantity?
It's the condition that the Lagrangian
not change if you shift the coordinate,
by amount epsilon.
If you shift the coordinate,
x dot doesn't change,
and using Noether's theorem,
which we talked about last time,
you can prove that m x dot is conserved.
Basically,
it's just a Lagrangian equation that d by
dt of m x dot is equal to zero.
So,
momentum is a special case of a conserved quantity,
which is conserved by virtue of a symmetry.
So that's what we're looking at.
That's another aspect of momentum,
another aspect conserved sometimes by virtue of a symmetry.
Sometimes these are the same things.
Sometimes they're not.
Sometimes they're the same concept,
sometimes they're not.
For example,
there are systems where the Lagrangian
involves velocities in a more complicated way.
In particular,
particle moving in a magnetic field has
another term that also depends on velocity,
where the momentum is in fact not mv.
Anybody know what the Lagrangian is for
a particle moving in a magnetic field?
h dot v.
Right.
There's another term,
the vector potential.
Let's...
The vector potential,
which is a vector field,
plus the vector potential dotted into
the velocity with the electric charge here.
So,
for example,
if I wanted to calculate
the momentum canonically conjugate to x,
I would want to differentiate the
Lagrangian with respect to x dot.
What does that give?
It gives mx dot.
And then from here there's another term.
This here is a sub x,
x dot,
plus a sub y,
y dot,
plus a sub z,
z dot,
and so forth.
And so there's another term,
which is plus the electric
charge times the vector potential.
So there's an example where
perfectly ordinary momentum is not m...
Well,
it's not so perfectly ordinary.
But where the momentum is mv,
it's mv.
So the momentum conjugate to a
Cartesian coordinate is not mass times velocity.
It's mass times velocity plus vector potential.
So these can diverge.
They don't necessarily have to be the same definition here.
They may be different.
Furthermore,
it's quite possible that momentum for
a given system is not conserved.
So these really are three different concepts,
which sometimes converge
and sometimes really define the same object.
Okay.
Now,
what we studied,
we took a field theory last time.
Let's forget that it had anything
to do with a string vibrating.
And it was just a Lagrangian...
It was just a field
theory in which the Lagrangian density...
Now I'll use...
Script L means Lagrange density.
The Lagrange density is equal...
Let me write the Lagrangian.
The Lagrangian is the integral over space,
dx.
If there's three dimensions of space,
this becomes d cubed x with three dimensions of space.
And then we wrote something with
a phi dot squared over two
minus some derivatives,
let's say d by dx,
phi sub x squared over two,
whatever else.
Now just like we define canonical momentum
conjugate to a coordinate
by the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to the velocity,
we can define a thing called field momentum.
Field momentum is not linear momentum.
It's not a vector in space.
It doesn't have a sense of direction.
Ordinary momentum has a direction in space.
It's a vector.
So,
of course,
it's the velocity.
Field momentum is the velocity.
Field momentum is not a vector.
It's a scalar,
in fact.
It's a scalar with respect to rotations.
But its definition is just
the derivative of Lagrangian with respect to phi dot.
That's the canonical momentum conjugate to phi.
So it's quite a different concept.
It has nothing to do with translation symmetry.
It has nothing to do with spatial translation symmetry.
It has only to do with the field phi.
So what is that canonical momentum?
It's usually called pi,
or often called pi.
Pi is like p,
except we're using Greek letters
now instead of Latin letters.
Pi is equal to the derivative of
the Lagrange density with respect to phi dot.
So it's field momentum.
It should not be confused with the kind of momentum
which,
when it hits you,
knocks you in some direction.
Okay?
All right.
It's invariant under a geometric rotation.
It is invariant under a geometric rotation.
Right.
It's not Lorentz invariant,
but it is invariant under a geometric rotation of space.
So this would not be the kind of momentum
which,
when it hit you,
would knock you in some direction.
It has nothing to do with motion along some axis.
It has to do with motion in field space,
if you like.
All right?
So that's another concept of momentum.
No.
Yes.
Now,
last time you were going to,
you did the first symmetry.
Yeah.
You added epsilon to this phi.
Right.
And then you're going to do,
you talked about another symmetry
where you displace essentially x.
And does that also come up with a conservation law?
Yes.
That's what we're going to talk about now.
In a moment.
Let me just review,
though,
to get back.
Yeah.
All right.
So let me just remind you of Noether's theorem,
or the slightly simplified version
of Noether's theorem that we used.
If you have a symmetry,
and a symmetry means an operation
where you replace each one of the q's
by q plus epsilon,
times f sub i of all of the q's.
In other words,
it's just a transformation with a small parameter in it.
If the Lagrangian doesn't change,
if the Lagrangian does not change,
or the Lagrange density,
let's just say the Lagrangian,
if the total Lagrangian doesn't change,
then there is a conserved quantity.
And the conserved quantity is
the sum over all the coordinates
of the momentum conjugate to the i-th coordinate
times f sub i of q.
In other words,
times this small shift.
You can neglect the epsilon there.
Just f sub i of q.
And that's the conserved quantity
which is conserved as a consequence of the symmetry.
Now in some cases,
as I said,
let's forget this over here,
in some cases,
it may correspond to one
of the other definitions of momentum.
It may be that the conserved,
sometimes this is called a conserved charge,
for reasons that will become clear.
But let's just call it the conserved quantity.
The conserved quantity may be momentum.
If this is Lagrangian,
then let's just go through it.
The delta x is just equal to epsilon.
That means f is equal to one.
And the conserved quantity is just p.
Just p.
Momentum.
So sometimes it can be that
the conserved quantity really is momentum.
Other times it may not be.
So let's go back now.
This Lagrangian,
as it stands,
has a symmetry.
And the symmetry is phi goes to phi plus epsilon.
Notice that this epsilon is just a number.
Epsilon,
it does not depend on where we're talking about.
It's not that phi of x is going
to phi of x plus epsilon of x.
It's just phi of x
going to phi plus a constant.
A small constant in this case.
Then we would say that f is equal to one.
And let's write out this Noether conserved quantity.
It's then in this case it becomes integral dx.
The integral dx replaces sum on i.
p sub i is replaced by pi of x.
p sub i.
Well,
first of all,
sum on i is equal to phi of x.
sum on i is integral dx.
p sub i becomes pi of x,
with pi of x being written up here.
And f in this particular
case is just equal to one.
So this becomes our conserved quantity.
The integral,
which is equal to the integral dx
of partial of phi with respect to t.
That's as long as this is equal to phi.
So there's nothing in the problem
which destroys the symmetry of field translation.
Now I'll tell you some
things that can destroy the symmetry,
which would undo this.
Not undo it,
but,
you know,
undo it,
or reverse the conclusion.
If there was another term in here,
which was minus mu phi squared,
for example.
We talked about such terms.
Then this term,
is not invariant when you shift phi.
Phi squared is most certainly not invariant
if you let phi change a little bit.
And so that kind of term would destroy the symmetry.
And it really would.
Another example,
is if we were talking about a string,
or something like a string,
and the string were pinned down at the end points.
Let's suppose we're talking about translation,
of the string along the vertical axis.
Every point gets moved up.
Well that would be a symmetry alright,
except for the fact that by definition,
the end points are supposed to be pinned down.
If the end points are supposed to be pinned down,
it's simply not a possible operation in the system
to move all the points vertically upward.
And so the symmetry again is destroyed.
It's for this reason,
that you can have,
let's look at a particular motion,
you can have standing waves,
let's say standing waves,
which,
you know,
go up,
oscillate up and down.
At this point over here,
all along the string,
phi dot is positive.
It goes up to the
top of its orbit up here,
and the string comes to rest.
So all the phi dots become equal to zero.
Evidently,
the integral of phi dot is not conserved.
On the other hand,
let me imagine a string,
let me give you a string connecting two points,
which does have a conservation law.
I think we talked about this last time.
Instead of pinning the string down here,
let's imagine a pair of poles.
Not poles in any mathematical sense,
but vertical poles.
And let's imagine that the rope or the string
was attached to these poles
by force.
You can imagine a string
increased by first
At this area,
it doesn't change its moves.
It's justате a singularkt from 0 to 1.
Now when we combine all of these cabeza,
conserved
so if you started the entire string moving
upward it would just continue to go upward
and upward and upward
wouldn't have standing waves like that
it would just levitate
okay now let's come to
some other I want to discuss
well three other conservation laws
the first we've already discussed again and it's just energy
conservation of energy
this I'm not going to derive again
it is a conservation law which follows
from a symmetry but it's a more subtle
symmetry
go back to classical mechanics
energy is conserved by virtue of
the symmetry
where time goes to time plus epsilon now
we're not going to get into that tonight
we're going to go back
to our notes in classical mechanics
and remember how that worked
it's a fairly involved little derivation
but the point is that as long as the Lagrangian
doesn't change when you shift time
energy is conserved it's almost
always almost always the case
that the Lagrangian is time independent
it's time independent in the sense
that there's no explicit dependence on time
and in that case energy is conserved
I'll remind you of the formula for energy the
general formula for energy is the formula for energy
if the Lagrangian I'll give you both a special case
and the general case
if the Lagrangian of a system
happens to be of the form
that it contains
velocities squared
q sub i dot
q sub j dot now this
is not really squared just quadratic in velocities
you can take the simple case
where it's the sum of velocity squared
it can contain coefficients
masses or whatever you like
let's just simplify it and say it's some sum
of coefficients I'll call them m sub i
over two times q sub i dot squared
this does not have to be linear
motion just as long as the Lagrangian
contains quadratic things like this
and also things which don't depend on the velocity
we usually call them the potential energy
in other words if it can be written
as a kinetic energy minus a potential energy
then it follows that the sum of
the potential energy and kinetic energy is conserved
t plus v
t plus u
t plus u is conserved
and as I said that is
an example of Nernst's formula for energy
and I'm not going to go through this theorem but a
more involved one that I don't want to go through again
we traced it through in the mechanics class
I have a question about explicit dependence of time
does that somehow imply an external force or something?
yeah it usually implies some external force
which is varying with respect to time
that's right that's the sort of thing that it involves
right
for example here's an example
suppose you have a harmonic oscillator
now if the harmonic oscillator particular is a constant
then the potential is fixed
in other words if the
spring constant is fixed with time
independent of time
then the energy is conserved
the Lagrangian is then x
dot squared m over 2 plus
sorry minus k over 2 x squared
usual harmonic oscillator
but now let's change things a little bit
let's imagine let's see how can
we imagine the spring constant changing
can you imagine the spring constant changing
with time?
yeah yeah the spring constant
might depend on the temperature
the temperature might vary with time
we don't want to take into account all
the motion and the molecules and everything else
so we're going to summarize all of this
by just saying the spring constant depends on time
now the Lagrangian has explicit time dependence
if it has explicit time dependence like that
then energy is not conserved
of course what's happening is that
energy is going from one form to another
but the mechanical energy described
just by this thing by itself
is not conserved
so if there's any explicit time dependence
in other words if the parameters of the problem
spring constant,
masses,
other parameters
if they depend on time explicitly
then the energy is not conserved
of course as I said that usually means
that we've ignored part of the system
and just treated it
by ignoring its dynamics
and just saying there was
some time dependence in the system
okay
in connection with that
is it the same thing to say
that the partial derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to time
the partial derivative
the partial derivative holding everything else fixed
meaning the fields and their time derivatives
yes
right so that's what it means
basically you've got q's,
q dots and t
and you
and if the partial derivative with respect to t
absolutely that's what it means
that's what it means
yeah
right
okay
which Gold what's his name
had said that
he said it the way you did
but he never said
who's he
Gold what's his name
the mechanical
oh Goldstein
Goldstein yeah
yeah
well
you know if Goldstein was teaching this class
he probably would have said it on the blackboard
when you asked the question
right
but I mean
I couldn't say it
yeah
zero
right
what the hell does that mean
yeah
good
all right
so let's write down then
the expression for the energy
for the simple field theory
let's not include
let's not include this m phi squared term
let's just take the simple field theory
it could have more dimensions
I've written it as if space was just one dimensional
you can add in y and z if you like
I'm not going to do it
it's too much writing
yeah
what is the energy
the energy
total energy
is then
one half
m
x dot
sorry
phi dot squared
you have to integrate it over space
kinetic energy
plus potential energy
and that means plus
in this case phi
so let's see
not m
just phi dot squared
plus
phi sub x squared
and if you like
plus phi y squared
blah blah blah
in other words
it's the sum of the square of the time derivative
and the space derivatives
that's the total energy
notice that it's always positive
or it's always positive
or zero
and let's in fact look at it
let's compute it
let's take the case of a wave
of waves going in one dimension
so our field now has some profile
and let's imagine a wave
moving in the positive x axis
that means it has some profile
but it's full dependent
and it's not just phi of x
but phi of x and t
and it has the form
phi of x minus c t
oh are there some c's in here
yeah
as it stands it's not dimensionally consistent
this is a derivative with respect to time
this is a derivative with respect to space
so I think we have
to put a c squared here
c is space over time
yeah that's right
we have to put a c squared here
let's put a c squared here
okay
now if we solve the equations of motion
we find out that there are solutions
which just move rigidly down the x axis
or up the x axis
two kinds of solutions
let's take the right moving solution
there's also a left moving solution
where we would change the sign of the sign
we change the sign of the c t term
and let's calculate this
phi dot squared plus c squared
d phi by the x squared
okay
this is phi
phi does not depend on x and t separately
it depends on the combination x minus c t
so what is phi dot
d phi by d t
that's the derivative of f with respect to its argument
so we just call that f prime
f prime means the derivative of f
with respect to what's inside its argument here
times
the derivative of the argument with respect to t
that's minus c
so that's minus c
minus c times f prime
that's the derivative of phi with respect to t
and the derivative of phi with respect to x
that's just f prime
differentiation with respect to x just gives f prime
okay so what is the energy then
the energy is the integral
is one half
the integral
phi dot squared
that's c squared f prime squared
that's the first term
and then the second term is
another c squared f prime squared
in other words
just forget the factor of two
and
get rid of one of these
that's the total energy of a wave
moving to the right
integral dx
what about a wave moving to the left
well the difference for a wave moving to the left
here's a wave moving to the left
I would change the sign here
but it would not change the sign of the square
of d phi by d t squared
so once again
it would be exactly the same expression
one half
let me remind you what it was
the sum of two terms
one of which was c
squared f prime squared over two
and the other of which was
c squared f prime squared over two
alright same thing
the square of phi is not going to change
the square of phi dot is not going to change
so this term won't change
it will be exactly the same
and so the energy of a left moving
wave and a right moving wave are the same
that's not surprising of course
and in fact it wouldn't change if
I rotated the wave into some other direction
if I were doing it in three dimensions
the profile of the wave counts
but not which direction it's moving in
so let's just write this out
that's the energy
good
any questions
about energy conservation?
yes
oh yeah it's the speed of light
sorry
yeah
well the speed of propagation
no it's
no you see
no okay let's talk about that
supposing this was sound
alright
you would put in there the speed of sound
okay
would that make sound Lorentz invariant
well it would be true
that the sound waves
the sound wave theory would
be invariant under certain transformations
but they would be the Lorentz
transformations with the wrong speed of light
okay
okay so you say so what
it's invariant with respect to the Lorentz
transformations with the wrong speed of light
but then there would be other things
for example the mechanical motion
of particles or other waves
which might be described by a Lorentz invariant theory
with the right speed of light
the combined things together would not
be Lorentz invariant in the usual sense
so
fields like the Higgs field
oh they all have the same speed of light
all have the same speed of light
right
miracle
and one has a perfect right to ask why
why is that so
but it's
you even have a right to
ask how do I know that
okay
we know it
well one way
the way we know it
is because these things tend to influence each other
the Higgs field affects the electron motion
affects the photon in various ways
and they all get mixed up together
in a rather serious way
if there was any violation of Lorentz invariants
it would infect its way through the Higgs field
and it would infect the rest of the physics
and we would know about
it unless it was extremely minute
unless the violation of
Lorentz invariants was extremely minute
so for example
just take electrons and photons
the maximum speed of an electron
is believed to be exactly the
same as the speed of light
believed to be exactly the same
therefore they both
both sets of objects
photons and electrons
are invariant under the same Lorentz transformation
what if the maximum speed of electrons
were slightly different
than the maximum speed of photons
or if the speed of gravitons were a
little bit different than the speed of photons
then the physics would not have an exact Lorentz invariance
because the two pieces of the
physics would have different Lorentz invariants
and the combined system together
wouldn't have a single Lorentz invariance
as long as electrons interact with photons
those are going to get themselves
mixed up in a way that
that they're going to affect each other
and we would know about
it from very very high precision
quantum electrodynamics experiments and so forth
unless that velocity difference was sufficiently small
that numerically we couldn't distinguish
the two forces of the
the speed of light
the speed of sound
right,
that's what I mean
and it will increase but asymptote to C
asymptote with respect to what?
when you say something asymptotes
you have to say asymptotes with respect to some something
two C's
no no no no
asymptotes with respect to some process
I mean with respect to some
the division of velocities
oh sorry there are two C's in this problem now
there's the speed of sound
and there's the speed of light
let's call the speed of sound
yes,
so I'm saying the asymptotes to the speed of light
oh oh oh ok so
yeah you're saying supposing a sound
good
you're saying supposing a sound wave
was going to be like this
going down the x-axis
and relative to u
it's moving with what a thousand
is it a thousand feet a second or something?
something like that
moving a thousand feet a second
but there I am zipping down the axis
with very very close to the speed of light
then I would see the sound wave
moving very close to the speed of light
yeah
and in that sense it's Lorentz and Bern
and that's well
uh
in that sense
but I don't think that's worth too much frankly
yeah
um
ok so
that's the energy
c squared times f prime squared
next I want to come
to the concept of linear momentum
linear momentum for fields
now this is not a momentum
which is conjugate to the field
this is actually the stuff
which if it hit a particle
it would make the particle move off along some axis
in particular it's a momentum
which will be different for waves
going to the left from the right
in fact for waves going to the right
the momentum will point that way
the linear momentum will point that way
and for waves going to the left
the linear momentum points the other direction
so
what
and
this is part of the ordinary momentum
but it's part of the ordinary momentum
which is carried by waves
in quantum mechanics it becomes the
ordinary momentum carried by photons for example
alright so it's the ordinary momentum
as carried by the waves
what does it have to do with
well ordinary momentum has to do with translation invariance
so we can ask
is this Lagrangian here invariant under the wave?
or is this a linear translation?
spatial translation
and if so
what is the conserved quantity?
and this is a little bit subtle
it's a little bit abstract
but I'm going to run you through it
and I'm going to work out for you
what the conserved quantity
that we identify with translation invariance is
okay
let's imagine
that we
take a wave
let's say that it's phi of x
we don't need to worry
about its time dependence right now
it's got some profile phi of x
and we take the whole wave
and we move it a little bit
we rigidly move it
if you take a look at that Lagrangian
it's quite obvious that
the integrated Lagrangian won't change
all I've done is I've displaced everything uniformly
and that should not change
the total amount of kinetic energy
or the total amount of potential energy
it's the same thing
it may change the kinetic energy at each point
but all you're doing is substituting this point over here
for this point over here
after the wave has been displaced a little bit
if I do displace it
or if I imagine displacing it
then anything that was originally going on over here
exactly the same thing is now going on over here
anything that was going on over
here is now going on over here
so when I add up all the
terms in the kinetic and potential energy
then after I shift the wave a little bit
they will be the same
kinetic and potential energy
not the kinetic energy the same as the potential
but the kinetic energy before and after
alright so how then
does phi of x change
when I displace the field a little bit
it does change
if I stand at a particular point
if I'm the eye in the
sky over here looking at that point
and I shift the wave
this is not an upside down A it's an eyeball
and I'm staring right at the field where I am
and I shift the wave a little bit
the field changes
so this shift of the field is associated
with a small change in phi
how much does phi change if I shift
the field to the right a little bit
what's the change in phi
that's right the change in phi
if I shift the field
to the right a little bit
derivative of phi with respect to x
times delta x
now is it plus or minus that
this is the hardest thing
in the world to figure out
okay let's check
supposing phi
you think it's minus
you think it's minus?
I think that the
I also think it's minus but I'm not sure why
you're moving backwards
yeah
yeah yeah
I think it's minus d
phi dx times delta x right
it's either one or the other
it's the rate at which phi is changing
times the amount that you shift by
okay
so that's the change in phi
okay so that's the change in phi
at every point in space
phi changes by amount this much
well
that's an example
it's a special case of this idea
that delta q
the change in a q
is epsilon times
the function of all the q's
in this case
epsilon is just epsilon
but f of q
is
the partial of phi
with respect to x
that's what represents
f of q
the small displacement of a small change in phi
when I do the operation
now we can very easily calculate the conserved quantity
remember what the rule is for the conserved quantity
I erased it off the blackboard
but
it's just to take pi
multiply it by f
and integrate it with the constant of phi
and integrate over space
that's the same as
sum of p sub i
times f sub i of q
so we take f of q
we multiply it by the canonical momentum
and we integrate it over all space
and that gives us a quantity
let's just call that quantity
I don't know what to call it
let me call it p
p because in fact it really is a certain momentum
alright what is it?
it's given by
d phi by dx
I guess it's minus d phi by dx
times pi
pi sub x
integrated over all space
that's the momentum which is conserved
by virtue of the invariance of the Lagrangian
with respect to spatial translation
that's a mouthful
the quantity which is conserved
by virtue of translation invariance
ok
what is pi x?
where do we have it?
pi x is just phi dot
so for our special case
this is just minus the integral
of d phi by dx
times d phi by dt
so we have a
that quantity is conserved
as I said
by virtue of translation invariance
let's suppose that our system
that we were talking about
was a combination of particles and waves
electromagnetic radiation
and electrically charged particles
supposing I displace
all of the waves
all the electromagnetic waves
by distance epsilon
but I don't displace the charged particles
do you expect the dynamics
to be invariant under that translation?
no
no,
in fact if I displace the radiation
so that it moves away from the charged particles
that obviously changes things
changes energies and so forth
but supposing I displace the waves
and the charged particles together
then I do explain that the charge particles are invariant
and I do expect that the Lagrangian not change
so in such a situation
I would expect that the total momentum
would have a contribution coming from it
from terms having to do with the electrons
and terms having to do with the waves
what would be the part of the momentum
that would just correspond to the electrons themselves?
mv for each electron
what would be conserved?
the thing that would be conserved
would be the field momentum
plus the ordinary momentum
of the charged particles
so this thing actually deserves to be called
the ordinary momentum
associated with the field itself
in fact roughly what we
prove by this line of argument
is that if this field
were to interact with a collection of ordinary particles
and bump them,
push them
and do whatever it does to them
that the momentum of the particles
plus the field would be conserved
if the Lagrangian is invariant
under a total shift of everything simultaneously
that's why this is called
it's not called the ordinary momentum
it's called the momentum
but which momentum?
let's call it the ordinary linear momentum
let's calculate it for our right moving wave
now it's quite possible that
I've got the sign wrong here
we will find out if I got the sign wrong
because any fool can see
including me
that a wave that's moving to the right
should have a positive momentum
and a wave moving to the
left should have a negative momentum
so if I've got the sign wrong
we'll find out
we'll find out because our right moving wave
moving down the positive x-axis
will wind up having negative momentum
negative momentum along the x-axis
that's a bad thing
so we'll change the sign
but let's do it
okay let's
here we are again
d phi by dt
is c times f prime
ah let's
we want
this is the left mover
I want the right mover
and then there's a minus sign here
right?
yeah
now we have a right mover
and what do we have then?
we have d phi by
dx times d phi by dt
and that looks to me like
the linear momentum
is the integral of the x
of minus
looks like I got it right
minus
d phi by dt
times d phi by dx
that gives me a factor of c
another minus sign
and f prime squared
squared
fortunately I seem to have gotten the sign right
and the linear momentum of
the right moving wave is positive
notice that it's closely related to the energy
of the right moving wave
in fact apart from the factor of c
the energy and the momentum are equal to each other
in fact we can write
that this is equal to c times p
there's an extra factor of c
in the energy that's not there in the momentum
what about a wave moving
to the left?
that's like this
that changes the sign
of this one
makes it plus
and changes the sign of the momentum
since the momentum has a natural minus sign in it
and that's like this
p in that case
becomes minus this
so a wave moving to the left
the momentum is exactly the same
except that it's moving
in the opposite direction
well it's exactly the same except that it's exactly opposite
in sign
it's not hard
to work out the more general case
where a wave may be moving in an arbitrary direction
and of course the answer is
that momentum is a vector
this kind of momentum is a vector
and it points along the
direction of motion of the wave
but these are two simple situations
so
we can then write
for these kind of waves
that energy and momentum are related
let's write down the general relationship
momentum is a vector
p is a vector
and the energy
a spatial vector
an ordinary three vector
energy is a spatial scalar
and energy is equal to c
times the magnitude
of the momentum
you know any particles that have this property
that their energy is equal to c times their momentum
photons
in fact any particle that
moves with the speed of light
has the property that its energy
is equal to its momentum times c
or the absolute value of magnitude
and the energy is equal to c times the momentum
and the magnitude of its momentum times c
so we've discovered another conservation law
the conservation of linear momentum
and the formula for it
doesn't involve
phi dot squared
and phi x squared
but involves the product of
phi x and phi
d phi by dx and d phi by dt
ok
um
yeah
if I was in two dimensions
and I had a wave
that was
symmetrical about the origin
does it have zero momentum?
yeah
though it's carrying energy?
yep
you're thinking about a spherical wave or a circular wave
somebody makes a puddle
you know
a wave going out and ripples
zero total momentum
but it does not have zero momentum density
I have not talked about the concept
of energy density and momentum density
we will
we need to talk about that
this is a good example,
a good reason
but yes it has
overall total zero
momentum
even though it has
non-zero energy
ok let's take a five minute break
I'm going to take a five minute break
I'll be back in a few minutes
ok let's talk about another conserved quantity
now this conserved quantity is associated
with a particular kind of field
a field of
whose field variable is complex
now
a complex field
complex in the sense of complex numbers
complex number z
is just a real part
plus i times an imaginary part
or we could call it
z1 plus
iz2
so every complex number
is just a pair of real numbers
but you deal with it in a certain way
by certain rules
the complex conjugate of z
is equal to
z1 minus iz2
or x minus iy
let me just write down some simple facts
about complex numbers
to just remind you
star
complex conjugate
what else do we need to know
z star
is equal to
z is equal to
is just x squared plus y squared
or z1 squared plus z2 squared
and finally
every complex number can also be written
as a magnitude r
times e to the i
theta
where theta is
an angle between zero and two pi
it represents
the position of the complex number
x
y
or it can also be written in terms of
r and theta
r e to the i theta
oh
last thing
z star
is r e to the minus i theta
alright that's
that's your course in complex numbers
now
a complex
field
on one level can be just thought of
as a pair of real fields
just for some reason
there are two fields in our problem
they're very similar to each other
they're very similar properties and we just
call them phi one and phi two
or
we group them together
and
possibly just for some notational
convenience we write
that phi is equal to phi one
plus i phi two
we also
write that phi star
is equal to
phi one minus i phi two
the derivative of phi
with respect to any coordinate
is equal to the derivative of
phi one
with respect to x mu
plus i
times the derivative of phi two
with respect to x mu
incidentally one and two here
do not mean derivatives
they just mean real and
I think that's
I think I might have done better to call it
phi real plus i phi imaginary
but I've already committed myself
phi one plus i phi two
so I'm not using the subscript notation now
to indicate derivatives
alright so the real and
imaginary part of derivatives
are just the derivatives of the real and imaginary
part and so forth it's all very simple
now let's write a Lagrangian
with this pair of fields
the two fields are very similar
to each other
each one has the same
kind of Lagrangian that we've written before
namely
L
equals integral
d three x
or I might have just written Lagrange density
but let's write it down
phi one
dot meaning time derivative
squared over two
plus derivatives
with respect to spatial position
of phi
squared over two
plus
sub one
x
y z all of them
can go in here
and I might even for fun add in
plus mu
over two
phi one squared
I might also add in many other things
but oh sorry minus I think
we got some minus signs here
minus signs
alright everybody recognize
that for phi one
just the same kind of Lagrangian
we've written down in the past
I've added in this mu term
the so called mass term
alright that's for one
now what about for field number two
that also enters into the Lagrangian
same thing
phi two dot squared over two
minus dx phi two
squared over two
add in y and z derivatives if you like
and then we have
but let's also add in minus mu over two
same mu
phi two squared
I can use
the complex notation to simplify this
first of all let's concentrate on this
phi one squared and phi two squared
phi one squared plus phi two squared
is the same as phi star phi
that's just phi star phi
what about
phi one dot squared plus phi two dot squared
that's
that's phi dot times phi star dot
a one squared plus a two squared
always means
a thing times its complex conjugate
so all of this
can be simplified
into the form
integral dx
phi dot
times phi dot
over two
this stands for phi one
dot squared plus phi two dot squared
likewise
for the spatial derivatives
dx phi star
times dx
phi over two
and finally
minus
mu over two
phi star phi
this Lagrangian of course
has all of the symmetries that we
have discussed so far
well it doesn't have the shifts
it has some of the symmetries
in particular it has energy conservation
it has momentum
conservation but it has
a new symmetry
and a new conserved quantity
one that plays a
very
major major role
in particle physics and quantum mechanics
but we are studying
it at the level of classical physics
at the moment
do you know what that symmetry is?
theta
right exactly
let's take phi
and multiply
it by
e to the i epsilon
epsilon is any
complex any real number now
any real number
what does that do in terms of the
you know if we plot
phi on the cartesian
axes in terms of a real and
imaginary part it just takes
phi and rotates it a little bit
it rotates the angle
um
it rotates the angle theta
theta a little bit
so it rotates
phi in this direction
it rotates phi star in the other direction
this is
a particular operation
that we can do on phi
ok
epsilon
I'm imagining for the moment that epsilon
is very small let's imagine epsilon is very small
we don't have to
but I want to make contact with the
idea of a small transformation
involving a small parameter epsilon
if epsilon is small
what is e to the i epsilon
it's one plus i epsilon
one plus i epsilon
if epsilon is small plus things
it's a higher order in epsilon
that's just the formula that
e to the x is equal
to one plus x plus
x squared over two factorial
plus x cubed over three factorial
blah blah blah blah blah
if I terminate this after the first term
for very small values of x
then e to the x is
one plus x
e to the i epsilon is one plus i epsilon
so for small
epsilon what we're doing is
multiplying phi
by one plus i epsilon
now is that a symmetry
is the Lagrangian changed
if I multiply phi by e to the i epsilon
and here it's obvious that it doesn't change
phi star phi
does not get changed
when I multiply phi by e to the i epsilon
the e to the i epsilon's
cancel when you multiply
phi times phi star
and so phi times phi star
is the same as phi
or anything
phi times phi star
phi dot times phi star dot
you know what I meant
phi star dot times phi dot
any of these
expressions involving a star
times an unstarred thing
will not change
if you just multiply phi
by e to the i epsilon
say it again
phi star e to the i epsilon
yeah exactly
when phi
phi by e to the i epsilon
then you must multiply
phi star by e to the minus i epsilon
so
if you change
phi by an amount e to the plus i epsilon
you change
phi star by a factor
e to the minus i epsilon
in other words you can write
that the change in phi
under this kind of transformation
is a change
is i epsilon
times phi
what is the change in phi star
it's minus i epsilon
times phi star
does everybody see
where I got this from
I just said the change in phi
is i epsilon times phi
that's the little change here
and I do the same thing
for phi star
I find out that it changes
by with a negative thing over here
okay
is this a symmetry
yes it is a symmetry
the Lagrangian does not change
because it always involves
things like phi times phi star
is there a conserved quantity associated with it
yes there is
I'll show you the little manipulation
you can go home and work it out
without using complex notation
I'm going to use complex notation
I'm going to do a slight cheat on you
but you can go home
and check what I've done
by using the actual real
components of phi
in the Lagrangian
but here's the trick
there are two independent components of phi
I'm going to pretend
that the two independent components of phi
are phi and phi star
and I'm going to pretend
that I'm going to do the big do
you can check
that this will actually work
and give you the right answer
so here's the idea
what is the canonical momentum
conjugate to phi
the canonical momentum
here it is
here's a Lagrangian
what's the canonical momentum
conjugate to phi
it's the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to phi dot
right that's it's definition
What's the canonical momentum conjugate to phi star?
That's the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to phi star dot.
That's phi dot.
Pi conjugate to phi star is equal to phi dot.
No,
no,
um,
yeah,
I guess there is an over 2.
Yeah,
you're right,
there is an over 2.
I missed that.
Yep,
there is an over 2.
It won't affect the value of the conserved quantity.
Now these two expressions are shorthands for the
momentum conjugate to phi 1 is phi 1 dot
and the momentum conjugate to
phi 2 is phi 2 dot.
They're shorthands for the two.
They're shorthands for that.
And they really just represent that.
Notice that the canonical momentum conjugate to phi star is
the complex conjugate of the canonical momentum conjugate to phi.
They're complex conjugates of each other,
pi and pi star.
Okay,
now let's work out the conserved quantity.
The conserved quantity,
we know what the change in phi is.
Remember what it is?
In other words,
we can say f sub phi is i times phi
and f sub phi star is minus i times phi star.
Remember what f is?
Everybody remember what f is?
It's the small change in
phi except for the factor epsilon.
Same f.
Same f as in Noether's theorem.
Now it's straightforward to work out.
I'm going to work this out for you another way.
I'm using a fancy notation,
the complex notation for something
which we'll do another way.
Let's just do it this way.
What's the conserved quantity?
It's pi sub phi times f sub phi.
Pi sub phi,
f sub phi,
plus pi sub phi star times f sub phi star.
Now what have I left out?
Integral over space.
That's the summation over i.
The analog of the summation over
i is the integral over space.
Let's see what it is.
Pi sub phi is phi star dot over 2.
So this is here equal to,
did I leave an i out somewhere?
No,
I didn't.
Phi star dot over 2 times f
phi and f phi is i times phi.
That's one term.
Now the second term,
pi sub phi star,
that's phi dot over 2.
And now f sub phi star,
but that's minus i times phi star.
So there's a minus i times phi star.
That's the most untransparent and least obvious expression I
think I've ever written down on this blackboard for you.
Phi star dot times phi
minus phi dot times phi star.
Integrated over space.
Let me just derive it another way,
which doesn't make use of this fancy,
complex notation.
Let's write phi is equal to
phi 1 plus i phi 2.
And now again I'm going to multiply.
Let's see what happens to phi
1 and phi 2 under this transformation.
Let's just do it.
Phi 1 plus i phi 2 gets
multiplied times e to the i epsilon,
which is 1 plus i epsilon.
And this is equal to phi 1 plus,
or minus,
excuse me,
phi 1 plus i phi 2 plus i
epsilon times phi 1 plus i phi 2.
All I've done is multiply it out.
What's the change in phi 1?
Well,
phi 1 is by definition
the real part of this expression.
The change in the real part,
let's look at it,
there's a real part from here,
the real part of i epsilon times this
thing here is minus epsilon times phi 2.
i times i is minus 1,
epsilon times phi 2.
And then there is plus i epsilon phi 1.
Phi 1.
Here's the rule.
The change in phi 1 is
equal to minus epsilon phi 2,
and the change in phi 2
is equal to epsilon times phi 1.
Now you just go through Noether's theorem using this form
for the changes of phi 1 and phi 2,
and you'll find exactly the
same expression for the conserved quantity,
written in terms of the real and imaginary part.
I'll leave you to do that.
Substitute in the real and imaginary parts
and just work out what the right answer is.
But this formula is quite neat.
Phi 1 star dot times phi
minus phi dot times phi star.
I'm losing it.
It's getting late.
Phi star dot phi.
Minus phi dot phi star.
Okay.
Anybody know what this conserved
quantity corresponds to in physics?
It's some sort of angular momentum.
Well,
it is a kind of angular momentum,
but it's not angular momentum.
It,
first of all,
doesn't have an axis associated with it.
What axis would you be talking about?
No axis.
It contains only space,
sorry,
it contains only time derivatives,
so it has no vectorial sense to it.
Angular momentum is a vector.
So it can't be that.
Yeah.
Electric charge.
Electric charge of what?
Electric charge of the field.
That's right.
Now,
where are we going?
We're going,
slowly creeping up on ideas of quantum field theory.
Remember that
when we finally get to think
about the relationship between particles and fields,
that every field has associated with it field quanta.
Every kind of particle is a quantum of some field.
So photons are quanta of the electromagnetic field.
Now,
they are not,
in any useful sense,
complex fields.
The electro,
the vector,
the quantum,
the quantum.
The electromagnetic field is real.
The electron is also the quantum of a field.
It's not a field that you're used to thinking about.
It's not a field that you measure
easily in the laboratory with a field detector.
But electrons have fields associated with them.
They are the quanta of a field.
They're not fields which exert forces on electrons.
They are the fields whose
quanta themselves are the electrons.
They're fields which are made up of flowing electrons,
if you like.
Other particles in nature.
Quarks.
Quarks are also charged particles.
And they also are described by fields.
Meaning to say that they are the quanta of fields.
Charged particles are always described by complex fields.
Complex fields.
This is the expression for the
electric charge carried
by such a field.
It's an integrated thing,
which means that the thing in the brackets here
is a kind of charge density.
If this is the thing that you
integrate over space to find the total charge,
then the thing in the bracket here
must in fact be the density of charge.
You integrate a charge density over space
to find the total charge.
This must be it.
So this expression in here
actually stands for charge density.
And if you think of the
field and its relationship to a
collection of a large number of particles,
then this is just a field description
of the average charge density of
the particles that make up the field.
Now this really hits home
only really when we get to
quantum field theory,
where the relationship between particles
and fields becomes more manifest.
But for the moment,
you can simply imagine
that a field moving along
has an electric charge.
What happens if this field
interacts with the electromagnetic field?
Well,
the electromagnetic field may
collide with this field and scatter it,
much as if this were a collection of charged particles
being influenced by the electromagnetic field.
The motion of wave packets of this field
might follow trajectories which are
similar to the charged particle trajectories
in an electromagnetic field.
So we're not getting deeply into
quantum field theory at this point,
but this is a conserved quantity,
which is,
when we move on to quantum
mechanics and to quantum field theory,
does become the electric charge of
the quanta described by the field 5.
Do you want to give a name to the integrand?
Charge density.
Right.
Now somebody...
Do they describe electromagnetic fields?
No,
they don't describe electromagnetic fields.
They describe the electric charges,
which are sources of those fields
and which are acted on by those fields.
They're not electromagnetic fields.
They're not electric and magnetic fields,
this phi.
They are the fields whose quanta are electrons.
This is sort of classical,
right?
Yeah,
this is classical.
Except for the fact that you have the complex fields,
so...
No,
that's classical.
That doesn't make it non-classical.
Right.
Well then,
if you...
Is there an example where you can plug that in
and show how that comes out charged,
like the...
Yes.
But in order to see that,
we would have to couple it to the electromagnetic field.
And I'll tell you how to do that eventually.
All right.
So this is Lagrangian by itself,
which is not yet coupled to the electromagnetic field.
So it's a system of charged particles,
but with no electromagnetic field around.
All right.
We will have to change this Lagrangian a little bit
when it comes in contact with the electromagnetic field.
And then the sort of
thing we would like to see,
for example,
is that a wave packet of this...
You know,
if we had a wave packet which looked like this,
moving down the axis in this direction,
and it encountered an electric field in this direction,
we would like to see that what it does
is to bend the trajectory of the wave packet
in the same way that an electromagnetic field would.
So obviously we have to
do more work to see that.
At the moment,
this is just a conserved quantity.
This is a conserved quantity.
But why did I do it?
I did it because ultimately it becomes electric charge.
And not just electric charge.
Many,
many different quantities in physics,
electric charge,
isotopic space,
in all the various different conserved quantities
that are associated with particles,
color charge,
strangeness,
all of those various quantities are described
by complex fields like this
or things very similar to this.
Can you do the same or similar thing
with two real fields and a rotation?
Yeah,
that's what this is.
That's exactly what...
Oh,
sorry.
Where did I write it?
When I wrote it in terms
of phi 1 and phi 2,
which I seem to have erased somewheres,
that was exactly the rotation properties of two real fields.
Oh,
absolutely.
Yeah,
it is the same.
Yeah.
Now let me give you another perspective on it,
which might be helpful.
I don't know,
it might not be helpful.
But let's come back to the string.
So we have the string connected between two points.
But now I want you to imagine that
the string is vibrating not just in the vertical direction
but also the horizontal direction.
So if we projected it onto a plane,
at any point the string would be a...
the string would intersect the plane at a point.
Okay?
Now,
that means that the actual configuration of the string
is described by two fields,
one of which can be thought of as
the y component
and the other could be
thought of as the z component,
or we could just call
them phi 1 and phi 2.
The two components of the position
anywheres along here,
the string intersects,
here's the origin,
the string intersects the plane at some point
and it describes,
it can be described by a complex field,
phi,
which could be phi 1 plus i phi 2,
or phi,
yeah,
phi 1 plus i phi 2.
So if we had a string
which was free to move in two directions,
x and y,
we could describe it either by two real fields,
one describing the x position
of the field along the string,
the other describing the y position.
Or we could describe it by a single complex field
a point on the complex plane.
What would you guess that for the string,
for the string,
for the mechanical analogy,
what would you guess that this corresponds to?
Anybody got an idea?
Somebody actually said the word before,
however in a different context.
It's the angular force.
The angular momentum of the string,
but the angular momentum of the string as it,
the angular momentum of the string about this axis.
In other words,
this string,
if you focused on a point on the string,
it would be moving,
it would be moving back and forth in various ways.
At any given instant,
it might have an angular momentum about this axis.
This is nothing but the angular momentum of that string
about the longitudinal axis.
So,
here's an example.
When you say this,
you mean the whole integral?
Yeah,
the whole integral.
The whole integral sums up the angular momentum
of each point along the string.
Right.
And the angular momentum density would be this.
Now,
this is not,
this is,
in the analogy,
in the analogy of field is like string,
is like violin string,
electric charge is like angular momentum
in the plane in which the string is moving.
Okay.
So,
for example,
a possible motion of such a string.
Possible motion could be a standing wave
oscillating up and down,
or a standing wave oscillating in and out,
but there are also oscillating waves which
just circulate around like this.
You take this bent string,
you give it a velocity into the blackboard,
and what does it do?
It,
it,
jump rope.
Rope skipping,
rope skipping.
yeah,
that's the analogy.
Rope skipping,
when the children play rope skipping,
they're giving the rope an angular momentum
about the axis defined by the distance
between the two children.
That angular momentum is a natural analog
of electric charge for this system here,
for the,
for the system of a string.
We're not getting yet into quantum field theory,
but do you know,
what do you know about angular momentum
in quantum mechanics?
It's quantized.
It happens to be quantized in units of h-bar,
but especially it's quantized.
It comes in discrete multiples of something.
What do you know about electric charge?
It comes in discrete multiples of the electric charge
of the electron.
Is it a coincidence?
Well,
maybe it's a coincidence,
but it has a common description
in terms of fields of similar description.
Yeah?
There's an...
Can you count the quarks?
If we count,
yeah,
I mean...
Right,
quarks count everything.
Count all charged particles.
But...
Quarks don't count in discrete multiples
of the charge of the electron.
You're right.
Discrete multiples of the charge of a quark.
Can you actually...
You're right.
Put this in a...
But that's a subtle business,
now,
that...
That is a truly subtle business,
the fractional charge of quarks.
So I'll ask you to
forget about it for the moment,
but maybe we'll get a
chance to come back to it.
Is there an example where you just have,
say,
instead of a string,
an actual electric field
that can be expressed as the complex...
Yeah.
You could take an electric field of a charge...
Sorry,
not the electric field.
You could take the electric field
associated with an electromagnetic wave.
Electromagnetic wave going down the z-axis
has an x-axis,
an x-component and a y-component.
Ex plus Iey.
That is to say,
you could make a complex electric field,
Ex plus Iey,
call that a...
And then a circularly polarized wave
would have this aspect of being like the jump rope.
All right?
In that case,
it wouldn't be electric charge.
It would be genuine angular momentum
that's going to be in the electric field.
Because it really corresponds to a spatial...
spatial direction.
It really corresponds to rotation of real space,
not rotation of this fictitious space.
So what's the simplest example
where you could really show that it's a charge
that's being conserved?
Look,
I say you have to study the connection
between this and the electromagnetic field,
and then you can show it's true.
They have to be two separate fields together.
Yeah.
You have to pick the electromagnetic field,
which means the vector potential,
and couple it in the appropriate way to this,
and then show that a wave packet of this stuff
will move as if it were a charged particle
in the electromagnetic wave.
And that's feasible.
We might even get to do it.
But not tonight.
There's an I in the front of that.
Right here.
So are we saying that the conserved quantity
is imaginary?
No.
This is the complex conjugate of this.
What happens if you take the difference
of two things,
a thing and its complex conjugate?
Hmm?
Yeah.
So the difference between this and this is pure imaginary,
and when it multiplies this,
it's pure real.
Good.
That's a good point.
If this were plus,
then we'd start to worry about it.
But it's minus,
which means that this quantity inside the bracket
is imaginary.
Oh,
in fact,
you get rid of the I over 2,
so that is just the real part.
Yeah.
That's right.
That's what I thought,
because you were almost there with the,
you had already written that pi star,
or you didn't write,
but you mentioned that pi phi star
is the complex conjugate of pi phi.
Yeah.
Okay.
And you also have,
actually,
f phi star is the complex conjugate of f phi.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
And so you already have
integral dx pi phi f phi
plus pi phi f phi star.
Yeah.
And that's already the real part.
Let me show you one more thing.
If we were talking about the string,
then the phi's themselves would become
the coordinate position,
x and y of the string.
What would the phi dots be?
Velocities.
This would be the cross product
of the position and the velocity,
which is called the angular momentum.
x times vy minus y times vx
is exactly what this would be.
So the mathematical structure of this thing
is very much the analog of the mathematics
of the rotation in an extra couple of dimensions.
It's not totally surprising that particle physicists
are always interested in extra dimensions.
Yeah.
We talked about the electromagnetic field
and the gravitational field,
but then you come and you say
the field whose quanta are electrons.
Is there a common name for that field?
Common name?
Quantum field.
Every type of quantum field
is associated with a particle.
Every particle type is associated with a field.
Every field type is associated with a particle.
And associated with the same connection
that connects photons to the electromagnetic field.
The electromagnetic field comes
in discrete quanta of energy.
We call photons.
Those photons are particles.
They can be isolated one at a time.
They can be sent through slits.
They make clicks when they hit photo detectors
and they behave like particles when they're sparse enough.
In the same way,
charged particles,
well,
in the opposite way,
charged particles can be grouped together
to form something which is similar to a field.
And those fields
come in discrete packets of energy
that describe particles.
If it's a charged particle,
it must be described by a field
which is capable of describing that charge.
So the field has to have a conserved quantity
associated with it.
And in the sort of coarse-grained,
roughly speaking,
you think of the field
as a sort of coarse-grained description of the charges.
The coarse-grained description of the charge
is just this quantity composed out of a field.
So there's probably
50,
100 elementary particles.
So there's 50,
100 fields.
Well,
presumably,
you could have a proton field too,
right?
What?
Could you have a proton field
so it's not an elementary particle?
Right.
You've got non-charged particles.
Well,
a proton field would be a construct
that you would build out of quark fields.
But yes,
you would have a proton field.
The molecular fields,
fields for describing molecules,
fields that describe bowling balls,
it's just not a very useful concept for bowling balls.
It's hard to build a kind of coherent,
simultaneous motion of a lot of bowling balls
that,
but in principle,
yes.
You would have a proton field.
Somebody was going to ask a question.
Yeah,
you talked about the relationship
of charged particles to electric fields
without particles that don't have a charge.
Say that again?
Particles that don't have a charge,
neutral particles,
do they relate to electric fields as well?
Do they what?
Do they connect the same way
a charged particle would to a,
you were talking about charged particles.
Uncharged particles are also described by fields,
but those fields don't interact
with the electromagnetic field.
At the moment,
we haven't described
the connection between these charge-carrying fields
and the electric and magnetic fields.
They're different animals.
They have different symbols.
Electric field is E.
Magnetic field is B.
This is neither of them.
This quantity that's in the bracket here,
what would you call that in electrodynamics?
Rho.
Standing for what?
For charge density.
How about current?
Can you guess?
Can you make a guess?
If this is the electric charge density,
would anybody like to venture a guess?
No,
no,
no.
That's not a bad guess.
But the reason it can't be right
is it's got to have a direction of space
associated with it.
The current flows in a direction.
Current is a vector.
Rho dot.
No,
rho dot doesn't have a sense of direction.
Rho dot is connected with the current.
It's the divergence of the current,
but...
Derivative of T?
Hmm?
Derivative of momentum.
It's very simple.
Let me rewrite this.
This is the charge density.
It's derivative with respect to T of phi
star times phi,
and then minus another term with an I.
One half of it.
X,
Y,
Z.
In other words,
derivative of phi times the derivative
with respect to X,
I.
I could be X,
Y,
or Z
times five star.
That's a thing now that has a vector index.
This has a direction in space.
It could be derivative with respect to X,
could be derivative with respect to Y,
could be derivative with respect to Z.
When you combine it with derivative with respect to T,
you get four components.
The four components form a four vector.
That four vector is composed out of
the electric charge density
and the electric charge flow.
The usual electric charge,
um,
is,
current.
So a very similar kind of thing,
except not with time derivatives
but space derivatives,
forms the electric charge current.
We haven't gotten to it,
but we will get to it.
Any other questions?
Good.
We've got a few minutes.
Um...
What would the,
uh,
in the example of the,
of the wire,
what would the,
uh,
the,
conserved quantity be for,
uh,
current flow?
For J?
For a wire?
Well,
uh...
Is charge density correspondent to angular momentum?
Oh,
you mean for the,
uh,
sorry,
for the,
yeah,
um...
Oh.
The wire,
you mean the,
uh,
the jump rope?
Jump rope.
Yeah.
Just exactly this.
This would be the flow of charge along the x-axis.
Or the flow of angular momentum along the x-axis.
There is a notion of,
of angular momentum density,
which can be just identified more
or less as the angular momentum
of each particle in the jump rope.
But now if you have
a wave going down the axis,
imagine,
okay,
so we have,
uh,
we have a rope,
and we start twirling it like this.
Waves go down the axis,
but they're sort of circularly polarized waves.
In that case,
there's a flux of angular momentum.
Angular momentum is traveling down the string.
And that traveling angular momentum is the analog of the,
uh,
of the electric charge,
um,
current.
Right.
Of course,
it's a different thing.
I mean,
it,
you don't have to take a wire and spin it
in order to make electric charge.
But you have to spin it in this internal space,
this,
uh,
this fake space of phi 1 and phi 2.
Yeah.
So,
this gives you some idea,
if nothing else,
about why,
uh,
as I said,
why,
uh,
particle physicists,
do have an interest in internal dimensions.
That the quantum numbers,
the conserved quantities that are associated with particles,
often,
in fact,
always,
can be considered,
can be considered motions in hidden spaces.
Now,
the hidden spaces may be purely mathematical,
or they may even be hidden spaces.
But,
uh,
one way or another,
the mathematics of these conserved quantities
is very closely related to the
mathematics of motion in extra spaces,
and in particular angular
momentum-type quantities in extra spaces,
extra dimensions of space.
So,
that's where we may ultimately get to,
maybe.
What would,
uh,
what would be your symmetry transformation to get to J?
No,
no,
J is not a conserved quantity.
It's the integral of rho,
which is the conserved quantity.
J is a flux of a conserved quantity.
So,
for example,
let's see,
and here's a sense in which
J is not a conserved quantity.
You can have a flow
of charge down an axis here,
okay,
some other kind of object,
a photon coming here,
scatters these particles and turns them around,
turns their direction around.
J turns around.
J goes from being positive to being negative.
So,
J is not conserved.
But the total amount of charge is conserved.
That there's one coulomb of charge here,
going to the right becomes one
coulomb of charge going to the left.
The,
um,
the,
uh,
the char- the charge flow,
the current is itself not conserved.
So,
every,
every conserved quantity typically has
a flow associated with it.
If you drain a battery,
charge is conserved.
But the current,
you drain a battery,
the charge is conserved,
but the current certainly is not the constant.
Right.
Right,
current itself is not conserved.
It's not conserved charges.
But it's generally the tr- the case
that conserved quantities have connected with them
a flow of the conserved quantity.
So,
total amount of water is conserved.
Uh,
the flow of water is not conserved,
but there is a flow that's
connected with the conserved quantity itself.
That's,
uh,
and we haven't discussed that connection,
except to say that,
uh,
say,
the field whose quanta are electrons,
uh,
has a phi one and phi two.
Mm-hmm.
Do the phi one and phi two have
any physical meaning that we can think of?
Not,
not really.
Um,
no more than,
uh,
saying out of it you can build,
these conserved quantities.
Uh,
perhaps if we were a zillion,
zillion times smaller,
we would see these extra dimensions
and see things moving around in them.
And say,
oh,
electric charge,
that's just the angular momentum of something spinning
in some one of the ten
dimensions of string theory or something.
Uh,
but,
uh,
from our perspective,
what we get to see out of the whole thing
is the electric charge,
and that's about all.
We don't get to see the internal motions that,
uh,
that might,
be connected with it.
We're too big.
Okay.
You have an equation of the rate
of change plus the value of the charge.
So the divergence of the conserved
quantity is always zero or something.
Yeah,
good.
So that's what we're gonna do next time.
But,
uh,
if you wanna jump ahead
of the game a little bit,
that's called the continuity equation.
Continuity equation is that the time derivative
of the density of charge plus the space derivatives,
in just one dimension,
this is derivatives,
partial derivative,
plus the space derivative of the,
uh,
charge flow,
the current,
is equal to zero.
That's,
of course,
a statement,
well,
I'll tell you what it's a statement of next time.
And we want to check that.
We want to check that,
that that's a true statement,
uh,
that the,
that it really behaves that way.
I,
uh,
I don't know.
ありがとうございました
d rho b t,
since rho is conserved,
isn't that...
No,
the integral of rho is conserved.
The integral of rho is conserved.
Right.
So I'll tell you what this equation says.
It says that if you have a
region of space with some charge in it,
the only way that the
charge can change in that region
is by a current flowing
into or out of the region.
So it says that you
can't have a change in charge
unless you have a current to carry that.
You can't have a change of charge in a region
unless there's a flow of charge out
of that region or into that region.
So it's the connection between the flow
and the change of charge in a given region.
And of course,
what this says is that
if there's a change of charge
on the inside of this region,
then there's a compensating change of
charge on the outside of the region.
So it's a kind of very local
way of describing the conservation of charge.
For example,
what's not allowed is for charge...
You might think that conservation
of charge would allow the following.
Charge to disappear over here,
and at the same instant that it disappears over here,
to reappear over here.
That would still satisfy the
rules of conservation of charge.
Total charge doesn't change.
But that's not the way things work.
The way they work is that
charge gets from here to here
by flowing through the region in between
so that you can detect the fact
the charge is flowing from here to here
by stationing yourself over here with a current detector
and discovering the charge has moved through here.
So conservation is more than
just saying a quantity doesn't change.
It says that when it does change,
you can account for that change by
a flow or a flux of the quantity
through the boundaries of a region.
And we're going to take that up.
Yeah?
Is there an experiment in
physics that shows that that happens?
Oh,
I'm sure there is.
I'm sure there's a zillion...
Yeah,
sure.
I mean...
Can I think of an experiment offhand?
No,
but just think about what it means.
It means that if you have a wire,
and the charges move from one...
The charges just move along the wire.
Electrons move a little bit to the left.
What happens?
Let's take a...
Let's take a look at that case.
Electrons in the wire all move to the right.
What happens to the wire?
What happens to the wire is
some minus charge shows up over here.
Some plus charge shows up over here.
Why?
All the electrons have moved to the right.
Each electron has moved to the right a little bit.
Each one has moved to
the right by the same amount.
There's no buildup of charge in the interior.
But there's an increase of charge.
Negative charge over here because some
one extra electron showed up here.
One extra electron disappeared from here.
So what you get is a net
charge on the ends of the wire.
That net charge on the ends
of the wire happens all right.
Happens every time you put the
wire in an electric field or something.
But if you were to stand
there and monitor what's going on,
you would see a flow of charge across there.
You wouldn't just see charge appear
over here and disappear over here.
You would see them all marching to the right.
So yes,
there are...
For example,
every time a charge increases
over here and decreases over here,
a magnetic field due to the
flow of charge in there is produced.
What I'm thinking of is quantum tunneling.
Where it suddenly appears on
the other side of the barrier.
So that means that it must have
been in the barrier at some time.
It was in the barrier,
but there'll be a flow
of charge to go with it.
You'll see a sudden...
If you have a detector in the barrier,
it will detect that charge.
Right.
You can't make the charge go through the barrier.
If there is a detector there,
it will detect the charge.
Yeah.
It'll also screw up the tunneling.
Kind of in general,
at least in classical theory,
I think that any time you
have some kind of a global...
I mean,
you can't say that there's a global law,
that essentially there are local
processes that it originates in.
Yeah.
In fact,
I would say that for most global laws,
at least global conservation laws,
but most global laws altogether...
I can't think of any
global laws except global conservation laws.
But they tend almost always to
be associated with local laws that are,
as you say...
Not always.
There are exceptions.
Things called multiplicative quantum numbers,
which are a little different.
But...
Okay.
So let's...
Yeah.
If you want to study something,
study the continuity equation,
the rho dt plus the j dx.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.