This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Today,
we're going to have our first
encounter with what is called gauge theory.
All of modern physics is based,
all of modern particle physics in particular,
and modern general relativity,
gravity physics,
all fundamental views of physics,
and a great deal,
I might add,
in condensed matter physics.
Not that I don't think
that condensed matter physics is fundamental.
I should not have made that distinction.
But condensed matter physics,
particle physics,
general relativity,
one of the most basic principles
is the principle of gauge invariance.
I'm sure you've all heard of it.
You probably wonder what it is.
Some of you may know what it is.
We're going to begin with our study of gauge symmetry,
or gauge invariance,
or gauge principle,
by studying a simple example.
Now,
in 1905,
Einstein pointed to the importance of very carefully
defining carefully and setting up
the idea of coordinate systems,
that there may be some hidden assumptions that one makes
when one speaks of things like,
well,
simultaneity is,
of course,
one of them,
but other such things,
the length of objects and so forth,
and that you really do have to be very
careful to operationally and carefully define what you mean
by various kinds of concepts.
Such as simultaneity,
for example.
Everybody thinks that they know what simultaneity means,
but comparing times at different places is not so obvious.
How you compare,
how you say when two times are equal,
when they correspond to different places,
especially since it takes light time
to go from one place to another.
So he was very careful,
and in being careful,
he invented the special theory of relativity,
but that,
how shall I say,
that idea of being careful about defining relative things
at different places of space,
and the ambiguities that could inherently be there,
because you're trying to
compare things at different locations,
that theme has sort of permeated physics since Einstein,
and that's what we're trying to do with Einstein's time.
The general theory of relativity makes it even worse,
that not only can't you compare detailed simultaneity,
but you can't even compare,
for example,
in an obvious way,
what you might mean by,
my finger is pointing that way,
over here,
you point your finger in some direction,
I point your finger in some direction,
good.
Are we pointing our fingers
in the same direction or not?
How do we tell?
Well,
we're looking,
and in looking we transfer photons,
back and forth,
and so forth,
and so we make comparisons
by sending photons back and forth,
but how do we decide without,
you know,
without an experiment to send something back and forth,
how do we decide whether this and this
are really pointing in the same direction or not?
Well,
one way is to try to
carefully bring this over to here,
and see if they're pointing in the
same direction when we line them up,
but how do I know that in
the process of going from here to here,
I didn't rotate my finger?
And,
of course,
in the back of our imagination,
we imagine that there is
located at each point of space
an idealized coordinate reference frame
that are oriented parallel to each other
when we move from one place to another,
but maybe that's a,
maybe that's a idea that is a little too naive.
Maybe we have to be more careful in comparing things.
Now,
we compare all kinds of things,
but the specific thing I want to talk about
is comparing the phase of complex wave fields.
A very important example of comparisons at different points
has to do with complex wave fields.
Now,
remember,
complex wave,
complex fields,
we've discussed them,
I called a field phi,
when it happened to be
made out of two real components,
phi one plus i phi two,
and,
of course,
I can either think of them as complex fields
and their complex conjugate,
or I can just think of,
incidentally,
this phi and this phi are the same thing.
I sometimes draw it this way
and sometimes draw it this way.
That's one way of thinking of
a complex field as a complex field.
The other way of thinking about
it is a pair of real fields,
in which case we would
say at every point in space
we have a set of axes,
one of which we call phi one,
and one of which we call phi two,
and at every point in space,
the field takes on some value.
At this point over here,
the field might be oriented,
our complex scalar field might be located at this point.
At that point over here,
it might be located at this point.
But in saying something like that,
we're implicitly assuming
that there's some kind of way
of relating directions in this space
at different points of space.
Let's,
just to get this idea
and to pin this idea down,
let's go back to the jump rope analogy.
The jump rope analogy for the complex field
is just that we have a string,
a long string,
could be a rope,
and that rope is at every point
free to move in two directions,
up and down and right and left,
from my perspective over here.
I should have brought in a rope.
I always,
ah.
Who wants to play jump rope?
Yeah,
okay,
good.
I don't know,
this is not going to go very far.
All we're going to do is swing the rope around,
but okay,
let's do it anyway.
Yeah,
you take that in.
Good,
okay.
So this is a rope,
which when we're stretched out is like this,
but it's actually free to move
both horizontally and vertically,
and then it has the capacity not just to vibrate,
but to vibrate in a
way that has some angular momentum.
Now,
in order to explain what,
not to explain,
but in order to do this,
to describe the configuration of this string,
I have to tell you not
just how far from the origin,
the origin now means the straight string
when it's as straight as possible,
how,
not only how far it's been displaced,
but at what angle it's been displaced.
So I have to describe both,
either a complex number at every point,
complex number could be x plus i y
for the position of the string,
or,
thank you,
or I could describe it either a pair of coordinates,
a complex number,
or an angle and a radius,
any number of ways of describing it.
But it's implicit in compa-
implicit in describing things
that the coordinate axes x and y
that I use over here on the string
are parallel to the coordinate axis over here,
or parallel to the coordinate axis over here.
So we have made an assumption
that it is possible to compare angles
at different points and say whether they're the same
or not the same.
It is not completely obvious
that that's a good assumption.
In fact,
really honestly,
when one takes general relativity into account
in the motion of strings and so forth,
it is not so obvious,
and in fact it's not even true,
that there's a unique way of comparing angles
at different places.
But we're not talking about angles in real space now.
We're talking about angles in a fictitious field space,
which is mathematically similar
to the rotation of the jump rope,
but we're talking about angles
in a mathematical field space.
And this situation comes up
when we ask questions like,
is the value of the complex field
at one location the same
as it is in another location or not?
In order to answer that question,
we have to compare angles in this,
among other things,
angles in this space at different points.
Now here's what we know.
For some field theories,
for some field theories,
namely those which have a concept of charge,
that there is an invariance,
a symmetry,
and the symmetry corresponds
to rotating the coordinates
phi 1 and phi 2.
Rotating them to some new direction,
or equivalently,
what's equivalently,
is rotating the position of the field
in,
not in space,
but in phi 1,
phi 2 space.
We either rotate the axes,
or actually physically change the value of the field
by rotating it.
In either case,
the coordinates of the field will change.
So,
we could imagine
a symmetry transformation of the fields
which can either,
as I said,
be described by physically changing the configuration,
or just changing the coordinates
that we use to describe the field.
And we know how to describe that.
We can describe it trigonometrically,
that phi 2 prime is equal to
cosine of an angle and so forth.
But we can also describe it
in complex notation very,
very neatly.
The transformation that comes out of it,
corresponds to rotation of coordinates,
can just be written
phi prime,
that's the value of the field after,
or the value of the coordinates of the field
after you've rotated the coordinates,
is equal to e to the i theta times phi,
the unrotated notation for the field.
Where theta is just the angle
of rotation here.
Now,
I hope nobody gets confused
between thetas and phis.
Phis are fields,
theta is just an angle of rotation
in this field space
of the coordinates which describe the field.
Now,
this is an operation
that we can do on a field.
It corresponds,
in the case of the jump rope,
to going at every point in the jump rope
and changing the angle by the same amount.
By the same amount.
That's the key phrase.
By the same amount,
theta is just a number,
and it rotates the field in the field space,
sort of rigidly,
rigidly everywhere by the same amount.
That's a symmetry,
for example,
of the Lagrangian
that we studied last time,
which,
what was it?
It was d mu phi star,
d mu phi...
Question?
Yeah,
is phi prime relative to,
is that the...
Phi prime...
Relative to the green line,
which is...
Yeah,
yeah,
that's right.
Phi could be the coordinates
relative to the black line.
Phi prime could be the coordinates
relative to the blue line,
green line.
Hm?
Isn't it even minus phi theta?
Because the angle's getting smaller
when you rotate by positive theta.
Yeah,
well,
it doesn't...
You may be right,
but...
If it's invariant under multiplication
by a phase like this for every angle,
it includes negative angles and positive angles.
So,
uh...
Quite possibly,
for this particular setup over here,
I may have inadvertently put the wrong sign here,
but it doesn't matter for anything.
Uh,
good.
So let's change the orientation
to conform correctly to the formula.
You're probably right that...
That I've rotated the coordinates the other way.
All right,
so phi prime...
And besides which,
I haven't told you
which was phi and which was phi prime.
So there's no way to compare it on...
I guess...
I guess we would call...
Let's see,
we'll call the coordinates...
Here,
phi prime.
Now I think we fixed it.
And phi...
Phi one prime and phi two prime.
Okay.
Uh,
this is either right or wrong,
and I don't really care.
Um...
Good.
Now,
we studied some Lagrangians.
We studied the Lagrangian,
the derivative of phi star
times the derivative of phi.
These are complex conjugates of each other.
We added,
for fun,
another term.
I think it was minus mu squared phi star phi.
And this Lagrangian is invariant
under this operation.
The reason is because
if phi is replaced by phi prime,
then phi star prime,
phi prime star,
is e to the minus i theta phi.
And furthermore,
the same is true of the derivatives.
Supposing I differentiate phi prime,
the derivative of phi prime with respect to x,
let's pick a particular coordinate with respect to x,
is equal to what?
Theta here is just a constant
for my purposes right now.
And so when I differentiate phi prime,
I get nothing from differentiating
the e to the i theta.
That just stays there.
Times derivative of phi with respect to x.
So the derivatives that appear here
also themselves just get rotated
by the same phase angle.
When you multiply them by their complex conjugates,
the e to the i thetas cancel.
e to the i thetas cancel here.
And so this is an example of a Lagrangian
which is invariant
with respect to
phi goes to phi e to the i theta.
Okay,
now you might ask,
what would happen though,
is it invariant with respect to rotation
or is it invariant with respect to rotation?
Well,
if you look at the
you can say that the Lagrangian is invariant under phase,
which means that you don't have an invariant sense
of what angle zero means.
You can rotate the whole picture,
but you can't say that the angle is invariant.
but comparing angle zero at different places is meaningful.
But supposing this Lagrangian turns out
to be invariant under a stronger symmetry,
a symmetry where you rotate the angle
at each point by an arbitrary angle,
which might differ from point to point.
In other words,
let's investigate whether the Lagrangian we've
written down is invariant under a symmetry
where we allow theta to be a function of x.
That means as we move along
from point to point in space,
we rotate the axes differently.
If there is no good sense in
which you can compare angles at different places,
then we would expect this to be just
as good a symmetry as when we rigidly rotate.
So we can think about this as
the difference between a kind of rigid rotation
and a rotation which varies from place to place.
Okay,
also x here.
Well,
let's examine that question.
First of all,
let's look,
let me remember that we're
supposed to integrate this over space,
and the full action would be integral d4x.
Let's look at the various terms in this Lagrangian and see
whether they change or not when we do such an operation.
Well,
what happens to phi star phi?
That's an easy one.
Phi star phi,
phi gets multiplied by e to the i theta,
phi star gets multiplied by
e to the minus i theta.
At each point separately,
those phase angles cancel.
So this term in the Lagrangian is fully invariant,
but it's not invariant.
Under these position-dependent,
let's call them position-dependent phase rotations,
there's another name
for position-dependent phase transformation.
It is gauge transformation.
That is what a gauge transformation is.
Or at least this is a
special case of the more general concept.
More general concept,
any kind of symmetry,
you can imagine doing it differently from point to point.
So this term,
we could check it off,
this term here is invariant.
Red check means that that term is invariant.
What about these terms which involve derivatives of phi?
If this is going to show up anywhere,
it's going to show up in questions having to
do with how phi varies from place to place,
and whether when we compare phi
at one point with a neighboring point,
whether this Lagrangian is invariant.
So let's check.
Let's calculate.
Alright,
let's...
Let's see,
I think,
do I want to switch the
definition of phi and phi prime?
I may.
Just to conform with my notes.
No,
I think I have it the way I want it.
Okay,
so...
This is the primed field.
Here's the unprimed field.
Let's calculate...
And here's the...
And...
Yeah,
you know what?
Let's...
Right.
Let's write the Lagrangian in terms of the primed variables.
Primed,
unprimed,
what's the difference?
We can just change,
it's just changing names.
It's just changing names of
what we call the field variables.
Here's the Lagrangian for the primed field.
Let's work it out now,
since we know the relationship between
the primed and the unprimed field,
let's work out whether this
Lagrangian has exactly the same form
if we substitute for phi prime,
phi.
Alright,
the first thing we have to do is figure
out what happens to the derivative of phi prime.
With respect to x mu.
That appears in the Lagrangian,
but I want to rewrite it in terms of phi.
Alright,
but now,
when I differentiate,
I get two terms.
I get one from differentiating this factor,
and one from differentiating this factor.
The first term,
well,
let's take the first term to be the simpler one,
when you differentiate phi,
that just gives you d phi by d x mu.
Okay.
times e to the i theta of x.
This doesn't worry me,
because I expect that when this
is multiplied by the complex conjugate,
it's going to go away.
Alright,
but then,
let's take the other term.
The other term,
you differentiate e to the i theta of x,
and multiply by phi.
Alright,
so what's the derivative of e
to the i theta of x?
That is i
times the derivative of theta with respect to x,
times e to the i theta.
I've used the derivative of an exponential,
is just equal to the
derivative of what's in the exponential,
times the exponential itself.
So,
both the terms have an e to the i theta.
That's a good thing,
because that'll probably cancel when
we multiply by the complex conjugate.
But,
we now have this greater derivative of x,
and this is the derivative of the phase angle.
The derivative of the transformation phase angle.
And that's not so obvious that that will cancel out.
In fact,
it won't.
So,
let's rewrite now the Lagrangian in
terms of phi instead of phi prime.
It's just a change of variables.
It's just a change of
what we meant by the field.
And let's see what we get.
Now we get integral d mu phi star,
let's see.
I should write down what happens
to the derivative of phi star.
The derivative of phi star,
phi prime star,
with respect to x mu,
what happens to it?
You just complex conjugate.
That's equal to the derivative of
phi star with respect to x,
e to the minus i theta.
That's the complex conjugate of this factor.
And then the complex conjugate here is
minus i d theta by d x mu
times e to the minus i
theta of x times phi star.
Alright.
The minus came because the derivative,
because the complex conjugate of i is minus i.
Alright.
Is everybody happy with this?
If not,
stop me now and I'll explain what's on the blackboard.
You put a star in the second term.
Star on which second term?
Here?
Where?
Here,
there's a star there.
Oh.
Yeah.
Phi star here,
yeah,
good.
Phi star here,
right.
Okay,
now,
if I didn't have to worry about this term here,
I would just multiply these two.
If I didn't have any x dependence in theta,
for example,
if x was,
if theta was independent of x,
these terms would not be here,
and I would just be multiplying this by this,
and the e to the i phi's would cancel,
and I would find out
that this Lagrangian was exactly equal
to the same thing except replacing phi prime by phi.
Okay.
But it's not true now.
Let's work out what we have.
We have d by d mu of phi star times,
let me factor out the
e to the minus i theta.
Minus i d theta by d x mu,
times phi star.
Now,
I kept for last e to the minus i theta.
Let's put it there.
Now we have to multiply that by the complex conjugate,
the derivative of phi,
or the derivative of phi prime.
That comes from here.
Each term has an e to the plus i theta,
which will cancel with the
e to the i theta here.
So that's good.
That e to the i theta cancels,
as before.
And what are we left with?
We're left with d phi by d x mu
plus i d theta by d x mu phi.
Let's add back in this
minus mu squared phi star phi.
All right.
So the cost of replacing phi star,
phi prime by phi,
by this position-dependent rotated phi,
is some extra terms in the Lagrangian.
And so the Lagrangian does not have the same form
that it started with.
It has a different form.
It now has things in it.
Now,
theta is not really a degree of freedom.
It's just an arbitrary angle that we chose
to vary throughout space in an arbitrary way.
But when we see we do that,
the structure,
the form of the Lagrangian changes.
It's not a symmetry.
It's only a symmetry if the Lagrangian
would have come back to exactly the same form.
So we can put a cross over this term.
This term is not invariant.
This term is invariant.
Lagrangian we wrote down is just not invariant
under this transformation.
What does that mean?
That means that if we...
That means,
among other things,
that if we did this operation on the field
where we rotated it from point to point,
we would change the energy of the field.
We changed the Lagrangian.
We changed the energy of the field.
We changed the momentum in the field.
It just isn't the same configuration
that we started with,
and it's not a configuration that has the same properties.
Now,
as did the Lagrangian,
we have different equations of motion,
different Lagrangian.
All right,
so our first conclusion then
is that the Lagrangian...
the complex scalar Lagrangian
has an invariance under rigid phase rotations,
but it is not invariant under gauge transformations.
Gauge transformations mean these nonrigid rotations
where you vary differently at different points.
Let me stop there and
take any questions that come up,
because this is the essence
and the heart of modern field theory,
basically,
this being the simplest example.
Yes?
I'm getting a little confused by your notation there.
D mu,
is that the same as d by dx mu?
Yes.
Yep.
I will write down again
a whole bunch of equivalences.
d phi by dx mu
is equal to phi mu
is equal to d mu phi.
Do I have any other names for it?
I don't think so.
But yes,
these are things all mean the same thing.
Okay,
but subscripts and superscripts?
Subscripts and superscripts are different.
Now,
how are they different?
They're not different if we,
let's see,
it's the time component which changes when we,
I think,
yeah,
right.
That,
yeah,
that may mean,
I may be off by a sign here.
This may be possibly a minus sign there,
but that's not the important issue here.
That second one doesn't have any imaginary components,
right?
Because it was,
it's supposed to,
there's supposed to be complex conjugate to multiply.
Sorry,
which,
yeah,
this has no imaginary component to it
because it's something times its complex conjugate,
but it still does remember this,
this,
right.
It looks like it can sort of
be combined with mu squared or something.
No,
mu squared is a different quantity.
Oh,
well,
no,
but I mean,
Of course,
everybody realizes this mu has nothing
to do with the mu in the,
in these mu's,
right.
I probably should call it m squared.
You get rid of the,
of the imaginary components,
but are you going to continue on this?
Hm?
Are you going to continue to expand this out or?
Oh,
if you like,
I can.
Yeah,
let's do it.
All right,
so this is d mu phi,
d mu phi star.
Oh,
I guess one of these should have upper indices,
shouldn't they?
I'm not sure how to do that.
Okay,
I know what to do.
Do you learn anything if you expand it out?
Hm?
No.
But let's do it anyway.
d mu phi and then d mu theta.
Oops,
d mu theta.
Do you learn anything if you expand it out?
I don't see anything.
Hm?
When you expand it out,
the first,
it just has two terms
because the imaginary parts go away.
No.
That's,
all right,
we will learn something.
d mu phi star times d mu phi.
Now that's just the good old Lagrangian
that we might have expected if there was a symmetry.
Then of course there is minus
i d theta by d x mu.
Hm?
Well,
let's see,
we're taking the cross terms now.
Let's write,
let me write the cross terms carefully.
The two cross terms.
They don't cancel.
Are you asking whether they cancel?
Yeah.
No,
they don't.
Then they do have an imaginary part.
No,
let's see what they have.
They have minus i d theta by d x mu.
All right,
first of all,
they multiply d theta by d x mu,
both of them.
This times this and this times this,
the two cross terms,
all right?
Both of them have i's in them.
And one of them has,
let's see what it has.
It has phi times d mu phi star.
And then it has minus phi star d mu phi.
And then finally we have minus i times plus
i is plus d mu theta by d x mu.
So it's d mu theta d mu theta.
It's just the square of the sums,
the sums or the differences of the squares
of various derivatives of theta times phi star phi.
Okay?
Now,
this does not cancel.
Phi derivative of phi star is not the same
thing as phi star times the derivative of phi.
These two are complex conjugates of each other.
When you subtract them,
you get something pure imaginary.
And that cancels this i here.
Now,
do you remember this quantity?
It was something that was invariant.
Conserved,
I guess.
It was the current.
The current,
j mu.
Its time component was the charge density.
Its space component was the current density.
Okay?
Together,
they satisfied the flow equation,
the continuity equation.
Right.
All right.
Okay,
so we at least see something familiar.
And then this term over
there is just whatever it is.
It contains a phi star phi,
which I suppose we could combine with this one,
minus m squared phi star phi.
Good.
All right.
So,
yeah.
We did learn something,
I think,
by,
we surely discovered this term here.
Good.
So,
answer is,
no cigar,
this Lagrangian is not
invariant under such a transformation.
But,
if that was the end of the story,
of course,
we would go home and say this
idea of gauge invariance is not important.
And,
you know,
75 years of physics down the drain.
All right.
So,
let's see if we can force it to be invariant.
But to do so,
we have to add another collection of fields.
To do so,
we have to add another
collection of fields into the brew.
And to give those fields also
transformation properties under the same transformation.
We're going to have to invent more fields
and more transformation properties to go with them.
In order to make this a simple equation.
Like this,
I'm going to take what we have in our inventory.
The new fields that were going to invent
are our first experience with the vector field.
Of course,
we have some vector fields.
Anytime we differentiate a scalar field,
it's a vector field.
But now,
we're going to invent some new fields,
which are,
how to say,
primordially,
they are vector fields from the beginning.
Fundamental fields,
and not derivatives of any other fields.
And we're going to give them a name,
we're going to call them A.
A mu.
mu.
Now,
a mu has four components.
I'm going to tell you right now what they correspond
to,
so that we won't be working in the blind,
so that I won't just be doing mathematical
formalism on the blackboard.
If you know anything about electromagnetism,
you know that the
electromagnetic field tensor,
sorry,
I won't even use that word,
that the electric and
magnetic fields can be written in terms
of vector potentials and a scalar potential.
I won't write them down now,
but there are four quantities,
the three components of the
vector potential,
and the fourth is
basically called the electrostatic potential.
And those
four quantities form a four vector.
The electrostatic potential being the time component,
and the
vector potential being the space
components of a four vector.
That's what these things are.
The time component being,
well,
being the electrostatic potential,
and the other three components being the space.
Do you remember,
for example,
what the magnetic
field is in terms of A,
in terms of the space components?
Del cross curl.
Yeah,
it's the curl of A.
And the electric field,
something else.
Something else that
can be written in terms of these.
And we'll come to them,
what they are.
Okay.
So,
we're
going to take a look at the magnetic field.
And we're going to take a look at the magnetic
field.
And we're going to invent four more fields.
Now these fields,
unlike theta here,
theta wasn't a dynamical field.
It's not something which has an equation of motion.
It was just
a transformation that we decided to do.
We picked it at will.
And when we picked it,
we found out that this was
not a symmetry unless theta was constant.
But now we're adding
more fields.
Okay?
And I'm going to add,
I'm going to add this field,
and I'm going to
assume that it also transforms.
under the same transformation.
What do I mean by that?
I mean there's some transformation
which involves all of the variables,
just in the same way that if I rotate
the coordinates of one particle,
I also need to rotate the coordinates
of another particle,
and so forth and so on.
There may be many degrees of freedom,
all which transform under the same transformation.
So we're going to assume,
we're going to basically postulate
that A also has a transformation property,
or must have a transformation property,
whenever we do such a transformation,
and the transformation property is going to be this.
It's going to be A mu,
let's call it,
hold on a second,
I've screwed up my notes here.
I seem to have notes from several different lectures
all mixed up together.
Yeah.
Yeah,
before we talk about the transformation property of A,
let's,
let's first talk about the Lagrangian.
talk about how A fits into the Lagrangian.
A is another variable which has an equation of motion,
it will also have waves,
those waves describe electromagnetic waves and so forth,
and A also has a Lagrangian of its own,
plus there are interactions between A and phi,
which means there are things in the Lagrangian
which involve both A and phi.
So let's go back to the phi prime Lagrangian.
Let's go back to the phi prime Lagrangian,
and we're going to talk about the phi prime Lagrangian,
which is the Lagrangian of A mu.
Our variables now are all our phi prime,
phi complex conjugate prime,
and I'll also call the vector potential,
the four-dimensional vector potential A mu,
I'll call it prime for a moment.
These are the prime variables.
The unprimed variables will be
obtained from these by some transformation.
And the Lagrangian for the prime variables,
I'm now going to modify.
I'm going to modify it to,
d mu phi star prime.
Let's put the star on the outside.
Star out here.
d mu phi prime.
And now I'm going to add something.
I,
a constant called E,
that constant will ultimately appear as the electric charge
of a charged particle.
But it's just a constant in the Lagrangian now,
a numerical number,
times A prime mu phi prime.
What I've done is I've replaced just derivative of phi
by a new thing,
which is the derivative of phi
plus I,
a times the vector potential times phi.
This is a new thing.
It's actually called the covariant derivative of phi,
but for the moment,
it's just a new object.
And we're going to multiply that by,
notice that it's complex conjugated.
Okay.
When you complex conjugate,
you've got to complex conjugate everything,
phi and I.
A is real.
A is real by assumption.
And that gets multiplied by d mu phi prime
plus I,
e,
A prime mu phi prime.
Plus or minus m squared phi star phi.
So I've modified the original starting Lagrangian
by replacing the derivative of phi
by a new thing,
derivative of phi,
or derivative of phi prime,
plus I,
e,
A times phi prime.
Sometimes people write this by saying,
just replace derivative with respect to mu
by derivative with respect to mu
plus I,
e,
A mu.
Just replace the derivative operation
by derivative plus multiplication by I,
e,
A mu.
So sometimes one says
that this is a new replacement for the derivative
which we call the covariant derivative.
Just a name.
This covariant has nothing to do with the covariant from,
yeah?
Is phi the very end of that?
Is it phi or phi prime?
Oh,
sorry.
Phi prime.
It doesn't matter.
It actually doesn't matter,
but right.
Okay,
right.
Good.
All right,
now supposing we carry through
the same set of operations
and,
in other words,
the same set of operations
where we're going to replace phi prime
by e to the I theta x phi.
What are we going to get?
Well,
exactly the same thing is going to happen
and this derivative here
is going to get replaced by d mu,
phi,
where is it?
Uh,
plus,
I'll do the complex conjugation at the end,
plus I d mu theta,
whoops,
lower d mu,
d mu theta times phi.
That's what happens to derivative of phi prime.
It just becomes derivative phi
plus I d mu theta times phi.
Okay.
But now we have to add plus Ie
A prime mu times phi.
Is this obvious what I've done
or do I need to explain it?
I think I may need
to explain it a little more.
All I'm doing is replacing
for phi prime
e to the I theta phi.
When I differentiate theta prime,
I'll get the extra term
I d mu theta times phi,
just as I did there.
Oh,
incidentally,
this also gets multiplied,
I guess,
by e to the minus I theta,
all pieces,
and this should be complex conjugated.
We can complex conjugate it by just...
I don't know if you can see this.
All right,
stop me now
if you don't understand what I did.
I don't understand what I did
because I lost an I.
Yeah.
Just complete substitution.
Wherever I saw phi prime,
I stuck e to the I theta times phi.
That complex conjugate,
and then add in a new term,
the new hypothetical term
that I've added into the Lagrangian
for fun,
for the fun of it,
just to see what happens.
That's one factor.
The other factor will cancel
the e to the I theta.
This will cancel as before.
And what we'll have then
is just the complex conjugate
of what's here,
d mu phi plus I d mu theta.
So,
d mu times phi
plus Ie a prime mu phi.
And let's forget the m squared phi.
All right,
minus m squared phi star phi.
Notice what's happened.
All that's happened...
Is there such a thing
as A super mu?
Yeah,
we're A super mu.
Good.
This is not A1 mu.
It's just A prime mu,
super mu.
Yeah,
if this has lower indices,
then the right-hand side
has to have upper indices.
And that's it.
Okay,
now look what's happened.
What's happened is
the Lagrangian sort of has changed
form on the one hand.
It changed form
what it started with
in that it now has this new term.
But there's another sense
in which it hasn't changed form.
If I combine d mu theta with A mu,
if I combine those together
with A prime,
in other words,
if I take d mu theta
plus A prime,
and I call that A,
I just call that A,
unprimed,
then this has exactly the same form
as it started with,
except both phi and A,
we've dropped their primes.
Has exactly the same form.
And so that tells me
that if I want to maintain the symmetry,
I have to have the same form
as I did with A.
I had better postulate
a transformation property of A,
namely,
that you simply add
the derivative of theta to it
to define the new field
after transformation.
So,
to have a symmetry,
we add another field into the brew,
A mu prime,
and that's equal to A mu
plus I,
no,
no I,
d mu theta.
This is the full transformation property,
or the full transformation structure
of the three fields,
phi,
phi prime,
phi star prime,
and A.
Actually,
how many fields are there?
Two here,
two here,
and four more here.
Six fields here,
six independent components.
The last symbol there,
is that a phi or a theta?
Where?
On the angle of time.
Theta,
theta,
theta.
Okay,
is that a function of x or not?
Yeah,
it's a function of x.
Otherwise,
how could you differentiate it?
Yeah,
but it's not a function of time.
It could be,
no,
no.
Derivative with respect to mu
means derivative with respect to everything.
So we're not just comparing reference points,
but we're comparing those frames
at different points of space,
also in time.
We're imagining that our coordinates
in this angular space
can be rotated in space,
and they can also be rotated,
they can be rotated from point to point in space,
and point to point in time.
So let's just go through it again.
We started with a new Lagrangian,
a new field theory,
that contains a new set of fields,
that enter into the old Lagrangian
in this new way.
Then we carried out the change of variables
from phi prime to phi,
and we discovered that basically what it does
is it keeps the same form for the Lagrangian,
except that we have to modify a prime
and add to it the derivative of theta.
This is the full structure of a gauge transformation,
and if we make these substitutions,
if we make these substitutions
into the original Lagrangian,
then the form of the Lagrangian does not change.
Then the form of the Lagrangian does not change,
and we can write that this is equal to,
I'm just going to replace this,
exactly the same thing,
except with all the primes dropped.
All right.
This is equal to,
same thing without primes.
That's the idea of a symmetry.
If the Lagrangian has exactly the same form
both before and after the transformation,
then you say there's a symmetry.
So this new field theory,
whatever it is,
is invariant under Lagrangian.
So we can write it as a local gauge transformation.
Local means that the phase parameter here
can depend on position.
Is that a gauge covariant
or is that you're using covariant?
Gauge invariant.
The Lagrangian is gauge invariant,
or the action is gauge invariant.
Invariant.
That's e to the one?
E to the one.
IEA.
That's A prime.
Well,
whatever,
but the E is just E to the one?
Yeah.
Charge.
Oh,
that's not E.
That's not the mathematical symbol 2.7128,
whatever it is.
This is the electric charge of some particle.
Now,
what particle?
The quanta of the field described by phi.
But that's yet to be proved,
that in any sense that this has...
Transformation,
you left out the E in there.
Oh,
you're right.
1 over E,
1 over E.
You're right.
Maybe that should be a
minus in front of that partial?
Which one?
In that transformation.
That one over E.
I thought it was plus.
Let's see.
No,
because he sort of worked it backwards,
and so it...
I thought it was plus.
Maybe that's...
Maybe...
Yeah,
I think...
No,
I think you're probably right.
I think you may be right.
Yeah.
Yeah,
I think we had that A...
you're right.
A was equal to A prime plus derivative,
I think.
Yeah.
That's right.
Okay.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Good.
I think we have it right now.
Okay.
So,
what we've discovered up until now is we can force,
if you like,
we can force a field theory
to have this new kind of invariance
where you transform things.
You can transform things from place to place,
not just rigidly.
In fact,
the only real symmetries of
nature are gauge symmetries like this.
All others are not really symmetries of nature.
Not yet.
All right.
Let's go back to the...
Now,
what I haven't indicated here is whether
there's other terms in the Lagrangian governing
A,
for example.
The phi part of the Lagrangian,
we've seen what the phi part of the Lagrangian corresponds
to.
It's out of phi...
Oh,
incidentally,
yeah,
same thing without primes.
Notice how A enters into the Lagrangian.
What will happen to this form of the Lagrangian
when we put A prime in or A in?
This will get replaced by A.
All right.
So,
in fact,
the Lagrangian...
Which I could write as having...
As a plus,
I think it's plus E times A prime.
This whole thing just becomes E...
Becomes A.
Now,
I don't know how familiar it is...
Did I leave out E?
I think I left out E.
Yeah,
E.
你愛妞
I don't know whether this strikes a bell
or rings a bell to you or not
um...
do you know what the Lagrangian for a current
in an electromagnetic field looks like,
an electric current in an
electromagnetic field
in particular a magnetic field
no,
not A dot B
A dot V
P goes to,
momentum goes to momentum less
E times the vector potential
this is true,
that's one way of seeing it
but if we're talking about a,
you know,
uniformly flowing,
a current of some sort
not an individual particle
what the,
what is the coupling of a current
to the electromagnetic field
okay,
I'll tell you right now
what is it?
A times that current
A times that current,
A dot J
look at what,
we're going to come back to this
we're going to come to come back to this
A dot J
uh...
and more generally
this would be the case of
it was only a space component,
this would be the coupling of a
magnetic field held to a current
well that's about what we see here
we see J
and we see A
so we see the pieces plus a time component piece
we see the pieces
that are are traditionally...
traditionally the interaction between electric charges
or electric currents and the electromagnetic
field.
Electromagnetic field is best described in terms
of the vector potential and the electric
and magnetic fields are things that we
build up out of the vector potential.
Okay,
now let's talk about the electromagnetic field
when there are no charges and currents.
In other words,
let's forget about phi.
Let's forget about phi and ask what kind of theory
describes A by itself.
What we're talking about
now is electromagnetic waves propagating
in the absence of charges.
Supposing we just forget phi.
Phi is the thing which describes
the charged currents.
It's the thing in quantum
mechanics which describes the charged particles.
The charged
particles are quanta of this field.
But let's forget charges.
We know that electromagnetism
has an interesting non-trivial behavior even
far from where there are any charges,
namely
electromagnetic waves propagating through empty space.
So there must be some dynamics
to the electromagnetic field,
which is even there.
But we're talking about a fairly random field.
just there in the absence of charges.
So it's not this.
It's something just involving
the electromagnetic field itself when this
field phi is equal to zero.
Oh,
this incidentally,
this would become a squared here,
a mu,
a mu.
So what shall we say
governs the electromagnetic field by itself?
Well,
I would like to maintain this gauge symmetry
if I'm going to go to all of this
effort to invent A just to make
this this this Lagrangian gauge invariant I
certainly don't want to destroy that
gauge invariance by by not having the
electromagnetic field Lagrangian by itself
be gauge invariant by not having
it so we want the electric we want
the Lagrangian that we make up let's call it
L that part of it which depends
on the vector potential in various ways the
vector potential and its derivatives we
want that Lagrangian also to be gauge
invariant
so that brings up the question then what
kind of combinations can I make up out
of just the electromagnetic field of just
a
magnetic field of a particular type of a
by itself the four components of a what
kind of combinations can I make up in
particular out of the derivatives of
a I'm mostly interested in the derivatives
of a it's typically derivatives of
fields which enter into Lagrangians there
may also be things without derivatives
but Lagrangians most important thing is
dependence on the velocities the derivatives
so what kind of thing can I
make out of the derivatives of a
that itself is gauge invariant that might enter
into Lagrangian
with the same gauge invariance that you have
up there in other words a transforming the
same way
yeah that's right with a transforming with
a transforming in this way in other
words invariant under a goes to a minus
1 over e times the derivative of the derivative
of the derivative of a
okay fine so what's that basically your right
hand is going to do is go hopefully
you got that you know where that number is
but I'm just trying to figure it back out
here let me see a
little bit here we can do
bam-bam down there you guys just
one minute I've done three minutes of
16 derivatives of A that we can concoct.
Derivative with respect to x of A sub x,
derivative with respect to y of A sub x,
and so forth.
There are 16 of them,
since there are four components of x
and four components of A.
They can all be summarized in
the form d nu A mu.
Mu can go from 0 to 3.
That's four components.
Nu can go from 0 to 3.
And so this is just a convenient way to represent
basically a matrix of 16 independent derivatives
of the four components of A.
Let's see what happens to this
when we make a gauge transformation.
When we make a gauge transformation,
A mu will go to A mu
minus 1 over E d mu theta.
So this will go to d nu of,
A mu,
minus I,
sorry,
minus 1 over I,
1 over E,
d mu theta.
In other words,
it will pick up an extra term.
The change in d nu
theta will be the extra term,
here's the extra term,
will be,
minus 1 over E,
d nu d mu theta.
What does this mean?
This means the second partial derivative,
first you differentiate with x mu,
and then you differentiate with respect to x nu.
Everybody understand what this symbol is?
d nu d mu theta?
It's the second partial derivative of theta
with respect to x nu and x mu.
Okay,
that in itself suggests,
if you're,
you know,
if you're fiddled with these things at all,
it would immediately suggest what
the invariant quantity you can make.
Let's look at the related quantity.
This could,
for example,
be,
if nu was 1,
let's take the case,
nu equals 1,
mu equals 2.
That would mean derivative with respect
to x of A sub y,
for example,
1 corresponds to x,
y corresponds to 2.
There's another quantity which also has an
index x and an index y in it,
and it's sort of the opposite.
It's dy A x.
Okay?
We could represent the matrix of those variables
as d mu A nu.
Alright,
so if x is,
if nu is 1 and mu is 2,
then this could be dx of A y,
and this would be dy of A x.
But each one has 16 components.
What happens to this quantity
when you make a transformation?
Well,
all I have to do is swap mu and nu.
I don't have to do much work.
It goes to d mu A nu.
All I've done is interchange mu and nu.
And then minus d nu,
no,
d mu,
d nu A,
d nu,
d mu,
d nu theta.
All I've done is interchange mu and nu.
Okay,
so d nu,
this goes to minus d nu,
d mu theta.
Okay.
Enough,
enough.
So I've got it with how many moves?
My whole value of a
Now it's pretty clear what to do to make something
which doesn't change under a gauge transformation.
Just,
oh,
well,
first of all,
the theorem.
The theorem is that the order of differentiation
of a variable of a function is immaterial.
The derivative with respect to mu
times the derivative with respect to nu
is the same as the derivative interchanged.
For example,
the derivative with respect to x
of the derivative with respect to y of theta
is the same as the derivative of sub y,
derivative of sub x of theta.
Order of operations for derivatives doesn't matter.
dx dy is the same as dy dx.
So,
that means that d nu d mu theta
is the same as d mu d nu theta.
Supposing I subtract these two things
and define a new quantity
d nu a mu minus d mu a nu.
That's not zero.
We're not subtracting the same thing,
we're not subtracting a thing from itself.
We're subtracting,
for example,
dx ay from dy ax.
That's not zero.
But what happens to it under a gauge transformation?
Nothing happens to it
because the shift cancels out.
The change in the two of these is the same
and when you subtract them,
the change cancels out.
So under a gauge transformation,
this just works.
This just goes to itself.
d nu a mu minus d mu a nu.
How many such quantities are there?
16 to begin with.
There are 16 quantities which are all invariant.
All 16 of them are invariant under gauge transformations.
Now,
there actually aren't 16.
Or at least there aren't 16 non-trivial ones.
10 of them,
10 of them?
Well,
first of all,
4 of them are zero.
All the ones in which
nu and mu are the same.
We can make a matrix out of these.
We can make a matrix out of these,
a 4 by 4 matrix.
Label the matrix entries 0,
1,
and 2.
And then in each entry,
we could put the appropriate d nu
a mu minus d mu a nu.
I think you get the idea.
What happens in the diagonals here?
There's 0.
This is d 0 a
0 minus d 0 a 0.
Here we would have d 1
a 1 minus d 1 a 1.
So all the diagonal entries are 0.
It's anti-symmetric.
Yes.
It's anti-symmetric,
which means
when you interchange mu and nu,
it changes sign.
So first of all,
it's 0 along the diagonal.
There are some entries off the diagonal.
For example,
over here,
we would have,
I think,
d 1 a 0,
minus d 0 a 1.
What would we have down here?
The opposite with the opposite sign,
because when we interchange mu and nu,
the minus sign here causes it to flip.
So whatever we have above the diagonal here,
we have exactly the same thing below the diagonal,
except with the sign changed.
So there's no use of keeping track of the things
above the diagonal and below the diagonal separately.
They're so closely related,
they're just opposites from each other,
that they're not independent.
And so how many independent quantities are there?
There's all the ones above the diagonal.
That's it.
Six independent derivatives of this type that we can form.
Six independent components of this anti-symmetric object.
What are those six independent components?
I will tell you now.
I don't want to hide it and
jump out and surprise you with it.
The six independent components are
the three independent components of the electric field,
and the three independent components of the magnetic field.
In fact,
we could put them up in here.
The three independent components of the electric field
are up in here.
I'll be more precise about them later.
And the three independent components
of the magnetic field are here.
For the moment,
we're just counting how
many independent quantities are there.
Six.
How many independent components of the
electric and magnetic field are there?
Six.
Six independent components of the electric field.
It sounds like they may be related.
In fact,
they are the same thing.
But the precise connections between them we'll come back to.
This object here,
d mu a mu minus d mu a nu,
which is made up out of first derivatives of A,
There's a symbol for it,
and a name for it.
It's called the electromagnetic field tensor.
okay it's called the electromagnetic field tensor
and it consists of the components of
electromagnetic field in B and the symbol for it is F
nu mu so F is just a complex of six objects
that forms an anti-symmetric tensor whose
components are really in disguise the electric
and magnetic fields we'll come back to them but
now we have something that we can build a gauge
invariant Lagrangian out of in fact this is the
only thing which is gauge invariant and made up
out of the first derivatives of a what kind of
thing would we like to have in a Lagrangian for
a well Lagrangians are usually functions of
the variables in their first derivatives in fact
that's always the case Lagrangians are
functions of the variables in their
first derivatives which variables are we talking
about we're talking about the a's anything which
doesn't have derivatives in it a a squared
anything like that is not going to be
gauge invariant it just won't a will change under
a gauge transformation and any simple function
of a that doesn't contain derivatives will not
be gauge invariant the only thing that's easy
to make up that's gauge invariant that contains
a and its first derivatives is f mu nu
that's it that's the only gauge invariant quantities that
there are which contain no more than first derivatives
and that's it so what can you do to
make a Lagrangian that has that's quadratic in
derivatives supposing we want to stick to this
pattern of things which are quadratic in
the derivatives and which is Lorentz invariant let's
come back now there's another invariant so we
wish to keep track of and that's Lorentz invariant
to keep track of Lorentz invariant by now should
be very easy all we have to do is contract
indices upper and lower indices as long
as all indices are contracted correctly then
Lorentz transformations will be a symmetry of
anything that we make it's pretty obvious
is only one thing that we
can make its f mu nu
f mu mu
this is basically sums and differences of squares
of the components of f I'll tell you
exactly what it is it's e squared the
electric field squared minus the magnetic field squared
okay
e squared minus b squared now we're going to come
and we're going to study the nature of this field
tensor and its relation to the electric and
magnetic fields in more detail but I'm sort of
outlining and sketching where we're going that we were
for so let's summarize if we wanted to have
this peculiar gauge invariance then we were forced to
introduce a new variable called a a itself had a
transformation property and it entered into a new
structure called the covariant derivative where is the
covariant derivative d mu plus i e a mu is the covariant derivative
then we discovered that if in the original Lagrangian we could have a
we replaced all derivatives by covariant derivatives.
That's the operation.
Replace all derivatives by covariant derivatives.
And at the same time,
allow the vector potential
to have its own transformation property.
Then the Lagrangian was invariant
under these gauge transformations.
So that's a kind of pretty thing,
that there is a Lagrangian that we can write down
that generalizes the original Lagrangian,
which
has this improved symmetry,
this more powerful symmetry,
or this bigger symmetry,
where you can vary the phases
from point to point in space.
Well,
then we said,
good.
Now let's talk about A by itself.
We've motivated why A has a certain gauge transformation
property.
Now let's ask,
can we make Lagrangians for A by itself,
which have this gauge transformation property,
that they're invariant?
And so we looked around for expressions
which would not transform when
you make a gauge transformation.
In fact,
we looked around for things that we could make up
out of the derivatives.
These are the 16 possible derivatives of A.
And the obvious answer is the anti-symmetric quantity
d mu A mu minus d mu A nu.
For that,
this extra piece which gets induced by the gauge
transformation cancels.
So we found this.
We found a gauge invariant,
F mu nu.
Anything that we make out of
F mu nu will be gauge invariant,
but not anything that we make will be Lorentz invariant.
Just F mu nu by itself is not Lorentz invariant.
It has open indices hanging around here.
It's not a scalar here.
That's what I mean when I say it's not invariant.
Yeah,
it's not a scalar.
It's not a scalar.
It has open indices here.
It has components.
So it'll transform in various ways.
But if we square it,
we'll get a new invariant.
But if we square it and
contract the indices in the right way,
it will become something which is Lorentz invariant.
And in fact,
it is just E squared minus B squared.
It's not obvious that this is Lorentz invariant,
but it is.
E squared minus B squared is a quantity which
is the same in every Lorentz frame.
If we have an electric
field someplace and a magnetic field,
and we look at it
from a different state of motion
or a different angle,
the electric field,
the magnetic field,
the electric and magnetic field components will transform.
In fact,
if we view an electric field from a moving frame,
we'll typically see a magnetic field.
If we view a magnetic field from a moving frame,
we'll see an electric field.
But whatever E squared minus B squared is,
it's the same in every reference frame.
That's the content of this expression.
E squared minus B squared
is invariant because all the indices
are properly contracted.
So now we have a candidate for the action
of the electromagnetic field itself.
We're not going to work
out the equations of motion tonight.
We'll do that another time.
But I'm showing you the logic that went in
to the idea of gauge symmetry.
Well,
let's continue.
That's really,
in a sense,
enough for one night,
isn't it?
Are you going to go into
what's conserved because you have a symmetry?
Yes.
Well,
not tonight,
though.
But I may.
I mean,
yeah,
I'd like to do that.
Yes?
Can you go back to
the analogy of the spinning rope
and describe,
if it's possible,
describe A in regards
to that analogy?
Well,
I'll tell you that the,
no,
I can't do that at this moment
because the analogy involves general relativity.
OK.
But let's put it this way.
In the rope analogy,
these variables phi
are actually coordinates of positions of the rope.
So what we're talking about when we
make these kind of transformations
is coordinate transformations,
which vary from place to place.
Coordinate transformations which vary from place to place
are the material of the general theory of relativity.
So until we would come
to the general theory of relativity,
that jump rope would not look gauge invariant.
But it is gauge invariant when gravity is taken.
But this is beyond,
right now,
beyond the level
of the course at the moment.
If and when we get to study general relativity,
remind me to come back to this,
and we
can see how the jump rope
also has its own gauge invariance.
But not now.
It's not the vector potential.
It's the vector potential.
And the vector potential would be certain components
of the gravitational field.
Certain components of the gravitational field,
which
are there in the general theory of relativity,
would become the analog of the vector potential.
So it's a correct question.
It's a good question.
But it's beyond our level at the moment.
All right.
I think I'm just going
to go on a little more,
and tell you
in a different way,
which,
of course,
is secretly
exactly the same way of
thinking about the electromagnetic field
and its interaction with particles.
This is the electromagnetic field and its interaction
with charged wave fields.
Phi is a charge-carrying wave field.
That's the language one would use,
or a charge-carrying scalar field that carries charge,
in the sense that waves of this field
constitute electric charge densities and electric currents.
And here we see the basic interaction a dot j,
which is the hallmark of the interaction of charges
with the vector potential.
Now,
when we study quantum mechanics,
the particle-field duality,
or the particle-field complementarity,
or whatever boring thing you call it,
or wanted to call it,
tells us that all fields are associated also
with particles.
And in fact,
the phi field is associated
with charged particles.
But we don't need to
study quantum mechanics to figure out
how char- to figure out,
to describe how charged particles
interact with the electromagnetic field.
We can just go back to
the basic particle description of charges
and ask,
in that language,
the original particle,
classical particles with carrying charge,
how do they interact with the electromagnetic field?
And so I want to completely change gears
and go back to classical particles
in the special theory of relativity.
Classical particles,
the Lagrangian for classical particles
in the special theory of relativity,
and then show you
how the electromagnetic field correspondence,
and in particular,
we'll also study the classical particles,
and then we'll see the idea of gauge invariance.
It takes on a different form,
has a different flavor to it,
but it's the same invariance.
Okay,
so let's think of a worldline of a particle.
Here's the worldline of a particle.
The worldline has to be chosen subject to
the rules of the principle of least action.
And so our first question is,
what is the action of a moving particle,
moving in the special theory of relativity?
For the moment,
let's forget fields.
No fields in the problem,
just a free particle.
Well,
there's really only one invariant that
we can make for a trajectory
that in any way looks anything like an action.
The natural quantity to identify with a
trajectory is the length of the trajectory.
The length of the trajectory is the relative,
the relativistic length of the trajectory.
The relativistic length of the trajectory is
the natural quantity to identify with the action.
In any case,
it's a candidate.
And the reason it's a
good candidate is because it's invariant.
It's invariant,
the proper time,
I should say the length of the trajectory,
I mean the proper time along the trajectory.
The proper time along the trajectory is basically
the action of a trajectory of a particle.
Well,
not quite.
You have to multiply the proper
time along the trajectory by the mass.
And for reasons which are pretty much conventional,
there's a minus sign.
Ah,
I hate these things.
Will we run out of them?
Let's see.
Minus.
Minus m,
the mass of the particle,
times the proper time between the initial point
and the final point along the trajectory.
But what's the proper time?
Well,
let's start with the proper time
along a little piece of trajectory.
That's d tau squared is equal to dt squared
minus dx squared plus dy squared plus dz squared.
I'm just going to write dx squared here.
In fact,
let's,
that stands for dx squared
plus dy squared plus dz squared.
Let me write it out once in full.
Minus dy squared minus dz squared.
That's d tau squared.
That's the proper time squared of a small little interval.
And I suppose I could
put a little arrow over this.
dx squared.
All right.
That's dt squared.
That's the proper time squared of a small little interval.
There are some speeds of
light which would go in here.
If we had speed of light,
where would they go?
Ah,
I don't know.
I'm going to leave them out.
They don't add anything to the discussion at this point.
Okay.
So this is d tau squared.
And d tau,
the actual proper time along the trajectory,
is just the square root of this.
So let's get rid of
the c squares because we don't,
because we're grownups and we don't need to take
the speed of light to not be equal to one.
And d tau is equal
to the square root of this.
The total path length,
or the total proper time along the path length,
is an integral.
An integral from the beginning to the end along
the trajectory of the square root of dt squared.
And I'm just going to write minus dx squared.
But please keep in mind that
that dx squared stands for d.
So that's the integral for dx
squared plus dy squared plus dz squared.
Okay.
That's the action.
Now what on earth does this mean?
The square root of the square of a differential.
All right.
First of all,
what it means is chop
up the trajectory into little pieces.
Calculate the square root of dt squared minus dx squared
along the trajectory for each little piece and add them up.
Basically,
that's all.
Add them up.
That's what the symbol means.
But we can make it
look like a more conventional integral.
By dividing inside the square
root and then multiplying out here.
I've basically multiplied and divided by dt.
But if I put a dt under the square root,
it becomes dt squared.
All right.
So what's in the square root here?
What's in the square root is the integral.
Sorry.
What's in the square root is 1.
dt squared minus dx squared.
You've got the integral.
1 over dt squared?
1 over dt squared.
Minus,
now what's dx by dt?
speed of light.
It's the velocity.
This is the square of the velocity.
The square of the three components of the velocity summed.
vx squared plus vy squared plus vz squared.
So this is just,
let me call it x dot squared.
Dot means derivative with respect to ordinary time.
Not proper time.
x dot squared and of course it stands for x
dot squared plus dy dot squared plus z dot squared
And I could also call it
just V squared if I wanted,
but I'm gonna leave it there as x dot squared
times Dt
No,
I don't want to call it nothing I just want
to express it in terms of the velocity itself minus M
Well now I have a
thing which looks like a Lagrangian.
I should put the minus M on the inside
We put on the inside in here
And put the minus sign also minus M
Square root of 1 minus x dot squared
Lagrangians are all our
Actions are always integrals over Lagrangians
integrals with respect to time of Lagrangian
Now we're not talking about field theory.
We're just talking about the motion of a particle
So there's no integration of a space
the degree of freedom now is just x
x y and z of
T
the position of the particle
as a function of time is
The degrees of freedom here's a Lagrangian which depends
on velocities it happens and doesn't depend independently on x
It only depends on x dot well.
This is the kind of
Lagrangians we've seen in the past
It's a little bit unusual
Instead of having an x dot squared as
a square root of 1 minus x dot squared
But it falls within the class of Lagrangians
which depend on the velocities and the coordinates
so it is a special case of a
conventional Lagrangian
Let's use that first of all to calculate the momentum
What's the formula in terms of a
Lagrangian for the momentum conjugate to x?
remember
The derivative of the Lagrangian
this whole thing is Lagrangian here
with respect to x x dot
All right,
so now we get to try out our skills at
Differentiating this is x dots.
Let me put y dot squared plus z dot squared
Okay,
anybody good at differentiating
the
x dot squared plus y
dot squared plus z dot squared
That gives us a square root
in the denominator with a 2
square root of 1 minus now
let me call it v squared
x dot squared plus y
dot squared plus z dot squared
And then we have to differentiate
the argument of the square root
So we have to separate a
line a 2 and an x dot
plus z dot
those two없ies cancel
which gets a line a 2 and and x dot
Now we get m
Times x dot
Better yet m times the x component of the velocity
over the square root of 1 minus v squared.
I think we saw that before.
We have studied this,
have we not?
Right.
This is v squared over c squared if
we were to put the c's back in.
Well,
that's nice.
We see that the canonical momentum is just the momentum.
The relativistic
momentum,
mass times velocity,
with the Einstein correction,
square root of 1 minus v squared
over c squared in the denominator.
What about the energy?
What about the energy of the particle?
The energy is the Hamiltonian.
So if you have to,
go back to your classical mechanics,
but
I'll tell you what the answer,
I'm going to just tell you the answer.
It's a little bit of algebra that goes into it,
but I'll tell you what you have to do.
The Hamiltonian of a system is the sum
over the degrees of freedom of the velocities times
the momenta minus the Lagrangian.
Do you remember that formula?
All right.
So we have this.
There's only one coordinate now,
or three coordinates to be more precise.
Three coordinates,
x,
y,
and z.
So,
for example,
one of the terms will be x dot,
that's q dot,
times p sub x times m
v sub x over the square root
of 1 minus v squared over c squared.
And then we have to
subtract off the Lagrangian,
which is plus m square
root of 1 minus v squared.
Okay.
A little bit of algebra,
not much.
We'll convince you.
Another factor of c.
Oh,
yeah,
let's get rid of the factors.
Let's get rid of the c's.
You're right.
Let's just get rid of them.
Yeah.
Because I've been loose in the coefficients
of c here in other places,
let's just leave c equal to 1.
Oh,
this isn't so hard.
This is x dot times vx is vx squared,
right?
Oh,
of course,
there's also contributions from y and z.
So this vx squared will become
m vx squared plus vy squared plus vc squared.
We should have added up the three terms.
This
just becomes m v squared,
all three components.
And then we have this.
This is m v squared.
So this is m v squared plus m.
So let's see.
So what is this?
Let's put them over a common
denominator.
Let's put them both over the same common denominator,
square root of 1
minus v squared.
Let's get rid of the square root here.
The v squares cancel,
and we just
get m over the square
root of 1 minus v squared.
Have we seen that before?
Yeah.
That's the energy.
If we wanted to give it proper
units of energy when the c's are
in there,
it would be mc squared
over v squared over c squared.
And that would be the energy
of the particle.
All right,
that's the canonical formulation of
a particle in special relativity,
not under the influence of any force field.
All right.
The question is,
what happens when
we...
include an electromagnetic field?
Now,
I'm getting tired,
so the question is,
yeah,
let's
see if I...
It's rather easy,
but...
Okay,
let's do it.
I don't want to stop here because
we're going to be gone for a week,
and I guess I'd like
to finish the line of argument and
then have everybody study it in some detail.
Suppose
there's an electromagnetic field.
An electromagnetic field is described by a vector potential,
a mu.
So let's suppose
there's a vector potential
or a four-dimensional vector potential,
a mu.
How can I combine
it with a particle to make an action
that involves the particle moving in the electromagnetic
field?
I'm not talking about the
action of the electromagnetic field now,
just the particle,
the influence of the electromagnetic field on it.
All right.
So what can I do?
I can't do anything.
involves a mu and a particle trajectory to
make something that involves a mu and the particle
trajectory,
which is Lorentz invariant.
Well,
there's not too many things.
First of all,
you could think of an infinite variety of things,
but most of them would
be exceedingly complicated.
There's one simple thing that you can write down.
Anybody know what it is?
a dot v.
Well,
this is a fourth vector.
Can you write it?
Okay.
That's a four vector.
So we don't want to use a conventional velocity,
dx vp.
a dot p?
p is not a thing
that you usually put in Lagrangians.
We usually put in,
all right,
but let's,
it's a simple thing.
Instead of a dot v,
instead of a dot v,
which is on the right track,
let's try a times,
not v mu,
but dx mu by d tau.
But wait a minute.
That's okay.
This is an interesting quantity.
a mu.
d mu times dx mu by d tau.
This is a four vector,
dx mu by d tau.
But this is not conventional velocity.
And it looks a little bit awkward.
But let's take the action.
Let's try to use this in an action.
What's the natural thing to do with this?
The natural thing to do with it
is to integrate it along the trajectory.
But do you integrate it dt?
And if not,
why not?
The answer is no.
You wouldn't want to integrate it dt,
because this would not be Lorentz invariant.
dt is not Lorentz invariant.
What is Lorentz invariant is d tau.
Another way of saying the whole same
thing is we could include in the action
just the integral of a mu dx mu.
What does this mean?
This means we go along the trajectory,
we tromp up the trajectory,
and for each little interval,
we take its dx mu,
and we multiply it by a mu.
a mu at that point.
a mu right at that point,
and we add them up.
That's a quantity which is relativistically invariant.
Why?
Because it's the summation of a bunch of scalars.
a mu dx mu,
a four vector with a lower index,
times a four vector with an upper index,
that's invariant,
that's a scalar.
And so we add them all up,
we get a scalar.
This is a good quantity to begin with.
Now,
I'm going to throw in one more factor here.
I'm going to throw in the electric charge.
That's just a numerical multiple,
the electric charge of the particle.
That ought to go in there.
Why should it go in there?
Well,
if the electric charge was zero,
then we should have no
interaction with the electromagnetic field.
So presumably,
the strength of interaction
between the electric and magnetic fields on the one hand
and the particle is through its electric charge,
so that's a reasonable thing to put in there.
But this doesn't look like a conventional Lagrangian.
Where's the velocity?
Where's the dt?
Where's the Lagrangian dt?
Well,
that's easy to fix.
Just divide by dt
and multiply by dt.
What does this mean?
It's integral E.
Now,
let's take the time component.
The time component would be A naught,
naught for time,
times,
now what's x naught?
x naught is t.
So that's just dt by dt.
That's one.
And then plus electric charge.
Let's take the x component.
A sub x times dx dt.
What is dx?
That's v sub x,
right?
That's the x component of the velocity.
If we combine all of the terms,
we'll just get A dot v dt.
So somebody earlier said that the Lagrangian for,
somebody earlier said that the interaction
between the vector potential
and the charged particle was through A dot v.
Well,
yes,
that's right.
Here you see it,
but there's another term,
integral A naught.
This is the interaction.
This is the Lagrangian,
or here.
This is the action
for a particle
in an electromagnetic field.
It's very simple.
It's just a line integral of A dot dx.
Do you have an E squared there?
E squared?
Yeah,
you have an E outside the parenthesis.
Oh,
sorry.
No,
no E squared.
No one in second.
That's right.
E times A dot v.
All right,
I don't want to pursue this too much now
other than to make one observation about it.
Just one observation about it,
and that's that it's gauge invariant,
that it has a certain gauge invariance
that is an action principle,
thought of as an action principle,
it has a gauge invariance.
So,
yeah,
even before I do that,
let me relate some of this stuff
to what's over here.
Supposing I have a particle
moving along a trajectory like that,
and it's a charged particle.
There's an electric current that flows.
Both time component,
there's an electric charge density,
and there's a flow of charge.
The flow of charge is
just because the charge is moving.
Now,
where is the current localized?
It's localized wherever the particle is.
It's right sitting on top of the particle.
So wherever the particle is,
there's a flow of current,
if the particle is moving,
and there's a charge density.
The charge density is just describing
the charge density of that single particle.
So there's a flow,
so there's a current along the trajectory,
along the trajectory of the particle.
The space component of the current,
the flux of the charge,
that's proportional to the velocity of the charge.
If the particle is not moving,
there's no flow of charge.
There may be a charge density,
but there's no flow of charge.
If the particle is moving,
there's a flow of charge.
So along this trajectory,
there is a J.
The time component is just the fact
that there's a charge there,
a charge density at the point where the particle is.
And the space components of J,
what are they proportional to?
They're proportional to the electric charge
of the particle times its velocity.
It's right at the point where the particle is.
There's a current which is proportional
to the velocity,
in the direction of the velocity,
and of course it also involves the electric charge.
Well,
let's see,
where did we have it?
We had the Lagrangian,
here it is,
A dot V.
What is A dot V?
A dot V
is clearly similar to
or E A dot V.
E times V is the current.
Where did I do it?
I lost it.
Yeah,
here it is.
J is E times V.
E times V is the current.
This is the current dotted into the vector potential.
Well,
that's pretty much what you have over here.
Current times vector potential.
So we see there's a similarity.
The similarity being that in both cases,
the vector potential is coupled directly
to the charge flow,
to the flux of charge
or to the density of charge.
And I just wanted to point
out that similarity at this point,
that in both cases,
it's charge current or current of charge
times vector potential,
which goes into the Lagrangian.
The last thing I want
to do is just talk about
the gauge invariance of this Lagrangian.
Is it gauge invariant?
Not quite,
but almost,
and it's good enough.
Let's look at the action between two points.
What will it mean to say
that the action is gauge invariant?
Well,
supposing the action changes
when I do a gauge transformation,
but it changes in a
way that has no effect whatever
on the motion of a particle.
In other words,
it changes in a way that has no implication
whatever for how the particle moves.
That's good enough to say that there's a symmetry.
So let's see what happens.
Supposing I make a gauge transformation on a mu.
What does that do?
What does it add to a mu?
a mu goes to a mu
plus 1 over e d mu theta,
where theta is just this arbitrary function theta of x.
Any function,
whatever,
I can make such a gauge transformation.
What happens to the action?
The action gets an extra piece to it.
We have to add to it e
times the integral of the change in a.
That's 1 over e.
That cancels the e.
d mu theta,
that's the shift in a,
times the x mu dt,
the tau.
Well,
just the x mu.
Just the x mu.
Anybody know what this integral is?
From the starting point to the end point,
along the trajectory,
the derivative of theta times the x mu,
the mu derivative of theta times the x mu.
The difference?
The angle?
Yeah.
It's just the difference of theta
between the end points of the integrand,
between the end points of the integral.
This is the change.
Let's break it up into little pieces.
This is the change in theta when
you change x by a little bit,
times the change in x.
Each little interval along here,
this integrand is just the change in theta from going,
and going from one point to the next.
When you add them all up,
it just gives you the total change in theta
in going from the initial point,
theta initial,
to theta final.
Sorry,
theta initial,
theta final.
This whole integral is just theta final minus theta initial.
Well,
why doesn't such a term in the action
have any implication for the trajectory?
Because it doesn't depend on the trajectory.
It just depends on the value of
the theta at the two end points,
and it doesn't depend on the trajectory.
No matter what trajectory you select,
this integral here is always going to be the same.
It's just the difference of theta
at the beginning and end of the trajectory.
So,
if this contributes something
which doesn't depend on the trajectory,
it will not have any influence whatever
on what trajectory the particle takes.
And in that sense,
this is not an interesting contribution to the action.
It has no implication for the motion of the particle.
The important part of the action doesn't change
the part which really influences
the particle does not change
when you make a gauge transformation.
So,
we see from this particle perspective
that gauge transformations are also important
in variances of the action of a charged particle
with the electromagnetic field.
So,
this time,
we're not talking about a field
carrying the charge.
We're just talking about a point charge
moving through space.
So,
we see from two different perspectives
that gauge symmetry is a fundamental symmetry
of the interaction of charges
with the electromagnetic field.
I will be gone next week.
I have to give a lecture someplace.
A couple of places.
And I'll be back the week after.
How many lessons have we had so far?
Seven.
Eight.
Seems to me it must be eight.
Yeah.
So,
we have two more.
And I think we're getting somewhere.
We've,
you know,
but I want to,
what I do want to go through now
is the electromagnetic field,
the equations of motion for the electromagnetic field,
why F mu nu is connected to E and B,
and to see that the electromagnetic field
actually has the effect
on a charged particle that you would expect,
namely that it exerts forces
of the electrical and magnetic kind.
Then we could maybe spend a
little bit of time with this
and see that the flow of charge
in this picture here also behaves
as you would expect for charges flowing through space
if the charges were described by this field.
Okay.
I think we're finished for tonight.
Kidney
The preceding program is copyrighted
by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.