This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Has anybody done the homework and
found the operator for circular polarization?
What is it?
Yeah.
Right.
Let's just do it quickly.
I'll come back to you.
Since we assigned it homework,
let's just do it quickly.
Before...
One and minus one.
Okay,
let me just write the other two cases.
There was the
There was the,
what do we call it,
the observable for the polarization when the polarization
was in the vertical and horizontal directions.
Okay.
This is probably,
can edit this back,
we don't even have time for the present.
And we want expand force of
one plus the horizontal minus vertical.
And we can call that
Damn it's one.
Why don't people throw these
away when they're no good anymore.
I don't
Then we will try this.
Ooh,
that's cool.
Okay,
there was the observable representing
polarization in the vertical and horizontal
plane,
plus for horizontal,
minus for vertical,
and we call that,
oh boy,
1 minus 1,
0,
0.
The x polarization state we labeled as 1,
The y polarization,
the
vertical polarization,
we labeled as 0,
1.
Okay,
so this is the object which has eigenvectors
x and y with eigenvalue plus 1 and minus 1.
Then there was the polarization state,
which
is the observable for the 45 degree case.
We called the states theta,
and we represented
that by cosine theta,
sine theta,
and then there was the orthogonal one,
which was theta
plus pi over 2,
and that had a column vector
which I think was sine of theta,
and minus
cosine theta,
I think,
if I remember.
Yeah,
that'll work.
This one is orthogonal to this
one,
sine times cosine minus cosine times sine,
that'll do it.
Well,
okay,
we're going
to talk about whether that matters or not.
Okay,
I guess we wrote it this way last time.
It doesn't matter,
in fact.
And this was 1,
1,
0,
0.
Sorry,
that was for the special case
of 45 degrees,
and we called that 45 degrees 1 over root 2,
1 over root 2.
And this one
would be 1 over root
2 minus 1 over root 2.
This would be this,
and this.
And finally,
we discussed the linear
analysis of the exponential function.
The next thing you want to do is,
circular polarization,
we've started to discuss it,
the two states of circular polarization,
again,
you can think of them as two distinct orthogonal states.
Orthogonal means physically
distinguishable in a single experiment.
And I guess I called that,
I guess I put a little
rotation notation like that.
This would be positively polarized lights,
positively polarized
circular polarization,
and the wave function for that,
or the one over square root of two,
and you can take it to be one i.
Here's the first place where complex numbers come in,
and the opposite polarization,
same one over square root of two,
one minus i.
These are,
yes,
these are again orthogonal,
you can check that.
Remember when you check it that you
should complex conjugate.
Subtlucon,
you can take the inner product
and then multiply the upper components and
add it to what you get
when you multiply the lower components.
Alright,
what is the observable?
It goes with circular polarization,
that,
I don't remember what I called it.
Does it
have a name?
I guess we can just put a little rotation symbol,
and that,
as was mentioned
a moment ago,
is minus ii.
Zero,
zero.
Subtlucon.
We can check that this observable,
when it acts on the polarization state,
on the circularly
polarized states,
these are eigenvectors with eigenvalue
plus one and minus one,
and that
you can check for yourselves.
It's very straightforward.
You just,
the hardest part of it is remembering
that i squared is minus one.
Subtlucon.
Mm-hm .
All right,
now,
where are we,
and what are we doing,
relative to what we did the first
day when we studied classical mechanics?
The first day when we studied classical mechanics,
what we discussed was the possible states of
a very simple system with a discrete number
number of states.
The discrete number of states could
have been two for a coin flip,
six for
a die,
or any number.
And we just then said the state of
a system is a point in a set
of states,
however many we have.
And we also discussed the
evolution of the system in terms
of arrows,
which took you from one state to the
next to the next to the next in discrete
time steps.
Thus far,
how far have we gotten by comparison with this?
Well,
we've gotten
to the point where we've described what a state is.
We've gotten to the point which
is about the analog of the place where we
would be when I would say that a state is
just a point among a set of points,
where the set of points represents the space of
states.
Now,
the space of states is a vector space.
Well,
we've gone a little bit beyond that.
We have also discussed observables.
What would observables be in classical physics?
Observables
would simply be numbers which would label these states.
Functions,
for example,
we could
assign this state over here,
the observable value,
some observable,
let's call it k again.
Now it wouldn't be a linear operator,
we would just call it k.
Now,
we would call it a state,
k.
Ah,
here's a good example of an observable.
The head coin flip.
We could assign heads
one and we could assign tails minus one.
What about the die?
Well,
the die already comes
equipped with a numerical observable.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five,
and six.
Of course,
nothing would prevent us from
relabeling so that six became one,
five became four,
and
then mix them up in some funny way.
But an observable then would just be an assignment
of a number to each state,
basically.
When the system moves around from one point in
the state space to another point,
the observable changes.
So when we flip the head and coin,
the head and tail back and forth,
the coin heads to tails to heads to tails,
we get a
sequence of observable values.
Subtitles by the Amara.org community
some...
what's the word?
Some tools
to go on and discuss the next sorts of things,
which are how systems move.
Well,
I'm not quite ready for that yet,
because I do want to...
I do want to review a little bit,
and to do
a little bit of mathematical formalism,
which we haven't discussed yet.
First of all,
let me remind you what you do with states,
when you have them.
States are vectors.
They're the bra vectors and ket vectors.
And there are two interesting,
physically interesting things that you can do.
Let us suppose you know the state of a system,
and you're interested in some observable.
Well,
one thing you can do is to
compute the average value of the observable,
the thing that most physicists call the expectation value.
Let's call the observable again just k for...
well,
k for...
Well,
yeah,
k is fine.
Sometimes I remember to put the
little hat on top of it,
sometimes I don't.
The average of it is just a sandwich,
k,
between the state,
the ket version of the state,
and the bra version of the state.
That's the average.
And it would be something which would be
useful if you were going to measure k,
if you were going to prepare the system,
and the same state over and over again,
and many,
many measurements of k,
and take the average.
It would be a useful thing to do.
And it's a physically interesting quantity.
Another thing is,
supposing we have two states.
Supposing we have a and b.
And as it happens,
a and b are eigenvectors of two different observables.
Let's say that a is an eigenvector of k,
with eigenvalue...
Let's call it...
alpha...
times a.
And let's suppose that b happens to
be an eigenvector of a totally different observable,
l,
which happens to have eigenvalue beta times b.
There are two eigenvectors,
but of different operators.
Then the interesting quantity that
we've discussed over and over again,
although I may not have spelled
it out in quite this detail,
is we could ask,
what's the probability that if we prepare a system
with a definite value of the observable k,
namely alpha,
we do something to the system
so as to make k definite,
and namely with a value of alpha,
then what's the probability that if
we then do something to the system,
we then measure l,
that we get beta?
What's the probability that if we measure l,
we get the answer beta,
given that we prepare the system
with a definite value of k,
namely equal to alpha?
The answer is...
the inner product of a with b...
squared.
Or another way to write it,
is times its complex conjugate,
which we can write as b times a.
That's equal...
that's equal to two things,
in fact.
We can call it the probability a,
b.
It's the probability,
again,
that if we prepare the state with alpha,
and then measure l,
that we get beta,
but it also happens to be the
probability that if we prepare the state
with l equals beta,
and then measure k,
that we get alpha.
Was that clear?
Well,
it hardly matters,
since you get the same answer.
Oh,
did I write it wrong?
You're right,
I did.
Right.
This one is the complex conjugate of this.
Now,
this is the complex conjugate of this.
And these are the two kinds of questions
that you ask in quantum mechanics.
Average values for an ensemble of many experiments,
and,
again,
probabilities,
which,
again,
only make sense for many repeated experiments.
Both of these have the feature
that the answers are insensitive
to a certain operation that you can do
on any one of the vectors in the space.
And the operation is called
multiplying the vector by a phase.
Oh,
before I go on,
let me just remind you of one thing,
that physical state vectors always should be normalized
to make the total probability equal to one.
That's one rule.
So we can think of
physical state vectors as unit vectors.
Simply,
that's the statement that the sums of the squares
of the coefficients,
when you expand the state in a basis,
those should add up to one.
All right.
But let's discuss a little bit
what's another operation that you can do.
You can take a state,
or the whole state,
not a piece of it
individually when you add up pieces,
but the whole state,
the whole vector,
and you can multiply it by a phase.
And I'm going to explain
what that means in a moment.
But the point is,
it doesn't make any difference whatever
to the physical properties of the state.
All right.
So first of all,
what does a phase mean?
A phase is a complex number.
Let's just remember very quickly,
for those who haven't read the book,
I've been using complex numbers for the last 50 years.
A complex number is an x and a y
with an x equal to iy.
It also can be represented
as an r and a theta.
And it can be represented in the form
x and x plus iy.
x plus iy,
that's the complex number z.
It can also be represented as a complex number z.
It can be written in the form r cosine theta,
that's x plus ir sine theta,
that's y.
And another way of expressing it,
which is just more or less notation,
is to write it as r
times e to the i theta.
e to the i theta
is just another way of writing
cosine theta plus i sine theta.
Very quickly,
when you multiply two complex numbers,
you multiply their r's
and you add their angles.
So if we had two complex numbers,
let's call one of them
r e to the i theta,
the other one let's call it,
what's another letter that's near r?
r two.
No.
Yes.
r one and theta one,
sorry,
theta one.
And another complex number r two,
e to the i theta two.
Adding them is easy in this form.
We just add the components.
Multiplying them is easy in this form.
When you multiply two complex numbers,
the result is r one r two.
You multiply the lengths,
and then you add the angles,
e to the i theta one plus theta two.
One more point.
The notion of complex conjugate,
the complex conjugate of a complex number
is just the corresponding complex number
in the lower half plane,
which has exactly the same form r,
except instead of e to the i theta,
it has e to the minus i theta.
So whatever z is,
r e to the i theta,
z star is r e to the minus i theta.
Now in particular,
there are special numbers,
which are called just pure phases,
special complex numbers,
for which r is equal to one.
They are the numbers which lie on the unit circle.
The numbers which lie on the unit circle
in other words,
for which r is equal to one,
and theta can vary around from zero to two pi,
those numbers are called phases.
Well actually,
usually,
the language is a little bit ambiguous.
Sometimes the angle is called the phase,
and sometimes any number,
which is of the form e
to the i times an angle,
is called a phase.
All right.
So e to the i,
e to the i,
theta is a special kind of number,
which I will call a phase,
even though sometimes the phase
is reserved for the angle there.
And it has the property
that when you multiply it by its complex conjugate,
let's call this z,
if we multiply z times z star,
and if z is a pure phase,
then the result is just one.
Why is that?
Because it's e to the i theta,
times e to the minus i theta.
And when you multiply complex numbers,
you just add the phases,
and e to the zero is just one.
All right.
So this is a special class of numbers,
which are characterized by z times z star equal one.
Good.
Now what does that have to do with these vectors?
Formally,
or just mathematically,
we distinguish two vectors.
Let's call one of them a,
and let's call the other e
to the i theta times a,
where theta is any angle,
a number.
All right.
This is a vector.
This is a number times a vector.
Formally speaking,
they're two different vectors,
just as a vector and twice the vector
are two different vectors.
So mathematically speaking,
this vector is not equal to this vector.
But all of the physical
properties of these two are identical.
How to see that?
Let's go back to the various things
that we might do with
or the various physical questions we might ask.
For example,
supposing we took psi here.
Let's take the case of the expectation value
or the average value of any observable at all.
It doesn't matter what k is.
Supposing we multiply psi by e to the i theta.
If we multiply psi by e to the i theta,
what happens?
In other words,
if we multiply the ket
by e to the i theta,
what happens to the corresponding bra?
Right.
The corresponding bra is psi
e to the minus i theta.
So what would happen
if in this sandwich,
in this k sandwich,
we replace the bread,
psi,
by e to the i theta times psi?
Well,
this,
the bra vector,
sorry,
the ket vector,
would pick up the factor e to the i theta.
This would get the factor e to the i theta.
This one would get the factor
e to the minus i theta.
Now remembering that e to the
i theta is just a number.
It's not an interesting operator of any kind.
e to the i theta times e
to the minus i theta is just one,
and this would just cancel out of the expression.
So there would be no change
in the expectation value of any operator
if we replaced any vector,
any one of them,
the vector which happens to
describe the system in particular,
if we multiply it by a phase.
So in that sense,
the phase is irrelevant.
We can choose the overall phase
of the state any way we like.
It doesn't make any difference to what we would measure.
Likewise,
in the probability,
if we multiplied either a or
b or both by a phase,
it would also cancel out
because,
let's suppose we multiplied b by a phase.
The ket vector over here
would get multiplied by a phase.
The bra vector over here would
get multiplied by the opposite phase,
and they would cancel.
You could do the same thing with a.
So again,
you see that there is no physical significance
to the phase of the wave function.
The norm of the wave function
should be set equal to one,
and the phase of the wave function is completely irrelevant.
Okay,
let's come back for a moment to polarization.
Polarization of photons.
I said,
for example,
that the vector x is equal to one,
zero,
and the vector y is equal to zero,
one.
Nothing would have stopped me
from replacing y by a new version of itself,
namely zero minus one.
Minus one,
multiplying by minus one is multiplying by a phase.
e to the i pi is equal to minus one.
So a special case of
multiplying a state by a phase
is just to multiply the whole state by minus one.
I could have done it with x also,
it doesn't matter.
All of these are physically...
This is physically identical to minus one,
zero.
It is also physically identi...
I shouldn't put equals.
They're not equals,
they're vectors.
What kind of symbol can I use?
Let's...
Two squigglies means approximately equal to...
Not even approximately equal to.
A dot over the equals.
Okay,
a dot over the equals,
which means has the same physical significance as.
That's not a double arrow.
That means something else.
We'll take the dot over the equals
to mean has the same physical significance as.
All right?
Putting a minus one,
but also,
we could also multiply it by any phase.
e to the i theta.
That's a double arrow.
And zero.
All...
No,
sorry.
Dot.
They all have the same physical meaning
as a state in which the
polarization lies in the horizontal direction.
Same thing with the polarization
lying in the vertical direction.
We can multiply by minus one,
or anything else.
Zero,
e to the i theta.
And that's a double arrow.
So,
we have to have the word similarity or congruent.
Uh...
Yeah,
I love them.
But I don't...
I'm not sure they're quite right.
So I will use the term
has the same physical significance as.
I know it's a lot of words,
but...
Well,
similar is literally
just multiplying by a factor.
All right.
For you,
I'll use similar.
Is similar to.
So,
similar is something that has to do with triangles,
I thought.
Anyway,
let's move on.
It's kind of shape preserving.
Hm?
I don't know.
It just has the same expectation values and probabilities.
That's all.
All right,
so we can come back to here now,
to these circular polarizations.
I could change the definition of the circular polarization.
For example,
I might multiply by i,
suppose I have a circle.
Supposing I took the
positively circularly polarized state
and changed its definition
by multiplying both top and bottom by i,
then this would become
similar to,
in Mike's terminology,
similar to
1 over square root of 2.
Now I'm going to multiply everything by i.
i is a pure phase.
It's e to the i pi over 2.
1 over square root of 2.
i minus 1.
i times 1 is i.
i times i is minus 1.
So this has exactly the same
physical content as this one here.
All right.
In this particular case,
we can count parameters.
We can now count
how many parameters it takes
to describe
the polarization of a physical photon.
The physical polarization state
of a photon.
So,
let's say,
Let's count.
All right.
We can start with a general vector.
Let's call it alpha beta.
That's two complex parameters.
Four real numbers
all together.
So a general vector in the vector space
has four real parameters
associated with it.
Now,
first of all,
there is one combination
that we set
and we freeze.
Namely,
alpha star alpha
plus beta star beta
is equal to 1.
That's the condition
that the sum of the probabilities
add up to 1.
So,
we started with four real parameters.
One equation among them.
How many are left?
Three.
Okay,
so there's three parameters left over.
Three parameters left over.
But,
now,
there is one more fact.
If we multiply
by a phase,
it doesn't change the content
of the state.
That means the overall phase
doesn't have any content.
There's no content
in the overall phase.
Equivalently,
I can always take the upper entry
to be real.
I can always multiply
by the appropriate phase.
You have to multiply the top and the bottom
by the same phase.
But we can always choose,
for example,
this would be arbitrary,
but we can always choose
to make the upper component real
by multiplying by the appropriate
phase to get rid
of the complex
part of alpha here.
So we could always choose alpha to be real.
Now that it's real,
let's give it another name,
a.
I'll use Latin letters
for the moment for real numbers
and complex numbers down here,
beta.
Alright,
so how many do I have left?
Um,
let's first of all
solve this relationship here.
We have to have
that the sums of the squares,
we have to have that a squared
plus beta star beta
equals one.
There's an easy way to solve that.
We just write that beta star beta
is one minus a squared,
and now we can write
that beta
is equal to the square root
of one minus a squared
times any phase,
e to the i theta.
If beta star
times beta
is equal to the square root
is a number,
that means that beta is the square root
of that number times a phase.
General fact
follows from
the definition of beta star and beta.
Alright,
so we
can now write that the most general
possibility is a real
number up here,
again,
I choose a real number arbitrarily here,
then to make sure that it's normalized,
I put one minus a squared
square root down here,
but then I still have the freedom
to put in a phase,
e to the i theta.
How many overall parameters
are there?
Two.
One real parameter here,
and one real parameter for theta.
So,
that
means there's a two parameter family,
a two parameter
family of
polarization states
for a single photon.
What are
those two parameters?
Physically,
why are there two parameters
associated with the
polarization of a photon?
So let's come back to an electromagnetic
wave.
The simplest
electromagnetic wave
is a wave which is polarized,
whose
electric field is along a particular axis.
Alright,
so the wave is going into the
blackboard,
its
polarization is along some axis
which we label theta.
Plane polarization.
That's only one parameter.
Incidentally,
it's not the same as this theta here.
That's only one parameter.
That polarization
could lie along any direction,
but if it's a plane polarized wave,
it then has a
one parameter family of them,
corresponding simply to the
direction of the electric field,
the direction of the electric field theta.
Now,
if I combine two waves
with a single wave,
with two different polarizations,
and the electric fields
are in phase with each other,
for example,
they're both cosines,
we add
then,
if the
electric fields are in phase
with each other,
it just gives
you a polarization in a different direction.
But if the
two directions
of polarization are out of phase
with respect to each other,
then
the electric field can sweep out a circle,
but it can also sweep out
an ellipse.
For example,
here's a wave that sweeps out an ellipse.
The x component of the electric
field is equal to
cosine of
x minus ct,
and if I take
ey equal
to sine of x minus ct,
then
if I stand,
let's say,
at
x equals 0,
and watch what's happening,
the electric field moves on a circle.
That's circularly polarized light.
But if I take ey to be one half
of that,
now,
the electric field in the y
direction
only grows to half the size
of its maximum
in the x direction.
I don't think I drew that well.
That becomes elliptical polarization.
It's elliptical
polarization,
but it's
described by a major and minor axis,
the major axis
in this case being along the x axis.
We can consider rotated
versions of that.
We can imagine combining electric
fields together in such a way as to create
elliptical polarization
along an arbitrary axis,
in other words,
with the major axis
being along any axis,
that's one variable,
the angle of the
major axis,
and the other
variable being the eccentricity
of the ellipse,
the ratio,
the aspect ratio
of the small diameter
to the large diameter.
That is the other
parameter.
So there are two parameters describing
the polarization.
One is the angle of the major axis,
and the other is the
eccentricity of the ellipse.
Two real parameters.
Now,
there are some special cases.
When the eccentricity goes to zero,
it becomes plain
eccentricity goes to zero
means it collapses to an infinitely thin
ellipse.
Then it becomes plain polarized.
In the limit that the eccentricity goes,
I suppose you would say to one,
then it becomes
circularly polarized,
and in that situation,
theta doesn't
matter anymore.
For a perfect circularly polarized
photon,
there's no special
axis for the major axis.
But in general,
in the arbitrary
situation,
in the generic situation,
two parameters,
two real parameters to describe
the polarization of a photon,
and so it's not so surprising
that we found two real
parameters describing the state of a
photon.
Somehow
these two real parameters
are in one-to-one correspondence.
Some functions of them are the
eccentricity of the ellipse
and the rotational
axis of the ellipse.
Not the rotational axis,
the long axis of the ellipse.
I'm not going to tell you how to...
Shall I tell you how to find out
which is which?
Okay.
I'll tell you what you can do.
Yeah.
You talked about the two parameters
that are also positive and negative.
Say it again.
There's also the positive and negative
locations of the polarization.
That's...
It's still corresponds to two...
Actually,
yeah.
Okay,
good.
Alright.
So there's one parameter
which corresponds to the eccentricity
of the ellipse.
It starts
at circular polarization and it starts to
squash down.
And it goes to zero.
If you go past zero,
does that
go right past zero?
Then the polarization changes...
The polarization goes in the other direction.
In other words,
if this is
rotating this way,
and we
squeeze it and squeeze it and squeeze it
until the lower part of the ellipse
passes the upper part of the ellipse,
then it rotates the other way.
So,
the two
parameters are enough
to describe
both polarizations.
When some
number goes negative,
it describes the other
polarization.
Yeah,
right.
You can think of it as negative eccentricity.
Right.
But supposing,
for example,
I
wanted to find the direction of the
major axis.
Well,
here's what I suspect.
I could ask the question,
what is the probability that if I measure
the linear polarization along
an axis theta,
that I'll get
plus one or minus one?
So let me first ask,
given this circular polarization
here,
and in fact
I better change the
name of this angle here.
I'm going to call it phi.
Now,
let's
take a
linear polarized photon.
Or let's take a state
of linear polarization.
As this one here.
That was described by
cosine theta
sine theta.
And now let's
ask,
supposing we start
with this photon,
and instead
of measuring the circular polarization
or the elliptical polarization,
let's measure
the linear polarization along the axis theta.
That means put a
polarizer,
a linear polarizer
along the direction theta,
and see
what the probability that you go
through is.
What's the probability that
it's polarized along the theta axis?
Well,
it's just the
inner product
of the state of the photon
with the eigenstate
describing a particular polarization
squared.
So the probability that this photon
is
that this
elliptically polarized photon
is measured
along the theta axis,
if I were to
measure the plane
polarization,
what is
that going to be?
It's going to be the
inner product of this
squared.
Let's write
down that inner product.
It's cosine theta times a
let's call this,
let's see,
we call
this theta
and this
psi.
Okay,
so what is
psi theta?
Inner product of
psi with theta.
Psi with theta
it's a
times cosine theta
plus
square root
of one minus a squared
e to the i theta
no,
e to the i phi
times sine theta
Do I have it right?
Doesn't one of them have to be
conjugated?
Yeah.
One of them should be
conjugated.
Good.
So,
e to the minus i theta
e to the minus i phi
This is not yet the probability,
let's compute the
probability.
We multiply this by
its complex conjugate.
Do we really want to carry
this out?
I don't really want to carry it out
but I want to tell you what
you do with it when you find it.
When you find it
you will then know the probability
that this particular
photon is polarized along
the theta axis.
Now,
how do we find the major axis
associated with psi?
We maximize
the probability
with respect to theta.
We look for the direction
theta which maximizes
the probability
that this photon
lies along this direction.
So what we would do
is to multiply this by its complex
conjugate.
That's too hard for me.
I don't feel like doing that.
Do I feel like doing it?
No,
definitely not.
Multiply this by its complex conjugate
homework assignment.
Multiply this by its complex conjugate.
Think of phi as fixed.
Phi is the fixed parameter
associated with this photon
and we're going to adjust this axis
until we maximize
until we have the best fit
until the linear polarization
maximizes
the probability
maximizes the overlap
with this elliptical polarization
here.
Maximizes the inner product
or the square of the inner product.
That will tell you
what the
major axis of psi is.
It's more or less intuitively clear
that whatever the major axis
of psi is,
in other words
if it corresponds to a
elliptical polarization
in this direction,
and then we measure
the
linear polarization in different
directions
that the
probability will be maximized
when the linear polarization
matches the
the diameter of the
the major diameter of the ellipse.
Alright,
so you think of
think of phi as fixed,
square this
and maximize it
with respect to theta.
In other words,
differentiate with respect to theta
and find the place where it's maximum.
That will tell you the angle
of the major axis.
The eccentricity
you can find in the
you can
uh
Okay,
the eccentricity
would have to do with the difference
of the probability that
the photon lied along that direction
or along that direction.
In other words
uh
if you find
that there's a very high probability
that this elliptic
photon is polarized
along some linear direction,
that will mean the eccentricity is small
and the
difference between
the two probabilities is some measure
of the uh
asymmetry of the ellipse.
I didn't really mean to get into this
I just really only wanted to point out
to you that there are two parameters
that govern the physics
of a particular state vector
and that those two parameters
are in one-to-one correspondence
with the two parameters associated
with the angle and eccentricity
of the uh
of the ellipse.
Yeah?
It seems like then the sense
counterclockwise or clockwise
is missing.
Say that again.
Well you have two parameters.
You have orientation and eccentricity
but what seems to be missing is
the sense of whether it's
clockwise or counterclockwise.
Okay,
well somebody just asked me that
and I thought I answered it,
but let me go through it again.
The eccentricity
is
a parameter
which can be negative or positive.
You start with an ellipse
which looks like this which is rotating
in this direction here.
Well let's start with a circle.
Circularly polarized
is not eccentric at all.
It goes in this direction.
Let's draw an axis in there.
It doesn't matter which axis,
any axis in there.
And now start changing the eccentricity
by squeezing the ellipse.
We squeeze the ellipse
and it goes down to here.
Alright.
Now eccentricity you would think
ends at the point where it's
linearly polarized.
At that point the eccentricity
goes to zero.
I think it's
counted as zero.
The eccentricity becomes zero
when it collapses to a line.
But you can keep going.
You can make the eccentricity negative.
When it goes negative these two
pass each other.
The upper branch here which is
moving from the bottom to the top
becomes the lower branch
and the lower branch becomes the upper branch.
So the point is
the real parameters,
you vary the two
real parameters here over their entire
range,
positive and negative,
you pick up both
senses of polarization as well as angle
and...
Okay?
Good.
Alright.
Alright,
now our next
step
is to understand how
the states
change with time.
That's the big next step.
How do they change with time?
The analog...
Oops,
no.
The analog of the classical
question,
if we
start with a space of states
which is just a bunch of points,
how do you
move from one to the next?
Now with just a set of discrete
points,
you would have to imagine
a kind of stroboscopic
time evolution where
you would divide time into little
intervals and at each
instant,
or at each interval,
make a jump from one state to the next.
There would be no way to do this continuously.
In quantum mechanics,
you can have a finite dimensional
vector space.
For example,
just the
two directions of polarization,
but you can
have continuous time evolution.
And the continuous time evolution goes
through the fact that you have sort of
continuous interpolations between
states.
You have not
only one zero
and zero one,
but you have continuous interpolations
between them.
For example,
the polarization vector
could rotate with time.
That would not
be circular polarization.
The linear polarization
could rotate with time.
That's a possible motion of the
polarization of a photon with time.
And although any time
you measure the polarization along the axis,
you only get one of two answers,
as if it were a coin,
plus or
minus,
nevertheless
the time evolution of it can be completely
continuous and does not
require that you think stroboscopically.
So quantum mechanics can
have discreteness of
possibilities and still have
evolution which is
continuous.
The question
is how do we describe the evolution
of quantum systems?
Now,
let's go back for a moment
to the evolution of classical systems.
When a classical
system evolves,
it's
just a permutation of the states.
The relationship between
states stays the same.
Now there's
only one relationship between
states in classical physics.
Well,
states I now mean this
discrete system.
Heads and
tails or
dice or whatever.
Some finite number of states.
That's all there are.
There's just a finite number of states.
There's only one relationship
between them that makes any
sense.
They're either the same
state or they're different.
That's the only
relationship between them.
They're the same or they're different.
If they're different,
we call them different.
If they're the same,
we call them the same.
One of the
features of classical physics
is a conservation
law that says that
with time,
different states
will maintain
their differences.
In other words,
it will not happen
that two different states,
let's call it A over
here and B over here,
will both evolve to C.
If they both evolve to C,
then you would lose the
distinction between the starting point.
If they both
went to C,
for example,
if our rule
of evolution for dice
was that five
goes to three
and two goes to three
and then a whole bunch of other ones here,
then if we arrived at three,
we wouldn't
know if we came from five or two.
That's not allowed in classical
physics.
Evolution,
which sort of
loses distinctions.
So if two states
start different and they evolve
with time,
they stay different.
That's the basic
conservation of relationships
between states.
The corresponding
thing in quantum mechanics
is very,
very similar.
The relationship
between states is made
and maintained with time.
What is the relationship between two states?
You can say they're
different or they're the same.
So supposing I have
two states,
let's call
them A and B again.
Of course,
what it means for them
to be the same is that A equals B.
They are the same vector.
What does it mean
for them to be different?
Well,
now we have to decide
exactly what we mean.
Yeah,
we could put dot here.
Fine.
We could
put dot there.
It would mean that
they are equal up to a phase.
We could use a stronger form of
equal,
but then
remember that we're not
really interested in
distinctions which are only distinctions
of phase.
But we could
put a dot there if we like.
But what is the concept of two states being
different?
Well,
it could just be
A equals not B,
but you could
have two vectors,
for example,
two polarization states,
one which is polarized horizontally
and one which is polarized
almost horizontally.
If we were to take that
photon which was polarized
almost horizontally and
measure its horizontal polarization,
we might in fact discover that
it was horizontally polarized.
In other words,
it might go through the
horizontal polarizer.
There's only one state which
is absolutely forbidden from going
through that horizontal polarizer
and for which we could
definitively say that
the photon was
different than the horizontally
polarized photon.
And it's the vertically
The vertically polarized
photon will not go through the polarizer.
So,
we could say
that the vertically polarized
photon is orthogonal
to the horizontally polarized
photon.
The orthogonality
relationship is the
relationship which is the analog
of classically different.
Measurably different than a single
experiment that you can tell
with one experiment that
it is one thing and not
the other.
So that's the
relationship that we would like
to express,
the relationship
of different,
and that's
the fact that that relationship
is that bA is equal to zero.
Or,
bA is equal to
one,
which would
say they were the same.
More generally,
the relationship between
two states is the overlap
between them.
It tells you how
similar they are.
If there's an overlap between
states,
it means that there's a finite
probability that if you
choose to measure one thing,
you'll get...
you know what the point is.
If aB is not
equal to zero,
but for example
close to one,
then the two states are quite a bit alike,
and if you measure some
observable which would distinguish them,
well,
they simply won't
be well distinguished.
So,
the important
relationship between states is
inner product.
If it's zero,
they're different.
If it's one,
they're the same.
Remember that
they are normalized states.
The only
way that the inner product can be one
is if they're the same.
Alright?
Or the inner product can be zero,
in which case they're orthogonal,
or it can be anything in between.
This is the basic relationship
between states.
The inner product between them.
Now,
just as in
classical mechanics,
distinctions or relationships
between states are maintained with time.
States which are
different stay different as time
evolves.
In quantum
mechanics,
the basic
rule is as a system evolves,
the inner product
between its states stays fixed.
In other words,
as time goes
on,
let's suppose we start
a system with state A,
another identical system
we start with B.
And
A and B have two,
have an inner product
between them.
And we let them
run with time.
A runs to A
prime.
B
runs to B prime.
After a certain amount of time,
the state vector changes.
In precise analogy with
the way the state might move around
in the space of
states in classical
reasoning,
A goes to A prime.
A
prime need not be orthogonal to A,
it'll just go to something else,
A prime.
And at the same time,
B,
if we started the system with B,
it would go to B prime.
The basic
conservation of information
idea,
the basic
conservation of distinctions
or relationships between states
simply says
that the inner product of B prime
with A prime
is the same as
the inner product of B with A.
In other words,
for example,
if A and B are the same state,
then after they
evolve,
A prime and B prime
will be the same.
If A and B are orthogonal,
and you run them for a while,
then the
result will remain orthogonal.
That's the basic assumption of
time evolution in quantum mechanics,
that the relationships
between states stays fixed with time.
Now,
you can,
can we
derive that?
No,
I don't think we can derive it.
It's an observed fact,
but it comes together
with a lot of
connections,
a lot of connections with
things that you do know,
such as
energy conservation.
So,
for the moment,
let's just take it as a given
that relationships between
states
are maintained with time.
And try to figure out what that
means.
Yeah?
You said that if you measure
the,
um,
the vertical photocomb going to a
horizontal photocomb,
it gets zero.
And therefore you know that it's different.
But how do you know that that is
a 45 degree photocomb
that just happens to
return to zero at that time?
Oh,
you don't.
You don't know.
The point is
that if you have,
if you have made a
photon which is horizontal,
and you then send it to a vertical
polarizer,
you know with certainty
that it will be balanced.
Every time you do it,
you can make a whole bunch of horizontally
polarized photons.
Every one
of them won't get through.
Okay,
and then one other related
question.
What about the uncertainty
when you create a horizontal photon
that,
or uncertainty
comes to me,
I don't think it would be difficult
to create a horizontal photon that's
back and forth long,
but won't go through
a vertical polarizer.
It seems always small,
finite,
the possibility of it going through
to a uncertainty principle.
Well the uncertainty principle doesn't
say that there's any
any necessary
uncertainty in the direction
of polarization of a photon.
The direction of
polarization of a photon is just one thing.
It usually takes
two things to define an uncertainty
relation.
But
you
can
polarize a photon as accurately
as you like if you can
hold your polarizer still enough
and your polarizer is perfectly
aligned.
So
there's no restriction
on
fixing
the polarization along a given axis.
What you can't do
is have the polarization be known
along two different axes.
There's no state in which
the photon is known to be able to go
through a polarization in this direction
and in this direction.
So it's an uncertainty between
polarizations in different
directions.
Not an uncertainty
in your ability to polarize
a photon along a given axis.
Alright,
so in order
to implement this idea,
well let's just discuss it a little
bit more.
Roughly speaking what it says,
if we don't
worry too much about the complex
aspects of complex vector spaces,
and we just think of ordinary
vector spaces,
let's say in three dimensions,
then
we can imagine that with
time,
the state vector
of a system,
this could represent the state
vector of a system,
it
moves with time.
It moves around with time,
just
so that the system evolves.
Properties of the system change with time.
But it evolves
in such a way that if two
states are orthogonal to
each other to begin with,
they stay orthogonal to each other.
It's a kind of
rotation of the space of
states which keeps angles
fixed.
Angles between
vectors stay fixed.
That's the assumption here.
Angles between vectors in the space of
states stay fixed and don't vary
with time,
although the vectors
themselves may vary with time.
So,
that's the idea that we want to implement.
To implement it,
we need some more mathematics.
We need the mathematics of unitary operators.
And we haven't discussed that yet,
so when we come back from a five minute break,
we'll discuss
a little more about Hermitian,
and then unitary operators.
Unitary operators are the operators
which preserve relationships
between the two states.
So,
let's take a break for five minutes.
Okay,
let's get started.
Now,
we need to
get some mathematical concepts.
So,
some of this is a little bit
repeat,
but let's go through it anyway.
Let's suppose we have a
linear operator
which is defined to act on
the vector space of kets.
Thus far,
we have really defined
linear operators as
unitary operators.
Let's call it L,
a linear operator.
Put a little hat on it to indicate
that it's a linear operator.
And it's defined through its action
on ket vectors.
So,
given an A,
the linear operator acts on it
to give another vector,
which I've called C.
Now,
you may wonder what happened to B.
Well,
B will come back,
but for the moment,
it's on it,
and it will give you some C.
That's a linear operator.
Well,
that's an operation.
The fact that it's linear entails
certain conditions,
that it acts on the sum of vectors
to give back sums,
and so forth and so on.
I won't go through that again.
But,
given a linear operator
which is defined in terms of its action
on kets,
we can also
define its action on
bra vectors in the following way.
I wish to define
now,
this is definition
but it's obviously a neat definition.
I wish to define
the operation of L
on a bra vector,
B.
So,
L acts on B
and it gives us some new bra vector.
That's the assumption.
When L acts on B,
it gives a new bra vector.
How am I going to find that bra vector?
Let's put in here a basis of vectors
and sum over N.
According to the principle
that when you sum over N
that you get the identity
sum on N
of N,
N
is the
identity operator.
I haven't done anything.
This is
L on B.
Okay?
But now,
I can define
this object over here
oops,
let's see,
this object over here
in the obvious way.
Let L act
to the right on a ket vector.
We know how L acts on every
ket vector.
That's implicit
in the definition of a linear operator
that we know how it acts on any
ket vector.
So,
instead of
allowing L to act on the bra vector
to the left,
interpret
this symbol as L acting
on the ket vector to the right
and then taking the inner product with B.
We can define this matrix element.
It's called a matrix element.
It's a sandwich
in this case with two different
kinds of bread,
N and B
with the bologna in between
being the linear operator L.
And we define it
even though we're imagining
that L is acting to the left
let's nevertheless define a single
symbol by
defining this by defining L acts
to the right on N and then
we take the inner product with B.
That gives us a definition
of
a
L acting on a bra vector.
You're assuming L is her
mission?
No,
not yet.
not particularly.
L is not her mission,
or can be
her mission,
but it's not.
But it's not necessarily.
You assume associativity?
Let's see.
Have I assumed associativity?
I always
assume associativity.
B on L.
Yeah,
yeah,
that's right.
Yeah,
We've assumed.
Now this is
definition,
if you like.
This is definition,
but it's clearly a
neat definition,
which
will allow us to do all sorts
of manipulations in a sort of
mechanical way without thinking very hard.
That's the
purpose of a good notation.
To not have to think
very hard when you use it and to use it
by inspection.
Alright,
so this is
the definition.
The answer is a bra vector.
These are numbers.
These are all numbers,
and they multiply
bra vectors in.
And so the result is a bra vector.
And this then defines for us
how the same operator
which was defined to act to the
right on ket vectors
acts to the left on bra vectors.
So,
linear operators can act either way.
Either to the left or
to the right.
And the notation has purposefully
been made so that
if we have a sandwich
I'm giving up on this one.
If we have a sandwich
B
L hat A
we can interpret this
in one of two ways.
The inner product of B
with
let's put a big bracket around it
to compile the associativity.
L hat acting
on A
or
as L hat
acting to the left on B
and then
inner product with A.
That's the
point of this particular
construction.
It doesn't matter
whether we think of
L hat acting on A
and then inner product with B
or L hat acting on B
and then inner product with A.
Let's define the Hermitian conjugate
of an operator L.
Supposing L is some
linear operator
such that
when it acts on any vector A
it gives us
a vector that I'll call C.
This is a correspondence.
It's a mapping
of vectors into vectors.
Starting with an A
you get a C and L
is thought of as a mapping.
There's a corresponding
mapping
which maps bra vectors.
Some operator
if L maps
A to C
then there's some object
which I'm going to call L
dagger or
the Hermitian conjugate of L
which acts the same way
x and y
except among bra vectors.
So if there's a correspondence
between every ket vector and a bra vector
then I can also
look for a correspondence
between operators
so that given an operator L
which takes A to C
there must be some other
operator which
acts to the left on bra vectors
which induces a kind of parallel
mapping.
Mapping among the bra vectors
which is the image
of the mapping among the ket vectors.
What's the connection
between L dagger
this is also an operator
what's the connection
between this operator
and this operator?
They're not the same necessarily.
In fact they're kind of complex
conjugates of each other.
This dagger here which is called
Hermitian conjugate
is a kind of complex conjugation.
It's not just simple conjugation
it's a little more than that.
Since the bra vector A
is the complex conjugate of the ket vector A
and the bra vector C
is the complex conjugate of the ket vector C
you wouldn't be too far off
if you were to say somehow
this Hermitian conjugation
is representing
some form of complex conjugation
and in fact it is.
Let's see if we can find the relationship
between L
and L dagger.
To do that let's take the
inner product of the topical
equation with B.
So here's our equation.
Now we're going to come over to here
take the inner product B
L hat A
and what is that?
That's B C
I've just
taken some arbitrary vector B
any vector B
and sandwiched or taken the inner product
of both sides of this equation
with B.
Now let's take
the inner product of this equation
not with the bra vector B
but with the ket vector B.
That says that A
L hat dagger.
There's too many symbols
I really don't need that hat do I?
There's really not much lost
if I were to leave the hats off the operators
but let's leave them.
B
I've now taken the inner product of this
side with the ket vector B
and that's equal to
C
B
Now what's the connection
between the two right hand sides here?
They're complex
conjugates of each other.
If I take the inner product of two vectors
but then I take them in the opposite order
invert bra to ket and
ket to bra,
then these are complex
conjugates of each other.
So these two are complex conjugates
and it follows that these two are complex conjugates
so now we can write down
one of the connections between
an operator and its Hermitian conjugate
and here it is right here
that every matrix element
of the original
operator L
is related
or is equal to
the complex conjugate of the
Hermitian conjugate but with the
bra's and the ket's interchanged.
In other words
to go from an operator to its
Hermitian conjugate
you interchange bra's and ket's
and you complex conjugate.
Now
let's
consider
a useful defining
a useful way
to
define complex conjugation now
we can define it in terms of
a basis,
supposing we have a
basis of vectors
and we consider the inner products
N L
conjugate M
if we know all of these
if we know all of the matrix
elements
matrix elements in a basis
and we can call these things
L N M
if we know all of these matrix
elements then we know everything
there is to know about the operator
are you assuming finite dimension?
for the moment let's assume
finite dimension
I am assuming finite dimension
but everything I say also applies
to the infinite dimensional case
so
you can think of
taking the limit where the
dimension of the vector space gets very very big
okay
what's that?
did you want a dagger on the right diagram?
thank you
I do
right
that is equal to
this is yet to be defined
we assume that we know
the matrix elements of L
but this is equal to
the complex conjugate
of the matrix element of L
with the bras and the kets interchanged
and complex conjugated
that's what this says over here
interchange bras and kets
and complex conjugate
alright
so we now know that
we can now write an equation
that well this of course is equal to
L M N
so here is the rule
if you have an operator represented
as a matrix L M N
wait
star
yes
thank you
right
alright so if you have an operator L M N
and what you want
is the matrix elements of the conjugate operator
the Hermitian conjugate
L N M
then all you do
is take the original operator
interchange
rows and columns
which is the same as interchanging bras and kets
and complex conjugate
in terms of matrices
what this means
is that if you have
a matrix
L 1 1
L 1 2
L 1 3 dot dot dot
L 2 1
L 2 2
L 2 3 dot dot dot
L 3 1
L 3 2
L 3 3 dot dot dot
this is the matrix
representing the operator L
then the matrix representing
the operator L dagger
Hermitian conjugate
you interchange
bras and kets that's the same as
interchanging rows and columns
and it's also the same as
reflecting the matrix
about the diagonal
interchange L 1 2 with L 2 1
interchange L 3 1
with L 1 3
that's reflecting it and at the same
time complex conjugate
so the matrix
elements of L dagger
are L 1 1
conjugate but instead of
putting L 1 2 conjugate
we'll put L 2 1
conjugate L 3 1
conjugate
and down here
L 2 1 conjugate
L 2 2 conjugate
L 2 3 conjugate
so notice what I've done
I've interchanged the rows and the columns
and complex conjugated
I didn't do it right
yup yup yup yup
and what's next
thank you
right
so take each one of these
interchange rows and columns
and complex conjugate
and that's the Hermitian conjugate operator
it
can be thought of as a kind of
complex conjugation
but notice that it also involves this
inversion of rows and columns
inverting rows and columns is called
transposing
so transpose and complex conjugate
combine together to form
Hermitian conjugate
easy idea not very hard
now the class of operators which are
their own Hermitian conjugates
are the Hermitian operators
the Hermitian operators are the ones
the special ones
which satisfy L is equal to
L dagger
in terms of matrix elements
first of all it says that the
diagonal matrix elements must be real
it says that L11 must equal L11 star
alright so on the diagonal
if this is to be equal to this
if L is to be equal to L Hermitian conjugate
then it says
L11 equals L11 star
well that just says that L11 is real
likewise for L22
and so forth
so the diagonal matrix
the diagonal elements of a Hermitian matrix
of a Hermitian matrix
are all real
Lii
is real
and then
as far as the off diagonal elements
let's
as far as the off diagonal elements go
they have the property
that if you reflect about the diagonal
they're replaced
the element is replaced by its complex conjugate
so Hermitian operators
this is L21 star
L22 is real
L13 should be L31 star
so that's L31
L13 star
this is L23 star
and so forth
L33 is real
alright so the rule for a Hermitian operator
is that the diagonal elements are real
and the off diagonal elements
the images
the mirror images
are complex conjugates of each other
that's a Hermitian operator
Hermitian operators
remember
I'll just remind you
Hermitian operators have the property
that their expectation values are real
their eigenvalues are real
and their eigenvectors
are real
and their vectors are mutually orthogonal
for different values of the eigenvalue
alright we've gone through that before
Hermitian operators
are the ones which correspond to
observables
well it depends on how many
independent states of a system
there are
again it depends on
what we're studying
we isolate out
as an interesting system
just the polarization of a photon
and don't worry about anything else
the 2x2 matrices
if we want to study a whole photon
then they become infinite dimensional matrices
because we have to take into account
either the position or the momentum of the photon
which can have any value
so in most real quantum mechanical systems
in fact in any real quantum mechanical system
they're really infinite matrices
alright
but infinite matrices
are hard to write on the blackboard
they're a little bit
easy but tedious
you know
so
and it's always the case
that in
or almost always the case
that in practice
we approximate the system
by a finite number of states
to actually do calculations
not always
but in most cases
we approximate
by finite dimensional matrices
okay
so for example
a particle moving on a line
where the particle can be anywhere
well we can approximate
that by a particle which can exist
anywhere in some very very
dense collection of positions
well still we have
an infinite number of points going between
minus infinity and plus infinity
nothing
too bad happens if instead of going
out to infinity we go out to Brooklyn
in this direction and
Hong Kong in this direction
and just make it very big
and so we work with very very large
numerically very very large matrices
as an approximation
to the infinite dimensional case
is
analytical reduction of states
analogous to this
analytic reduction of states I don't know what it means
okay
good so we have the idea of
permission matrices and these are the things
which
define or which are connected with
observables real eigenvalues
real expectation values
and
orthogonal mutually orthogonal
eigenvectors
they are not the things that we identify
with transformations of the
vector space that
preserve relations
remember our goal now is to find
the operations which were our
first
which preserve
relationships between vectors
I don't know I erased
it off the blackboard
so these are not the operations
which correspond
to the preservers
of relations
let's try to define those
oh incidentally let's just check first of all
that our polarization observables
are hermition
we had three of them we had one
which is one minus one zero zero
all right
the only rule is
for them to be hermition
is that the on diagonal
elements should be real
and the off diagonal elements when reflected
should be complex conjugates of each other
this obviously has this property
real on diagonal
and the off diagonals
are in fact complex conjugates of each other
zero being its own complex conjugate
all right
then we had another one which was zero one zero
one one zero
this was
and again
on diagonal elements real
zero is real
off diagonal elements complex conjugates of each other
and the last one
which was
p for circular polarization
that was
minus on
zero
i i zero zero
on diagonal real
off diagonal complex conjugates of each other
okay
so these three are hermition
and satisfy the rules of
being observables
okay
now we come to unitary operators
unitary operators are the ones which preserve relationships
so let's define what that means
yes
yes but it makes good sense
the things that you actually observe and measure
are always real numbers
the objects
whose expectation values are
always real for every vector
that's another way to define the hermitions
it's equivalent
that if you take any pair
of any vector
psi
l psi
if for any psi
is real
then it follows that
l is hermition
now I haven't proved that
but that's it's a couple of lines
it really is very fast
to prove that if l is hermition
then psi l psi is real
and vice versa
that's a fast
simple theorem
so the reality of the expectation value
which makes good sense
for a observable
and also the reality of the eigenvalues
which are the possible values that you can measure
those are
you know
the key signature of things that you actually observe
in the laboratory
I have a question
does the eigenvectors of the operator
have to span the vector space?
the eigenvectors of a hermition operator
span the vector space
that is not generally true
of non-hermition operators
it can be true but it's not necessarily true
but I mean
so an observable
has to have a
complete set of mutually orthogonal eigenvectors
right
now you can have a complete set of eigenvectors
which aren't orthogonal to each other
that can happen
and then the operator would not be
a hermition
or it could fail to
have a complete set of eigenvectors
so I can envision an operator that doesn't span
what's that?
I can envision an operator that doesn't span
yeah you can have
there are operators that don't have any eigenvectors
yeah
oh definitely not
it certainly would not be hermition
since every hermition operator has
a complete set of eigenvectors
a complete
orthonormal
an equivalent definition of hermition
is that it has a complete
orthonormal
collection of eigenvectors
with real eigenvalues
right
that's an equivalent definition
but now we're interested not in observables
but in transformations of the vector space
the transformations could
correspond to a number of things
they could define the way the system evolves with time
how vectors transform into other vectors
under time evolution
it could correspond to symmetries
what are the vectors
for example
here's an example
uh
given a polarization vector
given a polarization state
theta
we can imagine symmetry operations
which rotate
the plane of the polarization
we could say
supposing we're interested now in an operation
which rotates the polarization vector
by a certain angle
right
and we're interested in a vector
that uh
that is also a transformation on the space of states
just the rotation of the polarization vector
there's all kinds of transformations we could do
and we're interested in those transformations
which preserve the relationships between the vectors
so let's see if we can't
get a handle on that idea
take any two vectors in the vector space
a and b
our favorite two vectors again
let's take their inner product
a b
and we can see
in some sense that defines the
relationship between the two vectors
the degree to which they're similar or not similar
zero
they're orthogonal
they're as dissimilar as possible
one
and they're equal
as similar as possible
now
uh
let's imagine a transformation
which can act on any vector
let's call it u
and we can call it a vector
u stands for unitary but for the moment
we don't even know what that means
such that u on a
is equal to a prime
for every a there's an a prime
obtained by
acting with some
linear operator called u
alright
of course we can't
I don't know why I wrote a
here I think I should have written b
b prime
b and b prime are just labels
they could run over
any vector in the vector space
now the same
operation
has an image
among the bra vectors
remember if an operation takes
place among the ket vectors
the image of it involves
the Hermitian conjugate
so if this is true
then
the same
operation except when
interpreted in terms of bra vectors
will involve u dagger
alright so let me write this
correctly
supposing u
takes b
to b prime
and supposing
u takes a
to a prime
what does u do
excuse me
then it follows
that
a u dagger
is equal
to bra vector a prime
that's the definition of the
Hermitian conjugate
if u on a equals a prime
then u dagger on bra vector a
equals bra vector a prime
ok
now let's take
and let's consider
the relationship between
a b and a prime b prime
and let's require
them to be equal
in other words whatever u does
it doesn't disturb the relationship
between vectors
it hits a and gives a prime
it hits b and gives b prime
but it doesn't disturb
the relationship meaning
that the inner product of the
outputs is the same as the
inner product of the inputs
so what does that say let's just write it down
substituting for a prime
u dagger a
this is equal to
a
u dagger
that's a prime but then b prime
is u times b
ok
simply stated
b prime has been
replaced by u times b
a prime has been replaced
by u dagger times a
but this should be true
let's get rid of the intermediate
step here
let's get rid of this
here is what we require
of the transformation u
if u preserves relationships
then for any pair of vectors
a and b
a u dagger u b
should be equal to a b
but if a thing like this is true
for any pair of vectors
if for any vectors
any a and b
sticking an operator in between them
does nothing at all
then it follows
this is a theorem
that u dagger u
must be the identity operator
if you have some operator
that when you sandwich it
between any two vectors
gives you back the in it product
without the operator
then that operator is the unit operator
that's a theorem
that's easy to prove again
that if a u dagger u times b
is equal to a b
not just for one particular pair of vectors
but for any vectors
in the vector space
then it follows that u dagger u is
the identity operator
it does not say that u is the identity operator
it says u dagger times u
is the identity operator
in other words
u dagger undoes
whatever u does
if you multiply it by u dagger
it undoes it
that says that u dagger is the inverse of u
u dagger times u is one
says that u dagger is the inverse operator of u
another way to write the same thing
is that u dagger
is the inverse of u
meaning just the operator
of u
is the operator
that undoes whatever u does
operators with this property
that u dagger times u
the identity operator
those are called unitary
they are not themselves
identity operators
they can shift the vectors around
but they shift them around in a way
which preserves the relationships
that's the unitary operators
all operators
which preserve relationships
are unitary
so
um
yeah
are you using relationships in any broader sense
or just preserving them or not?
that's all I mean by it
mathematically that's what I mean by it
physically of course it means
it preserves
the
if you like we can call this
the square of this
we can call it the probability
of b then a
I'm choosing shorthand
for something much more complicated
if b then a
that the relationship
is preserved
for example with time
if u represents the time evolution of a system
so okay
so this is the class of unitary operators
u dagger u is equal to one
and u is equal to one
so we have only a couple of minutes
so I'm going to tell you now
some of the properties of unitary operators
which uh
some of which we will prove
some of which you can find in books
and some of which are obvious
first of all
in fact
I'm just going to tell you the properties
I'm not going to justify them right now
unitary operators have one feature
in common with hermitian operators
they also have
complete orthonormal
sets of eigenvectors
so there's a complete
there exists for each unitary
a complete basis n
such that u on n
gives an eigenvalue
lambda n times n
but the eigenvalues
are definitely not real
or they can be real
but in general they're certainly not
in general real numbers
the lambdas do have a special property
let's see if we can figure out
what that property is
if u has a complete set of eigenvectors
what can we say about the eigenvalues
so let's use the fact
oh
uh
let's see
I think I'm running
I think we'll quit at this point
but let's say
let's just quit let's stop now
let's stop now and next week
we will consider the properties of unitaries
and then we're going to
go into the issue of hamiltonians
and how systems change with time
systems change with time
by unitary transformation
that's the message
the unitary operators are the things
which take you from one time step to another
and I think we've had enough
I've had enough for tonight
I think we've had enough for tonight
the preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University
please visit us at
stanford.edu