This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Now,
how much people after Michelson-Morley really,
there were all kinds
of explanations of Michelson-Morley experiment.
Ether drift,
that the ether was being swept
along with the earth and so forth.
Or Lorentz contraction.
Yeah,
I mean,
Lorentz contraction,
of course,
was correct.
But the way Lorentz thought about it
is things moving relative to the ether
somehow got squeezed by the ether.
Well,
I suppose you could always describe it that way,
but it wasn't the right way that
Einstein thought about it in the end.
So they had these mechanistic descriptions.
They had these mechanistic attempts at explanations,
which were not the real form.
They were the far-reaching principle that Einstein came to.
So I don't know how much
the Michelson-Morley experiment really shook the foundations,
but it certainly was a signal
that there was something going on
that was different than what they expected.
So Michelson-Morley.
And does everybody know what the problem with radiation was?
The problem with black body radiation?
The ultraviolet.
The ultraviolet catastrophe.
Well,
if not,
I'll explain it right now.
It was a conflict.
It was a conflict between two sets of principles.
One principle was the wave theory of light.
And the wave theory of
light said that light could come,
light,
electromagnetic radiation,
could come in any wavelength,
whatever.
Each wavelength behaved like a harmonic oscillator.
The mathematics of a wave of a given wavelength,
is just the mathematics of an oscillation.
So,
and this was understood long
before the quantum mechanics of oscillations.
Was understood in the late 19th century,
that the mechanics of light,
the mechanics of,
not just light,
any kind of waves,
that each wave was basically a harmonic oscillator.
Each wavelength of waves.
That was number one.
The other thing,
that it was in conflict with,
was the principle of statistical mechanics.
According to the principles of statistical mechanics,
there's something called the equi partition of energy.
That,
if you have a collection of harmonic oscillators,
and it doesn't matter what
the frequency of the oscillators are.
There are many,
many different oscillators,
with different frequencies.
When they come into thermal equilibrium,
each one has the same amount of energy,
basically it said that the energy of an oscillation,
is equal to Boltzmann's constant times the temperature,
quite independently of what the
frequency of the oscillator is.
Alright,
so now you have light in a cavity,
or electromagnetic radiation in a cavity.
And in that cavity you can
have waves bouncing back and forth.
You can't have waves which of course
are longer than the size of the cavity.
They won't fit into the cavity.
But you can have waves of arbitrary
wavelength that will fit into the cavity.
Very small wavelengths.
Wavelengths like that,
that just barely fit into the cavity.
And every single wavelength
corresponds to a harmonic oscillator,
according to the principles of statistical mechanics.
According to the principles of Boltzmann,
and Maxwell,
and Gibbs,
and the other people who invented statistical mechanics,
every one of these oscillations should
have exactly the same amount of energy.
Well,
that just means an infinite amount of energy,
because there's an infinite number
of different kinds of waves
that can be supported inside the cavity.
Well,
that's a disaster.
If you bring the cavity to thermal equilibrium,
and it has an infinite
number of different kinds of oscillations,
each with the same energy,
then there's an infinite amount of energy in the cavity,
and it would simply melt,
and it would just destroy the cavity,
or vaporize the cavity,
or destroy the cavity in one way or another.
The result is something was deeply wrong.
Now,
how wrong,
people didn't really know.
They thought maybe there was something wrong
with the way the atoms emitted radiation.
For some reason,
they didn't emit very high frequency radiation.
Nobody really knew.
Planck did not recognize.
Planck was not the one who recognized.
He did write down,
E equals h nu.
No,
he wrote down,
E equals n times h nu.
He did say that energy comes in discrete multiples
of a certain constant times the frequency of oscillators,
and it comes in multiples of that.
He did write that down.
But he was not thinking
about the radiation in the cavity.
His theory was that the oscillators in the walls
the walls of the cavity,
the things which emitted the radiation,
that those things had frequencies which
were integer multiples of h nu.
That was his theory,
and therefore could only emit radiation of
integer multiples of E equals h nu.
He didn't have a correct
theory of what was going on.
He wrote this equation down,
but the equation didn't apply
to the radiation in the cavity,
it applied to the things in the walls,
according to Planck.
He managed to fit the
curves of blackbody radiation correctly.
He managed to reproduce the spectrum of blackbody radiation,
but by arguments which really didn't make sense.
The main thing in the argument is that
there was a parameter h in the problem.
The way we understand it now is to say
you simply can't have in each one of these oscillations,
you can't have less than one quantum.
If each quantum,
if each oscillator has the same energy,
and you take oscillators which have very,
very high frequency,
then they will have to have less than one quantum.
In other words,
if E equals kT,
and kT is a certain number,
temperature,
Boltzmann's constant is just a numerical constant,
whatever the temperature is,
then there will be frequencies which are so large
that this energy is less than one quantum,
one quantum of energy.
According to classical physics,
no problem.
You can have an oscillator with any amount of energy.
According to quantum mechanics,
you cannot have less than
one quantum of worth of energy.
Less than one quantum means no quanta.
And so Einstein's idea was that
the waves inside the cavity were quantized,
and all those waves which had frequencies so large,
or wavelengths so small,
that h knew exceeded kT,
they just wouldn't be there.
That was Einstein's idea.
They wouldn't be there because you
couldn't have less than one frequency.
So,
you could have less than one photon for each oscillator.
now at first,
of course,
people did not believe Einstein,
that light was composed of particles,
that it was composed of discrete quanta.
For about 20 years,
a little bit less than 20 years,
for about 18 years,
people,
Einstein was very famous,
they all agreed he had done something wonderful
when he had said that the radiation
inside the cavity had E equals h nu,
but yet they didn't believe it.
They thought there was going to
be some way to wiggle out,
and somehow the wave theory of
light would wind up being correct.
They didn't believe it.
They didn't believe it until experiments were done
where light shines off atoms,
gives the atom a kick,
and radiation goes off in other directions.
This is the Compton effect.
The Compton effect of scattering
of light by charged particles,
and it was discovered that the energies and the angles
exactly conformed to what you would expect
from the scattering of particles.
Particles come in,
particles go out,
and if you use energy and momentum conservation,
then you can predict various
things about the angles and energy
that the radiation goes off in.
Those things did not follow just from wave theory.
They followed from wave theory,
supplemented with the energy,
with the idea that the radiation comes in discrete packets,
and when those experiments were done,
it basically took 18 years for people
to buy into the theory of photons,
and within weeks,
literally within weeks,
or maybe it was months,
I'm not sure,
everybody agreed light is made out of photons.
So it's one of these critical
things that happens all of a sudden,
and you wonder why it took so long,
but a certain particular experiment sharply,
sharply separated the time when people believed in photons
until they didn't.
By that time,
of course,
everybody knew that the foundations
of classical mechanics were wrong when it came to atoms,
but they didn't want to believe that
the wave theory of light was wrong.
Of course,
the wave theory of light was not wrong,
it was just sort of incomplete.
Didn't the photoelectric effect show that
there were photons in the wave?
Yeah,
you would think that the
photoelectric effect would have been enough,
but psychologically it was not enough.
Right,
exactly.
I've got a candidate date of 1915,
when Bohr explained the hydrogen atom.
It was 1913.
13,
using Planck's constant.
Yeah,
yeah,
when he reproduced the Rydberg constant,
the levels of,
yeah,
that was certainly a very critical time,
but that was not enough for them to believe
that they were going to be
able to buy into the photon theory.
So the photon theory of
light they didn't buy into yet.
They did recognize that something radically different
was governing the motion of atoms and electrons in atoms
than classical mechanics,
and that's absolutely right.
I mean,
Bohr's explanation of atomic levels was a sharp transition.
So there were several sharp transitions,
but the whole thing stretched
itself out over about 20 years,
from 19,
well,
25 years,
from 1900,
Planck's discovery of the Planck constant,
to basically 1926,
27,
something like that,
with,
well,
26,
which was Schrödinger,
Heisenberg,
and a little bit later,
Dirac,
putting the elements together.
It was Einstein,
it was Einstein who understood most clearly
and said it most forcefully,
very early,
I'm not sure exactly what year,
that whatever's going on,
because of this new quantum structure,
one had to suppose that
nature was fundamentally not deterministic.
He was the one who
said that the emission of radiation,
he realized,
was a spontaneous,
he spoke about spontaneous emission of photons
from atoms and from other things,
and he understood that it was not deterministic,
that it was essentially probabilistic,
and it was he who first said,
nature is not,
he who first said,
God rolls dice.
And it was not Bohr,
not,
not Bohr,
anybody else.
It was Einstein who said that first.
And I think it's kind of interesting,
though,
that Bohr and the people
who were working with the atom
were still working with,
with essentially particles
in specific orbits and things like that.
Yes,
yes.
And they were trying to jigger
it to get the quantum effects.
That's right.
So it's not completely clear
that they recognized the magnitude of their problem.
Right.
When,
when Heisenberg finally decided something's,
something's wrong with the whole thing,
we have to jump it,
let's try.
Yeah.
But as I said,
Einstein had already said,
the world is not deterministic,
and you can never ever know enough to,
to be able to predict the emission of,
the time of emission of a photon.
There's nothing you can do to measure,
that you can measure enough to know
when an atom is going to decay.
He also talked about radioactivity the same way.
He said there's nothing you can do,
no measurement that you can make in the atom.
He,
he sensed that.
He could tell from what was going on that,
that physics was fundamentally limited
to probabilistic explanations of things.
I'm just wondering,
since every,
every observation of a photon involves an electron,
Or some charged particle,
some charge.
Isn't it enough that one of those particles is quantized?
Um,
it's enough to know that one of them is quantized
to prove that the other is.
Uh,
you really can't,
you really can't couple together classical things
to quantum mechanical things.
It doesn't make sense.
You run into,
you run into contradiction.
Uh,
trying to keep part of a,
part of a theory classical and the rest quantum mechanical.
It really does run itself into the ground,
uh,
pretty quickly.
So,
it's enough to know that one is quantum mechanical
to know that the other has to be quantum mechanical.
Um,
but,
uh,
yeah.
Yeah,
so,
so why did Einstein never really accept the theory?
I mean,
he was never really satisfied with quantum mechanics,
even though,
what you just said,
I mean,
he was one of the first scientists.
Well,
I don't really know.
Um,
If I had to guess,
I would guess he was very,
very uncomfortable
with the idea of a probabilistic theory.
What does probability mean?
You flip a coin a thousand times.
What does it tell you about nature
that the probability is 50% heads,
50% tails?
Does it tell you anything about nature?
Does it tell you that,
uh,
that it will turn up heads 500 times?
No,
it doesn't tell you that.
Does it tell you 500
times within the margin of error,
the margin of error being what,
square of 1,030?
No,
it doesn't tell you that.
Does it tell you that
you cannot flip a thousand heads?
No,
it doesn't tell you that.
What does it tell you?
It tells you that it's
improbable to flip a thousand heads.
Well,
probability is being defined in terms of probability.
What ultimately does it say about nature
that,
uh,
that if you flip a coin a thousand times
that the probability is heads that it will turn up,
uh,
the probability is 50% that it will turn up heads?
I think the only thing I
can think of that makes sense
is to say you'd be very,
very surprised
if you're outside the margin of error.
It doesn't happen very often.
Why doesn't it happen very often?
It could happen very often.
It could happen every time.
Probability theory doesn't tell you
that improbable things don't happen.
It just tells you they're improbable.
Well,
what does improbable mean?
It just means they hardly ever happen.
Well,
what do you mean they hardly ever happen?
They could happen every time.
Oh,
but they're improbable.
It doesn't say anything.
It just says you'd be surprised.
I think Einstein was probably troubled by the idea
that the most fundamental principles in physics
were dependent on nothing more than
what he would be surprised by.
That's my guess.
I think it's probably true.
The impression that I had gotten was that
he realized fairly early that
there was this probabilistic thing
about quantum mechanics,
quantum theory.
And a lot of people felt
that the new quantum theory was fundamental,
and he thought that it wasn't
because he realized this about the theory.
Say it again?
He realized that he saw the probabilistic
nature of the theory as a defect.
Yeah.
And a lot of people thought it
was the be-all and end-all fundamental theory
because it's at the atomic level,
it must be fundamental.
Right.
What's peculiar is how naive he was
at his attempts to outflank quantum mechanics.
That's what's surprising.
Not that he was troubled by quantum mechanics.
Everybody who grows up in physics becomes
troubled by quantum mechanics at some point.
What's surprising is how naive his
attempts to get around it were.
Just,
well,
it doesn't matter because
it historically didn't go anywhere.
Let's get back to the Schrodinger equation.
We were studying the Schrodinger equation,
and let's really go through it now.
And finally tonight,
I think,
if we can get to it,
we will understand the connection with classical mechanics,
why momentum in quantum mechanics,
which is one thing,
is related to momentum in classical mechanics,
which is another thing,
what energy,
why energy,
why the Hamiltonian of quantum mechanics
is called energy and so forth.
And of course the answer is,
because in contexts where things are heavy
enough to behave according to approximate classical mechanics,
these quantities that have been defined in quantum mechanics
behave approximately like the corresponding quantities in classical mechanics.
But always keep in mind,
quantum mechanics is more fundamental.
You don't derive quantum mechanics from classical mechanics.
You derive the other way.
So that's what we're going to do tonight.
But let's come back to the Schrodinger equation.
Let me remind you what it is.
It says it's the equation which tells
you how the state vector changes with time.
It contains Planck's constant h-bar.
And it says that the rate of change
of the state vector with respect to time
is equal to an operator,
a Hermitian observable operator that's called h.
When I remember to do so,
I put a little hat on top of it
to indicate that it's an operator acting on psi.
That's called the general,
we should call it the general Schrodinger equation.
Of course,
it's not the exact thing that Schrodinger wrote down.
We'll supplement this.
I want to make a list of
some of the equations that we need.
Another equation is that momentum,
this says that energy is related to time.
Time derivatives with a factor of i h-bar.
A similar equation,
similar looking equation,
is that momentum,
I don't need to,
momentum is an operator.
Its whole purpose in life is
to act on a state vector.
I won't bother writing,
well,
maybe I will write.
Nah,
let's not write the state vector for it.
Let's just write p,
that that's equal to minus i h-bar.
d by dx.
In other words,
the time derivative of the wave function
is obtained by the Hamiltonian acting on the wave function.
The space derivative of the wave
function is related to the momentum operator
by the same factor i h-bar.
The minus sign in there,
the fact that there's a minus
sign here and no minus sign here,
is something of a convention.
Now,
it just historically evolved that way,
that there's a minus sign
here and no minus sign here.
We could change conventions and
put a minus sign there too.
We won't,
because after all,
these are venerable conventions,
so we'll stick with them.
Alright,
now,
last but not least,
we're thinking about a particle moving along a line.
It has a Hamiltonian,
and here's where we use
classical physics to make a guess.
Not a derivation,
but a guess.
Pure guess that the Hamiltonian of classical physics,
now so far we don't know
any particular relationship between this Hamiltonian
and the classical physics Hamiltonian,
but that's equal to our free
particle to p squared over 2m.
The fact that it's proportional
to p squared and not p,
let's start with that.
p is a vector for which
for a particle moving along a line
means that it has either a
forward sense or a backward sense.
Momentum can go this way
or it can go this way.
Alright?
We wouldn't want the energy to depend
on whether the momentum is in that direction
or in that direction.
We expect that the energy of
a particle moving to the left
with a certain momentum is the
same as the energy of a particle
moving to the right with the same momentum.
And so it makes a lot of sense to
say that it's proportional to p squared and not p.
If p was here by itself,
then the energy would be opposite
for positive momentum and negative momentum.
The fact that there's a 2m here,
well,
that's essentially the definition of mass,
if you like.
Again,
you could call it something else,
you don't need to call it m,
but the fact is that energy
is proportional to p squared over 2m.
Fairly general fact
about ordinary non-relativistic particles.
So we make the guess.
We try it out
and see what we learn from it
to suppose that the Hamiltonian of quantum mechanics
is also p squared over 2m.
But now it's in the sense of operators.
The operator h is the
operator p hat squared over 2m.
And as I said,
keep in mind the real derivation
goes from this blackboard to this blackboard.
And we're going to do that derivation tonight.
So let's see what that means.
What is the meaning of this equation
and how does it connect together
with the other equations above it?
The only other thing you need to know
is what it means,
I wrote down what p is,
what does p squared mean?
p squared simply means you
act twice with the same operator.
You act with the operator on a state vector
and then you operate with it again,
once followed by the second time.
Alright,
so this is enough for us to now
write down the Schrodinger equation for a free particle.
Instead of writing the ket vector psi,
I will just remember,
that wave function psi of x form a vector space.
The wave function is in general
not just a function of position,
it is a function of position.
It's square tells you the probability
for finding the particle at different locations.
But of course it's also implicitly a function of time.
It changes with time.
It's dependence on time is logically of a different kind
than its dependence on space.
The state vector is psi of x,
but the state vector changes with time.
Okay,
so that's the way to think about it.
Now,
we wouldn't speak for example about psi star psi
being the probability for different times.
That doesn't make any sense.
What's the probability that the time is such and such?
Well,
that doesn't make any sense.
But it does make sense to say,
what's the probability that the particle is located
at a particular position at a certain time?
So,
the dependence on x and
t are quite logically quite different.
x is an observable.
Of course,
when I look at my clock,
I also observe the time.
But what I'm really doing is observing
the position of the hands on the clock.
Those are positions.
Okay,
so let's write down the Schrodinger equation now.
All we have to do
is substitute into the top equation.
And we get,
what do we get?
We get i.
Let's write down the top equation.
Let's pull down.
We get i h bar d
psi of x and t by dt.
That's the left-hand side.
The right-hand side,
we use h is equal to p squared over 2m.
So,
first of all,
it's a 1 over 2m.
And then p acts twice.
p is minus i h bar d psi.
h bar d by dx.
So,
we get minus i h bar d by dx.
But we write it twice.
Minus i h bar d by dx.
Acting on psi of x and t.
So,
what does this mean?
First of all,
we can take out the factor
of minus i h bar squared.
Minus i times minus i is minus 1.
So,
first of all,
let's get rid of the i's.
It gives us our overall minus sign.
There's an h bar squared.
So,
let's take out the h bar squared.
And we have d by dx
multiplying the d by dx times psi.
d by dx times psi just means,
it means nothing but derivative
of psi with respect to x.
Differentiating it again just
gives us the second derivative.
So,
this whole thing becomes nothing but the second
derivative with respect to x of psi of x.
And that's our Schrodinger equation.
That's the Schrodinger equation for a free particle.
It's the actual equation
that Schrodinger actually wrote down.
We could get into y here.
He wrote this down,
but let's not.
Let's just pursue it and work
at it from the other end.
And we'll eventually see why he wrote it down.
Okay,
now let's look for solutions of this equation.
Let's look for solutions which have
the character of being plane waves.
Let's look for wave-like solutions.
In other words,
let's look for solutions whose
x dependence is of the form
e to the i p over h bar x.
Let's look for solutions of that type.
Why p over h bar?
Well,
I can just describe them that way.
Let's say y p over h bar.
Well,
if I differentiate,
just look for solutions of that form.
Omega means?
Hm?
You want omega there maybe?
No,
I don't want omega there.
Omega multiplies time.
Okay,
so let's put in omega.
Omega has to do with time dependence.
Let's put in a factor
e to the i omega t.
In other words,
let's assume that the wave function oscillates with time
and oscillates with space.
The justification for this will
be that the difference between
the two is that there do exist solutions like this.
These solutions,
if we find them,
will at any instant of time
be eigenvectors of the momentum operator.
Remember,
eigenvectors of the momentum operator have the form
as wave functions e to the
i p x over h bar.
Those are eigenvectors of the momentum operator.
They're the things which minus i h bar
d by dx act on to give an eigenvector.
They're eigenvectors.
They're eigenvectors of the momentum operator.
The time dependence here,
well,
this tells us that wave functions have time dependence.
And I'm guessing,
I'm guessing now that they oscillate with time.
That's an oscillation,
typical oscillation.
Let's plug this into the Schrodinger equation and
see if we can find out what omega is.
Omega is the unknown.
Of course,
there may be no such solution like this.
We may find that it,
that,
you know,
we run the bus into the ditch.
That we can't find solutions like this.
But of course,
if we couldn't,
I wouldn't have written it down.
Okay,
what happens if we take psi of
x and differentiate it with respect to time?
Every time we differentiate with respect to time,
we pull down a factor of i omega.
So the left-hand side is just going to be,
give us an i omega times
i h bar times psi itself.
Here's psi.
Alright.
When I differentiate with respect to time,
it'll give me back the same thing except
with an i omega in front of it.
So that's just psi of x and t.
i omega times i h bar,
that's just minus h bar omega.
Now let's look on the right-hand side.
On the right-hand side,
every time I differentiate with respect to x,
it pulls down i p over h bar.
It gives me a factor
of i p over h bar.
So let's write it all down.
Is equal to...
Minus h bar squared over 2m.
Incidentally,
I could have cancelled out a
factor of h bar from here,
so it doesn't appear here and only appears once here.
We'll do it in this form.
Now,
what is the second derivative of psi?
The second derivative of psi
just contains this factor squared.
i p over h bar squared.
So,
that gives me i squared is minus 1.
That turns this minus sign into a plus sign.
It gives me p squared over h bar squared.
And then,
just psi again.
Alright,
so now let's clean it up a little bit.
h bar squared over h bar squared.
That cancels.
Cancel out the h bars.
And we get p squared over 2m times psi.
The left-hand side minus omega times h bar times psi.
The right-hand side,
p squared over 2m times psi.
Cancel out the psi's.
And what do we find?
We find that the frequency minus
omega must equal p squared over 2m.
Yes,
divided by 2mh.
Thank you.
Now,
what we're doing from a mathematical point
of view is actually finding the eigenvectors.
One way of saying it is we're finding the eigenvalues.
The eigenvalues of the Hamiltonian.
Omega,
when the...
Okay,
let's...
We'll come back to it.
We'll come back to the eigenvalues of the Hamiltonian.
That's what omega basically is.
An eigenvalue of the Hamiltonian.
But,
we find that the omegas have to be
equal to minus p squared over 2m h bar.
Let's now use that to rewrite the wave function.
The wave function that we found now
has the form psi of x and t.
And of course,
this is only one of many solutions.
Is of the form e to the i p over h
bar x minus i p squared over 2m h bar t.
So,
it oscillates with x.
And it oscillates with t.
The x oscillation is governed by the momentum itself.
And the t oscillation is governed by the momentum.
If we forget the h bars.
In a little while,
I'll probably set h bar equal to 1.
Notice how h bar comes into these formulas.
It always comes in in the form of a coordinate.
Now,
a coordinate,
I can either mean x or t.
Think of both x's and t's as being coordinates.
It always comes in the form x
over h bar or t over h bar.
Once you know that,
you can set h bar to 1 and recover
it later by sticking it back into the equations.
x over h bar is the only way
in which Planck's constant enters into this wave function.
And t over h bar.
So,
every time you see x
and every time you see t,
put an h bar in the denominator.
And that will recover for
you the factors of Planck's constant.
Alright,
so here was the,
this is the simplest solution of
the Schrodinger equation for a free particle.
It corresponds to a particle of momentum
p and energy p squared over 2m.
Notice there is another wave function
which corresponds to exactly the same energy.
What is it?
If this is a particle moving to the right.
Okay.
It corresponds to a momentum p which is positive.
Then there's another one,
if we fix p.
Fix p.
p is some positive number for example.
The energy is p squared over 2m.
There are two states,
two configurations with the same energy.
One has p going that way,
the other has p going that way.
So there's another wave function we could have written down.
I'll write it down side by side with this.
Which would have had the form e to
the minus i p over h bar x.
But the time dependence is exactly the same.
Why is that?
That's because this only depends on p squared.
Alright.
So if I change the sign of p,
it doesn't change the sign of p squared.
And it's minus i p
squared over 2m h bar t.
These are two wave functions.
Which both correspond to the same energy.
But opposite going momentum.
You can add them together with arbitrary coefficients.
They will no longer be eigenvectors of the momentum.
Because you're mixing together two momenta.
But they will have the same energy.
So if you add wave functions like this.
The energy of the combined wave
function is still p squared over 2m.
2m,
not n.
m.
But you're mixing two momenta.
Depending on the coefficients that you
would put these two together with.
Let's put them together with some coefficients.
Let's call this one alpha.
And let's call this one beta.
Alright.
What's the probability that the
particle is moving to the right?
Alpha star alpha.
Alpha star alpha is the coefficient
of the eigenvector with right moving momentum.
And the probability that it's moving
to the left is beta star beta.
What's the probability that it
has energy p squared over 2m?
Alright.
So this is a simple example.
What constitutes the special relation?
I don't know.
Special relationship.
That knocked me off balance.
Alright.
Now,
what's the general solution?
This is a special solution
of the Schrodinger equation corresponding,
or it's a family of special solutions,
with an alpha and a beta,
but they all correspond to the same energy.
What is the general solution of the Schrodinger equation?
The general solution is sums or
integrals of wave functions like this.
We can take wave functions of the form,
e to the i,
p over h bar,
x minus i,
p squared over 2m h bar t.
And now we can add them,
or better yet,
we've added them there,
but now we can better yet integrate them,
dp,
and just for reasons of convention,
I put in the standard
square root of 2 pi here,
but you don't need to,
times an amplitude,
psi of p,
or psi twiddle of p.
Now,
in this expression here,
I don't have to include
a left-moving and a right-moving momentum.
Since I'm integrating over p,
let's say from minus infinity to infinity,
there are contributions in here where p
is positive and contributions where p is negative.
So this wave function,
which is a sum,
which is a superposition,
a quantum superposition,
of states with different momentum p,
very much like any quantum superposition,
it's a quantum superposition
of states with different momenta,
and also in general different energies.
It's true,
the left-moving and the right-moving with the
same value of p have the same energy,
but in general,
when I integrate up lots of different momenta,
I have states in there of very different energy.
So this is a quantum superposition that
is not only a superposition of different momenta,
but also different energies.
What's the probability,
for example,
that this particle has momentum p?
Now,
when I say it has momentum p,
I really mean the momentum
density as a function of p.
Because momentum is a continuous variable,
we describe it by a momentum density.
The probability that the momentum is
between p and p plus dp,
but what's the probability density
for the momentum to be p?
Well,
that's just psi star,
psi twiddle of p times psi twiddle star of p.
Yes?
I thought the dummy variable of integration was p.
Oh,
okay,
yes,
yes.
The dummy variable of integration is p.
Good,
thank you.
And so what is the,
why is...
Oh,
this is in the integral.
that's in the integral.
That's in the integral,
absolutely.
Oh,
okay.
That's in the integral.
What's the parameters of the...
The parameters of what?
Of the psi twiddle of p.
The parameters.
What's fixed?
What is fixed?
The side-decks of t.
I guess nothing is fixed.
Nothing's fixed.
Yeah,
and m.
oh,
yeah,
sure,
sure.
H-bar is fixed,
m is fixed,
i is fixed,
e is fixed,
infinity is fixed,
pi is fixed,
2 is fixed.
Right?
But other than that,
other than almost everything on the board,
nothing is fixed.
We're integrating over p,
which means we're summing up waves of different wavelength,
we're summing up waves of different wavelength,
some moving to the right,
some moving to the left,
and we're summing them up
with an amplitude psi of p.
Each wave has a time dependence,
so we're summing up these things.
Each one is oscillating.
The different ones,
they're oscillating with different frequencies.
It's a mess.
The whole thing is doing very,
very complicated things,
but it can all be represented
as a superposition of different momentum eigenstates.
All right,
now I come back to my question.
What is the probability density?
What's the probability density
that the particle has momentum,
let's say q,
let's not call it p
since p is an integration variable.
Probability density p of q.
That,
of course,
is nothing but this amplitude squared.
Again,
it's the same sort of thing.
We're adding up wave functions with different coefficients.
So this probability is
psi twiddle star of q,
psi of q.
I've just picked a particular value of momentum.
I didn't want to call
it p because in this formula,
p is an integration variable.
One more twiddle.
Did I miss a twiddle?
Thank you.
Good.
All right.
Up there,
it's a function of momentum.
Down here,
it's a function of position.
No,
it's not a function of position.
Oh,
I'm sorry.
We should,
you're thinking of p's and q's
in the sense of positions and momentum.
No.
p,
q here is a momentum.
Yeah,
we could just call it p prime or something.
maybe I should do that.
No,
I don't have to.
I've already established the notation that position is x.
And p's and q's both mean momentum here.
But it's a fair point.
If I use x for position,
then I won't use q for position.
Good.
Thank you.
All right.
So this is the probability
that the particle has momentum q.
What's the probability that the energy is e?
Well,
the probability that the energy is e,
you get two contributions with the same energy.
You first write e equals p squared over 2m.
That tells you what p to look for.
If I want the probability
that the particle has energy e,
I look for those pieces of the wave function
where the momentum satisfies p squared over 2m equals e.
In other words,
I look for p squared equals 2me.
How many p's are there such
that p squared is equal to 2me?
Two.
Namely,
the two possible square roots.
The two possible square roots.
Can this be seen?
No,
it can't.
But believe me,
there's a plus or minus sign here.
Plus or minus square root
of 2me is equal to p.
So what I do is
I look in this wave function
or in this general wave function here
for the contributions which have a given energy,
there will be two of them.
Okay.
And the probability,
let's call these p plus minus.
p plus minus is plus or minus.
I'm going to rewrite it.
I'm going to rewrite it so everybody can see it.
p plus or minus equals plus or minus.
Now I forgot what it was.
Square root of 2me,
right?
I think that's it.
Yeah.
So what I do is I go
to the two wave functions in here
which have this value of energy,
and I take the total
probability for that value of energy.
What's it going to be?
It's going to be that probability,
let's say probability for a given energy
is going to be psi twiddle of p plus
star psi twiddle of p plus.
That's the probability that the momentum is p plus
plus the probability that the momentum is p minus.
Where p plus and p minus
are just opposite values of the momentum.
One going one way,
one going the other way.
Alright,
so that's the Schrodinger equation for a free particle.
Probably,
but I think by now I may have,
where?
Yeah,
no,
not in there.
Not,
no,
no.
Nope.
The energy in terms of the
momentum does not have an h bar.
Energy in terms of momentum is
just the same as in classical physics.
So have we got it?
We found general solution of...
Yeah,
that's the general solution of the Schrodinger equation.
I don't have to roll over the shape of it.
Yep,
that's it.
And psi,
of course,
can be complex.
So it's parameterized by a complex function of p.
And that's it.
That's all of the solutions.
Well,
I take that back.
There are other solutions,
but the other solutions have the
property that they either blow up
or do something terrible in infinity.
They are...
They simply blow up at infinity.
These are all of the solutions
that don't blow up at infinity.
In other words,
which don't have all of their probability
way out at infinity.
This is all of them.
Yeah.
All the relevant solutions.
Does that depend on the assumption
you made at the very beginning
that you can...
that they're separable?
That you can separate the
e to the i omega t
and i p x over...
over h bar?
If...
If they weren't separable,
would that still be the general solution?
this wouldn't be the equation.
And if this weren't the equation,
this wouldn't be the solution.
Let's talk about the case where they're not separable.
The case where they're not separable...
Separable just means the wave function factors...
No,
it's always separable in the sense
that there's a function of x
which may not be a simple e to
the i p x times an oscillation in t.
We'll prove that.
I hope we'll prove that.
I hope we have time to prove it.
Is there an arbitrary phase?
Arbitrary phase.
Yeah,
you can put an arbitrary coefficient here,
complex or real.
Yeah.
Yeah,
it will still...
Any...
And in fact,
these are the arbitrary coefficients.
So this could contain a phase.
Okay.
Phase p depends on p.
Yeah,
the phase...
the psi of p can contain
a phase which depends on p,
absolutely.
If it didn't depend on p,
it wouldn't be very interesting.
A phase that depends on p is interesting.
In other words,
it affects the probabilities.
Okay,
let's...
We want to come to a more...
Let's see.
Yeah,
just a second.
Let me just see my notes.
Yeah.
Psi twiddle.
Psi twiddle is the Fourier transform of psi of x.
Of psi of x at time 0.
Supposing you go to time 0.
If we go to time 0,
this is a good question.
Let's pursue it.
Let's go to time t equals 0.
At time t equals 0,
this wave function is just minus infinity to infinity,
integral dp,
over square root of 2 pi,
e to the i px,
psi twiddle of p.
That's equal to psi of x at time equals 0.
Let's just call it psi of x.
This is the definition of the
Fourier transform of psi of x.
If we happen to have known...
Here might be the way
we might set up a problem.
Supposing we knew that at time t equals 0,
the wave function of the particle was psi of x.
I don't know how we know.
We know that the wave function is
psi of x at time t equals 0.
And we want to find it at a later time.
What do we do?
Well,
the first thing we do
is we find the Fourier transform,
psi twiddle of p.
Let me remind you how you do that.
Let's see.
Let's put it up here.
Psi twiddle of p
is equal to the integral from minus infinity to infinity.
Now not integral dp,
but integral dx.
Integral dx.
e to the minus i px over square
root of 2 pi times psi of x.
So if somebody tells us what psi of
x is at a certain instant of time,
let's say at time t equals 0,
we can reconstruct this.
We can reconstruct what psi of p is.
Remember now the reciprocal relationship between Fourier
transform of x and Fourier transform of p.
Fourier transforms are reciprocally related in such a way that if psi of
x is an integral e to the i px psi twiddle of p,
then psi twiddle of p is integral,
same kind of integral,
except over x with a minus sign up here.
This is the reciprocal relationship between
functions and their Fourier transforms.
So you first find psi twiddle of p.
Once you've found psi twiddle of p,
you stick it into this formula,
which is basically the same formula,
except that it now has time dependence.
In other words,
then this becomes psi of x and t.
This becomes psi of x and t.
So you start out at time t equals
0 with some knowledge of the wave function.
You compute the Fourier transform.
That tells you psi twiddle of p.
You then stick it into this time dependent formula here.
The only time dependence is that for each wave,
there's an e to the i
p squared over 2m times t.
And that gives you the full
time dependence of the wave function.
Now the wave function will evolve in a complicated way.
The different waves that are in
it are oscillating with different time dependencies.
So for example,
the shape of the wave function will not be preserved.
If we start out with
some general wave function like that,
and we start evolving it,
the different Fourier components
oscillate with different periods.
The result is the whole thing is
going to move in a complicated pattern,
which is not going to preserve its shape.
But,
nevertheless,
that's the evolution of the wave function.
Once you know this,
you can then ask what's
the probability at a later time
that the particle is located in some particular place.
So the kind of problem we might solve is
by hook or crook,
somebody tells us what the initial wave function is.
And what we want to find
out is not at that instant
of time what the probability for its location is.
That's easy.
That's just psi star of x,
psi of x.
But we want to find out what
the probability will be at a later time.
After all this complicated motion has taken place,
what's the probability to find
the particle at a particular place?
We go through this operation.
We find psi twiddle of p.
We plug it into here.
That gives us psi of x and t.
We can put this on a computer,
calculate psi of x and t,
and then psi star of x and
t times psi of x and t
is the new probability at a later time
for locating the particle in different places.
That's the logic.
That's the way quantum mechanics works.
Okay.
Any other questions?
Yes?
So you can also derive the
psi twiddle of p and t
and also evolve the psi twiddle of x and t?
Psi twiddle of p and
t is really just this combination.
You see,
if I called all of this,
everything here,
let's put an e to the minus i,
and group this together,
then we see that we can combine
psi twiddle of p with this factor here,
and this just becomes the time-dependent Fourier transform
of psi of x and t.
Does that answer your question?
Good.
Right,
so another way to say it
is that the Fourier transform evolves with time,
and it evolves with this phase factor here.
But,
as I said,
the important thing is
this time-dependence of the Fourier transform
translates in general into a rather complicated
variation of the wave function with time,
but you can always find it in this way.
Yeah?
If the wave doesn't preserve its shape with time,
that's a dispersive wave,
and it means that different components
propagate at different speeds.
Absolutely.
Right?
Now,
this is true.
Right.
The different components do propagate
with different speeds,
for sure.
It's not surprising,
since the different components
correspond to different momenta.
In fact,
there are several different kinds of speeds,
group velocity,
phase velocity,
and so forth,
but I won't do that now,
group velocity and phase velocity.
Yeah,
okay.
Remind me to tell you something about the schedule
for this class,
because I will be gone for some period,
and I don't want you to show
up here when I won't be here.
When might you be here?
When I'm off the air.
Okay.
Now,
the next thing we want to
do is we want to study
the evolution of the expectation values.
First of all,
we want to study a more complicated
kind of Schrodinger equation in which the particle
is subjected to forces,
in which the particle is moving
in the presence of energy.
And then we want to study
the potential of a potential function.
That's one thing we're going to want to do,
and work out the Schrodinger equation.
But the other thing we're
going to want to do is,
once we've done that,
we want to see how wave packets move.
A wave packet is simply
a concentrated wave of some sort
which moves along with some sort of coherent motion.
The center of the wave packet,
or the average position
of the wave packet,
moves in some way,
and it had better be
that at least in the appropriate circumstances,
that the motion of the wave packet looks pretty much
like the corresponding motion of a classical system,
of a classical particle.
We're going to want to work that out.
We'll do that tonight.
But before we study
the more complicated Schrodinger equation,
I want to remind you
how you calculate the time evolution
of expectation values,
because that's what we're going to do.
We're going to do it for the Schrodinger equation.
So,
two steps.
Question?
Yeah.
Just a quick question.
So that equation there for psi of x of t,
so that could be for a photon,
right?
Well,
photons are not nonrelativistic particles.
This is really the theory of nonrelativistic particles.
So you wouldn't apply this
in this form to a photon.
Photons simply don't have energies
which are p squared over 2m.
In fact,
they don't have any m.
So you wouldn't apply it in
quite this form to a photon.
Is that the question?
Yeah.
You would have to...
The rule is that this is an appropriate description
for particles moving much,
much slower than the speed of light.
Okay.
The question is whether I should...
Well,
I'm trying to...
Okay.
Let's put a little variety into this.
Let's back off the particle on a line
and remind ourselves how we compute
the time dependence of expectation values.
Then we'll come back to a more complicated
version of a particle moving on a line.
Let's take...
some observable.
Ah,
that's a surprise,
red.
Let's take an observable.
Let's call it k.
And let's take its average value,
its expectation value.
There's its expectation value.
And let's study its time dependence.
This is the closest thing to
the corresponding classical evolution of that observable.
Right?
Its expectation value.
To calculate it,
and we're imagining some fixed observable.
The observable itself is not changing with time.
It could be position.
It could be momentum.
It could be spin.
It could be polarization.
But we're not changing it with time.
What is changing with time is the state vectors.
So,
we use the rule for differentiating products.
k is not time dependent,
but the two sys here are.
And let's write this just in
the form bra vector time derivative.
The dot indicates time derivative.
k,
sy,
plus sy k times sy dot.
I'm going over stuff which we did last time.
Now,
we use the Schrodinger equation.
Let's use the Schrodinger equation over here for sy dot.
Sy dot is either plus or minus i h sy.
I am now going to
set h bar equal to one.
H bar equal to one,
because it'll drive me crazy to
keep track of it in these equations.
H bar is equal to one.
Does anybody remember whether sy dot is plus i
times h sy or minus i times h sy?
I don't.
Minus i.
Sy dot is the same thing as sy k.
And now,
sy dot is,
I forgot what I just said.
Did I say minus or plus?
I.
Hmm?
Minus i.
So,
minus i,
this one is minus i,
I hope I'm right,
times h times sy.
Notice we have k over here and h over here.
How about this one over here?
This one over here,
we have to apply the
time evolution to the bra vector.
That involves a complex conjugation.
The minus i will become a plus i.
This becomes i,
sy,
h,
k,
sy.
We have two different terms.
One of them has h,
k.
The other one has k,
h.
The result is i times the expectation
value of the commutator of h with k.
Remember what the commutator is?
It's h,
k minus k,
h.
I won't bother putting in the size here.
I just indicate the expectation value of the commutator.
The commutator of h and k.
That's the rule.
In fact,
let's just write this as the time
derivative of the expectation value of k.
For any state,
it doesn't matter what state we choose,
that is the way the expectation value will evolve.
Now,
of course,
both sides will depend on what state we're talking about.
The relationship between the two is always the same,
but the actual magnitude,
the magnitude of each of these sides
depends on what state we're talking about.
This is the rule that we're going to use to
try to figure out how things evolve in the Schrodinger,
how the motion of a wave packet evolves in time.
For example,
we could apply this to the position,
to x,
to x itself,
to the position operator,
and find out how the average
position of a particle changes with time.
We could apply it to the momentum
and find out how the average momentum
of a particle changes with time.
So let's put this upstairs
and keep it for future reference
while we do a couple of other simple things.
Evidently,
we're going to have to compute commutators.
Commutators are the things that
we're going to have to compute
to see how things evolve with time.
So let's study a little
bit about commutators in quantum mechanics.
Just a few simple things.
Oh,
incidentally,
let's compare this with another equation.
The corresponding classical equation
is that the time derivative
of an observable,
we won't put brackets around it now
because now it really means the time derivative
of some classical quantity.
Anybody remember what it's given by?
By the Poisson bracket.
The Poisson bracket,
I can't remember if it's k
with h or h with k.
I always have trouble with these signs.
Hm?
K with h?
Are you sure?
Are you absolutely sure?
OK,
I'll trust you.
So how come it's reversed?
Well,
first of all,
there's an i in there,
among other things.
I doubt that it is reversed.
Let me just find my own notes.
I have h with k in my notes.
We can find out that
the time derivative of a function,
So I can just find out fast enough.
Everybody will send you an email.
Hm?
That's true,
but I'm going to write h with k.
Last time you had it the other way around.
Last time I had it the other way around?
Yeah,
I had k with an h.
Well,
it's one way or the other.
OK,
let's figure it out.
We have some function,
let's call it k since we've already called it k.
k of x and p,
for example.
The time derivative of k of x and p
is equal to the derivative
of k with respect to x
times the derivative of x,
just the x dt,
let's call it x dot,
plus the derivative of k with
respect to p times p dot.
I don't like this red pen,
but I've sort of run out of black pens.
No,
I haven't.
Here's another one.
Let's hope it's got something in it.
All right,
this is true.
Now,
do you remember Hamilton's equations?
Hamilton's equations say that x dot is dh dp.
So this is dh dp.
And that's correct.
It really is dh dp,
not minus dh dp.
p dot is minus dh dx.
This is correct.
Now,
what is this?
This is the Poisson bracket of k with h.
You were right,
Michael,
I think.
Well,
I was just reading that.
What did you say?
You did that in your head while I was...
Oh.
k with h is right.
Okay.
So you can always go back to the basic principle
and figure out what's going on.
That's correct.
Is it possible that we made
a mistake in the quantum equation?
I can't tell.
I'm not sure.
The sign of the ih could
be the sign of the ih.
That's the choice,
the bra ket.
Yeah.
It could be,
and maybe it's right.
I don't remember.
That's where that order came from,
is that we chose the bra to be
a minus i and the ket to be...
And I think that's right with all
of the conventions I've used up till now.
So it looks like that's the way it is.
It's just the way it is.
The i kdh?
Change the sign...
change it to minus i.
Yeah,
yeah.
Yeah.
There's nothing sacred about the sign of i.
I suppose that's the way it is.
I'm a little surprised,
but nevertheless...
Oh.
No,
I think it's right.
I think that's the right convention,
although it seems weird.
Yeah,
I think all the conventions are right.
it's okay.
It's right.
All right,
so let's consider then the
connection between Poisson brackets and commutators.
There must be some connection between them.
They must somehow be the same
thing or almost the same thing.
So let's look at various Poisson brackets and various commutators
and just see to what extent they're similar to each other,
to what extent they're different.
In fact,
we're not going to bother with the differences.
They are sometimes different,
but almost in most contexts
they're very similar to each other.
Poisson brackets and commutators.
So let's start with some function of position.
It could be the position itself.
And take its Poisson bracket with momentum.
The definition of that is df by dx,
dp by dp,
but that's just one.
Let's write it.
dp by dp minus df by dp,
dp by dx.
The second term is zero on at least two counts.
The f,
sorry,
the f by dp.
First of all,
the f by dp is zero.
f doesn't depend on p.
And second of all,
the p by dx doesn't,
the p doesn't depend on x.
So the second term here is completely zero.
The derivative of p with respect to itself is one.
And we find the lovely fact
that the Poisson bracket is zero.
The Poisson bracket of any function of x with p
is just the derivative of f with respect to x.
In other words,
the operation of,
there should be a verb for this,
a single verb for it.
But the operation of Poisson bracketing with p,
Poissing,
Poissing with respect to,
Poissing f with p gives you the following.
You can do df by dx.
What about commuting f of x?
Let's take f of x
now to be a quantum operator.
What does it mean?
It means f of x is an operator
which multiplies a wave function by f of x.
It takes any function of x,
psi of x,
and multiplies it by f of
x to give a new wave function.
That's the operation,
quantum mechanically,
of f of x.
Let's figure out what the commutator
is of f of x with p.
To do that,
we just write down f of x.
Now,
p is minus i h bar.
I'm going to keep the
h bars in for a minute.
Minus,
I should have kept the h bars in here also.
The h bar here is here.
Okay.
If you put a minus i there,
that's what's in this book as Ehrenfest's theorem.
You think there's a minus sign?
I'm not even going to try.
I'm just saying you have kh,
and it's minus i.
It's correct as written,
or you can have minus i and kh.
Oh,
I see,
I see.
Yeah,
okay,
good.
Right.
Okay,
so,
and I put the h bar back in
because I want to keep track of it.
There's no h bar,
of course,
in classical physics.
Classical physics has no h bars.
All right,
so let's take the commutator of f
of x with minus i d by dx.
That's what p is,
and there's an h bar in there,
right?
Minus i h bar d by dx.
I want the commutator of f
of x with this object over here.
That means I take f of x times this.
Okay.
Minus the opposite order.
Let's put a bracket around there.
Minus i h bar d
by dx times f of x.
That's the commutator between f of
x and the thing inside the bracket,
which happens to be p.
Now,
what do I do with this?
How am I going to find
out what this is equal to?
The way to find out what it's equal to
is to apply it to an arbitrary wave function,
any wave function.
So let's take this and apply
it to an arbitrary wave function,
psi of x,
and see what we get.
That's the way to figure out what an operator does,
is apply it to a wave function.
Okay,
let's see if we can figure it out.
Do I have the...
yeah.
Okay.
First of all,
the first term.
The first term gives us f of x.
It gives us minus i h bar,
minus i h bar.
That's from here.
f of x,
and then the derivative of psi with respect to x.
Right?
d by dx just hits
psi of x and differentiates it.
So what it does is it multiplies,
it first differentiates and then multiplies by f of x.
The second term gives me a plus i.
Plus i h bar.
Minus times minus is plus h bar.
But now the derivative operation hits
the product f of x times psi.
First f of x multiplies psi,
and then you differentiate.
You get two terms.
So let's put some great big bracket around this.
We get two terms.
The first term just differentiates psi,
leaving f alone.
So that gives you f of
x times d psi by dx.
That's the first term.
The second term differentiates f and leaves psi alone.
So that gives me plus df
by dx times psi of x.
Everything inside the bracket.
That's the operation of this commutator
acting on a wave function psi.
Now some terms cancel.
Here's d psi by dx times
i times minus i h bar f.
Here's the same thing with a plus sign.
These cancel each other.
So we might as well just erase them.
I think we've done this kind of manipulation before,
but let's do it.
This term cancels this term.
All we have left is i h bar.
df by dx.
Now df by dx is just a function of x.
It's just a function of x,
which we then multiply by psi of x.
Here's what we learned.
We learned that taking this complicated commutator
and applying it to any psi of x
is the same thing as multiplying psi of
x by i h bar df by dx.
We can now write.
Very simply,
that the commutator is just equal.
The commutator as an operator is just equal
to multiplication by i h bar df by dx.
So now I have a simple formula.
The commutator of f with p,
let's call it p now.
Minus p times f.
Has exactly the same action as multiplying
by i h bar df by dx.
Well,
let's just compare that.
Poisson bracket,
poissing with p gives us df by dx.
Commuting with p gives us
i h bar df by dx.
We could also do a similar calculation to find out
what the commutator of x with a function of p is.
This is easy for one reason.
Remember there's this reciprocal
relationship between p and x.
They come in completely parallel to each other.
p and x can be sort of interchanged.
They're simply Fourier transforms of each other.
And it wouldn't be surprising if this
formula just gave way to a similar formula
in which we differentiate f
of p with respect to p.
Here when we commute f of x with p,
we get the f by dx.
Here what you get is i h
bar df of p with respect to p.
So p is the commutator of x.
So poissing with either x or p differentiates.
Poissing with p differentiates with respect to x.
Poissing with x differentiates with respect to p.
Now let me just see
if I have the sign right.
I think I do.
Yeah,
there's an easy way to tell.
The easy way to tell is supposing
f of x was nothing but x itself.
Let's write down what this says
if f of x is just x.
Then it says that the commutator of x is x.
So the commutator of x with p is
equal to i h bar times dx by dx.
That's just 1.
So it says commutator of x
with p is i h bar.
That's what happens if you just
say f is equal to x.
Then df by dx is 1.
Let's suppose that f of p is just p.
Then this would also say exactly the same thing.
It would say commutator of x with
p is i h bar times 1.
So I have the sign right.
If I had put another sign here,
I would have an inconsistency between these two formulas.
Commutator of x with p is i h bar.
What's the Poisson bracket of x with p?
That's 1.
We can kind of read off this.
The relationship between Poisson brackets and commutators.
They appear to be,
at least in simple situations,
they appear to be essentially the same thing
except for a factor of i h bar.
We can write this in the form
that Poisson bracket is equal to commutator.
Now,
where does the i h bar go?
That's the question.
i h bar goes here,
I believe.
Is that correct?
Notice,
incidentally,
that the commutator,
whatever it happens to be,
let's say x and p,
as an example,
x and p,
x and p.
The commutator is much,
much smaller than the Poisson bracket
by a factor of Planck's constant.
Planck's constant is a terribly small number.
Commutators are very small.
That's natural because in classical physics,
x p minus p x,
that's 0.
Commutators are 0 in the classical limit.
The limit that h bar is equal to 0.
Commutators are 0.
They're only non-zero when h
bar is not equal to 0.
Then,
so here we see how h
bar gets into the commutation relations.
Okay,
so let's just check a few facts about commutators.
Let's look at commutators and Poisson brackets and
see that they're pretty parallel to each other.
Here's an example.
A B Poisson bracket.
What's the relationship between that and,
I'm writing equal,
but I'm going to change it in a moment,
B A?
What's the relation?
Well,
one of them is derivative
of A with respect to x,
derivative of B with respect to p minus the opposite.
The other one is exactly the same thing,
except in the opposite order.
They're negatives of each other.
Poisson brackets have this anti-symmetry that Poisson bracket of A
with B is minus the Poisson bracket of B with A.
Well,
of course,
that's also true of commutators.
The commutator is A B minus B A.
That's obviously minus B A.
Minus A B.
Here we have A B with a plus sign.
Okay.
So Poisson brackets and commutators
share the property of anti-symmetry,
it's called,
that when you invert the order of the
two things which you're either Poissing or commuting,
the sign changes.
So that's a good sign.
They have some algebraic similarity.
Let me give you another example,
which is a very useful fact.
When you're trying to either
compute quickly commutators or Poisson brackets.
Oh,
good.
An empty blackboard.
Supposing you have a product,
A B,
and you want to take its
Poisson bracket with a third thing,
C.
You can build up a lot of stuff
by starting with some simple things and constructing products.
Let's work out what that is.
That's D A B.
By D X.
But let me work,
alright,
that's D A B.
By D X.
D C by D P.
Minus D A B.
By D P.
D C by D X.
But now let's work out the derivative of A B.
That's A.
Times the X derivative of B.
Plus.
B.
Times the X derivative of A.
All times.
The derivative of C with respect to P.
And this one.
Is minus.
A.
D P B.
Plus B.
D P A.
All times.
D C by D X.
Now let's group these.
Let's find all the terms with
A standing out in front of them.
We have A.
Times something.
D X B.
D P C.
Alright,
D,
this is derivative of B with respect to X.
Derivative of C with respect to P.
Let's write it in the same notation.
Take this one and this one.
What does it give you?
It gives you A times the
Poisson bracket of B with C.
Look at it.
A times D X B.
D P C.
Minus A times D P B.
D X C.
That is nothing but A times
the Poisson bracket of B with C.
Now there's the other term.
We've gotten rid of this
and we've gotten rid of this.
Now there's the term with B undifferentiated.
Two of them.
Two terms with B undifferentiated.
So let's put the B out here.
And what does it multiply?
It multiplies the X derivative of
A times the P derivative of C.
Minus the opposite order.
And that's just the Poisson bracket.
Minus the Poisson bracket of A with C.
It doesn't matter that I put the B on
the right here and the A on the left.
We're talking about classical physics.
Classical physics,
the order of multiplication doesn't matter.
I just wrote it that way because that's
the way it comes out in quantum mechanics.
But look what it says.
It says if you have AB Poisson with C,
it gives you A times B Poisson with C.
Plus B times A Poisson with C.
It's a simple rule.
A simple rule that will carry you
a long ways in calculating Poisson brackets.
Let's compare it with commutators.
Let's do the corresponding thing.
Let's ask.
Could it be the same for commutators?
Alright,
so let's take AB commuted with C.
Same operation except in terms of commutators.
This would suggest that it's given by
A commutator BC plus commutator AC with B.
Is this true or is it not true?
Well,
it's easy to find out.
On the left side,
we have ABC minus CAB.
AB is a single entity.
AB times C.
Minus C times AB.
Do I have it right?
Yes.
That's the commutator.
Let's check over here.
Here we have A times BC minus CB.
That's the commutator of BC.
And here we have AC minus CA times B.
Let's see what we have.
We have ABC.
Here we have ABC.
Here we have ABC minus CAB.
Here we have CAB with a minus sign.
And then we have ACB minus ACB,
I hope.
Did I lose a minus sign?
Oh,
yes.
Minus ACB plus ACB is zero.
So,
in fact,
commutators have exactly the
same property as Poisson brackets.
This tells you,
if you only know some very simple Poisson brackets,
like just X with P,
you can start building up complicated products of
Xs and Ps and commuting them or Poissing them,
and you'll get the same answers.
You'll get the same answers.
So Poisson brackets are the natural analog.
Sorry.
Commutators are the natural analog.
The analog are Poisson brackets.
The equality is not always absolutely true.
And the reason is sometimes
you get expressions in quantum mechanics,
which are a little bit,
in classical mechanics,
which are a little bit ambiguous in quantum mechanics.
If I do some complicated calculation,
and at the end of the
day I get X cubed P,
then I don't know whether in quantum
mechanics this stands for X cubed P,
it might stand for X squared P X,
it might stand for X P X squared,
or it might stand for P X cubed.
There are different operators in quantum mechanics.
So there is some ambiguity that
when you calculate a Poisson bracket,
you don't always know exactly what
it stands for in quantum mechanics.
But apart from ambiguities like this,
Poisson brackets and commutators are equal to
within a factor of I H bar.
All right.
So that's something that's very useful,
and we'll use it.
We're getting late,
so we're running out of time.
But I do want to,
first,
I want to,
I'm going to do this quickly now.
We're going to write the Schrodinger
equation for a particle and a potential,
and then we're going to study
the classical limit using these principles
to find out how the
averages of the wave packets move.
That's our goal for tonight.
Work out,
or to write down the Schrodinger equation
for a particle moving in a potential.
We're not going to do much with it.
We're not going to solve it.
We're just going to calculate how
a wave packet moves in time.
All right.
The starting point is,
as always,
I d psi by dt,
X and t is equal to
H times psi of X and t.
But now H is not just going to be partial.
It's going to be P squared over 2m.
But it's going to be P squared
over 2m plus some potential energy function,
which only depends on X.
U of X is the potential energy.
It corresponds to a force,
which is minus the derivative
of U with respect to X.
And so we're going to plug that into here.
What does the P squared over 2m give us?
I've left out H bar,
incidentally,
and I'm going to keep leaving
out H bar for the moment,
for the rest of the night.
Left out H bar.
What did we get before?
We got P squared over 2m gave us,
I believe,
minus 1 over 2m times
second derivative with respect to X.
Sorry,
I'm going to put back the H bars.
But let's leave them out for the moment.
That's the P squared over 2m term.
What does U of X mean?
U of X just means multiplication
by the function U of X.
That's all it means.
So the second term here is plus
U of X times psi of X.
I d psi by dt.
This is the Schrodinger equation
that Schrodinger actually wrote down.
It says the time rate of change of
psi is just exactly what it was before,
plus an extra term,
which is U of X times psi of X.
Why is the psi of X here?
Why not just U of X?
Because U of X is an
operator that operates on the state vector.
So always there's a state vector in there somewhere.
It's either differentiated or undifferentiated.
It's there.
This is the Schrodinger equation.
Let's put in the H bars again.
There's an I H bar here.
I think there's an H bar squared here,
and no H bar at all here.
Okay,
that's Schrodinger.
That is literally the Schrodinger
equation that Schrodinger wrote down.
Yeah?
P is a P now a function of T.
P is not a function of T.
It's just a different,
it's an operation.
The average of P is a function of time.
The average of P is a function of time,
and that's what we're going to calculate.
P itself is just the operator P,
I d by dx.
It has no explicit time dependence.
The fact that momentum changes with time
is the fact that its average changes with time.
Why does its average change with time?
Because psi changes with time,
not because P changes with time.
So that's what I wanted to,
this is the,
this is the Schrodinger equation.
But I'm actually more interested
in the form of the Hamiltonian.
Here's the form of the Hamiltonian,
and I want to compute,
I would like to compute
how the average of X and P change with time.
They change with time because psi changes with time.
This is a complicated equation now.
A wave packet may come in,
it may hit the potential.
There's a potential U of X,
which,
let's draw the potential as a dotted line.
It might look like this.
The wave packet comes in,
experiences the fact that there's a potential.
Previously,
it didn't have any potential.
It did whatever it did,
which may have been complicated,
but now it's even more complicated.
It does something because the potential is there,
and we would like to find out,
on the average,
what does it do?
On the average,
how does the center of this wave packet move?
Right?
Now,
the answer is that if the wave,
if the potential is a very smooth function,
if it varies very smoothly on the
scale of the oscillations of the wave function,
then the center of the wave
function moves exactly according to classical physics.
But let's see if we can see that.
We have the rules for Poisson brackets and commutators.
I'll erase off the blackboard here,
but of course we all have them memorized.
And we have,
here's the equation,
here's the operative equation that we want to apply.
Let's first figure out,
what should we do?
Let's first figure out how X,
how the average of X changes with time.
The average of X changes with time.
This is dx dt.
We don't have to stick in the
wave functions now and do the whole thing.
We know it's just equal to
the expectation value of the commutator of,
well,
it's I H bar,
I over H bar,
commutator of H,
which is P squared over 2M,
plus U of X,
that's H,
with K,
and K is just X.
Okay.
First thing,
the commutator of U of X with X is zero.
A thing commutes with any function of itself.
X and X squared commute,
X and X cubed commute,
X with sine of X commute,
because all they are is multiplication by functions of X,
and it doesn't matter which order you multiply them.
So the first thing is,
in calculating the commutator of the Hamiltonian with X,
U doesn't come into it at all.
Let's erase it.
U commutes completely with X.
It's gone.
The important thing is the commutator
of X with P squared over 2M.
Let's write it down.
It's I over H bar,
2M in the denominator,
and then the commutator of P squared with X.
How do we calculate the
commutator of P squared with X?
We use this trick.
Remember the trick.
Commutator AB with C
is A commutator BC
plus BCA.
That's the trick we're going to use.
So what's the commutator of P squared with X?
Just this piece of it here
is P
commutator P with X
plus
A and B are both P now.
A and B are both P.
So it's P
commutator PX
plus
with P.
That's just using for AB
P squared.
Well what's the commutator of P with X?
Not quite.
Minus I H bar.
Commutator of X with P is I H bar.
Commutator of P with X is minus I H bar.
Each one of these
commutators here is just minus I H bar.
Minus I H bar.
H bar is just a number
and all of this is just equal to twice
minus 2 I H bar
times P.
Okay,
let's group it together.
On your formula of the second part
BCA
maybe that should be ACB.
Yeah,
I think so.
Well AB with C
is A
yeah,
yeah.
Sorry.
A with C times B.
Good.
Okay.
Alright,
let's group it together
and see what we have here.
We have I over 2 over P.
So we have 2M H bar.
And then we have minus 2I
let's just erase this
and put minus 2I H bar P.
I times I is minus 1.
That cancels this minus over here.
The 2 cancels the 2 over here
and the H bars cancel.
H bar cancels H bar.
2 cancels 2.
I times I is minus 1.
That cancels the minus here.
And what's the net result?
The result is P over M.
Average of P over M.
What have I discovered?
I've discovered that the average velocity
What is this?
This is just the average velocity of the particle
is equal to the average momentum divided by the mass.
Okay.
Not supr-
Wow,
is it surprising?
Uh,
not...
Perhaps it's not so surprising
because if it wouldn't have come out this way
we would have said something's wrong with the connection
between classical mechanics and quantum mechanics.
But it does come out correct
that the average velocity is the average momentum
divided by the mass.
Just as we would expect.
Now,
what about the average
what about the time dependence of the momentum?
It's the time dependence of the momentum
which is given by F equals M A.
Force is time derivative of momentum.
That's classical physics.
That's the interesting part here.
Let's see if we can recover Newton's equations
at least as an average.
At least as an average.
That's what we want to do is recover Newton's equations.
Newton's equation.
F equals M A.
So let's apply exactly the same rule
to the average of momentum
d by dp,
d by dt.
And that's given by
I over h bar
commutator of
P squared over 2m
plus U
plus U of x.
With what?
P.
Okay,
this time
it's the U of x which is important.
P commutes with P squared.
That's not there.
It's just the commutator of P with U of x.
So this whole thing is I over h bar
times
the commutator of U of x
with P.
Do you remember what the commutator
of U of x with P is?
Poising with P does what?
It differentiates with respect to x.
Poising with P differentiates with respect to x.
That was one of the first things we worked out
which has long gone off the blackboard unfortunately.
But commuting with P also differentiates with respect to x.
Well,
we worked that out.
that we work that out,
commuting a function of x with p
gives you the derivative of the function of x
and so this all gives us then i over h-bar
and then I can't remember,
then I think it's plus another i
times
h-bar times du dx,
right?
h-bar
h-bar cancels h-bar,
i times i is minus
and what we find out is
that the derivative of the momentum
is minus the derivative of u with respect to x
there's another word for the derivative
of u with respect to x
and it is force
yeah,
it's also the gradient,
force,
f
alright,
so first of all we find
that the velocity
of the momentum
is given by p over m
that's one of the two equations of Newton
actually,
the definition of momentum
and the other piece of it
is that the force
is equal to the time derivative
of the momentum
that's all the content of Newton's equations
force is derivative of momentum
it's actually mass times acceleration
since momentum we've already shown
is m times velocity
this says momentum
and this says force is m times the derivative
of the velocity
which is the acceleration
so we see that
the identification of minus i d by dx with momentum
and i d by dt with Hamiltonian
as energy
is a,
you can't call it a correct identification
what you can say
is that it's an identification which
in the classical world is called momentum
but when we look at it as effective
it's tablegraphing
where you get to the quartz
if the quadruple rate for this
the Challenger daqui
and then there's also longer you can revert to
show it's negative and there's some others.
If you do those,
are those all analogous?
Mm-hmm.
No.
Would you say that in
classical mechanics what you have is
a resultant force
whereas in quantum mechanics
you don't get a resultant force
because you have
the whole thing evolves.
The average
is a rough equivalent
of a resultant force.
What's a resultant force?
It has to do with adding vectors.
Well,
when you take the
gradient of a function,
obviously it has vectors pointing in
other directions.
Well,
here we're only doing one dimension
at the moment.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
Thank you.