Stanford University
Okay.
Alright,
so I figured I have to start with a review
because I do understand it's been two quarters since
you last had lectures from me on quantum mechanics.
On the other hand,
they can't spend the whole quarter doing that.
What I want to spend the quarter
on is the applications of quantum mechanics,
not the technology,
but the physics problems.
And the basic physics problems that
I want to go through this quarter
are those for which
quantum mechanics was originally invented,
discovered,
invented by...
I...
Einstein,
Heisenberg,
Schrödinger,
Pauli,
all those people.
Namely,
atoms.
Electrons.
I'm going to do atoms first,
and you say,
how can I do atoms first before I do electrons?
Electrons are a part of atoms.
It's alright,
we'll do a little bit about electrons,
just almost nothing,
but just enough to be able to write
down the basic equations of the hydrogen atom.
Discuss the hydrogen atom a little bit,
and then move on to further investigations of the electron.
And once...
And when we say the electron,
we're actually studying a class of particles,
not just electrons,
a wide class of particles which behave like electrons,
which include mu particles,
quarks,
other things like that.
And then,
the photon.
So it's going to be atoms,
electrons,
and electrons.
And photons.
But one of the themes that will recur is symmetries.
Symmetries of nature and how
symmetries are realized in quantum mechanics.
How symmetries are represented in quantum mechanics,
and what they tell us about the quantum mechanical system.
Symmetries in quantum mechanics
are an extremely powerful tool,
which...
I'm going to tell you what a symmetry is,
if you don't know what a symmetry is,
it's okay.
At the moment.
But let's begin with a very,
very lightening review
of the last quarter of quantum mechanics.
First of all,
the whole story begins by asking how
do you represent the state of a system.
We could go back a step
and ask what is a system,
but I'll assume you know what a system is.
And how do you represent the states of a system.
In classical mechanics,
the states of a system are represented as points
in phase space.
In quantum mechanics,
they're represented by state vectors.
The idea of a vector is not
a vector like a pointer in space,
pointing in a certain direction in space.
It's an abstract notion.
You can add vectors.
You can multiply them by constants.
And the mathematical structure of a state vector
is a mathematical vector in a vector space.
The vector space is not three-dimensional,
except in special cases.
It could be any-dimensional.
So we represent states
by state vectors,
and the symbol for a state vector
is Dirac's ket symbol,
ket,
K-E-T,
which is the latter half of the term braket,
like bra-ket or bra-ket.
Every state can be either represented by a ket symbol
or by a corresponding bra-vector.
Together,
we often put them together to form a braket,
or a bracket.
The bra-vectors are in one-to-one
correspondence with the ket vectors,
and you should really think of
them roughly as being the complex conjugates,
in the same sense as complex conjugates of complex numbers.
Complex numbers are ubiquitous.
They are part of the mechanism of the quantum mechanics,
and so are complex vectors.
So state vectors are represented by,
or states,
states are represented by state vectors.
The state vectors,
well,
we could say a little bit more,
but if I were to say the whole thing,
of course,
we would then go through the entire quarter,
so I won't.
In addition,
there are observables,
things that you measure.
Measurables are observables.
In classical mechanics,
there are also observables.
They're the things you measure,
but we don't spend a lot
of time talking about their mathematical structure.
We just assume you know what I'm talking about
when I say position of a particle is measurable,
or momentum of a particle,
or the energy of a particle,
or whatever.
In quantum mechanics,
we have to be very precise
what we mean by an observable.
And observables are represented by
linear,
Hermitian operators.
I'll label them with,
what are these?
Let's see.
These are Greek letters.
What kind of letters are those?
English?
Roman?
Latin?
I don't know.
Are they Latin?
Hmm?
It's capital alpha.
Yeah,
it's true.
It's capital alpha.
Okay.
But Latin letters are representing observables,
and they are
Hermitian operators that act on the vectors.
Hermitian,
for our purposes,
translates or is the quantum mechanical equivalent of real.
Real as in real or complex or imaginary.
They are the real operators
which are equal to their own Hermitian conjugate.
Every such operator
in the space of states is called an observable,
and presumably there is really a way to observe it.
The eigenvalues and eigenvectors
of these Hermitian operators play a special role.
So let me just remind you,
what is an eigenvalue and an eigenvector?
If you have a Hermitian operator,
you can search for vectors.
Let's label the vector.
Let's label it little a.
Or better yet,
alpha,
since we want to label it with a Greek index.
Let's label it with an alpha.
And a,
being an operator,
can act on alpha,
and alpha is an eigenvector of a
if the action is a.
So the action of a is just to multiply
the vector alpha by a number.
In this case,
I'm using a redundant notation,
the same notation for the eigenvalue and the eigenvector.
And this says that the eigenvalue,
the eigenvector alpha,
is an eigenvector of a with eigenvalue alpha.
And the significance of that equation
is that,
first of all,
the set of eigenvalues
of an operator,
or of an observable,
are the set of possible results of measurement.
If you have a quantity,
which when you measure it,
can take on the value 1,
3,
and 7,
then the eigenvalues of that operator
are 1,
3,
and 7,
and so forth.
The eigenvectors are the state vectors of the system
for which,
if you make a measurement,
the answer is definite,
not statistical,
determined,
deterministic,
and the answer to the measurement is alpha.
So I assume you all remember this.
I'm doing this mostly to just refresh your memory.
Now,
the particular systems
we're going to be discussing mostly in this quarter
are systems of particles.
Particles are largely characterized
by saying that things which are not things
which have a location in space,
an ordinary location in space.
For example,
if space is one-dimensional,
then a particle is a thing
which has a coordinate x.
It's located somewhere as an x.
If space is three-dimensional,
then particles move around.
They have x,
y,
and z,
and so forth.
Let's write formulas for the case of one dimension,
but I'll tell you what to do
for three dimensions in a moment.
Okay.
Oh,
sorry.
Let's come back to one point
that I need to emphasize.
For every bra and every ket,
let's call the bra,
let's call it phi.
It is not necessarily the particular bra
that goes together with psi,
with the ket psi.
For every pair like that,
there is an inner product.
There is a number.
That number is in general a complex number,
and it is represented as a number.
It is represented as the inner product.
Inner product.
And it's a number.
It's a number for every pair of vectors.
It represents a kind of product of the two vectors.
It's similar in its mathematical structure
to the dot product between two vectors
in ordinary space,
but it's a more abstract object.
It's the inner product between two vectors,
and it plays an important role
in the logic of quantum mechanics.
In particular,
if two states
are distinguishable uniquely
by the property that there's some observable
that you could measure
which would be different than the two of them,
let's suppose there's some quantity
that you could measure,
and it is definite
that the answer in the state psi
is different than the state phi,
then we would say those two states
are distinctly different.
There's no chance of confusing them.
There's a measurement you could do
to distinguish them.
Then those states are said to be orthogonal.
Orthogonal means physically identifiably different,
and mathematically,
it's the statement that the two vectors
have inner product equal to zero.
So,
orthogonality is a fundamental property
of relationships between vectors
which says that they are different.
You can't confuse them.
Well,
you can confuse them,
but you shouldn't confuse them.
Okay.
Now,
when it comes to particles,
the most important observable
is the position of a particle.
And so let's just discuss particles
moving on a line.
The line is the x-axis.
The location of the particle
is just a value of x,
and obviously,
x should be thought of
as an observable.
Okay.
In particular,
there are states
which are labeled by a value of position.
Let's call it x-naught.
This is the point x-naught over here.
I'm just using the naught here
to indicate a particular position.
There are states
which are labeled by x-naught,
which have the property
that if you measure the particle,
the particle's position,
you will definitely find it at x-naught.
Okay?
Good.
The next concept...
Oh,
and of course,
state vectors for different values,
let's call them x and x-prime.
If x and x-prime are two different positions,
x and x-prime,
then clearly those two states
are distinguishable,
operationally and by measurement,
they're distinguishable,
so these two states are orthogonal.
Now,
take any state,
any state whatever of this particle,
call it psi.
Its inner product
with the state representing the particle at x
is called the wave function.
The wave function of the particle,
and it's written as psi of x.
It's the psi that goes into the Schrodinger equation.
It's Schrodinger's psi.
I believe that Schrodinger was the first one
to call it psi.
P-S-I.
And the meaning of the wave function
is closely related to,
but not the same,
as the probability
that the particle is at position x.
Psi of x is an arbitrary function.
Well,
it's not completely arbitrary,
but let's say it's some function.
What does it represent?
Psi of x?
Psi of x is closely related to the probability
to find the particle at position x,
but it's not quite that.
The probability itself,
let's call it p of x,
is the product of the wave function
times its complex conjugate.
The wave function times its complex conjugate
is positive.
Any number,
any complex number,
times its own conjugate
is always positive.
Probabilities are always positive.
Psi of x's are generally complex numbers.
They can be positive,
they can be negative,
they can be imaginary,
they can be whatever you like.
So it would not make sense to say
that psi is a probability,
but it does make sense to say
psi times psi star is a probability.
Good,
all right.
That's the most important property of a particle,
that it has a position.
It has eigenvectors
which represent particles of known position.
And we can construct,
of course,
a position operator.
A position operator just multiplies
psi of x by x itself.
By x.
So that's the idea of position.
The other important observable for a particle,
of course there are many observables for a particle,
but the other particularly important one
is called the what?
The momentum.
In classical mechanics and in quantum mechanics,
positions and momentum come together.
Oh,
before we do that,
I should discuss the issue of a particle moving
not just in one dimension.
What happens if a particle is moving in three dimensions?
In other words,
like a real particle.
Then it has three observable positions,
the three components of its position,
namely x,
y,
and z,
if you like.
But since you can rotate axes,
you can just think of the position
as a point in three-dimensional space.
In that case,
we would just think of x here
as a point in three-dimensional space.
We could fill it out.
We could fill out the equations by saying
there are states which represent particles
at known locations in three dimensions,
x,
y,
and z.
This represents a particle located
at a point in three dimensions.
So,
we would have a point in three-dimensional space
over here,
x,
y,
and z.
And the rules would be similar,
very similar.
The inner products of x prime,
y prime,
z prime,
that would be zero if there's any mismatch,
not if x is not equal to x prime
and y is not equal to y,
but if the entire point,
if the entire point is not the same
as the point x prime,
y prime,
z prime,
then these are observably different positions
for a particle,
and the states are orthogonal to each other.
I'm going to suppress the y and z,
but keep in mind that the position of a particle
depends on the dimensionality of the space
that we're talking about,
and in the real world,
space is three-dimensional.
Okay,
for each component of position,
there is also a component of momentum.
In classical physics,
for non-relativistic classical physics,
the momentum is just the mass
times that component of the velocity.
In quantum mechanics,
the momentum is also an observable,
and is also represented by an operator,
by a Hermitian operator.
Hermitian operators can be thought of
in the abstract as objects of the same nature,
objects which act on mathematical vectors,
the space of states,
or they can be thought of more concretely
as operations on wave functions.
Either one.
You can think of them concretely
as operations that you...
What about x itself?
What is the operation
that represents the operator x?
Well,
it's just taking the state vector,
the psi of x,
or taking the wave function,
and multiplying it by x.
If psi of x is a function
representing the probability amplitude,
psi of x is called the probability amplitude
or the wave function of a particle,
then if you want to apply
the operator representing position
to psi of x,
you just multiply psi of x by x.
That's all.
The eigenvectors of x
are the wave functions
which are highly peaked,
very,
very narrow,
Dirac delta functions.
All right,
in the same way,
the momentum operator...
Now,
I'm not going to explain this in detail.
For this,
you go back to the lecture notes,
or to the lectures themselves.
What lecture was it that we talked about
about momentum?
Anybody remember?
Art?
Several of them,
but I think around eight.
Around eight?
Yeah,
yeah,
eight.
Eight was...
That's right.
I remember with great grief
lecture eight,
right?
Okay.
So the momentum of a particle
is represented by an operator called p,
and p also does something to psi of x.
What it does to psi
of x is it differentiates it.
It differentiates it with respect to x,
but not quite.
The real thing is that
it multiplies it by minus i,
the complex number i.
There's a factor of Planck's constant,
and that's the constant of the momentum.
So it's a constant,
h bar,
and then it differentiates psi,
d by dx,
psi of x.
That is the operator
that acts on wave functions
that represents the observable momentum.
Everybody remember this?
Yeah.
We went through it.
Okay,
now,
what about the eigenvectors of momentum?
The eigenvectors of position
are Dirac delta functions.
They are functions which are zero everywheres
except at the eigenvalue position.
In other words,
the eigenvector representing a particle
known to be at x-north
is a function which is zero everywheres
except at x-north,
where it's very high and very narrow.
Let's not worry about its precise mathematical definition.
It's called a Dirac delta function.
And it's not too hard to believe
that if the wave function of a particle
is so concentrated at a particular point,
that the probability for finding it
is zero everywheres except at that point.
That,
of course,
makes sense.
Now,
what are the states?
The states for which the momentum is certain.
In other words,
what wave functions correspond to particles
with definite momentum?
And those are gotten by solving the eigenvalue equation.
The eigenvalue equation is that p,
whatever it is,
in fact,
we know what it is.
Well,
let's write the abstract equation first,
that p on psi is equal to little p-naught,
times psi,
the eigenvalue being little p-naught.
Little p-naught is the value of momentum
that this particle has.
And in this particular state,
the momentum of the particle is known to be p-naught.
This equation translates,
just replacing p by minus i h-bar d by dx,
minus i h-bar d psi by dx,
is equal to p-naught,
the number,
a numerical number,
times psi of x.
Psi is a function of x.
Psi of x.
And this is easy to solve.
This is one of these equations which says
that the derivative of something
is proportional to that same thing.
Derivative of psi,
apart from a numerical number,
the numerical number we could
get rid of the i h-bar,
on this side,
it would reappear on this side,
this is the equation of the type
that represents an exponential.
The derivative of something is
proportional to the something itself,
and the solution of it
is e to the i,
p-naught x,
divided by Planck's constant.
Now I often get very tired of writing Planck's constant,
and I often just set it aside,
and I set it equal to one.
We'll sometimes do that,
in fact,
from,
I'll try to track it for the time being,
but later on I may just drop it.
And I think by the time I do drop it,
I will have done it enough times
that you'll know where the right,
the right place where it goes.
Question.
Yeah.
In the two equations you just wrote there,
the upper one with the,
with the kets,
that would say that those are,
or that's a eigenvector.
Yeah,
that says that eigenvector,
that psi is an eigenvector of p,
with eigenvalue p-naught.
But the one below holds for any wavefunction,
right?
Any,
you think any wavefunction is e to the i,
p-a,
p-x?
No,
no,
the equation before it.
Here?
Same holds for any wavefunction.
No,
most wavefunctions don't satisfy this equation.
Oh,
okay.
No.
In fact,
it's,
it's true for basically this wavefunction.
Okay.
Now,
you'll notice,
of course,
that there's a huge difference
between the eigenvectors of position,
which are these narrow little spiky functions,
and the eigenvectors of momentum in particular.
Let's take the probability that's associated
with e to the i,
p-naught,
x.
That's,
multiply it by its own complex conjugate.
What happens if you multiply
this by its own complex conjugate?
You get one.
e to the i something times
e to the minus i something
is just plain one.
So this wavefunction,
the one which represents a particle
with a definite momentum,
its probability distribution is smeared out
over the entire line.
By complete contrast,
the eigenvector of a particle located at a definite position
is highly concentrated,
infinitely narrow,
and this,
of course,
is a manifestation
of the uncertainty principle.
If you know,
well,
if you know the momentum of a particle,
then its position is completely uncertain,
and likewise,
if you know the position of a particle,
its momentum is also completely uncertain.
I'll refer you back to the lecture notes
for that purpose.
That's basically all.
That's basically quantum mechanics in a nutshell.
Question,
please.
I'm a little bit confused.
I thought you said this,
we know it's p zero.
Yeah.
So it's known.
Yeah,
the momentum is known.
The momentum is known.
Momentum.
But then when you try
to calculate the probability of this...
No,
no,
the probability for position.
What,
given that the momentum is p-naught,
now an experimenter is going to do an experiment
not to check its momentum,
but is going to do
an experiment which measures its position.
Two different kinds of experiments.
And that was phi of x.
Phi of x is the...
Sorry.
The probability,
amplitude for position.
That's right.
If the argument...
That's correct.
Now,
there is also a notion of an amplitude
for finding different momenta,
and I'll just remind you that's connected
to Fourier transforms of psi of x.
But I'm not going to do that now.
If we need Fourier transforms,
we'll come back to it.
At the moment,
Fourier transforms and the momentum representation,
this is called the position representation.
The representation of state vectors by psi of x's
is called the position representation.
There is also a momentum representation,
but it will take us too far field right now.
Question?
Yes.
What is the probability of the position?
Phi star psi of x.
If the psi function,
the wave function,
is the direct delta function,
what is it when you multiply that,
when you get the probability,
what does that look like?
It looks like the square of a delta function,
which is just higher than the delta function,
but it's concentrated at the origin.
It's concentrated at the origin,
and we have not talked about normalizing wave functions,
making the area under here equal to one.
That's a thing that we want to do,
but as I said,
I hesitate to go into any given thing too deeply
because we'll wind up doing the whole class again.
Yeah?
So these state vectors are
all represented by column vectors?
Is that it?
You can represent them by column vectors,
in other words,
but it would be a little awkward
to represent psi of x by a column vector.
x takes on a continuous infinity of values,
whereas the column vector is useful for a quantity
which takes on some discrete set of values.
So you can think of it formally in your head
as some kind of continuous column vector.
That's for the ket vectors,
and the bra vectors you
can think of as rho vectors.
Okay?
But when we need that,
I'll remind you.
By then,
you will have gone back and studied the lecture notes,
and you won't need it.
Okay.
Next thing.
How do things change with time?
Things do change with time,
and the evolution of a system with time
is a special case of transformations
that you can do on the state of a system.
That,
of course,
is also true in classical mechanics,
where the motion of a system
is represented as a transformation in phase space,
a transformation of the phase space position.
In quantum mechanics,
the evolution of a system
is a special case of a transformation
that you can do on the space of states,
taking every state to some other state.
And,
of course,
the idea is
very straightforward.
If the state at one instant of time
is some psi,
at some later instant of time
it is something else,
and that something else is a transform
or a transformation of the original psi.
There are some rules in quantum mechanics
about the nature of that transformation.
Oh,
that transformation depends on
the amount of elapsed time.
Okay?
If the amount of elapsed time
is very,
very short,
then you would expect this transformation
to practically be the identity transform.
In fact,
let's go back.
If the amount of time that's elapsed is zero,
then,
of course,
the transformation is completely trivial.
It just gives back the same state.
You can say in that case
that the transformation was just the identity operation
on the state vector.
But more generally,
the time evolution is characterized,
or the time evolution operation,
let's now call it operator.
It is an operator in the sense of operators.
It's an operator,
but it's an operator which depends
on the amount of elapsed time.
So let's give it a name.
It's usually called u.
u stands for unitary,
but we'll come back in a moment
for what unitary means.
And it's parameterized
by an amount of elapsed time.
And it's such that when it acts on a state
at a given instant of time,
it takes you to the state
at an amount of time t later.
So,
for example,
if it acts on the state
whatever the state happens to be
at time t equals zero,
then it will give you psi at time t.
It just updates the state.
If it acts on some state
which happens to represent things
not at time zero,
but let's say at time t1,
then it takes you to the state
at time t1 plus t.
In other words,
it represents the evolution
of the system from t1 to t1 plus t.
That's the notion of u.
That's the notion of a time evolution operator.
It's a linear operator,
but it is not a Hermitian operator.
What kind of operator is it?
Well,
now we need a postulate,
and the postulate is,
we can say the postulate very easily,
it goes back to this
minus first law of physics
that I harp on all the time,
that information is conserved.
In quantum mechanics,
what it means is that
if you start with two vectors,
two states,
which are observably different,
which cannot be confused,
in other words,
which are orthogonal,
and you let both of them evolve,
they will stay orthogonal.
It will not happen that two states
that are observably different
will evolve into states
which are not observably different.
All right,
so what that says
is that orthogonal vectors remain orthogonal.
In fact,
you can do a little bit better.
You can prove from that statement
that the inner product between vectors
is unchanged by time.
So let me just explore that idea a little bit.
Whatever u is,
it preserves the relationships
between pairs of vectors.
So for example,
if we start with psi and phi,
two vectors,
they may be orthogonal
or they may not be orthogonal.
If they're orthogonal,
this inner product is zero.
If they're not orthogonal,
it is whatever it is.
Then the postulate is that
if we transform psi
and we transform phi,
now,
phi is a bra vector,
and it transforms with a bra vector.
So what does that mean?
Well,
if we take the Hermitian conjugate of u,
that would be u dagger,
so,
phi,
what this equation says
is that the transform of psi,
when you take its inner product
with the transform of phi,
is the same as the inner product of psi
with phi in the beginning.
It says that the inner products between vectors
don't change with time.
That can only be true
for arbitrary pair of psi and phi
if u dagger times u
is the unit operator.
And that's called a unitary operator.
u dagger times u
is the unit operator
or the identity operator
or just one.
That's the notion of a unitary operator
and the time evolution,
in fact,
all transformations,
all interesting transformations
that you do on the space of states,
and we're going to talk about others
besides time evolution,
all interesting transformations,
ways of transforming vectors
into other vectors,
are unitary.
u dagger u is equal to one.
That's different than saying u is equal to one,
of course.
u is a unitary operator.
All right,
let's pursue it.
Yeah.
Question?
The way you first said it is
if psi and phi were orthogonal,
they would remain orthogonal,
but this is a stronger statement than that.
This is a...
Actually,
it's not.
You can prove that if u is a linear operator
and it maintains orthogonality,
then you can prove that it maintains
all inner products.
But this is the time evolution
of two state...
or two systems of different states.
Even if they're not orthogonal,
the overlap is conserved or whatever.
That's right.
And I said that's...
What you're saying is correct,
but I would say,
if the
if orthogonality is preserved with time,
then it's possible to prove
that inner products are preserved with time.
That's a little exercise.
First of all,
think about it
in just ordinary three-dimensional space.
Supposing you have some operation on vectors,
ordinary vectors,
which preserves orthogonality.
Okay,
what kind of operations,
operators on pairs of vectors
will preserve the fact that they're orthogonal?
Rotations.
Rotations,
right.
Rotations also have the property
that they preserve the inner products
or the dot products.
It's the same mathematics.
So this is the definition of a vector.
So if you have a unitary operator,
there are many unitary operators.
So there are many possible things
that could represent the evolution of a system,
but they're all unitary.
Okay,
let's...
Excuse me.
What would be an example of non-unitary transformation?
Oh.
Our mission operators are usually not unitary,
except that the momentum is not a unitary operator.
The position is not a unitary operator.
Uh...
Okay,
unitary operators are operators
whose eigenvalues are phases.
Everybody know what a phase means?
An e to the i times a real number.
A point on the unit circle.
A phase represents,
on the complex plane,
a point on the unit circle.
One is a point on the unit circle.
i is a point on the unit circle.
Minus one and minus i.
One over the square root
of two times one plus i
is a phase.
The unitary operators
are the analogs for operators of phases.
Their eigenvalues are all phases.
So if I have a unitary operator
and I look at its eigenvalues,
they will be points sprinkled around
on the unit circle.
That's why they're called unitary,
because in some sense their length
or the magnitude of their eigenvalues is unit.
Okay.
Now let's...
Let's see what more we can learn about u
from making some reasonable assumptions.
The first reasonable assumption
is that if t is equal to zero,
then u is just equal to zero.
So u is equal to one.
All it says is that if
you don't allow any time to elapse,
the vector just comes back to itself,
and u is equal to the unit operator.
So u of zero
is equal to i,
the identity operator,
the operator whose matrix representation is just one,
one along the diagonals.
It's just the operator which does nothing.
It just takes the thing back to itself.
Now is u unitary?
Sure it is.
The Hermitian conjugate of u
is the Hermitian conjugate of the identity operator,
which is just the identity operator itself.
And identity times identity is just identity.
So yes,
one is one,
or the unit operator is unitary.
And it's...
It's the time evolution when no evolution happens.
Okay,
what about evolution by a vector?
A very,
very small amount of time.
Okay.
So let's instead of writing u of zero,
let's write u of epsilon.
Take u of epsilon.
It is not one.
Something happens over time evolution,
but it is close to one.
It's close to one.
That,
of course,
is an assumption.
That's the assumption that systems evolve continuously,
that they don't make radical jumps
over very,
very short periods of time.
And it is an assumption.
It's an assumption ultimately
which is justified by experiment.
All right.
So that says that u of a small time epsilon,
if we were to expand it in small epsilon,
would be one plus something proportional to epsilon
times an operator which is a finite...
operator.
The smallness of epsilon is represented by epsilon here
times something which I'll temporarily call h,
but it's a wrong identification.
In a minute we're going to change it.
Okay.
Let me not call it h.
What's another letter?
Give me another letter quick,
quick.
Yeah,
G.
Good.
All right.
So u is of this form.
There's nothing wrong with this.
This is a correct thing.
The only question is what do we know about G?
So let's write down u conjugate,
permission conjugate of epsilon.
That's equal to one plus epsilon times G conjugate,
the permission conjugate of G.
And now let's multiply these together
and insist that the answer,
the leading order in epsilon is just one.
Okay.
So that will say that one plus epsilon G dagger
times one plus epsilon G is equal to one.
Looks a little queer.
One times one is one.
So what's left over,
what's left over is epsilon times G dagger plus G.
And that must be zero.
To order epsilon,
working to order epsilon,
the condition that u is unitary
is the condition that G plus its own permission conjugate
is equal to zero.
In other words,
getting rid of the epsilon,
that the conjugate of G
is equal to minus G itself.
Operators with this peculiar problem
have to know that this is a pure imaginary thing.
Do you know numbers that have that property?
Do you know any number that has the property
that it's minus its own complex conjugate?
It is true,
but there's a wider class of them.
Pure imaginary things.
So this is the analog
of G being pure imaginary.
If we multiply it by I,
it becomes permission.
This is called anti-permission.
Permission is when G dagger equals G.
Did we write that someplace?
Yeah.
A equals A dagger is an observable.
G dagger equals minus G.
We can fix that very simply.
Just define G dagger to be,
now do I want plus or minus?
I always forget.
It always takes me a minute or two to,
I want to write one plus I epsilon H.
But I think the right answer is minus.
That's a,
whether you put a plus
sign or a minus sign here
is a convention,
complete convention.
It defines H.
This one becomes one plus I epsilon H.
H dagger.
And the condition just becomes that H equals H dagger.
In other words,
if I put a minus I epsilon H,
no,
plus I epsilon H dagger,
minus I epsilon H,
then the condition that U is unitary
is just the condition that H is Hermitian.
In other words,
that H is an observable.
Yeah.
What assumption are we making
that allows us to ignore the epsilon squared term?
We're just working to order epsilon.
We could work to order epsilon squared,
but then we would have to be consistent about it
and put an epsilon squared term in here.
The epsilon squared term that we
would want to put in here
would be minus epsilon squared.
So we would have to put in here
epsilon squared over two times H squared.
But we consistently work to one power in epsilon
and assume that epsilon is small enough
that we can ignore epsilon squared.
We can do that consistently.
We've done it over and over and over.
But then you're perfectly right.
We do have to come back
and check that the formulas make sense to higher order.
And they do.
I'll discuss that a little bit.
But working systematically to order epsilon,
and dropping anything of higher order in epsilon...
I just wondered if we
were following the details of it,
we'd have to say that H is approximately hermitian
or something like that.
Yes.
Well,
okay.
With this definition,
you would say H is approximately hermitian,
but allowing...
Notice that epsilon factors out
of both sides of this equation.
So once it's factored out,
it just says that H...
No,
I think the thing which is approximately
approximate is this relationship here.
Yeah.
And I'll come back and tell you what to do
if it...
I'll tell you the right formula
in a little while,
at some point.
Okay,
so what do we learn?
We learn that the...
that the unitary time evolution
which contains a U of T
also is specified
in terms of a certain observable
that I've called H.
H stands for Hamiltonian.
It also stands for hermitian,
but it stands for Hamiltonian.
It is the Hamiltonian of quantum mechanics.
And so we come to the conclusion
that there exists an H,
we will call it the Hamiltonian,
and it is related to the time evolution
for small time intervals
by one minus I epsilon H.
What is the general equation
if epsilon is not small?
Incidentally,
if epsilon is not small,
we might want to call it T.
We might give up calling it epsilon.
Epsilon is usually reserved
for a very small quantity.
We might try writing U of T,
but this wouldn't be right
for large times.
It wouldn't be large for large times.
Let's see if we can improve it a little bit.
Well,
you know,
I think I won't spend time at it.
I will just tell you the answer.
The answer is
that this really should be written
as E to the IHT.
Now,
why do I...
Let me just say a word or two about exponentials.
If you have an exponential
E to some small number,
and let's just call the small number epsilon,
where epsilon is small,
times an ordinary number,
and let me call the ordinary number little h.
Epsilon times h is a small number.
For a very small epsilon,
E to the epsilon h is 1 plus epsilon h.
Does everybody know that?
That's the formal Taylor series expansion
of keeping only the first term,
assuming the second term
and higher terms are negligible.
Now,
supposing you want to take...
You want to make epsilon a little bigger.
Instead of just epsilon,
I want to take E
to the 2 epsilon times h.
E to the 2 epsilon times h
is just the square of E to the epsilon h.
E to the 2 times something is just a square,
so it's equal to 1 plus epsilon h squared.
Supposing you do this over and over and over,
which incidentally is equal to
1 plus 2 epsilon h
plus epsilon squared h squared.
But this is still an approximation.
This was an approximation to this.
This is still an approximation to this.
Here's a theorem
that if you do this over and over enough times,
let's say n times,
E to the epsilon times n times h,
such that epsilon times n is finite.
In other words,
epsilon times n,
epsilon is an infinitesimally small number,
but I do it enough times
so that n times epsilon is a finite number.
Namely,
t,
I do this over and over.
What happens,
excuse me,
let me go back.
Let's do it this way.
1 plus epsilon h,
and I do this a number of times,
a large number of times n,
such that n times epsilon,
equals t.
What do I get?
Anybody know?
It's a binomial expansion.
Well,
it's a binomial expansion,
but it's also a construction
of the exponential function.
Okay.
It's a rigorous theorem that
as epsilon gets small
and n gets large,
in such a way that
n times epsilon is kept fixed,
this just becomes
E to the,
h,
t.
Say it again?
One person talk.
I think it's right.
Right.
And the way you can just understand it
is by saying that for small epsilon,
1 plus epsilon h
is the same as
E to the epsilon h,
and if you take it to the nth power,
the epsilon just multiplies the n
and becomes t.
Okay.
So I will tell you right now
the generalization of this
for finite times,
this will be a minus sign here,
1 minus IHt
for finite t
really becomes E to the minus IHt,
and this is an important fact,
but,
for small intervals,
small epsilon,
we can just be consistent
and work to order epsilon.
We'll find out everything we need to know.
Okay,
so there's a concept now of a Hamiltonian.
Let's see if we can
understand this equation a little bit better.
Let's take the wave function psi,
or the state vector,
state vector psi,
at a time t plus epsilon.
I am starting at time t
with a certain wave function,
and I'm allowing it to change
over a tiny time interval.
What is the answer to this?
The answer to this is that it is equal
to E to the IH epsilon
times psi at time t.
Let's just see what I did.
Minus or plus,
sorry,
minus,
minus here.
Starting at time t,
let's update by a small little time epsilon
the rule is we multiply by U of t.
Sorry,
U of epsilon.
We're updating by an amount of time epsilon,
and that's equivalent to multiplying by
E to the minus IH epsilon times psi of t.
So this is the rule for going from a time
to a neighboring time.
But now let's write that out as
1 minus IH epsilon
times psi of t.
And let's write this side,
I'm not going to,
forget the,
okay,
yeah,
let's put them in.
And this one here is
psi of t plus epsilon.
Now let's multiply out.
1 times psi of t is psi of t,
but let's take that over to the left-hand side.
That'll give us psi of t plus epsilon
minus psi of t.
Just the term coming from 1.
The term coming from 1
will give us the difference between
psi of t plus epsilon
minus psi of t.
You see where we're going.
We're building a differential equation
for psi.
Psi of t plus epsilon minus psi of t
is just equal to minus IH epsilon psi of t.
And finally,
divide by epsilon.
Okay,
what's the left-hand side?
The left-hand side is the time derivative
of the state vector psi.
And the right-hand side is
just minus IH psi of t.
Okay,
so that leads us,
finally,
to the Schrodinger equation.
The Schrodinger equation says
that the psi by d...
The psi by dt,
this could be a wave function
or it could be the state vector.
I will leave the notation a little bit abused.
I won't bother writing the ket vector here.
It stands for both the equation
for the state vector
or the equation for the wave function itself.
The psi by dt
is equal
to minus IH psi.
If you want to put vectors in,
if you want to turn it into an equation
for a state vector,
you put
ket notations there.
Otherwise,
it's just the equation for a wave function.
This is the Schrodinger equation.
This is the time-dependent Schrodinger,
Schrodinger equation.
Okay,
this is
Schrodinger equation
time-dependent,
the TdSe,
time-dependent Schrodinger equation.
And what it tells you
is how the state vector changes
as a function of time
if you are so lucky to know
what the Hamiltonian is.
Hamiltonian is a Hermitian operator
and you can make all kinds of quantum mechanical systems
just to play with by choosing different Hs.
We did this last quarter.
Okay,
what about the time-independent Schrodinger equation?
The time-independent Schrodinger equation
is just the statement that H
is a Hermitian operator.
It has eigenvalues.
It has eigenvectors.
Its eigenvalues are the observable
values that you would get if you measured H.
And what are they called?
They have another name.
Energy levels.
Incidentally,
I promised you that I would keep around
Planck's constant,
and I've already dropped it.
It goes over here.
It goes over there.
I don't promise by any means
that I will be consistent about Planck's constant.
Yes,
I will be completely consistent
by choosing Planck's constant
to always be equal to one.
Sometimes I'll put it in,
sometimes I won't put it in,
but I will never confuse it with
I or the square root of two.
Okay,
so that's the time-dependent.
The time-independent Schrodinger equation,
that's just the eigenvalue equation
for the eigenvalues of H.
And all it says is that H
on an eigenvector of the energy,
a state with definite energy,
is equal to E times the energy,
E being the eigenvalue of H.
So this equation here
is the equation which tells you
how to find the states
and the values of energy that go with them
that correspond to states of definite energy.
You solve this equation,
and it gives you a whole bunch of possible eigenvalues
and eigenvectors.
Those are the eigenvectors and eigenvalues
of the energy operator.
Okay,
and again,
we went through this,
we did some examples last two quarters ago.
On the other hand,
this equation
tells you how the state vector changes with time,
and as you can see,
it's the same H
in both equations,
so the question of the energy levels
of a system are intimately bound up
with the way that the system changes with time.
Okay,
so...
Good.
And that's quantum mechanics in a...
I said before it was quantum mechanics in a nutshell.
Well,
it's a slightly bigger nut,
but that's it.
That's what you need to know.
That's a summary of a quarter's worth
of quantum mechanics.
Any questions?
Okay.
Can you...
If in the time-dependent equation...
Time...
It's the time-independent Schrodinger equation.
If in the time-dependent Schrodinger equation,
you replace psi with E...
Psi with E?
Yeah,
can you do...
Then you can drop the ket things.
Right?
Then it becomes just an equi...
a differential equation,
because H times E will be just E times E.
No,
we...
no.
We don't want to drop the ket symbol.
Leave the ket symbol there.
All right,
leave the ket symbol there for the moment.
What we can do is we can ask
how a eigenvector changes with time.
That we can do.
So we can plug in here,
and we can ask how the eigenvector changes with time,
and the answer is that
the eigenvector will change with time
by just multiplying it by I times the energy level.
That's what tells us how eigenvectors change with time.
Anybody remember the answer,
how an eigenvector changes with time?
It just gets multiplied by E to
the I times the energy times time.
Okay,
so that...
We can go through that.
We don't need...
It's in the notes.
Go back to it and check it out.
All right,
now,
the time evolution is one example
of transformations that you can do on a system
which preserve certain facts about the system,
in particular which preserve
the inner products between vectors.
In other words,
which preserve the logical relationship
between vectors,
preserve the notion of orthogonality,
preserve the notion of vectors being the same vectors,
and that kind of...
There are many other kinds of transformations
that you may want to do on a system.
In particular,
among them are symmetry transformations.
We will need to talk about symmetry transformations.
Now,
I will tell you where we're going.
One of the most important symmetries of nature
that occur over and over and over again
in all sorts of contexts,
but in particular in the theory of atoms,
is rotational symmetry.
A atom,
in particular a hydrogen atom,
a hydrogen atom is an electron moving
in a central force field.
The equations of a hydrogen atom are rotationally symmetric,
and that's because the potential energy,
the Coulomb potential,
is rotationally symmetric.
It's a central force.
And so hydrogen atoms,
and basically all systems in nature really,
but hydrogen atoms in particular,
enjoy rotational symmetry.
If you rotate...
All it means is that if you rotate your coordinates,
the description of the hydrogen atom doesn't change.
Or another way to say it
is if you rotate the hydrogen atom,
it's still a hydrogen atom.
It may or may not be the same state,
but it's still a hydrogen atom
described by the same set of equations.
So the notion of a symmetry
is central in quantum mechanics.
It is also in classical mechanics,
but it comes up and
really hits you over the head
in quantum mechanics.
And we need to explore,
largely for the purposes of understanding
rotational symmetry,
we need to understand the concept of a symmetry.
So I'm going to spend 15 minutes
explaining exactly what a symmetry is.
Keep in mind,
if you want to keep one in mind,
there are two that you can keep in mind
for just to have something in your head.
One of them is rotation symmetry,
where it just says that if you take a system
which satisfies a certain set of equations,
and you rotate it,
physically rotate it,
physically rotate it about an axis,
you may or may not change it.
I can tell you this,
if you rotate me,
you'll change me.
You will.
If the Earth weren't here,
and I was in outer space and free space,
then the Lennard equation,
whatever the equation governing me is,
would be the same for the rotated or the unrotated.
Another way of saying it is I couldn't tell
whether I was rotated or not.
If you rotate me and then just go away,
I can't tell that I was rotated
because the equations that govern my metabolism,
my internal structure and so forth
are exactly the same as had I not been rotated.
Okay,
so rotation symmetry is one example.
Another example is translation symmetry.
If you take me in outer space,
and you set me down,
and you say,
how do I feel?
I feel fine.
You take the same state,
but you translate me over by a meter,
and you ask me how I feel,
I say exactly the same as I felt before.
It's a symmetry.
On the other hand,
there are situations
where translations may not be a symmetry.
You know,
if there was a furnace over there,
a fire,
hot fire,
and you put me over here,
and you said,
how do you feel?
I feel fine.
Now translate me over to here,
how do you feel?
Well,
I don't feel so fine.
So the presence of an object
may break translation symmetry.
On the other hand,
if you think about it a minute,
wait a minute,
what if I really translate everything,
me and the furnace?
Then we restore the translation symmetry.
So symmetries are operations,
or there are operations that you can do
on states of systems,
and if the operation doesn't change,
the equations doesn't change,
the properties of the system doesn't change,
the way you describe the system,
then that transformation is called a symmetry.
For a free particle,
for any ordinary system,
if it's out in outer space,
far from anything else,
and you translate it,
that's a symmetry.
You rotate it,
What if you squeeze it,
change its dimensions by squeezing it?
That's generally not a symmetry.
You know,
if you take a crystal of rock salt or something,
and you squeeze down on it
and compress it by a factor of two,
it doesn't behave the same way.
So there are all kinds of things
which are not symmetries.
Nevertheless,
there still may be operations
that you can define,
but they may not be symmetries.
Okay,
let's talk about the condition.
Let's first of all try to quantify that idea.
We have states.
Let's...
The generic or typical state of the system
that we're interested in is called psi.
We're going to do an operation on it.
That operation might correspond to rotating the system,
it might correspond to translating the system,
or it might correspond to something uglier than that,
like squeezing it or stretching it,
but doing something to it.
And let's represent that
by...
an operator v.
I use v because I've already used u,
but I intend it to be a unitary operator.
Why a unitary operator?
Well,
if I really have a symmetry,
and I have two states
which are different than each other,
I apply the symmetry operation,
I expect them to stay different.
If there are two states of...
of me,
happy me and sad me,
they're different from each other,
they're observably different,
there's an observable that you can measure,
the happiness operator,
and they're different.
If you then rotate the state
out in outer space,
the distinction should remain.
So that means that orthogonal states
should remain orthogonal
when you do a symmetry operation,
and that says that the operator v should be unitary.
So v is unitary,
and it represents
v equals v dagger v equals 1.
I don't use u because I'm saving u
for the special case of time translation,
of evolution.
Okay.
Now,
let's suppose...
Yeah.
This is a little bit tricky,
so we'll...
There's u's and there's v's,
and it's quite tricky.
It takes me half an hour each time
I try to do this to get it right,
but it's also very,
very simple.
Okay.
Let's suppose that a wave function
or a state vector,
I'll use them interchangeably,
let's call it psi 1,
under time evolution,
becomes psi 2.
If I take psi 1
and I allow it to evolve with time,
let's represent that by putting a little u here.
u represents time evolution.
v does not.
v is something else.
And if I take psi 1
and allow it to evolve
for a certain amount of time,
it will become psi 2.
Okay.
So that's under u.
Another way to say that over here
is that u on psi 1
is equal to psi 2.
That's all.
Evolve psi 1 for a little bit of time,
and you get psi 2.
Okay.
Now,
let's imagine the transformed version of this.
Transformed,
it could be by rotation,
it could be by translation,
by some symmetry,
by some symmetry operation.
What does this equation say for the transformed things?
Well,
let's call this psi prime.
Now,
there are too many.
Let's keep in mind exactly what's going on here.
1 and 2 represent some initial state
and some final state.
Evolution from one to another.
Prime and unprimed represent the
action of the symmetry operation,
which could be rotation.
Could be rotation or it could be translation.
Okay.
Here's what I maintain.
If there really is a symmetry,
then psi 1 prime...
If we were talking about rotations,
then psi 1 prime is just
the rotated state of psi 1.
Psi 1 prime will evolve...
to...
the rotated version of psi 2.
Let's see what that says.
Okay.
If I evolve myself...
over a period of time,
and I'm in some state,
and I get some other state,
I go from happy to not so happy.
Then,
when I rotate myself,
I should also find,
under the same evolution,
that I go from the rotated happy state
to the rotated not so happy state.
That's what it really means to have a symmetry.
That the evolution of the transformed...
state behaves the same way as the original state.
It's a little bit tricky.
Okay.
Let's see if we can make
an equation out of this now.
Yeah.
Okay.
So,
the first row here
is just the equation that psi 2
is u psi 1.
That's what this says.
The second equation...
Let's go to the second equation.
To go from unprimed to prime,
you multiply by v.
So,
the second equation here says that
v is the relative of psi 1 prime.
v,
it says that...
I'm sorry.
This always confuses me.
It says that psi 2 prime
is equal to u times psi 1 prime.
So,
I'm going to do a little bit of math here.
To go from 1 to 2 is time evolution.
To go from unprimed to prime is v,
is the symmetry operation.
All right.
So,
psi 1 prime is v times psi 1.
All right.
So,
we have uv times psi 2
is u times psi 1 prime
and psi 2 prime.
And psi 1 prime is v times psi 1.
Okay.
That's the right-hand side.
The left-hand side is v on psi 2,
but psi 2 is u times psi 1.
So,
after perpetual confusion
that has...
It stumps me every time I try to do this
on the blackboard.
What it says is that
if a thing is a symmetry,
in other words,
if it preserves the way evolution takes place,
if it's a transformation
which preserves the time relationships between vectors,
then it says that v times u
must be equal to u times v.
This,
of course,
must be true for every state
if it's to be a true symmetry of nature.
A true symmetry of nature,
rotation symmetry,
for example,
is not something which only applies
if I'm standing vertically upright.
It should apply to any particular state
of the system.
And so,
if v times u
on any psi 1
is equal to u times v on any psi 1,
what it says is that symmetries of nature
are such,
they're operations,
they're v's,
unitary operators,
which commute
with the time evolution operator.
For all t?
For all...
Time.
Yes,
in fact,
for all time.
We'll see,
it's enough for it to be true for one time
and it will be true for all time.
But yes,
that's correct.
Okay.
So,
unitary operations,
things you can do to the state vectors
which preserve orthogonality,
which commute with the time evolution operator,
are symmetries
that preserve the evolution,
the evolutionary relationships.
So physically you're saying
you can rotate and then wait,
or you can wait and then rotate.
Exactly.
The words are very simple
and they make perfect sense.
And...
Yes,
that's exactly what it says.
Okay.
So how do we identify symmetries?
We look for operations
which commute with a time evolution operator.
Now,
remember that the time evolution operator
is itself...
Let's take the limit of a small time evolution
just to analyze it a little bit.
This says...
Well,
first of all,
yeah,
okay,
it says that v times 1 plus i epsilon h...
1 minus i epsilon h,
is equal to 1 minus i epsilon h,
this is the first order again,
times v.
I'm just expanding it out.
The first order is good enough.
It gives us everything we really want to know.
First of all,
v times 1 is equal to 1 times v,
so those cancel.
And what it says is
that minus i epsilon v h
is equal to 1 minus i epsilon h,
which is equal to 1 minus i epsilon h v.
Well,
canceling out the minus i epsilon,
it says that v commutes with the Hamiltonian.
Okay.
Let's cancel out these things,
the minus i epsilons.
A symmetry is a unitary operation
which commutes with the Hamiltonian.
Any unitary operation which commutes with the Hamiltonian
is a symmetry,
and any symmetry is a unitary operation
which commutes with the Hamiltonian.
That's very abstract.
That's extremely abstract,
and in order to appreciate it,
we have to do a couple of examples.
We'll do some examples in a moment,
but let's just focus on that,
that unitary operations on the space of states
which commute with the Hamiltonian
are symmetries.
What limited v to being unitary?
What limits?
Sorry.
What required that v is unitary?
Oh,
yeah.
A symmetry,
whatever a symmetry is,
it preserves logical relationships
between the vectors.
So it's an assumption.
It's an assumption that the symmetries of nature
take orthogonal states to orthogonal states.
Okay.
That seems plausible.
A symmetry should not take two states
which are distinctly different from each other
and act on them to give states
which are not distinctly different from each other.
You wouldn't call that a symmetry.
You could say mutually exclusive.
Yeah.
Mutually exclusive things should stay mutually exclusive.
Right.
Okay.
So we now have an abstract mathematical definition
of any symmetry operator,
of any symmetry.
This will become much clearer
when we do some examples.
Symmetry,
commutator of h with v
is equal to zero.
That's what it says.
Do you remember from two quarters ago
what the commutator of a thing with a Hamiltonian is?
The time derivative of it.
Yeah.
So what this says
is that whatever the operator v is,
it's conserved.
Conservation of a certain quantity,
in this case v,
meaning that it commutes with a Hamiltonian,
is the same as saying there's a symmetry.
You've seen this before in classical mechanics.
What's the connection between symmetries
and conservation laws called in classical mechanics?
It's called Noether's theorem.
Right?
It's much simpler in quantum mechanics.
We don't need any fancy Lagrangian or anything else.
All we need to know is that
time evolution commutes with
the symmetry operation itself.
And that can be read in two different ways.
It can say that doing the symmetry operation,
well,
it says what it says.
It can be read two different ways,
but they both say the same thing.
Okay,
so that's...
Now let's go one step further.
There are different kinds of symmetries.
Let me give you some examples
of two different kinds of symmetries.
There are discrete symmetries
and there are continuous symmetries.
Let me give you an example of a discrete symmetry.
Think about reflection in a mirror.
Reflection in a mirror takes a
right hand to a left hand.
Okay?
That's the mirror image of a left hand
as a right hand.
That's a discrete operation.
It takes left to right,
but there's nothing sort of in between.
It's just a discrete operation left to right.
Let me give you another example of a discrete operation.
Let's suppose we have a pair of electrons
or a pair of particles.
A pair of particles,
and they happen to be
the same kind of particle.
A pair of electrons or a pair of protons.
Then if I take the two particles
and I interchange them,
whatever the state is,
I interchange one particle with the other particle.
That's a symmetry.
Why?
Because the particles are of exactly the same kind.
A proton over here and a proton over here
is the same as a proton
over here and a proton over here.
That's just interchange of them.
Those are discrete operations.
Discrete operations means
that there's sort of nothing in between.
Or let's say heads and tails.
Just say heads and tails.
A head and a tail.
If the coin happens to have no markings on it,
whether it's heads or tails,
and you turn it over,
then the physics of the coin and the flipped coin
are exactly the same.
Those are discrete operations.
By discrete,
I mean in distinction
to continuous operations.
Continuous operations are like rotation in space.
Rotation in space,
you can do a very small rotation.
Small means one by a very small number
at a very small angle.
In fact,
you can go further.
You can say that every rotation about an axis
can be built up by tiny rotations
about that same axis.
That means that the rotations have a continuity to them
that the flip of a coin does not have.
Flip of a coin is
either its heads or its tails
and there's nothing in between for classical coins.
For systems in three-dimensional systems,
you can rotate them.
You can rotate them by 90 degrees.
That's a transformation.
But you can build up that 90-degree rotation
by lots of little infinitesimal transformations.
Those are called continuous symmetries.
What about translation symmetry?
Is translation symmetry continuous or discrete?
Well,
it's continuous.
You can take any translation of a system
and think of it as being compounded
in a way that it's not continuous.
You can build up a lot of small transformations
out of lots of small translations.
The continuous symmetries are the ones,
in particular,
the rotation symmetries
and translation symmetries,
are the ones I want to focus on.
What do we know about continuous symmetries?
We know we can build them
out of lots of little elementary small transformations.
So let's focus on the small transformations.
We're going through basically the same manipulations
that we went through over here.
Time translation is a continuous thing.
You can build up a time translation by 10 seconds
by thinking of it as lots of little time translations
by microseconds.
And that led us to the conclusion
that u's are related
to her mission operators
through this relationship here.
Exactly the same is true
of every continuous symmetry.
Exactly the same thing is true.
Every continuous symmetry
can be thought of as being built up
by little infinitesimal ones
which have the form 1 minus i epsilon
not times a Hamiltonian,
but something,
some her mission operator.
Let's call it G.
G stands for generator.
And what we're thinking about now
is a symmetry transformation,
but one of them which is very close
to being the identity.
Such a transformation
can always be represented
as something close to the unit operator,
and close to the unit operator
means just shifted by a small amount.
By the same argument
that told us that H is her mission,
G is also her mission.
Symmetry operations,
which are continuous,
can be represented in terms of
infinitesimal transformations
which are generated by a generator G.
And if we plug this into here,
and we then write
the commutator of H
with 1 minus i epsilon G
is equal to 0,
what does that say?
What's the commutator of H with 1?
Commutator of anything with 1 is 0.
Everything commutes with a simple,
with the operator 0.
The i epsilon,
that factors out,
and what it tells us is that
symmetry operations are generated by,
this is what it means to be generated by,
generated by means can be built up
by lots of little ones,
they're generated by things
which commute with the Hamiltonian.
So,
if you want to find all of the symmetries
of a problem,
you'll start looking around
for all the things which commute
with the Hamiltonian.
There's another feature of things
which commute with the Hamiltonian.
Do you remember from last quarter?
It's true both in,
yeah,
what was that?
They're conserved.
So,
conservation and symmetry
are closely connected.
If you want to find all of the symmetries
of a problem,
it's equivalent to finding
all the things which are conserved.
All right,
now this was very abstract,
and so we need to do an example or two
to get the idea.
Let's do an example.
And let's begin with translation.
Translation of a particle
from one place to another.
Okay.
Translation of a wave function.
We want to take a wave function.
Here's a wave function.
And we're going to move it a little bit.
We're going to translate it.
To a new wave function.
And we want to find out
what operation does that.
If we have a psi of x,
what operation do we do
to translate it
to a new position?
We're going to take that new position
to only deviate by a small amount,
by amount epsilon.
But we know what the answer is.
The answer is psi of x
goes to
psi of x plus epsilon.
Epsilon now could be a large number.
We're just translating by a large number.
But specifically,
I want to think about
the case of a small translation.
Translation by a little bit.
Okay.
So,
psi of x,
in other words,
we can write that the translated wave function
is a small number.
In fact,
we can write it this way.
Whatever v is,
whatever v is,
we haven't figured out what v is yet.
But whatever v is,
it acts on psi of x
to give us
psi of x plus epsilon.
That's pretty easy.
That's what a v is.
That's what the v does in this case.
It acts on psi of x
and it translates the wave function
by amount epsilon.
Okay.
Now,
if epsilon is small,
we can also write that this is equal to,
psi of x plus the derivative of psi
with respect to x times epsilon.
So,
what v does,
what v on psi does
is it gives back the same psi
plus something proportional to the derivative.
Okay.
That suggests,
it doesn't suggest,
it proves
that whatever v is,
is it's the unit operator.
That's the first term here.
It acts on psi of x
to give back psi of x
plus a small change.
And the small change is epsilon
times the derivative operation.
I haven't written on x,
we could write on x,
v,
sorry,
times psi.
v is the derivative of psi.
So,
is the unit operator
plus epsilon times the derivative operator.
We can act on any wave function
and what it will give us
is the wave function infinitesimally displaced.
Okay.
Now,
what about d psi by dx?
What about d by dx?
d by dx is an operator.
It operates on wave functions.
It's a linear operator.
It's connected with the momentum operator.
Remember the relationship.
The momentum operator p
equals minus i h bar d by dx.
All right.
So,
what do we want to do?
We want to write,
let's multiply by i.
Get rid of the i here
and divide by h bar.
Differentiation is i over h bar times momentum.
So,
let's write this that way.
One plus epsilon i epsilon
over h bar times the momentum.
We now have an example
of a infinitesimal symmetry operation.
By infinitesimal,
I mean just by a little bit of a shift.
And we found out what its generator is.
The g.
Where was it?
Did we have g here?
Well,
yeah.
v is 1 minus i epsilon g.
In this case,
I would have much preferred that I defined things
so that this came out to be minus here.
But,
You lost the minus sign up here.
Yeah.
So,
みんなの胸を開く
The momentum definition.
Hmm?
Yeah.
Oh.
Upper right.
Yeah,
this one.
I think that's right.
The minus sign.
Yeah.
大家
No,
that's right.
What about by minus r?
You think this is wrong?
No.
That's right.
So let's see.
So I substituted.
I think I got this right.
Wait,
wait,
sorry,
did I?
Yeah,
that's right.
Do you disagree with this?
No,
I think it's right.
All right.
Now,
I think if I shift
the wave function to the right,
if I shift the wave function to the right,
that's really putting a minus sign here.
Yeah.
Yeah,
I made a mistake in
defining a shift to the right.
It looks like it should be x plus epsilon,
but psi of x goes to psi of x.
So psi of x minus epsilon.
So this is actually a minus sign here.
If you track that through,
we will find out
that there's a minus sign here.
Yeah.
OK,
so it identifies for us what the symmetry generated
g is for translations.
And what is it?
It's the momentum divided by Planck's constant.
All right.
Momentum divided by Planck's constant.
We can write that the generator of translations,
here's the language,
the generators of,
the generator of x translation is p sub x,
p sub x,
strictly speaking,
divided by Planck's constant.
We can drop the Planck's constant.
I will drop the Planck's constant.
And as a matter of fact,
the definition,
the official definition really doesn't
have the Planck's constant in it.
But there's an example.
There's an example,
p of x.
Now,
is p of x,
is the momentum along the x-axis conserved?
Depends on the Hamiltonian.
It depends on the Hamiltonian.
So let's write down a Hamiltonian.
The Hamiltonian for a free particle,
a particle moving in empty space
with no forces acting on it,
h,
in that case,
is just p squared over 2m.
The momentum squared divided by twice the mass.
If this is a one-dimensional problem,
then it really is just px,
just the x component of momentum.
Does the x,
does the Hamiltonian commute with p?
Well,
that becomes equivalent to the question of whether px
commutes with px squared.
Yes.
Every operator commutes with every function of itself.
p of x commutes with p of x squared.
It commutes with p of x cubed.
It commutes with any function of p of x.
So for a free particle moving along the x-axis,
we first of all find that the momentum is conserved.
And of course,
we also have a translation symmetry.
The translation symmetry is just the fact
that the free particle will behave the
same way wherever you start it.
If you start it here and it gets to here,
then if you start,
change the starting point,
it'll just,
everything will just translate.
Okay,
so that's,
that's an example.
P is both a conserved
quantity and the generator of translations.
What if there are more directions of space?
If there are more directions of space,
and if there are more directions of space,
then there are several symmetries.
You can translate along the x-axis.
You can translate along the y-axis.
You can translate along the z-axis.
In that case,
the Hamiltonian becomes px squared plus py
squared over 2m plus pz squared over 2m.
And the translation symmetry along
the x-axis is still just px.
Translation along the y-axis,
the generator is py and so forth.
And each of them commutes with the Hamiltonian.
So this is an example of
the connection between symmetries and conservation laws,
which is very simple.
The next time,
it looks like we're about out of time,
the next time we will do rotation symmetry.
Rotation symmetry is much,
it's much more interesting,
it's much more involved,
it,
and it will bring us
to the subject of group theory.
There's some group theory.
There's some group theory here,
but the group theory is completely trivial.
The next time,
we will talk about rotations in space.
And what's interesting about rotations in space
is they don't commute with each other.
A rotation about x followed by a rotation by
y is not the same as a rotation by y,
a rotation by x.
And that will give us the idea of non-commuting symmetries.
Symmetries,
collections of symmetries which
don't commute with each other,
and when we find those,
we're going to have a rotation.
So,
the question is,
they have power.
They have real power to tell us about
all kinds of physical properties of a system.
Okay,
so next time,
rotation symmetry.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.