Stanford University
Okay,
if we're ready,
let's go then.
We talked last time about angular momentum operators.
And I started to show you how
the algebra of the angular momentum operators works,
how multiplets with different angular momentum
have certain numbers of states,
and the states form,
they're called multiplets.
I'll come back to them in a minute,
but let's just talk more generally
about what angular momentum is about.
A good example is an object,
a particle,
moving in a central force field.
Here's the center.
Particle.
Particle moves around in a central force field.
It has a radial position and an angular position.
The angular position really means two angles,
an azimuthal and a polar angle.
So it's a three-dimensional system.
And the angular momentum is conserved.
The angular momentum is a vector,
and the angular momentum always is
in the plane perpendicular to the motion.
Plane perpendicular to the orbit.
So there's the angular momentum.
The orbit,
the orbital plane is perpendicular to it.
And because the angular momentum is conserved as a vector,
the orbital plane is also conserved.
The orbital plane stays the same,
but of course the radial
position moves around in a circle.
Not a circle,
take it back.
Moves around in some orbit.
That's classical.
Quantum mechanically,
the particle is described by a wave function.
The angular momentum operator has to do
with the angular dependence of the wave function.
In general,
the wave function in a situation like this
would be a function of position,
of course.
It's always a function of position.
Could be a function of x,
y,
and z.
But you could also write it
as a function of the angular momentum.
It's a function of the radial coordinate,
the radial distance,
and two angles,
polar and azimuthal angle.
We talked a little bit the first time,
maybe the first time,
maybe the last time,
I can't remember.
We talked a little bit
about angular momentum in two dimensions.
Let's go back to that for a moment.
If everything was in two dimensions,
then the angular momentum would just be
the generator of rotations about the perpendicular axis.
And its structure as a quantum mechanical operator
would just be angular momentum is equal to minus i
times the derivative with respect to the angle.
That's the analog of momentum being minus i
times derivative with respect to position.
What it tells you is how
the wave function changes with angle.
So let me just remind you,
if you look for angular momentum eigenstates,
then what you're looking for is functions
which satisfy minus i d by d theta,
let's say functions of r and theta.
In two dimensions,
we don't have to worry about phi,
just r and theta.
And if we're looking for
an eigenvector of the angular momentum,
we want to set that equal to a number,
the eigenvalue,
l times psi of r and theta.
It's a little differential equation,
and it doesn't really depend on r.
r is just a spectator here.
r,
the derivative is with respect to theta.
So this is an equation about the theta dependence,
and it doesn't really care about r.
We know what the solution of equations like this is.
The solution is psi equals e,
to the i,
l,
theta.
e to the i,
l,
theta,
where l has to be an integer,
an integer in order that the
wave function comes back to itself
when you go around a closed curve.
Well,
what about the r dependence?
What should the r dependence be?
This doesn't tell you what the r dependence is.
So the answer is,
you have an angular momentum eigenfunction,
no matter what,
let's not use the same function,
let's use a different function,
let's call it chi of r.
Any wave function that looks like e to the i,
l,
theta,
it doesn't matter what its r dependence is,
it will be an angular momentum eigenstate.
So angular momentum has to do with the angular dependence
of the wave function.
The,
um,
the radial dependence is irrelevant to the angular momentum.
It may be relevant to the energy,
but it's not relevant to the angular momentum.
And the same is true in three dimensions.
In three dimensions,
angular momentum also has to do
with the angular dependence,
and there are particular wave functions,
generally,
arbitrary functions of radius,
doesn't matter what they are,
times specific functions,
they're usually called y,
of theta and phi,
which are analogous
to the e to the i,
l,
thetas.
And those wave functions
are the things
which determine the angular momentum of the state.
They're the things which change
when you rotate the configuration,
and angular momentum has to do
with rotating conditions.
So when we talked about angular momentum eigenstates,
we were really talking about
these functions of theta and phi.
Now,
it's awkward to worry about theta and phi.
We don't have to.
What we did last time was
we used a bunch of tricks.
So let me go back
to those tricks and remind you,
but keep in mind,
at every stage,
what we're talking about is the angular dependence
of wave functions.
Okay.
Let's recall what we learned last time.
We started with the angular momentum operators,
Lz,
Lx,
Ly.
We found out that they have certain commutation relations,
Lx with Ly,
equals I,
Lz.
There's H bars in here,
but I'm not going to belabor them.
I don't care about them right now.
Lx,
Ly equals I,
Lz,
and cyclic permutations to more like it.
Then we started to play some games.
We played some games because Dirac taught us
to play those games,
not because any of us would have been smart enough
to figure them out ourselves.
I don't know,
maybe we would have,
who knows.
But the trick was to construct,
well,
to pick one of the operators
and work in the basis of that operator.
In other words,
pick Lz
and work with eigenvectors of Lz
with eigenvalue M.
We don't know offhand what the spectrum of eigenvalues is,
but let's just postulate
or let's just define the eigenvalues to be little m.
Forget for the moment whether they're integers or not.
They may or may not be integers,
but this defines the eigenvector of Lz
with eigenvalue M.
We worked in that basis and we found,
to our great joy,
that the operators Lx plus or minus I,
Ly,
which we called Lz,
L plus or minus,
had some nice properties,
were useful.
I'm not going to write down the properties.
You have them written down from last time,
I hope.
They follow,
the properties follow.
It's commutation properties.
They follow from the commutation properties of the Ls,
but here's what we learned.
We found out that if we start
with an eigenvector of Lz with eigenvalue M,
and we hit it with L plus,
I guess,
forgot whether we put the
pluses and minuses upstairs or downstairs,
doesn't matter.
What did that do?
That gave us another eigenvector
with M plus one.
We worked out that was a consequence
of the simple algebra of these commutation relations.
We worked it out by just
sticking in the equations.
It was a couple of lines.
And we found out that L plus
is a raising operator.
This is called a raising operator.
If this line represents the
spectrum of possible values of M,
zero,
and so forth,
this tells us that we found another eigenvector,
which is one unit up.
It has not yet told
us anything about whether the M's
are integers or not,
but it tells us that if we find one,
we can find another one
by hitting it with L plus.
Likewise,
we can find another one
by hitting it with L minus.
So L pluses and L minuses
are operators which take you up and down
the spectrum of eigenvalues of Lz.
Okay,
that was the first thing that we discovered
from the algebra of these things.
The next thing we asked was,
well,
does this go on forever and ever and ever?
It will go on forever and ever and ever
unless it comes to an end.
How can it come to an end?
The only way it can come to an end
is if L plus,
instead of giving
another non-zero eigenvector,
gives us zero.
That's the only way it can come to an end.
And if it does come to an end,
and typically they do come to an end,
if it does come to an end,
that's the end of the spectrum of raising
that you get by raising,
and let's suppose that's over here.
Then,
we have things separated by an integer,
but we have one more thing that we know.
We know that the z-axis,
that there's nothing preferential
about the plus z-axis.
If we simply rotated the whole picture around
and replaced the plus z-axis
by the minus z-axis,
all the rules would be the same.
So for that reason,
the spectrum has to be symmetric
about the origin.
Anything you can say about Lz,
you can say exactly the same thing
about minus Lz,
because they're just related by rotation.
So if the spectrum ends at some point here,
it has to end going downward
at exactly the same point,
except reflected.
Now,
each action of L plus or minus
displaces you by an integer.
How is it possible to come to an end
with the ends being symmetric like this?
If they have to be integers.
For example,
if this point was at three quarters here,
and you kept going down,
down,
you would never come to minus three quarters.
Is that right?
Yeah.
You'd never come to,
yes,
you'd never come to minus three quarters.
The only way that it can happen
that you can end and be symmetric
is if you start at an integer,
that's one possibility.
Let's say this is integer two here,
and then end at minus two.
That's one possibility.
And the only other possibility
is that you start at a half integer.
For example,
the simplest case
would be
that the spectrum ends at a half
and ends in the other direction at minus a half.
That's still separated by an integer.
In that case,
L plus would take you
from the lower state to the upper state.
L minus would take you
from the upper state to the lower state.
But what would happen if L plus
hit the upper state?
It would give zero.
If L minus hits the lower state,
it would give zero.
So that's the way we know
what the spectrum of the angular momenta is.
The spectrum is either integers or half integers.
And each collection of states like this
is aitez.
Let's say that this
was actually the state of the initial
how long did it emanate and
how much time did it do,
how long did it take each state to
1,
2,
3,
and over here.
So there'd be how many states?
7 states here.
7 possible states.
The highest state has the
maximum value of M before it's
killed by the next action of the operator.
The maximum value of M is
called L.
L equals the maximum value of
M for that particular collection of
states.
Minus L is of course the minimum value of M.
And so the values of M go
from minus L to plus L,
and then nothing beyond that from above,
nothing beyond it
from below.
How many states is that all together?
7 states.
And so the values of M
go from minus L to plus L.
And then nothing beyond that from above,
nothing beyond it from below.
How many states is that all together?
If you go from minus L to plus L,
2L plus 1.
Okay,
so a multiplet,
a collection of
states,
is characterized with a given value of,
well we'll see what they have a
given value of.
But a collection of states of this type,
a multiplet,
has
typically 2L plus 1 states,
and a collection of states of this type,
a
collection of states of this type.
So it basically is two L plus 1 states.
Two L plus 1 states.
That's the first thing we find.
Or an infinite number of states?
Could have it,
that's the other.
Sure.
That's just L equals infinity.
Right.
But that is a possibility.
It is a possibility.
But,
um,
It's a possibility.
It's not one that we're going to worry about
the pathological
The reason they're pathological
for a variety of reasons
The number a lot of the reasons that they're pathological
but among other things energy usually
depends on the angular momentum as
You increase the angular momentum keeping
other things fixed the energy goes up
and
And
If you're interested in states of finite energy,
then you're not interested in
states with infinite angular momentum
Okay,
let's do one more little exercise
What characterizes these multiplets well,
I'll tell you what characterizes these multiplets.
It's the magnitude of the angular momentum
All of the states
In this 2l plus 1 collection have the
same value of the magnitude of the angular momentum
Now what do we mean by
the magnitude of the angular momentum?
We mean by the magnitude of the angular momentum
is exactly what you would mean in classical physics
Or I should say the square
of the magnitude of the angular momentum.
It's the magnitude of
the angular momentum vector squared and
that's equal to LX squared plus ly squared plus
LZ squared
The only difference between classical physics
and quantum physics is these are now
Operators,
they're not just numbers in the usual sense.
They're quantum mechanical operators and let's
see what we can find out
about L squared in
particular L squared from multiplet of
2l plus 1 states in other words supposing we
have a multiplet which terminates from above at L
terminates from below at minus L
What can we say about its L squared?
Okay,
so here's the tricks and they're all tricks,
but they're nice tricks
This is equal to LZ squared
Now first classical
LX squared plus ly squared that's plus
LX plus Ily do I want that?
No,
I want LX minus Ily
I
Times LX plus Ily
This is LX squared plus ly
squared and the cross term zero classically
So this is a correct equation classically.
It's not quite right quantum mechanically and the
reason is that LX and ly don't commute
We actually have an extra term here.
We have the extra term.
Let's see what it is.
It's I
LX ly
That's this product and then minus Ily LX
So it has the commutator of LX ly in it.
Sorry the commutator of
LX and ly
Yeah
In other words we've overshot by writing
in LX minus Ily times LX plus Ily
We have to subtract this
minus I
Commutator LX
LX
That's just the extra piece that's there because LX
times ly is not equal to ly times LX
Okay,
so that's straightforward
But what is the commutator of LX with a y?
LX with ly is I LZ
so
This is equal to LZ squared
Now we're going to get an I from the LZ.
There's an I here and then
there's another I from the commutator
I times minus I is plus 1
so this will give me plus LZ
LZ squared plus LZ and then we
have plus L minus times L plus
Okay,
you with me?
That's L squared the square of the angular momentum
Now let's apply that let's
take this operator and apply it
to the maximum highest M state
M equals L M equals L
M equals L
So let's take this L squared
on
L
L is the highest state there.
Okay,
what do we get?
We get LZ squared on L
plus LZ times L
plus L minus L plus
L plus L minus L plus
times L
Okay,
first of all,
what is this script L here?
It's an eigenvector.
Remember what it stands for
It stands for the eigenvector of LZ
with the highest possible value in this multiplet
What is LZ?
LZ is equal to little L
The state up here LZ is equal to little L.
Let's just go back a minute
Too many letters.
I'm sorry for so many letters,
but that's just the way it is
LZ or the state M was
defined to be an eigenvector of LZ
That's what this says
In particular,
the top eigenvector here
We can just substitute for M
We substitute L
So here we have it
LZ on L is just
the numerical number L on L
What about LZ squared?
L squared on L
It's just L squared.
You're just hitting it with the operator LZ twice
The first time you hit it,
it gives you an L
The second time you hit it,
it gives you another L
So that's L squared
Okay,
that was easy,
but what about this here guy?
What are we going to do about it?
It's zero
Why?
Because L plus
When it hits the top
Runs out of states
That was the definition of the top here
The definition of the top state
Is that L plus gives zero
So,
we can just erase this
And now we've learned something
That this state L is an eigenvector
Of the square of the angular momentum
Let's write it this way
Let's write it down
L squared plus L
Times L
Or better yet
L times L plus one
Just to remind you where it came from
An L squared came from here
And an L came from here
L squared plus L is L times L plus one
So what do we find?
We find out
That the states in this multiplet here
The top state there
The top,
the highest state there
Has an eigenvalue of L squared
Which is L times L plus one
The square of the angular momentum for that state
Is not little L squared
It's almost just little L squared
There's a little quantum correction here
If we were doing classical mechanics
We would expect that the square of the angular momentum
Would just be the square of the angular momentum
About the Z axis for the top state there
Incidentally,
the highest state
Is like the state rotating about the Z axis
Where all of the angular momentum
Is in the vertical direction
That's why it has the highest value
In the other direction it would be smaller
Okay,
so we find a little surprise
It's not just L squared
It's L times L plus one
But then there's another surprise
And this is something
This is a nice little exercise for you
Do it yourself,
it's very easy
But I'll let you work it out yourself
Every one of these states in this same multiplet
Have exactly the same value of L squared
They all have the same magnitude
For the square of the angular momentum
Basically what this multiplet is
Is it's a quantum mechanical version
Of a state with a given angular momentum
Except in any possible direction
They all have the same L squared
The same square of the angular momentum
But they have different projections
Onto the Z axis
What's new in quantum mechanics
Is that the projection onto the Z axis
Is quantized
Comes in integer multiples
Okay,
so that's
That's what we know about angular momentum
Question?
Yeah
Could you state a little bit
I don't understand the words that you said
In terms of the little exercise
Oh,
okay,
good
Yeah
Here's the exercise
Okay
Let's
Good
What we've shown is that L squared
On the maximum of the Z axis
Is equal to L times L plus 1 on L
In other words that
This eigenvector here
Happens also to be an eigenvector
Of the square of the angular momentum
Next step
I would like to show
That L minus 1
Also equals L times L plus 1
Times L minus 1
In other words,
that the next state down
has exactly the same value for L squared.
Okay?
How do you do that?
Well,
you say
start with L squared,
and now hit this
with L minus on L.
L minus on L is the
state L minus 1,
and we want to prove
that that's equal to L times L plus 1
times L minus on L.
That's the thing you
want to prove.
Okay.
Can anybody guess how
to prove it?
Does the algebra here suggest
anything?
I'll tell you what it suggests
to me.
It's
suggests to me that we figure out what
the commutator of L squared with L minus
is.
Imagine we discovered,
imagine we
discovered a marvelous fact,
which I'm
not telling you is true.
It's true,
though.
That L squared and L minus commute.
Supposing we discovered that.
Then I
could say that this was also equal,
trying to prove this relationship,
of
course,
to L squared.
I would then say
that this is equal to L minus times L
squared L,
right?
But what's L squared on
L?
Let's see,
what do we want to do here?
Um...
Okay.
So,
what do we want to do here?
Um...
What do we want to do here?
If this commutes with this,
we can push this
through here.
That's then equal to L times
L plus 1.
Yeah,
we would have proved this
relationship.
We would have proved this
We would have proved that
this is equal to L minus times L times L
plus 1 L,
which is exactly what this says.
Okay.
So,
if we can prove that L squared
commutes with L minus,
then we can prove
that the state L plus 1 is also an eigenvector
of L squared.
What about L minus 2?
What about the next state down?
Same thing.
We just go down until we run out of states.
Um...
Here's the...
Okay,
here's the exercise.
The exercise is to find the state L plus 1.
The exercise is to prove that L squared
commutes with any one of the components
of angular momentum.
Let's call it L sub i.
L x L y L 0.
If it commutes with any of the components,
then it will certainly commute
with L plus and L minus.
L plus and L minus is just L x
plus i or plus or minus i L y.
So,
there's an exercise to prove that L squared
commutes with any one of the...
L's.
Um...
Alright,
so here's what we found from
the things that I showed you plus
the little exercise that you can do yourself.
Is that when you find a multiplet like this,
going from L to minus L,
such that there's no more above
it and no more below it,
you've found not only eigenvectors of L z,
eigenvectors for which L z is equal to M,
but you've also found eigenvectors of
the square of the angular momentum
with eigenvalue L times L plus 1.
Where L is just the maximum value of M.
So,
for each one of these little L's,
there are two L plus 1 states,
and they all have the same squared value.
So,
what's the same squared angular momentum?
Roughly speaking,
they have the same squared angular momentum
because they're just tilted tilts
away from the vertical axis.
That's a rough statement.
That's...
Quantum mechanically,
it's a little trickier than that.
But that's the classical analog.
That,
uh...
That by rotating and changing the
z component of the angular momentum,
you haven't changed L squared.
Okay.
So,
that's what we know about angular momentum multiplets.
Yeah.
Um,
can you raise the board to show your factorization?
So,
when you factored L x squared plus L y squared,
you could have just as fairly gotten
L plus L minus as the operator.
And then I would have had the opposite sign here.
Okay.
Yeah.
It would have given you exactly the same thing.
If you had the L minus to the right,
you would want to hit it on
the lowest state instead of the highest state,
but the sign of this would change.
It would all work out.
It would all work out the same way.
It's a good question,
but...
Uh...
Okay.
So,
what we found is that there
are collections of functions of the angles.
These eigenvectors are functions.
They're functions of the angles.
Why?
Because rotation only affects the angular dependence.
They're functions,
and what characterizes them?
A value of M,
the eigenvector of L z.
So,
whatever they are,
they're functions which have a little subscript M,
and that's the z component,
but they also have...
They're also eigenvectors of L squared,
or in other words,
they can be characterized by a little L.
And they're called Ylm,
and they're functions of theta and phi.
You know what these things are called?
Ylms of theta and phi?
Spherical harmonics.
They're functions on a unit sphere.
Functions of theta and phi.
And they're the analogs on the sphere of
e to the plus or minus il theta.
il...
il theta.
They're the three-dimensional analogs.
This is the two-dimensional functions.
Strictly speaking,
these are functions on a circle,
so they're one-dimensional functions.
But think of them as functions for a two-dimensional sphere.
So,
if you look at the three-dimensional problem,
these are the corresponding
functions for the three-dimensional problem.
And we don't really care very
much about exactly what they are.
We're going to finesse exactly what they are.
We're never going to really need it.
We could figure out what these functions are,
but we're never going to need it.
All we ever have to really know is that
for every little value of L,
there are two L plus one of them.
The two L plus one
of them have magnetic quantum numbers,
M,
that range from zero to L and to minus L.
And that the square of the angular
momentum is L times L plus one.
That's all we're ever going to have to really know.
Um...
to do atomic physics.
Okay,
any questions about the structure of angular momentum?
Well,
I think we're going to have to
look at the structure of angular momentum.
the structure of the angular momentum multiplets.
And they all have the same energy.
They all have the same energy,
and the reason is
because the angular momentum commutes with the Hamiltonian.
That means,
when you apply L to a function,
it doesn't change the energy.
So they all have the same energy.
At least for a problem of a central force.
For central force,
the angular momentum commutes with the Hamiltonian,
and that's enough to prove that
all of these have the same energy.
Okay.
No questions?
We'll move on.
In fact,
let's move now to the central force problem.
Now,
I'm going...
I'm not going to take you through
all of the manipulations involving partial derivatives,
all over the place with respect
to theta and phi and so forth.
We're going to do this by
using a little bit of intuition
from classical physics,
and work out with a tiny bit of cheating.
The cheating is going to be to use classical physics
to make a guess or two,
but the guesses are well motivated,
and we can do this rigorously.
What is it we want to do?
We want to solve the Schrodinger equation
for a problem with a Hamiltonian,
which is p squared over 2m.
Now,
p stands for the three components of momentum.
So it's a vector,
p squared over 2m,
kinetic energy,
plus some potential energy
which only depends on the radius.
Central force problem.
Later we'll be specific about what central force is,
central force problem.
Of course,
what we're going to think about is the Coulomb force.
But for the moment,
let's not specialize.
And let's do classical physics first.
Okay,
first statement,
the angular momentum is conserved.
Now,
you could check it.
You could work it out by
working out the equations of motion
and seeing that the angular momentum is conserved.
You can also just say angular momentum is conserved
whenever you have rotational symmetry,
and that's correct.
The same statement as saying
that you have momentum conservation
whenever you have translation invariance.
It's Noether's theorem.
Classically,
quantum...
Thank you.
Heavy,
heavy scone.
That's a good scone,
man.
All right,
so let's believe angular momentum is conserved.
Angular momentum is a vector,
oops,
excuse me,
r cross p.
It's conserved.
That means its magnitude is conserved,
but also its direction is conserved.
And that means,
as I said before,
that the plane of the orbit is also conserved.
So once we know the plane of the orbit
is also conserved and that everything is rotationally symmetric,
we might as well classically put
this whole thing in the xy plane.
So there's our orbit.
Orbits do not have to be circles.
Most orbits are not circles.
In fact,
for a general problem,
most orbits are not circles.
Most orbits won't even be closed.
If you take a general potential,
most orbits will not be closed.
They will...
They will precess about...
The axis of the orbit will precess.
We're not going to worry too
much about whether the orbits are closed.
It's not our concern right now.
Now,
next.
Let's look at an orbit.
Here's r.
And let's put the momentum over here.
The momentum is along some direction.
It's in the plane because we know
that the motion is in a plane.
So it's in the plane
and it's pointing in some direction.
It may or may not be perpendicular to r.
In fact,
it could even be...
The velocity could be along r.
There are orbits,
for example,
which just go back and forth through the origin.
So there's no rule that says
that the momentum is perpendicular to r.
There is a rule that says the angular
momentum is perpendicular to both r and momentum.
But that's...
We're finished with that.
Okay,
let's take the momentum vector
and decompose it
into an angular part.
Let's call it the theta component,
p theta.
And a...
A p r component.
So the momentum has two components.
One along the angular direction
and one along the r direction.
What about p squared?
p squared is the sum of
the squares of both of them.
So h is p r squared
plus p theta squared over 2m.
And that's it.
Well,
what about the angular momentum,
the magnitude of the angular momentum?
The magnitude of the angular momentum
is p theta times r.
Is that clear to you?
P theta times r is the angular momentum.
R cross p.
R cross p,
the magnitude of it
is the magnitude of r
times the magnitude of p theta.
So the magnitude of the angular momentum
is equal to p theta times r,
everybody magnitude,
p theta times r.
Or another way to write it is that,
first of all,
L squared is equal to p
theta squared times r squared.
And now let's write p theta squared is L squared
over r squared.
That was easy.
And let's stick it into the Hamiltonian.
pr squared plus p theta,
this is not,
I'm sorry,
you didn't correct me,
plus V of r.
Okay,
pr squared,
well that's just pr squared.
h is pr squared over 2m.
What about p theta squared?
p theta squared is L
squared divided by r squared plus V of r.
Let's erase all of this.
Now look at what we have.
We have a problem which
for all practical purposes could be
thought of as a problem in one dimension,
namely the radial direction,
pr squared,
plus a potential energy V of r,
plus another term in the potential energy.
Remember that L is conserved.
So once you pick L,
you're going to have a problem.
Once you know what the angular momentum is,
it doesn't change on you.
So once you know what it is,
you can freeze it.
And you can say the Hamiltonian of the system
is just pr squared as though it was just a
one-dimensional problem,
plus an extra term which
goes like 1 over r squared,
plus the
original V of r.
What is this term called?
Physically,
what is it?
Is it attractive or is it repulsive?
Repulsive.
How do you tell whether it's attractive or repulsive?
It's attractive.
Why do you think it's attractive?
Potential energy.
1 over r squared gets bigger as you move away.
So,
sorry,
r squared gets bigger as you move away.
1 over r squared decreases as you move away.
So which one is attractive?
So which way is this force pushing you?
Forces push you toward smaller energy.
Forces always push you toward smaller energy.
That's why they're minus the derivative
of the potential with respect to position.
This is pushing you away from the origin.
What kind of thing is this,
pushing you away from the origin?
There was nothing in this problem
that pushed you away from the origin.
What is it?
Centrifugal force.
Yeah,
sure.
It's centrifugal force.
Or this is the potential energy.
It's the energy that's
associated with the centrifugal force.
And it gets very big when r gets small.
When r gets small,
for fixed angular momentum,
it really repels you away from the origin.
And so if an object comes in
with a given amount of angular momentum,
it can't get very close to the origin.
What it does is swing around the origin.
Okay,
so this is what keeps the
particle from getting to the origin.
And it is the centrifugal force.
There's only one situation where it's not there.
When is it not there?
For l equals zero.
Right?
And then for l equals zero,
we're talking about an orbit
which just goes through the origin.
Back and forth and back and forth through the origin.
It has no angular momentum.
And this term isn't there.
But as long as there's any momentum,
it's not there.
If there's any angular momentum,
then it can't get to the
origin because there's this huge repulsion.
It's not a real repulsion.
It's the centrifugal force.
But it's there.
P of r.
What about P of r?
That's just the momentum associated with the r direction.
Okay?
Let's go one little bit more with the classical physics.
Let's plot this effective potential energy.
This becomes the effective potential
energy for the one-dimensional problem.
It has the ordinary potential
energy plus the centrifugal barrier.
This is called the centrifugal barrier.
And it looks like this.
Let's suppose V of r is attractive.
For example,
it could be the attraction
of the electron to the proton.
Uh...
Then V of r would look something like that.
Let's do it a little better.
V of r would be negative because it's attraction.
And it would be 1 over r.
So it would look something like this.
Now,
what of...
That's V of r.
What about L squared over r squared?
Well,
depending on L,
whether or not...
For any L except L equals 0,
it's going to blow up at the origin,
like 1 over r squared,
and then fall quickly to 0.
In fact,
if V of r is the Coulomb potential,
it goes like 1 over r,
it falls more slowly than the centrifugal barrier.
Centrifugal barrier falls very quickly to 0,
1 over r squared,
and V over r a little more slowly.
What does the combination of them look like?
Well,
the combination of them...
Which is dominant at small r?
For small r,
which one is bigger?
1 over r squared or 1 over r?
1 over r squared is much bigger.
So,
very close to the origin,
this is the dominant thing.
What about for large r,
if V is 1 over r?
Supposing V is the Coulomb potential.
1 over r is bigger than 1 over r squared.
So,
asymptotically,
far out,
the Coulomb potential wins.
And what happens in between?
What happens in between looks like this.
Okay,
so what kind of motions do you have?
We have an effective problem,
which is completely one-dimensional now.
It only depends on the r-axis.
And all of the angular story is fixed
by the angular momentum.
So,
once you know the angular momentum,
it becomes a one-dimensional problem.
What do you think motion
in this kind of potential looks like?
Well,
the simplest kind of orbit,
or the simplest kind of motion,
would just be equilibrium
down at the bottom of the potential.
That's an orbit in which r doesn't change.
It's a circular orbit.
Okay,
that's a circular orbit.
What other kind of orbits can you have?
Well,
what other kind of motions could you have?
in a potential which looks like this,
basically you can have oscillations,
back and forth.
Oscillations which go back and forth
take the particle from a minimum distance
from the origin to a maximum,
and back again.
So these are orbits
which go from a minimum distance
to a maximum distance and back again.
For the Coulomb potential,
they would be the elliptical orbits.
All right.
And that's the classical physics.
In a nutshell,
that's the classical physics.
What about the quantum physics?
For the quantum physics,
we have a wave function.
Wave function,
instead of,
we don't have a particle position,
we don't have a momentum,
we have a wave function.
And the wave function is
psi of r and also angles.
But the angular structure
is totally taken into account
by knowing the angular momentum.
If we know the angular momentum,
then we know that the angular part
of the wave function is just one of these
spherical harmonics,
which I've erased,
but,
that's gone.
But we don't have to worry about it.
It's a one-dimensional problem,
psi of r,
and what does it satisfy?
It satisfies the Schrödinger equation
that h on psi of r,
let's say the time-independent
Schrödinger equation.
What is the time-independent
Schrödinger equation?
What do you put on the right-hand side?
The energy.
And it determines the eigenvalues
and the eigenvectors of energy.
Now what is h?
h begins with pr squared.
What is pr?
pr is of course
i h bar d by dr.
As always,
in quantum mechanics,
a component of the momentum
is i h bar times derivative
with respect to the corresponding coordinate.
So,
pr squared,
here's pr squared,
pr squared is going to equal
minus,
because of two factors of i,
h bar squared,
I'm putting in the x,
h bar is now,
second derivative with respect to r.
That's the first term in the Hamiltonian.
I left something out.
I left out twice the mass.
Whose mass might I be talking about,
incidentally?
The planet Mercury?
More likely the electron for this discussion.
But it could be the planet Mercury too.
I don't think we would bother doing
quantum mechanics then.
d second by dr squared.
That's the first term in the Hamiltonian.
The second term in the Hamiltonian
is exactly what's written there.
Plus,
1 over 2m,
l squared over r squared.
But what is l squared?
Now we come back to here.
l squared is not little l squared,
it's l times l plus 1.
Why?
Because this is the square of the angular momentum.
What appeared there was the square,
it was lx squared plus ly squared plus lz squared.
And so this becomes l
times l plus 1
over r squared.
That's one of the effects of quantum mechanics.
Just to change
l squared to l times l plus 1.
And finally,
l squared plus v of r.
v of r.
And you can plug in your favorite potential into there.
What do we do with it?
We act on psi.
And psi is now a function of r.
Psi of r.
Equals e psi of r.
And that's our Schrodinger equation.
The solutions of that equation
are the eigenvectors of energy
with given angular momentum.
And the eigenvalues are the energy levels.
I have a feeling I left
out some h-bar squares in here.
I probably did,
because where did it come from?
It came from p theta squared.
It's probably an h-bar squared in here,
too.
If you track it.
I think.
Yeah.
Yes.
Alright,
that's what we would like to solve.
We'd like to solve this,
find the energy levels of an atom.
We would like to find
the wave functions of an atom.
We'd like to know what
the electron probability distribution is like.
And so forth.
Okay,
so we're not going to do that.
We're not going to do it because
it's just a matter of solving differential equations.
And this is not a course in differential equations.
But we can still sort of scan it out.
Well,
I have a question.
Yeah.
For a given l,
I think what you said earlier
suggested that they were all the same energy levels.
Say it again.
But all the eigenvalues,
one of them gives you the same energy level.
Yeah,
all of those,
all of these levels here,
the two l plus one of them,
have the same value of little l.
And therefore the same energy.
Oh,
okay.
Yeah.
So if you were able to replace
l squared with l l plus one
because psi is a linear combination of the m's?
Hmm.
What's this?
But that applies to any value of l.
We said,
right?
Yeah.
So if we know the angular momentum,
if we know the angular momentum quantum number
of the wave function,
then we can plug it in.
What l is really the maximum eigenvalue?
It's the maximum eigenvalue for that multiplic.
Yeah.
There are wave functions of any angular momentum,
but they come in these,
and the pattern is that they come
in these two l plus one multiplets.
The two l plus one
multiplets are the quantum mechanical analog.
Now if you find a wave
function and you rotate it around.
Right.
This tells you what the energy levels
associated with a given l are.
And now you want to solve it.
Okay.
Too hard to solve for most potentials.
Most potentials you write down,
you'd have to solve it numerically.
The Coulomb potential happens to be solvable.
If you want to solve it,
the solutions to this equation are called
Giegenbauer polynomials,
or Giegenbauer functions.
Good luck.
Look up Giegenbauer functions.
You will learn very little
from it.
I used to know what a Giegenbauer polynomial is.
I do not anymore.
Okay.
Let's look at the effective potential.
What we're doing is we're solving the Schrodinger equation
in a potential which looks like this.
We're solving the Schrodinger equation
for a problem which effectively has
a potential energy which looks like this.
And we want to know what kind of wave functions
and what kind of energy levels will it be.
Okay.
If you know anything about solving Schrodinger equations,
then you know that given l,
given l,
in other words,
we're given the potential,
you know that first of all,
typically there are more than one bound state.
A bound state is a state which is confined
with a wave function which
doesn't leak out too far.
They correspond to discrete energy levels.
And you know that the thing which characterizes
the energy level is the number of nodes
in the wave function.
Does everybody know what a node is?
A wave function which is never zero,
let's say it's always positive,
has no nodes.
If it goes up,
goes down,
passes through the origin,
and then it has one node.
So here are some functions
with different numbers of nodes.
Here's,
oops,
here's a function with no nodes.
Here's a function with one node.
How about a function with two nodes?
A function with two nodes goes up,
comes down,
goes back up,
and comes back down.
The number of nodes are what characterize
the different energy levels
of a solution to the Schrodinger equation.
The more nodes,
the higher the energy.
Why would it be that the more nodes,
the higher the energy?
What's that?
Yeah.
Something like that.
The more nodes,
the faster it wiggles.
The faster it wiggles,
the larger the momentum.
Momentum is characterized by
wiggles.
The wave functions of momentum states wiggle.
The higher the momentum,
the faster they wiggle.
The more they wiggle,
the more nodes they're going to have.
So generally speaking,
it's a theorem.
It's actually not,
The lowest energy state in the given potential
has no nodes.
The first excited state has one node.
The next excited state has two nodes.
Eventually you may or may not run out of solutions,
but
they're ordered according to the number of nodes.
So let's start.
Let's see now what we can say about the spectrum
of an atom.
It doesn't have to be a realistic atom.
This could be an atom with one over r potential,
like a realistic atom.
It could be one over square root of r.
It could be e to the minus r,
but some potential.
What can we say?
Let's see if we can organize
the energy levels and the states of the atom.
Okay,
let's see how I do this.
Yeah,
let's plot horizontally
the different angular momenta.
Little l's.
Little l.
l equals zero.
Zero.
l equals one.
l equals two.
l equals three.
And so forth.
Now each one of these l's
has its own Schrodinger equation.
Remember,
the Schrodinger equation involves l as a parameter.
So each l may have several bound states.
Several solutions.
Let's take l equals zero.
l equals zero will have a lowest energy state.
Let's see,
what are we plotting here?
Let's plot energy vertically.
Okay,
there will be the lowest energy level.
It has no nodes in l equals zero.
So it's someplace over here.
Okay.
What's the next state with l equals zero?
The next state with l equals
zero has a node in it.
Same potential,
one node.
So it's up here over somewheres.
How many states are there for every,
for l equals zero,
each wave,
each case,
has one state.
l times l plus one
is one when l is equal to zero.
Is that right?
No.
No,
no,
no.
Two l plus one is,
uh,
two l plus,
two l,
two l plus one is,
uh,
right,
two l plus one is one.
So every one of the states with l equals zero,
one node,
two nodes,
three nodes,
and four node,
they all have one state associated with them.
There's some,
they're not equally spaced.
They are whatever they are.
Whatever they are.
Okay.
Those are the energy levels with zero angular momentum.
Now let's go to angular momentum one.
At angular momentum one,
there is also a state with one,
with no nodes.
We solve the same Schrodinger equation
except with l equals one here.
l times l plus one,
when l is equal to one,
one times two is,
uh,
two,
right?
One times two is two.
On the other hand,
for l equals zero,
this was zero.
Okay,
so,
same Schrodinger equation,
different value of l.
At l equals one,
we will also find things with one node.
Will their energy be larger or smaller
than the l equals zero state with no l,
with no node?
Just a wild guess.
Yeah,
it's got angular momentum.
It's,
you know,
it's swinging around there.
It's got angular momentum.
And besides which,
this is a positive term in the Hamiltonian.
So how could it possibly lower the energy?
It can't.
So the l equals one state
with no nodes
will lie somewhat above
the corresponding state with l equals zero.
Likewise,
the state with two nodes
will lie above this one.
And
just by virtue,
the whole spectrum may move over,
but it will move up a little bit
because the angular momentum is higher.
How many states are there
at each one of these levels?
I've drawn a little dash,
a little dash here,
to indicate a possible energy level,
an energy level.
But what is its degeneracy?
How many states are there
at each one of those dashes?
Two l plus one?
Three.
So we should really draw these
as three little dashes
if I was trying to separate them
and indicate three states.
Each one of these
is a triplet.
What about at l equals two?
At l equals two,
we've put in a little more angular momentum.
Surely we've raised the energy again,
and in fact we will have.
How many states will there be
for each state at l equals two?
Five.
Two l plus one.
So when we go up to l equals two,
let's move them over a little bit,
l equals two,
we will have them go up a little bit,
and we'll have five states.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five.
And so it goes.
l equals three.
Two l plus one,
let's see,
three times two is six,
seven states,
and so forth.
And that's about what it looks like.
That's about what the general solution looks like
for sort of arbitrary potential.
At some point,
when the energy gets too high,
just like in classical physics,
what happens when the energy gets too high?
When the energy gets too high
for an orbit around the sun?
It escapes.
It exceeds the escape velocity,
and it's no longer bound to the sun.
Likewise,
when the energy gets too high,
the electron escapes,
and so there's a bound to the energy up here.
No states above there are actually bound.
So all the bound states have
basically negative energy.
Energy starts,
it should be,
it goes negative down here.
And this is what the spectrum of a,
of anything in a central force looks like.
The Coulomb potential has a very special feature.
It's almost accidental.
It's not exact.
It is an exact statement about
the nonrelativistic Coulomb potential,
but it is not an exact statement about atoms,
the statement I'm going to tell you.
It's violated by every possible way.
It's a very possible correction
to the simplest theory of the atom.
It's violated by the finite size of the nucleus.
It's violated by relativistic corrections.
It's violated by the fact
that the electron has a spin
which couples to the,
everything on earth violates it.
So it's something of an accident.
It's very special to the Coulomb force.
And it goes as follows.
The first level here,
which is moved up a little bit,
this is the zero node state.
The zero node state for L equals one
happens to be,
have exactly the same energy
as the one node state for L equals zero.
Here's the one node state for L equals zero.
The zero node state,
the first one that occurs for L equals one
occurs at exactly the same energy
as the one node state for L equals zero.
That's a mouthful.
What about the two node state?
The two nodes,
sorry,
the one node state of L equals one
occurs at the same energy as the two node state
of L equals zero.
Exactly the same.
Exactly the same for the simple Coulomb force.
And so on and so forth.
This is a pattern.
Now you go to L equals two.
The L equals two zero node state,
in other words,
the lowest L equals two state,
has exactly the same energy as,
which is this now.
This is no node,
one node,
two nodes.
It's up here.
And there are five states.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five.
What about the L equals three?
The L equals three begins up here.
Seven states.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six,
seven.
And so forth.
That's the pattern and it's an accident.
It's not completely an accident.
Nothing in mathematics is ever an accident.
But you can say things are accidental
when,
you know,
just small changes in the potential
or small changes in anything ruin it.
And this in that sense is an accident.
I'm not going to prove it.
It sounds like an extra symmetry law.
It sounds like extra degeneracy.
It sounds like there are degeneracies between states.
It is a symmetry,
but it's a rather bizarre one.
It's a rather bizarre one that you would never notice
if you were thinking about this.
As I said,
it's very special to the Coulomb potential
and is not exact.
So I think we won't bother proving it.
It's a nuisance to prove.
But it is a fact.
It's a very special fact about
the special one over r potential.
So there it is.
That's the spectrum.
What is the degeneracy at each level?
Here's the lowest energy level.
There's only one state.
It has angular momentum zero.
It's called the ground state.
It's the lowest energy state of the atom.
If this were the hydrogen atom,
for example,
it would be the most deeply bound state.
Then you go up one level.
You go to the first node
of the zero angular momentum state
or no nodes for the angular momentum.
And how many states do you get?
This is one.
This is four.
How about the next one up?
One,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six,
seven,
eight,
nine.
Nine states at the next level.
Anybody want to guess what the next one is?
Sixteen is right.
So for the Coulomb potential,
for the Coulomb potential,
the states are degenerate like this
and the degeneracy is always
the square of some integer.
You said the Coulomb level remains the atom
or you were just talking about the friction?
The hydrogen atom approximately satisfies this.
It's a very good approximation.
But all kinds of things violate it.
Relativistic corrections.
And as I said,
just the finite size of the nucleus
is enough to disturb this.
Now the nucleus is very,
very small.
Why does the finite size of the nucleus disturb it?
The nucleus is a little ball of charge.
We've pretended the charge was a point at the center.
That would give us exactly the Coulomb potential.
If the charge were distributed over a little ball,
the potential energy would be slightly different
than the exact Coulomb,
especially when you get into the nucleus.
The electron can pass through the nucleus.
It's just a ball of charge.
The nucleus is just a ball of charge.
The electron is repelled.
Sorry,
it's attracted to the nucleus.
And it can pass through the nucleus.
When it passes through the nucleus,
it senses the fact that the charge distribution
is not the perfect 1 over r potential.
If the potential is anything but 1 over r,
this degeneracy fails.
So because the nucleus has a finite size,
there's a very,
very slight deviation.
There's a very slight deviation away from this.
Now,
the nucleus is 100,000 times smaller
than the size of the atomic wave functions.
So the nucleus is very small,
and this is a very negligible effect.
But the only point is just
that this is something of an accident
and not particularly deep.
I don't know anything deep about it,
the fact that it has this kind of degeneracy.
And that's the spectrum of the hydrogen atom.
That's the spectrum of the hydrogen atom
and the idealized approximation,
non-relativistic,
perfect Coulomb potential.
Okay?
One state,
the ground state.
Four states above it.
Nine states above that.
Is that the way real atoms work?
No,
it's not the way real atoms work.
Real atoms have two degenerate ground states,
eight first excited states,
18 next excited states,
32 next excited states.
And so there's something missing in this analysis
by a factor of two.
Spin.
Yeah.
Right.
So we haven't talked about spin,
and I think we won't tonight.
That's...
All of this is,
of course,
just trickery for solving the Schrodinger equation.
Let me write the Schrodinger equation
in its original form before we went to angular variables.
It wouldn't be particularly helpful to try to solve it,
but we might just try to write it down.
P squared means Px squared
plus Py squared plus Pz squared.
It can also mean Pr squared plus P theta squared.
But it means Px squared plus Py.
So this really means minus...
What is it?
H bar squared
d second with respect to x squared
plus d second with respect to y squared
plus d second with respect to z squared
of psi
plus V of r
times psi equals E psi.
That's the equation we really set out to solve.
You solve it
by going first to polar coordinates
or radial coordinates,
radial and angular coordinates,
and then using the algebra
of the angular momentum
to deal with the angular parts of it.
And it's very simple.
The angular parts of it are all subsumed by saying
you work with angular momentum eigenstates.
L squared is the thing that comes in,
and L squared is nothing
but L times L plus 1.
By that time,
you're down to a one-dimensional equation
or a differential Schrodinger equation,
and you use whatever mathematical strategy
you know for solving such things.
Once you get it down to one direction,
it's just an ordinary differential equation.
It's not even a partial differential equation.
You only have derivatives with respect to r.
So at worst,
it's a numerical problem.
Good question.
First is the difference between the idealized Coulomb law
and what you measure.
Could that be a way of
determining the size of the nucleus?
No,
no.
There are too many corrections which are much bigger.
No.
I just point out the nuclear size
because it's an easy one to think about.
But it's minuscule.
No.
And the second question is,
you get back to the very beginning
between classical mechanics and quantum mechanics,
the biggest difference is capital L squared
is equal to little l squared in classical,
and it's equal to L
times L minus 1 in quantum.
What's that?
Capital L squared is equal to little l squared
times little l squared plus 1.
No.
Big L squared is L times L plus 1.
Yeah,
yeah.
I just said it wrong.
Yeah.
And that difference is caused by
the fact that the things don't commute.
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
In other words,
it's a little quantum correction.
Okay,
right.
That's right.
Right.
It's a little quantum correction.
Yeah.
Do wave functions have compact support?
No.
They're spread,
but they fall off very
rapidly as you move away from...
Compact support would literally mean
they go to zero outside a certain distance.
It's a statement that the wave function
has compact support would mean that it's zero
out past a certain point,
but it's exponentially small.
They decrease exponentially.
For practical purposes,
if you go out past a certain distance,
each wave function becomes
negligibly small.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah,
but there is some non-zero
probability you could find something.
Yeah.
It's arbitrarily far away,
but it goes to zero exponentially with distance.
Right.
Question?
Yeah.
When L is zero,
little l,
the shape is not like this.
It's just the Coulomb potential,
right?
Oh,
yeah,
yeah.
Good.
That's right.
For when L...
When L is zero,
then there's no centrifugal barrier.
Right.
So what is the meaning of
the stable point in this case?
You mean the point that's going to be a point?
The point at the origin?
No.
Before it was in this well.
Okay.
Now the well is gone.
Yeah.
That's right.
So classically,
it would just go to the center.
It would just go to the
center and sit at the center.
Quantum mechanically,
it can't both sit at the center and...
It would go to the center,
not only go to the center,
but it would be at rest at the
center.
The state of lowest energy would be at the center,
where it would have negative infinite
energy.
You would lower the potential
energy by getting to the center,
and you would lower the potential
energy by making the momentum zero.
You can't have both.
You can't have the momentum and the position definite.
There's a compromise,
and the compromise is for the
wave function to have a little bit
of spread away from the origin here.
The Schrodinger equation has a solution,
and the solution has some sort of exponential
function.
Okay.
So now we might have our internal
ray of rise coincidentally being Indonesians and
no longer reach at all.
So we could go to the center,
so here you could have a more geographical
We're in southern Saudi Arabia,
something like that.
Yeah well,
that..
And this is the root of what?
This path here.
Okay,
this is motivated by classical mechanics up to here.
Okay?
Classical mechanics motivated p squared over
2m where p was a vector
and allowed us to write this down.
Once we write this down,
we have a very,
very precise quantum mechanical problem.
An exact Schrodinger equation.
I did a little bit of
guesswork in going from here to here.
Classically,
it's completely rigorous to go from px
squared plus py squared plus pz squared
to go to pr squared plus p theta squared.
You have to justify the step quantum mechanically.
But that's something that would
take an hour at the blackboard
and you wouldn't learn very much from it.
Another question.
If I may,
please.
You have z there,
which implies 3 dimensions,
but you said you reduced it to
2 dimensions by going only r and theta.
Classically.
Quantum mechanically,
the wave function fills up 3 dimensions.
Every wave function fills up 3 dimensions.
Classically,
and the trick is to say,
angular momentum is conserved.
That means the plane of the orbit is conserved.
Just change coordinates so your xy plane
is in the plane of the orbit.
Can't do that quantum mechanically.
But you did it.
No,
I didn't.
No.
But the fact that you can't do it,
believe it or not,
is just a statement that L squared
is replaced by L times L plus 1.
Yeah.
It's these other Lx's and Ly's creeping into...
If you could just put in for L squared,
Lz squared,
then it would just be little L squared.
The fact that it's 3 dimensional comes back at
you just from the L times L plus 1.
Yeah.
It's more,
I think,
what you did with the harmonic oscillator.
Is there always a raising
and lowering after any of these?
No.
Only when you're very lucky.
And I would say basically physics
has been lucky this way twice.
But,
however,
the harmonic oscillator piece of luck is very pervasive.
Almost everything in nature can be well approximated,
or many things in nature
can be approximated by harmonic oscillators.
For example,
even the...
Not L equals 0,
but go to the higher angular momentum states.
In the higher angular momentum states,
the potential looks like this.
And there are orbits which oscillate
back and forth at the bottom here.
And the simplest approximation to those orbits
is to treat them as a harmonic oscillator.
So there's all kinds of
places where there are harmonic oscillators,
and because of that,
the trick of...
whatever trickery goes into the
harmonic oscillator is very pervasive.
But there are not many mathematical
cases where raising and lowering operators are...
Sometimes they're called ladder operators.
Only when you're very lucky.
Okay.
That does it for atoms for the moment.
We're going to come back to atoms.
We're going to talk about spin.
We're going to talk about the fact that
the electron is a fermion instead of a boson,
and how that determines atomic structure a little bit,
and how atoms radiate and give off photons.
All that stuff we'll come back to.
But let's forget atoms for the time being,
and come to the harmonic oscillator.
As I said,
everything in physics which has an equal length,
if you disturb the equilibrium a little bit,
chances are it's going to behave like a harmonic oscillator.
So it's a very pervasive thing.
And the model for it...
There's just a particle or a
weight on the end of a spring.
We're going to simplify it a little bit.
Some of the parameters aren't terribly important.
Well,
imagine a weight...
hanging by a spring.
It has an equilibrium position,
and the deviation from the equilibrium position...
Not the deviation from where it's hanging,
but the deviation from the equilibrium position.
We'll call that x.
I'm going to take the mass
of the weight to be one.
Now we can redo it for other masses.
It's a little exercise to do it.
But there's nothing new.
Nothing new happens.
So the mass is one.
And the spring constant...
The spring constant k...
k is the standard terminology for a spring constant...
we'll call omega squared.
We're going to find out in a moment...
that omega is the frequency of oscillation.
But the spring constant is omega squared.
What is the energy of a classical oscillator?
The energy...
Let's call it...
Let's give it its name...
The Hamiltonian.
The Hamiltonian...
is the usual p squared...
Now p is one-dimensional.
It's just the momentum...
The x momentum...
p squared over 2m...
is p squared over 2...
m has been set equal to one...
plus k...
omega squared...
x squared over 2.
Let's work out...
Let's just check that this is right.
What we're going to do is work out...
the Hamilton equations of motion.
If you don't remember Hamilton's equations of motion...
it's okay,
I'll tell you.
Hamilton's...
Hamilton's equations of motion...
are dh by dp...
equals x dot...
and dh...
by dx...
equals minus p dot.
How many people remember...
Minus p dot.
Thank you.
Everybody remember that?
Of course you do.
Okay,
let's check.
Let's see what we get.
dh by dp is equal to x dot.
dh by dp is...
p.
So this says that...
p equals x dot,
right?
That's not too bad.
Momentum is equal to velocity.
What happened to the mass?
Oh,
I set the mass equal to one.
So that's okay.
It's alright.
I'm a physicist.
I'm allowed to do that.
p is equal to x dot.
That's good.
Now what about the h by the x?
The h by the x is...
omega squared...
x.
Plus or minus?
Minus.
Okay,
let's check...
Newton's equations.
Let's calculate the acceleration.
The acceleration...
is x double dot.
That's p dot.
But p dot...
is equal to...
p dot...
Do I have the sign wrong here?
The h by the x equals minus p dot...
equals plus omega x squared.
The h by the x is plus omega x squared.
So...
x double dot...
is equal to minus omega squared x.
is minus omega squared x.
That's the equation of an oscillator with frequency omega.
Everybody recognize it?
x double dot is minus omega squared x.
Acceleration...
m was set equal to one.
Acceleration is equal to restoring force...
with,
as I said,
k is equal to omega squared.
Okay,
so this is the right Hamiltonian
for the harmonic oscillator.
And now what we want to
do is find all its energy levels...
Eigenvectors...
and find out what it does...
quantum mechanically.
Quantum mechanically.
Classically we know what it does.
It swings back and forth with frequency omega.
Okay,
let's see what we can do with it.
It's the sum of squares.
What do you do with the sum of squares?
You factor it.
And you get...
Everybody knows that you factor the sum of squares.
Well,
not everybody knows that.
Dirac knew it.
Alright,
so let's write,
first of all,
a one-half downstairs.
And let's write p plus i omega x
times p minus i omega x.
Is this looking familiar?
Not from the harmonic oscillator,
but from about an hour ago?
Lx plus i Ly
and Lx minus i Ly.
Yeah,
okay.
So,
let's do this.
Is this right?
Yeah,
that's right.
I'm also going to put...
Yeah,
I'm going to put an omega downstairs
and an omega upstairs.
Only because it's convention.
Okay.
Now...
Let me not put those omegas.
I'll do that later.
Is this right,
quantum mechanically?
Correct.
No.
Because there's a term
P times x
and x times p
but they don't cancel
because x and p don't commute.
So let's see.
So what do I have to subtract here?
I have to subtract minus one-half
from here
and then I will have
i
Now we have
omega
We have x times p
minus p times x
x times p minus p times x
and I think
I think I have it right.
I've subtracted it
because it was appearing in here
in an unwanted way.
So I've subtracted it
and now I use one more thing.
This is the commutator
of x and p.
What's the commutator of x and p?
i.
I've dropped h bars
all over the place.
We'll put back the h bars
later.
Okay.
x p minus p x
that's i.
Commutator of x with p
equals i.
Okay.
Strictly i h bar
if I wanted to keep the
uh
Why is that true?
Hmm?
You don't remember that?
From two years ago?
Okay.
That's the basic
canonical commutation relations
of a coordinate and its corresponding
momentum.
We use the
one dimensional case.
Yeah,
It's not p x.
No.
Then you have a problem.
Then it'll be zero.
x commutes with p y p z.
Yeah.
This is
x and p x.
There's only one coordinate in this problem.
That's what I'm saying.
If you had the other dimensions
you would have to clarify.
If you had other dimensions
you'd have to worry about them.
Okay.
This is the one dimensional
harmonic oscillator.
So what is x p minus p x?
Alright,
let's keep the h bar around for a second.
Uh,
we'll keep
the h bar around for a second.
Later on we'll drop it.
It's i h bar
minus i times i is plus i
so this
becomes plus
h bar omega over 2.
Okay.
This is a constant.
What's it called?
It's got a name.
It's called the zero point energy.
It's there even
when the harmonic oscillator is in
its ground state.
We're going to see that.
Even in its ground state
where this is zero,
everything else is zero,
this still remains.
Why is there a ground state energy?
Uh,
let's um,
let's ask,
why does a harmonic oscillator
have a ground state energy?
Why isn't the energy zero?
What's the energy of the ground state classically?
Zero.
How does it get to be zero?
Well,
the ground
state is
just the oscillator
at rest,
p equals zero,
at position zero.
Both of these are zero.
Quantum mechanically,
you can't have both x and p
be zero simultaneously.
Furthermore,
both of these are
positive,
and therefore they can't cancel each other,
so there's got to be a little bit of energy
in the ground state.
It's the Heisenberg
uncertainty principle which tells you that you couldn't
have had zero energy in the ground state.
Okay,
but once you know that,
here,
let's
the Hamiltonian is
this thing over here,
plus a constant.
Let's drop,
the constant may or may not
be important,
but it's just
an additive number.
Every energy level has
an extra h-bar omega
over two.
We're not going to lose anything terribly important
if we drop it.
Um,
I'm going to drop it,
but
later on we can come back and add it
back in as an overall
additive constant in the energy.
Yeah?
Can you say anything further
by the fact that it comes out
as positive instead of negative?
Okay,
it
couldn't have been negative because
x squared plus p squared is positive.
The energy is x squared plus
p squared,
that's a positive definite operator.
It can't come out to be negative.
Alright.
Alright,
so let's concentrate on this thing over
here.
Let's
forget where it came from,
or forget
where it came from,
and we just want to know what's
the properties of this operator.
Here's
a certain operator.
It is the
Hamiltonian apart from this addit- I'm going to
say it once more.
There's an additive constant
and now I'm not going to
say it again until I put
it back eventually.
But
this is the Hamiltonian.
Okay.
And we want to understand what its spectrum is,
what its eigenvectors are,
what is its properties.
We have two
operators.
It factorizes
very nicely.
It makes
sense to give these operators
names.
And I'm going to
do something just for future benefit.
I'm going to put an
omega up here,
and I'm going to put a square root
of omega down-
here's what we're going to do.
We're going to
put a square root of two omega downstairs,
and a square
root of two omega downstairs here.
You see what I did.
I took the two that was
downstairs and I split it between these two.
And I took the omega
which I stuck upstairs and
split it between the two factors
again.
This is the standard way that
even the classical harmonic oscillator
is often written in this way.
We need to
give these guys names.
P minus i omega
x over square root of
two omega and P plus i
omega x.
Their role is going to be
exactly the same as the raising and lowering
operators in the
angular momentum case.
It's going to take us up and down a ladder.
This time
it'll be a ladder of energy levels.
Not a ladder of angular
momentum.
Okay,
so let's give them names.
A plus
is equal to P
plus i omega x
over square root of two
omega and A minus
is the same thing
but with a minus i x.
Over square root of two omega.
They are Hermitian
conjugates of each other.
They're Hermitian conjugates of each other
because
one plus i omega
x minus i omega x.
And we can now write
that the Hamiltonian
is omega
times A plus A minus.
That is really simple
except who knows what's buried in the A plus
and the A minus.
It's a crappy looking thing
for sure to have square roots of omega
and square roots of two
but it turns out not to be so crappy.
Okay.
What
What should we do with
these A pluses and A minuses?
What would
Dirac do?
Yeah,
he'd do that
but he'd probably stare at it for a while
and say I can't figure out the eigenvalues.
He would commute them.
He would say what's their commutator?
Here I have
a Hamiltonian which is A plus A minus
I don't know much about A plus and A minus
but let's figure out what their
commutator is.
See,
I'm bored.
I've got nothing else to do.
I like to sit around
and commute things.
Okay.
So let's take the commutator
of A minus
with A plus.
Okay,
that's going to be
commutator
of
now there's going to be
a two omega downstairs,
right?
Two omega downstairs.
One over two omega.
And then there's going to be
the commutator of P minus I omega X
with P plus I omega X.
Now,
who commutes with who here?
Well,
who doesn't commute with who?
Who doesn't commute with whom?
Alright.
P doesn't commute with X
and X doesn't commute with P.
That's all.
X commutes with X
and P commutes with P.
So what do we have here?
We have equals one over two omega
now we have
an I omega
let's take this
let's take this one here first.
Then we have a minus
I omega
minus I omega
from here and then the
commutator of X with P.
What's the commutator of X with P?
I.
So that gives us an I.
I times minus I
is plus one
we have an omega
over omega
all together this is just one half.
But that was only one term.
That was this commutator
of this one with this one.
The other one is the commutator of P
with I omega X
it's exactly the same.
If you work it out you'll
see it's exactly the same number
and so all together you get two of them
plus a half
and the commutator is one.
And so you get two of them
we now know two things
turns out this is enough
this is really all you have to know
you can throw away everything else
the Hamiltonian
is omega
times A plus A minus
and the commutator of
A minus with A plus
is one
there's one more fact here
and it's the fact that A plus
and A minus
are Hermitian conjugates of each other
that plays a role.
Okay.
Good.
Let's give
this thing
A plus A minus by itself a name
let's call it capital N
it even gets simpler now
the commutator of H
is omega times N
and the next step of course
if we were Dirac would be to start
substituting N with A plus and N with A minus
it's a good thing to do
you find out that the commutator algebra is very simple
but I don't think we have to do it
I think we can
proceed
without doing that
let's see what we can learn
first of all
this N object is a
Hermitian operator
if you take an operator
N Hermitian conjugate
it's always Hermitian
that's something you can check
that means N has a complete set of eigenvectors
well of course N is Hermitian
it's basically apart from the factor omega
it's the Hamiltonian
it started Hermitian it stays Hermitian
so N is a Hermitian operator
and that means it has a complete set
of eigenvalues and eigenvectors
what we want to do is find those eigenvalues
and eigenvectors
those eigenvalues and eigenvectors
are the energy levels
the eigenstates of the Hamiltonian
ok so let's
see what we can learn
we want to find the eigenvalues
of N
once we know the eigenvalues of N
we know everything we want to know
so let's suppose that N
has an eigenvector called
little n
and that the eigenvalue
is just little n
I haven't made any
assumptions about whether little n
is an integer or anything else
I've called it N
because it is an integer
but we haven't proved that
let's just call it little n
big N is an operator
it's A plus A minus
little n is an eigenvalue
this is the eigenvalue equation
ok
and we can also write it
in another way
we can write it
A plus A minus on little n
is little n times N
ok
I've just written that big N
is A plus A minus
these two equations are the same thing
now let's take
the commutation relation here
let's write it out
A minus A plus
minus A plus
A minus
equals
one
but let's take this operator
this equation and operate
on the state N
and see what we get
alright
you agree with this equation?
it's just a commutation relation
A minus A plus
A plus A minus
equals one
but then
hmm?
what's that?
right
thank you
ok
yeah
good
and let's multiply it
I'm looking at it
I'm staring at it
trying to figure out what to do with it
I know what I really want to do with it
what I want to do with it
is I want to apply A plus
what I want to do is show
that A plus will increase the energy
I want to show that
A plus is a raising operator
so
what I want
I want to concentrate
not on N
but on A plus times N
so I have to multiply it by A plus
this is my goal
to show that A plus times N
is something interesting
that raising with this A plus operator
does something interesting
ok so now we have an equation
let's see what we get
first of all we have
A plus A minus
A plus
so we have a term here on N
now what about the second term
minus
A plus
ah
what's A plus A minus on N
right
so this is
minus
A plus
minus N
times N
I've written that A plus A minus
is a raising operator
so I have to multiply it by N
what we get
so I get
minus A
minus N
times N
what do I get
N plus one
oh that's good
let's see
this one got shifted over to the right
it gave me this N
and the other one gave me the one
but what about this one over here
A plus times A minus
is the operator capital N
this is the state that I'm interested in
so N
on this state A plus
on N
let's put a circle around it
is equal to
N plus one
times that same state
so guess what I found
I was expected that
the raising operator
gives me a new eigenvector of capital N
with an eigenvalue
one unit up
okay
so here's what we found pictorially
pictorially
if I plot
on the vertical axis here
the eigenvalues
of N
then if I
find one
little N
then there's another one above it
and another one above it
unless of course I run out
but we're going to prove that we can't run out
there's another one above it
and another one above it
each one
being shifted by one unit
N
N plus one,
N plus two and so forth
so if I find a solution
an eigenvalue N
there'll be another one at N plus one
there'll be another one at N plus two
another one at N plus three
and furthermore you go from
one to the other
by applying the operator
A plus
A plus takes you from
an eigenvector with eigenvalue
N to an eigenvalue
N plus one and so forth
these of course have higher
and higher energy because
the energy is just omega
times N
what about going down
how do you go down
what's the thing that takes you down
A minus
so it's a straightforward thing
to prove that
same deal
that A minus on N
takes you down
how far down can it take you
can it take you
indefinitely down
why not
because the harmonic oscillator
Hamiltonian is positive
it's only got positive terms
you cannot get to negative values
the operator
is a positive definite operator
which means it only has
positive eigenvalues
in fact it's a theorem
that if you multiply an operator
by its own conjugate
by its own Hermitian conjugate
its eigenvalues are positive
or at worst zero
so it can't go indefinitely down
there's got to be
a last one
that last one
is called the ground state
and it's usually labeled O
you can't go indefinitely down
what does that mean
what takes you down
is A minus
so A minus on N
takes you to N plus one
N minus one
or it takes you to zero
or it just kills the equation
it just kills the state
so there's nothing below it
those are the only two mathematical possibilities
A minus takes you down
or you just run out of states
there are no states below it
that's what happens
A minus on O
is just zero
so there's nothing down below
N equals zero
the first state
corresponds to N equals zero
N equals zero
so that's the first one
question
if we take N
and we apply A minus
to get to N minus one
and then if we apply A plus to that
does that get to N
yeah
but then A plus A minus
times N is N times N
let's do it again
the eigenvalue of A plus A minus
is N times N one
so if we're applying A minus
and then A plus
is that one or N times N
so let's be careful
I've been a little bit careless
I've written that A plus
on N
is equal to N plus one
but I haven't discussed
the normalization of these states
is not
N M
equals delta N M
there's a numerical
factor
there's a numerical factor
and if we wanted to keep track of that
numerical factor
I'm quite tired now
and I think we have to quit
but there is a square
root of N plus one here
times N plus one
now try your trick again
and see what you get
and I think it's also
true that A minus
on N
is the square root of N
times N minus one
if I'm not mistaken
I think that's correct
now what do you want to do
you want to try
A plus times A minus
on N
was that the game
somebody asked me
ok let's see what we get
alright
A minus on N
gives me
A plus
then we're going to have square root of N
N minus one
now what happens
when A plus
hits
N minus one here
it gives me another square root of N
so this
gives me two factors of square root of N
times N
so I was a little bit sloppy
I didn't tell you what the normalization
of the states were
the states are not normalized
by that I mean they're not
Kronecker delta normalized
they're normalized to some
weird factors with square roots of N in them
when we need that
and we will need it
we'll write it down
but I
it's getting a little too late
for all possible details
ok
oh incidentally yeah just one point
notice
that this equation here
says that when A minus
hits the ground state
it does give zero
yeah
does the ground state have to be zero
or can it be above zero
above zero what
no it has to be zero
it has to be zero
is that clear why it has to be zero
well yeah
yeah
let's see
ummm
well square root of zero is zero
yeah
if the vector is
if the vector N minus one is zero
is it zero like
we can prove it
I'm a little bit tired now
and I don't know what the proof is
but it's a good question
it is the answer is zero
the answer is that the spectrum of capital N here
is all of the integers starting at zero
ok
so that tells us
that the energy spectrum
is omega times an integer
there is an h bar in here
and I'll go through the h bars
I'll tell you where the
h bars are hiding next time
but um it tells you that the energy
spectrum is omega
times an integer plus
the famous
one half h bar omega
that we threw away
so there's the ground state energy
plus on top of it
is the spectrum of integer space levels
that's the harmonic oscillator
and um
we'll play with it more
but more important
we'll use it to solve some important problems
ok
for more please visit us at stanford.edu