Stanford University
Harmonic oscillator.
Let's just very briefly review the harmonic oscillator because it's going to
come up time and time again in what happens from here on in.
As I said,
harmonic oscillators are ubiquitous.
They occur all over the place.
Anytime you have a system which has an equilibrium state,
it could be classical or it could be quantum mechanical,
but classical in particular,
if it has an equilibrium state
and you displace it from equilibrium,
generally speaking,
it will oscillate.
It may oscillate with more than one frequency.
For example,
a violin string can oscillate in the fundamental range.
The fundamental frequency,
the first harmonic,
the second harmonic,
and if you pluck it in odd ways,
you can make some nasty noises,
as I'm sure that Art knows.
I've done it many times.
The nastiness because of multiple
overtones clashing with each other.
Well,
that's probably not quite right,
but you know what I mean.
All right,
but nevertheless,
the oscillations of a violin
string are a collection of oscillations.
They're a collection of oscillators of different frequency,
but more important to us are the oscillators which
comprise the oscillations of the electromagnetic field and other fields.
We're going to come to that,
and we're going to do
a little bit of quantum electrodynamics,
just a little bit,
but basically,
if you have radiation,
for example,
in a cavity or in a
wave guide or something like that,
it's going to oscillate.
Then the radiation,
the electric and magnetic
fields oscillate with different frequencies.
Again,
what would be the equilibrium
configuration of the radiation field?
I should start with something
which has an equilibrium configuration.
What is the equilibrium
configuration of the electromagnetic field?
The answer is no electromagnetic field.
The vacuum,
empty space with no electromagnetic field.
empty space with no electromagnetic oscillations in it.
No electromagnetic oscillations,
in other words,
just empty space with no electric and magnetic fields,
is the equilibrium position of
the electric and magnetic fields,
if you like.
If you give the system a knock by,
for example,
sending in some microwaves or something,
the system will start to oscillate.
And like the...
Violin string,
it can oscillate in all of its various frequencies,
and those oscillations are called photons,
or that's not quite right.
The oscillations are described
or describe collections of photons,
and we'll come to that,
but not tonight.
Okay,
so harmonic oscillators are terribly important in many ways.
Incidentally,
sound waves are also oscillations.
A sound wave moving through a crystal is,
again,
a collection of oscillations.
You can think of it wrongly,
as each crystal oscillating
independently of every other crystal.
Sorry,
each atom oscillating independently of every other atom.
But that's not really the way it works.
Each atom exerts a force on the other atom,
and so when you displace one,
it gives a knock to the next one,
and waves go through the crystal.
The waves,
again,
are described by harmonic oscillators,
and the quanta of the oscillations are not called photons,
they're called phonons,
for example.
So these are things we're going to study,
but to prepare ourselves for that,
we studied a bit the harmonic oscillator,
and I want to expand on it a bit.
Remind you what the rules are.
We started with the harmonic oscillator with a Hamiltonian,
or a Hamiltonian oscillator.
Which I wrote as p squared over twice the mass,
and I set the mass equal to one,
just to make my life simple.
You can go back and do it
with a mass not equal to one.
I believe in our book art
we do it with a general mass,
so we do it with...yeah,
okay,
so it's done with a general mass.
And then plus omega squared.
That's the spring constant,
but it also happens that omega
is the frequency of the oscillator.
X squared over two.
And we constructed creation and annihilation operators,
A plus or minus,
which happen to have been momentum plus I omega X.
Now notice,
not finished yet,
but notice if I,
classically,
if I were to take,
this is plus or minus,
if I were to take the two operators,
A plus and A minus,
and multiply them together,
and then divide by two,
I would construct the Hamiltonian.
Alright,
so we'll come back to that in a minute,
but in order to be consistent
with the notations that are ancient,
we'll put a square root of two omega here.
And those are the A pluses or minus,
and if you work out,
classically,
or quantum mechanically,
the Hamiltonian in terms of A plus or minus,
here's what you find.
Oh,
one more quantity.
One more quantity is called N.
N is equal to A plus A minus,
as simple as that.
And the last time we proved that the spectrum of
eigenvalues of N were just the integers starting at zero.
We showed that A plus and
minus were raising and lowering operators,
which raised and lowered the eigenvalues of N.
Alright,
so this is an operator whose eigenvalues are one,
zero,
start with zero,
no negative ones,
zero,
one,
two,
three,
dot,
dot.
And finally,
not finally,
but moreover,
the Hamiltonian is equal to omega,
and the Hamiltonian is equal to N.
Now,
I have left out H bar.
I'm going to leave it out,
but then I'm just going
to show you where it goes.
If we leave out H bar,
the Hamiltonian is just omega times N.
Now where does that come from?
If you multiply A plus times A minus,
clearly you get something which looks like this.
There's a two downstairs.
That's this two.
And there's an omega downstairs.
That's why I have to
compensate it with an omega here,
omega N.
But quantum mechanically,
there's a little correction,
and the correction comes because the P's,
because the A plus and A minus don't commute.
And that gave us an N plus one half.
The one half is called the ground state energy,
or the vacu-
well,
if it was a field theory,
we would call it the vacuum energy.
If it is a simple harmonic oscillator,
we call it either the zero
point energy or the ground state energy.
And it's really a consequence of the uncertainty principle
that you can't have both
P and X simultaneously being zero.
And since the Hamiltonian involves P squared plus X squared,
there's no way they can cancel each other.
So there's always going to be a
residual bit of ground state energy there.
You don't lose very much if you
just cross it out and forget it.
Because an additive constant in the energy of a system
really doesn't change its equations of motion.
So you can ignore it,
but it is there,
for some purposes.
Alright,
what I wanted to do was to show you-
is there anything else?
Yeah,
there's one other important point,
or equation,
that went into showing that
the A pluses and A minuses
were raising and lowering operators.
It was the commutation relations of
the A plus and A minus.
They're Axe rule.
Whenever you see two things,
commute them.
Alright?
Sometimes,
of course,
you get garbage.
But the commutators are A minus with A plus,
just equal to one.
Had I not put this in the equation,
if I had put the square
roots of two omegas down there,
the commutator would have been something a little messier.
And so really the reason for dividing
by square root of two omega here
was to get rid of anything on the right-hand side,
to divide it away.
This commutation relation,
together with the definition of n,
tells you that n is quantized in integers,
and the connection with the
Hamiltonian is such that the Hamiltonian,
the energy levels,
are these.
Question?
Yeah?
Last time,
you didn't go in and explain
why it went down to state zero,
and you said you could take it back.
Yeah.
Why it stops at zero?
No,
why zero is included.
Oh,
Okay,
we're going to do it.
Yeah,
okay.
What we're going to do
is we're going to demonstrate explicitly
what the ground state is.
That there is a ground state,
and we'll find the ground state
by actually solving the Schrodinger equation.
And we'll see that there
definitely is a state with zero.
So,
what is a wave function?
A wave function in this context,
let's just put parallel to this
very tricky and clever operator structure here,
let's write down the wave
function description of the same thing.
State vectors are replaced by wave functions
which are functions of position.
If we're talking about energy eigenstates,
we could label the wave functions
with a little n down here,
indicating which integer they correspond to.
The ground state,
for example,
will be psi zero.
The first excited state would be psi one,
and so forth.
So,
state vectors become wave functions.
Operators,
x,
the operator x becomes just
multiplication by the coordinate x.
I'm trying to remember to use capital letters for operators
and lowercase letters for just numbers.
Lowercase.
Okay,
the momentum,
is replaced by minus i,
d by just derivative with respect to x.
Again,
there's an h-bar in there if
you want to keep track of h-bars.
Oh,
if you do want to keep track of h-bars,
here's where it goes,
right here.
And that's the only place where you
have to modify what I've done here.
Yeah,
I guess maybe also,
here,
we want to put an h-bar downstairs here,
I think.
But,
um,
and you can always figure out where
the h-bars go by using dimensional analysis.
Using dimensional analysis and
remembering the units of h-bar
will tell you uniquely where to put the h-bars.
Okay,
so there's momentum.
And,
uh,
let's check and see
if there is a solution of,
of the equation,
a minus
on psi
is equal to zero.
In other words,
is there a state,
You know,
I can answer your question faster without,
let me,
let me answer your question quickly without,
and then come back to calculating.
Um,
we know that there has to be a state,
which is the bottom state.
We can't keep going down and down and down
for the simple reason
that the Hamiltonian is positive.
It's p squared plus x squared.
p squared plus omega squared x squared.
An operator like that has no negative eigenvalues.
Just as classically,
it's either positive or zero,
quantum mechanically,
it also can't be negative.
And so there's got to be a bottom.
There's got to be a floor to the tower of,
uh,
of energy levels.
Okay.
How can we have a floor?
The only way we can have a floor
is if
the bottom state,
let's call it O,
let's call it ground state,
is annihilated
by the annihilated means
that you get zero
when you hit it with a minus.
If it didn't get zero,
whatever you got on the right-hand side
would be a state of one unit lower energy.
There is no state.
There is no state with one unit lower energy.
The only way for that to happen
is for this to just give zero.
Now,
once we know
that a minus on O gives zero,
then we can look at n.
So let's look at n now.
What does n do
when it hits the bottom state?
Well,
it is by definition
a plus a minus on O,
but we already know that
a minus on O gives zero,
so this is zero.
It's an eigenvector of n
with zero eigenvalue.
So there must be an eigen...
The bottom state has to have
zero value of n.
That's an abstract argument,
but,
yeah.
So if zero is an eigenvector of n,
shouldn't there be an eigenvector of zero
on the far right-hand side?
Sorry?
It's O.
Hmm?
Wait,
wait,
wait.
This zero here,
this state,
and this are two different things.
Right.
That's the eigenvector.
That's the eigenvector,
and it's normalized to one,
and it's not zero in any sense.
It's just that its name is zero.
You know,
if I called my friend Art here zero,
that wouldn't mean Art wasn't here
or didn't exist.
It would just mean I'm,
you know,
being unpleasant,
I'm calling him zero.
You can still write the
ket over there if you want.
Yeah,
you can write zero as a ket,
but you have to understand it's not this zero.
It's just zero.
So zero times is...
Zero times anything is zero.
So you can write...
The fact is that it's a vector
on the left-hand and right-hand side,
so you can put the vector in there
and it's just a zero vector.
Thank you.
Yeah,
but you must not call it this vector.
Whatever name you give it,
you've got to give it some...
The tradition is just not
to write it as a vector,
but just to call it zero.
Yeah.
In the abstract theory of vector spaces,
you introduce a vector called zero,
and it's sort of special.
It's the only one that doesn't have a ket sign.
But as you say,
it is just another vector,
a rather special one.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right,
so the bottom of the tower,
the bottom of the...
The bottom of the energy spectrum
has to be energy h-bar omega times one-half
with n equal to zero,
big N equal to zero,
also little n.
But let's see if we can...
See how far we can go in calculating
all of the wave functions.
Can we calculate the wave functions themselves?
Now,
you might ask,
I can write a Schrodinger...
I can write a Schrodinger equation.
I just use for p in the top equation,
I use p for the top equation,
for t,
d by dx.
For a time-independent Schrodinger equation,
the right-hand side is just the energy eigenvalue times psi.
Question.
Is it really true that
you can only solve that equation?
In fact,
we could write down the equation.
Let's write down the equation.
Just time-independent Schro...
Here it is.
Time-independent Schrodinger equation.
It's minus d by dx squared...
Oh,
boy.
Ordinary derivative.
Minus one-half.
The one-half is the half
in front of the Hamiltonian there.
p squared is d second by dx squared,
psi of x,
plus the potential energy,
plus omega squared x squared times psi of x.
And if this is the time-independent Schrodinger equation,
then what I want to
do is to solve the equation.
That this is equal to,
let's call it e,
for the eigenvalue for energy,
times psi of x.
That's the same as writing p
squared plus omega squared x squared
on a vector is equal to e times that vector.
Okay.
Now,
if you know anything about differential equations,
you'll know this is a second-order differential equation.
You can always solve it for
any value of the energy here.
Okay.
But what will happen for most values of the energy
is the wave function will
not go to zero at infinity.
Even worse,
it will exponentially explode and get big.
It won't be normalizable.
It will not have a finite probability under it.
There's no way to normalize it.
If you try to normalize it,
it'll just be zero because you'll,
you know,
the integral under the square of
the wave function will be infinite,
to get rid of that infinity,
you'll have to divide,
you'll have to divide by it,
and the wave function will just be zero everywheres.
So,
the rule is,
one more rule,
and we've talked about this,
you know,
last quarter,
or three quarters ago,
or whenever it was,
is that what you mean by an honest vector here
is one whose square integral,
whose integral,
the square of,
which is square integrable,
integral,
psi star psi,
equals one.
Okay.
There were some exceptions to this.
For a particle moving on an infinite line,
sometimes we introduce momentum states and position states,
which are a little weird in this way,
but we would like the total probability to be finite,
certainly not exponentially exploding.
So,
this is one additional restriction,
and it's when the wave
functions are restricted in this manner,
when they really form an honest and good vector space,
then that's when the rest of this applies here.
It only applies if we're interested
in the square integrable wave functions,
which we are,
and so the point is that
when we write down the Schrödinger equation,
the Schrodinger equation,
there are certain definite values of energy
which will have square integrable wave functions.
Those are the true honest eigenfunctions.
If the wave function blows up and goes to infinity,
we just throw them away.
We say they're not in the space.
Okay,
let's see if we can find sine naught,
the ground state wave function.
We could write the original Schrödinger equation for it.
But we can be smarter than that.
Instead of writing h on psi equals e psi,
let's write a smarter equation,
a simpler equation.
Let's use the fact that we know
that the annihilation operator,
the lowering operator,
excuse me,
the lowering operator on the ground state,
I don't need to call this sine naught,
just naught,
gives zero.
Okay,
what is A minus?
A minus,
I just want to get my signs right,
A minus is proportional to p minus i omega x.
Now,
there's some factors in the denominator there,
but we don't care about them
because we're just going to write that
this times psi of x equals zero.
And numerical factors like square roots of omega,
they don't matter in this equation.
Just multiply through by them.
And now,
remember what p is.
p is minus i d by dx.
Minus i d by dx,
minus i omega x times psi of x equals zero.
Now we have a much
simpler equation than we had before.
It doesn't even have any second derivatives in it.
It only has first derivatives in it.
So we can try to solve it.
The trick for solving an equation of motion like this,
anybody know what the trick is?
There's only a finite number
of tricks in solving differential equations.
There's a handful of tricks.
What's that?
Separation of variables.
No,
there's only one variable.
What are you going to separate?
That's it.
Wrong hand.
Right.
Okay.
One very standard trick for linear equations like this
is to write the wave function
as the exponential of something else.
Now,
this is just a matter of experience.
I can't tell you how to guess that.
Yeah,
you can guess it because
when you multiply through by dx,
you get x dx.
So the equation comes out
as a derivative over a derivative.
Over a,
you know,
d,
over a,
you know.
Right.
But it's the form of a logarithm.
Yeah,
exactly.
All right.
So this happens to be the
kind of equation that you solve.
You can solve it in many ways,
but one way of solving it is just to write
psi of x is equal to e to some f of
x and try to figure out what f of x is.
All right.
So let's try it.
First of all,
of course,
we can get rid of the i's here.
i and i factor out.
Furthermore,
we can get rid of the minus
sign because both of them have minus signs.
And now what's the derivative of psi of x?
To calculate the derivative of psi of x,
we simply differentiate,
and we find that let's call it psi prime,
which means the derivative,
is equal to f prime.
That's the derivative of f times
e to the f of x.
To differentiate an exponential,
you just differentiate the thing that the,
in the argument of the exponential here,
and multiply again by f of x,
e to the f of x.
Okay.
That's psi prime.
That's this here.
And then we add to that,
let's,
we want to add to that
plus omega x psi of x.
Which means we're going to add to this
plus omega x e to the f of x.
Now you see what Michael was saying,
that the e to the f of x factors out.
We can get rid of it.
And that's where the trick,
that's why the trick was done in the first place.
Let's get rid of all of this here.
And our equation is just df
dx plus omega x equals zero.
That's it.
Equals zero.
The fdx came from here,
plus omega x.
They both multiplied psi.
So we got rid of psi.
And that's our equation.
Alright,
this is really easy to solve.
A function whose derivative is a linear thing,
what kind of function is that?
A quadratic thing.
So the solution is quite clearly
going to be proportional to x squared.
In fact,
it's going to be f of
x is equal to one half,
omega x squared,
plus a constant.
Let's put the constant in there.
And that's all.
Not the minus.
Hmm?
Minus,
minus,
minus.
Thank you.
Minus one half,
omega x squared.
That tells us that psi of x is
equal to e to the minus one half,
omega x squared.
What about the constant?
Well,
we can add it in,
but that just puts a numerical
constant in front of the exponential.
Since I haven't bothered worrying
too much about normalizing it,
I'm not going to bother with the constant.
Numerical constant out in front is there.
It's got a one over
square root of omega in it,
but it's not terribly interesting for our purposes.
This is psi naught.
Pi naught of x.
And notice that it goes to zero very,
very fast with x.
e to the minus x squared.
It's a Gaussian.
It's a bell-shaped curve that goes to
zero as e to the minus one half,
omega x squared.
And it's very,
very square integrable.
I mean,
if we square it and integrate it,
it's extremely convergent.
And so we've succeeded in finding...
Now we could go back and check
that the original Schrodinger equation is satisfied.
In other words,
we could plug this wave function into the Schrodinger
Hamiltonian up above and calculate what the energy eigenvalue is.
But we already know what it is.
It's going to be omega times one half.
We know that from all the algebraic tricks over here.
So if we stuck this function back into the Schrodinger,
into this Schrodinger equation,
we would discover that e is equal to one half.
Just by putting it in,
plugging it in,
and doing it.
So we know the ground state wave function.
We have one eigenvector of the energy.
We see what its physical properties are.
It's concentrated near the origin.
It's very smooth because a Gaussian function is very smooth.
It does what you might expect a ground
state wave function of a harmonic oscillator to do.
It just sits at the origin.
It sits very close to the origin.
Or at least by close now,
I mean that it's concentrated near the origin.
And,
um,
yeah.
Yeah,
it's the ground state.
What about the first excited state?
I'll do the first excited state for you.
It's very,
it's almost trivial.
And then you can go home and have
a lot of fun calculating the next 50 states.
It's,
uh,
sort of mindless,
um,
fun.
But how do you do it?
It's how you do it that's
more interesting than what you get.
Well,
I don't know,
they're both interesting.
But you do it by saying,
look,
I know what the first excited state is abstractly.
Abstractly the first excited state is equal
to A plus times the ground state.
I know what the ground state is
and I know what A plus is.
So let's just apply A plus to the ground state.
Here's the ground state.
A plus is P plus I omega X.
And that will tell us
what the first excited state is.
All right.
So in terms of wave functions,
psi 1 of X is equal or
proportional to P plus I omega X.
Now P is minus I d
by dx plus I omega X
on E to the minus one half omega X squared.
So all we have to do
now is to calculate a derivative.
But,
you know,
I already did this.
We did it with the opposite sign here.
We did it with A minus to get zero.
If I do it with
the opposite sign and get zero,
that means if I do it with the sign here,
I'm just going to get twice
the answer that I would get.
Go back.
I did this operation on here and got zero.
That's the way I solved the equation.
All right.
So if this plus this acting on this gives zero,
then it must mean that this term and this term
give the same thing apart from the sign.
But once I know that,
then I know that when you
change the sign of the over here,
instead of having them cancel,
they'll just double the answer.
So this is just going to be twice I omega.
That's not so interesting.
It's just a numerical factor.
Happens to be imaginary,
but who cares?
But it has X times E to
the minus one half omega X squared.
So structurally it's different.
It's not just the Gaussian function.
It's the Gaussian function times X.
What does that look like?
That looks like this.
Again,
it's very small far away.
The fact that there's an X
here doesn't make it big far away,
because it's totally overwhelmed by the
E to the minus X squared.
But it has to be minus.
It has to be minus when X is negative.
Yeah,
good.
It's negative,
yeah.
Well,
it's twice an imaginary number times omega.
Right.
But whatever it does on one side,
it has the opposite sign on the other side.
It's an odd function.
Odd meaning it changes sign
when it goes through the origin.
Right.
So let's make it negative on this side.
It goes down and then comes up
zero and then goes to zero again.
It's odd,
meaning to say that when you reflect it,
it changes sign.
It's anti-symmetric.
You would say it's anti-symmetric.
The probability,
which is the square of this,
is symmetric.
But notice that the probability
goes to zero at the origin.
If you're in the first
excited state of the harmonic oscillator,
the probability that you find the
oscillator at the origin is zero.
Interesting fact.
That's the first excited state.
The ground state had no nodes.
A node means that the wave function is zero somewheres.
The first excited state has no nodes.
It will only include a big wave.
The second excited state's not negative.
It's just a drift.
The
second excited state was theulator.
term,
x cubed after a while.
Each time you'll get a higher and higher order
polynomial and each time you'll add a node.
So the next wave function,
the spin
of the the second excited state looks
looks has two nodes.
The third one has three nodes.
And if you work out the
17th,
it looks something like this.
Each time you act with a plus,
you wind up
pushing the wave function out more.
For example,
zero,
the ground state,
was
concentrated near the center.
The factor of x here tended to push it
out a little bit Why does it push it out?
Because X is bigger far away than it is
nearby and so pushes it out.
After you've done 17 factors or maybe it's 24 or
whatever,
you'll find that the wave function
is pushed out near the wings
small near the origin,
oscillating,
and then,
and then plop goes to
zero
either symmetric or anti-symmetric
and as you go up
you get more and more wiggles
and the whole thing gets pushed out further and further
what do the wiggles mean?
what's the implication of the wiggles?
wiggles mean momentum
what's the implication of
it being far away from the origin?
potential energy
so as you keep exciting it
you create more and more potential energy
by pushing the wave function
out where x squared is large
but at the same time you create more and more
momentum as that oscillator
swings through the origin
what's happening is
the oscillator is trying to do what
classical physics tells you it ought to do
that the higher the energy
the more likely it is to be found far away
but it also may be found close
and if it's found close it
ought to have a high momentum
so that's why it tends to
oscillate very quickly near the origin
and more slowly far away
but that's the basic physics of it
I don't know if I drew it well
it should oscillate more rapidly near the center
and less rapidly far away
just indirectly
indicating the fact when it swings through the origin
of course it has more momentum
okay that's uh
those are the first two wave functions
yes
um so it seems like uh
as n becomes very large
uh the correspondence principle does not
hold for the simple harmonic oscillator
what would you say the correspondence principle is?
um that when n becomes very
large it looks like a classical
it does well
it and in fact
what you have to do to see the classical motion
is you have to see the classical motion
you have to take wave packets
you have to superpose many energy levels
for example
if you take the ground state
start with the ground state
that's a nice smooth wave packet
now displace it
displace it off to the side here
it's no longer the ground state
in fact it's not even an energy eigenstate altogether
it does have an average energy
but now
take the time dependent schrodinger equation
the time dependent schrodinger equation
has every energy level oscillate with a different frequency
the result is
that this wave function is not time independent
and what happens it starts to swing back and forth
it starts to swing back and forth
as it swings near the center
it gets lots and lots of wiggles
but it stays of the same general shape
wiggles,
and then it comes out this side after a while,
nice and smooth again,
and then it swings back
and forth and back and forth.
And it looks very much like a classical oscillator.
And in fact,
the higher the energy,
the more it looks like a classical oscillator.
Just because the higher the
energy and the bigger the swings,
the smaller the ratio of the
uncertainty to the size of the swing.
When the swing gets very big,
it sort of dominates the spatial structure of it.
Okay,
that's the basic physics of the harmonic oscillator.
You can work out the second level,
third level.
By the time you get to the fourth level,
you won't want to see it anymore,
but it's straightforward.
Good.
Question?
Yeah.
On your drawing of the second moment.
Shouldn't it go through zero at zero?
Is it going to be x squared?
No,
I don't think so.
I think there's a constant term also.
Yeah.
Yeah,
it's not just x squared times.
Yeah.
Right.
Question.
In the Hamiltonian you wrote originally,
you know,
the left,
it already implicitly contained
the normal idea of the second moment.
Yeah.
However,
if you look at your
next Answer,
it goes everywhere.
All the key poo what I were describing there,
same answer as first question.
It always lose a point.
If you are
fast at math.
functions that were not square integrable,
then A plus and A minus would not be
Hermitian conjugates of each other.
That's where it's assumed.
And I did assume that.
And,
um,
right.
So,
Is there a way in general
of recognizing where the Hamiltonian rich is?
Yeah,
if it's a harmonic oscillator.
And here and there,
sort of sporadically,
and this or that,
sometimes you encounter
a solvable example.
And when they're solvable,
they can usually be solved by these kind of
tricks.
But they're very rare in the space of possibilities.
And
um,
by some fortunate accident,
the harmonic oscillator is one of them,
and the hydrogen atom,
or
the idealized hydrogen atom,
non-relativistic hydrogen atom with a point nucleus,
happens
to be one of the solvable examples.
Uh,
okay.
Now,
I have in my notes two other subjects for tonight.
Um,
with the idea of
uh,
discussing atoms a little bit further,
but more than atoms,
discussing everything that there is
about quantum mechanics and field theory.
Two things,
spin and boson-fermion difference,
the difference between what bosons and fermions are.
I have,
uh,
well,
I guess I'll go according to my,
um,
to my notes here.
I'll follow my notes.
I have spin first,
and then bosons and fermions.
So let's talk about half-spin.
The spin of the electron,
or the spin of the proton,
which happens to be half-spin,
which means that the spin,
or the angular momentum of an electron at rest,
at rest it has no orbital angular momentum,
it has no r cross p,
all it has is spin.
So spin is a kind of
angular momentum that's attached to a particle.
It's your choice.
Your choice,
whether you want to think of
it as just an abstract concept,
or whether you want to think
of it as a tiny little thing,
which is literally spinning.
Spinning about an axis.
And when I say it has no momentum,
I mean to say it
has no center of mass momentum.
Uh,
and it's a matter of choice and taste,
whether you want to think of
it as literally being a little spin,
or just an abstract property that you,
uh,
mathematical property that you can,
understand.
that you attach to the electron.
But whatever it is,
it is angular momentum.
It transforms under rotation.
When you transform,
when you rotate coordinates,
the state transforms.
Now,
we've already been through this.
We spent most of a
quarter talking about the half-spin system.
So I'm going to go through it quickly.
You should go back and read
the early parts of the previous lectures.
We talked about a spin having two states,
up or down.
But then we said,
wait a minute,
if it can be up or down,
it can also be left or right.
But if it can be left or right,
it can be in or out.
And we worked out the states describing those things,
the operators which describe,
the components of the spin.
And I didn't tell you,
but we were talking about
the angular momentum of a spinning particle,
or of a half-spin particle.
So let's see how we can understand that
now that we've talked about angular momentum.
The thing that characterizes angular momentum
is,
first of all,
that there are three components
of it.
But just the fact that
there are three components of it
is not enough.
It must be that those three components
are literally associated with the x,
y,
and z directions of space.
You could have them connected with something else,
some other internal dimensions or whatever.
But once you have matrices,
once you discover that your system is being described
by matrices,
Three of the three relationships
and finally,
you have three of them which
have the commutation relations of angular momentum,
and they are angular momentum.
Actually there's no choice about that,
as long as the three matrices you're talking about are literally associated
with an x and a y and a z direction of space.
So let me write down again what
the basic commutation relations of angular momentum are.
L,
i,
l,
j,
and let's write just L,
x.
Let's see.
Let's take the L,
z with the L,
x.
L,
z with L,
x is just equal to i times L,
y.
And the other two are just cyclic permutations.
You may have noticed that these commutation relations are
closely related to the commutation relations of the Pauli matrices.
So let's write the three Pauli matrices and change them.
And let's check whether this is
true of the three Pauli matrices.
Here they are.
Sigma z is equal to 1,
minus 1,
0,
0.
Now we've made a choice.
We've made an arbitrary choice.
We've decided to take sigma z as the first one.
We've chosen sigma z to be the diagonal matrix.
In other words,
we are working in the representation
of the z component of the spin.
We've chosen to take that to be diagonal.
And of course the eigenvalues,
what are the eigenvalues of this matrix?
The eigenvalues of this matrix
are plus 1 and minus 1,
representing up and down.
Okay,
then there was sigma x.
Sigma x was 1,
1,
0,
0.
And finally sigma y is equal to minus i,
i,
0,
0.
There are ambiguities in these.
You can rotate them and change them,
but there's no,
nothing important happens.
There's no minus in sigma x?
No minus in sigma x.
All three are Hermitian.
A real matrix,
meaning to say if its entries are real numbers,
if it's Hermitian,
it's symmetric.
That's this and this.
If a matrix is Hermitian and imaginary,
it must be anti-symmetric.
So that's this.
Okay,
let's check this.
Let's check the commutation relations.
Let's multiply sigma z by sigma x.
And that's equal to 1,
minus 1,
0,
1,
0.
This times this is 0,
this times this is 1 up in here,
0.
Down here,
minus 1.
That's not quite sigma y,
but it's almost sigma y.
It would be sigma y,
I think,
is it i times sigma y?
Or minus,
it's i times sigma y.
Yeah.
Now,
that's nice,
but it's not the commutator.
The commutator is this minus...
Sigma x,
sigma z.
That's the commutator.
And that has 0,
1,
0.
0,
minus 1.
And if you go through it,
you don't get 0.
What do you get?
Exactly the same thing you got over here.
Equals i sigma y.
So we have not quite what we wanted.
We have instead...
Commutator of sigma z with sigma x...
Is twice i sigma y.
Does this mean these are not angular momentum?
Or does it mean that we're not talking about rotations?
No.
It just means we've
normalized the sigma matrices incorrectly.
Here's the trick.
Take s and define it to be sigma over 2.
For each component.
For each component,
take s being half the Pauli matrix.
Seems a little bit odd,
but nobody told us what the
angular momentum was supposed to be.
So let's just take it.
And see what we get.
Then we get...
Let's put a 2 in here.
A 2 in here.
And that altogether divides by 4.
Right?
I put a 2 here,
a 2 here.
I've divided the whole thing by 4.
2 divided by 4 is 1 half.
So,
yes.
Half the Pauli matrices satisfy
exactly what they're supposed to satisfy.
S z with s x.
S z with h is equal to i s y.
And likewise for the other commutation relations.
So we see this little system of
2x2 matrices acting on 2 component vectors,
up or down,
are actually representing a very
primitive and simple angular momentum system.
It's a thing which you can
think of as attached to the particle.
Attached to the particle is a little spin,
and the little spin is
simply described by this system here.
But now we can answer the question,
what are the eigenvalues of,
let's say,
the z component of the angular momentum?
Let's go to the z component of the angular momentum.
The z component of the angular momentum,
let's put some twos here now
that we know what we want,
one half,
minus a half,
half,
two,
two.
Notice that the eigenvalues of the z component of
angular momentum are a half and minus a half.
When we were working out angular momentum,
I told you,
and I showed you,
that there were two kinds of multiplets.
There were the half spin multiplets,
let's put zero over here,
sorry,
there were the integer multiplets,
and the two spin multiplets,
where the magnetic quantum number m was zero,
one,
two,
three,
minus one,
minus two,
minus three,
and so forth,
with the central point being at
zero here being one of the possibilities.
Now remember,
the raising and lowering operators shift you by an integer,
but that doesn't say you start at zero.
It says zero.
It says either you start with
zero or you start at a half,
a half,
minus a half,
and then three halves,
minus three halves,
depending on the overall angular momentum.
If it's spin a half,
then there's only a half and minus a half.
And that's what we have here.
We could have guessed all of this by saying,
look,
we seem to have the
mathematical possibility of having half spin.
That means there are two states.
Once we know there are two states,
we can say the angular momentum of
this one must be plus a half,
the z component must be plus a half,
that were minus a half,
and we can go and start building the structure
up the way we did in the first case.
So,
if you look at the
first case,
the z component is minus a half,
and the z component is minus a half,
and the z component is minus a half.
Yes,
nuclei can be particles.
They are particles.
They have no angular momentum in their rest frame.
On the other hand,
some nuclei do have spin.
But some atoms have spin.
But the important thing is,
or what we're going to concentrate on,
is the half spin particles.
The electrons,
the muon,
neutrinos,
quarks,
all the ones that really we think of as fundamental,
or some of the ones we think of as fundamental,
have half spin.
Okay,
all of this means that there
are two kinds of angular momentum.
Orbital angular momentum,
and this is true in classical physics too,
orbital angular momentum is the angular
momentum of the center of mass,
of a system.
In the center of mass frame,
if the system is spinning,
then it has spin.
The same is true here.
And what is the total angular momentum?
The total angular momentum is the sum of them.
It's a vector.
So it's the vector sum of
the two kinds of angular momentum.
And it's true here too.
So I'll write down the equation,
but we're not going to do very much with it.
The total angular momentum is called J.
Again,
it's a notation.
I don't know where it comes from.
It's again a vector.
And it's equal to the orbital angular momentum L,
which is R cross P,
plus the spin,
plus S.
I just tell you that because
you'll see that all over the place
when you're doing quantum mechanics,
particularly in atomic physics.
You'll see that the total angular momentum is called J,
and it's L plus S,
for a particle.
So I give it from the dollar to the hour,
a point of temperature cube.
We're also going to operate so far
We're going to go toorder.
I'm going to go to or derecho,
but we're going to go to order tahun
and we're going to go to Masovian ペナ
which s is the bouton
How do you,
like if you're given some system with a J,
how do you identify S?
You're usually given something different.
You're usually given the knowledge
that the spin is a half,
for example,
and that the orbital angular momentum could be 1,
0.
If the orbital angular momentum is 0,
then the only angular momentum it has is the spin.
If the orbital angular momentum is 1,
then we need some rules for what we get
if we add an angular momentum 1
to an angular momentum of a half.
The question is,
what do you get?
And I wasn't going to go into that now.
The problem of the addition of angular momentum,
it's a straightforward problem,
but we won't do it tonight.
I'd be happy to go.
I threw it another night.
But there are rules,
mathematical rules,
for adding angular momentum of two systems.
Basically,
you have two systems.
You have the spin system and the orbital system.
Or you could just have two spins.
Or you could have two
different orbital angular momentum systems.
The net system has its own angular momentum,
and there are rules,
quantum mechanical rules,
for adding that.
But there are rules,
quantum mechanical rules,
for adding that.
Let's not do it now.
Question?
Yeah.
You said we could think of this,
not the orbital,
but the spin,
as being either actually like this physical thing spinning,
or we could think of
it in a more theoretical way.
Or abstractly.
What is the background for,
the experimental background or whatever,
that made them introduce this notion of spin?
Well,
the first experimental background
came partly from spectroscopy,
and partly,
more importantly,
from the periodic table.
So that's what I want to get.
I want to get to
the periodic table a little bit,
and show you how spin comes into it.
It was Pauli who realized
that to understand the periodic table,
the electron had to have a spin.
It had to have an additional property.
Okay,
that brings us to the issue of fermions and bosons,
which is closely connected to the Pauli exclusion principle,
at least in the case of fermions.
Let me just motivate it in
terms of chemistry a little bit.
It was one of the motivations.
The other came from spectroscopy,
but it's not as clear,
it's not as obvious.
If you remember,
the angular momentum squared,
L squared,
is equal to L times L plus 1.
Is that what I want?
Yeah.
And if we look,
when we look at the levels,
the energy levels of the hydrogen atom solutions,
which we didn't do,
but I just told you a fact.
I told you a fact that there's some extra degeneracies.
Each one of these has two L plus 1 states.
But there were additional degeneracies.
I'll redraw them for you.
The horizontal axis is L.
The vertical axis is energy.
These are the energy levels of the hydrogen atom.
And down at the bottom is
the ground state of the hydrogen atom
with the lowest energy level of all.
And it's an S-wave,
meaning to say it has no angular momentum,
no orbital angular momentum.
The solutions of the Schrodinger equation.
The energy is in fact negative.
You start at some negative value,
minus 13 point something electron volts.
But I'm just putting it here arbitrarily at zero,
somewhere up here.
Okay,
so that's the first level.
Now,
at the L equals zero,
there are states with,
this is the state with
no nodes in the wave function.
Then there's one with one node,
two nodes,
three nodes,
and so forth.
So there are more states here.
I'm just drawing them schematically,
completely schematically.
Okay,
there are more.
In fact,
they get closer and closer together as
they get up here near E equals zero.
But that's not too important for us.
Now we go to L equals one.
And at L equals one,
there's the lowest energy state of L equals one.
Each L equals one state has three components.
Two L plus one has three components.
And the ground state of L equals one,
has more energy than the
ground state of L equals zero.
Why?
Because it's got angular momentum.
So of course it has some more energy.
So it's going to be up a little bit higher.
In fact,
this whole collection of levels here,
is going to be raised
up because of the angular momentum.
And it's raised up in a rather surprising and,
I suppose you could say elegant.
I'm not sure it's elegant.
It's,
it is what it is.
All right.
So the first L equals one level
occurs at the same place as
the second L equals zero level.
It's degenerate with it.
So it's three states over here.
And then the pattern continues.
The next three states are degenerate with this.
And so forth.
Degenerate means it has the same energy.
Then you go to L equals two.
I'll use a different color.
You go to L equals two,
which is over here.
And what you find when you solve the equations,
this is supposed to be at the same level here,
is you find again,
the first L equals two state is higher
than the first L equals one state,
but it happens to occur exactly
where the second L equals two state is,
which is exactly where the
third L equals zero state is.
It's a mouthful,
but you know what I mean.
You go up to here.
And how many states are there?
Five.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five.
One,
two,
three,
four,
five,
and so forth.
And that's the pattern.
All right,
now you count the number of states.
Now you count the number of states.
One here at this energy level.
Whoops.
Yeah,
one here.
Four here.
Zero angular momentum plus angular momentum one.
Four.
Nine here.
Sixteen here.
Evidently L squared levels.
If you look at the way electrons fill the shells
in idealized,
very idealized chemical description
of a periodic table where it's up there,
but you see,
that first of all,
there's hydrogen,
which has one electron.
And when you look at helium,
which has two electrons,
you find out that the,
it's consistent,
it's consistent with an energy
which would be what you would get
if you put both electrons into the ground state.
Things are a bit different because instead of having,
let's go to helium.
This is hydrogen.
Let's go now to helium.
Helium has a nucleus of charge two.
Q equals two.
Charge two.
So it pulls on the electrons tighter.
The whole structure is rescaled,
but that's not important.
The charge is bigger.
That pulls the electrons in closer.
But the basic structure is the same.
And now you look at helium.
You find out first of all there's a helium ion.
Helium ion means one electron instead of two electrons.
And you study the helium ion.
And the helium ion looks
exactly the same as the hydrogen.
With the exception that you'll have
to plug in twice as much charge.
That spreads the energy levels out and rescales them.
But same structure.
So the ion looks like,
exactly like the,
and the ground state of the helium,
ground state of the helium ion,
looks as if it's one electron in
the ground state of the helium wave function.
Then you put another electron in.
Okay,
what do you expect?
Well,
the natural expectation would be
if you put another electron in,
the ground state of that will be,
put that electron also in the lowest energy state.
Why do anything else?
If you want to keep
the energy as low as possible,
put them all into the ground state.
So,
you try that.
Second electron into the ground state wave function,
and it works just fine.
It gives you the right rough description of the helium.
It's not quite exactly right because
it's ignoring the interaction between the electrons.
Just pretending the electrons
are just experiencing the nucleus.
Let's take that as a working approximation.
Ignore the interaction between the electrons.
Put two electrons into the ground
state of the helium wave function,
and it works.
It gives you the right energy for the helium.
Well,
what happens if you were to make a
helium ion by putting an extra electron in,
instead of the ion with only one electron?
Incidentally,
there's also an ion with no electrons.
It's just called a deuteron,
a helium nucleus.
Okay,
one electron,
two electron.
You put three electrons in.
What's the guess?
Right into the ground state.
Why anything else?
But no,
that's not what happens.
What happens is it goes into the first excited state.
So,
you put two electrons in
the helium into the ground state,
and the third one doesn't want to be there.
It wants to get into the next excited state.
Why?
It could have saved energy.
You could have had a lower
energy state in the ground state
if that electron went into the,
um,
went into the ground state.
Okay,
so along comes Pauli and says,
I have an idea.
My idea is that no two electrons
can ever get into the same state.
Something about electrons is such,
I won't call it a repulsion.
It's not right to call it a repulsion.
It's an exclusion principle.
When an electron is in a state,
you can't fit another one in.
Somehow the mathematics won't allow it.
But wait a minute.
We already said we could put
two electrons into the helium ground state.
So it's talking nonsense.
The Pauli exclusion principle doesn't work.
It only works somehow when
you put a third one in.
No,
Pauli said that's not what's going on.
He said really you can't put
two electrons into the same state,
but an electron has more
properties than just its orbital motion.
He said I'm going to make up a new property.
And the new property has to be such
that the electron comes with two values of it.
Two values of it.
In that case,
you can put the electron,
one electron,
into the ground state.
And let's call it the up electron.
Remember,
the electron can now have two properties.
We're going to call them up and down.
We can call them left or right,
or we can call them anything we want.
But let's give them the new property.
Which Pauli eventually realized had
something to do with angular momentum.
And said if you can
put two electrons in a state,
not because you're allowed,
you can't put two electrons in a state,
but you can put two electrons
into the same orbital angular momentum state
if you give them opposite spin.
If one of them is put in in the up state
and the other one is put in in the down state,
then I can save my crazy exclusion principle.
I can save my crazy exclusion principle if
I assume that the electron has one more property
in addition to its orbital motion that it
has a thing which I will call a spin.
Now in fact,
there were previous reasons to believe
in an angular momentum like that.
But they're not as transparent and
I won't try to get into them.
That was his basic reasoning.
Electron has another property.
A two-valued property.
Once he knew there was a two-valued property,
he was off and going.
He invented matrices to describe that two-valued property.
And before you know it,
he had the Pauli matrices
and he understood the whole thing.
But let's go to the next atom.
Let's see.
We go to lithium.
Lithium has three electrons.
We would naturally expect for lithium,
you do the same game.
Now the nucleus has charge three,
so it's much more attractive.
Charge three,
you put two electrons into the ground state.
That works for the no electron case,
the one electron case,
the two electron case lithium ions.
It works perfectly well to put
the electrons into the ground state.
Not if there's no electrons,
but if there's one or two.
And indeed,
you find out that when
you put the third electron in,
into the lithium to make it neutral,
it goes into the first excited state.
It goes into the first excited state,
meaning the state with angular momentum one.
And that works out well.
It works out the energy levels of the
lithium atom work out reasonably well that way.
What about the second atom?
What about the ion of lithium?
Well,
you filled up the two lowest energy states.
You've only put,
you have three states here.
You could add,
oh,
you could add another electron
in any one of these states.
Let's go back a step.
Let's go,
let me go back a step.
Let's forget for a moment the spin.
And let's talk about the,
um,
the atoms if there was no spin,
but if there was a Pauli exclusion principle.
Let's try a Pauli's old idea,
except without the spin.
What would you find?
Indeed,
you would find two,
you would find one,
helium.
In helium,
you would find one electron,
am I saying this right?
In the ground state.
But then,
to keep the energy low,
you could put the second electron
in any one of four states.
In any one of four states.
If you didn't want to double,
you didn't want to violate the exclusion principle.
There would be four distinct helium atoms.
Four distinct helium atoms depending on which
state you put the next electron in.
That was not right.
The helium ground state was unique.
Did not have this peculiarity.
What Pauli's idea was,
no,
you don't go to the second state here,
and there are not four possibilities.
There's just the helium atom with one electron,
and the helium atom with two electrons,
both in the ground state.
Now you come to lithium.
Now you come to lithium,
you put the first electron in.
Forgetting spin,
where can it go?
First electron here.
I'm getting tired as usual.
What I'm trying to do is
explain why there are eight different...
Can you see this periodic table up there?
Alright.
The second row has eight entries,
I hope.
Has eight entries.
It has eight entries.
How do we understand those eight entries?
Two times four.
One extra electron.
We add an electron.
Yeah.
We add the first two electrons
and put them in the ground state,
and that's the...
and we're finished with the ground state.
Then,
how many more states do we have
if we only occupy the first excited state?
In other words,
how many different ways can we make atoms?
Well,
we can put an electron in any one
of four states in the first excited state,
but if we're allowed to play with a spin,
then there's any one of eight.
Any one of eight possibilities.
Hmm?
Two six.
Two six?
Are you making a mistake?
P orbitals are six.
Two P six,
one is one.
Four.
There's two P orbitals in each of three spatial directions,
so there's two electrons in P.
There are four states at the first excited level.
Eight.
Three...six are P,
and the other two are S1.
Yeah.
Okay.
Is the angular momentum zero
and the three angular momentum one?
I think that's...that's it.
There's angular momentum zero
and three angular momentum one.
Yeah,
that's the four,
but if now you double it by the spin,
it becomes eight.
Yeah.
So you have a total of eight,
not two.
Right.
That's fine.
Okay.
That's how spin was discovered.
That's how spin was discovered,
and the fact that it really was angular momentum,
that
was...that could be checked by putting
the atom in a magnetic field.
If the electron's additional degree
of freedom was really angular momentum,
that would mean
that since the electron is charged,
that the electron...
If the electron is charged,
that the electron would be behaving like a little magnet.
If it was really spinning and it was charged,
it would behave like a little...like a magnet,
like an electromagnet current going around in a loop.
If that were the case,
and you put the electron into a magnetic field,
preferentially it would
either...it would lie along the magnetic field
or opposite to the magnetic field with two
different energy levels.
Okay?
So if you took the hydrogen atom with one electron,
and now you put it in the magnetic
field,
the two possibilities for the electron
spin along the magnetic field and opposite
to the magnetic field would
now have two different energy levels.
So the two states of the hydrogen atom,
which previously had been...the ground state...ground
state of the hydrogen atom with an electron in it,
the electron could have been pointed
in one way or the other way.
They had exactly the same energy in the first approximation,
and now you put it in a magnetic
field and you find that the energy levels are split.
And they split exactly as if the electron
were a little magnet because of its angular
momentum.
So the fact that it had angular momentum,
that could be tested by putting it in a magnetic
field.
The fact that it had two levels...
That was consistent with the Pauli exclusion
principle and the fact that...or the assumed
fact that you can't put
two electrons into the same state.
Now this was all wild guessing.
It was wild guessing that you couldn't
put two electrons in the same state.
It wasn't quite so wild that it was
angular momentum because that could be tested experimentally.
But the next step,
which I think was...was it Pauli?
It was...the one person that it wasn't was
the person that the idea was named for,
Fermi.
Dirac.
It must have been Dirac again.
It might have been Pauli.
It was either Pauli or
Dirac who had the idea that...
The idea that there are two kinds of particles.
Particles which satisfied the Pauli exclusion principle
where you couldn't put two in the
same state and particles where you
could put two in the same state.
And not only that,
it was preferential to put more
than one in the same state.
It was already known that photons...
Photons for our purposes now are just particles.
It was already known that a classical wave
of photons was simply a collection of a large
number of photons all in the same state.
All in the same quantum state.
So it was known that there were particles
that you could put into the same state.
Einstein figured them out and again it was
named after Bozer because Einstein figured it out and...
It wasn't Bozer.
Although Bozer did some...
Was he in the mix somewhere?
What's that?
Enrico Fermi.
Was he in that same group?
No.
He came later.
And his contribution was different.
The discovery of what is called the statistics of particles,
their boson or fermion character
was Einstein and Pauli I believe.
Or it might have been Einstein,
Dirac and Pauli.
I'm not sure what the actual history was.
And it was not...
It was not the other people,
although they made major contributions.
I think it was Einstein who
gave Bozer the credit for the discovery.
When you talk about photons,
they're independent particles.
But when we talk about electrons,
we associate them with a hydrogen.
What happens if you have just a stream of electrons?
You can't put two of them in the same state.
That's why you can't make a laser that lasers electrons.
A laser creates lots of photons
all in the same quantum state.
You would have a pretty wild thing if
you could get electrons into the same state and
do the same kind of things with them,
but you can't.
You have a rather remarkable microscope that you could...
You have electron microscopes,
but this would be a rather superior electron microscope.
So the momentum,
this L,
it's not related to rotation around the circle.
It's related to rotation around the nucleus.
It is.
Of course it is.
There is no nucleus.
It's just L.
Oh,
then it's just R cross P.
You know,
a particle moving in free space,
just moving along a line,
can have an angular momentum,
R cross P,
relative to some origin.
Yeah,
yeah.
The angular momentum is relative to an origin.
That's because R is relative to an origin.
The definition of R is relative to an origin.
Fixing an origin,
you need to...
And the whole idea of rotation is about some origin.
The whole idea of rotation picks...
I should have emphasized that in the beginning.
Whenever you're talking about angular momentum,
whenever you're talking about rotation,
you're picking a special point to study it about.
Now,
in the case of an atom,
it's natural to pick the nucleus
to be the point of symmetry.
For a particle moving in free space,
every point is a point of symmetry,
rotational symmetry.
So it becomes a less interesting thing.
But for the atom,
there's a natural center to talk about rotations about.
I should have emphasized that.
Question?
Yeah.
So why are there two rows of
eight elements and then two rows of 18?
18 is twice 9.
But why are there two...
I don't know why.
At some point,
the whole picture breaks down and doesn't make any sense.
And pretty quickly,
in fact.
The picture of shells and filling shells
is more than a little bit naive.
It completely overlooks the
interactions between the electrons.
Now,
by the time you have a fairly large atom,
there's basically as many electrons in the inner core
as there are protons at the center.
So to ignore the interaction of
the outer electrons with the inner electrons
makes no sense at all.
So,
I mean,
the whole thing breaks down pretty badly.
And then there's a zillion rules that I don't know.
There's this impression that the more electrons you have,
the bigger and the bigger the atom gets,
but actually they don't get that much bigger.
No,
they don't get bigger practically,
not at all.
And the reason is because the more electrons,
what happens is very simple.
The more protons you have in the nucleus,
the larger the charge.
That tends to pull in
the inner core of the electrons,
the inner shells of the electrons.
And what's left over,
if you have,
let's say,
one valence electron,
is one valence electron moving in what kind of field?
The field that it's moving in,
is n protons and n minus one electrons.
So that one extra valence
electron basically thinks it's hydrogen,
and it's no bigger than hydrogen,
really.
It's essentially almost the same size as hydrogen.
So I think that's what you were saying.
Atoms do not get bigger appreciably.
They get very slowly bigger,
but they don't get appreciably bigger as you add electrons.
As you add protons and electrons at the same time.
The other interesting thing that I ran into is that
with hydrogen atoms,
the reason that they stay
as far apart from each other
is because of electrical repulsion.
Hydrogen atoms?
Oh,
there's also an important component
from the Pauli exclusion principle.
Well,
that's what I was going to say.
That's the exception.
The rule is for most atoms,
it's Pauli repulsion.
That keeps them apart.
Okay.
Where are we?
Yeah,
so we want to talk
about what bosons and fermions are.
Yes?
This might be too much to answer,
but is the exclusion principle a separate postulate?
No,
at that time,
yes.
Now it is not.
Now it's part of basic special regression.
It's part of the special
relativity together with quantum mechanics.
Quantum mechanics without special relativity,
it's a postulate,
but the postulate can be phrased
in a more elegant mathematical way,
and that's what we're going to do.
We're going to phrase the
postulate in a more elegant way.
Once you introduce special relativity and
you combine it with quantum mechanics,
it's not a new postulate.
It's a consequence of special relativity.
It's a consequence of the discovery of the universe,
which was Dirac's discovery.
Okay.
Instead of talking about one particle,
let's talk about two particles.
Well,
let's go back to classical
statistical mechanics for a minute.
In classical statistical mechanics,
or classical mechanics of a system of particles,
if all the particles are the same kind of particle,
the question is,
do you treat them as
identical particles in this following sense,
in counting the number of configurations?
For example,
we put particles into boxes.
The boxes could be little boxes in phase space,
or it could just be boxes.
Four boxes we can put particles into.
Let's say we have two particles,
and they're both the same kind of particles.
So here's a configuration.
We can put two of
them both into the same box.
That's clearly a unique configuration.
Or I can put one particle in one box
and the other particle in the other box.
Is that one configuration,
or is it two configurations?
If these particles have names,
Harry and Sally.
Yeah.
If they have names,
then you could put Harry here,
Sally here,
or you could put Harry here and Sally here,
and they seem to be two different configurations.
In counting configurations,
in calculating entropy and so forth,
this could be,
this sounds like it's a difference.
Now,
whether it is an important difference
or not is a separate issue,
but do you count these as separate configurations?
You could always imagine that these particles
which are identical to you
have a little tiny little bit of paint on them
that paints their name on them,
but it's such a weak little bit of paint,
classical paint,
not quantized paint.
Classical paint that's so faint,
so terribly faint,
that no experiment that you ever could do
could detect the name imprinted on the particle,
but
you would have to say
they were different particles.
Harry here and Sally there would be different
than Sally here and Harry there.
Or,
you can say,
no,
I'm going to do statistical mechanics
as if these were the same configuration,
not think of the particles as labeled.
Now,
in fact,
you get the same answers.
It doesn't make any difference
for classical statistical mechanics,
but it's a conceptual difference.
Putting a particle here and a particle here,
is it or is it
not the same as switching them
if they're the same kind of particle?
So that's a classical version
of the notion of identical particles,
and in classical statistical mechanics,
we usually assume
that these are the same configurations.
Harry,
Sally,
they're the same configurations,
and that's the way we do our counting.
How many configurations are there
for a large number of particles?
Well,
typically,
you get some n factorial
different ways of relabeling the particles,
and that goes into statistical mechanics.
If you've taken statistical mechanics course,
you know that in partition functions,
there are these one over n factorials in them,
and it's simply keeping track of the fact
that if you interchange two particles,
it's the same configuration.
That's an assumption you make.
In quantum mechanics,
you don't have the luxury
of doing one or the other.
It is very definitely that particles are identical
in the sense that they do not carry labels.
Two electrons,
one electron here
and the other electron here
is mathematically identical,
and you couldn't do it otherwise,
exchanging the electrons.
Same with true of photons.
Now,
having a photon here and an electron here
is not the same as having an electron here
and a photon here.
That's clear.
That should be obvious.
They're very different properties,
and you can tell those two configurations apart.
But interchanging and swapping around
which electron is which,
that's a non-transformation
on the state of a system,
and it also is true of photons.
So let's think about that
and what it tells us about a system.
Let's think about the quantum state
of a pair of identical particles.
Let's take a pair of identical particles.
This could be two electrons.
And for the moment,
let's forget spin or anything else.
We just have two electrons in some states.
Let's forget spin.
How do we describe two particles?
One particle is described by a wave function,
psi of x,
where x is the position of the electron.
What about two electrons?
And in fact,
let's go back a step.
What is the psi of x?
What is its meaning?
It's the overlap or the inner product
of an electron at x
with the state of the system psi.
If psi is the state vector of the electron,
then its projection or its inner product
onto a state localized at x
is called psi of x.
Suppose there were two electrons.
How do you characterize the states of two electrons?
Well,
you characterize them by two positions,
position of one and position of the other.
Let's call them x1 and x2.
That does not stand for different directions of space now.
It stands for the two electrons.
x1 and x2,
and the wave function is a function
of two coordinates instead of one,
psi of x1 and x2.
That's the wave function of a two-particle system.
It's a function of,
and if you want the probability,
the probability is a probability to find
particle one at position x1,
particle two at position x2.
So we have functions of two variables
when we have two particles.
Now let's think of the operation
of swapping the two particles.
Taking particle one and replacing it by particle two,
and particle two by particle one.
Well,
that's a transformation.
That's a transformation that generally
will change psi of x1 and x2.
It'll change it from psi of x1,
x2 to what?
To psi of x2 and x1,
which is not the same thing in general.
A function of two variables
does not have to be symmetric.
It does not have to be such that if you
interchange the two arguments,
you get the same function back.
So in general,
a transformation,
it's a transformation which swaps the two particles.
Let's call that transformation,
let's give it a name.
It's an operator.
It operates on a wave function
and gives a new wave function.
So let's name it.
Let's call it the swap operation.
Let's call it S.
And here's what S does.
S acts on a state with particle one
at position x1 and particle two at position x2.
How do I know which is particle one?
Particle one comes first.
Particle two comes second.
What does the swap operation do
when it acts on a particle at position one
and a second particle at position two?
It just swaps them.
It gives you particle two,
sorry,
particle one at position x2
and particle two at position x1.
It just swaps them.
If the particles had little names attached to them,
this would mean something.
Here you would have Harry at position one
and Sally at position two.
Here you would have Sally at position two
and Harry at position...
I'm not sure I said it right,
but you know what I mean.
You change them.
You just do a little dance and switch them.
So this is a possible operation
that you can do on the state of two particles.
Here's an interesting fact.
Take the operation s squared.
What does s squared do?
It swaps and then it swaps again.
It swaps and it swaps again.
What happens if you swap twice?
You get back the same thing.
Obviously you get back the same thing
even if the particles have little names attached to them.
If you interchange Harry and Sally
and then interchange Harry and Sally again,
you get back to the original naming.
So what do we know about s squared?
s squared must be one as an operator.
s squared must be one.
It's a unitary operator.
Why should it be a unitary operator?
Because all transformations on the
space of states are unitary.
So here's what we know about s.
s is unitary.
That means it doesn't change probabilities.
It doesn't change inner products.
And s squared is equal to one.
What are the eigenvalues of a matrix or an operator
whose square is one?
Either one or minus one.
The only possibility.
s squared is equal to one
means that the eigenvalues are plus one or minus one.
Okay,
let's make a new principle.
The new principle is that electrons
or that identical particles
they could be photons,
they could be electrons,
whatever
that for a specific kind of particle
the wave function when you
when you interchange two particles
always comes back to the same wave function
that's if s is equal to one
or comes back to its negative
if s is equal to minus one.
See what that means.
Let's take the case plus one.
I think I'm beginning to fade.
I think it's time to quit.
I think you're probably also beginning to fade.
We'll go through fermions and bosons next time.
But the basic idea is
classifying the wave functions of particles
in terms of what happens when you switch the particles.
It's a basic quantum mechanical process
or a basic quantum mechanical operation
the swapping of particles.
And
the notion of identical particles
is basically telling you that something simple happens
when you swap two particles.
Either the wave function does this
or it does that.
And we'll do it next week.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.