Stanford University.
Okay,
we're entering today into the world of quantum field theory.
Quantum field theory is,
of course,
the description of nature as we know it,
with the exception of gravity.
And so practically everything that we know,
with the exception of gravity,
in principle,
we think,
is explainable if only we had the computational power
to be able to solve quantum field
theories with the accuracy that would be appropriate.
Now the problem is,
of course,
that problems tend to be much too complicated to solve,
except for some very special problems.
You can understand the hydrogen atom,
but by the time you get to the boron atom,
they're too complicated.
And so forth,
and certainly studying human beings is well beyond the
capacity of any quantum field theorist that I know.
But nevertheless,
apart from gravity,
quantum field theory seems to be all there is.
And we're going to enter into the
study of it today in a very,
very,
very elementary way.
We're going to study today the idea
of what is called quantum field theory.
And it's called second quantization.
But before we do,
and second quantization is about quantum fields,
but we'll come to it,
I want to review something first and
maybe generalize that something a little bit.
The thing that I want to study or to
remind you of or go through with you is,
again,
the harmonic oscillator.
But a new aspect of the harmonic oscillator,
a couple of new aspects,
of course,
is that the harmonic oscillator is a
very important element of the quantum field theory.
And I'm going to talk about the harmonic oscillator
just so that we have it in front of us,
because the harmonic oscillator is the central ingredient,
the central mathematical structure that
goes into quantum field theory.
So we need to understand it,
make sure we understand it well.
But we're not going to worry about springs and,
you know,
systems oscillating.
When I speak about the harmonic oscillator,
I'm really speaking about the harmonic field theory.
I'm really speaking about the
algebra of those little operators,
a plus and a minus,
and the product of a plus times a minus,
which is what?
Do you remember?
What is it?
It's the number operator.
It's the number of the excitations.
So I'll remind you now.
We'll go through it a little bit,
and I'll tell you one or two facts
that I may not have told you about.
Particularly,
all right.
So let's just write down the
rules for a single harmonic oscillator.
There are A pluses.
They act on states to elevate
them up to the next level.
There are A minuses,
which take you down.
At the bottom level,
the ground state,
A minus gives you nothing.
It just annihilates the state.
All right.
So A minus is the lowering operator.
And...
A plus is the raising operator.
We're going to learn to call
them creation operators and annihilation operators.
What is it that they create and annihilate?
As we'll see,
particles.
But let's just use the same
conventions that we've used up till now.
And...
There is also A plus times A minus.
That was the thing,
if you remember,
that went into the Hamiltonian.
If you remember,
the Hamiltonian was just basically A plus,
A minus.
What was it?
A plus is...
X plus I omega P divided
by some square root of 2 omega.
A minus is the same sort of
thing with a minus sign in there.
And if you multiply them together,
you get things with X squared...
X squared plus...
Do I have that right?
P plus...
No,
no.
I have it wrong.
It's P plus omega X.
And if you multiply the two of them together,
you get P squared plus omega squared X squared
plus this extra little term
that was the ground state energy.
And so that was...
That went into the Hamiltonian.
A plus times A minus.
And we called it the number operator.
It was the thing whose eigenvalues,
whose observable values,
were the integer level spacing,
or the integer levels of the harmonic oscillator.
So I believe we called this capital N,
if I remember.
And its eigenvalues we called little n.
The observable values of it.
One more thing.
The commutation relations of A plus and A minus.
That's what made...
Oh,
A plus and A minus
are Hermitian conjugates of each other.
That's an important mathematical fact.
But the other mathematical fact is that the commutator
of A minus with A plus is equal to 1.
That's what made everything work.
That's what we used to find the properties of what
happens when we act with A plus and A minus.
We used those commutation relations.
That was basically it.
That's all that went into the harmonic oscillator.
Now,
I'm going to suppose I have many harmonic oscillators.
You could just think of
them as a collection of springs.
Collection of springs.
Or you could think of them as
the various oscillations of a violin string.
Or whatever,
for whatever reason,
there happen to be many
independent systems that are undergoing oscillation,
or that can undergo oscillations,
possibly with different frequencies.
Possibly with different frequencies.
Where does the frequency come into all of this?
The frequency,
well,
first of all,
it comes in here.
But by the time we
get to that point over there,
the place where the frequency came in
was just the fact that the energy
is equal h-bar times the frequency
times this n here.
There's also plus a half a,
I'm going to leave out the half,
the ground state.
It's not important for us.
So that's where the frequency came in.
It came in just as telling us what the energy
for each increase of the number operator was.
The frequency,
together with h-bar,
determine each time,
we go up a level,
how much energy it cost
to jump the oscillator up one level.
Or how much energy we might
get back in some other form
if the oscillator jumps down.
If it jumps up for some reason,
that's how much energy we have to pay,
h-bar omega.
If it jumps down,
that's how much energy we get.
And,
as I said,
that's the single harmonic oscillator.
But now if we have many harmonic oscillators,
we can label them.
We can label them with an index.
And I'll use the index i,
but i does not stand for
the square root of minus one.
It's just a label which goes over
all the possible oscillators that I'm interested in.
There may be a finite number,
there may be an infinite number.
In the examples that we'll be interested in,
there are an infinite number.
Alright,
so now we get to label,
the oscillators,
just by putting in,
well,
okay,
we have to be a little careful over here.
Each oscillator,
think of it as an independent system.
As a system which is just an independent,
uh,
degree of freedom.
And when you have independent degrees of freedom,
the operators for one subsystem
commute with the operators for the other subs-
for any other subsystem.
That's a rule.
We went through it,
uh,
two years ago or a year ago,
whenever it was.
The operators describing system A,
and the operators for describing system B,
if A and B are truly independent systems,
they commute with each other.
Why?
Because to not commute
would tell you that you cannot measure them independently.
If you can't measure them independently,
they're not independent systems.
So presumably if you had two springs,
you could take one off way over there,
and the other one way off over there,
and there's no reason why they should influence each other.
Their operators,
everything about them,
commutes.
And so we can write the following,
that,
let's write out all the commutation relations,
because they're important.
Let's forget this for the moment.
Let's first take
the commutation relations of the lowering operators,
I with J.
The first oscillator with the fourteenth oscillator.
Okay,
let's,
well first of all,
if I is not equal to J,
they're talking about different oscillators.
If we're talking about different oscillators,
they must commute.
But if we're talking about the same oscillator,
then the commutator should be
exactly the same as it was
for the single oscillator case,
namely one.
So how do we write that?
We write that by putting the Kronecker delta over here.
All that means,
oh,
so now,
zero,
sorry,
zero.
Annihilation operators all commute with each other.
Even for a single oscillator,
the annihilation operator commutes with itself,
because everything commutes with itself.
Same thing for the creation operators,
or the raising operators.
But,
now,
here's what I wanted to say a moment ago.
If I take the annihilation operator,
and take its commutator with the creation operator,
then if I is not J,
we're talking about two different oscillators.
They don't know about each other,
they don't talk to each other,
or at least they may talk to each other,
but they are independent of each other,
and the commutator must be zero.
On the other hand,
if it's the same oscillator
that we're talking about,
then the commutator must be one.
So,
this is equal to delta I J.
This is the algebra of the operators of many,
many harmonic oscillators.
You need to know that.
And one more thing,
what's the total energy?
The total energy is just the sum of the energy
of all the oscillators.
So,
let's write that.
The total energy,
which we can take to be the Hamiltonian,
is the sum over all I,
all the oscillators,
the first oscillator,
the second oscillator,
of omega,
I'll include the h-bar for the moment,
I'll probably forget about it before the night is over,
omega,
but which omega?
Each oscillator may have a different frequency.
So,
each oscillator,
the contribution of the ith oscillator,
is proportional to the frequency of the ith oscillator,
times n sub i.
We're going to give a
name to n sub i now.
We're going to call n sub i,
and a soggy 1 I,
是
or n sub i but n,
we're going to call them occupation numbers
not occupation like what's your occupation
but occupation in the sense of
you are sitting there occupying some space
okay all right these are the occupation numbers
it's just a name for the moment
what is it that's doing the occupying
well we'll find out but this says that each oscillator
has an energy proportional to its occupation number
times omega times its frequency with the h bar
being there there is the
extra half of ground state energy
i want to ignore it it's of no
interest it plays no role it's just an additive
constant additive constants in energy are
don't make any difference okay that's
the whole theory if you like
well not quite
not quite now how do we label states
if we have many oscillators if we have
one if we have one oscillator we can label
a complete basis of states just by
the level or the occupation number
of the oscillator remember we have all
these states n equals zero which is the ground state
which we sometimes just call o
n equals one which we call one n
equals two and so forth and so on
we label the states by the occupation number
that's a state what if we have many oscillators
and i now imagine that i lay
them out there are many oscillators here's the
first one over here second one
over here third one over here
fourth one over here i equals
one i equals two and so forth
right then in order to
specify a state i have to specify
the occupation number or one way of
specifying a complete basis of states one
way of specifying a basis of states
is to label was to write down the occupation
number of each oscillator how many
quanta or how many units of
energy are there so to speak
in the first oscillator i'm going to
call the first oscillator and no and one
and two and three
if there's a finite number of oscillators
it terminates if there's an infinite number it
doesn't do you know any situations where
at least mathematically there's an infinite number of
oscillators what's that the continuum well if yeah
an example would be an
a very idealized mathematical violin string
a violin string has any number of
harmonics everyone can oscillate with a different frequency
that's a mathematically idealized of course the
real violin string is made out of atoms
and there aren't really that many possibilities but
a violin string would be a mathematically ideal
idealized violin string
would have an infinite number of oscillators but of
course the very very high n the very high i
would correspond to extremely rapid frequencies and
really because of the atomic structure of the
violin string it really doesn't have that many oscillators
but that's an example mathematically
of infinitely many and we're going
to be interested in that case
okay let's talk about ah let's
come over to another blackboard over here
we're a little more a little
more oscillation a little more oscillator mathematics
i told you in the originally that
if you act
as an alternating field where we have an interlinear
of problems
what's that
a
is
movement
e
one
are
because they have a different,
observably different number of n.
So states with different values
of an eigenvalue are orthogonal.
So the usual normalization would be that the
inner product of n with m is delta nm,
or in other words,
each state nn is equal to 1,
nm is equal to 0.
For n not equal to m,
they're orthogonal.
For n equal to n,
we normally would take them to be normalized states.
That's standard quantum mechanical notation procedure.
With that notation,
in other words,
each one of these states is of unit length.
Each one of these states is of unit length,
but with that notation,
a plus on n does not give n plus 1.
It gives a numerical correlation.
So we have a numerical coefficient in front,
and the numerical coefficient is the
square root of n plus 1.
Let me prove that for you.
Let's see if we can prove it.
Ah,
we can do it over here.
Okay.
Let's not put the answer in.
Let's just call this some numerical coefficient,
and we don't know what it is yet.
We don't know what it is yet.
It's some cn,
and we're going to try
to figure out what it is.
What's our tool?
Our tool is the commutation relations for the oscillators.
It's a single oscillator now,
not multiple oscillators.
Okay.
Let's write.
This is a ket vector.
This is a ket vector equation.
Let's write the corresponding bra vector equation.
When you write,
when you go from a ket
vector equation to a bra vector equation,
what do you do with the operators?
The kets go to bras.
What about the operators?
Hermitian conjugate.
All right.
The Hermitian conjugate of a plus is a minus.
So,
another.
Another way to write the same fact is the Hermitian
conjugate on the bra vector n is equal to cn.
I'm assuming that cn is real.
We can do the complex case.
It doesn't matter.
We can.
It's okay to think of cn as real.
I don't.
It doesn't.
It doesn't matter.
But let's let it be real.
If it wasn't real,
then we would want the complex conjugated.
But we can choose it to be real.
And then n plus 1.
That's the exact same equation except bras.
Kets go to bras.
Operators go to their Hermitian conjugate.
And numbers go to their complex conjugate.
But I'm taking c to
be equal to a real number.
Okay.
Now,
here's what we're going to do.
We're going to put this equation next to it.
We're going to take the inner
product of this equation with this equation.
With the bottom one,
we're going to take the inner
product of this equation with this equation.
With the top one.
Let's write it out.
n,
a minus,
a plus,
n.
That's what happens if you take the inner product
of the left side here with the right side here.
And that's going to equal cn squared times
the inner product of this vector with this vector.
But what's the inner product of this with this?
Every one of these vectors.
Every one of these vectors is normalized to 1.
So it's just 1.
So now we have a tool
to figure out what cn is.
All right.
All we have to do is juggle the
a pluses and a minuses in a clever way.
How do we want to,
what do we want to do?
I think I erased an equation over here.
I should have written,
yeah.
Let's write down the guiding equation over here.
Or over here.
n.
On the nth.
Nth state is equal to
little n on the nth state.
Why is that true?
Come on.
Definition of being an eigenvector.
Little n is the eigenvector of big N.
Big N acts on the eigenstate
with eigenvalue n to give little n.
That's the definition of an eigenvector.
Question?
Yes.
I don't see why the interproctor of n plus 1,
but n plus 1 is 1.
Because I've used the rule.
But we haven't normalized it yet.
No,
no,
no.
Now I've assumed they're normalized.
I'm assuming now that the n vectors are normalized.
And having.
No,
no.
I have put the ambiguity into the c's.
Right.
I may assume that they're normalized.
And then seek to.
Got it?
Right.
Yeah.
Okay,
good.
All right.
So big N is nothing but a plus a minus.
So let's put that here.
A plus a minus.
That's almost what I have here.
A plus.
I don't have a plus a minus.
I have a minus a plus.
But what I know.
Is what a plus a minus does.
What can I do?
What's that operation?
Commute.
And here is our commutator.
The commutator is 1.
So what that says.
Is that this same thing.
Is equal to n.
A plus a minus.
A plus.
Plus 1.
That's the commutator term.
N.
Okay.
Now I'm in good shape.
Because I know what a plus a minus does.
When it acts on n.
It just multiplies by little n.
So all of this just gives me.
N plus 1.
Times the inner product of n with itself.
Which is what?
So there we have it.
Cn squared is equal to n plus 1.
And therefore Cn is the
square root of n plus 1.
We now know.
What the creation operator does in all of its glory.
It increases the occupation number by 1.
And it multiplies by the number
square root of n plus 1.
We can get rid of the rest of this.
We don't need it anymore.
Next.
What about a minus on n.
Well.
You go through.
Essentially.
The.
same little game.
You can do it yourself,
it doesn't take,
it's not very hard.
This time you don't even have to do any commutator.
They'll wind up in the
right order and what you'll find out is
that this is equal to the square root of
n times n minus 1.
In other words,
it takes you down a level but multiplies by
the square root of n.
Notice that this one,
yeah okay,
that's,
that's what
you find.
Once you know this formula here,
you don't have to worry about the
fact of what happens when
a minus hits the bottom level.
When a minus hits the
bottom level,
the bottom level is n equals 0,
you get 0.
So this equation as
it stands now encodes the fact
that the lowering operator annihilates or kills
or gives away the lower limit.
So the lower limit is 0
when it acts on the ground state,
at just the square root of n here.
So this is more oscillator stuff that
I assume that Dirac was responsible for.
And now we know,
I think,
everything we need to know about harmonic oscillators,
at least for the moment.
And that was just a mathematical interlude,
if you like,
to,
so that we'd
have it in front of us when we need it.
Let's put it up on top.
Any questions about harmonic
oscillators or multiple harmonic oscillators?
Oh,
oh.
One thing,
what happens,
here's a particular vector or a particular state,authentic
which has a certain set of occupation numbers.
Let's hit it with a
creation operator for the i-th oscillator.
We're going to the i-th oscillator,
and we're applying one unit of creation to it,
or one unit of elevation.
What does it do?
Well,
it goes over to the i-th slot.
If this were 3,
if i was 3,
it would go over to this slot,
and it increases the occupation number by one unit,
but only for the particular
i that we wrote down here.
So if we go to the 7th oscillator,
and we apply the creation operator,
it increases the 7th oscillator level.
It does not increase the 6th one,
it doesn't increase the 5th one.
You know,
if there's an oscillator over there,
it's over there.
And it's not to be confused with anybody else.
And so,
what this does is it
leaves all the other ones alone.
Let's say i-th.
i is out here somewhere.
n1,
n2,
dot,
until we get up to the i-th place.
And then it gives us ni plus 1,
and then beyond that,
nothing.
But this is not quite right.
This is not quite right because it fails to
take into account the square root of n plus 1.
So,
what we actually have to write...
What am I writing?
I'm writing nonsense.
So,
what we have to write is,
n1,
dot,
ni plus 1,
dot.
But,
we have to put in a
square root of ni plus 1.
So,
in other words,
it works exactly the same as a single oscillator,
with all the other ones just being bystanders,
which play no role when you
hit it with the i-th oscillator.
If you hit it with the j-th oscillator,
some other occupation number would get increased.
Likewise,
for the lowering operators or the annihilation operators,
same kind of understanding.
So,
as I said,
that's what we need to know about oscillators.
Now,
we're going to come to quantum fields.
Real,
genuine quantum fields,
but in a very simple context.
Non-relativistic quantum mechanics,
ordinary quantum mechanics.
Not relativity yet.
We're not doing special relativity,
just ordinary quantum mechanics.
In ordinary quantum mechanics,
there's some kind of funny
connection between particles and fields.
Particles are described by wave functions.
Wave functions are functions of position.
They sort of look like fields.
What are fields?
Fields are things,
degrees of freedom,
which depend on position and on time,
in particular.
But let's just say position for the moment.
Let's freeze time.
Fields are functions of position.
The wave function of a
particle is a function of position.
And so you might think,
that's all there is to it.
That's the connection between particles and fields.
But it's not.
It's not.
Let me...
Or at least it's only
a very tiny part of it.
And in fact,
not the real idea.
It's right up here.
Psi of x.
Psi of x is the wave function of one particle
where x is the position of that particle.
x could stand for x,
y,
and z,
of course.
It doesn't necessarily stand for just x.
But psi is a function of x.
But what is it?
It's not an observable quantity.
It's the state vector.
It's the state vector in the position representation.
It's not an observable.
You don't do experiments to
measure the state of a particle.
You don't measure the wave function of a particle.
You do experiments to measure the position of a particle.
Or the momentum of a particle.
Or the angular momentum of a particle.
But not the state of a particle.
You don't measure...
That's not a measurable thing.
It's a thing which tells you a
great deal about the probabilities of various measurements.
But it itself is not an observable.
So that's the first thing.
Not...
Not an observable.
Next fact.
If we have several particles,
then psi is not a function of one position.
It's a function of all the positions.
I'm gonna...
I want to exaggerate a notation a little bit.
A small psi.
A lowercase psi.
And it's a wave function.
If I have two particles,
let's call them x and y.
Again,
not the x coordinate and the y coordinate of space.
But just the coordinates of two particles.
Then the wave function is a function of two positions.
Alright?
A function of several positions.
In fact,
it's a function of the position of all particles.
Third fact.
What was the third fact?
Ah.
The third fact is given a wave function
which may depend on x1 through some number,
whatever,
x15.
Fifteen particles.
It's the description of a fixed number of particles.
We describe fifteen particles with
the fifteen particle wave function.
Fixed number of particles.
That is not the idea of a quantum field.
By contrast,
now,
I'll tell you by contrast what a quantum field is.
And in many respects,
it's everything that this is not.
Although,
we tend to use the same
notation for it and it's closely related.
Okay.
First of all,
a quantum field,
this is a wave,
these are wave functions.
And they represent state vectors.
Capital Psi is different.
Number one,
it's an observable.
It's a thing you can measure.
Let's just think for a moment.
When we get to the real thing,
more complicated,
serious quantum field theory,
it's going to be things like the electromagnetic field.
It's going to be
the quantum mechanical electromagnetic field.
The electromagnetic field is most certainly an observable.
We observe it.
And so,
first of all,
whatever Psi is,
it is an observable.
Number two,
Psi is a function of only one coordinate.
Oh,
incidentally,
the fact that it's an
observable means that it's an operator.
It means that it's an
operator in the space of states.
It's not itself a state.
It is a operator.
That must be if it's going to be an observable.
Number two,
it's a function of only one coordinate.
Of one position.
Function of one free vector,
so to speak.
And finally,
it describes systems of any number of particles.
Any number of particles.
In other words,
it's capable of describing systems
where particle numbers can change even.
Where particle numbers can change.
How can particle numbers change?
Well,
if we were thinking about the electromagnetic field,
and we remember that electromagnetic field is photons,
every time electromagnetic field is radiated,
it changes the number of photons.
So,
whatever Psi is,
it's a description,
it's an observable,
it's an operator,
it's a function of one position,
and it represents the quantum
mechanics of any number of particles.
Not a fixed number of particles.
That's number one.
I don't want to go too fast,
because this is tricky stuff.
Yeah?
So when you say function of one position,
you mean the position x,
where x can vary?
x can vary.
Yes,
x can vary,
but it's a function of only one x.
Oh boy.
It's a function of only one x,
but that doesn't mean it's a
function of x when x is five.
It means it's a function of x,
x can be anything,
but it's not a function of x1,
x2,
and x3.
But what happens to y,
though?
I keep telling you,
y...
I mean,
y is just not y.
Yeah.
It's just a function of one coordinate.
One coordinate in real world means three coordinates,
means x,
y,
and z.
But that's not what that y is.
No,
no,
that's not what that y is.
That y...
two particles.
One is named x,
the other is named y.
Right.
Why?
Because who's on first?
That's why.
So that's really just a special case of an xy.
You've got two particles in psi xy.
Yes.
You've got 15 particles in psi x1,
x2.
Yeah,
yeah,
that's right.
Okay.
Right.
Y is just x2.
X is x1.
Right.
And one and two label two different particles.
How do these just transform to each other?
How do you explain one in terms of the other?
We can do that.
That's the whole...
That's the whole point.
I laid out for you the big contrast,
and now we want to
know what's the connection between them.
It's going to take a little while.
But it's not...
Different kind of particles?
No,
same kind of particles.
Same kind of particles.
And in particular,
bosons will come to fermions later.
We'll come to fermions later.
Yes,
this is the theory of bosons.
Everything we're doing tonight will be bosons.
Excuse me.
I had a question back
on the left-hand board about the...
What's that?
The what?
A question on the left-hand
board about the harmonic oscillators.
Is the assumption about the independence
of the different operators exact or approximately
correct?
Exact.
Okay.
So,
for example,
pi would not be used
to index the number of particles.
It's not going to index the electrons in an atom.
Say it again?
I would not be using...
I?
Yeah,
the subscript.
That wouldn't be used to index...
I could be labeling the states
of an electron in an atom.
Now,
you've got to be careful.
If the electrons are interacting,
then it's more complicated.
But if you just had non-interacting electrons in an atom,
I would be labeling the states
of the atom.
Okay,
but we're going to come to that.
Okay.
Yeah,
let's come to it right now.
Let's go back to single particle quantum mechanics.
This is the theory of many particles.
Well,
it could be the theory of no particles.
It could be the theory of one particle.
It could be the theory of two particles.
Variable number of particles.
Let's go back to the theory of just one particle.
Okay.
And for simplicity,
I'm going to take a particular example.
A particle in a box.
The potential energy is such that the
particle can't get out of a box.
Just one direction of space,
although nothing I'm saying is going to depend on that.
This is a boson in a box?
A boson.
For the moment,
it doesn't matter.
If there's only one of them,
If there's one of them,
there's no question of
whether there's an exclusion principle
or not.
Right?
So one of them doesn't matter.
Let's think about the energy eigenstates
of a particle in a box.
They're wave functions.
For example,
the lowest energy wave function will
be the smoothest wave function that satisfies
the Schrodinger equation.
And it'll typically look something like that.
It'll be a sine function that
just barely fits in the box.
It fits in the box.
From one end to the other.
And that's a wave function.
It's a wave function in the
sense of this one over here.
Let's give it a name.
Let's call it psi 1 of x.
This should be little psi.
Just make sure it's little psi.
It's just a wave function of
a one particle system in a box.
Psi 1 of x.
What does the one represent?
Just that it's the first energy level.
The lowest energy level.
What about the next energy level?
The next energy level is some other wave function.
And as you go up in energy,
the wave functions tend to be more variable.
The next one would have a node.
Like that.
We can call that psi 2 of x.
I'm using a funny notation.
I'm going to call it psi 2 of x.
That's not a good notation.
The index here is not the number of nodes.
It's one more than the number of nodes,
the number of nodes in the box.
So the next one would be psi 2 of x.
Would have a higher energy
and so forth and so on.
The 1s and the 2s here do not represent,
go down the line,
psi i of x.
Now this I is will be
the same as this I eventually,
but at the moment they're two
different things.
In this case it's labeling oscillators,
in this case it's
labeling state vectors of one particle in a box,
just one particle.
Each one has an energy.
I won't write down what
the energy is other than to
remind you that each of these
wave functions does have an energy.
Okay,
everybody all right with that?
One particle wave functions?
Now,
let's
imagine now that we have many particles.
We have many particles of an
undetermined number.
But some number of them with in state one,
some number of particles in the box
occupying state one,
some number of particles occupying state two,
some
number of particles occupying state three,
and so forth.
That is a pretty good description of a
wide class or a basis of states in fact.
If I know
that is a basis of states saying
how many particles occupy each energy level.
So let's write that down now.
Here's a family of states.
Number of particles in state one,
number of particles in state two,
number of
particles in state three.
Oh boy,
deja vu.
Where is,
ah,
here it is over here.
Absolutely identical to the way I labeled
the states of a multiple harmonic oscillator system.
Now,
of course,
the,
there are
infinitely many possible states
in here of arbitrary wavelength,
arbitrarily small
wavelength,
and that's the reason why we need to
study any number of oscillators up to infinity.
Okay,
so here is a parallel between,
and you wouldn't want to do this for,
you couldn't
do this for fermions.
For fermions you can either have no particle in a,
with a particular
state or one particle,
never two.
Okay,
can't put two.
So in writing down the idea that
you can have any number
of particles in the first state,
any number in the second state,
any number in the third state,
we're assuming to begin with
that we're talking about bosons.
Okay.
But notice.
There's a complete parallel here.
Because there's a complete parallel,
it means we can
invent,
this is an invention out of the head,
operators which do exactly the same thing
as the creation and annihilation operators do.
Now they literally create particles.
For
example,
a plus one on n1 dot dot dot
gives me square root of a plus one.
And then you
can add a square root of n plus one,
n1 plus one,
times n1 plus one,
n2,
n3,
and so forth.
It increases the number of particles in the first state,
whatever it was,
it adds one,
and multiplies by the standard square root.
Why does it multiply by the standard square
root?
That's a definition.
But it's a definition which is very cleverly chosen.
It's a definition
among other things so that we can use
all the apparatus that we have about oscillators,
which is very helpful,
as we'll see.
Likewise,
with the annihilation operator.
Now I'll call
them creation and annihilation operators.
They create and annihilate or remove particles
from the system.
Okay,
that's the basic idea
of creation and annihilation operators.
Question.
Yeah.
On your top line there,
n1 n2 n3,
n4 n3,
n5 n5,
n6 n6,
n7 n7,
n8 n9,
n11 n12,
n12 n13,
n14 n14,
n15 n16,
n17 n18,
n192,
n193,
I thought n1 and n2 were the quantum states.
One two and three are the quantum states.
N1 and two and n3 are the number of particles
in that state.
One two and three are one
two and three up to i,
and past.
Okay,
so this
is tricky.
There's a lot of notation,
but the notation,
it's not hard,
it's just a bit
to remember.
So I'm going slow for that reason and repeating myself.
Question please.
What's the physical meaning in
this environment of that square root?
A plus,
A minus on n is equal to n times n,
right?
Well,
A plus is often a lot like
A minus,
so it better be that A plus and
A minus are somehow square roots of n,
but we
can do better than that.
Let's see,
how can we do better than that?
Hmm.
Let's use the commutation relations.
No.
Okay.
Let's suppose we didn't know this.
Let's suppose we didn't know this,
but we did know about the square roots of n.
Okay,
let's suppose we didn't know,
we knew about the square roots of n.
Okay.
Let's use our commutation relations to write this
as A minus A plus on n minus one,
I think.
Yes?
A minus A plus is equal
to A plus A minus plus one.
Plus one,
right?
Hmm?
One minus?
One minus,
yeah.
Well,
let's see.
A plus A minus A plus minus
A plus A minus is equal to one.
So,
plus one.
Yeah.
You were right.
I was right.
A plus A minus over to the other side.
You get a plus.
Then take the one over and you
get a minus.
Minus one.
Right.
I had it right.
If it doesn't work out,
we'll change it.
Okay.
Now,
what does A plus on n do?
According to assumption,
it gives you square root of
n plus one times n plus one.
Okay.
That's this over here.
But we still have to multiply by A minus.
And then we have another minus n.
That's what we have here,
right?
Okay.
This is just a number,
square root of n plus one.
Let's put it over here.
Square root of n plus one.
What does A minus do when it
acts on square root of n plus one?
Oh,
sorry,
on n plus one?
N.
No,
I think,
yeah,
it gives us n,
but what's the numerical number?
Square root of n plus one.
Square root of n plus one,
right?
Yeah.
So,
we get two square roots of n plus one,
which gives what?
N plus one.
Times n minus one times n,
which is just good old n times n.
In other words,
those square roots of n are there to ensure
that this vector is really an eigenvector of A plus,
A minus.
And roughly speaking,
very roughly,
A plus and A minus are
of the same order of magnitude.
One is P plus Ix,
the other is P minus Ix.
Same order of magnitude.
And since altogether they add up or
they multiply together to give you n,
each one is roughly the square root of n.
Question?
Yeah.
So,
you just sort of define A plus and A minus.
You haven't really defined them,
but you've defined the sort
of various properties that they have,
like the connotation property.
Yeah.
So,
we don't have a definition yet
other than kind of its behavior.
We're making it up.
Okay.
We're defining.
We're not making up randomly,
but we're defining things.
And then we're going to see how they work.
Forgive me.
My question was,
I understand when you apply A plus,
you create a particle.
Mm-hmm.
That's a very tangible thing.
I didn't understand what does that
square root do in a tangible sense?
Mm-hmm.
That's my question.
Nothing.
That's all.
Well.
Just kidding.
Or maybe nothing.
Sometimes mathematics is just mathematics.
Okay.
I mean,
sometimes.
It's like for ordinary quantum mechanics,
you have to normalize the wave function.
Mm-hmm.
And one particle is the same thing here.
Okay.
All right.
Right.
Why doesn't particle disappear?
Why doesn't it become a different state?
What?
When you do A minus,
why does it disappear?
Why doesn't it change?
Why doesn't it become a different state?
That's the definition of A minus.
You can't ask why about a definition.
I define A minus
so that it decreases the number of particles.
Okay.
Definition.
In mathematics,
we make definitions,
and then we find the consequences of them.
So.
The question is,
why is it a useful definition?
Well,
it's a useful definition because we
want to explore systems of various numbers of particles.
In fact,
we want to explore
systems where the number of particles can change.
For example,
we might radiate a photon.
How would we go about mathematically
indicating that we created a photon?
We take the state
and we hit it with a photon creation operator.
Or a photon might be absorbed.
A atom might absorb a photon.
How do we write the fact,
or how do we explain the fact that
the photon has disappeared?
We express it by saying an annihilation operator has acted.
So the purpose of all of this is not
only to be able to study systems of arbitrary number
of particles,
but even to be able to
study systems of variable number of particles.
Okay.
Another question?
Mm-hmm.
So,
here's what I think you're doing.
What you're doing is you're defining these operators,
how they act on a random basis.
Yeah.
And since eigenvectors form a basis,
that tells us how they act on all vectors.
Okay,
I got that part.
Right on.
Okay,
now we've got this definition
of A plus and A minus.
We haven't shown,
but one
assumes that one can show that you
have the commutation relationships that you've got
up there.
Yeah.
With these definitions,
it will follow that these operators have the same
commutation there.
Right.
In other words,
the system of...
Of a variable number of particles here can
be represented just as a system of harmonic
oscillators,
and an oscillator for each state.
For each single particle state,
for each single
particle wave function,
an oscillator and the occupation
number of that oscillator is the
number of particles that
are occupying that particular state.
So the terminology is well
chosen.
Occupation,
now we know what it means.
It's not you occupying your seat.
It's the
particle occupying a state,
and a boson in particular.
These are creation and annihilation operators for particles.
How would you label...
What's the vacuum in this language?
The vacuum...
Well,
first of all,
it's the...
It's the state which is annihilated
by all of the annihilation operators.
It's the state
which when you try to lower any occupation number,
there's nothing there.
Nothing to
lower,
so the state becomes zero.
But the vacuum is simply the state with zero occupation
number in every state.
It has the property that
all the occupation numbers are zero,
and
it has the property that any one of
the A minuses gives zero when it acts.
So the ground state is unoccupied as well?
The ground state is unoccupied.
Right.
But if it was occupied,
you still couldn't lower it?
If it were occupied,
you can lower it.
The ground state?
No,
the ground state is not occupied.
You can't occupy...
That didn't make sense.
Okay.
The ground state is unoccupied.
So you can't write in the vacuum the same thing.
Sorry.
Let's...
While we're at it,
let's write an expression which we
can now do for the energy
of the system.
In order to write an expression
for the energy of the system,
we need to know
the energy of each one of these wave functions.
Each wave function has associated
with it an energy eigenvalue.
What should we call them?
The energies?
We could call them E,
couldn't we?
I'm going to call them omega,
or actually H-bar omega.
But let's just call the energy level of the ith...
Let's kill H-bar,
forget H-bar,
because I've already forgotten it.
And just say the energy...
The energy of a particle in
the first state would be omega one.
the second state would be omega two.
And so forth.
The energy of a particle in
the ith state would be omega I.
Let's write an expression in terms of creation and
annihilation operators for the energy of the whole system.
This is easy.
The energy of the whole system is first of all
the energy of all of the particles in the first state.
So that's the number of particles in the first state.
N1 times the energy that's associated
with the particle in the first state,
omega one.
Plus the number of particles in
the second state times omega two.
Plus and so forth and so on.
So it's the sum of
N sub I omega sub I.
Now that's a true statement,
but I want to write it as an operator statement.
These N's are eigenvalues,
but they're eigenvalues of the number operator.
So we can really write this in operator
form by saying it's the sum over all states,
single particle states,
of omega I times the
occupation number of the ith state.
And what is the occupation number of the ith state?
A dagger I A I.
Notice that each one of these
is just basically the oscillator formula.
This is just the oscillator formula.
There would be an h bar in here.
Put an h bar if you like.
This is just the oscillator formula,
but now it's summed over all the possible states here.
And you can think of it two ways.
You can think of it somehow the
system of particles is equivalent to oscillators.
And those are just the oscillator energies.
Or you can say it's just the
sum of the energy of all the particles.
The number of particles in the first mode,
first state,
times the energy of the first state.
Plus the second state times the energy
of the second state and so forth.
And it comes out to the same thing.
Yeah?
What is A I?
A I?
A minus I,
sorry.
Okay.
Good.
So A,
what is A dagger?
Creation.
Oh,
sorry.
A plus?
Yeah.
Okay.
Good.
Thanks.
In many contexts,
I'm sorry.
once you go to quantum field theory,
which is what we're doing now,
A plus just becomes A dagger
and A minus just becomes A.
Well,
I'll try to stick with the same notation.
I don't want to change notations now.
Okay.
So let's just think for a minute what we're doing.
We're inventing some kind of object
which is a bunch of oscillators.
On the other hand,
the violin string is a bunch of oscillators.
The violin string is a field.
If you look at radiation in a cavity,
radiation bouncing between mirrors,
it's a bunch of oscillators.
People speak,
I mean this goes back from long before quantum mechanics,
speak about radiation as a collection of oscillators.
Radiation oscillators.
Long before quantum mechanics.
And so we're beginning to build
up from thinking about ordinary particles,
we're beginning to build up an idea
of collections of particles as harmonic oscillators.
And soon enough,
we're going to see the connection with fields.
Okay.
If there are no more questions,
maybe we'll take a five-minute break because...
Okay.
I need to stop for a few minutes.
And organize your thoughts and we'll field
a few questions before we go on.
So that's the Hamiltonian.
Is what?
That's the Hamiltonian.
That is the Hamiltonian.
We're going to find other
very elegant ways to write it.
But that is the Hamiltonian.
Right.
Okay.
I want to be able
to remember where I left off.
Okay.
Good.
What do you do with them?
You put them on the...
I'm not sure what he's doing.
I don't know what he does with them either.
He's loading up the website.
Yeah.
I assume he puts them up.
I don't know.
I don't know if he puts them up directly.
I always put them up.
I thought that was the idea,
but I don't remember.
Yeah.
Okay.
Ah.
Take a nap.
What's that?
The energy levels aren't spaced evenly in the box.
No,
that has nothing to do with it.
the energy levels...
No,
it's not the energy levels of the single
particles in the boxes which are evenly spaced.
It's the energy levels of no particle,
one particle,
two particles,
three particles,
which are evenly spaced for each oscillator.
Right.
But isn't it in the
simple harmonic oscillator for single particles,
the energy levels are all spaced apart?
Yes.
Okay.
Yeah.
No.
No,
we're not talking about particles which are
moving in a potential which is an oscillator.
You could.
You could think of a lot of
particles in a potential of an oscillator.
Then you would have two kinds of oscillators.
The particles would be oscillators and the
creation and annihilation operators would be oscillators.
But now we're just talking about...
Any collection of single particle states.
Single particle states is just what you would have thought
about when you're just thinking about one particle quantum mechanics.
But now,
since we can talk about any number of particles,
we can generalize in this way.
So,
there's the pulsating of the slow.
Okay.
We can control the level
of all the particles in this.
We can have the liquid spin the
how the air comes in and out.
Yeah.
How it works is that you can...
I mean,
it can't be done by the switch.
It can't be done by the...
No,
no,
no.
It can't be done by the switch.
No,
no,
no.
It can't be done by the switch.
Yeah.
It's pretty much the same thing.
All the particles that are in one little hole,
they're really...
It's really...
Okay.
Let's get back.
Yeah.
there some questions?
Because I don't want to go too fast
I know that there's a lot of little
indices and little pieces and nuts and bolts here
which if we go fast,
they'll slip out of your head and they
slip out of my head from time to time
Yes?
Is there a connection between
the Fourier and the decomposition?
For sure
If Fourier decomposition,
you're going to have arbitrary amplitudes
The a's are the complex amplitudes of Fourier coefficients
We'll come to that
Yes,
it's deeply related with Fourier analysis
Absolutely
Are we assuming that all
the particles have the same energy?
Same energy?
No,
no,
no
If they're in the first state,
they have energy at one
All the particles which are in
the first state have the same energy
All the particles in the second state
have the same energy as each other
but not as the ones in the first state
So,
you know
But they interact with each other
Well,
okay,
for the moment we're talking
about particles that don't interact
For the moment we're talking about particles
which simply don't interact with each other
That's the starting point
Later we have to ask what kind of things do
we have to do to get the particles to interact
What Giorgio was saying is that
if particles really interacted with each other
the energies wouldn't really be additive
There wouldn't just be the energy of
particle one plus the energy of particle two
There would be the energy of particle
one plus the energy of particle two
plus any kind of potential energy between them,
for example
So,
right,
that's correct
For the moment we're talking about free particles
Free particles means particles which
don't interact with each other
Okay,
now we come
No other questions?
Yes
So in non-right-tempistic quantum field theory there's still
a half a boson in the ground state?
Yes,
but it doesn't play
It doesn't do anything
It's just zero-point energy
And why doesn't zero-point energy,
why is it irrelevant for everything?
Well,
if you think what does...
Energy is Hamiltonian
What happens if you add a constant,
a number,
to a Hamiltonian?
Well,
a number commutes with everything
And if you remember what the Hamiltonian does for you
is it provides a method of getting equations of motion
The time dependence of something
is related to the commutator
of that thing with the Hamiltonian
Constants do nothing
They commute with everything
Another way of saying it
is in keeping track of energies
the only thing that really counts is energy differences
Not the...
So you can throw away that ground state energy
except for certain very special purposes that
are not going to concern us right now
Okay,
quantum fields
A field is a function of space
It's not a function of two points
of space or three points of space
So it's not like the wave
function of a many particle system
It's a thing which only depends on one coordinate
It's also an operator
Why?
Because it's an observable
You observe fields,
you measure them
What was the third point about...
No,
I don't remember
But...
Any...yeah,
and somehow...
Somehow this has to do with your
ability to change the number of particles
Okay,
so I'm...what we're going to do is
I'm going to give you the rule
for the quantum field of this system of particles
And then we're going to explore how it works
If you ask me previously...
Prematurely why that's the definition
Well,
it won't work
It won't work
The best thing to do...sometimes it's
just best to follow the definition
And I promise you we won't go too
far before you start to see why it works
and why it's interesting and why that's the definition
But it's better not to try
to intuit out from the beginning
why this is the particular definition
Rather get used to it and familiar with it
and in a short amount of time
you'll understand why that's the thing to do
The definitions...the value of the
definitions depends on their utility
Alright,
on what you can do with them and...
I might say this to begin with
Quantum field theory,
at least in the way we're thinking about it here
among other things is a bookkeeping device
It's a bookkeeping device for keeping track
of many particles,
for keeping track of the quantum mechanics
of particles which come and go,
change their state
even disappear and reappear,
whatever
It's a kind of bookkeeping device
Whenever you have operators like this,
you're doing bookkeeping
It's a little more than that
because you can actually measure these fields
The things when they go by you,
you feel them,
they have an effect on you
But for the moment we can
just think of it as bookkeeping
And...
Whether a definition is a useful definition or not
depends on what you try to do with it
And I can tell you with
quantum fields you can do a lot
Yeah
Could you take a minute or two to say just
a little bit about the history of quantum field theory
when it was developed,
who developed it?
Well...
We go way,
way back
We can start with the
question of who invented field theory
Alright
Who invented field theory?
Anybody know who invented field theory?
I suppose it was Faraday
with the electric and magnetic field
So I think probably the idea can best be...
The original history started with,
I think,
with Faraday
Maxwell invented field equations
Faraday didn't have field equations,
he just had a feel for the fields
A feel for the fields
And...
And was able to visualize them
Maxwell wrote down,
as far as I know
Well,
it's probably not true that he was the
first one to write down a wave equation
There were wave equations
Waves of water,
waves of other things
But I think it can fairly be said that
Maxwell wrote down the first modern version of field theory
But it was classical field theory
Um...
The need to quantize fields
Or the need to do something involving H-bar
Goes back to Planck
Planck...
Well,
it goes back before Planck
We have not talked...
We will eventually talk about
what is called the ultraviolet catastrophe
Won't talk about it now
But Planck realized that classical field theory would
not be adequate for studying thermodynamics of radiation
Introduced Planck's constant
And in the process
Uh...
Basically said some things about harmonic oscillators
Which were more or less correct
He didn't realize that the radiation
field itself was made out of oscillators
Or photons,
as we call...
Or quanta of the field
He was thinking about the oscillators
in the walls of a cavity
Namely the atoms
Which he thought of and envisioned as literally oscillators
Little oscillating charges
And um...
His application of Planck's constant
And this...
He didn't have his mathematics
But the idea that the energy levels were integer spaced
He wrongly thought that that
had to do with the um...
With the oscillators in the walls of the cavity
It was Einstein who first um...
Understood that the...
That the quantization of oscillations
Had to do with the electromagnetic field
With Maxwell's electromagnetic field
So as with almost everything else
It was Einstein who uh...
Had the first inklings of this
But then later
It was Heisenberg,
Pauli,
Dirac was the...
Dirac was the person who really put
it together in the form we're talking about
Uh...
And that was...
Basically around 1929
Around 1929 a lot of these ideas uh...
First really surfaced
But um...
You know as usual Einstein uh...
Had...
Really did have all the ideas and uh...
Um...
Although he hadn't articulated them
in exactly the modern form
But um...
After that
The whole history
But uh...
Not for tonight
Um...
This notion of particles or variable
number of particles as harmonic oscillators
That's a good question
Who was the first one?
I'm guessing Dirac again
But I'm not sure that he
was the first one to identify
Particle creation and annihilation as a form of um...
Harmonic oscillator mathematics
I would guess it was Dirac
Probably around 1930
What was the first major problem that
they could solve that hadn't been solved before?
The first major problem was the
problem of the ultraviolet catastrophe of uh...
Of um...
Or basically why radiation was quantized
Einstein knew radiation was quantized
Okay he knew that radiation came in photons
But he didn't have a
mathematical way to think about it
Uh...
The first major problem that was solved
Was a formal mathematical quantum mechanics
That was consistent with the rest of quantum mechanics
That included the idea that radiation came in photons
That radiation came so far away from us that
it was impossible to find it in the universe
So far we have never even
talked about what a photon is
We're getting close
A photon has something to do with the electromagnetic field
And...
It's a unit of energy
It's like...
These occupation numbers
Okay
The things which occupy the occupation numbers are quanta
If the particles we're talking about
are the quanta of the electromagnetic field
They're called photons
So...
That's where we're going
We're...
Really getting close to talking about what a photon is
Or what a quantum of a field is
In fact...
Right now we're going to introduce
the notion of a quantum field
The simplest version of it
I'm going to give it to you as a definition
And we're going to see what
it does and how it works
Okay
So,
psi is a quantum field
And I'm going...
Again,
because it's a quantum field,
it's an operator
It's something you can measure
I'm going to call it capital Psi
It's an operator,
but it's an operator which depends on position
So it's not a single operator
It's an operator for each of the...
For each position
For each position,
a separate operator
It acts on a space of states
The space of states...
What is the space of states?
Where is it?
We erased it?
Well,
the space of states...
And one and two...
Incidentally,
this is called a Fox space
F-O-K
F-O-C-K
F-O-K was a Russian physicist
I doubt very much that he
was the first one to use this
But he wasn't
But it got named after him for the
usual reasons that things get named after people
Namely,
no reason
Okay
The quantum field psi of x
It's just a very short definition
It's equal to the sum over
all of the single particle wave functions
Sum over i
A contribution for each one of these states
So it's a sum over i
It contains psi i of x
The single particle wave function
These are things like sines and cosines
Sines and cosines of different wave number
Of different wavelength
That's what goes there
And what multiplies it
The coefficients
The coefficients are the creation and annihilation operators
In this case,
the annihilation operators
i
Now,
somebody asked me if any of
this has to do with Fourier analysis
If the size...
If the size were momentum eigenstates
That means they're sines and cosines
Then...
Then these operators A-
Would look...
Would resemble very closely the coefficients
That occur in Fourier analysis
That is,
they are the quantum version of the Fourier coefficients
When you expand the thing in sines and cosines
Now,
it might not be sines and cosines
It's whatever the...
The orthonormal family of states
Of single particle states is
That's it
That's the definition of a quantum field
The simplest...
The simplest example
What's that?
The left hand side is the operator,
right?
The right hand side...
Does it include the psi there?
These sines are just numbers
Now,
in fact,
there's a separate number for each position
Psi of x are just classical...
Just functions
So if I want to know what
the quantum field is at x equals 0
I plug in x equals 0 here
If I want to know what it is
at x equals the square root of pi
I put in the square root of pi here
So it's a...
It's a whole set of function...
Sorry,
it's a whole set of operators
One for each position in space
That's a lot of operators
Why so rich?
Why are there so many operators?
The reason is because we're trying to study a system
Where there can be infinite...
Any number of particles
That's a lot of states
A lot of states,
a lot of operators
Just because the number of particles is totally unbounded
In this idea
Okay,
so there's an operator at each position
This x and this x are the same
The sines are different
This is an operator
This is just a function
A function of position
The operator is in here
That's where the operator is
There is the complex conjugate or the Hermitian conjugate
This is an operator
It's not a number
But it has a Hermitian conjugate
It's exactly the same thing except
That we put creation operators there
And psi star here
These quantum fields are not Hermitian
They're not Hermitian because the creation
and annihilation operators are not Hermitian
And so they're not really observables
But if you add psi and psi star,
or psi dagger
Or you subtract them
You can make Hermitian combinations out of them
And those really are things that
you could observe in the laboratory
Just because they're Hermitian operators
Now we're going to explore these objects
I'm going to go slow
But the first thing I want to show
you is what the action of psi is
Psi of x,
capital Psi of x
When it hits the vacuum
What does it do when
you apply it to the vacuum?
Let's take psi dagger
Incidentally,
what does psi do when the vacuum hits the vacuum?
It kills it,
it annihilates it
Why?
Because it's only got annihilation operators in it
Psi dagger,
however,
has creation operators
It creates a particle
Each term in here creates a particle
It doesn't create a lot of particles
It creates a superposition of particles
But one particle in a superposition of states
So let's see if we
can figure out what it does
When it hits the vacuum
Okay,
so here's what we're going to do
Let's take single particle quantum mechanics
One particle quantum mechanics to begin with
In other words,
forget all this fancy stuff with oscillators
Just good old quantum mechanics of a single particle
There's a complete set of states
The complete set of states are the position states
Let's see,
how do I want to write this?
Okay
States which are located where the
particle is located at position x
They're a complete set of states
That means they're a complete basis of states
And that means that you can,
if you sum over all positions
Or integrate over all positions
I'll use a,
I'll keep it simple
I'll imagine summing over positions
But we may have to do an integral
If we sum over all positions
What do we get on the right hand side?
One
One,
the unit operator
That's a general rule for any basis of states
Okay,
now
Let's see,
I just
I'm just trying to remember which way I did this
That's a true statement
But what I actually wanted was a different statement
It is a true statement
But what I actually wanted was
This statement
Sum over i
As usual,
about this time at night I start making mistakes
And I was just about to make a mistake,
but I caught myself
What are these i's,
do you remember?
They're the one particle states
The ones which look like this
Psi 1,
psi 2,
psi 3,
psi 4,
and psi 5,
and so forth
They are a complete,
they're the energy eigenstates
They are a complete set of states
If I take all the
signs that can fit into here,
for example
Sine of x,
sine of 2x,
sine of 3x,
sine of 4x
That's a complete set of states
Each one of these i's here
Is a state whose wave function is psi i
But the psi i's are a complete set of states
And so it follows
That this expression here is just the unit operator
This is true for any complete basis of states
You can go back to your quantum
mechanics and you'll remember what this means
Now
That means
This is a little bit of trickery,
but there's nothing deep going on here
The sum over i
Of i i
That's an operator
That's the unit operator,
it's trivial
It's a unit operator
And what happens if I apply it
To a state in which the
particle is known to be at x
What do I get?
I get a particle at x
I've done nothing
I've just rewritten the particle at position x
On the other hand,
what is this object over here?
A coefficient
Well,
it's a coefficient,
alright
But it's also a wave function
Do I have it?
Yes,
it's a wave function
It's the wave function
Of
The state i
The inner product of a particle at x
With the state vector i
Is just
Is it psi or is it psi star?
Anybody know?
I know
Happens to be psi star
So,
this can also be written
As the sum over i
Psi star
Of i of x
Times the state i
That's a particle located at point x
Now let me slow down here and
Get any question about this
Because I'm sure this must be a little bit confusing
This is the unit operator
We apply it on a state located at x
And it gives us a state located at x
On the other hand,
this inner product
Of a particle at x
With the wave function psi
Or the state vector psi
Is just psi star of i
It's just a wave function
Okay?
But what about this
What about the state here?
That state
Is a one particle
Is one particle
With wave function
Psi i
I can write it another way
I can write it as follows
i
Is
Is equal
To a plus i
On the vacuum
The vacuum has no particles in it
If I create a particle
In the state i
Then indeed I have a particle at i
I have a particle in the state i
So I can substitute for this
I can substitute a plus
i
On the vacuum
No,
one particle
One particle
This is one particle
In the state i
That's all,
just one particle
And it gives me a particle
At position x
But wait a second
The thing that I wrote down here
Is exactly the quantum field psi dagger
So we can now write this in another form
We can write a particle at position x
Is psi dagger
At position x
On the vacuum
So now we know what psi is
And what psi dagger is
It's an operator which creates a particle at position x
If we have no particles
And we want to create a particle
We want to change the number of particles
By adding one at position x
Then
The way to do it
Is to apply psi dagger
To the vacuum
Creates a particle at position x
What if we wanted to
create another particle at position y
Well it's not too hard to work out
But what do you expect?
You expect
Just hit it with the field operator
We'll call this the field operator now
Or the creation,
the field operator
We just hit it with another side dagger
But at position y
So whatever the state is
If you want to add
a particle at a particular location
That's the job of the quantum field
It's a function of x
Y
No,
not y
Ooh
It's a function of x because
It has to know where to put the particle
It's an operator that puts a particle at x
It's not the operator that puts the particle at y
So it must be itself a function of x
That's what
In a simple situation
In a simple situation that we're working on now
That's the meaning of the quantum field
It creates a particle at position x
The creation and annihilation operators
Create particles in the energy eigenstates
You apply a dagger to the vacuum
And you get a particle
Not at position i,
that doesn't mean anything
But in the wave function i
Sines and cosines and so forth
That's the meaning of a plus
On the other hand when you
combine them together into the quantum field
The quantum field creates a particle at position x
What do you think the annihilation operator
What do you think the other piece does
That removes a particle at x
If there's one there
What if there's none there
Then it annihilates the state
So
So psi dagger creates a particle at position x
Whether or not there's one there
Psi annihilates a particle at x
Or gives zero if there's no particle there
Question please
Where is the information
What kind of particle could be created buried in
It should be in the little a plus
First of all
First of all we're talking about bosons
If you get fermions you don't do them this way
Which bosons?
Right
There's a separate quantum field for each species of boson
So what kind of bosons are there in the world
There's photons
There's gravitons
There are Higgs bosons
There are gluons
For each species of boson
There is a separate quantum field
that creates that kind of particle
In this manner
Right
So the particle is
Is it being created with
a delta function probability distribution
By psi of x
That's right
Right
That's exactly right
So
Right
Excuse me
So if there's nothing
If there's no particle at position x
Then psi of x does nothing?
No it gives zero
What does give zero mean?
The same thing that when
When an annihilation operator hits a
state with no particle in it
Or when the annihilation operator hits the
The ground state
Yeah
Gives zero
It's doing nothing
No
No?
It's giving zero
Giving zero
What is
Thinking of it
In terms of particles and positions
No
If there's nothing at that position
What does it mean to give zero
To a position I guess
You started with a vacuum
The vacuum is not zero
Oh no
The vacuum is a state
It's a normalized state whose length is one
It's a good state
There's nothing wrong with it
It's there
It's a
But it has properties
The properties are those of empty space
When an annihilation operator hits it
It literally gives zero
The zero vector
The vector of zero length
Now I can understand what that is
How can you have a zero
Zero is the unique and only vector
That if you add it to any other vector
You get the same one back
It's a vector in a vector space
Go back to vector spaces
Vector spaces have in them zero vectors
Zero vectors are vectors of zero length
It's not interesting
It doesn't have any properties
It's just a
It doesn't describe
It doesn't describe anything
It doesn't describe physically the thing itself
It doesn't describe physically anything
It's just
If you add vacuum you get something else
Hm
So if you add the zero state
To the vacuum
You get the same thing
What if you add the vacuum
Oh you certainly don't get the
If you add the vacuum
Let's say to a one particle state
Then you get a state
Which has
Let's say you add it with equal coefficients
Just to be simple
Then you get a state
That has a probability of a half
Of having a particle
And a probability of half
Not having a particle
You see the
If you add the zero state
Not the vacuum
To a one particle state
You just get the one particle state
If you add the vacuum to the one particle state
You get something
That has a statistical probability
Of let's say a half to have a particle
And a statistical probability
To not have a particle
Zero cannot be normalized
It is definitely not normalized
It's of zero length
The one thing that you can't normalize
Is a vector of zero length
Right
The vacuum is not a vector of zero length
It
For a little bit of time
People generally get confused
By the notation
This looks like it's zero
But it's not zero
It's just a name
The zero here
Does not mean
That it's a vector of zero length
It does not mean
That if you add it to another vector
You get back the same vector
It's just the name of the vector
And it represents
A perfectly good physical state
It happens to be a state
With no particles in it
But it's a state
So
It's empty space
But it's a state
So we could have put a half in there
You could
You know you could have called it
Um
Right
You know
You could have called it
George Bush
Or whatever you want to call it
It doesn't matter
Once you've annihilated it
We're talking about annihilation
No
Once you've annihilated the vacuum
You can't create anything
That it gives
Right
We won't talk about
Annihilation
And George Bush
In this
Yeah
Once
That's right
Once you've annihilated it
You can't put anything back
So
You know
It's just
It's just zero
It's literally zero
Right
Any operator that acts on the zero vector
Just gives back the zero vector
Doesn't give anything interesting
Right
You know
It's like
One minus one is zero
Take any vector
And subtract it from the same vector
And you get zero
If you add zero to any number
You get the same number
Add the vector zero to
You know
Here
Here's the zero vector
Right there
So
We're talking about
Has no length
The vacuum on the other hand
Has a length of one
As a vector in the vector space
Normalized
Not easy
But you get used to it
On the left board
The lower sum
Yeah
Does the order of those operators
No
This
Only this is an operator
At each point x
This is just an ordinary
Number
Doesn't matter which order you put it in
Numbers times operators
Are operators times numbers
Right
So just think of psi of x
As a collection of numbers
One for each x
Right
So the
Complex numbers
Hmm
In general complex numbers
Yeah
They will in general be complex numbers
That of course depends on the solutions
To the Schrodinger equation
Whether it's real or complex
But that's right
Yeah
So
Yeah I think this to me that
The quantum field description of a particle
Is you basically do a creation operator
On the vacuum space
How would you define a second particle
By applying again another
You want to put a particle in a position y
On top of this
A phi star to the
Yeah
Left of it
If you wanted to put another particle
At position y
Okay let's make a two particle state
Good
Let's make a two particle state
And make
And one more observation about it
Here's a two particle state
This is a particle at x
And a particle at y
Now x and y are two particles
So x and y could be the same point
Or they could be different points
Let me point one thing out
One interesting fact
The size are made out of
Annihilation operators
There are no creation operators
In here at all
Every annihilation operator commutes
With every other annihilation operator
Okay
Wait is side dagger a creation operator
No
I'm sorry did I make a mistake
Yeah
Right
Side dagger is a creation operator
Of course
But still it's true
That every creation operator
This is the important thing
It wasn't whether it was creation or annihilation
Each one commutes with every other one
Okay
Every operator in here creates
Annihilation operators
Every operator in here commutes
With every operator in here
That means side dagger of y
And side dagger of x commute
Let's call this the state with a particle
At y and x
Well this is also equal to
Side dagger of x
Times side of y
On o
Dagger
Thank you I'm losing it
And that's equal to the state
With a particle at x
And a particle at y
Notice they're equal to each other
They're equal as a consequence of the fact
That these commute
Alright
The fact that these commute
Because they're built out of a state
Of oscillators in a certain way
Tells us that it doesn't matter
Which order we put the part
Which order we write the particles in here
In other words
Particle one at y
Particle two at x
Is the same as particle one at x
Particle two at y
That's the defining property of bosons
That it doesn't matter which order
You express them
A particle
Particle
Harry over here and Jeffrey over here
Is the same as Jeffrey over here
And Harry over there
So that's fully equivalent to symmetrization?
It's fully equivalent to symmetrization
And it tells you that the particles
Are most definitely bosons
So I didn't have
I didn't really have to say from the beginning
Well we're going to study bosons
I could have started with this construction
And we would have derived
That the particles studied this way are bosons
So the interesting question is
Well how the hell then do you make fermions?
Yeah
That's more abstract
So does this imply that x and
y are the same kind of bosons?
X and y?
X and y are positions
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah
They're the same kind of bosons
That's right
So a given quantum field
Describes one type of particle
There's a quantum field for photons
Well actually there are two quantum fields for photons
Because of the two polarizations
There's a quantum field
Let's say a photon is along some axis
There's a quantum field for the photons
Polarized one way
Another quantum field for the photons
Polarized the other way
There's a quantum field for
Each different type of particle
There's a separate quantum field
And if you want to make that kind of particle
You apply that quantum field
So that's what a quantum field is
Or at least
In its simplest incarnation
And I assure you this is the simplest
But the basic concept
Or the connection
You see what we're doing is
We're talking about the connection
Between particles and fields
Here is the connection between particles and fields
This is the field
When you apply it to the vacuum
You create a particle
You define the field to be this
You define
Yes that's right
We defined it
But once we've defined it
It's an operator
If we add it to its complex conjugate
It's a Hermitian operator
Hermitian operators are observables
All of a sudden it takes on a life
As something that we can measure
And do all the things with observables that we do
So to all the properties of the field
Come out of these creation and annihilation operators
Yes
None of this would be interesting
If we were talking about a situation
Where you could not create and annihilate particles
The whole point of this
Well I take
Let me say a little less strongly
None of this would be interesting
If we were only working
In a context where there were 37 particles
Never 36
Never 45
But 37 particles
End of story
We wouldn't do this
If we're interested in studying
the whole set of possibilities
Of any number of particles
Then this is a good tool
But even better
When we're studying the possibility
Of the number of particles itself being ambiguous
Meaning to say a statistical variable
A quantum mechanical variable
We can study states in which there's a superposition
Of different numbers of particles
No particle
One particle
Two particles
And these have real meaning
An electromagnetic wave
A laser wave is like that
A laser wave is not a definite number of particles
It's a superposition
One,
two,
three
Zero,
one,
two,
three
And good
Okay
Now we're finished for tonight
For more
Please visit us at
Stanford.edu
The Interdimensional Fermi Laboratory