Stanford University.
All right, so we spoke a little bit about quantum fields.
The quanta of the fields, creation operators, annihilation operators.
We even went so far as to talk about the Hamiltonian operator
for a very simple quantum field, satisfying particles, satisfying the Schrodinger equation.
Write it down.
This is what it looked like.
Integral over position.
Now when I write dx, you don't need to imagine that it's one-dimensional.
You can imagine that it's multi-dimensional and x stands for a collection of coordinates, x, y, and z.
But I'll write it as if it were one-dimensional.
And then there's the quantum field, psi dagger.
That's the creation operator.
It creates a particle at position x.
And then there's a minus sign.
Let's put the minus sign explicitly over here.
Del squared, the second derivative operator.
And if we put the mass in, the mass goes downstairs here.
That's p squared over 2m.
That's the standard kinetic energy of a particle.
And then psi.
If the particle also happens to be in a potential, if there's a potential energy,
then you would add in here, and this of course is also of x,
and then there's a v of x, the potential,
times psi dagger.
And then the energy of the particle is psi dagger of x, psi of x.
And the way you would understand this term is just every particle,
if it's at position x, has a potential energy v of x.
Psi dagger of x times psi of x, what is that?
That's the density of particles at point x.
So this is just counting the number of particles at point x
and giving each one an energy, a potential energy v of x.
You would write that down classically too.
You would write down that if you had a gas of particles,
and they were moving in some potential,
you would write that the potential energy is the integral of all space,
the density of particles at point x,
times the potential at that point x.
Okay, so that's the Hamiltonian of a system of particles
non-interacting with each other.
They may be interacting with some potential.
Okay, I'm going to leave out the O.
Tell you what, yeah.
Let's forget this term for a moment.
No, I'll tell you what, I'm going to put it back,
but I'm going to put it back v of x,
and I'm going to take v of x to be a constant.
Now we all know that a constant term, potential energy,
doesn't exert any forces.
So it really doesn't do anything, but let's put it anyway.
A constant, it doesn't matter what we call it,
times psi dagger of x, psi of x.
Okay.
What kind of term in the energy would this correspond to?
Well, it's a term which, when you integrate it over x,
it just counts the total number of particles.
So, if it counts the number of particles,
it's just an energy proportional to the number of particles.
It's giving each particle an energy.
How much energy does a particle have?
I'm not talking about its kinetic energy.
We've already got its kinetic energy,
but just a particle standing still.
Does a particle standing still have any energy?
Yeah, as mc squared.
So if we wanted to put that in,
if we wanted to keep track of the fact that every particle has an energy mc squared,
we would put it over here.
Whatever it is, it's a number.
The reason I want to include this here is for a very simple reason.
I want to spend a minute or two talking about energy,
not energy conservation, momentum conservation.
How do we see,
from this expression,
that momentum is conserved?
What does it mean for momentum to be conserved?
Well, what does the Hamiltonian do?
What's the role of the Hamiltonian?
The role of the Hamiltonian is to update the state of the system.
If the state of the system at time t is psi of t,
now I'm using psi to indicate a state.
I'd better not do that.
I've already used psi for several different things.
One of them is for the field operator.
One of them is for the single particle wave functions.
I'd better not use it again.
So let's use a different terminology for the state vector of a system.
Let's not call it psi.
The vector itself, let's call it phi.
Right, if the state of the system at one instant of time,
let's say at time t,
is the vector psi of phi,
excuse me, phi of t,
then what is it at the next instant of time displaced
by time epsilon?
Well, the answer is,
that's what the Hamiltonian does.
It gives you one,
minus,
minus i epsilon,
that's the little time interval,
little separation of time,
the Hamiltonian,
times phi itself.
Sorry, this is phi of t plus epsilon.
The field, or sorry, the state,
at a slightly displaced time.
And so what h does,
is it just updates
things.
You can write this as just phi of t.
That's the same state back again.
Nothing has happened.
Plus a little correction after time epsilon,
which is minus i epsilon,
times the Hamiltonian acting on phi.
That's what the Hamiltonian does.
And you can think of it as being iterated.
You can do it over and over and over again
at each step.
That of course is another way of talking about
the Schrodinger equation.
The Schrodinger equation says
the time derivative of phi
is equal to h times phi.
So that's what the Hamiltonian does.
It changes the state from one instant to another.
What would it mean
to say that momentum is conserved?
What it means is that the Hamiltonian,
when it acts on a state of definite momentum,
does not change the momentum.
Whatever the Hamiltonian does,
if it acts on a state of a given momentum,
it must give back a state of the same momentum
if momentum is conserved.
I'm not saying it is conserved.
I'm saying that's what it would mean.
If the momentum is conserved,
it means that when the Hamiltonian acts,
it doesn't change the momentum of the system.
It may change other things,
but it doesn't change the momentum.
Okay, we can check that.
This is an interesting thing to check.
For this Hamiltonian,
does it change the momentum of the system?
Okay, let's begin by looking at this term here.
Let's forget the other term and see what it does
when it acts on a state with a given total momentum.
Okay, so what do we want to do?
We want to rewrite this in the momentum basis.
Let me remind you how that worked.
That was just a good old Fourier transform.
Okay, so the way that works
is you say the creation operator for a...
Oh, this happens to be the annihilation operator.
But the annihilation operator for a particle at point x
is an integral over all of the momentum
to the square root of 2 pi,
if you want to keep track of it.
In fact, there's a square root of 2 pi,
for each direction of space.
So if this were three-dimensional,
there would be a 2 pi cubed,
but again, this is incidental and not important.
And then, what we called psi twiddle, I believe, of p.
This is the annihilation operator
for a particle of momentum p.
This annihilates a particle of momentum x.
This annihilates a particle of momentum p,
but then we have to multiply this by e to the i p x
and integrate over p.
That's the creation operator x
in terms of the creation operator
for a particle of momentum p.
Now, I'm interested in what this operator does
when it acts on a state,
but I'm interested in what it does to the momentum.
So the natural thing to do is to rewrite this
in terms of the momentum variables.
So let's do that.
Let's go down here.
mc squared, that's just a number.
And now, we have integral dx.
Now, each one of these can be rewritten that way.
Alright, so there's an integral.
Let's write a second equation here.
Psi dagger of x
is a similar integral.
I'm not going to write it as an integral of p
because I've already used p.
p is an integration variable.
I don't want to reuse it.
I don't want to recycle it.
I want to use another variable.
Let's call it q, dq,
over 2 pi.
Psi dagger twiddle of q.
And now there's an e to the minus i q x.
Why is it e to the minus i q x?
Because we're supposed to put the complex conjugate wave functions here.
Everything gets complex conjugated.
Okay, let's take psi of x times psi dagger of x,
exactly the thing which appears here.
And then let's integrate it over x and see what we get.
Just for fun.
This is sort of fun like going to the dentist, right?
Yeah, okay.
So we multiply the two of these together.
And we get a double integral.
What's that?
That?
Ah, okay.
Okay, so we get to the dentist.
And the dentist, first of all, says 1 over 2 pi.
1 over 2 pi for each direction.
And then there is
psi twiddle of p times psi dagger.
I suppose we should put them in the opposite order
since over here,
the daggers stand to the left.
So let's stand the daggers to the left.
Psi twiddle dagger of q.
That's this one.
And then psi twiddle of p.
We're going to integrate over p and q in a moment.
But let's first put e to the i p minus q x.
That's this factor, e to the i p minus q x.
Question?
No.
Okay.
And then we integrate over x.
This instruction here is to integrate over x.
Okay.
Does anybody remember what you get
when you integrate e to the i something times x over x?
A delta function.
Now the way, if you forget that,
the way to think about it is the following.
Supposing p minus q is not 0,
then this is an oscillating thing.
If p minus q is not 0,
then it oscillates with x.
What happens if you integrate something which oscillates
as much positive as negative?
Dp dq.
Yeah. Sorry. Dp dq.
Okay.
Yeah.
Yeah, it just depends on the nature of the oscillation,
but if it's all symmetric, then it cancels out.
That's right. Okay.
This is a mnemonic.
This is not a rigorous argument.
But if p is not equal to q,
it oscillates, it has a sine in it, a cosine in it.
The sines and cosines are as positive as they are negative,
and that must integrate to 0.
On the other hand, if p is equal to q,
then this is just 1,
and the integral of 1 over all space is infinite.
So this is a function of p minus q,
which is 0 if p minus q is not 0,
in other words, if p is not equal to q,
and it's infinite if p equals q.
Obviously, this is proportional to the Dirac delta function,
and with the 2 pi there, it is the Dirac delta function.
So this all becomes...
We can erase...
We can erase the e to the i,
p minus q,
erase the integral dx,
and just write that this is delta of p minus q,
and we also get rid of the 1 over 2 pi.
Okay.
What happens if we integrate psi dagger of q times psi of p
with a function which is 0 unless p is equal to q?
Well, that's just the instruction.
Do the integral, but set p equal to q.
If you set p equal to q, there's only one integration,
and this is just equal to
psi dagger twiddle of q.
Let's write it as p.
The instruction here is set q equal to p,
so this is p psi of p.
Okay. Now, what do we have here?
We have an operator which contains a destruction operator,
or an annihilation operator,
times a creation operator.
It's an annihilation operator for a particle of momentum p,
so if it finds a particle of momentum p,
it pulls it out and kills it, you know, it annihilates it,
but then it puts back a particle of the same momentum.
Notice, here was the important thing,
that by the time you're finished,
p had to equal q.
p had to equal q tells you that if you remove a particle,
you put back a particle of the same momentum,
and the momentum doesn't change
when this operator operates on a state,
it does not change the momentum.
Whatever it takes out, it puts back.
Okay.
What was the working ingredient here?
It was the integral over x,
which turned this into a delta function.
Okay. The integral over x turned it into a delta function,
and the delta function,
you can say, was the delta function of momentum conservation.
Momentum, that when the Hamiltonian acts,
when it updates the state a little bit,
we somehow no longer have the little,
the updating of the state,
but when it updates the state a little bit,
it doesn't change the momentum.
Okay.
Now, we can go,
we can do the same thing
with this term here,
let's do it,
let's go through it,
just to peek,
just so that you see how the machinery works.
Quick question, please.
Yeah.
What happened to the being infinite
when p is equal to q?
Somehow, we don't talk about it.
No, no, that's okay.
Whenever you integrate a Dirac delta function
with another function,
you just get that function at point zero.
That's the definition of Dirac delta function.
The fact that it's infinite but of zero width.
See, it's a thing which is infinitely high
but infinitely narrow.
The area under it is one unit.
Okay.
So it doesn't give anything infinite,
it just gives back,
and in this case,
it just tells you,
set p minus q equal to zero,
which is the same thing as setting p equal to q.
Okay.
Before I look at this term here,
let me just point out that this could be more general.
Let's suppose we had a term in the Hamiltonian
which had, for whatever reason,
for reasons that we'll talk about later,
we had a whole bunch of fields.
They could even be fields for different kinds of particles.
Creation operator and annihilation operator
for different kinds of particles.
And instead of having just a single field,
just two of them,
we could imagine in the Hamiltonian,
and we'll discuss what this means,
that we could have any number of side daggers,
a particle of type A,
particle of type B,
any number of size,
particle of type C,
particle of type D,
they could all be the same or not the same,
any number of side daggers and any number of size.
So, let's suppose in some insane world,
we put this thing into the Hamiltonian.
What would happen?
Well, instead of getting what we have up here,
this simple expression,
what we would have is a whole bunch of integrals,
a p integration for each field that appears here.
Let's, yeah,
whole bunches of p's,
the p's could stand for the half of the particles
that are being created, for example,
dp1, dp2, dp3, and so forth,
however many particles,
or however many fields there are with dagger.
And then,
oh no, those are q's, sorry,
q's go with the daggers,
p's go with the size.
Alright, so we have some q's also,
dq1, however many of those there are.
And then we have a bunch of creation and annihilation operators
of exactly the same kind,
except many of them now.
side dagger of p1,
or side twiddle of p1, dot dot dot,
side daggers,
size of q's,
q1, dot dot dot.
But then the all important exponentials.
The all important exponentials,
and they read, for each side,
let's see, for each,
I think I did it wrong again,
q, p.
If I wanted to follow the same notation up there,
p.
Then I would have an e to the i,
and then for each p,
p1 plus p2 plus p3,
all times x,
each one would come in with its own e to the i, px,
and you'd add them all up in the exponent,
but then you'd also have minus i,
q1 plus q2, dot dot dot, x.
In other words, instead of just having a single p and a single q,
you would have a bunch of p's,
for all the creation operators,
which ones get the p's,
p's go with the annihilation operators,
and q's go with the creation operators.
Okay.
And you have to integrate it over x.
You have to integrate it over x.
What does the integration over x give you?
Again, it gives you a delta function,
and it's a delta function of the sum of all the p's,
minus the sum of all the q's.
In other words, it's a rule,
that the sum of the p's has to be equal to the sum of the q's.
The sum of the p's,
is equal to the sum of the q's.
So,
the sum of the p's,
is equal to the sum of the q's.
The sum of the p's,
is
all the particles that you take out.
The things of the annihilation operators.
The sum of the p's,
is all of the momentum of the particles that you put in.
So it's just a rule.
It says, the rule just says,
the total momentum of the particles
that you take out,
must equal the total momentum of the particles that you put back.
It's a rule,
that
follows from this kind of Hamiltonian here.
Now, what's really going on,
is the fact that this Hamiltonian is translation invariant.
But I wanted to show you how
the machinery works.
And so whenever you see a Hamiltonian of this form,
that it has a whole bunch of
size and side daggers,
but you integrate it over space.
It's the integral over space,
which gives you the delta function.
which says,
momentum conservation,
momentum conservation, momentum conservation.
It doesn't say that each,
that p1 should be equal to q1,
and p2 should equal q2.
It says the sum of all the incoming momentum
should be the same as the sum of all the outgoing momentum.
Okay, so that's momentum conservation.
In the Hamiltonian,
that's the product of all these field operators?
Yeah,
the product of all these field operators.
Why would you do that?
We'll come to why you might do that.
Not why you might,
but why you might.
So,
let's go back to
points of quantum field theory.
But before we do it,
let's take this term in the Hamiltonian over here.
This has the additional derivatives.
Let's go back and ask
what would happen
to this calculation,
the first, the original one here,
if we changed it
by
differentiating with
minus del squared
the psi dagger.
Before we multiply it with psi,
what does minus del squared,
this is just the second derivative,
what does it do when it hits here?
Well, to know,
we just go over to this side.
Let's differentiate this side twice with x.
What depends on x?
Well, dq doesn't depend on x,
2 pi doesn't depend on x,
in fact, psi dagger doesn't depend on x.
The only thing that depends on x
are these oscillating wave functions here.
So what happens
if you differentiate twice
the oscillation here?
q squared, plus q squared.
Minus iq times minus iq,
so this would give us
q squared.
In other words, the square of the momentum
of the particle
that you're creating here.
Isn't it minus?
No.
It's minus.
No, it's minus.
Look at the far left side of the equation,
there's a minus sign.
There's a minus here, and then a minus...
I didn't see that.
Right.
There's a minus here, that's why this
well, this minus is here because that's what goes in the Hamiltonian,
but, um, yeah.
Okay, so what's
the upshot?
It's the same kind of expression that we had before.
Again, you get to integrate
e to the i p minus qx.
It's again going to give you
um,
our momentum conservation.
But instead of just having integral
psi dagger of
so I'd take a twiddle of p
times psi
twiddle of p,
that just
counted the total number of particles
of each momentum and added them up.
There's another factor of
p squared.
It's this thing here,
which when you use the delta function
just gives you p squared.
What is this thing giving you?
First of all, it conserves momentum.
The momentum in and the momentum out
have to be the same, for exactly the same
reason, but it's just weighing
each particle with its, with the square
of its momentum. In other words,
it's counting the kinetic energy of each
particle. It's just adding up
all the particles, adding up the number
operator for each momentum,
and multiplying it by p squared. I suppose
where's the 2m? We left out the 2m.
p squared over 2m.
So it's doing exactly
what it's supposed to do. It's counting up the kinetic
energy of the particles, and
momentum is conserved
because of the
delta function.
Okay, let me show you an example of
an interesting term
that you could put into the Hamiltonian.
Let's suppose you had
two species of particles.
Let's call one
an electron and the other a proton.
Species.
Now, I'm cheating because
if I really wanted to do electrons and protons,
I wouldn't be doing boson operators.
Okay,
so these are fake electrons
and protons which happen to be
bosons.
Let's forget the mc squared term.
No, we're not going to work
with the mc squared term.
What's that?
In the conservation of
energy, kinetic energy.
It's only in the case when
Kinetic energy,
momentum or energy?
Kinetic energy.
That's only true in the case where
the potential energy is constant.
We haven't put any, exactly, yes so.
That is so.
That is a true statement.
What is the interpretation of the side dagger
in the Hamiltonian?
It counts.
Psi times psi dagger is a
counting operator.
In this case, it's counting the number of
particles with each momentum and multiplying
by p squared.
No, no, he just,
he didn't see the multiplication there.
Oh, okay, good.
Yeah. You know, there's another trick
you can do.
This thing looks negative, doesn't it?
But of course everybody knows the kinetic energy
of a particle is positive.
So what's going on?
Well, everybody
know how to integrate by parts
if you have
psi dagger
of x
and you have two derivatives
with a minus sign,
d by dx
times d by dx
times psi.
I'm not going
to work this out in detail. I'm going to tell you
the result.
The d by dx's both act
to the right.
They act on psi.
Integration by parts allows
you to take one of these derivatives
and shift it to the other side.
In fact, integration by parts
would allow you to take both of them
and shift them to the other side.
But I don't want to shift both of them. I just want to shift one of them.
But what do you have to do when you
integrate by parts in addition to taking
the derivative and shifting it to the other factor?
Change the sign.
You also have to worry about
edge effects, but
we won't worry
about that now.
So, you can rewrite this
as
d by dx
of psi dagger
times d by dx
of psi
and now this is just a square of something
and it's positive.
Integrated dx.
That's kind of interesting
to see in the Hamiltonian
the square of the derivative
of psi.
It's very much like
any other field theory
where
what you see in the Hamiltonian is
squares of derivatives of the fields.
In this case, squares of the space
derivatives of the fields.
And it's positive.
It's positive because
the derivative of psi dagger
times the derivative of psi
is positive.
Okay, let's take
another example of a possible
thing in the Hamiltonian
and discuss what it means.
Now, again, without
mathematical proofs because
we're just
belabor points
that were essentially already made,
but let's add in here
let's assume there are two kinds of particles first.
I'm not going to give them names.
I'm going to call them A and B.
You can call them proton and electron
if you like.
Then first of all, there's the energy of the electrons.
So this is the field operator
for electrons.
It creates and annihilates electrons.
It does nothing to protons.
This is the kinetic energy of all the electrons.
We have to add to that
the kinetic energy of all the protons.
So,
this is
this is twice m electron,
this is twice m proton,
and then
psi
proton of x.
Okay, so far all I
have is the
is the kinetic
energies. Now,
I'm going to add something. It's not the realistic
real interaction between electrons
and protons. This is just a model interaction.
And what I'm going to add
is plus the integral
over space, integral of the
x, times
the
creation
operator
of an electron at point x
times
the creation operator of a proton
at point x
times the annihilation
operator of an electron at point x.
of a proton
at the same point x.
And
yes.
Okay.
This comes along
and it annihilates a proton
and an electron if it finds them.
Where does it annihilate them?
It annihilates them at position x.
So if that happens,
it turns to be an electron and a proton.
And let's draw this the following way.
This is a space-time diagram.
Here's a space-time diagram. Here's time.
This is just a way to visualize.
This is not
to be taken too seriously
at the moment.
But an electron and a proton are moving around.
Here they are.
This is time. This is space.
These are
the world lines of the electrons and the proton.
The electron and the proton.
If they're not at the same
place,
then you can't, then this is not going to
give anything if it acts on the state.
This will act on a state and will only act
if it finds both a proton
and an electron at the same place.
It doesn't matter
what place, because you're integrating
over x, you'll get some kind of thing
no matter where x is
if there are two particles at the same place.
But if there are not two particles at the same
place, it just gives zero.
Okay, so first of all, it looks
for particles at the same place.
If it finds particles at the
same place,
it annihilates the proton,
it annihilates the electron,
but then it creates
a proton,
and it creates an electron
at the same point.
It scatters
the electron and the proton,
is what it does. Electron and proton
come in, and when they're at
the same point, and then they go out,
and it scatters them.
Is the momentum
conserved? Yes, the momentum is
conserved for exactly the reason we wrote
up there. But are the individual
momentums conserved? No.
The individual momentums are not
conserved. I should have gone through that
here. The individual momentums are not conserved.
The only conservation of
momentum is the overall conservation.
So when an operator
like this comes along
and hits the state of
an electron-proton system,
it scatters the electron-proton
system.
So it's a scattering operator. It's equivalent
to a potential energy between
the electron and proton
when they're at the same spot.
Of course, real electrons and protons
interact even if they're not at the same
spot to the Coulomb potential,
but we're just taking little steps
one at a time.
Okay, so
if
through experiment, you
discovered that there was an interaction
where electrons and protons
by a short range
of potential,
short range meaning it only acts when they're at the same
point, scatter each other,
this is what you would put into the Hamiltonian.
So it's a kind
of experimental, you know,
a bit of experimental physics to tell you
what kind of things
the particles can do, and once
you know what they can do, you mock it up
by expressions
like this. Let's do some more.
Let's see what else we could imagine having.
Another thing we could imagine
having...
Why is that part of the Hamiltonian?
The energy doesn't
change, right?
That's equivalent
to a potential energy in the Hamiltonian
between the electron and the proton.
Oh.
Any other questions?
But, you know,
what Hamiltonians do is change
states from one instant to the next.
If you discovered experimentally
that an electron
and a proton over a short period
of time will scatter each other
if they're at the same place,
you've got to say there must be something
in the Hamiltonian, the thing which updates
the state, which corresponds
to that scattering. And that's the kind of thing you would
write down.
So when you see in quantum field theory
expressions like
this, interactions involving
products of fields,
maybe products for
different fields, different kinds of
particles, they're representing
these basic simple interactions
where particles, if they're at the same point
can interact with each other.
Another example, supposing
experimentally you discovered
that particle
of type A
could decay
and form
particle of type B and particle
of type C. Again, this is time.
Read it
from bottom to top.
Particle A comes along
and you discover
that
there's a process where
particle A disappears at a point
and particle B and C
appear at the same point.
You discover in your
bubble chamber, you discover
tracks which lead you
to conclude that
A came in, B and C went out
and
they came out from the same
place that A came in. What would you write down?
Well, okay.
So,
you need something to
remove the A.
What happens over a short period of time
is an A disappears,
that's an annihilation operator,
and a B and a C are created.
So let's try that. What kind of thing might we write down?
We might write down the
annihilation operator
for A,
for field A,
at position X, that's the
annihilation operator, and then
two creation operators, one for B and one for C.
And you'd say, look, I've discovered experimentally
that the state of the system changes
in such a way that an A
disappears,
that's this, and a B and a C
are produced. Furthermore,
because every point of space
is like every other point of space,
you would
begin to suspect this could happen not only
at point X, but it could happen anywhere.
So, you integrate it
over X.
Weigh all points of space equally.
Once you do this,
you can read off
from what we talked about over here
that the momentum is conserved.
The momentum
of A becomes the momentum
of B and C. Now, energy conservation
is a little more complicated.
But energy is always
conserved, let's put it that way.
Okay, so
over the long
run, anyway.
Okay, so this is
what else would you put
into this Hamiltonian, or this term
in the Hamiltonian, besides these products of fields?
How about a number?
For example, in both
cases, incidentally, I should have said that
also in this case over here.
The possible number plus
G,
the coupling constant.
The coupling constant
is a number, which can be anything.
And it can
be extremely
small if the particles are very
weakly interacting. That would mean
that even if the particles arrive at the same
point, the probability
that they scatter is small.
And you would
experimentally verify this. You would
scatter two particles, and you would discover
most of the time they don't interact.
In that case, G is a small number.
If the particles have a
large interaction
probability, then G is a large
number. And G is called the
coupling constant.
Okay, we're on our
way to building quantum field theories.
Let me say one more thing
about
this term here.
What goes
in the Hamiltonian must be hermition.
That's a rule.
Hamiltonians are hermition, and
that's equal or equivalent to the
statement that the time evolution is
unitary. Time evolution
is unitary because it's got to
conserve probabilities.
Okay, so
is this hermition?
Well, it's not hermition.
It's not hermition.
And the reason it's not hermition
is because the hermition conjugates of
a psi dagger are a psi.
And the hermition conjugates of a
psi are a psi dagger.
To make it hermition, you must add
its hermition conjugate.
Its hermition conjugate
is the same operator,
except with everything
replaced by its conjugate.
And you also have to remember
when you hermition conjugate things, you've got to
change the order, but in this case it wouldn't
matter. But let's
do it anyway.
It doesn't matter in this case, because if they're
different fields, they commute with each other.
So let's, um, but we can do it.
We can do it.
Psi dagger A of X
times
psi
B of X
times psi C of X.
Now how is this different than this?
The answer is every creation
operator has been replaced by an annihilation
operator. Every annihilation operator
has been replaced by a creation operator.
And the process
described by the second half
here, let's look what it says,
it annihilates
a C and it annihilates a B
and creates an A.
So it's just the whole thing turned over.
B and C come in
and A go out.
So, once you discover
that there's a process
where A goes to B and C,
you can
immediately conclude that it must also
be the case that if you have a B and a C,
they can
turn into an A.
Okay?
What's that?
Is there any kind of exception to this?
Is there any exception to this?
No.
If there is,
we don't know about it.
Okay, so now we have the basic rules,
basic rules
of a simple version of
quantum field theory.
You have creation and annihilation
operators.
You have fields made out of them.
The fields are functions
of position and they can be thought of as creation
and annihilation operators for particles at
definite positions. Each
type of particle has its own field.
And you write down Hamiltonians.
The Hamiltonians always contain, or
typically contain,
typically contain the kinetic
energies of the particles.
That's the top thing there.
And then, in addition,
various other concoctions
which, um,
let's put it this way.
In the first round of particle physics,
those concoctions largely came
from experiment.
Well, electrodynamics,
of course, came from a little more
than just experiment.
But a classic example is
the theory of beta decay.
The theory of beta decay is
a neutron decaying
into a particle.
A proton, an electron,
and a neutrino.
Proton goes to electron,
and so forth.
So what would you write there?
Then you would have four operators.
This would be
annihilate a neutron,
create a proton,
create
an electron,
and create a neutrino.
Let's go one step further.
When I wrote that, um,
psi
of,
well,
phi of
t plus epsilon
is equal
to phi of t
minus i h bar
minus i
epsilon h
times phi of t.
This, of course, was an approximation.
It was an approximation
to leading first order in
small quantities, namely epsilon.
What would happen if I made
epsilon a little bit bigger?
Well, there would be a next term
which would be order epsilon squared.
You know what it would be?
It would be minus
epsilon squared
over two
times h squared
phi.
So,
this is
the order of
epsilon squared
over two
times h squared
over two times h squared.
This is just another way of saying
that if,
well, it's the Schrodinger equation.
The Schrodinger equation gives you
the derivative of psi proportional
to h times psi.
But it can also give you the second derivative of psi.
And that's proportional to h squared
times psi.
So this is what you would learn if you went to the next
order in small quantities
that
in the next order in small quantities
there's a change in the state
from one instant to another which is proportional
to h squared times psi.
That's very interesting
because, for example,
one of the things it would say
we could draw some
diagrams now.
What does h squared do?
Well, we could take h squared
and multiply it all out.
Okay, and we could try to see what it does.
But that's dumb.
The easy way to do it is
just to use the pictures.
Take the pictures
and let's erase this.
And the pictures say that
in lowest order
a thing which can happen
is b and c can come together
and make a.
That's just the Hamiltonian itself
or this term in the Hamiltonian.
But supposing the Hamiltonian
actually is a constant
and the Hamiltonian
is a constant
acted again on this.
Well, here's another term in the Hamiltonian.
The same term can act twice.
Oops, this is wrong. B and c.
But this term
can't really act twice
because for it to act twice
it has to find, the second time,
it has to find a b and a c again.
Well, in the first round here
the b and the c were eaten.
No b and c.
So this term can't act successively twice.
But what can happen is
when you square the Hamiltonian
this term times this term.
In other words,
let's write it out.
It's got
psi b
psi c
times
psi dagger a
and then
then psi a
psi b
psi c
A big mess.
That's the square of
a term or a piece of the square
of the term of the Hamiltonian.
But it's very easy to see what it says.
It says it takes a b and a c and it makes an a
and the, uh, yeah, it takes a b
and a c and turns it into an a
and then it takes the a
annihilates the a
and puts back a b and a c.
The effect of this
is to contribute or to create
a scattering between b and c.
The a
that's just temporary.
The b and the c came in
in the form of a
they annihilated the form a
and a then converted back to b and c
using the same Hamiltonian.
So it's not just that the Hamiltonian
updates the state.
All the powers of the Hamiltonian
give you a vast variety
of different processes that can happen
that contribute
to the amplitude for scattering.
This is the amplitude for scattering
b goes to c
and the only rule
at least the only rule we've set up till now
is that momentum is conserved.
Total momentum.
The momentum of c can change,
the momentum of b can change,
but going from beginning to end
the total momentum should be the same.
Okay.
Should that psi sub c on the left
should that have a dagger?
Possibly, yes.
Right, so you see
once you learn this little piece of information
you can do a lot of things.
Oh my goodness, all sorts of other things can happen.
Well, we now know
what did I just do?
I erased
a and b
goes to c.
Good.
Here's something else that can happen.
a can come in
create b and c
but now
if there happened to have been another
b around, let's suppose
there was another b around to begin with
yeah
this says
that if b finds a c
to annihilate with
then it can make an a.
So again, in the second order
of the Hamiltonian
where you iterate the Hamiltonian twice
you not only get processors
in which a goes to b and c
and b and c go to a
or that b and c go back to b and c
but now you have a scattering amplitude
where a and b scatter with each other
with the exchange
of a c. This is called an exchange
diagram. It looks as though
you're drawing a picture where a c
jumps over from here to here.
All it is is a contribution to the
scattering coming from the Hamiltonian
twice, acting twice.
So in following
the evolution of the system when the Hamiltonian
acts twice, the first
time it can take an a
and a b to c leaving this b
over here alone. This is a different b.
Leaving it alone
not doing anything. And then the second
power of the Hamiltonian can take
c and b and convert it back to a.
So you see, once you have
these simple terms
in the Hamiltonian, you have a vast
forest of many
many different kinds of interactions
that are mediated by
the same simple term
in the Hamiltonian. That's why
quantum field theory is powerful.
A small number of terms
in the Hamiltonian can lead to a huge
number of different reactions.
All related
by having the same form
in the Hamiltonian, the same coupling constant
for example
the coupling constant, yeah
if there's a coupling
constant governing a term in the Hamiltonian
here, then when you square the Hamiltonian
you might get the coupling
constant squared.
In fact you would here
each one of these vertices
these are called vertices, they carry
a coupling constant in the Hamiltonian.
So this
process would have a coupling constant
squared in front of it.
So this would correlate
an enormous amount of data
about all of the possible interactions
of a's, b's and c's.
There are many, of course
this is the most common thing in the world
in particle physics
is to be studying those correlations.
So if
I assume you can have a
decaying into b and c
and then b and c coming back together
form an a. But what is that?
Say it again now.
Oh, a going to b and c and then b and c
coming back together. That's a self energy
diagram for an a.
It changes the structure of a. What it tells
you is that a real a particle
that you might measure in the laboratory
spends, has a probability
to be not just an a
but to be a b and c
close to each other. So what it means
is that if you found an a in your
laboratory
and you scattered something
off it, with some probability
you would find that that a
behaved as if it were a b and a c
together, close together.
So for example
um
you know
electron, one such
process, one
example of this
would be an electron
emitting a photon.
Electron
comes in, electron goes out,
emits a photon.
Okay, so
the operator for that would be
side dagger
electron.
Sorry, side electron that
annihilates an electron.
Side dagger
create an electron
and then a photon creation operator.
Photons, the photon
field is called a.
All at the same point.
So it absorbs an electron, creates
an electron and emits a photon.
Okay, so one of the things that can
happen is, Kevin points
out, is you can have the
electron moving along
becoming an electron, emitting
a photon and then the photon
coming back and becoming an electron.
Now, don't take
too literally
the statement, this happens
and then that happens and then that happens.
This is really just standing for a term
second order in the Hamiltonian.
Iterating the Hamiltonian
twice. But it's clearly
very tempting to
to try to describe
this by saying sequence
of things happen. Now of course if you
go into the system and look and see
whether that something happened
you screw up the whole thing as usual
in quantum mechanics.
So, but what
this does tell you
is that if you scatter another
electron off the first electron
you will find some of
the time that this
electron contains a photon.
That what you thought was a single
electron really looks
like a composite of an
electron with a
with a photon.
The probability to find
a photon there is small.
It's about 1%. But
but that's what
it says. So
it really should be thought
of as a correction
to the structure of the electron
rather than a
than a new process.
It only becomes a new process
when you interfere with it and you look
and see what's inside and
some of the times you will find that what's inside
contains a photon.
Of course what will happen
if you look for the photon, you'll discover the photon
some of the times, you'll scatter
the photon out and you'll completely screw up
the electron. You'll excite
the electron and things will happen.
At that first vertex
are both energy and momentum concerned?
No, only
momentum. Only
momentum.
Right. And as I said
these things are not literally happening
they're shorthands
for the mathematics in this case of just
squaring the Hamiltonian.
So what actually happens is
superposition of all possible
things. And so that's why
the energy of any individual one
do not be conserved.
And there's all kinds of, don't forget, there's all
sorts of terms in the energy and counting
up all the energy, don't
forget to count up these interaction terms.
So the energy isn't just
the sum of the energy of the particles but that
sort of gets hidden in these pictures.
That
missing
energy that's in the interactions
you might say
allows the
pictures
to violate energy conservation
at each vertex.
But, you know, if you get confused
you just go back to where it came from. It came
from the Schrodinger equation going to the
second order in small quantities.
And that's what it means.
Now we're not going to do Feynman diagrams
in their full blown glory, but
this is where they come from
and this is where
the
the rest is just
technology and
tricks to calculate
things with. But this is the
basic physics of it. Yeah.
I was just
thinking about the electric
field of the electron there.
Well, good.
This is the electric field of the electron.
Well, that's what I was going to ask about.
No.
Because it seems to me that at least
in a
literal sense, I mean it
seems like
the field, the presence
of the field at some distance
isn't
literally created
by radiation.
Say that again.
It's
not,
you could say it's the propagation of the
field ahead of the electron
obeys
the same weight equation
as radiation would, but
it's not literally the radiation.
No, it's not literally the radiation,
although if you take a very high
energy electron,
1% of the time
it behaves as if it
were a real electron and a
real photon. That's because
photons move at the speed of light.
These photons are clearly
not going to move at the speed of light. It's got to go
from here to here and the electron is not
moving with the speed of light.
So, literally thinking of these
as photons moving around is not going to work.
But if the electron itself is
moving with the speed of light,
or close to it, very close to it,
then it really does behave as
though it were a
superposition of an electron
and then an electron with a real
photon, with a genuine photon.
I'm actually thinking of things where the electrons are
moving rather slowly, and the field
is moving very quickly
as a wave ahead of it.
And then...
Now, then you're going to get yourself completely confused
trying to form a model for what's going on.
Well, I'm just saying it's not literally
creating real photons
to fill the field.
Right.
Don't try
to create a
mechanical model of what's going on.
It won't work.
No, no, but there's
effects like self-interference
in the two-slit experiment,
self-interference of a single
photon.
Okay?
You have to have
sort of the wave
of the wave
version of the photon
I mean, you know,
the...
meets up with
its own field.
Right? Coming through...
It has nothing to do with this, though.
Well, it's...
It was related to my question.
And you have the...
Haranoff-Bohm
experiment, so that
you know, the field is
present where
you know, it's not really radiation.
Yeah, no, this is
not the radiation field. This is the induction field.
Right, but as I tell you,
when the electron is fast, it can be thought of as
a radiation field.
Can you finish your thought? You were starting to say about...
Lost it. It's gone. It's finished.
You were starting to say that if
you try to create a model of this,
it will fail. Well,
you try to create...
You know, your brain is always trying to
create classical models, classical pictures
for things.
You
can get some experience doing some
calculations, and after a while you know
how to deal with these diagrams,
and you start to give some
literalness
to the diagrams,
which really is not really
right. It's
just a mathematical trick to calculate
h squared, h cubed. They
basically were calculating e to the i ht
by expanding it out
in powers of h.
Right?
e to the i ht
is the time development,
and that's what we're expanding out here.
1 minus i epsilon h
minus epsilon square over 2.
This 2 is the 2 of
the exponential
expansion. What's the next term?
I guess it's plus i epsilon h
1 cubed h cubed
over 3 factorial.
Right.
Now,
how do you actually calculate
the probability of a given scattering?
That, of course, requires
some
technology
which we haven't done.
But,
okay.
So somehow, and I
imagine we're not going to be seeing it tonight or next
week, this mechanism
if you
do the right
mathematics with this
mechanism, and you have an electron here
and an electron here,
you can somehow
show the Coulomb attraction
as a classical limit of this
process.
Yes. But the way you would do it, the simplest way to do it,
well, yes, the answer is yes.
But it's not literally that a photon
jumps from one place to another.
No.
That's a little bit too simplistic. Yeah?
Are the coupling constants calculated
because these poles are in there?
No. Sometimes
Sometimes relationships between
coupling constants can be calculated
from symmetry principles.
But,
generally the coupling
constants are basically experimental
input.
So,
disappointing, isn't it?
Yeah?
On the other hand,
think about what happens
when there is a relation
between coupling constants that's
dictated by the mathematics, some symmetry
principle. Then
it relates to otherwise
independent and
different reactions.
When that happens and you go in the laboratory
and you discover that the reactions
behave according to the way the coupling
constants, which have been determined from
first principles, tell you they're supposed to behave,
that's exhilarating.
It doesn't happen very often.
But it happens. It does happen.
The difference between an accidental
symmetry...
Yeah.
Accidental symmetries are accidents
and they usually don't tell you very much.
Gauge symmetries are
the symmetries which tell you something.
Okay.
Well, I take
back what I said. Accidental symmetries also tell
you things.
Important things.
We're going to...
I had promised to start fermions today
and I'm going to.
But instead of talking about
fermion fields, which we'll come to
next time, let's talk about the Dirac
equation. Let's start the Dirac
equation today.
From one point of view, the Dirac equation...
First of all, that means we're
entering into relativity theory.
We're using relativity theory.
Thus far,
what we did was
to study non-relativistic
second quantization.
Now we want to
move on
a little bit and study the
relativistic electron.
We're going to study...we're going to begin with
a one-dimensional electron. An electron
is only moving in one direction dimension.
The simplest possible
theory of an electron.
It's not a realistic theory. Electrons
move in three dimensions.
But it's the easiest
place to get started. Without having
to throw a bunch of formulas and a
bunch of symbols, we can study
the one-dimensional electron
and learn quite a lot.
Without getting
spurious complexity
because of the three-dimensionality of space.
Then we come back to three dimensions.
Three plus one, three dimensions.
Right. Okay.
So...
The electron ought to have a Schrodinger equation.
Particles should
have Schrodinger equations.
On the other hand, it shouldn't be...
If we're dealing with relativity...
Incidentally, the reason why
we deal with relativity when we deal with
electrons is because electrons are pretty light.
They move around in...
They move around in...of course,
in an accelerator we can get them up to
the speed of light. But I'm
thinking now back to the age of Dirac.
Why would Dirac have bothered
using a relativistic theory
other than curiosity, perhaps, about
how relativistic electrons work?
And the answer is that
in an atom, and particularly
in a hydrogen atom,
the electron moves
with an appreciable fraction of the speed
of light, about one percent of the speed of light.
So relativity is
an important correction for the motion of
electron. If you take
heavy atoms, where
the inner electrons are closer
to the nucleus, they are really moving
and they can be pretty close to...
They're not moving with the speed of light, but they
can be moving with even more appreciable
velocities.
So if you want to get
atoms right,
not just, you know, to
zeroth order, you want to get the corrections to
atoms right, important corrections
are relativistic.
So,
now whether Dirac was motivated
by that fact, or he was just motivated
by
curiosity about how to make relativistic
Schrodinger equations, I don't know.
Okay,
we begin
in formulating the idea
of a Schrodinger
equation for a particle,
we begin pretty much with a
classical relationship
between energy and momentum.
We start
with energy as a function of momentum
and then we
go from quantum mechanics to
classical mechanics,
because that's the logic.
But what we tend to know about
is classical physics, and so
we usually go in the other direction.
And for an ordinary
non-relativistic particle,
the energy, which I'll call a Hamiltonian,
let's call it E, let's call it E,
but remember it is the Hamiltonian,
it's
E equals
E squared over 2m.
That's the energy as a function
of momentum, and then to go to
quantum mechanics, we replace energy
by Hamiltonian,
which we then
replace by
I d by dt.
In other words, the Hamiltonian
is the thing which gives you the time derivative
of the wave function, that's on the
left side, and on the right side
we replace p
by minus I
d by dx.
And that gives us the Schrodinger equation.
d psi by dt
or I d psi by dt
is minus d squared over
2m, second derivative,
you know the story.
Schrodinger equation.
Okay, so Dirac said, why don't I do the same thing?
What's the energy as a
function of momentum?
It's ugly.
Square root of p squared
plus m squared. Let's write down, because we'll
need it later, the relation between
energy and momentum.
E squared
equals p squared
plus m squared. Now I've set the
speed of light equal to 1, and I will do so
continuously throughout.
Speed of light is equal to 1.
E squared is equal to p squared
plus m squared. From this,
you can write down immediately
an equation. If you
take e to be
I d by dt, then what is
e squared?
It's the second derivative
with respect to t. Minus the second
derivative with respect to t. So
you would write down
minus second
derivative with respect to t squared,
that's e,
on some phi
of x, or psi of x, some
wave function,
equals
p squared, that's minus
d by dx squared,
psi,
plus m squared psi,
or phi,
whatever, phi, psi, I don't know.
Doesn't matter, whatever we call it.
The wave function of the electron.
Or the wave function of something.
Anybody know what the name of this equation
is?
I seem to have a...
Yeah, that's right.
That's right.
That's the Klein-Gordon equation.
And you might say,
Dirac, why didn't he do this?
I don't know why
he didn't do this. He had an argument.
His argument was, look, we're supposed
to write, according to
my principles of quantum mechanics,
which are in my textbook,
we're supposed to write
i d by dt
is equal to h times psi
We're not supposed to have to square
the second derivative.
I don't want to know what the
h squared is,
I want to know what h is.
That's what I wrote in my book, and I'm going to
stick by it.
So he wants an equation
that reads
i
d, let's call it psi,
now it's not a field operator,
it's just a wave function for an electron,
by dt
is equal to some
operator on psi.
What kind of an operator?
Well, it's got to have the momentum,
it's got to have the mass.
He could just put here the square root of
p squared plus m squared,
and then write,
the following strange equation,
is equal to
square root
of p squared,
which is minus d by dx
squared
plus m squared
psi.
What on earth does that mean?
What does the square root of
d by dx squared plus m squared mean?
It doesn't mean very much.
Well,
you can give it some technical meaning,
but it's pretty horrible.
It's not a nice,
the square root of a differential operator
like this is not a nice thing.
So I think that Dirac
just backed away from it
and said,
I don't like that.
I don't have a convincing case against it,
but I'm going to start over again.
I'm going to start from the beginning.
Here's what he said.
We'll do it in the one-dimensional case,
and then we'll come back to...
Let's start
the one-dimensional case
with a
massless particle,
a particle with no mass.
An electron that doesn't have a mass.
We'll put the mass back in,
and we'll see how that works.
So,
here's what you know about a particle
moving along the x-axis
with the speed of light.
It's massless, so it moves with the speed of light.
Its momentum
is equal
to its energy.
Strictly speaking, if I put the speed
of light back, it would go over here.
Energy is equal to c
times the momentum.
This is true for a photon.
It's true for any massless particle.
This is a massless particle
moving to the right. What about a massless particle
moving to the left, incidentally?
Yeah, p would be negative in that case.
p would be positive if the particle
moves to the right.
If the particle moves to the left, then p is negative,
but clearly the energy should still be positive,
so we would have to write
p equals minus c.
Well, we only get to write one thing. We don't get to write
both.
So let's start with p equals e
and content ourselves
with studying a particle moving to the right.
So we know what this says.
We've actually studied this equation.
This equation, if we now say that
e is equal to the Hamiltonian
and Hamiltonian is
i d by dt,
it says
i d psi by dt
that's h psi
is equal to
the momentum of the massless particle.
So that's equal to
p times psi, and that's minus i
d psi by dx.
That's a pretty simple equation.
What does it say? It says
d psi by dt
plus d psi by dx
equals zero.
What kind of, what are the solutions of such an equation?
No?
They're functions of x minus t.
Any function
of x minus t
will satisfy this equation.
A function of x minus t
is a wave which is moving
along the axis to the right
with
the speed of light. Speed of light now
being chosen to be equal to one.
Any function
of x minus t
psi is a
function of x minus t
that means it describes a wave
moving to the right
of rigid
profile. Profile
doesn't change, but the location
of the center of the wave changes, and it
moves with the speed of light.
Okay, this is a fine equation.
Very nice.
Two things wrong with it.
Two things, and they're unrelated
things. They're unrelated. They're not the
same thing. The first thing
that's wrong with it is it's got negative energy.
What if the momentum is negative?
We're allowed to have negative momentum.
Momentum is a
observable which can be positive or negative.
It's negative
if it's
pointing along the minus x axis.
It's positive if it's along the plus x axis.
It's got
particles of negative energy with
negative momentum.
This sounds very
dangerous. It sounds
like we can
take those, we can just
keep filling up the world
with more and more negative
energy particles, lowering the
energy, lowering it, lowering it
without bound from below.
That's a pretty dangerous
situation. We don't want that.
So first
problem with this is it contains
particles of negative energy.
We've got to fix that.
The second problem
with it is it only has particles
which move to the right.
Okay.
Well, we could imagine
a theory of particles that only
move to the right, but it wouldn't look like
certainly wouldn't look like
garden variety electrons.
We don't know any particles that only move along
one direction.
If it can move to the right,
it can also move to the left.
So
that's another thing we can try to fix.
Okay, so here's what Dirac
said.
He said
in effect,
in effect, it's not exactly what he said, but
in effect he said, let's
take two species
this is to
get rid of the left-right story, not
the energy story, to get rid of
the left-right story. He said let's take
two species. Let's call it
psi 1 and psi 2.
Two species
of electrons, one of which
we'll think of as the species of electrons
which move to the right, and the other we'll think of
as the species of electrons which go to the left.
And let's just write down
two separate equations.
Let's call them
and think of two separate kinds
of particles.
Or
we can say a particle can be
one kind or the other.
If we have only one
particle, it could be the right kind
or the left kind. And so
let's put a psi 1
here. This is the equation
for particles which move to the right.
And what about the equation
for particles to move to the left, which we'll
call psi 2. That's the
equation
psi 2
by dt
minus
d psi 2 by dx
is equal
to zero.
Now, in quantum
mechanics, of course, if you
can have a particle of type 1
and a particle of type 2, you can have
a linear superposition of them.
So you can have particles
which have a probability
of half, for example, of moving to the left
and half moving to the right.
But these are the
wave
functions of the two kinds of particles.
So Dirac-Nicks said,
look, it looks to me like
what we're talking about is a particle
with a degree of freedom,
an extra degree
of freedom, not just
x,
not just the coordinate position
or equivalently the momentum,
you can trade one for the other, but
it looks like it has a discrete thing,
a plus oneness
or a minus oneness,
sort of like a spin.
It's not a spin, but sort of
like a spin. It can either
be up or it can be down.
Up in this case means traveling
to the right, down means traveling
to the left. So
he understood a little bit about matrices
and so forth, and he
said, look, let's write this in
matrix form. Let's
introduce observables
which tell you whether
you're 1 or 2,
and that means that
what we want to do is take our size
and think of them as a column vector.
Psi 1 and psi 2,
put them together
like so.
This is the amplitude that the particle
is right moving,
this is the amplitude that the particle is left
moving, and
let's introduce matrices.
In particular, let's introduce
a matrix
whose eigenvectors
are 1 or 2.
In other words,
1 or 2.
Here's a matrix
which
the eigenvectors
are
1 with eigenvalue 1
and
minus 1 with eigenvalue 2.
So here is an observable
which distinguishes
the two kinds of particles.
Either up,
well it's not up or down, but it's moving
to the right or it's moving to the left,
and we'll just give this matrix a name.
Now,
if it was spin,
and it's the observable,
it is the observable, the matrix observable
or the operator, the linear operator,
which distinguishes between
the two kinds of particles.
It's very much like a spin
being up or a spin being down, except that it's not spin.
Okay,
this matrix has a name.
Anybody know what its name is?
I forget. No, I don't.
Sigma 1?
It is sigma 3.
It's a Pauli matrix,
but it's a Pauli matrix in the context
where we're thinking about spin,
and spin has to do with angular momentum.
It's just not that here.
Alright? It's just a different thing.
Dirac
called it alpha.
He called it alpha,
so let's call it alpha.
It's exactly that matrix.
And then he wrote,
I'm saying he did this,
he actually didn't do this.
He plunged right in and did it in three dimensions.
But, uh,
I don't know,
for all I know, maybe he did do this, but, uh...
It might make a certain,
a different kind of sense in
three dimensions.
When you have the direction,
vector type direction.
Yeah, right, it does.
But if he were doing it in one dimension,
which is the easy baby way to get started,
and it's not so baby, it's correct,
you would write that
H instead of the Hamiltonian,
instead of, E is the Hamiltonian,
but now we're
thinking of it as a Hamiltonian, not just a number,
the Hamiltonian
is
P if the particle is moving
to the right, and minus
P if the particle,
the two kinds of particles,
when moved to the right, they'll go.
So it's P if it's a right mover,
and minus P if it's a left mover,
but the right movers and the left movers
are distinguished by alpha.
So we can summarize it
by just writing H equals
alpha P.
If alpha is plus one,
it's a right mover,
if alpha is minus one, it's a left mover.
So it puts together
into a single structure
a
particle with a degree of freedom
which is its position, and another
degree of freedom which is its alpha.
Puts it together,
and says H is equal to alpha P.
This now becomes
an equation, you can write it in a number
of ways. Here is one way of
writing it.
But we can also write it
as I
d by dt
of
psi one, psi two,
a two component
column vector,
is equal
to alpha,
which is the matrix one minus
one, O O,
times
minus I
d psi by dx.
Let's put the minus I
over here.
Or?
Hmm?
Yeah, I'm sorry.
d by dx,
good. d by dx,
of
psi one, psi two. Or we can just condense it. We don't need all of this stuff. We can just write I d psi by dt is equal to minus I alpha d psi by dx. But remember that psi is this two component column vector. They all are the same thing.
Keep in mind that
and
since alpha has both positive and negative eigenvalue,
this describes both right moving and left moving waves.
Okay, so by the trick of introducing
the Dirac matrix alpha
and a two component structure
for the wave function,
we now have cured the problem
of the one way street.
It's now a two way street.
And electrons,
an electron can go either to the left or the right.
I said there were two things wrong.
The first I said was the negative energy.
We still have that.
The second was the one wayness.
I forgot a third one.
So far the electron has no mass.
This is something moving with the speed of light.
Okay?
This is not what we want.
We want an electron which moves with less than the speed of light.
In other words, we want an electron with a mass.
Okay?
I think I could have done this.
It took the genius of Dirac
to make the next step.
He said,
here's what he said,
well, let's
He said, let's just add a term to the Hamiltonian
and see if we can get it to come out to be a mass.
I'm going to add something here
that ought to be proportional to the mass.
m of course means mc squared, strictly.
It's the energy of a particle at rest
when it has no momentum.
So we want something to account
for the energy of a particle
when it has no momentum.
But since all of these equations
now are acting on these two
component columns,
in general, this thing has
to be a matrix.
It's got to be something which can act.
It could be the unit matrix for all I know.
But let's not prejudice it.
Let's add something here proportional to the mass.
And let's introduce
another matrix
and let's call it beta.
Okay.
Now here I have a feeling
I probably would not have caught this.
Dirac did.
And moreover
caught it in three dimensions
which is a little bit harder
but not much.
Okay.
So this is some operator.
It's a genuine operator.
P is the momentum operator.
Alpha is the alpha operator.
Beta is some operator
which has only to do
with the
two componentness.
Doesn't have to do with x.
It doesn't have to do with p.
It just acts on the two component spinners.
We'll call them spinners for what they are.
And here's what he said.
He said, look, here's what I know.
I know that in a relativistic theory
the energy squared
which is the Hamiltonian squared
should equal p squared plus m squared.
Let's insist on this.
Let's insist that when I square this
when I square h
that I get p squared plus m squared.
So let's see what that says.
Alright, so that says
h squared which is e squared
should equal
alpha p plus beta m
times
alpha p
plus beta m.
Okay, first of all
I'm going to get a p squared term.
It's going to be alpha squared
or incidentally alpha commutes with p.
It acts in a different tensor product space.
We don't have to worry about
commutation between alphas and p's.
Okay, the first term is
alpha squared p squared.
That looks good.
We want to get p squared.
We got alpha squared p squared.
It's easy to deal with.
Let's just insist that alpha squared be one.
But wait a minute.
We already know what alpha is.
It's square is one.
So we're in good shape
with a p squared term.
That's good.
If we use the fact that we know
what alpha is
then this is just p squared.
How about the
m squared term?
There's another term which is beta squared m squared.
Well I don't know what beta is yet.
I haven't decided what beta is yet.
But what do I know?
I know that p squared should be one.
So let's write down what we know.
Alpha squared equals one.
That's good.
We have that already.
Beta squared equals one.
There's lots of matrices around
whose square is equal to one.
So not to worry.
Any one of the Pauli matrices
whose square is equal to one.
One means the identity matrix.
Yes. Any of the Pauli matrices
whose square is equal to one.
The identity matrix itself
is taken care of that.
But now this is p squared plus m squared.
But then we have
an extra term.
And the extra term is alpha beta
It's a product of p with m.
And it's got
one term which has alpha beta
and another term which has beta alpha.
So it has alpha beta
plus beta alpha
times pn.
We don't want that term.
That term is
something we don't want.
Hmm?
So they should anti-commute.
So we want that alpha beta
plus beta alpha
is equal to zero.
And once we do that
then we have our cake and eat it.
We first of all have an equation
of this very simple kind
that Dirac liked so much.
Namely, where is it?
H on psi equals d psi i d c.
For one thing.
And we also have
that e squared equals p squared plus m squared.
All we have to do is find a matrix
which anti-commutes.
That means when you change the order
the sign changes.
Which anti-commutes with alpha.
Now, I
Pauli
had already invented his matrices
and Dirac
had he done things this way
would have instantly recognized
that the matrix would be
one of the Pauli matrices
and he also would have known
that any pair of the Pauli matrices
anti-commute.
So he could simply take for beta
any other of the Pauli matrices
In practice he took those equations
that you wrote down
and just said well
he already knows the Pauli matrices
do that.
Yeah.
He did have Pauli
to back him up on this.
He had done lots of work with these.
He just used unknowns here.
He just used unknowns.
He did.
But then he said let's find some matrices
which do this.
Alright, so in this case
we have a choice about beta
but let's
resolve that ambiguity.
It's not a real genuine
ambiguity.
It's a convention.
So we have a second matrix beta.
This is alpha and this is beta.
Namely 0, 1, 1, 0.
You can go home and check
that alpha times beta
is minus beta times alpha.
I'm not going to do it on the blackboard.
It's a straightforward thing.
They do anti-commute and so Dirac
now had his
his
equation and let's see what it says.
Let's see what kind of equation he had.
It's not Einstein's beta, right?
What's that?
It's not what?
The relativistic beta.
No, no, it's a matrix. It's Pauli matrix.
No, no, it's definitely not that.
We just don't have enough letters.
Yeah. I'm following Dirac's notation.
So the two matrices of beta are called Dirac matrices.
In this case, they're 2x2 matrices.
We'll find out
probably next week that you can't
do it with 2x2 matrices in three dimensions
but we'll do something else.
Okay, so let's see what this says.
This says,
where was our equation?
It says I d psi dt
where psi is a two component
spinner
is equal to
alpha p
times psi
plus beta m
where m is the mass.
Okay, let's write it out.
As a two component equation,
this is I
and in the first slot here
we would write d psi by dt
Well, let's write it
I d by dt
psi 1
psi 2
And this
seems to be
this stands for a column
made out of I d psi 1 dt
and I d psi 2 by dt
Then we have alpha
and alpha is
1 minus 1
0, 0
times p
but p is minus
I d by dx
So we have a minus I
equals minus I
d by dx
of psi 1
and psi 2
Now so far
we're just rewriting the two equations here
We're just rewriting these two equations
Separate equations for psi 1 and psi 2
And the reason they're separate
is because this matrix is diagonal
It does not mix
psi 1 with psi 2
But then we have beta
And so let's add
plus beta
and beta is
1, 1, 0, 0
We have to multiply it by m
So let's put the m right in here
m right in here
psi 1, psi 2
If we write out this term
we'll find that the upper
because the psi 1 is off diagonal
sorry
because the beta is off diagonal
What does this do?
It switches psi 1 and psi 2
So we have beta
and beta
switches psi 1 and psi 2
So this term
this term here just becomes
m
psi 2, psi 1
So let's come back to this equation
over here
What it does
I'll never get the I in the right place
So let's put the I in the right place
I, I, I
minus I
equals
m psi 2
and the other one is m psi 1
So you see, once you introduce
the mass term
the two components are not independent anymore
they interact with each other
The equation couples
one to the other
And what does
that coupling do?
It gives the particle a mass
and if you work out how it moves
it moves slower than the speed of light
It moves as if it were a particle
with e squared equals
p squared plus m squared
In other words, a relativistic particle of finite mass
This is what Dirac
did
to get rid of the left-right
nonsense
and at the same time
to get a mass
Now I suspect he knew something else
that the mass
was connected with the left-rightness
If you have
a particle which is massless
it's consistent
it can only go along the right
along
in one dimension
go in one direction
The reason is because
any Lawrence transformation
of a particle moving to the right
Is still a particle moving to the right
If it is moving with the speed of light
gehen
So, particles which move with the speed of light
Steven P with the speed of light
right ones don't talk to each other through Lorentz transformations.
If a particle has a mass, you can bring it to rest.
Or you can, yeah, you can maybe not bring it to rest, but you can bring it to some finite
momentum along the x, a finite velocity along the x-axis.
So it's moving with half the speed of light this way.
And then you get on your horse and run with three quarters of the speed of light.
It is now moving in the opposite direction.
So it's just not possible to have a massive particle which only moves to the right.
So Dirac knew, again, I imagine he knew, that the left-rightness was coupled together with
the mass issue, and that by fixing the left-right issue, he could potentially create a mass
for the electron.
Yeah?
Is this in some sense a chiral oscillation?
What's that?
Is this in some sense related to chiral oscillation?
Yeah.
Is this a chiral oscillation?
The left-rightness is called the chirality in this case.
It means handedness.
In this case.
In this case, the…
Two, swapping of two and one is what I'm thinking.
Yeah.
No, in this case, no, in this case, the handedness is just the alpha matrix over here.
It's not a swap, but it's the mass term which is the swap.
Yeah, I was just talking about the whole, the full equation.
Is there, is there a chiral oscillation built in?
Yeah.
Is there a chiral oscillation built into that?
The mass term is the chiral oscillation.
Yeah.
Oh absolutely.
Yeah, mm-hm.
Why should a fermion equation come from the square root of a boson equation?
No, no, no, no.
This has nothing to do with fermions or bosons.
E squared equals P squared plus M squared for any part, for any relativistic system.
Yeah, as long as it's not massless.
Yeah.
E squared is equal to P squared plus M squared.
That has nothing particular to do with whether it's a, every particle satisfies that.
Right.
So it's true, you can sort of think of the Dirac equation as a kind of square root of
the Klein-Gordon equation, but I don't think that's particularly helpful.
All right.
So the last thing we have to do is get straight.
D minus M.
D plus M.
Yeah.
Well, we'll first wave of the linear reaction into certain factorization which is sort of
left movers, right movers.
Uh-huh.
No.
Right, so we have two things to do with the Dirac equation.
One is to understand how to get rid of the negative energies.
This has not gotten rid of the negative energies.
Now we have negative energy right movers and negative energy left movers.
We made it worse.
And the other is to get the three-dimensional space.
But that's easy.
Yeah.
You just pointed back and you said that Dirac is the big one, not the right side side space.
you said the Dirac equation, does this pair of equations constitute the Dirac equation?
for the one-dimensional case, yeah
yeah this is a really long version of the Dirac equation
the usual equation
no, the Dirac equation would be written this way
i d psi by dt is equal to minus, sorry, is equal to, yeah, minus i alpha d psi by dx plus beta m psi
that would be the Dirac equation written in one form
you can also write it another way which is also these days more familiar
you multiply both sides of the equation by beta
and you write i, ah, let's come to it next time, it's enough for tonight, it's enough for tonight
there's a more symmetric way to write it
which is pretty and the standard way to write it but it doesn't add anything at this point
good, okay, we're finished
for more please visit us at stanford.edu