Stanford University.
Most of the basic ideas that we're going
to talk about this quarter originated out of
questions having to do with renormalization.
Puzzles and sometimes puzzles, sometimes
useful observations about the renormalization of
the standard model.
So I thought it would be a good idea to
spend a little bit of time explaining to you, we've
done this before.
We've done this a couple of times.
But still, to describe what renormalization
is, it's a combination of two things.
It's a combination of learning how to eliminate
out of the description of physics things having
to do with distances which are so small
that they're irrelevant to the questions that you're
asking.
And the other half of it is very simple.
It's dimensional analysis.
In fact, it's learning to think about
how dimensional analysis tells you the answer
to some of the very difficult problems of
quantum field theory that have to do with
distances much, much smaller than
you might be interested in.
Here's some simple examples.
I'm going to show you a few examples.
I'm going to show you a few examples of
renormalization, namely getting rid of things which are too
small to be interesting to you.
If you're interested in the nucleus and how
the nucleus works, you may begin with quarks.
Quarks are the fundamental
underlying constituents of the nucleus.
But for many, many purposes, the nucleus
is really a collection of protons and neutrons.
And it doesn't matter very much what
those protons and neutrons are made out of.
So a simple step is to solve the
theory of quantum chromodynamics to discover and to
compute the properties of the protons and neutrons.
But then once you're finished with that,
in computing the properties of the protons and
neutrons, you might mean their mass, you might
mean their spin, a few other properties, but
also the forces between them.
Also the forces between them.
In a nucleus, the protons and neutrons move pretty slowly.
So there's no real need or
no strong need for relativity theory.
Basically the nucleus is, roughly
speaking, described by the non-relativistic quantum
mechanics of protons and neutrons.
And all you really need from the quark theory
is to find out what the properties of protons
and neutrons are.
Masses.
Spins.
And the forces between them.
Once you've got that, you can forget where
it came from and say protons, neutrons, and
some simple forces between them.
But then if you're interested in atoms, you
may not be terribly interested in what makes
up the nucleus.
You use nuclear physics to calculate the
properties of nuclei, which nuclei exist, which nuclei
are...
I don't know.
I don't know what they're...
In fact, if you're interested in atomic physics,
you're not even very interested in the mass
of the nucleus.
But still, you might want to know the mass
of a given nucleus, a few of its properties,
not much.
Basically just its mass and its charge.
Once you have the mass and the charge
of the nucleus, you can forget completely where it
came from.
You can forget protons and neutrons.
And you can say there are nuclei.
There are 92 of them.
Well, more than 92.
Of course, there are isotopes.
But you can start over again and
say the elementary particles for today's thoughts...
Not today's, but I mean if you were
doing nuclear physics, if you're doing atomic physics,
you say we start over again with
a new set of the elementary particles.
We forget quarks.
We forget protons and neutrons.
And we start with nuclei.
92 of them, or however many of
them there are, plus, of course, electrons.
Electrons are pretty small.
But we can't get rid of the electrons
and still be able to do atomic physics.
So we're going to start over
again and say the elementary particles.
We forget quarks.
We forget neutrons and neutrons.
We forget protons and neutrons.
We forget electrons.
Because we don't know how to do atomic physics.
So we calculate the properties of atoms.
Atoms mean nuclei plus electrons.
We calculate their properties, and once we
have their properties we can say, all right,
here's the collection of atoms that exist in nature.
There's cookie atoms and coffee atoms
and chocolate atoms, ketchup atoms, all those
various kinds of atoms.
And once you have them, you don't
need to ask where they came from anymore.
Well, you might want to know a little bit
more than that, because if you have to calculate,
we're going to talk a little bit about
the properties of, we're not going to talk about
the properties of molecules tonight, but we're going
to talk about how you think about molecules,
how you go from atoms to molecules.
But in going from atoms and
molecules, it's the same kind of deal.
You figure out how atoms build themselves
into molecules, and once you have molecules,
you can more or less forget where they
came from, and start putting them together in tinker
toy assemblies, and build up anything from there.
So at each stage, you eliminated the things
which were smaller than you were really interested
in, and the result was a more
coarse-grained description, perhaps not as exact a description,
but a far more useful description for your purposes.
Well, the same thing is true in quantum mechanics.
Quantum field theory, where you have things
at all possible scales, every possible wavelength
constitutes a degree of freedom, waves
of arbitrary wavelength, arbitrarily small wavelengths.
But in describing physics at one length scale,
you don't really want to have to deal with
all the things at very, very small
length scales which are uninteresting to you, so
you invent a way.
You invent a way of summing up all
of the effects of very small distances and replacing
it by effective new parameters in your description.
That's all that renormalization really is.
That, together with some dimensional analysis.
Let me give you an example of renormalization.
Again, it's just this example of going
from atoms to molecules, or from going from...
from nuclei plus electrons to atoms, and how
you deal with atomic forces and so forth.
Where atomic forces come from, how they
come out of electrons, protons, not protons and
neutrons, but nuclei and electrons.
This is a classic example.
It's not usually thought of
as renormalization, but it is renormalization.
Where getting rid of the very small degrees
of freedom and also the very fast degrees
of freedom.
Small usually goes with fast.
The smaller a system is,
typically the faster its motion is.
So you're getting rid of not only
small things, but also very rapid things.
That's the goal of renormalization.
So let's start with something we
know very well, the theory of atoms.
The theory of atoms is very simple.
It's just a nucleus.
It's just a nucleus and a bunch of electrons.
And what I'm actually interested
in is a pair of atoms.
It could be a pair of hydrogen atoms,
but that could be more complicated than a pair
of hydrogen atoms.
Just some pair of atoms.
And what I'm interested in is describing the
dynamics of this pair of atoms in a simpler
way than the complex structure of electrons.
Electrons, a cloud of electrons, and
all that very, very complicated stuff.
What I'd like to describe
them by is simply two particles.
Two particles that I call atoms with forces between them.
How do you understand those forces?
Now, the advantage that you have here, which
is an advantage, is that the electron motions
are very, very fast by comparison
with the motions of the nuclei.
Nuclei are heavy.
Nuclei are a thousand times or two
thousand times the lightest nucleus, the hydrogen nucleus,
is two thousand times heavier than an electron.
And bigger nuclei are even more massive.
So you can almost think of the atom as
a heavy bowling ball with a bunch of little flies
surrounding it, and the flies moving very,
very much faster than the bowling ball is
going to move.
Because a given force is just not going to move.
Right?
It's not going to accelerate the bowling ball very much.
So you can make an approximation.
And in your first approximation, you say
that the bowling ball nuclei are so heavy
that they don't move at all.
What I want to calculate is the
effective potential, the potential energy between two
nuclei, or between two atoms, in a
way that gets rid of the electrons.
In fact, which gets rid of
separately the electrons and the molecules.
So what do you do?
You start, this is a quantum mechanical
problem, and as any quantum mechanical problem, you
start with a Hamiltonian.
The Hamiltonian is just another expression
for the quantum mechanical version of energy.
So let me write down for you what Hamiltonian
I would write down if I really wanted to do
this problem.
I would say, first of all, I'm not
interested in corrections coming from the special theory
of relativity.
From relativity theory.
That's not interesting for molecules.
So, you begin with non-relativistic quantum mechanics.
And that means the energy, first of all,
consists of the kinetic energy of the nuclei.
Let's take the two nuclei to be the same.
It could be, for example, hydrogen.
Alright, so the momentum of the
first nucleus, let's call it P1.
P1 squared divided by twice the mass of the nucleus.
That's the kinetic energy of the first
nucleus, just the nucleus, not the atom.
Then plus P2 squared, that's the
kinetic energy of the second nucleus.
And then, of course, there is
the Coulomb force between the nuclei.
The Coulomb force between the nuclei is plus
E squared, and the energy is plus E squared
divided by the distance between them, R12.
Let's just call it R12.
That's the, and I've left out
dimensional, you know, dimensional four-pies and stuff
like that.
That's not what I'm interested in.
And then what comes next?
The electrons.
So let's sum up everything that goes
into the electrons, everything that involves the
electrons.
First of all is the
kinetic energy of all the electrons.
Okay?
So, let's call the electrons, let's
call the momentum of the electrons Q.
Q sub I squared over
twice the mass of the nucleus.
Twice the mass of an electron.
Let's call that small mass.
Here's big mass for the nucleus,
here's small mass for the electrons.
And this is the sum over all the electrons.
Sum over all the electrons.
That's there, that's the kinetic energy.
Then there's the forces between the electrons.
That's plus E squared divided by,
let's call it little r Ij.
That's the distance between the ith and the jth electron.
This is the coulomb
energy between them, electrostatic energy.
And what have I left out?
Oh, I have left out the
force between the protons and the electrons.
So, that's one more term.
I guess we can call it
minus E squared because they're opposite charge.
Attractive.
Minus E squared divided by the distance
between the ith electron and the jth electron.
Either one of the nucleus.
I don't know what to call it.
Let's call it capital R one I.
That means the distance between the
first nucleus and the ith electron.
And then another one for the second electron.
R sub one, sorry, R two I.
Alright.
There are things which involve the electrons
and there are things which involve the nucleus.
So, here are all the things that involve the electrons.
Now, intuitively, and I won't try to prove
this, intuitively, there are two time scales here.
One time scale is long and it has to
do with the very slow motions of the nuclei.
Why are the motions of the nuclei slow?
Because the nuclei are very heavy.
And they move around under modest forces, in fact.
They're never accelerated very much inside a molecule.
And so we think of them as very, very slow
by comparison with the very, very rapid motions of the electrons.
Electrons, much more rapid than the...
So the electrons form a blur.
And we're trying to get rid of
that blur or replace it by something else.
Well, this is fairly easy to do.
In principle, in concept.
To actually do it might be more difficult.
But in concept, it's very simple.
You take everything in the
Hamiltonian here that involves the electrons,
group it together, and think of it
as the Hamiltonian of the electrons alone.
But what about the positions of the nuclei?
For present purposes now, we're going
to say the nuclei move so slow,
and the electrons adjust their wave function so rapidly,
that in first approximation, we can say,
the nuclei are not moving at all.
They're fixed, they're nailed down, they're stationary,
and we just fix them.
And we think of this
as a Hamiltonian for the electrons
in a fixed background,
the fixed background being
the nailed down stationary nuclei.
So we fix the positions of the nuclei.
Once the positions of the nuclei are fixed,
then this becomes the...
the expression for the energy or for the Hamiltonian,
but it's still a function
of the position of the nuclei.
It's a function of the position of
the nuclei, but those can just be...
You set the momentum to zero.
Well, whose momentum?
For the moment, yes.
In fact, for the moment, we don't even need to...
We just say they're nailed down, they're very, very heavy.
Okay?
We're not going to violate the
uncertainty principle or anything like that,
because eventually we're going to take those momenta
back into account,
and the approximation here is just that they move slowly.
All right, then we take this Hamiltonian,
which only involves the electron coordinates
and the fixed positions of the...
of the nuclei,
and we solve it.
What does that mean?
We solve the Schrodinger equation,
and we solve the Schrodinger
equation for the lowest energy state.
We find the lowest energy state,
and in fact, more important,
the lowest energy eigenvalue,
the energy, the ground state energy,
basically the ground state energy of the electrons
in the background of the nuclei.
Let's call that something.
Let's call that...
Let's see.
Let's just call it E.
E of electrons.
All the terms that involve electrons.
And what is it a function of?
The only thing it's a function of
is the positions of the nuclei.
That's all.
Everything else is taken care of.
This is the lowest energy state,
the lowest energy associated with
the positions of R1 and R2.
Those are the positions of the...
of the...
of the nuclei.
Now what do we do next?
Now we say, okay, let's take all of this
and forget about it,
erase it.
We can't forget about it, of course,
not completely.
But we can replace it by
the energy of the electrons
as a function of R1 and R2.
That's plus E of electrons
of R1 and R2.
What do we have now?
Now we have a problem
involving only the protons,
or only the nuclei,
excuse me, only the nuclei,
a potential energy between them
that was originally there,
plus another term in the energy
which also can be regarded
as potential energy.
It's a function of the position
of the two nuclei,
and therefore it's a contribution
to the potential energy.
This is the way that we eliminate
out of the problem the electrons
and replace it with something else.
In fact, it's only a function
of the distance between the electrons.
And so what we actually find
is that the entire dynamics
of the electrons is summarized.
We first of all have the Coulomb potential
between the nuclei,
but then another term
in the potential energy,
and the other term
in the potential energy.
When you combine it with this term here,
it gives you a force,
or gives you a potential energy,
which looks something like this.
When the nuclei are extremely close together,
it's completely dominated by the Coulomb term here,
repulsive,
when they're far away,
there isn't much energy between them,
and in between there's some attraction,
and that attraction is due to the electrons.
However, we never have to think
about the electrons again.
For this hydrogen molecule,
or whatever it is,
we don't have to think about it.
We just have an effective potential between them,
and we solve the problem of two protons
in a potential like that.
We know what the solution's going to look like.
It's going to sit at the bottom here.
It's going to be some wave function.
And that's a process of,
number one, eliminating fast degrees of freedom,
but we can also call it renormalization.
We started with a potential
which was just this potential.
We got rid of the high frequency degrees of freedom,
and the entire potential energy
was then replaced
by another function.
So the potential was renormalized.
That's the basic idea.
All renormalization is associated with that idea.
Eliminating very, very fast degrees of freedom,
and replacing them by an effective,
slow,
renormalized Hamiltonian.
Hamiltonian, or however you're doing your dynamics.
Okay, so that's,
that's renormalization.
We want to apply that to quantum field theory.
So I'm going to show you how you apply that
to quantum field theory.
What is it that you,
what is it that you get rid of?
What you get rid of,
you can either think of it
as things associated with very small distances,
or you can think of it
as things having to do with
either very high frequencies,
or very, very short wavelengths.
Short wavelengths,
entail high frequencies.
And so the things that we're getting rid of
in the problem are
the degrees of freedom associated with
very high energies,
very high frequencies.
Let's see.
Yeah, before we do that,
let's just go through some dimensional analysis,
some very simple dimensional analysis.
Just take a break from,
from renormalization theory for a minute,
and I just want to do some simple things.
I want to do some simple dimensional analysis.
First of all, in physics in general,
there are three length scales that you need,
distance, time, and mass.
And we can get rid of two of them
in elementary particle physics
by taking the two-dimensional parameters
of elementary particle physics,
namely h-bar and c,
and setting them equal to one.
That's two,
that's a specification of two,
two combinations of the,
of the scales in the problem,
of the dimensions in the scale
of, in the problem.
But it still leaves one dimension
that you have to specify,
one dimension that you need,
one quantity with dimensions.
And that dimension can be
taken to be a length scale.
Right?
Once you've set h-bar equal to one
and c equal to one,
there's only one dimensional quantity
that has to be specified.
It can be taken to be a mass,
it can be taken to be an energy,
it can be taken to be a momentum,
or it can be taken to be a length,
or it can be taken to be a time,
but you need one specification.
Alright, with these notations here,
then the units of mass,
the bracket means the units of mass,
are the same as the units of energy.
Why?
Because e equals mc squared,
and c is equal to one,
and also equal to the units of momentum.
Also true,
that the units of length,
what should we call that?
Length,
are the same as the units of time,
that's because c is equal to one,
but the units of length and time
are not the same as the units of length
and are mass and energy,
in fact, they are inverse.
So, one dimensional specification,
either a unit of mass, length, or time,
but once you fix it, that's it.
And all masses have units of inverse length,
all momenta have units of inverse length,
and so forth.
So, let's keep that in mind,
first of all.
That's a bit of dimensional analysis.
We have only units of length.
Everything else is determined,
or mass, depending on how we think of that.
Okay, let's now talk about
a typical quantum field theory,
let's see, I think we'll start with
a scalar quantum field theory,
and I'll show you what's entailed
in renormalization.
We have, for simplicity now,
just a quantum field theory with
a single scalar field, phi,
that's all there is.
It has a Lagrangian,
and from the Lagrangian,
we derive Feynman diagrams.
We're going to talk about those
Feynman diagrams a little bit,
and even set up roughly what a calculation
of a Feynman diagram would look like,
some simple ones.
Okay, so there's a Lagrangian.
Here is the Lagrangian for phi.
It's very simple.
It's just the derivative of phi
with respect to either space or time squared.
We've done these things before.
That's the kinetic term in the Lagrangian.
And then there may be a potential energy
in the Lagrangian, minus V of phi,
which is a function of phi.
Now, what are the units of a Lagrangian?
The units of a Lagrangian...
Okay.
What do we do with a Lagrangian?
We integrate it over...
We use a Lagrangian in the principle
of least action.
That's what a Lagrangian is for.
It's whole...
In classical physics, in any case.
In quantum physics, it's used in the path integral.
But basically, in either case,
the quantity of real interest is the action itself.
And what is the action in terms of the Lagrangian?
It's the integral of the Lagrangian.
But the integral of the Lagrangian over what?
And space.
Time and space.
This is the Lagrangian of a field theory.
So the interest in quantity,
which is usually called S,
sometimes S, sometimes action,
sometimes I, it doesn't matter,
but for now it's S for action.
Huh?
S for sex.
That's like action, isn't it?
No, no, no, I didn't say that.
All right, S for action,
and that's the integral d4x of the Lagrangian.
And the action is always something...
Yeah, question.
Action has units of h-bar.
But h-bar has been set equal to one.
So h-bar is now dimensionless.
Action is dimensionless.
There's no dimensions at all.
And that means whatever the Lagrangian is,
it must have inverse length to the fourth power.
The Lagrangian must have inverse length to the fourth power.
The Lagrangian density in here.
Must have inverse length to the fourth power.
Now, what I'm really after
is the dimensions of the field itself, phi.
What is the dimension of phi itself?
So let's see if we can figure it out.
The Lagrangian has to be...
Let's take this term here.
This term here is derivative of phi
with respect to x squared,
and it has to have dimensions
of inverse length to the fourth.
Inverse length to the fourth,
because it has to cancel this d4x here.
d4x, or x has units of length.
This must have units of length to the minus four.
Okay?
Well, whatever the units of phi are,
the units of the derivative of phi
are the units of phi
times length to the minus one.
That's the unit of the derivative of phi.
Differentiating with respect to x just gives you a length.
And that's the unit of length inverse.
And now the square of this
is just the dimension of phi squared
times length to the minus two,
and that has to give
you length to the minus four.
And that tells you that the units of phi squared
must be length to the minus two.
Or, to summarize,
the units of a scalar field,
the units of a scalar field
are just inverse length,
length to the minus one.
Good thing to keep in mind.
Very, very useful for all kinds of purposes.
Um...
That's an example of using some simple dimensional analysis.
Now, what about the rules of Feynman graphs?
Let's talk about the rules
of Feynman graphs a little bit.
First of all, the Feynman graphs
all come from V of phi.
V of phi might have things,
like, in it.
What does it have in it?
V of phi has things in
it like m squared over two.
That's just a parameter.
It really is, of course, secretly the square
of the mass of the field divided by two,
times phi squared.
And then it can have things involving,
let's call it g times phi cubed.
And then it can have
things with phi fourth in it.
Let's call the coefficient of phi fourth lambda.
That's a traditional notation.
Lambda phi fourth, and on and on and on.
It can have all kinds of terms in it.
And notice that these terms also have dimensions.
These terms also have dimensions.
In fact, the phi squared has
units of length to the minus two.
Phi cubed has units of length to the minus three,
and so forth and so on.
And from that, we can read off
what the dimensions of V of phi are.
Okay.
Now, let's talk about Feynman diagrams.
Feynman diagrams are built out of vertices,
and the vertices come from the potential here.
Is g units of mass?
G, let's see.
So, yeah, g must have a unit of mass, yeah.
Why is it mass?
The whole thing has to have
units of length to the minus four.
All right, here's length to the minus three.
This must be inverse length,
but inverse length is the same as mass.
Right.
So, g would have units of mass.
This obviously has units of mass squared.
What about the dimensions of lambda?
Dimension.
Dimension less.
No dimensions at all.
That's significant.
Dimensionless coupling constants are especially important
in renormalization theory.
The other ones have units of either mass, mass squared,
and of course, if you introduce more terms up here,
then you can follow what the dimensions are.
Okay, now, a quantum field theory or the rules
of Feynman diagrams are built out of two elements.
One element are the vertices,
and the vertices are read off from the potential here.
For example, g phi cubed,
represents a vertex in which three particles come together.
And the coefficient of such a vertex
in a Feynman diagram is just g.
All right.
Phi to the fourth, that's four particles coming together.
This one has coefficient g.
This one has coefficient lambda.
What about m phi squared?
Well, m phi squared is a very simple thing.
A particle comes in, let's
put a little cross to indicate,
and goes back out.
All right.
Just, I put a little cross there
just to indicate that something happened there.
Namely, the particle was absorbed and re-emitted,
and the coefficient is just m squared over two.
So when you're building a Feynman diagram,
a Feynman diagram has a value.
The value corresponds to the
amplitude for a process to happen.
All right, it has a value.
And in building it up, there's the
elements of the vertices and the propagators.
The propagators represent the motion
from one point to another.
All right, so let's talk about the propagators.
The propagators, from one space-time point to another,
we can just draw them as lines in between.
Of course, the particle doesn't
really move along a straight line.
That's not the implication here.
The particle is a quantum mechanical particle.
But the motion from one point to another,
or the emission from one point,
the detection of another point,
we'll call a propagator,
and we'll just indicate it by a
line going from one point to another.
Now, I'm going to tell you
what the meaning of the propagator is,
the mathematical meaning of the propagator.
The mathematical meaning of the propagator
is just the amplitude that if
you start a particle at one point,
that if you create a particle at one point,
that you detect it at another point.
But mathematically, what it corresponds to
is to starting with a vacuum,
applying the field operator,
phi at, let's call it, x,
x, let's call this point x,
and let's call this point y.
These are not the x
and y coordinates of a point.
These are point x and point y.
So you've created a particle at x,
and now you want to remove the particle at y,
so that might be some phi of y.
The creation operator creates it,
the creation operator that's in
phi of x creates a particle,
and you can think of it two ways.
You can think of, let's think of it this way.
The action of phi of y on the
bra vector zero creates a particle at y.
The action of phi of x
here creates a particle at zero,
but this can be read, create a particle at x,
what's the amplitude that, after a certain amount of time,
goes by that you find a particle at y?
That's the meaning of this symbol here,
the amplitude that if you created a particle at x,
you would detect it at y.
And that's what the propagator is.
That is what the propagator is.
It's just the amplitude that if
you create a particle at x,
you'll detect it at y.
But now I can ask, what
are the dimensions of this object here?
What are the dimensions of this object?
The vacuum, that's just a
state, the state of lowest energy.
Vacuums and states don't have dimensions.
You wouldn't say the state has a certain mass.
No, the state is just a specification of a configuration.
It has no dimensions, but phi has dimensions.
Phi has dimensions of inverse length.
So what's the dimension of this object?
Inverse length squared.
Now, if there is no mass for phi,
then there is no length scale in the problem,
other than just the distance between x and y.
x and y would be the only thing
which would specify any length scale in the problem.
So can you guess what this answer, what
the answer to this quantity has to be?
One over length squared.
One over length squared, but what length?
Inverse length squared.
Right.
I don't think it would make sense
to put here one over length squared,
one over length squared.
No, that doesn't look good.
How about one over length squared?
Now, how about one over length squared?
I don't know, what do
I even mean by length squared?
x is a four vector and
length squared is a four vector.
What do I even mean by that?
The obvious thing is one over the distance between them,
length squared, and the distance
now meaning the Lorentz invariant distance,
the proper time or the proper separation between them.
One over length squared.
So that's something we learned from dimensional analysis,
that if there is no mass in the problem,
if the particle doesn't have a mass,
then the propagator is just one
over the distance between the points squared.
Notice something important.
It blows up.
It gets very big when the
distance between the two points is close.
So the amplitude for starting at one point
and detecting a particle at a very close point,
just on dimensional grounds,
blows up and it diverges.
That's the source of all
divergences in quantum field theory,
that propagators have divergences like this.
And that can cause infinities in problems,
just the fact that the propagator
becomes so big at small distances.
Okay.
Everything else is just building
up Feynman diagrams and calculating them.
But, also of course interpreting them.
Okay, so let's now start with the idea of renormalization
and how it works in this very simple context.
Let's start with renormalization of the mass.
Now notice that in scalar field theory,
the parameter that appears is actually the mass squared.
It turns out that the mass
rarely appears in scalar field theory.
It only appears by virtue of taking
the square root of the mass squared.
The thing which appears in the dynamics of
the theory is typically the square of the mass.
It has to do with the fact that energy
is the square root of p squared plus m squared.
It's always m squared which appears.
So we might as well
ask about renormalization of m squared.
What does it mean and how do we do it?
So from this picture over here,
we see that the interpretation of a mass term
is just a basic simple function of the mass term.
It's a basic simple Feynman diagram or
a simple vertex in a Feynman diagram
where a particle is absorbed at a
point and emitted from the same point.
Now does it have to be exactly the same point?
Well, if we have a microscope
which is only good up to,
you know, we've built accelerators which
study things down to a distance scale
of 10 to the minus whatever it
is, 17 centimeters or whatever it is,
we're not really interested in the details of
what goes on on distances smaller than that.
So if we can find a process
in nature which would mimic this vertex,
even if that vertex might be separated and
fuzzy over a very, very tiny mass length scale,
we might not be interested in that.
If we're blurring our eyes to such fine distinctions,
anything, any diagram which absorbs a particle
and re-emits it from a nearby point
would be counted as part of
the mass term in an effective description
in which we don't look to it.
In other words, in its description where we
get rid of all the very short distance
and high frequency degrees of freedom.
So let's ask, are there any
Feynman diagrams that we can build
that will mimic just a particle
coming in and a particle going out?
Well, I'll give you one.
First of all, let's build it
out of this vertex over here,
the phi to the fourth vertex.
The lambda vertex.
Here's a very simple process.
A particle comes in, goes out,
but here's a Feynman diagram.
This is a little bit crazy,
but still it's a Feynman diagram,
where a particle is emitted and comes
back to essentially exactly the same point.
Okay?
Comes back to exactly the same point.
Really what's happening is the
particle's not going anywhere, of course.
It's just being emitted and absorbed very quickly.
That's the way to think about it.
This is a Feynman diagram, and
if we want to calculate it,
I'm going to show you how
to use the rules for calculating it.
It's the amplitude for a process in which
a particle comes in and goes back out.
And this whole apparatus here may
be on such a small scale
that we might not even see it.
It might be too small a
scale for us to be interested in.
But what is this propagator?
This propagator is...
Where did I write the propagators?
Did I erase them already?
No, here it is.
It's just 1 over squared.
But x and y are
the same point in this problem.
Well, maybe they're not exactly the same point.
Maybe I'm sort of blurring distinctions down
to some what's called a cutoff scale,
down to some very, very small distance scale.
We might want to ignore separations on that small scale.
That's called the cutoff in a quantum field theory.
Cutoff, meaning to say we don't
think about scales smaller than that,
it's a sort of arbitrary thing
to do, but we can do it.
Let's say we're not going to be interested
in distinctions on scales smaller than scale delta.
All right.
Then what should we put in here?
We should put in a propagator which
is separated by distances no longer than delta.
We should put in a propagator
which is separated by distance delta.
If we're interested in physics on length
scales a little bit longer than delta,
but we are not interested
on length scales smaller than delta,
then we might want to
say let's calculate the Feynman diagram,
but smearing this vertex here, smearing it,
make it a little bit smeary in space-time,
smearing it over a distance of size delta.
Then what will we get?
We'll get 1 over delta squared for the propagator.
1 over delta squared for the propagator.
We're throwing away all scales smaller than delta.
And what did I leave out?
I left out the coefficient lambda
coming from the 5 fourth term.
Lambda over delta squared.
So what's the amplitude then in this approximation for
a particle to come in, be absorbed, and be re-emitted?
Well, it's got two terms.
It has the original mass term.
It can happen in two ways.
It can happen just by the original
mass term absorbing it and re-emitting it.
And then it can happen by this more complicated process.
And the total amplitude then is the original mass term.
Let's give it a new name.
I'm going to give it a new name over here.
I'm going to call it m sub 0.
0 standing for original starting value.
m sub 0 squared over 2 plus this over here.
Another way to say it is if you're not
going to look at distinctions on such small scales,
that the effective mass term, the
effective mass and the effective mass term,
is m 0 squared over
2 plus lambda over delta squared.
So this is an example of the renormalization of mass.
It's getting rid of all degrees of freedom
on scales too small to be interesting to us,
too fast to be interesting to us,
and lumping the two together.
Lumping the two together into a single blurry effect,
which we'll just make a blurry cross here.
Stuff comes in and goes out.
And the amplitude, the quantum mechanical amplitude for it,
is m 0 squared plus lambda over delta squared.
All right. That's mass renormalization.
Are there other...
In other words, the true mass of a particle,
the mass that you would see in the laboratory
for experiments in which nothing
moves so rapidly and so fast
that you can see where your accelerator
simply doesn't expose distances smaller than delta,
the effective mass that you see is this.
Yeah, m 0 squared over...
Well, yeah, all right.
This is the effective mass term in the Lagrangian,
the effective mass.
And of course, the lambda over delta squared here,
there's pi's and other things in there.
There are numerical things in there.
So it's not just dimensional analysis.
Dimensional analysis plus evaluation of some integrals.
But most of it can be done by just...
Much of it can be done by dimensional analysis.
Okay. So this is the shift in the mass
due to getting rid of very, very high frequency fluctuations
and summing them up and
putting them into an effective description.
Change in mass, this would be called the renormalized mass.
But of course, we're not finished.
We haven't evaluated every possible Feynman
diagram that can go into this.
Let's do another Feynman diagram for the same thing.
Just to see how it works.
All right, let's see.
I'll put it over here.
This is a Feynman diagram that looks like this.
Again, it's using...
This is separated over here.
Separate this over here.
Here's another Feynman diagram.
Let's evaluate it.
It also has a particle coming
in and a particle going out.
But now we have something new.
We have two points.
What do we do with those two points?
What do we do with those two
points in order to get rid of things
on scales smaller than delta?
Well, we basically evaluate that diagram
when the distance between these
two points is again about delta.
Strictly speaking, you might integrate
over the position of these points.
Let's even do that.
Let's even think about that.
In fact, we should think about that.
Let's hold this point fixed.
This is the point where the first particle is absorbed.
And the second particle is absorbed
or emitted from a nearby point.
But remember that quantum
mechanical amplitudes are always sums
over all the possible ways that a thing can happen.
So if we fix this
point where the particle is absorbed,
we should want to integrate or sum over
all the places where it can be emitted,
all the nearby places it could be emitted from.
So let's see what that would give us.
I think we know that
the propagator is 1 over squared.
What's that?
The little bar across the circle would be three particles.
Yeah, three particles.
That one?
Yeah.
We're still examining the effects of this.
This term has four particles coming together at a vertex.
So here's four particles coming together at a vertex,
and here's four particles coming together at a vertex again.
Good.
This diagram is higher order in lambda.
It's to the next order in lambda.
This one only has one lambda.
Let's move this over here.
Lambda over delta squared.
That's what this one gives.
Now we look at this one over here.
This one will contain two factors of lambda.
If lambda happens to be a small number,
you might say this one is smaller.
If lambda is small, then lambda squared is smaller.
But let's work it out.
And this will typically be true
if lambda is a small number.
But let's see what kind of things we get.
So we're going to get lambda squared.
So this is a higher order Feynman diagram.
It's a second order Feynman diagram
instead of a first order Feynman diagram.
It contains the coupling constant,
or the constant lambda, quadratically.
And then it contains three
propagators going between these two points.
Let's call the point of absorption here x,
and let's call the point where the emission takes place,
let's call it x plus delta.
I don't just want to call it y,
I want to call it x plus delta to
indicate that there's a separation delta between the two points.
So what do we have?
We have three propagators between these two points.
What are those three propagators?
Each propagator is a one over delta squared.
The distance between these two points is delta.
The propagator is one over delta squared.
So this means,
one over delta to the sixth.
One over delta to the sixth.
But now I'm not finished.
Where does this, if the particle is emitted at x,
it can be emitted at x plus,
it can be, if it's absorbed at x,
it can be emitted at x plus delta,
but we're really interested in
the amplitude integrated over delta.
All possible ways that this event can happen,
particle being absorbed by, at x,
emitted from any nearby position,
any nearby position where we're not going to look too
closely about whether this position is the same or not.
The right thing to do is to integrate this.
Now I know I'm throwing rules at you,
but you can imagine that these rules make sense.
Quantum mechanical amplitudes are always sums over all the
possible ways of going from one place to another.
All the possible ways of getting from
the initial particle to the final particle,
having been absorbed at x,
you can be emitted at any point x plus delta,
but then you have to integrate over delta.
Alright, what is the integral over delta?
How many dimensional integral is it?
Delta is a four vector.
Did I give you a hint?
We have one over delta to the sixth,
but now we have to integrate over delta.
But what does the integral over delta mean?
It means the integral over the four coordinates,
the four space-time coordinates of delta, right?
Delta is a four vector.
If you want to integrate over a four vector,
you have to integrate over its four components.
So we can write this d delta naught, d delta x,
d delta one, d delta two, d delta three, and so forth.
Or we can just write d fourth delta.
That means that it's an integral over delta,
over the four components of delta.
Okay, now where are we going to integrate it between?
Well, we might want to integrate it to large distances,
but it's not going to matter,
because this is going to
be so concentrated at small distances
that it's mainly dominated by when these
two points are close to each other.
So, the important thing to know is that
the integral goes from small distances of order delta
to larger distances.
From small distances of order delta to
sort of the lower end of integration here,
delta, for each one of the coordinates.
Now, you care to guess how big this integral is?
Lambda is a dimensionless number.
It comes on the outside of the integral.
Lambda squared.
Put it over here.
But how can I evaluate this integral?
d fourth lambda over lambda to the sixth.
Lambda to the sixth means lambda squared cubed.
The answer is dimensional analysis.
We are not going to
do any integrals in this class.
We're just going to say,
dimensional analysis tells us the answer to this integral.
What does the integral depend on?
Just on the lower end of integration here.
That's all.
That we don't take into
account distances smaller than the cutoff.
That's all it means.
There's a cutoff in the field theory.
And we cut off the distance scales at distance delta.
The answer to this integral can only depend on delta.
There's nothing else for it to depend on.
So, what's the answer got to be?
One over delta squared.
That's all it can be.
So, notice what we get from here.
We get something that looks very much...
Of course, there's a number here.
You have to sit down and calculate more carefully.
There's pi's and other things.
So, there's some numerical factor here.
But the numerical factor is not terribly interesting to us.
I mean, if we were trying to
do a high precision experiment, it would be.
But what do we find for this here?
This here is the same as
this, except with a lambda squared.
Lambda squared over delta squared.
There are many, many other diagrams which
will also contribute one over delta squared
with higher powers of lambda.
For example, here's another diagram.
That one will also give...
But how many powers of lambda?
One, two, three, four.
This will give a lambda
to the fourth of some kind.
There's other powers.
There's lambda cubes also.
So, the answer is that
there's an infinite series of terms,
each with one over delta squared.
Each with one over delta squared,
plus a few other things.
For example, we haven't used this term here.
Let's see what we would get
from this term, from the pi cubed.
How do we make a diagram...
Okay, this is interesting.
A little more subtle dimensional analysis.
What do we get if we
have an integral that looks like this?
An integral from delta to infinity of something
which goes at small distances like one over delta.
Let's say a one-dimensional integral now.
One-dimensional integral would be delta.
What does that look like?
That's a logarithm, right?
That's a logarithmic integral.
Now, on dimensional grounds, you would look at
this and say this has no dimensions at all.
So, you might think that it's a constant.
But it's not a constant
because it's actually a divergent integral.
Whenever you find a divergent integral, you
have to be a little more careful.
An integral like this you'll just recognize as a logarithm,
and the answer will be logarithm of delta.
So, whenever you get an integral which
has as many powers in the numerator
as it has in the denominator, it's always a logarithm.
That's a rule. We're not going to use
it very much, but it's an interesting rule.
In dimensional analysis, an integral with as many
powers in the numerator as in the denominator
always becomes a logarithm.
If there's more powers in the
denominator, then you just use dimensional analysis.
You would say that this one...
Sorry, this would just be one over delta.
Okay, so let's do this diagram here.
This doesn't have a line running down the middle,
and it's composed out of two cubic vertices.
Two cubic vertices with three
particles coming into each vertex there.
So what is this one going to be?
Alright, there are two propagators.
That's a one over delta to the fourth.
Each propagator is a one over delta squared.
We have to integrate it.
And what about the vertices?
Each vertex is a g.
So there's g squared.
d fourth delta.
Again, we have to integrate over
all the positions of this point,
keeping this point fixed.
The particle is absorbed here,
emitted from some nearby point,
but we have to take
into account that that nearby point
could be smeared over some range of locations.
How about this?
What do we get for this?
Here we have as many powers
in the numerator as in the denominator.
Alright?
log
And again, we integrate from delta to whatever.
This one gives us g squared logarithm of delta.
So we see there are times that
we don't get 1 over delta squared.
Sometimes we get logarithm, other possibilities also.
But the single biggest thing,
what do I mean by big?
When delta is small, when the
cutoff distance is small, which is bigger?
1 over delta squared or log delta?
Logarithm is a very wimpy function.
It doesn't vary very much.
Logarithm is much weaker than any power.
1 over delta squared, when delta is small,
is very dominant over the logarithm of delta here.
Nevertheless, there are these logarithmic corrections
to the mass, but the dominant
things when the cutoff gets small, if you
have a very small distance cutoff, is these powers.
These inverse powers of 1 over delta squared.
All right.
So this is called the log of delta squared.
This is called mass renormalization.
Yeah?
Just a quick question.
Log to any base?
Yeah, well, yeah, that is a good question, of course.
And that's because I didn't tell
you exactly how to calculate it.
Let's just say log to the base e.
But the point is, if you change the base of the
logarithm, what happens to a log if you change the base?
Not an additive constant,
a numerical multiplicative constant.
But I didn't tell you what the multiplicative factors
here, the pi's and all that stuff are anyway.
So that would be absorbed
into the multiplicative factor here.
So in a typical calculation, there will be
some pi's and e's and other stuff here.
And by changing the base of the
logarithm, you'll just change these coefficients here.
So it doesn't...
Or units of length or something like that.
No, these are dimensionless.
These are completely dimensionless.
So...
Yeah.
Just change the numerical coefficient.
What about units of mass?
Oh, in this case, you're right.
Yeah.
For this case, yes.
Right.
The point is, yeah, the g's have units of mass.
But what are they supposed to be giving?
They're supposed to be giving a correction
to something which is a mass squared.
So the units of this g squared here is
the same as the units of this mass squared.
That means the rest of it is dimensionless.
Well, all I was saying was that you
could absorb which logarithm it is into your length...
You can.
But you can also just notice that
this and this have the same units.
And say, look, there's a numerical number here
that has to be computed by somebody with
a little more power than we're exhibiting here.
But you're right.
It can be absorbed into units.
Okay.
That's it.
Thank you.
That's the idea of mass renormalization.
Yeah.
This gives an amplitude.
And amplitude squared is a probability of this happening?
It is.
But more important, this kind of
amplitude represents the mass of a particle.
It's more important for our purposes now that
a diagram in which a particle is absorbed
in a location and emitted very nearby is
an effective description of the mass of the particle.
Now, of course, it's not obvious how this translates
into the inertia of a particle and so forth.
For our purposes now, it's
just a parameter in a Lagrangian.
But we're seeing that the renormalized parameter,
the parameter after you get rid of distances
smaller than a certain length scale,
the corrections to it, here they are.
Well, it's not just the mass that gets renormalized.
Let's do another example.
Well, even if you just...
Well, even if you just have the mass renormalization,
you still have an infinite number of terms, don't you?
An infinite number of what?
A lot of those diagrams.
Yeah.
So, I mean, you can keep going.
Oh, yes.
Yeah, let's keep going.
Right?
So it's already infinite.
Now, if lambda is small, it may be that
the series is a series of smaller and smaller
terms, and it might converge.
But still, there are an
infinite number of terms, and every...
Yeah.
Right.
Depends on, yeah, what happens to lambda, right?
Yeah.
Right.
Let's talk about the renormalization of lambda.
Lambda is also something that gets
renormalized, so let's talk about that.
It's not just the mass that gets renormalized.
Every term in the Lagrangian can also get renormalized.
Let's see how that works.
Delta has the units of length, right?
Big delta has units of length, yeah.
So small delta.
So when you do log of it, don't you
get really weird things, because log has all sorts of
powers?
Have all sorts of what?
All sorts of powers, when you do the expansion log.
A log is counted as dimensionless,
because really a log always means...
Log of delta over some other scale in the problem.
And I didn't want to get into that.
The logs are confusing.
The real things that I'm interested in are these things.
And these are less confusing.
These are dimensionally just what you'd expect.
I'm sorry I told you about logs.
Often what happens is the...
Is the logarithm is...
The logarithm is really log of delta times
some energy scale in the problem that you're
interested in.
But let's get rid of logs.
Logs are...
Actually, you meant lowercase delta in that case, right?
Lowercase delta what?
Oh, you were using...
Have I mixed up lowercase delta and uppercase delta?
Yeah, capital delta was the inside the integral...
Oh, yeah, yeah.
And the answer should involve small delta.
Right, sorry.
Good.
The answer always involves small delta.
Big delta is an integration variable.
All right, let's take another example.
From an operational point of view,
meaning an experimental point of view,
lambda phi to the fourth is
nothing but the amplitude for a particle,
for two particles to come in and
to go out again as two particles.
And from an operational experimental point of view,
if all of this takes place again on
a scale which is too small to see,
you lump it all up into an
effective coefficient of phi to the fourth.
Two particles in, two particles out, phi to the fourth.
All right, so, for example, you could
have Feynman diagrams which look like this.
This will also contribute a
renormalization to phi to the fourth.
I'm not going to work it out.
The reason I'm not going to work it out
is because I know it will give a log,
and I don't want to
tell you any more about logs.
It will give you a log.
But each one of these terms here
is something which in itself can be renormalized.
So what's going on is the
effect of very small distance physics
when you sum it all up
and take it all into account
the same way we took the electrons into account
when we studied...
molecules, for example.
We take them into account, we solve
for them, we get rid of them,
we do whatever has to be done,
and we find some effective description which
doesn't involve those microscopic degrees of freedom.
The result is renormalization of everything.
Everything gets changed, everything gets shifted.
So the parameters of the theory that you measure
are not the parameters of the
theory that you input into the theory.
That's the main lesson.
The parameters of the theory you measure
are those which take into account all the short
distance physics on scales smaller than you can see.
Would you repeat that again?
What you measure includes the scales smaller than
what you see or not what you see?
Yeah, what you measure has taken into account
by summing all the finite numbers,
by summing all the Feynman diagrams involving
length scales smaller than what you can see,
it has an effective output
which is the sum of all that stuff
which you lump together.
You lump it together into
a single thing that you call
the mass squared over two.
So the physical mass squared, the thing you measure
when you do an experiment
that, let's say, relatively low energy,
that doesn't involve really, really small distances,
is this renormalized mass here, which
is the sum of all that junk.
So is the conclusion that somehow
or another the M0 term must be,
cancel all of those other terms?
Exactly.
Yeah, we're going to come to that shortly.
But before we do, let's talk
about the renormalization of some other masses.
This is the renormalization of
the mass of a scalar particle.
You might think it works essentially
the same way for a fermion,
and it doesn't.
Fermions are better behaved.
I would call this bad behavior.
Bad behavior in the following sense.
You wanted to get out an answer.
Imagine in your head that the cutoff distance scale
is something very, very small.
Imagine in your head that the cutoff
distance scale might be the Planck scale.
We might be trying to account for all physics
on scales between the experimental scale all
the ways down to the Planck scale.
All the ways down to
that very, very small Planck scale.
Then what we would put in for
delta here would be the Planck length.
The Planck length is terribly small.
It's 19 orders of magnitude smaller
than the size of a proton.
17 orders of magnitude smaller than
the most current up-to-date accelerator experiments.
17, maybe 16 orders of magnitude.
And so delta squared is a very,
very small number in ordinary particle physics units.
For example, if we use GeV,
then the Planck distance would be
10 to the minus 19th inverse GeVs.
And 1 over delta squared would be what?
10 to the 38th in...
10 to the 38th, but what kind
of answer do we want to get?
For example, for the Higgs boson.
The Higgs boson is an example of a scalar particle.
What kind of answer do we want to get?
We want to get something like about 200 GeV.
But what are we getting?
We're getting 10 to the 38th.
This is terrible.
We don't want to get 10 to the 38th.
The only way to avoid it, incidentally,
the signs of all of these things,
some of them may be plus,
some of them may be minus.
I didn't track the signs of anything.
And m naught squared itself can be negative or positive.
We want to get out a certain
answer, which is of order 200 GeV,
but we're getting contributions.
We're getting contributions which are
17 orders of magnitude bigger.
The only way that this can make sense is
if all of this cancels precisely to 17 digits.
To 17 digits, this has to
cancel and leave over something in the...
Sorry, in the 30...
Sorry, it has to cancel not the 17.
34 digits.
And leave over something, I think it's in
the 35th, or maybe it's in the 34th digit.
This is called fine-tuning.
This is the fine-tuning problem of the Higgs boson.
Let's just recall what we know about
the mass term of the Higgs boson,
and where we know it from.
The Higgs boson has a potential, or the
Higgs field has a potential, which looks like that.
Near the origin, it looks like phi
squared all right, but with a negative coefficient.
I never told you that this m-naught squared was positive.
It can be negative or positive.
Yeah?
Is lambda less or greater than 1?
Lambda is assumed to be a number
which is not much bigger than 1.
Now, why do we assume that?
We assume that, first of all, because this would all
be nonsense if the terms, I mean, you know, completely intractable,
if the numbers got bigger and bigger and bigger.
But even more than that, we know that this kind
of quantum field theory becomes mathematically inconsistent when lambda gets big.
So lambda of order 1 is as big as it
could be, and it really should be smaller than that.
So assume that lambda is modestly small.
Now, let's, modestly small but not humongously small.
There's no reason for it to be very small.
And in fact, experimentally, we know that.
We know that it can't be too small.
We know it's a number of order 1%.
Even if it's less than 1, there's still a lot
of terms that are in there just because of the deltas.
Well, if lambda itself was 10 to the
minus 38, we might not worry about it.
No, no, if it's, you know, 0.9, then, you know, it falls
off, but it still has a number of terms that you have to...
Oh, there's an infinite number of terms, and all, you
know, you have to go a long way down this chain
before lambda to the high power
over delta is a relatively small number.
So it means that a whole
bunch of them have to conspire.
You know, I'm not sure, maybe 50 or something
have to conspire to give this ridiculously small answer.
Small...
Lambda?
Lambda is typically a number of order 1%.
Yeah, right.
Let me just remind you what we know about lambda.
We speculated, or I will tell you that
there's good reasons, we won't go into them,
why the potential for the Higgs boson, first of
all, why it has to have this Mexican hat shape,
that was in order to facilitate the problem
of getting masses, spontaneous symmetry breaking, and so forth.
But the potential, typical potential, would be of the form
minus, let's call it mu squared, over 2 phi squared.
I've called it, instead of calling it m naught squared, I've
called it minus mu squared because it's got to be negative.
We know that it has to
be negative to get spontaneous symmetry breaking.
Plus, again, lambda phi to the fourth.
And there might be more terms there, but
the other terms are believed not to be important.
All right.
What if we...
Where does the minimum occur?
The minimum occurs, we can calculate the
minimum by differentiating with respect to phi,
and setting it, setting the derivative equal to zero.
And what you'll find is that at
the minimum, at the minimum, phi min squared,
which we also called f squared,
remember we call this distance here f,
we also call that f squared,
that was equal
to mu squared over lambda.
If lambda is a number of
order of magnitude one and so forth,
and f, do you remember about f?
How big did f have to be?
For experimental reasons.
Remember all the masses of
the z and the w boson
were all controlled by f.
The known masses of the z boson
told us that f was about 200 GeV.
All right.
That tells us that unless lambda
is some absurdly different number than one,
which it shouldn't be,
that mu is also a number
which is of order 200 GeV.
In other words, this mass
term is of order 200 GeV,
even if it's negative, to hell
with the fact that it's negative,
it's of order 200 GeV,
but yet it is composed out
of this ridiculous sum of terms,
every one of which is 38 orders of...
which can be as big as 38 orders of magnitude,
bigger than the thing you're trying to get.
This is known as the fine-tuning problem.
Sometimes it's called the gauge hierarchy problem,
the hierarchy problem,
the hierarchy being the hierarchy of mass scales
from the Planck scale down to
the scale of ordinary particle physics.
Enormous gap, enormous ratio of scales.
And it's not just that
there's a small number in physics,
the mass scale of light particles.
There's this incredibly finely tuned thing,
which is composed of many pieces,
all of which have to add up to something small.
So that's ridiculous.
I mean, you know, we've understood
that that's a ridiculous idea for...
oh, I don't know, sometime in
the early 80s or late 70s,
when this problem was first identified.
And the question is, what do you do about it?
But before I get onto that,
let's talk about the
mass renormalization of other particles,
the other particles of the standard model,
and why they are not in themselves a problem.
It's really just one fine-tuning.
You don't have to separately
fine-tune the mass of the electron
and those sorts of things.
Why doesn't the electron have the same kind of problem?
Okay, so let's talk about fermions.
Fermions don't have the same sort of problem.
They're just a bunch of particles.
So let's talk about the mass term of a fermion.
The mass term of a fermion
involves the mass, not the mass squared,
and it's contained in the term in the Lagrangian,
which is m psi-bar-psi.
Psi are the fermion fields that
describe the creation and annihilation of fermions.
And the term in the Lagrangian
that controls or that defines the fermions,
the mass of the electron or
the quark or whatever it is,
just has the form m psi-bar-psi.
Now, as I told you
last time, or several times ago,
first of all, psi-bar-psi is also a term in Lagrangian
which creates a process where a
fermion comes in and gets re-emitted.
Psi absorbs a fermion at
a position, and psi-bar emits it.
So, again, it's very, very much like this term,
except it only involves the
mass and not the mass squared.
But that's not a big deal.
We can certainly imagine
diagrams which re-normalize the mass,
but I'm going to show you now why
it's not as big a deal for the fermions.
So, you remember I told
you a couple of times ago
that psi-bar-psi is a thing
which always absorbs a left-handed particle
and emits a right-handed particle,
or absorbs a right-handed particle
and emits a left-handed particle.
It flips you between handedness of the fermion.
If the fermion is moving down, and the
psi-bar has an axis with a right-handed helicity,
a right-handed spin relative to its direction of motion,
then the mass term will flip it.
That's an important thing to know.
So this is a thing which takes
left to right or right to left.
Now, what kind of thing is left to right?
Well, it could re-normalize the mass of the electron.
For example, one of the things
that we put into the standard model
was the emission by the fermions of a scalar,
or the emission of a gauge boson.
Emission of a scalar, or
the scalar, let's represent this way,
the scalar is a dotted line, the gauge boson.
This could be quantum electrodynamics.
In quantum electrodynamics, the only thing
that can happen to an electron,
is it emits a gauge boson, a photon.
What happens to the handedness of an
electron when it emits a gauge boson?
The answer is nothing.
The handedness doesn't change.
So, emitting a gauge boson takes
left to left or right to right.
You can work that out
from the properties of the Lagrangian,
that the emission of a photon
doesn't flip the helicity of a fermion.
What about the emission of a scalar particle?
Well, it turns out the scalar
particle does flip from left to right,
or from right to left.
So gauge bosons don't flip.
Scalar particles do flip the direction of
rotation of the spin of the electron,
relative to its momentum.
Okay, now let's look at processes which
could renormalize the mass of the electron.
And this is fun.
This is a little bit of a surprise.
Supposing the electron starts out with no mass.
Notice in the boson case,
where is it?
Even if the particle started with no mass,
it gets this huge,
humongous contribution from renormalization.
And the renormalized mass is not dependent,
the renormalization of the mass is
not dependent on whether the electron had,
or whether the particle had
the mass in the first place.
Just all these terms would be
there, even if this one weren't there.
Now let's take the case of the electron.
So what kind of things can we have?
Here's the electron moving along.
It could emit and absorb a photon.
Now by definition,
a mass term, practically by definition,
a mass term is recognized as
an amplitude for left to become right,
or right to become left.
From an experimental point of view, a mass term
was recognized as an oscillation between left and right.
Can we get left going to right?
Can that be?
Can that happen?
And let's suppose the starting
mass of the electron is zero.
Let's begin with the electron mass being zero.
Is there any way to go from left to right?
Well, you could emit a photon and reabsorb a photon,
but a photon always takes left to left,
or right to right,
and there's no way by a
sequence of emissions and absorptions of photons
to make a left go to right.
The conclusion is in quantum electrodynamics,
or in any theory which only
involves the emission of gauge bosons,
fermions get no mass renormalization at all.
They get no mass renormalization at all,
so the electromagnetic self-energy of an electron,
if the electron started massless,
if it started massless,
the correction would be zero.
A massless electron is a massless electron,
is a consistent thing,
well, in pure quantum electrodynamics,
not in the standard model,
but in pure quantum electrodynamics,
a massless electron is a consistent thing,
and if it starts out massless,
the bear, or the starting point, the input mass,
it will stay that way.
Why?
Because photons emitted and reabsorbed will
not flip from left to right.
What about supposing now there is a scalar particle
that the electron couples to?
The Higgs field is an example.
Let's suppose that the Higgs
field can be absorbed and reemitted,
or, sorry, emitted and reabsorbed.
What kind of thing does that make?
Can that make left go to right?
No, it can't, because the
scalar emission here always takes left,
where is it, always takes left to right,
or right to left.
This is the scalar particle here.
The scalar particle always involves transition,
and so here you can go
from left to right all right,
but then in the reabsorption here
you're going to go back to left.
And if you think about it,
no matter how complicated the Feynman diagram is,
it's always going to involve an even number of vertices,
because it involves an even number of vertices.
Whatever gets emitted must get reabsorbed.
That's all it comes down to.
If it's going to be just electron goes to electron,
whatever gets emitted must get reabsorbed,
the number of vertices must be even,
and if the number of vertices is even from this,
then you can't make left go to right.
And so again, scalar emission
and absorption will have no effect
on the mass of the
electron if it starts from zero.
Okay, can you ever get a
shift of the mass of the electron?
For example, in quantum electrodynamics.
And the answer is yes, but
only if you start with a mass.
What does a mass do?
A mass can be thought of
as a vertex in a Feynman diagram,
which does take left to right,
but the coefficient is proportional to the input mass.
So let me draw a Feynman diagram which does create,
which does shift the mass of the electron.
All you have to do is,
emit and absorb a photon,
but in the middle here,
have one of these mass insertions,
which itself flips from left to right.
Then you can start with left,
emitting the photon takes you to right,
but then the mass term takes you back to left,
and then, oh sorry, I didn't do that right.
Left goes to left,
and then the mass term takes left to right,
and then right to right.
The value of this Feynman diagram contains two factors,
or three factors.
It contains the electric charge twice.
Remember, the Feynman diagram for the emission of a photon
is proportional to the electric charge.
The coupling constant is the electric charge.
So this kind of Feynman diagram
would have the electric charge squared,
but it also has the original starting mass.
Original starting mass.
Let's call it m naught.
So we see that the shift in the mass
is proportional to the mass itself.
So now we can write down
that the mass of the electron
will consist of m naught,
plus something of order e squared times m naught,
plus more complicated diagrams,
e to the fourth times m naught.
In such a way,
that if the starting mass was zero to begin with,
it would remain zero.
The implication of that is that
not if the starting mass was zero
that it would remain zero,
it's that if the starting mass was very small,
it would remain small.
You would still ask the question,
why is the electron so
light compared to some fundamental scale,
but at least you wouldn't have this fine-tuning problem.
You would not be canceling out
differences between large numbers to make a small number.
You'd say, for reasons I don't know,
the mass of the electron may be small,
and all the corrections to it are even smaller.
So fermions are, in that sense,
better behaved than
scalar particles.
What about gauge bosons?
Well, gauge bosons have the same problem.
They have the same property,
that if they start out massless,
I won't go into it,
if they start out massless,
they remain massless to all orders.
So what that means
is that to understand the
mass scales of the standard model,
the fine-tuning problem,
there's really only one fine-tuning problem.
It's the fine-tuning that's associated with the Higgs boson.
If you get that one right,
all the other ones will be okay,
because all the other masses are direct responses
to the shift of the Higgs field.
Where is it?
I don't know.
We erased it, I guess.
Yeah.
To the shift of the Higgs field.
And if the shift of the Higgs field is controlled,
and if it doesn't undergo this enormous renormalization
and shift off to some huge amount,
then everything else will be okay.
There will be no other fine-tunings.
The only fine-tuning in the standard model,
no, really,
crazy fine-tuning,
the only really crazy fine-tuning
is the mass term from the Higgs boson,
which has to be about 38 orders of magnitude smaller
than whatever fundamental scale you might envision.
That's the great puzzle
that supersymmetry
and other kinds of theories like that
are intended to address.
Roughly speaking,
the question is,
is there any kind of context
where the Higgs boson cannot get a mass correction
which is enormously large?
Is there any kind of theory
where the Higgs boson itself
will also be a particle
whose mass isn't driven to enormously large values
by renormalization?
And so the answer is yes, we know some.
There's one other fine-tuning,
extreme fine-tuning in physics.
It only comes into play, though,
when you start thinking about gravity.
Before you think about gravity,
if you don't think about gravity,
then it's not a problem.
It is a problem that's associated with renormalization,
and it's the problem of
the renormalization of vacuum energy.
Renormalization of vacuum energy
is also a serious problem.
It's also a thing of very serious need for fine-tuning.
And I'll just tell you what it is
since we're dealing with fine-tuning.
First of all,
what the energy of the vacuum is,
for most purposes in physics, doesn't matter.
Why not?
Well, it's an additive constant to all energies.
If empty space has a vacuum,
it's energy, so be it.
But then as long as when you add a particle,
it adds the right amount of energy,
that's okay.
Who cares what the vacuum energy is?
It doesn't play any role in physics.
The real point is that only energy differences
are important in physics.
Energy differences.
So when you think about the mass of the electron,
don't think about it as the energy of electron.
Think about it as the extra energy
that you have to add to the vacuum.
Whatever the vacuum energy is,
you have to add a little energy
when you add an electron.
So it's energy differences.
The energy difference between the energy of an electron
and the energy of a vacuum,
which is really what we
call the mass of the electron.
So who cares then if the vacuum
gets its energy shifted by a large amount
as long as everything else gets shifted along with it?
So let's come back to who cares in a minute,
but let's just ask what
does happen to the vacuum energy.
And the vacuum energy is,
is something which is also renormalized,
and it's renormalized by diagrams
which have no input and no output particles.
In other words, just vacuum to vacuum.
The effect of such diagrams is to renormalize
the energy of the vacuum,
but who cares?
I mean, the vacuum energy is of no physical significance,
but nevertheless, let's ask what it looks like.
So for example, in the 5-4th theory,
let's do the 5-4th theory,
so there are, oh, yeah,
let's draw a diagram from the 5-4th theory
that involves no in particles and no out particles,
just vacuum to vacuum.
Here it is.
Four particles at the vertex here,
and that's it.
How big is that diagram?
Numerically, how big is it?
Well, it contains lambda,
and then it contains a propagator from here
back to the same place.
That's a factor of 1 over delta squared.
After I, it's a factor of 1 over delta squared
if this little separation here is of order delta,
but then there's another one here,
which is another 1 over delta squared,
so the whole thing is
1 over delta to the 4th.
Every diagram that you can write down
will typically go as 1 over delta to the 4th
times, there are more complicated ones,
but they'll also go as
1 over delta to the 4th,
and so the vacuum energy is also something
that gets renormalized.
Because it gets renormalized,
it means that if you
really want it to be 0,
you better fine-tune it to very high precision,
but on the other hand, who cares what it is?
We don't care what it is.
We don't care what it is
until gravity becomes important,
and the reason is that in standard theory,
the source of the gravitational field is 0,
and that's because the vacuum has energy.
If the vacuum has energy,
it means that the vacuum itself,
empty space, gravitates.
We're not going to go into this now,
this of course has to do with dark energy,
it has to do with the cosmological constant,
we'll talk about it another time,
but yes, this is also something
that has to be fine-tuned,
and it has to be fine-tuned once again
to enormously high precision.
So really, strictly speaking,
there are two fine-tuning problems in physics,
at least two.
Two that we know about.
One of them is the vacuum energy,
which has to be tuned to something like
123 decimal places,
and the other is the Higgs mass,
which only has to be tuned to something like
30 or 35 decimal places,
or something like that.
These are the two problems,
in many respects,
these are the sort of biggest puzzles
in particle physics at the present time,
of course it may turn out that these puzzles
are simply due to a misstatement of the problem.
You know, it often happens that really,
really thorny puzzles go away
when you state the problem correctly,
but it's been a long time since these problems
were identified, and nobody really knows
what the solution to them is.
Supersymmetry is a potential solution
to the fine-tuning of the Higgs boson.
It is not a potential solution to the fine-tuning
of the cosmological constant.
So the next time, I'm getting a little tired,
I think we'll quit early tonight,
time for a couple of questions,
but the next time I'll start to tell you
a little bit about what supersymmetry is.
It looked like when we had the summation
for the Higgs...
For the mass of the Higgs?
Yes.
Yeah.
It would actually depend on delta,
but delta was kind of arbitrary.
You said plane distance, but it could be
10 times the plane distance.
It could be 10 times the plane distance.
So does the fine-tuning depend on the delta?
That doesn't make any sense.
We can talk about all the contributions
to the mass of the particle,
which come from fluctuations
of wavelengths from degrees of freedom
down to some very small distance scale.
The answer will depend on that scale.
It will depend on that scale.
So the real question is,
ordinary quantum field theory,
how far down in scale do
we expect it to make sense
before it becomes nonsense?
All those modes, all those frequencies
are real things that we think are really there,
because quantum field theory makes sense
for delta scales.
That's a sort of lower bound
on what these effects are.
What I'm saying is if we have some scale
where we expect that physics will change,
it could be the Planck scale,
it could be some unification scale,
if we have some idea where physics changes,
then the physics down to that scale
contributes some contribution,
and it will only be bigger than that.
That's the point. It will only be bigger.
This is kind of a lower bound.
Now, what do you choose for delta in practice?
In practice, you choose for delta
the distance down to which
you think you understand physics
at the present time.
So we have the standard model.
The standard model appears to make sense
to very, very small distance scales.
We talked a little bit about unification
of coupling constants, didn't we?
About how the coupling constants seem to track together,
and they seem to come together at something like
about 10 to the 16th GeV.
Well, a lot of us think that that's the scale
where quantum field theory continues down to.
Beyond that 10 to the 16th GeV,
even smaller scales, it can only get worse.
But if you believe that quantum field theory
in the standard model makes sense
to some small length scale,
let's say 10 to the 16th GeV,
or whatever it is,
then you're obligated to say
where the effects of all the scales in between,
what they did to the theory,
how they renormalized the theory,
and what canceled them all out.
And it can only get worse by thinking about
even smaller scales.
So, right, so we think we have a pretty good
understanding of physics down to scales
which are many times smaller than
the weak interaction scale,
in this ordinary weak interaction scale.
We have a good understanding of it,
only though, if we can explain what happened
to the mass contributions
and the renormalization contributions
from scales between the experimental scale
and the smaller scale where we think
the theory makes sense.
So in that sense, what I've described
is sort of the lower bound
on how bad these things can be.
With delta, we simply take to be the scale
at which we still believe the theory makes sense.
Yeah?
What's the definition of a scalar particle?
Like, can you give an example of a scalar particle?
A Higgs particle.
Higgs particle.
It is the scalar particle.
It's a scalar particle.
There's probably more of them.
We've never actually detected an elementary particle
that we would call a scalar particle.
How do you define a scalar particle?
How do you...
What is a scalar particle?
How do you define it?
It's not a lot of permutations.
It doesn't transform under rotation of coordinates.
It doesn't transform under rotation.
A photon is a vector particle.
It's described by a vector potential,
which, when you rotate coordinates,
the components of the vector change.
The gravitational field is a tensor particle.
Fermions...
Simply stated, let me say it even simpler.
A scalar particle is a particle with spin zero.
No angular momentum.
No spin angular momentum.
That's the simplest statement of it.
The z particle is a gauge boson as well?
The z particle is a spin one particle.
Oh, it's a spin one particle.
All gauge particles are spin one.
W plus and W minus are spin ones.
They're the same as the z part...
The spin is the same as the z particle,
which is the same as a photon.
All these particles called gauge bosons are very similar.
I keep emphasizing they're very, very similar
and parallel to...
to the photon.
They have a Maxwell-like description.
For the vacuum energy problem you discussed,
how come the...
the...
the Bose ground state doesn't
cancel the Fermion ground state?
Okay.
Right.
That would require, again,
a huge amount of fine-tuning.
The actual answers are a little more delicate.
They involve various numbers here and so forth.
There's infinitely many such terms,
some of them positive, some of them negative.
And the ones...
some of the ones from Fermions are negative,
some of the ones from...
from bosons are positive.
But unless the masses of the particles
and the coupling constants
were very delicately matched,
they wouldn't cancel.
Matching them is what supersymmetry does.
Supersymmetry does exactly that.
It cancels out the...
The question was why
Fermions and bosons...
The questioner knows something.
Well, the questioner knew
is that at least the simplest Feynman diagrams
for the vacuum energy of Fermions
is negative the simplest corresponding diagram
for bosons is positive.
And in principle,
if a Fermion and a
boson had exactly the same mass,
they could cancel each other in the vacuum energy.
But if they have slightly different masses,
then you're going to get, again,
these quantities here with huge coefficients,
which may be proportional to the mass difference,
for example, of a Fermion and a boson,
but...
or different coupling constants.
You would have to fine-tune it in any case
to get it to work out.
That's what supersymmetry sometimes does.
Okay.
If you want to know other questions...
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.