Stanford University.
All right, let's move on to supersymmetry.
Now, I have struggled to
find a way to explain supersymmetry.
And I took it as a challenge.
My own opinion from looking through my
notes right now is that I have
failed that challenge.
But I can only do my best.
Supersymmetry is probably the most
abstract construction in all of physics.
It is incredibly abstract.
Using among other things, these bizarre Grassman numbers,
which aren't numbers at all.
I'm not going to go into that.
But which are objects which do
some things that numbers can't do.
On the other hand, supersymmetry is full of them.
And we need to understand them a little bit.
So I told you about Grassman numbers last time.
Let me just review very quickly.
And then I want to tell you about supersymmetry itself.
Supersymmetry is a form of symmetry,
similar in some respects to other symmetries.
Other symmetries might be
rotation symmetry, translation symmetry,
the symmetries of spacetime.
Supersymmetry is a symmetry of spacetime,
but a very, very bizarre one.
And in order to make it a supersymmetry
of spacetime, one has to expand the notion of
four-dimensional spacetime to something
radically new, really strangely new.
It's that strange newness of this new kind
of symmetry that I want to talk about today.
Okay.
Let's talk about Grassman numbers.
Grassman numbers are mathematical constructions.
They can be represented by matrices,
but it doesn't help very much.
All right.
So I will indicate them sometimes by
epsilon, sometimes by theta, usually by Greek numbers.
And there may be several of them in a problem.
So let's label them epsilon sub i.
Sometimes, when there's an even number, there's a problem.
They are small number, and everyone means Mario.
We say, like in a ray
of dawn, they're something the balance.
They're something that is equal to Не.
And so we can change these numbers.
We can bring them together, but it's
not essential that we put them down.
Then we can put them down again and again.
Everywhere on this here picture you are won't
go through that newness of this new amarition.
Next month, then, we're going to have a game
I'd like to encourage you to warm up slowly
to each of the things that we're talking about.
One way to do this is to
pop some of this mäp també, neветė and
right? If there's an even number of
them, it's often the case that you'll group
them in pairs and make complex
combinations out of them. So for example,
if there were only two in your
problem, if there were only two Grassman numbers,
you could call them epsilon 1 and
epsilon 2, or you could call them epsilon
and epsilon bar. In my notation
tonight, the bar stands for complex conjugate.
That's a common notation for complex conjugate,
is to put a bar on top of
things, similar to star. Alright? So
there are these Grassman numbers, comma, not
times, there are these Grassman numbers
which have the odd property that they
anti-commute. The square of any one of them
is 0. It is not itself 0, but the
square of any one of them is 0.
And epsilon 1 times epsilon 2 is
minus epsilon 2 times epsilon 1. We'll come
back to that. In a Grassman
algebra, there are first of all these
anti-commuting Grassman numbers, and we'll
call those things odd. They
certainly are odd, but they're odd in
the sense which is mathematical also, odd
versus even.
The other kind of numbers in such a
set up are ordinary numbers. Let's just
call them n for number. These are not
Grassman numbers, they're numbers like 7, 3, minus
4, x plus i, y, and they can be
complex, and they're ordinary numbers, n,
and those are called even. Even elements
of the Grassman algebra and odd elements
of the Grassman algebra. The rule is,
an odd times an odd, in other words
the product of two Grassman numbers, is an
even element. That means it commutes with
other things. An odd times an even, what
did I say? Did I say odd times odd is
even? I hope I did. Odd times odd is even,
odd times even is odd,
and even times even is even.
Okay.
So for example, what that
means, odd Grassman numbers always anticommute.
Epsilon with epsilon, these don't have to be
the same, they could be epsilon i with
epsilon j, they anticommute. This means epsilon i,
epsilon j, plus epsilon j, epsilon i is
equal to zero. It also means that every
epsilon squared is equal to zero, because the anticommutator
of something with itself is just its square. Alright,
so these are the odd elements. The even elements
commute, let's say n m for two numbers equals
zero. This means n times m equals m times n.
And the convention is that even
elements and odd elements also commute.
So epsilon times n is n times epsilon.
The only anticommuters are a pair of epsilons.
Okay. So that's the oddness
and evenness of Grassman numbers. Yeah.
Are you making a distinction between Grassman algebra
and numbers, or is it one and the same?
Well, the elements of the Grassman algebra are the Grassman
numbers. Right. So I'm only making the numbers equal to zero.
I'm making the distinction between, you know, yeah. The
things which you act on are the Grassman numbers.
The rules are the algebra. Okay. Now,
there's Grassman algebra, which we've stated over here.
There are, there's the theory of functions of Grassman
variables. Okay. What is a function of a Grassman variable?
Let's say a function of one Grassman variable. Well, one way
to express that function is as a power series in epsilon.
So it'll be some a, which is independent of epsilon. Incidentally,
a could either be a Grassman number or a non-Grassman number,
but it doesn't depend on epsilon. We're thinking
about functions of a particular Grassman element, epsilon.
a plus b times epsilon.
But nothing after that, because
epsilon squared is equal to zero.
Now, if there's more than one Grassman variable,
you might have a function of several of them.
Let's say two of them. Either epsilon one
and epsilon two or epsilon and epsilon bar.
In that case, you would have function of epsilon one and
epsilon two would begin with something which is independent of the epsilons.
Then,
there could be, let's call it b
one epsilon one plus b two epsilon two,
and then some c epsilon one epsilon two.
Nothing after that.
Why not? Because if you multiply it by
another one of the epsilons, you get zero again.
That's if there are only two epsilons in the problem.
You could also write this in terms
of, if you made a complex equation,
if you made a complex combination epsilon and epsilon bar,
you could write this in the form
a plus, I guess we can call it,
b bar times epsilon plus epsilon bar
times another b plus c epsilon bar epsilon.
It doesn't matter whether you use
the complex combinations or the real combinations.
Either way, the sum terminates after c because
another factor of epsilon will set it to zero.
That's if there are only two epsilons in the problem.
If there are more, depending on
the number of epsilon variables there are,
the series will stop after some number of terms,
after you've used them all up, so to speak.
So, there aren't very many functions.
Usually, when you write a function of Grassman variables,
you assume that all the
terms are either odd or even.
For example, if f is
an even function, a commuting function,
then a would be even, b would have to
be odd so that b times epsilon is even,
this b would be odd,
and c would be even.
The other possibility is that f itself
is an odd element of the Grassman algebra,
then a would have to be an odd element,
b would be even, and c would be odd.
So you can have functions which are
either, but nevertheless, no matter what they are,
if they're functions of a
finite number of Grassman variables,
the number of functions is not very big.
They're polynomials and they end at some point.
Okay, that's the algebra of Grassman variables.
And the functional analysis of them.
Well, forget the functional analysis,
just the functions of them.
Yeah.
Can they be used in trigonometric functions as well?
Well, you could write the sine of epsilon,
but the sine function is just an expansion in powers,
and so it would just end at
the first, the sine of epsilon is epsilon.
Yeah.
There's just not enough structure
there to make interesting functions
other than a couple of polynomials.
Now, there's even a calculus of Grassman variables,
both differential and integral.
The notion of a indefinite integral doesn't really exist.
The notion of a definite, well, yeah,
the notion of a definite integral exists,
or just the integral of a function of epsilon.
Maybe I'll go through it the next time.
I don't think I'll go through
it tonight, the integral calculus of,
but it's very easy to remember.
Derivatives and integrals are exactly the same thing.
They don't differ.
But we'll come to, I won't do integrals tonight.
I'll just tell you about
the differential calculus of Grassman variables.
The derivative with respect to theta,
sorry, theta is a Grassman variable now.
Let theta be a Grassman variable.
I don't know why I started
calling it theta instead of epsilon.
Yes, I actually do know why,
but for the moment, no difference.
Derivative with respect to a Grassman variable of
a function of a Grassman variable is very simple.
First of all, if the function
doesn't depend at all on theta,
for example, if it only consists of
a constant, then the answer is zero.
Derivative with respect to theta,
of a plus b, let's say theta times b,
that's just equal to b.
Just exactly as if you were
just differentiating with respect to theta.
Now you do have to be a little bit careful.
Let's suppose that this function here
was an odd, an even element,
of the Grassman algebra.
That means a is an even element.
Okay, no big deal.
But it also means that b is an odd element.
That means you have to distinguish
between b theta and theta b.
They're different, and they're opposite in sign.
So if b is an odd element,
b theta and theta b are different.
If you want to differentiate with respect to theta,
first bring the theta dependence to the left,
and then hit it, and the derivative just gives b.
That's just one of the rules
of fiddling around with these Grassman numbers.
So there isn't much to
the calculus of Grassman variables either.
Of course, you can ask me,
what if you have a function of,
let's take the derivative with respect to theta.
of a function, now this is a complex theta,
of a function which is an a
plus b theta plus, let's call it b,
plus b bar, b bar theta, b
theta bar, b plus c theta bar theta.
This is the generic situation if
you have two thetas in the problem,
and I've arbitrarily organized them into two complex pairs.
You could use theta one and theta two also.
Let's see what this is.
The derivative with respect to theta of a is zero,
so that's the first term, plus,
now we have to be careful, is
this an odd or an even function here?
So let's say it's an
even function, just to be specific.
a is even. What is b?
Odd, is that right? Odd.
Odd.
So that means when I hit it with respect to,
derivative with respect to theta, I had
better bring the theta to the left.
What happens when I bring the theta to the left?
Minus.
So the next one would be minus b bar.
Now, the derivative of theta, of
theta bar with respect to theta,
that's zero, theta bar was a different variable than theta.
We could use theta one
and theta two, it doesn't matter,
but the derivative of one variable with
respect to another variable is just zero,
so we get zero from here.
Now, what about the derivative with
respect to theta of this term here?
Same.
We're going to get plus c.
Are we going to get
theta bar or minus theta bar?
Minus theta bar.
Minus theta bar because in order
to hit it with the derivative,
we first have to bring the c through.
We bring the c through to the other side.
Okay?
And that costs us a sign,
so that's minus c theta bar.
That's an example of a derivative,
a derivative operation on Grassman variables.
The only thing you ever have
to remember is to reorder things
so that when you differentiate,
you're always differentiating something that's
right next to the derivative.
Okay.
Let me prove a little theorem, which is important.
You have minus signs on both terms.
Yeah, that's because I had, uh, yeah.
Yes?
Both of these, yes.
That's because you had to bring the
theta through an odd element over here,
gave you a minus sign,
and you had to bring the
theta through theta bar over here.
Oh, sorry!
I made a mistake.
No, no, no, right.
What did I say?
Um, yeah, no, that's right.
That's right.
Hmm?
Yeah, if the whole thing is an even element,
then c must be even.
All right.
Now, the whole thing could be an odd element.
Let's suppose the whole thing, the whole function here,
was an odd element.
In that case, in that case,
a,
would be odd,
b bar would be even,
b would be even,
and c would be odd.
Let's see what we get.
The differenti- again, differentiating a gives us nothing,
but now, we can bring
the theta past the b bar
because the b bar is an even element,
and then differentiate it.
So this time we will get plus b bar,
not minus,
and over here,
we have to bring theta through two odd elements
to get it to the left.
That will not cost us a sign.
Each time we bring it through, we get a sign,
but we bring it through two odd elements,
no more signs,
so that's also plus c theta bar.
All right, so you just
have to do the bookkeeping carefully.
It's amazing that these things are useful.
Let me give you another little theorem, yeah.
You could just as easily have
written a function c theta theta bar,
couldn't you?
Yeah, you could just write a function c theta.
Then the signs of the derivatives of c would change.
Sorry, let's just write a function c theta theta bar.
Now, what's your point?
The point is that then the sign,
that if you had an even function,
it would be plus c theta,
and the odd function would be minus c theta bar.
Theta bar.
Yeah.
So what is the significance of
the way that it turns out
if we just easily reverse the terms?
C could be an odd function.
What is the significance?
What's the significance of it just
turning out to be an odd function?
It's a bookkeeping device for keeping track of fermions,
is what it is.
There's no significance.
Are there any?
No, there's no significance.
I think it's more relative than the significance
we will attach to it as we go on.
I think you would change the sign of c.
In which case?
If c is odd?
He wants to write the function
of theta and theta bar reversed,
so you just change the sign of c.
Oh, yeah.
Sorry?
I already have c.
If I change the order of theta and theta bar,
then I should write minus c theta theta bar.
c theta bar theta is minus c theta theta bar.
So if you reverse the order,
then you just define the constant.
It's a rule.
It's a mathematical rule, a new kind of number.
A new kind of number, when
you switch two of the odd elements,
you change the sign.
If c is also an odd
element, then you bring something past c,
you also change the sign.
But when you change the
sign, you don't change its parity.
You don't change odd to even.
That's right.
Any of these manipulations do not change odd to even,
but they can change the sign of the object.
I'm confused about something.
I think it's minor.
So I'm thinking of our coefficients a, b, and c
as drawn from the complex number field.
They could be complex numbers,
but they're not the same.
They're not the same.
But they're not the same.
There are two different numbers,
if they happen to be even.
If they're even.
If a is even, it could be a complex number,
but it could also be something else.
It could be the product of
an even number of epsilons or thetas.
But if we only have, so
if we have two of them, though,
then a product, then it will vanish of its thing.
If we have two of which?
If our grassland field has
two, only two independent elements
If there are only two elements
Well, you always include the
numbers along with the odd elements
So typically we might have
some finite number of odd elements
but all either the complex or the real numbers
Now, you can define more sophisticated things
You can define things which only have
a finite number of ordinary numbers also
Just the integers modulo 5 or something like that
that would also allow you to make Grassman algebras
The ones we're really interested in
are the ones that have complex numbers
and some finite number of Grassman elements that we'll call
from time to time I'll call them epsilon,
from time to time I'll call them theta
I'm sorry, with this
The first case was the entire function was even
and then the second case the entire function was odd
I guess, I don't remember
Okay
Yeah
The two derivatives are opposites of each other
What's that?
The first one was beta plus c4
Negative
Minus
And then the second version was the opposite of that
You want to go through it again?
No, no, no
I'm saying is that...
They're like symmetrical, these two answers
Is that not a general characteristic of this stuff?
Sometimes
Sometimes, but the rules are simple
Whenever a Grassman element
goes past another Grassman element
it changes the sign
Now in fact, you can also think
of derivative with respect to a theta
as a kind of Grassman element
But let me show you another interesting fact
But let me start with
ordinary functions of ordinary variables first
Let's take just a function of a single variable
And consider the differential operators
derivative with respect to x
and multiplication by x
Those are two operators and they have the following property
The product...
Which way is it?
Uh...
Yeah
Let's...
d by dx times x minus x d by dx
Have you ever seen this thing before?
It's the commutator of x with d by d...
Or of d by dx with x
Okay
You know where it occurs?
It occurs in quantum mechanics
It occurs in quantum mechanics because the momentum
of a particle is represented by an operator
which is minus i d by dx
Alright
What is this commutator?
d by dx times x minus x d by dx
Well, you all know how to
do it, but I'll do it anyway
You take it and you apply it to a function
any function
and you see what you get
Alright, so let's begin with the first term
The first term gives us derivative with respect to x
of x times f of x
And that's the sum of two terms
The first term, the derivative hits x and gives one
So this just gives f of x
And the other term, the derivative hits f
So it's plus x times, let's
call it f prime of x
where prime indicates derivative
The derivative can hit x and leave f
or it can hit f and leave x
Now what about in the opposite order?
In the opposite order we have x times derivative
with respect to x times f of x
That's just x times f prime
Now the x is on the
left, the derivative hits f of x
and that's just x times f prime
So, the difference between these
is just the difference between this and this
The x times f primes cancel
and what we find out is that
this is just equal to f of x
That all can be rewritten in a simple package
The commutator of derivative with respect to x
with x is just one
Why one?
Because it does nothing
It just acts on a function
and gives back the same function
So this is a simple
theorem about the commutator of derivatives
with multiplication by f of x
What about derivatives with respect to Grassman variables?
You might guess, and you would be right
that exactly the same thing is true
except for one thing, what is it?
Anti-commutator
Let's check that out
Let's just check it out
for the function a plus b theta
I'll work it for the even case,
you can work it out for yourself
I'll work it out for the odd case
where a is an even element
and b is an odd element
That's the case I'll do
Let's first hit it with theta d by d theta
and then we'll have to
hit it with the opposite order
Alright, now d by d theta
when it hits a gives what?
Zero
How about d by d theta times b theta?
b is an odd element so we'd have
to bring this around to the other side
This will give us
Forget this for a moment, this will
just give us minus b theta, right?
Sorry, just minus b
Minus b
But then we're going to hit it with theta again
Okay, so it's minus b theta
Theta on the left
But this is also equal to b theta
b is an odd element
I could have done this, yeah okay it's fine
It just gives me back b theta, right?
Everybody see what I did?
Okay, good
So that's the first thing, we can erase all this
Now what about the opposite order?
d by d theta theta times a plus b theta
Theta times a just gives us theta times a
But what about theta times b times theta?
That's zero
I could bring the theta through here
And then I would have the product of two thetas
And the product of two thetas is zero
So this is just equal
To the derivative with respect to theta
Of theta times a, right?
Which is?
a
So now supposing I add these
I add these
Then I get the anticomponent
So I have a product commutator
Of theta with d by d theta
Acting on an arbitrary function
a plus b theta
Gives back a plus b theta
Here's a, here's b theta
So this is one
So for Grassman derivatives
With respect to Grassman variables
Theta, the anticomponent
Is the commutator of theta
With d by d theta is one
Whereas for ordinary numbers
Or ordinary functions of ordinary variables
It's the commutator of a derivative
With respect to a coordinate
Is equal to one
So I showed you this for a variety of reasons
But one of them was just to show you
How to manipulate these objects
And as I said, the only rule
That you have to keep track of
Is that you pass one odd element
Past another one to change the sign
Otherwise
It's just like ordinary algebra
Much simpler because there's only a few functions
And not very many rules
Just because there isn't very much
To have rules about
Question
You discussed odd and even functions
Are there mixed functions where you have
You can invent mixed functions
But you really
They're really not
Normally you don't allow mixed functions
An expression should either be odd or even
You can investigate and start playing yourself
With what happens if you have mixed functions
But normally
An object is either real
Sorry, is either odd or even
I'm just wondering if
That f of x that you've got there
I'm sorry, is that odd?
No, no, no, this is just ordinary functions
Ordinary functions, even functions
I was just reminding you of something here
This is kind of the
commutator of x with p, right?
This could be p
Or if we multiplied it by minus i
Then this would be the commutator of x with p
Is equal to i
Leaving out h bar, yeah
So we talked about
Graphic numbers with like one or two
Multiple components, right?
Is there a limit?
Is there a what?
Is there a limit to it?
A limit to what?
How many you can have?
Oh, you can have any number
You can have any number
But
Algebra just gets more complex
You can have any number of them
Right
Alright, so that is what a
What a
Grassman
Algebra, Grassman calculus
The only thing that I didn't tell you
As I said
Was how integrals work
I'm going to tell you right now
Maybe I'll work this out for you
But not right now
The integral d theta
Of a function of theta
Is the same thing
As the derivative with respect to theta
As f of theta
I won't tell you why right now
If we, if it happens that we need derivatives
I will show you why it's true
Okay
It's the only rule that
allows you to integrate by parts
If you insist that the
integration by parts formula be true
Then it's, then it's necessarily true that
derivatives and integrals are the same thing
So that makes calculus very, very easy
Alright, now let's review for a
few seconds or a couple of minutes
The idea of symmetry groups
And then we're going to come to supersymmetry
Symmetry groups
Alright, so let's just very quickly review
We have some group elements
I'm interested in continuous groups now
And let's call the group elements G
G sub i, this is the i-th group element
I could, and
I here just indexes whatever you want to index
And as I showed you last time
The whole structure of the group
Is encoded in the algebra of commutators
The Lie algebra, it's called the Lie algebra
The Lie algebra of commutators
Of the, these G's are, oh sorry
These G's are not the group elements
These G's are the generators of the group
The generators of the group, the infinitesimal elements
Unitary group for an element
very close to the group element
Close to the identity is one plus i
Times a small number
This epsilon is not at the moment a Grassman number
Times G
And there are a collection of independent
Linearly independent generators
In the case of the rotation group
Those generators are just the
angular components of the angular momentum
The different components of the angular momentum
The L's, Lx, Ly, and Lz
For more complicated groups
There are more generators
But there's a collection of generators
And the important thing about the generators
Is the commutators of them
That tells you
It's basically an infinitesimal version
Of the table of multiplication of group elements
G i, G j
The commutator of two group elements
What does it have to do with?
It has to do with group operations
About different axes, so to speak
And then undoing them
What you get left over with
We talked about that
Alright, the general rule is that
The commutator of two group elements
Or two group generators
Is another generator
In the standard formula
There's always an i here
And then there's a set of constants
Let's call them C
I, J, K
Times an element G, K
That the commutator of the i-th and j-th element
This is summed over K, of course
Repeated indices
That the commutator of one generator with another
Is a linear combination of generators
That's the structure of all continuous groups
And these constants here
They're just numbers
They have some symmetry properties
They're called the structure constants of the group
What are they for the rotation group?
Anybody remember?
The permutation symbol
Yeah, the permutation symbol
Epsilon i, J, K, for example
But in general, they're just a set of
They have some symmetry properties
For example, the left-hand side
The commutator is always anti-symmetric
Under i and j
G i, J
G i, commutator G, J
Changes sign when you flip them
So it's anti-symmetric under interchange of i and j
And in fact, you could discover by a few manipulations
That it's anti-symmetric under interchange
of any two of them
But that's not important
The important thing is that the algebra closes
That means that the commutators of generators
Give back generators again
That's fundamental to the character of
What a group is
Now, the G's typically
For sensible symmetry groups
Are always Hermitian operators
They're Hermitian matrices
That means they have real eigenvalues
That does not prevent you
From putting them together into complex combinations
Let me give you an example of
one that we've studied in the past
Take the angular momentum components, L and V
Lx, Ly, and Lz
Those represent angular momentum
They're observable quantities
They're conserved in the real world
And of course they're Hermitian
Because observable quantities are Hermitian
That does not prevent you from putting together
Combinations like Lx plus or minus Ily
Do you remember what these things were?
Raising and lowering operators
What did they do?
They acted on state vectors
With a given value of Lz
We called it m
And it either raised or lowered m by one unit
So I just point out to you that
It's often the case that we combine them together
In complex combinations
For various algebraic purposes that are useful to us
Alright
In putting them together into complex combinations
That doesn't change the fact
that the original objects were Hermitian
Okay
One last point before we get to supersymmetry
Is that when you have a real symmetry
Real symmetry
Of a physical system
It also implies something about the connection
Between the generators and the Hamiltonian
In particular
It says
That the Hamiltonian of the
system commutes with the generators
Commutator H with the generators is equal to zero
That's another way of saying
That when the generator acts on a state
It doesn't change the energy
I think we proved that last time
That when you have a symmetry
It means that the generators
When they act on a state
Do not change its energy
That's another way of saying
That G commutes with H
And it also says something else
It says that the time derivative
Of the generator is zero
As a quantum mechanical equation of motion
It says that G is a conservative equation
Of the quantity
So I put those things together
I'm just reminding you of them
Because we're going to play that game now
With generators
All the ordinary things of physics
Always represent physical quantities
Which are even elements
Of a Grassman algebra
Anything you measure
When you measure it
You get a number
The number is a number
It's not an odd element of a Grassman algebra
And so all the
Fermion fields are odd
But you never measure
Fermion fields by themselves
You can't measure the field of a Fermion
You can only measure
The square of the field of a Fermion
Or something like that
The things you measure in nature
Are things which you should think of
As even elements
If there's any reason at all
To be thinking about a Grassman algebra
If there's any reason
And you can't measure it
For any reason
The symmetry elements
Rotation symmetries
All the normal symmetries of nature
Involve commutators
And not the
And not anti-commutators
Supersymmetry is a symmetry
Where the generators
Are odd elements of a Grassman algebra
Which means everything you would say
About ordinary symmetries
You say exactly the same thing
Except you put anti-commutators there
Alright, so I'm going to give you
Now an example
Let's invent two generators
G
Sorry, Q
Q and Q dagger
Or Q bar
And you can't say that
It's a complex conjugate
That's a complex conjugate
As I said
It's sometimes profitable
To combine the generators of groups
Into complex combinations
Supersymmetry is nicely expressed
In terms of complex combinations
These are intended to be odd elements
Alright
Odd elements means
That the anti-commutator of Q with itself
Is zero
The anti-commutator of Q with Q bar
Might be something else
Just in the same way
That when you have any other kind of group
When you commute two generators
You get a third generator
You may find out
That when you anti-commute Q with Q bar
You get something else
Would it be an even or an odd element
Of the algebra
Even
Alright
So, if you have a group
That's a group
That's a group that's even
Alright
So let's
I'm going to construct for you an example
It's constructed out of fermion fields
Or basically something simpler than that
I think we may have even talked about it
But I'm going to go through the details of it
Because it is the basic
The basic supersymmetry
The most primitive version of the supersymmetry
Is the most primitive version
It's related
To the real supersymmetry
The same way that quantum field theory
Is related to the harmonic oscillator
That's how primitive it is
But
If you know all about harmonic oscillators
You know a lot about quantum field theory
Because quantum field theory
Is just a collection of harmonic oscillators
Same thing here
Very similar
But now we have to introduce
Two kinds of creation and annihilation operators
We can think of them as odd and even
The even ones are just harmonic oscillator
Creation and annihilation operators
A plus or A minus
And I'll just remind you what
the algebra of these things is
The commutator of A plus with A plus
Is the same as the commutator
of A minus with A minus
Is equal to zero
And the commutator of A minus with A plus
Is equal to one
That's the algebra of creation and annihilation operators
And all these are perfectly conventional
Harmonic oscillator raising and lowering operators
Now we'll also introduce a collection of
Fermionic creation and annihilation operators
Same exact rules
Except anti-commutator
Commutator of two creation operators
Is equal to the commutator of two annihilation operators
Anti-commutator, excuse me
Is equal to zero
And the anti-commutator
Of a creation operator
With an annihilation operator for fermions
Is again equal to one
Incidentally, this says that C
plus squared is equal to zero
And this says that C
minus squared is equal to zero
Only one creation operator for fermion
And only one creation operator for a boson
Okay
So we're not talking about anything
as complicated as a quantum field
We could just be talking about
A fermion or a boson at rest
It's either there or it's not there
Or if it's a boson, there are one of them
Or two of them or three of them
We're not worried about its motion
Just a question
A boson at rest
How many of them are there
That's controlled by the
And we can create and annihilate them
Or a fermion at rest
Not worried about their momentum
Okay
Now I will construct for you
The
Generators of a supergroup
Or of a supersymmetry
Let's suppose these particles
Have a mass m
Let's suppose they have a mass m
And the energy
Is just the sum of all
the masses of all the particles
Mc squared
If we're interested in the energy
It's just the total number of fermions
Times the mass of a fermion
Plus the total number of bosons
Times the mass of a boson
If the mass of the fermions and the bosons
Happens to be the same
Then the total number of particles
Fermions or bosons
Times the mass of the particle
So let's call the mass of the particle m
And let's write
Q is equal to square root of m
That's a convention of course
Putting a square root of m there is a convention
Times the creation operator
Of a boson
Times the annihilation operator
Of a fermion
So what does it do
We talked about this last time
Let me just remind you
It removes a fermion if there's one there
And it replaces it by a boson
So it's a thing which takes a fermion
And makes a boson out of it
Likewise for this one
Except not quite likewise
Square root of m
Times a minus c plus
Oh I forgot to write down something
We didn't discuss the
Commutators of the a's with the c's
The a's are even
The c's are odd
And the a's are even
The rule is any a
Whether plus or minus
Commutes
With any c
They all commute
Among themselves
Alright so that means in particular
That it doesn't matter which order
You can take this odd element
The c's are odd elements
And bring it past the even elements
Doesn't matter
Likewise here
These are the generators
Of the supersymmetry
Algebra
Alright what do we want to do
I would like to know what the
Anti-commutator of
Q with q bar is
That's the analog of knowing
What the commutators are
For group elements
They tell you the structure of the group
So let's see if we can figure out the analog
Here for
These supersymmetry
Operations
And as I said
What they do
They don't rotate things in space
They don't translate things in space
They simply take a fermion
And replace it by a boson
Or vice versa
But let's work out the anti-commutator
Let's work out the mathematics of them
It's fun
It's not very hard
Okay anti-commutator
It's not hard
But if I try doing it in real time
I will surely make mistakes
I'm a bit puzzled
So I will use my notes
Okay anti-commutator of
Q with q dagger
What is that
Well first of all
It has an m in front of it
Q times a q dagger
Will have an m
Q and q bar
Q dagger and q bar
Are the same thing
No difference
Q and q bar
That will have m
And q and q
I can't do this
But I can do
If I do this
It's going to be
A plus c minus
That's q
And then q bar
Q bar should be
A minus c plus
That's q times q bar
But now I have to add
Q bar times q
In the opposite order
So I will add here
order, a minus c plus times a plus
c minus. Whoops, that's it. That's the anti-commutator,
this times this plus the opposite order. Okay, let's
work on it a little bit. It's not very
hard. First of all, you can take the a's
past the c's, right? You can pass an odd element,
an even element right past an odd element,
it costs you nothing. So we can write this
as m, I just want to put all the a's
together and all the c's together, a plus a minus times
c minus c plus. And then over here, it's plus
a minus a plus c plus c minus. Okay, so far,
nothing very interesting about it.
But now let me show you how to do it.
Let me add and subtract something. Now here's
where I've got to do it carefully. Let's add
inside the bracket, inside the bracket, plus, let's
get it right, a plus a minus c plus
c minus. But now I've added it, I'm not
allowed to just go around adding things, I've got
to subtract it.
So
just like last time, I'm going to divide the
gap between those two, so now I'm sorry, I'm
talking about the two not just the
two I used to have on the table.
I'm 제가
going to subtract also its area
in between the tag Lady key.
So
I just want to put all theive here in the
bracket, and if I'm Natureаю R, so I'm going to
call this first theier, enter whatever that is, enter
it in anal to the end of the bracket.
I'm going to add win over to this here.
And then talking of loop during the reformation,
once again I'm going to raise the dash, I'm
going to curl, and then out marking here.
Let's say it's R.
Sometimes when I collapse putting your caps
in with my favorites, it sehr Customs, and
today we go with R.
If you can go with that, that makes sense.
But what is that?
So, the c plus c mi- the c minus
c plus and the c plus c minus add together,
making 1, and this thing first of all contains m,
times, it looks like it's got twice,
a plus a minus, right?
Agreed? That's the first term.
Now what about this term?
This term has c plus c
minus and c plus c minus again,
but it has a minus a
plus minus a plus a minus.
So what does it have? It has
the commutator of a minus with a plus.
What is that?
So, this comes down and
adds plus c plus c minus,
all times twice m.
Somehow I,
hmm?
Say it again. Oh no, no 2.
There's no 2, is there?
No, where did I get? No 2.
No 2.
Good, because I hated that 2.
Okay, what is a plus a minus
in harmonic oscillator language?
It's the number of bosons.
What is c plus c minus?
It's the number of fermions.
So, we can write that
this is equal to the mass
of,
times the number of bosons,
plus the number of fermions.
Now notice I have assumed that the mass
of the fermions and the bosons is the same.
I've assumed that.
We'll explore a little what
would happen if I did that.
If I didn't assume that,
all right, then I wouldn't have gotten,
I would have gotten whatever I got here.
What is this expression here?
We're talking about part of,
we're not thinking about the motion of particles.
We're talking about particles at rest.
For a particle at rest, its
mass is equal to its energy.
All right?
So, this is the mass of a
particle times the total number of particles.
It's the total energy of the system,
and we can either call it the energy,
or the Hamiltonian.
So, here's what we've discovered.
We've discovered that the anticommutator of Q with Q bar,
for this simple system,
is the Hamiltonian.
Now,
first of all, the Hamiltonian is an even element.
Is the Hamiltonian a generator of a symmetry group?
Yes.
It's the generator of time translations.
Time translations are a symmetry of systems
with time translation invariance.
And the Hamiltonian is the generator of time translations.
All right, let's finish up,
let's finish up the group.
We have to find out,
we know, what we've discovered
is that the Qs by themselves
are not enough
to form
a closed algebra.
are not enough to form a closed algebra.
When you,
when you anticommute the Qs with themselves,
you get back the energy, or the Hamiltonian.
What happens if you anticommute
a Q with a Q, incidentally?
That's just Q squared.
Where is Q? Go up to the top.
Q squared will have a C, two C minuses.
Two C minuses.
Q squared will have A plus,
A plus,
C minus,
C minus.
But C minus squared is zero.
So the anticommutator of Q with itself is zero.
The anticommutator of Q dagger with itself is zero.
Zero is okay on the right hand
side of a commutation relation for a group.
All right.
What about,
what's missing?
What haven't I,
which pieces of the algebra,
haven't I considered?
H with Q, right?
We've,
by comm,
anticommuting Q with Q,
we found out that it's got to contain the Hamiltonian.
Now this is very odd,
that the symmetry group
not only contains these operations,
which take fermions to bosons,
but it also contains the Hamiltonian,
which means time translations.
Very interesting.
Okay, what about Q with H?
I'm not going to do it on the blackboard.
I'm going to leave it for
you as an exercise to do.
All you have to do, here's H,
commute it with Q,
but I'll just show you an
easy way to think about the answer.
Q with H is zero.
Anticommutator of Q with H is zero.
Not because it's an odd or,
sorry, not anticommutator.
You don't,
you don't anticommute odd with even.
You commute odd with even.
A commutator of Q with H.
Happens,
Which is even?
Hmm?
Which is even? H?
H is even.
H is even. H is the energy.
You wouldn't,
you wouldn't like a system whose energy was a,
Grassman variable.
No, not good.
Okay, happens that this is zero.
Now it would not be zero,
I'm going to show you why in a moment.
It would not be zero if the masses of
the bosons and the fermions were not the same.
So let me show you how,
how you can see that it's zero if,
and actually only if,
the mass of the boson is the
same as the mass of the fermion.
This is,
we've done this sort of manipulation many times.
You take QH minus HQ,
and you act on any statement,
on any state which has a definite energy,
any state which has a definite energy.
Okay?
Whatever.
Okay.
What does Q do?
Q either removes,
I can't remember,
does Q remove a fermion
and replace it by a boson?
Or the other way?
Whatever it does,
it takes one particle out and puts another particle in,
of exactly the same mass,
if the masses are equal.
Assume for the moment,
that the masses of the
bosons and the fermions are equal.
Then what's the energy of the state that you get,
when you act with Q
on a state of definite energy?
Same energy,
because you've just taken one particle
out and put another one back in,
but a particle of the same mass.
Okay?
So,
this must equal,
H acts on QE,
that just gives me E minus E,
times QE.
Why?
Because Q times E is an eigenvector of the energy.
On the other hand,
what about QH on E?
What does it do?
Well, H acts on E,
to give just E.
In other words, it just gives us,
Q times E times E.
These are the same.
Cancels.
That's always true.
Anytime you have an operator,
which acts and doesn't change the energy of a state,
it always commutes with the Hamiltonian.
Things which commute with the Hamiltonian,
are things which, when you act on states,
don't change the energy.
This object,
as long as the bosons and
the fermions have the same mass,
then Q does not,
change the energy of the state.
And if that's the case,
then Q commutes with the Hamiltonian.
What if the two particles didn't have the same mass?
No, then it just wouldn't commute.
And you wouldn't,
you wouldn't have a nice closed algebra here.
You'd get something else on the other hand,
on the other side here,
which would,
eventually,
make a mess out of it.
Can we go back just a moment?
Yeah.
Before you erase that?
Too late, but go ahead.
I'll, I'll,
if you ask the question,
we'll, yeah.
You want me to put it back?
Okay.
That, that,
that thing referred to the,
fact that,
you, you made,
you started off assuming E was an eigenvector of H.
Yeah.
And you said that Q,
that,
because of that,
Q is also an eigenvector
of H with the same energy.
Right, right.
Same energy, okay.
That's the,
that's the point I'd like to
just do it again and then-
All right.
I, I think I wasn't very complete about the argument.
Let's do it again.
QH minus HQ,
acting on any eigenvector of the energy.
Okay?
Any eigenvector of the energy.
Why does Q on E have the same energy?
It's the same energy because it
replaces a particle with one energy.
With exactly the same-
Same, same energy.
Right.
Okay?
It's also, so that's-
So Q times E is an eigenvector of H.
Because the energy-
Because it has the same energy.
And must, must stay, okay, and, and, and it's-
If E is an eigenvector of the
energy, it means it has a definite energy.
Right.
It's an eigen-
Now Q times E has exactly the same energy.
Can't have an indefinite energy.
All right?
So it's an eigenvector of H with the eigenvalue E.
And so we can write that H over
here can just be replaced by E times QE.
Okay?
Over here, this time it's even easier.
H acts on E to give E times E, right?
And it'll give us the same thing.
It'll give us QE times E.
Right.
Well, I think that the simpler
way to do it is to-
The simpler way, asimple-
Or the way I thought of it when you put-
When you said it the first time was that
once you decide that, that you have an eigen-
Another eigenvector of the same eigenvalue, you
can replace the operator with the eigenvalue.
Exactly.
And eigenvalue-
Yeah.
I mean, scalars-
Absolutely.
That's right.
I just was being a little bit pedantic.
Uh.
But you see-
And of course, E is just a number,
so it can go past Q, that doesn't matter.
And this is equal to zero.
Now, there's one other element of the argument here
which I didn't make, which I will make now.
This is true for every eigenvector of the energy.
And if the eigenvectors of the energy are
a complete basis of states, then if something-
If an object-
Let's just call it K, K for object.
If it acts on a complete set of states, every state in a complete
set of states to give zero, there's only one conclusion, K is equal to zero.
So anything which gives zero on
a complete set of states gives zero.
So if the eigenvectors of the energy are complete, which they normally are,
then it follows that commutator of Q with H must be equal to zero.
That also says that Q is a conserved quantity.
It says that Q is a conserved quantity,
but it's an odd element of the algebra.
It has an odd number of fermions in it.
It's a new thing, it's
a thing we haven't seen before.
And what was also true that we haven't seen before is
a group of symmetries which takes one kind of particle to another
when it's a set of states.
And when you commute them, you get something which, in
this case the Hamiltonian, has to do with symmetries of spacetime.
Okay? Symmetries of spacetime.
It mixes up internal symmetries which change particles one into
another with the energy which is the generator of time translations.
So this is something entirely new that-
Well, of course it's not entirely new. It goes back to
1972 or 73 or something like that, but it is rather unusual.
That's called a supersymmetry.
Now there's another way to think
about it which is even more exotic.
And the more exotic-
This is fairly exotic, but it gets more exotic.
The more exotic way is to say that-
That there are new dimensions of spacetime.
Now in the simple example we're doing
here, there is no space, there's only time.
There's only the energy, there's no position where
we put the particles, there's no translation symmetry.
There is time. Why is there time?
Well, if there's energy, there's time.
Let me just remind you what the
connection between the Hamiltonian and time is.
What is the connection between Hamiltonian and time?
The relation between Hamiltonian and time.
The partial t, the derivative of it.
Yeah.
We can write it in two ways.
We can write that the
time derivative of a state vector,
I think it's i times the time derivative,
is the Hamiltonian times psi.
In fact, that's one of the definitions of the Hamiltonian.
It's the thing which you act
on a state to shift the time.
Another way to write the same thing,
this is in the form of an
infinitesimal shift or a differential shift of time,
but if you want to shift
the time by a non-differential amount,
you write that e to the minus i h-
now let's shift the time by an amount delta.
Delta.
I'm not going to call it
t, I'm going to call it delta
because later on I'm going to
want it to be a small amount.
That's e on psi is equal to psi
at time t is equal to psi at what?
t plus delta.
The relationship between these two is just to expand
is just to shift by amount delta by differentiating
and if you expand out this e
to the minus i h-t for small delta,
you'll get something proportional to h.
So these are really the same statement.
That whenever you have a Hamiltonian,
you have a rule for updating state vectors,
translating them in time.
So this is odd.
It says that the anticommutator of two of these solutions,
the supersymmetry generators,
amounts to a small translation in time.
It's mixing up space-time with identity of particles,
operations which mix one particle to another.
We've seen operations that mix one particle with another.
For example, the symmetries of color or isospin.
They mix protons with neutrons, for example.
Isospin symmetry takes a proton into a neutron.
Color symmetries take red quarks
to blue quarks and so forth.
But nothing you ever do with them,
no combination of those symmetries
ever shift time or shift space.
They have nothing to do with space and time.
They just shifted red to blue to green
or up quarks to down quarks,
but never anything to do with space-time.
Here we're finding some kind of very unusual symmetry,
which when you anticommute two cues,
you get a small shift of time.
There is a way to think about this
where the supersymmetry generators are shifts,
just like the Hamiltonian itself,
are shifts of coordinates,
but not ordinary coordinates.
What kind of coordinates would you guess?
Grassman coordinates.
So one way of thinking about supersymmetry
is to increase the number of coordinates of space-time.
Now in this example, there's only time,
so space-time is just time.
I'm going through in detail
a very, very simple supersymmetry example
just to show you how it works.
But let's...
go a little further.
Let's suppose we have some function.
It could be the wave function of something
or it could be a field operator of some kind.
Let's call it psi.
If it were just psi of x,
I would say it was
the wave function of a particle
as a function of its position.
All right?
But I'm not going to have psi of x.
I'm going to have psi of theta and theta bar.
And of course, it's also going
to be a function of time.
We could also put x in
here, but we won't for now.
This is the wave function
to find some kind of strange super particle
located at Grassman coordinates theta and theta bar.
Now of course, that's the most
bizarre thing you've ever heard of.
And it's very strange.
Let's imagine some symmetries.
The first symmetry is going
to be good old time translation.
Good old t goes to t plus...
I don't know, delta.
What's the general...
And of course, what happens to psi
when you shift t a little bit?
In other words, what's the change in psi
Well, psi of theta theta bar and t
goes to psi of theta theta bar t
plus the derivative of psi
with respect to t times delta.
Right?
You shift t a little bit.
That differentiates it and multiplies it
by delta.
All right?
Ordinary stuff.
This is still theta and theta bar.
You've done nothing to theta and theta bar.
And if you like, you can remember
that the derivative of psi with respect to t
is related to the Hamiltonian acting on psi
with an i, with an i.
So this has to do then,
if I multiply and divide by i,
I can write this as the
operation of the Hamiltonian on psi.
All right.
This, of course, is a symmetry
of any good quantum mechanical system
time translation invariance.
And I haven't done anything except tell you
what a shift of time
does to a function of time.
But now there are other symmetries.
If these were x's and not theta's,
you might have space translation symmetry.
They would be associated with derivatives of psi
with respect to space.
The question comes up, is there any kind of symmetry
which has to do with shifting the theta's?
Is there any notion, any
kind of possible mathematical notion
of a function, which is
a function of time and theta's,
but where a shift of theta
has some nice interesting mathematical meaning?
So we're going to invent symmetries
where theta goes to theta plus epsilon.
Now theta is an odd variable of a Grassman algebra.
So is epsilon.
Otherwise you wouldn't be allowed to do this.
We might also allow theta bar to do something.
For a moment let's just
leave theta bar out of it.
And also at the same time,
at the same time that we shift theta,
we're going to shift t a little bit.
T is going to go to t plus what?
I theta bar times epsilon.
Now that is a very weird thing to write down.
At least this is an even element.
Theta and epsilon are both odd elements.
At least this is an even
element and time is an even element.
But what on earth can this mean?
It's a very odd thing to write down,
but let's pursue it a little bit.
Let's see if we can find out
what the generator is which does that.
What happens to psi
when you shift theta a little bit?
Shift, I'm not going to shift theta bar,
I'm going to keep it simple.
Just shift theta a little bit
and shift time by the same amount.
What happens to psi?
Psi goes to psi plus the
amount that you shift theta by,
let's call it epsilon,
times the derivative of psi with respect to theta.
That's just the formula when you shift,
an argument of a function by a small amount,
you differentiate with respect to the argument
and multiply by the amount that you shift.
And then we're also shifting time,
and we're shifting time by this amount here,
so let's write it down.
It will give us, I think it's
a minus if I kept track carefully
of all the odd and even elements.
Epsilon, theta bar,
d psi by dt.
Now what have I done here?
I've said I've shifted time a little bit,
so that means psi must shift
because of the shift of time.
How much does it shift?
It shifts by d psi dt times
the amount that I shifted the time.
I think there should be an
i here if I'm not mistaken.
This doesn't make any real sense, obviously,
in any kind of normal mathematics,
but we're following our nose and seeing what we get.
Here's what psi is.
Here's how psi shifts.
Let's factor epsilon out of it.
Here's what we get.
If we were just shifting time,
we would call the coefficient,
here, of the small shift,
we would call it the Hamiltonian acting on psi.
All right?
Let's factor psi out of this
and think of this as an operation acting on psi.
It's an operation acting on psi.
Let's give it a name.
Let's give this operation a name.
Differentiating with respect to theta,
that means shifting this abstract,
this very, very abstract additional coordinate
and at the same time shifting time
by an amount proportional to theta bar.
Let's give that operation a name.
It's a generator of something.
It's a generator.
It's an infinitesimal generator of something.
Anybody got a suggestion what I should call it?
How about q?
It's an odd element because it's
a derivative with respect to theta
and it's got a theta bar here.
Let's call it q.
q bar, as I said,
I think there's an i here.
q bar is its complex conjugate.
It has derivative with respect to theta bar.
It has a theta here and
probably a change of sign of i.
So in the same way,
you can invent a q bar,
which is just its complex conjugate.
And guess what happens
when you take q and q bar and anticommute them?
Can you guess what happens?
Let's write it out.
Let's take q and q bar and anticommute them.
So we have the anticommutator of d by d theta.
Is it minus?
I think it's minus i theta bar d by dt.
The anticommutator of that with d by d theta bar,
I'm not going to try
to be careful about the signs.
I'll screw them up.
Let's just guess.
i theta d by dt.
Let's see if we can figure out what we get.
The anticommutator of d derivative with respect to theta
and derivative with respect to theta bar.
I didn't tell you what
that was, but can you guess?
Anticommutator of two derivatives of theta
is very much like the
commutator of two ordinary derivatives.
It's zero.
Commutator of ordinary derivatives is zero.
Commutator of two different derivatives with respect to
Grassman variables is also zero.
So this term here gives us zero.
What's the anticommutator of theta bar with theta?
It's also zero.
Anticommutator of any odd element with
any odd element is also zero.
And the derivative with respect to theta, the t here,
that just goes through for the ride.
It doesn't change anything.
So the anticommutator of this
one with this one is zero.
But what about the anticommutator of this with this?
It contains the anticommutator of
d by d theta with theta.
What is that?
No, no, just d by d theta with theta.
We worked that out.
哇
One. One. All right?
What about the anti-commutator of theta bar?
Well, this is theta with theta here,
and then there is theta
bar with d by d theta.
Both of them give one.
What's the net result?
The net result is d by
d, is i d by dt.
It's i d by dt.
The full anti-commutator here,
it looks to me like there's a
factor of two that I screwed up.
Somewhere in here I should have a factor of two.
I don't know where.
Probably in the definition.
Probably the definition of this should be
a half of q or twice q.
Not important.
The anti-commutator of this with this is just minus i,
I think it's minus i, d by dt.
What is minus i d by dt?
H.
So,
here's a representation of q and q bar,
not in terms of creation and annihilation operators,
but as operations in a fictitious new kind of space-time
that involves anti-commuting coordinates.
It's the generators of a symmetry transformation
which shifts time by a very peculiar amount,
theta bar times epsilon,
while you shift theta by amount epsilon.
The upshot of this is there's a symmetry structure.
There's a geometric structure here.
There's a generalized kind of geometric structure
involving spaces which contain not only
ordinary coordinates like x and t,
but which contain these Grassman coordinates,
which are very hard to get your head around.
But motion,
moving around,
in this space,
first of all entails moving
around in the x's and t's.
The generators of those transformations
are just momentum and energy,
just as you would expect,
but also transformations which move
you around in this theta space.
And those transformations are the supersymmetry generators.
That's called superspace.
The symmetries are called supersymmetry,
and the space,
this generalized space where you think about,
fields and functions and so forth,
in this way,
is called superspace.
Now, I'm going to stop here because
I think I've probably flooded you with information.
No.
I'm sorry, Brian.
You finished the conclusion of that thing is equal to,
you said it a lot, but I didn't-
It's a factor of two.
It's two and minus.
It's i d by dt.
Okay.
It's a factor of two.
All right.
It comes from commuting d by d theta with theta,
and getting the i d by dt from here,
and then anti-commuting theta bar
with d by d theta bar,
which gives you another one times d by dt.
Okay.
Does it use somewhere that epsilon is small?
I would see where-
Well, epsilon is an anti-commuting parameter.
Its square is zero.
So anything to second order in epsilon is always zero.
Okay.
Right.
So you always get to
think of anti-commuting things as small.
Right.
That's a good question, but it's an-
All right.
I'm going to stop here because
this is a lot of information,
but the upshot of it, as I said, is supersymmetry,
first of all, is a
symmetry which takes fermions to bosons.
It can be represented rather
simply just in terms of operations,
which replace fermions with bosons,
but exactly the same algebra,
exactly the same al-
Oh, the unusual thing here is that the
operations close only if you include the Hamiltonian.
That's telling you that somehow the symmetry operations contain
not just the mixing up of fermions and bosons,
but when you do it once and then
you do it twice and you anti-commute them,
you get a translation in time.
That's made completely manifest here,
by saying there's extra dimensions.
The extra dimensions
include these anti-commuting dimensions,
and the supersymmetry generators are sort
of translations in the theta space,
together with certain translations in time.
So it's a rather marvelous structure.
It gets even more marvelous when
you make curved space out of it,
curved super space,
and when you make curved super space general relations,
you get a relatively more spectacular structure.
It's called super relativity,
which is called super gravity.
It's a rather spectacular structure.
And as I said,
it's somehow an extremely
deep generalization of ordinary space-time.
Whether it will turn up an experiment is another question.
I think we'll quit for now,
because we're going to go on,
but we're going to go on
and spend a little more time
on the mathematics of supersymmetry.
But for the time being,
I think that's probably enough.
Well, in one sense,
it's just a bookkeeping device for
keeping track of fermions and bosons.
In another sense,
it seems to be much deeper than that.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.