Stanford University.
Let's just come back to
fermions and bosons for a moment.
And I'm not interested now in the emotion.
We've talked about this before.
Just fermions and bosons at rest,
they're described by creation and annihilation operators.
You create a particle with a creation
operator, you annihilate it with an annihilation operator.
I'm not interested in their momentum.
They're either there or they're not there.
And we can describe them in terms
of, you know the story, creation and annihilation
operators.
For if we're talking about bosons,
then we introduce creation and annihilation operators,
A plus, A minus.
We multiply them together.
We multiply them, that expression,
by the mass of the particle.
And just M A plus A minus.
That's the mass.
Times the number of quanta, A plus
times A minus is the number of quanta.
And we can just say that's the energy.
The mass times the number of bosonic quanta.
That's the energy of the bosonic system.
If we also add fermions in.
We add fermions in by a similar pattern.
Creation and annihilation operators for fermions we've
called C. And if the fermions in the
boson system are to be initialized, C
is going to be the initialization operator.
So we are going to
keep the fermions in that form.
And we're not going to just add them.
the bosons have exactly the same energy or
mass, we can call it mass or energy, then
we would just add to the number of bosons
also the number of fermions, C plus, C minus.
And that would be the thing we
would call the energy or the Hamiltonian.
Let me just say a word or two
about the Lagrangian formulation of bosons and fermions.
Again we're concentrating now on just fermions
and bosons without worrying about their motion
in three-dimensional space.
For bosons we invent the field.
The field is called, also for fermions, but
for bosons we might call the field phi, we
usually call it phi, and we give it a Lagrangian.
Incidentally, just to remind you, this is
nothing but the mathematics of a harmonic
object.
It's a single oscillator, of a single harmonic oscillator.
So to describe the field theory in
this very, very simplified context, the field theory
is just, the field theory of
the bosons is just a harmonic oscillator.
We introduce a variable phi, it's like
the coordinate of the oscillator, and we give
it a Lagrangian phi-triple.
Phi dot squared over two plus the frequency
squared, which is just m squared, phi squared
over two.
To get spatial gradients, not thinking about
things varying in space or moving in space,
this is the simplest situation, simplest setup.
There's only a time direction,
no space directions to worry about.
And now we can work out the equations
of motion, the Lagrangian equations of motion, straightforward.
This is a simple equation.
The derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to
phi dot, remember what they are, the Lagrangian
equations of motion, partial of L with respect to
phi dot, d by dt, is equal to partial
of L with respect to phi.
All right?
D by, dL by d
phi dot, that's just phi dot.
This would give us the second derivative.
So this just becomes a
phi double dot, two time derivatives.
And that's equal to phi.
Oh, I'm sorry.
What did I do wrong here?
Sorry?
Yeah, L minus, t minus v.
T minus v.
Right.
Energy is t plus v.
Lagrangian is t minus v.
All right?
And that's equal to the derivative
of the Lagrangian with respect to phi.
That's equal to m squared minus
m squared equal minus m squared phi.
All right?
So that's the derivative of
the Lagrangian with respect to phi.
That's equal to m squared minus
m squared equal minus m squared phi.
And the solutions of this differential
equation, second order differential equation, it has
oscillating solutions.
And the oscillations oscillate with a frequency m.
Not m squared, but m.
And so not surprisingly, the mathematics of all
of this, the quantum mechanics of it is
just the quantum mechanics of a single
harmonic oscillator, one creation and one annihilation
operator.
All right?
It has a ground state.
It has no point.
It has no particles.
You add particles with a dagger,
you take them away with a minus.
Sorry.
You add particles with a plus, you take
them away with a minus, and so forth.
Now, let's come now to the fermions.
The fermions, Lagrangian for fermions is
in some sense simpler than for bosons.
It only involves a first power of a time derivative.
It doesn't involve phi dot c.
It's a first power of a time derivative.
It only involves pi times pi.
But to pull out the Binance
equation, that's not going to make money.
You can just do this.
It's going to make money.
But the professor is catches theprised.
He has gone too far.
You can't sell it to the
people who are solving all this.
You have to use 3 Alright,
so basically what's going on is a
Inhale İ 23 sigue I SHIFT
I H where, and when we take
broschial coordinates, we doомa trub, likso theı
we dance fre ci con doô fım yı
fî 我 depois solalfa scripture
you muș swimu B exhaust están
and va b dinner là căён
Suppose this was a Lagrangian.
Is this an interesting Lagrangian?
Does it give an interesting equation of motion?
All right, so let's work out the equation of motion.
Partial of L with respect to
phi dot, that's equal to phi.
Now we have to take the derivative of that.
So d by dt of this
is just equal to what? Phi dot?
And that should equal dl by d
phi, which is just equal to phi dot.
That's not much of an equation of motion.
It puts no restriction whatever on anything.
It just says phi dot
equals phi dot. It's a tautology.
Every possible trajectory satisfies it.
The only thing you might want to...
say is, well, maybe the trajectories ought to
be differentiable so that phi dot means something.
But other than that, no restriction. It
is not a useful or interesting Lagrangian.
This is connected with the fact
that this is a total time derivative.
It's equal to one half of
the time derivative of phi squared.
And whenever a Lagrangian is a
time derivative of something, it's always trivial.
It never gives an interesting equation of motion.
You can throw away total
time derivatives out of a Lagrangian.
Doesn't matter what it's a time derivative of.
It just doesn't matter. It doesn't
make any interesting equation of motion.
But now let's suppose that phi was a fermionic variable.
If it's a fermionic variable, it means it
has to be treated like a Grassman number.
Okay.
Partial of L with respect to phi dot.
We differentiate.
We differentiate with respect to phi dot.
And that indeed gives us phi.
And we take the time derivative of it.
But what about partial of L with respect to phi?
If phi and phi dot are Grassman
variables, and you differentiate with respect to phi,
you have to push it past the
phi dot, which is also a Grassman variable.
You get a minus sign.
In other words, if you wanted to write this in the other
order so that you could directly differentiate it with respect to phi,
you would have to put a minus sign in.
And so, you would get partial of L
with respect to phi is minus phi dot.
What's the equation of motion now?
It is phi dot is equal to minus phi dot.
That seems equally stupid.
But it's not.
It's not equally stupid.
Bring it over to the other side.
It's twice phi dot equals zero.
And it gives you some information.
It tells you.
Phi dot is zero.
That's highly restrictive.
It means the solutions are highly restrictive.
And this Lagrangian has some punch to it.
Maybe too much punch for our taste.
Maybe too much punch.
Let's add something to this Lagrangian here.
Well, let's also add, yeah.
If all we had was phi dot squared, incidentally, then our
equation of motion would be phi double dot is equal to zero.
Analogous to, but not the
same as phi dot equals zero.
In fact, now that these are fermions,
we should give them a different name.
I should rename everything on
this blackboard and call it psi.
Just so we don't mix up fermions and bosons.
Fermions, I'll always call psi.
Why is it taking longer to just...
This is psi, psi, psi dot equals zero.
All right.
Now I want to put in, in order to get
this side to oscillate, I had to put a restoring force.
This was the restoring force, the m squared phi squared.
That's what this was doing here.
Without it, we would just
have phi double dot equals zero.
Is there a possibility of making psi oscillate?
What do we do to make psi oscillate?
To make psi oscillate, we add
to the Lagrangian plus m psi squared.
Supposing we add plus m psi squared, not m squared, but m times
psi squared, similar to this, but with only a single power of m.
Then what happens?
Well, then we will get psi dot equals twice...
Let's see, do I want to make...
I think I just might want to put...
There's some two in here that I'll
want to put in in a moment.
Psi dot equals minus psi dot.
That's what I got from this term here.
But what will I get from this term?
We'll get plus m psi.
In other words, let's go back over it again.
Partial of L with respect to psi dot.
That's just psi.
And d by dt of it, just psi dot.
That has to equal the derivative of
the Lagrangian with respect to psi dot.
That's psi dot, with respect to psi.
That's psi dot.
Plus m, twice m.
Psi, I guess.
Minus sine.
Minus sine, why?
Because it's a grass one.
What's that?
Well...
No.
Actually, psi squared is zero.
What we really should be doing is having
two different psi's here, to really get it right.
Okay.
Let's do it more consistently.
Let's put two different psi's.
A psi one and a psi two.
It could also be the real
and imaginary parts of a complex psi.
Let's take the Lagrangian now.
Psi one dot, psi two,
plus psi two dot, or plus...
Uh...
Psi two dot, psi one.
If these were bosons, this
Lagrangian would be completely trivial.
Let's see why.
It's for a similar kind of reason.
If these were bosons, supposing we took
the equation of motion for psi two.
The equation of motion for
psi two, or for psi one.
Partial of L with respect to psi
one dot is equal to psi two.
And if we differentiate that, we get psi two dot.
This is the equation for psi one.
And that is equal to, from here, psi two dot.
In other words, it's again
trivial, if these were bosonic variables.
We would just have psi dot
two equals psi two, psi dot two.
And also psi one dot
is equal to psi one dot.
It would say nothing.
But, because when we differentiate with
respect to psi one over here,
there's a sign change,
the equation of motion becomes more interesting.
Now...
Isn't it just psi as a constant?
Yeah, it is just psi as a constant.
That's the solution to the...
It's a differential equation, it has a solution.
The solution of psi could be any constant.
Alright?
Now, if we add to this,
plus m, psi one, psi two.
Let's add m, psi one, psi two.
And see what we get.
Okay?
Alright, so let's again take the
equation of motion for psi one.
That gives us psi two dot.
Alright?
And from here, what do I get from here?
Minus m, psi one?
Well, let's first do this one.
From here.
That gives us partial...
That equals psi two dot,
differentiating with respect to psi one,
and from here, we get plus m, psi two.
I think I did that right?
Did I do that right?
Is it minus or plus?
Differentiating with respect to psi one.
The derivative with respect to
psi one dot is psi two,
and then you differentiate that with respect to time.
That's psi two dot.
Here we differentiate again with respect to psi one,
but now we get a minus sign because
the psi one is in the wrong place.
We have to push it through to here,
defer it to differentiate it.
That gives us a minus psi two dot.
Excuse me, minus psi two dot.
What's that?
Euler's equation is minus the s...
No, no.
Euler's equation is dl by
d, let's call it x dot,
is equal, d by dt,
is equal to dl by dx.
No minus sign from Euler.
Right.
Psi two dot is equal to minus psi two dot
plus m,
now I'm differentiating with respect to psi one,
so that just gives me psi two.
All right.
I think if I were being consistent with standard notation,
I would probably put a half here,
and then my equation would come
out to have a half here,
a half here.
When I shift this over to the left-hand side,
I would just have psi two
dot is equal to m psi two.
Now what kind of solutions does this have?
Euler's equation is m psi two dot.
We need an i somewheres, don't we?
Let's put an i over here,
because an i does belong over here and over here.
Plus.
Okay, so we would have i
psi two dot equals m psi two.
Now what kind of solutions does it have?
Oscillating.
All right.
So this is now a fermionic variable,
which oscillates with time.
It has i times d by dt is energy.
i d by dt is energy,
and so each quanta has energy m.
Now what about psi one dot?
What happens to psi one?
Well, if you go through with psi one,
uh,
with psi one,
will we find the same thing,
or will we find a minus sign?
A minus sign.
I think we'll find a minus sign.
I think.
You did it with regards to psi one.
Yeah, when I differentiate with respect to psi one,
I get an equation.
I get an equation of motion for psi two.
Now I want the equation
of motion for psi one itself.
With respect to psi two.
And I,
either I'll get a minus sign here or not,
I'm not sure.
I think I should get a minus
sign here if I did it right.
Okay.
But in each case, it's an oscillation.
All right.
The point, the interesting point,
is that the Lagrangian for a Fermi field,
instead of having m squared times psi squared,
has just m times psi,
where m is the frequency,
and the kinetic term only has one time derivative.
You've seen that before in the Dirac equation.
The Dirac equation is a
first order core equation in time,
whereas the Klein-Gordon equation,
which is like this,
is second order in time.
Yeah.
It seems to me that this Lagrangian is,
because their Grasp and Variables is sensitive
to the order that you write psi,
Yes it is.
psi dot and substitute and two one in.
I don't think the physics is,
but I think the final
physics probably doesn't depend on it.
But,
all right.
I just wanted to go through
the Lagrangian formulation of this system.
And it consists of a Lagrangian,
which contains phi dot squared over two,
minus m squared phi squared over two,
and then,
something like,
I think there's a half again,
psi star,
well, psi,
yeah,
psi one, or we can
take it to be psi star,
dot times psi,
with an i,
plus psi,
dot,
psi star,
plus m,
psi.
All I've done here was,
replace psi one and psi
two by psi one plus i,
psi two and psi one minus i,
psi two,
and I find that I can rewrite it like this.
Real and imaginary parts of psi,
just being,
what I called psi one and psi two here.
All right.
This is,
this is,
basically,
the Dirac equation,
in a very, very simple context,
where there's only one direction of space-time,
namely time,
just ignoring space altogether.
Harmonic,
the boson is a harmonic oscillator,
and the fermion is just a,
a component of,
a complex psi field.
Okay.
Now we want to come to supersymmetry.
This Lagrangian does have supersymmetry.
Let's just review that quickly.
This Lagrangian has a symmetry between fermions and bosons.
It obviously does.
You take out a fermion,
and you put back in a boson,
or vice versa,
and you don't change the energy.
All right.
So there's some kind of operation,
which takes a fermion to a boson,
or removes a fermion,
replaces it by a boson,
and those are the super generators.
Those are the cues.
So let's write those out.
Q dagger
is a dagger,
a plus,
let's just call it a plus,
c minus,
and for, just for convenience and notation,
let's put a square root of twice the mass here.
That's, we haven't, since we haven't defined Q dagger yet,
I'm free to put any number
that I like in front of it.
What does it do?
It removes a fermion and puts in a boson.
The conjugate of it, Q,
is just a minus c plus
times the square root of 2m.
Again, as I said, the square root
of 2m is there as a convention,
the convention having been
established in some other context.
Okay.
These are the,
Q operators,
and they satisfy an algebra.
They have a anti-commutator algebra.
Not a commutator algebra like angular momentum,
but an anti-commutator algebra.
Well, it has some pieces which are
commuting and some pieces which are anti-commuting.
So if I anti-commute Q dagger with Q,
we've done that before,
I'll tell you what we get,
we get twice m,
and then,
a dagger a,
plus c dagger c.
Or a dagger a minus,
minus.
The dagger and plus are the same thing.
Okay.
In other words,
we get twice the Hamiltonian.
We could have made it simpler and
just made it one times the Hamiltonian
if I wouldn't have put the 2 there,
but then I would have
disagreed with somebody else's notation,
and since by now the notations are completely standardized,
I put the 2 here,
so that we would agree with everybody else's notation.
This is one fact.
What about the anti-commutator of Q dagger with Q dagger?
Well, that will have,
for example,
the product of two c pluses.
There'll be a c plus from
here and a c plus from here.
Every term in this anti-commutator will have two c,
sorry,
two c minuses,
I guess,
and c minus squared is just 0.
So this is 0,
as is anti-commutator of Q with Q.
One last thing to do,
on the right-hand side of this algebra,
we wound up with h,
then h somehow belongs with Q in a common algebra,
in a common algebra,
but h is a commuting thing.
It's not, it's an ordinary number,
it's not a Grassman number,
and when you commute or,
when you commute or do whatever you do,
with Grassman's times ordinary numbers,
the rule is commute,
not anti-commute.
All right, so we could check one last thing.
We could check what's the
commutator of Q and Q dagger,
I'll just write Q dagger,
but it's the same for Q,
with h.
And this is easy to work out.
I leave it as a homework assignment
to work out the algebra of it.
The algebra of it is a couple of lines.
What's the answer?
Q.
Q?
Okay.
No, it's 0.
All right.
Uh, it's 0.
It's 0.
If there was just an a by itself,
then the commutator would have an a.
If there was just a c by itself,
the commutator would have a c,
but with both of them there,
the commutator is equal to 0.
Check that.
Check that for yourselves.
You actually wrote it on the board.
I did?
Here, it's on the board.
Oh, we worked out the commutator?
Yeah.
Okay, well, the commutator is 0,
and that has an implication.
It has an implication as obscure as whatever Q is.
And Q is an obscure thing.
It's a, it's a, a Grassman variable,
or it's a kind of,
it's got a fermionic character to it.
When you measure it,
well, you don't measure it.
But what does it mean to commute with a Hamiltonian?
It first of all means a symmetry.
But it also means,
it means that,
that there's some symmetry in the system.
In this particular case,
taking out a boson and putting in a fermion.
But also,
it means that Qs are conserved quantities.
They're conserved quantities.
They don't change with time.
And so,
you can label states.
By their values.
Labels in the same way
that you label them with energies,
or charge, or other things.
These are called supercharges, incidentally.
They're called supercharges
because they're conserved quantities.
Super, I don't know why,
but charge, like electric charge,
it's conserved.
That's the important thing about it, it's conserved.
Alright, so there's this algebra of
commutators and anti-commutators.
Of course, there's one more, which is a stupid one.
It's just that the commutator ever
has a set of variables,
and the set of H with
H is also equal to zero.
Everything commutes with itself.
And so,
we have a closed algebra
of a set of variables, H and Q.
Now, there's another way of thinking about supersymmetry,
and it's by adding dimensions to spacetime.
Grassman dimensions.
So let's go through that again.
Uh,
remember,
that things like Hamiltonians and momenta,
now I'm adding back in position for a moment,
just temporarily for a moment,
uh, spatial position.
Hamiltonian is represented in quantum mechanics
as I times the derivative with respect to time.
So, for example, the Schrodinger equation
says H on psi is equal to something,
uh, it becomes an equation for the time derivative
of the wave function.
So H is I d by dt.
What about momentum?
Minus I d by dx.
So, very often,
very, very often,
in fact, almost always,
it's the case that symmetry generators
are related to derivatives
with respect to some kind of variables.
What about angular momentum?
Angular momentum, which rotates space,
is related to various combinations
of x and d by dx.
They're related to differential operators,
namely the differential operators which
just rotate you a little bit.
So, when we look at these q's,
you might ask,
are they related to some sort of differential operators,
but not derivatives with respect to t or x,
but derivatives with respect to theta?
Why?
These are Grassman numbers, after all.
And so if they're Grassman numbers,
and they have to do with symmetries,
they should have to do with symmetries
of coordinates which are Grassman numbers themselves.
So I think we wrote down the last time
the, uh, the representation.
We add a complex dimension to time,
t and theta.
Theta, or we can also add,
theta is always a constant,
and it's a complex Grassman variable.
We can put in theta bar also,
the complex conjugate of it.
I will interchangeably use the notation bar
and complex conjugate.
It means the same thing.
So, our degrees of freedom depend on t
and these Grassman coordinates.
A very, very obscure and odd thing to have invented,
but let's do it.
Let's see what it means.
Okay, so now we'll write, first of all,
q dagger is equal to
derivative with respect to theta bar.
It's possible that I'm changing notation
relative to last time.
I don't remember.
d by d theta bar
minus i theta d by dt.
And q, now here I know that
I had a mistake the other day.
Because somebody pointed it out to me,
is d by d theta.
And I think the last time around I
wrote plus i theta bar d by dt.
But that was wrong.
Did I write minus?
Then why did somebody come
up afterwards and say that they...
Because it worked out for them.
It works out if you have two pluses.
No, the first one, I
think the first one was plus
and the second was minus.
They were different signs.
Which one you were writing last time?
No, you had minus then plus
and I think it worked out
if you do plus and plus.
Yeah, it'll also work out with minus and minus.
I assure you of that.
Yeah.
Yeah, it'll also work out with minus and minus.
The usual notation, look, part of it is convention.
Part of it is convention.
But the fact that these two are not the same,
the fact that these two signs should be the same,
that's dictated by these commutation relations,
these anti-commutation relations.
These signs should be the same.
Now, it looks funny.
This is the complex conjugate of this.
You might think you should have
changed the sign of i here.
But go back a step.
Remember that in quantum mechanics,
things which are real correspond
to things which are hermitian.
And observable.
Remember the fact that momentum is
equal to minus i d by dx?
That's a little bit peculiar, isn't it?
Because momentum is a real quantity.
And so the right-hand side
had better be a hermitian operator.
And the answer is that d
by dx is not a hermitian operator.
i times d by dx is a hermitian operator.
You can work that out.
I've done that in the past.
I'm not going to work it out now.
When you see a differential operator like d by dx,
think of it as pure imaginary.
It's pure imaginary.
It is not real.
The thing which is the real differential
operator is minus i d by dx.
So i d by dt is thought of as real.
And when you complex conjugate
it, you don't change its sign.
That's a...
a thing that I got wrong last time.
Both these signs should be the same.
Now if you anti-commute them,
where does the anti-commutator come from?
The anti-commutator comes...
When you anti-commute these, you'll have an anti-commutator
of d by d theta with theta...
d by d theta bar with theta bar.
What's that anti-commutator?
It's 1.
So it'll give you a i d by dt.
And the other way, also,
will give you an i d by dt.
I'm wondering now if I do
really need the sign to be...
Yeah, I think...
Yeah, the p-commutator vanishes.
The p-p...
p-p bar of the commutator vanishes.
So the first and fourth terms go away.
Right? The non-cross terms.
Yeah, these commute with each other.
Or anti-commute with each other.
These anti-commute with each other.
And these here...
No, I think it's minus.
I think it really is minus.
Yeah, so it must be plus.
Hmm.
It's either plus or minus.
I thought...
You know, I worked it out
at home and I got minus.
And now that I see it in front of me,
i d by dt is h.
Yeah, okay.
Okay.
All right, you've...
I guess it's plus.
My mistake.
In any case, you will get a 2h here.
The 2...
Where does the 2 come from?
The 2 comes from the two terms,
the anti-commutator of d by
d theta bar with theta bar,
and the anti-commutator of d by d theta with theta.
So when you anti-commute these,
you'll get exactly twice...
twice...
twice i d by dt.
This d by dt will
just stand there on the right.
Okay?
And i d by dt is h.
Up here.
So that's the basic algebra
of this very, very simple supersymmetric system.
All right, the next thing
is to introduce fields.
Now, in the world that we're considering now,
there's only one dimension of space-time,
and it's only time.
We're going to come back and put in space.
It'll make complexity
and make it more complicated than this.
But until we put in space,
there's only one dimension of time.
You know, physicists are constantly thinking
of multidimensional spaces.
They think of four-dimensional space-time,
which has four...
one dimension of time and three dimensions of space.
They think of ten-dimensional space-time,
which has one dimension of time,
nine dimensions of space.
We sometimes think of five dimensions.
It's called Kaluza-Klein theory.
Four dimensions of space, one dimension of time.
We even think about one-dimensional space-time,
which has one dimension of
time and no dimensions of space.
And that's what we're doing here,
just for simplicity,
just to see how the machinery works.
All right, so now we should introduce a field,
and that field should depend on
time and the thetas.
Well, that's all there is,
is that it's time and the thetas.
So let's call the field capital Phi.
It is not this Phi over here.
That Phi is small phi.
This Phi, big Phi, is a superfield.
It's a superfield, which means it depends on time
and the thetas.
Let's write out all possible expressions
that could go into it.
We're going to assume that Phi is a bosonic object,
in other words, that it's an ordinary number.
That means the first term, which contains no thetas,
is an ordinary field,
and it could be this field right over here.
Function of time.
Then we can have things proportional to theta bar.
Theta bar times psi.
Psi is a fermionic variable.
Theta is a Grassman variable.
Theta bar is a Grassman variable.
Then we can have psi bar times theta.
The last thing we can have is
what I will call d theta bar theta.
What comes after theta bar theta?
Well, you could have theta squared times theta bar,
but that's zero.
You could have theta times theta bar squared.
That's zero.
You can't have more powers
than just theta times theta bar.
So it terminates there.
That's it.
That's the general dependence of
a superfield in this context,
in this very simple quantum mechanics context,
or this very simple one-dimensional world.
A function of time.
Of course, these are also functions of time.
And d is also a function of time.
But this is the general expansion.
That's a...
Now, what do these supersymmetric transformations do
when they act on phi?
What does an ordinary transformation like t goes to a...
like a shift of t do?
A shift of t just takes phi to
phi of t plus a shifted value of t.
What does a supersymmetry transformation do?
It's a coordinate.
It's a coordinate transformation on the
t theta theta bar set of axes.
That's all it is.
It's a coordinate transformation.
But here I'm going to write down what it is,
and then I'll show you that it
really does agree with these things here.
It is the transformation t goes to t.
Now I'm going to introduce a new Grassman number.
The new Grassman number will be called psi,
and it also has a conjugate.
Let me tell you what I'm doing in another form.
What I'm imagining doing that
you ordinarily might do in space,
ordinarily space,
you might shift the coordinate x by writing
x goes to x plus a small shift.
A small shift epsilon.
That's a coordinate transformation you might do,
which would just shift your x axis.
Epsilon would be a parameter of the transformation.
Now what we're doing,
all right, let me see.
What we're doing now is we're shifting theta.
Theta goes to theta plus a Grassman number psi.
Theta bar.
Theta bar goes to theta bar
plus the conjugate Grassman number theta bar.
So they're shifts.
They're translations of the theta axes.
That's all.
Just translations in theta space.
But at the same time, you translate time.
But how much do you translate time by?
Time goes to t plus or minus t minus i.
Time goes to t plus or minus i.
T plus i炷 bar theta minus i炷 theta bar.
I will not swear to the
signs because I worked them out
and they seem to change.
They seem to have this magical way of changing
in the drive over from home to get here,
the signs seem to change on the paper.
And I don't know why.
Some....
It must be, oh, when I
commute to work, the signs change.
Ah, why didn't I think of that?
Did it change back and forth?
I don't know.
What is the D again?
What is what?
On the top, the big...
D?
Yeah, D of T.
D is just another variable.
It's just a power series.
It's just a coefficient.
If phi is a function of T,
theta and theta bar,
we can expand it in a power series expansion
in powers of theta and theta bar.
We can also expand it in powers of T,
but that would not be a useful thing to do.
We just leave it as a function of T,
but expand it in powers of theta bar,
theta,
theta bar,
and that's it.
Can't go any further than that.
So that's the most general
function of theta and theta bar
with a T dependence in
each one of its places here.
Now, what does that mean?
That means that the system contains a boson variable,
fermion variables in the complex conjugate,
and it appears like another boson variable.
It appears that there's another boson.
It appears there are two boson variables,
but in fact, we're going
to find that's not the case.
We're going to find that something,
I think the reason D is
called D is D for dummy,
dummy variable.
I didn't invent the terminology,
and I'm not sure why it's called D.
Okay, so now let's,
this is the field.
What do we need to have a field equation?
We need an action.
Okay.
So I'm going to tell
you now how you build actions.
You build actions by building up various kinds of products,
derivatives, and so forth of fields,
and you make a Lagrangian,
and then you integrate the Lagrangian over position,
over time, to make an action.
You integrate the action.
What do you do in ordinary field theory?
You integrate the action over time and space.
Here, we will integrate the action
over T and theta and theta bar.
We're just going to more or less think
of theta and theta bar as ordinary coordinates.
I think we're finished here.
And write an action.
The action is going to contain various
kinds of expressions involving capital phi here,
and its derivatives.
Okay.
Just as we would do if the,
theta and theta bar were ordinary coordinates.
All right.
So we're going to have an action.
Action.
And the action is going to be an integral dt,
an integral d theta,
an integral d theta bar,
of some,
let's call it lambda.
I don't want to call it an ordinary Lagrangian.
It's super Lagrangian.
Let's call it lambda instead of L.
Normally, I would use L for lambda.
But I'm going to call it super Lagrangian.
The term Lagrangian would not be used for this thing.
We'll call it capital lambda, the super Lagrangian.
And the super Lagrangian is
itself a super field, like this.
But it may be, for example, it
might contain the square of super fields.
It might contain all kinds of
derivatives of super fields and so forth.
So whatever it is, the Lagrangian itself might have,
a similar expansion in powers of no
theta, theta bar, theta, and theta bar theta.
That's all it can have.
The Lagrangian here is a function
of t, theta, and theta bar.
Now, we have to integrate over theta.
Keeping in mind that this lambda contains various terms,
let's call it,
let's call it lambda one plus,
well, it'll have various terms of exactly the same kind.
The first term will be bosonic.
The second term will have
a theta bar times a fermion.
The third term will have times a fermion.
And the fourth term will have theta, theta bar.
But what goes here may be more complicated.
It won't just be a simple field.
It'll contain time derivatives, quadratic
things, all sorts of stuff.
All right.
What happens when you integrate a function,
theta, theta bar,
when you integrate a function with
respect to theta and theta bar?
Did I tell you last
time how to integrate over thetas?
Yeah.
What happens?
It is the same as differentiation.
You get the last term.
No, not the constant term.
The one which contains the maximum
number of thetas and theta bars.
And that's all you get.
So, whatever this Lagrangian is,
this part of it just picks out the
last term which is proportional to theta bar theta.
It's called the d-term of the Lagrangian,
although it is not necessarily just
the d-term in this expression here.
It's the last term.
It's called a d-term, but without naming it.
It's just the last term.
In fact, we can call it lambda theta bar theta.
The last term in the expansion of lambda.
Integral dt.
In other words, whatever the last term in lambda is,
it's just the ordinary Lagrangian.
The ordinary Lagrangian is a
thing that we integrate with time,
having never heard of thetas and theta bars.
And whatever this last term is here,
it's just going to be what we
can redefine to be the ordinary Lagrangian.
So, supersymmetric theories have super Lagrangians,
which go into an expression like this.
But they also have ordinary Lagrangians,
which are just the last term in this expansion here.
The trick is to keep the
system invariant under the supersymmetry transformations.
In other words, to make
sure that the symmetry is preserved.
And that's a neat, that's a
trick that we're going to discuss.
Okay, so we need to know
how to build various kinds of expressions
out of the super field.
We need to know how
to build expressions which involve derivatives,
which involve higher powers of the field.
Exactly the things that we might
do if we had an ordinary field
and we wanted to build a Lagrangian.
We would differentiate phi, square the derivatives,
we would multiply higher powers of phi,
all the usual things we
do to build an interesting Lagrangian.
We're going to try to
do, and we're going to succeed,
we're going to try to do for phi here.
Before we do that, yeah, before we do that,
oh, oh, I know what we missed.
Yeah, what I didn't show
you is that these transformations here
are the things which are generated by these q's.
I didn't tell you what
the connection between these transformations
and this one, did I tell you?
Well, we did derive that.
All right, let's, we did derive it,
but let's just go back through it again.
If we have a super field like this,
and we shift the arguments a little bit,
what happens to the super field?
What's the change in the super field?
Let's write the change in the
super field if we make these changes.
This is the change in the super field.
All right.
First of all, this one
says shift theta a little bit.
So, that says shift theta,
differentiate the super field
with respect to theta,
and then multiply that by xi.
Like that.
We've shifted theta by amount xi.
The change in the field is
the derivative with respect to theta,
times xi.
Now we've also shifted theta bar,
plus the derivative
of phi with respect to theta bar,
times xi bar, I think.
Yeah.
And last, we're shifting the time variable a little bit.
So what do I do when I
shift the time variable a little bit?
I take a time variable.
I take a time derivative, right?
Take a time derivative, plus phi dot,
times the amount by which I shift phi.
The amount by which I shift t.
So that will give me
a phi dot times minus i,
xi theta bar,
minus i, xi bar, theta, I believe.
That's what happens.
That's the small change in phi
when I make such a transformation.
Simultaneous transformation of theta, theta bar, and t.
That's how phi shifts.
Now let's collect together the pieces that multiply xi.
That's d phi by d theta,
and also phi dot times xi times theta.
Let's see.
The pieces which multiply xi,
here it is, xi,
equals xi times d by d theta.
I'm going to put phi out here in a minute.
Phi out here.
We first differentiate with respect to theta,
and then,
where's the other piece?
What have I done here?
This should be minor.
Multiplies, right?
Multiplies.
Yeah.
Okay.
d by d theta.
Now, what's the other thing that multiplies xi?
It is minus i, xi bar,
You have to see the other key out there.
I got the xi outside.
Times d by dt.
All times theta.
Oops, nope, there's a theta,
theta bar.
Theta bar.
Now, apart from that nuisance little sign,
that for some reason or another,
I seem to have wrong.
It is just.
Yeah, in order to hit it with a derivative,
you're going to need to
move the theta past the epsilon,
past the xi.
I don't think that's what's wrong.
No?
No, the xi is a gauss.
I'm not differentiating.
This is it.
Xi is a Grasmann number, right?
You got to bring the theta.
Xi is a Grasmann number.
And then you got to bring the theta bar over.
Why?
I don't have to.
In fact, I don't want to.
I want to leave it this way.
Yeah, I want to leave it this way.
Then there's another term, incidentally.
The other term is sort of a complex conjugate
with xi bar times similar stuff times phi.
Well, I seem to have some systematic trouble with sign.
No, but don't you have the,
you have the phi outside, right?
On the right hand side?
Yeah, here.
But here you have it on the left hand side,
you got to take it across, right?
No.
See, I think this is
where your plus sign comes in
because when you take the time derivative,
the i goes in the denominator.
i goes in the denominator, yeah.
Yeah, see, your change is plus i,
but the d by dt is
going to put the change of t
in the denominator, right?
よっ
partial derivative with respect to time.
No, I'm saying that you have
t goes to t plus something
minus something,
minus i something.
And that's going, in the d by dt expression,
it's going to be in the denominator.
No, no, no. When you shift the
argument of a function a little bit,
you just differentiate with respect
to the thing that you're shifting
and multiply it by
the amount that you shifted the
argument by.
Now, there's a very simple cure to this.
The reason that I wrote
minus here
was because I was tracking
some sign conventions that I had
inconsistent back over here
someplace. I don't know where.
Someplace over here I had some sign convention inconsistent.
Yeah, I'm
fuzzy about the signs.
That's my problem with this subject.
I can never keep track of the signs.
They come
and they go, and I can't keep track of them.
Alright. In any case, a consistent
set of signs would probably have to have
a plus here.
And
then it must be plus over here.
Okay.
So what is this thing here inside the bracket?
What is that differential
operator inside the bracket?
It's just q.
So this is xi
times the differential operator
q, and then from here
plus xi
bar times
q bar
acting on
phi.
And remember what these things are. These are derivatives
and various kinds of differential
operators.
And you simply work it through.
You simply take these derivatives,
act on phi,
phi,
and you want to differentiate with respect to the
thetas. It's straightforward.
You just, the only thing, you have to
keep track of the signs.
And that's what these q's are.
They're like momentum.
They're like momentum,
but not for shifts of
x, but for shifts
of these thetas
simultaneously
shifting time in this way.
That's the basic symmetry that's called
supersymmetry.
It's a kind of shift symmetry in these
Grassman coordinates.
But not just a shift symmetry.
If it was just a shift symmetry in the
Grassman coordinates,
then there would only be these d by d thetas
in the d by d theta bars.
There would be no i theta
d by dt and so forth.
So then you would just have these terms.
What would be the anti-commutator of
a q with a q dagger
if it was only d by d thetas?
Zero.
So it would not satisfy this algebra.
Where the devil is the algebra?
Who knows? I've lost it by now.
Yeah, you would not have
the right-hand side containing the energy.
It would not represent the algebra that we started with.
Now, the algebra we started with was very simple.
We're making something fairly
simple into something fairly complicated,
into a complicated story.
But you can see the story is kind of interesting.
It's saying that the basic symmetry can be thought of
as a geometric symmetry.
As a geometric symmetry of shifting and translating
in this space, which now contains not only time,
but also theta and theta bar.
I think you had mentioned at some point
that there was a backwards in time element.
That may be where you had the minus sign.
Possibly.
Yeah, I don't know what happened to the sign.
Yeah?
Is there any physical realization
of the extended definition of time
that you have here?
Well...
It really just...
It's just a book...
From one point of view, it's just a bookkeeping device
that keeps track of this simple algebra here.
The reason that it is
important to go this route here,
this more complicated route here,
is because we're going to want to make Lagrangians,
which are systems,
which are more complicated,
than just harmonic oscillators interacting with size,
or not interacting with size.
This is a very simple system up there.
Harmonic oscillator and C-C dagger and nothing else.
There's no interactions.
The particles don't interact with each other.
They don't scatter off each other.
They don't do anything.
To have something interesting happen,
we have to make more complicated Lagrangians.
And the question is,
how do you make Lagrangians
that...
at every stage preserve the supersymmetry?
In other words, which preserve...
that at every stage the bosons and the fermions
are going to have exactly the same mass.
That's not obvious how to do.
How do we do it in relativistic physics?
How do we make sure that our dynamics
is relativistically invariant,
or translation invariant, or whatever?
Well, we write Lagrangians,
and we make sure that the Lagrangians...
have the symmetries that we want.
So when we're doing Lorentz invariants,
we invent vectors and tensors and all these objects.
We have a whole tensor algebra,
and we build out of all
of the objects of the theory,
we build scalars.
The Lagrangian has to be a scalar.
If the Lagrangian is a scalar,
if it's made up, it can
be made up out of vectors,
tensors, all kinds of things,
derivatives of vectors, derivatives of tensors.
If the Lagrangian is a scalar,
the theory will be invariant under Lorentz transformation.
We're doing, we're trying to do,
and not only trying to do,
we will succeed in doing it,
but it's much more abstract.
Basically constructing the methods of
producing invariant Lagrangians.
Invariant under what?
Invariant under these new kinds of transformations,
which contain shifts of theta and transformations of theta.
So that's the goal, to have
a calculus of constructing invariant quantities,
and in particular invariant Lagrangians.
And those Lagrangians may be much, much more complicated
than that simple free field.
That's a free field, no interaction
between the fermions and the bosons.
How would you construct something where
the fermions and the bosons interacted?
That you need this machinery for.
You need machinery like this to,
to know how to do that.
Okay, so let's talk about that machinery a little bit.
What can you do with
a superfield to make another superfield?
One of the things you can do is square it.
You can square a superfield.
Let's go through the exercise of squaring the superfield.
And that makes another superfield.
So let's just take, we have phi.
Phi is equal to, where is it?
It's over here.
Let's write it out.
It's equal to phi plus theta
bar psi plus psi bar theta.
Okay.
So I have phi bar theta
plus d times theta bar theta.
Do I have it right?
Yeah.
Okay.
Now I want to square it.
The best way to square a thing
is to write down another version of it.
And,
Okay.
Let's, phi squared.
Phi times phi.
Which is just phi squared.
I wrote it as phi times phi.
Just phi squared.
All right.
So let's see what it contains.
Well, it will contain the bosonic
variable phi squared, the ordinary number squared.
Okay.
Then it will contain phi, it will contain a
term with theta bar plus theta bar times phi psi.
Then it will contain plus a
theta term, phi psi bar theta.
And now last from this term, it
will contain phi d theta bar theta.
Right?
That's the first term I
get when I multiply this through.
Now, next one.
Multiply this by this.
And what will we get?
We will get theta bar phi psi.
In other words, I'll just get this times this
is the same as this one times that one.
Is that right?
Yeah.
That one again.
Now I will get this times this.
That will give me theta bar.
And then I will get phi bar theta.
That will give me, let's put it over here.
Theta bar psi psi bar theta.
That's this times this.
And what about the last term over here?
Zero.
Because it contains theta bar times theta bar.
Now, next.
We have this times this.
That looks exactly like this here.
That's plus phi psi bar theta.
This one times this one.
Then we have psi bar theta
plus psi bar theta theta bar psi.
That's this one times this one.
This product gives zero to thetas.
And this one also gives zero.
And there's only one more term.
The last term is plus d.
No.
Yeah.
It's only one last term.
It's d times phi times theta bar theta.
That's it.
All the other terms are zero.
There's nothing else besides that.
And now we can add them up.
This combines with this to give a factor of two.
This combines with this to give a factor of three.
And then we have all these
last terms here with theta bar theta.
Let's see what there is.
There is phi times d and d times phi.
Phi and d commute with each other.
So there's just a factor of two.
Phi, d, theta bar theta.
Get rid of this.
And here we have another theta bar theta.
Let's bring this theta bar theta through
here, past here, and then past here.
Do I actually have the signs right?
I can't tell.
I do not know.
If it's worked out, this one should
have the same sign as this one.
So let's bring theta bar through.
If I bring theta bar through
two variables, it doesn't change signs.
So this will be plus theta bar theta.
Oh, I know what to do.
Yeah, I want to mind.
Now I'm going to.
I always like, for reasons that have nothing to do with
anything, I always like to keep the bars on the left.
And it's just a way
of keeping a mnemonic for me.
So I always like to
put the bars to the left.
So if I put the bar on
the left here, that will change the sign.
All right, that looks nice now.
Now I believe that.
Now what about this one over here?
All I want to do is bring psi through, so
it's over here, but then shift theta and theta bar.
That's going to give another sign.
It's just going to give twice this.
Okay.
Here's phi squared.
Now what do I want to do with phi squared?
It might be a thing that I
would want to put in a Lagrangian.
Why not?
It's a perfectly good super field, phi squared.
And I told you before that we're going to build up our Lagrangian or
our super Lagrangian out of powers of phi, derivatives of phi, and so forth.
All right, so this might
be a thing in a Lagrangian.
What would I do with it then?
In other words, it could be part of lambda.
Maybe not the whole thing, but part of lambda.
Good.
It's part of lambda.
What do I do with it?
I integrate it.
I integrate it, d theta, d
theta bar, to find the ordinary Lagrangian.
In other words, I pick out the last term.
Remember, integrating over theta and theta bar is just picking out
the last term, the last term which contains theta and theta bar.
All this work just to pick out the last term.
Just to pick out the last term here.
So if I put this into the Lagrangian, what it would give me
would just be twice phi d minus, I guess, twice psi bar psi.
That would go into a Lagrangian
that would be guaranteed to be supersymmetric
because it was built up out of...
a superfield which had a characteristic
distinct transformation under the supersymmetry transformations.
All right, so this is
the way you build up Lagrangians.
Now, this is not a very interesting Lagrangian.
It...
What does it have?
Phi times d.
We don't know what d is.
And psi bar psi.
It has no time derivatives.
Hasn't got any time derivatives.
We'd like to put in something like a kinetic term
to get some time derivatives.
So what we have to know
is how to build derivatives of superfields.
How to build derivatives of superfields.
You might think, well, just time differentiate them.
That's not the right way.
Because when you time differentiate a superfield,
you don't get another superfield.
So you have to be more careful in that.
Are you getting exhausted?
No.
I'm not.
Are you getting exhausted?
No.
Really?
I am.
Okay, so we have to know now how...
We've figured out how to build powers of superfields.
Incidentally, there would be nothing to stop us
from writing phi cubed or
phi fourth or phi anything else.
It's a little exercise.
Take phi cubed and pick out the last term.
See what you get.
What you're going to get is
various things with phi squared d.
You're going to get things
with psi bar psi times phi.
But it's an interesting exercise
to try, in fact, to
take phi to the nth power.
Phi to the nth power
and see what the last term is.
There's a rule, and the rule...
I'll let you try to work it out.
For the nth power.
We don't want to compute the whole nth power.
All we want to do
is pull out the last term,
the theta bar theta term,
and that'll be a term, an interesting term,
candidate for a term in Lagrangian.
Okay, now.
What about derivatives?
Derivatives are subtle.
I want to define a...
a constraint.
A constraint on a superfield
which preserves the fact that it's supersymmetric,
that it has supersymmetry.
I'll tell you what I'm thinking about.
Let's suppose we were talking about ordinary space.
Ordinary space, we might have two coordinates.
x and y.
I'm interested in...
I'm thinking to myself,
I really don't have a field
which is a function of two coordinates.
I really have a field which
is a function of only one coordinate
or one combination of the coordinates.
For example, it might be a function
only of x squared plus y squared,
or it might be only a function of x,
or it might only be a function of y.
In other words, it might satisfy some rule
such as the derivative of the function,
or the field, whatever it is,
with respect to y squared,
where y is equal to zero.
Now that's a kind of stupid thing.
It says that f is only a function of x.
Why did I introduce a
y dependence in the first place?
Well, never mind, but I might be interested in fields
which only depend on y.
Now, supposing the theory that I was considering
was rotationally invariant.
Would it make sense to say,
let me only choose those functions of y...
Sorry.
Let me only choose those functions of position
as possible fields which are independent of y?
Of course not, because if
a theory is rotationally invariant,
a thing which only depends
on x when you rotate it
will suddenly have some y dependence.
So this would not be a rotationally invariant constraint.
It would not make sense to say,
let's only think of fields
which satisfy the derivative of f with
respect to y is equal to zero.
Why not?
Because it can't be rotationally invariant.
And if the physics we're
trying to imagine is rotationally invariant,
that's one way of saying it.
Another way of saying it is,
if I apply this constraint,
let's give a name to this.
Let's call fields which satisfy this constraint,
let's call them...
What shall I call them?
Magic fields.
Okay.
These are magic fields here.
Now...
Or f is a magic field.
If...
If f satisfy this, by definition it's a magic field.
Okay.
Now, let's rotate coordinates.
In other words, let's apply a rotation
in the form of an
infinitesimal generator, for example, to f.
We rotate f by acting with
the angular rotation generators, L, on f.
That just corresponds to a rotation, a
small rotation of f, whatever it is.
Is L times f still...
Is rotating the field still a magic field?
Is the result of rotating the field...
In other words, what we're doing actually
is writing a small change in f,
we're writing a...
Rotate the field.
The change in f is equal to,
I suppose, I times L times f,
where L is the angular momentum generator
of some kind of derivative, just a
derivative which rotates things a little bit.
All right.
Will delta f also be a magic field?
No, it won't.
And the reason is,
if you take a thing which doesn't depend on y,
but does depend on x,
and rotate it,
it no longer satisfies that same constraint.
Now, what's a way of doing this mathematically?
We'll do the...
Let's call this constraint...
Let's call it d.
d for derivative with respect to y.
Let's just call it dy equals 0.
This defines being magic.
All right.
Let's ask whether f plus delta f is magic.
So the question is whether
d is also equal to 0.
Well, delta f is just proportional...
d times f, that's 0, by definition.
f is magic.
All right.
But what about d times delta f?
Well, d times f is proportional to f,
and delta f is proportional to l times f.
Is that magic?
Well, there would be one thing which would assure
that l times f was still magic.
It would be that l commutes with d.
Supposing l commuted with d,
then we would say this was l d f,
and we've already assumed that d times f
was a derivative along the y axis.
The only problem here is that it's just not true
that d commutes with l.
l is a rotation, is a generator of rotation.
d is a derivative along the y axis.
And when you rotate or when you commute,
what do you get when you commute
a derivative with respect to y with a rotation?
Do you know?
No.
A derivative with respect to x.
Remember what these, what an l is.
An l is an infinitesimal rotation.
What does it do?
It rotates the components of vectors.
All right.
It rotates the x component of vector
into a y component of vector.
If you commute the rotation generator
with the translation generator,
you just get the rotation generator
in the other direction.
That's what you get.
So these don't commute.
But the test, the test for whether a constraint,
here's the question,
is a constraint like this consistent with a symmetry?
Is imposing a constraint on a field
consistent with a symmetry?
It's consistent with a symmetry
when the constraint commutes
with the symmetry generators.
That's the test.
Does the constraint commute
with the symmetry generators?
No.
Okay.
So let's now ask.
Does the symmetry generators,
in the case we're interested in,
are the q's?
Where did the q's go?
The q's have gone off the blackboard somewheres.
Have them where?
On the bottom of the board.
Yeah.
Okay.
Right.
We have the q's.
They're in the blackboard space.
For example, q, I think,
is equal to d by d theta plus,
did we say, i theta bar d by dt?
Yeah.
And q bar is equal to d theta bar
plus i theta d by dt.
Okay.
Let's see if we can build up
some kind of derivative.
I'm just going to tell you the answer.
It's a very simple answer.
For a derivative,
and I'm going to call it capital D,
just call it capital D,
it's going to start with d by d theta.
It's basically derivative with respect to theta,
but not quite,
because d by d theta
does not commute
with q bar.
d by d theta does not commute with,
sorry, it does not commute with this term here,
or anticommute, anticommute.
We're interested in asking
whether we can find a d
which anticommutes with q and q bar.
That's the analog of commuting
with, in ordinary algebra.
Is there a d
which is a kind of derivative
with respect to theta,
but which has the property that it commutes
with both q and q bar?
If it does,
then it's a candidate
for something
which allows us to define a constraint
which is invariant under the q's and q bars.
Okay, so does d by d
theta commute with q and q bar?
No, it doesn't commute with this term here.
Can I add anything to it to make it commute?
Well, the natural thing to try to add to it
is something like appears here.
Well, let's try.
Plus i theta bar d by dt.
Uh-uh, that's not going to work
because we know this is just q,
and q doesn't anticommute with q bar.
But what happens if I put a minus sign here?
I'll let you work it out.
The answer is it commutes with both of these.
I think you checked that.
Isn't that what you had checked?
Yeah, that was the problem.
That was the problem, right.
I had misidentified one of these
and called it this.
Yeah, it's a nice check
to prove that this d anticommutes
with both q and q bar.
So does d bar.
It's particularly useful
that we establish
that the commutator,
the commutator of theta with d by d theta...
The anticommutator.
The...
Yes, the anticommutator of theta...
The anticommutator is...
What was it?
One.
Yeah.
Okay.
Yes.
Yeah.
Okay.
Let's look and see whether this commutes with q.
Does d commute with q?
Well, d by d theta commutes
with d by d theta...
Anti-commutes!
When I say commutes,
I mean anticommutes.
d by d theta anticommutes
with d by d theta.
with theta bar.
All right.
Theta bar anticommutes with theta,
and theta bar anticommutes
with theta bar.
So this one anticommutes
with this one trivially.
That's trivial.
But now we have to check,
does this anticommute
with q bar?
And that's a little
non-trivial, you have an anti-commutator from here, d
by d theta with theta, but then you
also have an anti-commutator from here, and
they cancel. They cancel. So whatever d and
d bar are, they commute with both q and
q bar. What does that mean? That means that
the constraint, that if I say let's
consider superfields which have the property that d
bar, I don't, not both of them, both of
them is too strong a constraint, that d bar on
the superfield is equal to zero. This says
that in some way the field is constrained
when you differentiate it with this kind
of derivative here, it doesn't change. That's
a constraint. First question, supposing we
change phi by a supersymmetry transformation,
delta phi contains things like q phi and q
bar phi, it contains things like q phi and
q bar phi.
Is the change in the superfields, the change
in the superfields, the change in the superfields,
the change in phi, does it also satisfy
this constraint? And the answer is yes. Let's see
why. If we assume that d bar on phi is
equal to zero, then let's try to find out whether
d bar q phi, is that equal to zero? We've
made a little shift in phi by applying q to
it, and now we want to, let's call, let's
call it a little shift in phi, and now we
want to, let's call it a little shift in
phi. Let's say that if d bar phi is equal
to zero, we could give it the name magic,
but it actually has a name. It's called chiral.
A superfield which satisfies this constraint is
called a chiral superfield. It's the analog
of the magic constraint that we talked about
before. But let's find out, is this magic
constraint or chiral constraint, is it something
that survives after you make a little supersymmetry
transformation?
If not, then what?
If not, then we throw away this constraint.
All right, so let's see whether d bar, whether
q times phi is magic or chiral. Well, the answer
is easy. If d bar phi is equal to zero,
and if q anticommutes with d bar, which we
proved over here, we can rewrite this as minus
q d bar phi.
So d bar phi is equal to zero, because we
assumed that d bar times phi is equal to zero.
So if phi is chiral, then the small shift
of it, when you rotate it or when you shift
it by the supersymmetry transformation, is still
chiral. Well, that's a good sign. It
says, what it says, basically, is that this
is an invariant thing to impose. It's invariant,
but it's not a super-symmetric thing.
So what does that mean? Well, it's
invariant, but it's not a super-symmetric thing. It's
invariant, but it's not a super-symmetric thing.
It's invariant, but it's not a super-symmetric
thing.
It's invariant, but it's not a super-symmetric thing.
It's invariant, but it's not under anything
you can think of but under the supersymmetry
transformations.
Imposing this on a field is an allowable
thing to do. Supersymmetry doesn't get in your way.
It doesn't, a supersymmetric transformation
on q doesn't violate this constraint.
That's the fact.
OK, so there we are.
That is the notion of a chiral superfield.
OK.
Thank you.
we are plunging deep into the morass.
We're going to do it.
We're going to go for the whole thing.
Okay.
So let's consider then a chiral superfield
that satisfies d bar equals zero.
That turns out to say something,
well, let's see, how should we do this?
Okay.
There's an easy way to construct
phi's which satisfy this constraint here.
It's kind of neat.
I'll show you how it works.
Supposing this was just d by d theta bar
on phi is equal to zero.
It's not.
But supposing it only contained this term here,
was equal to zero.
What would that say?
That would just say that phi
is integral to d by d theta bar
independent of theta bar.
It would say that phi has the form
phi plus theta times,
let's call it,
theta times,
psi bar times theta.
But then nothing else
because everything else would have theta bars.
So if d by d theta
bar on phi was equal to zero,
it would be an enormous simplification of the superfield,
it would say it contains only two terms,
a phi and a psi bar times theta,
nothing else.
Okay.
But that's not what we're doing.
That's not what we're doing.
This d bar is more complicated.
But nevertheless,
this is almost right.
So let me tell you what's right.
You write that phi is equal,
not t,
but let's call it tau.
And theta.
That is swelling away,
unless it's grown over to the top.
O has nothing to do with it.
It's just got to be,
not all it has to do
is grow with that current here.
But essentially it often just wants to go away,
because if you want to go back,
you want to solve次,
you just want to use ifs and elsevs.
This plus,
plus equal to,
are called p of theta.
Okay.
You can pull out XB,
you have to squeeze them together.
You can't pull them together,
because that just now,
you're marca cheque,
to do, shift time by an amount i theta
bar theta, and write that a field only depends
on tau and theta. This is like saying
that the field only depended on one combination
of coordinates. It only depends on tau, which is
t plus i theta bar theta, and theta, but
not theta bar separately. It only depends
on theta bar through this combination. Let's
prove, let's prove that any field of this type,
in other words it's a phi of t plus
i theta bar theta and theta. Let's
prove that it satisfies this relationship here. Well,
d bar
Sorry, this relationship. d bar is i d by
d theta bar. Okay? Where do we, it starts
with d by d theta bar, and then it has a
minus i theta d by dt. What happens when you differentiate
this with respect to theta bar? Differentiating this
with respect to theta bar gives us, the
only place we see theta
bar is together with t here.
So that gives us plus i theta bar theta
bar theta bar theta bar theta bar theta bar theta
2 plus i, I think it's minus i theta
d phi by dt. When you differentiate with respect
to theta, to theta bar here it's
equivalent to differentiating with respect to time, and
then multiplying by i theta. That's the derivative
with respect to theta bar. Now, what about
the derivative with respect to time?
that also gives you a time derivative
and also multiplies by theta but with
the opposite sign. So any function of
this form here which only depends on
theta bar in the special way here satisfies
d bar on it is equal to zero.
It's another way, saying d bar is equal
to zero is another way of saying that
phi only depends on theta bar in
this very very special way. Well that
then solves our problem. We can start
with any phi which only depends on tau
and theta and then later on just
remember that tau is the shifted value
of time. So what is this?
This is phi of t plus
psi of tau plus psi bar of tau
theta and nothing more. We just have to
remember that t is not tau, that we have
to shift tau a little bit. This is getting
a little bit more complicated. So
we can start with this one.
Is that the only formulation that satisfies the constraint?
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay, so this is the form of a chiral
super field. Now let's work it out in detail.
Let's work it out in its full
ugly glory. In its full ugly glory,
we have a super field.
Let's just remember what tau is. Tau
is t plus i theta bar theta.
Alright, let's start with this one over here. That
starts out as phi of t, but then we shift
theta theta bar a little bit, so we have to
put in plus i theta bar theta times phi dot.
We're just doing a Taylor expansion in this shift
here. We've shifted by amount i theta bar theta,
so that's phi plus i theta bar theta times
phi dot. And then what would be the next term?
The next term, I guess, would be one half
i squared, which is minus one half, theta bar...
You're expanding out the phi of tau?
Hmm?
You're expanding out the phi of tau plus the...
Yeah, I'm... This is phi of...
The phi of tau.
Oh boy.
You're substituting tau.
Yeah, yeah, I'm just substituting... Yeah, I want to
substitute in here tau plus i theta bar theta.
They gave you the first two terms.
Hmm?
They gave you the first two terms, right?
Yeah.
And then I can just...
Then there's no higher term, because theta bar theta squared
is zero. Theta bar theta times theta bar theta is zero.
I guess that's true. I guess that's true.
And then we have plus
psi bar of t times theta,
but then we also have to differentiate
psi bar plus psi bar dot of t,
times theta bar theta theta, but that's zero.
Theta bar theta times theta is zero, so that's zero.
That's the whole thing.
A chiral superfield is just a phi and a psi combined together, plus an
extra term here, which has theta bar theta in it, coming from this shift.
That's all a chiral superfield is.
Now, it seems like a very heavy machinery.
Uh...
To do some fairly simple things,
this is what the chiral superfield is.
What can we do with it?
Well, basically, we can square it or multiply it
by its complex conjugate and use it in a Lagrangian.
Let's see what kind of things would happen if
we squared it and put it into a Lagrangian.
So we want to... square it
means multiply it by its complex conjugate.
In other words, uh...
We have d bar phi equals zero.
Here's phi.
Let's multiply it by its complex conjugate.
That will make another chiral superfield.
Multiply them together, and then integrate
them with d theta d theta bar.
So I think all we have to do
is write this down next to its complex conjugate.
So, phi star of t, if phi is complex, typically now
phi is complex, plus i theta bar theta times phi star dot,
then plus psi of t theta bar.
On a middle term, wouldn't you do theta theta bar?
Could you do it in the conjugate?
Maybe.
Um...
I'm really too tired to figure it out now.
And I'm not recognizing it, frankly.
It doesn't look right.
Um...
I think I'm going to have
to stop here and repair my notes.
Uh...
d phi times...
Can you tell us the punchline yet?
Yeah.
The punchline is if you do it right, and you
take d phi and d bar phi, multiply them together,
and integrate them over theta and
theta bar, you will get this Lagrangian.
That's the punchline.
Yeah.
Uh...
But I think I better do it over next time.
This is more than one lecture's
worth, and I've run out of steam.
The point is...
Let's say what the point is.
The point is to build supersymmetric Lagrangians.
Lagrangians...
What is a supersymmetric Lagrangian?
It's one which has this fantastic symmetry
that you can replace bosons by fermions,
and that in fact means that it guarantees that fermions
and bosons come in matched multiplets with exactly the same mass,
and will do exactly these things which we
required of a Lagrangian which will cancel all, uh...
No.
If it comes in matched fermion-boson pairs, then
you can prove all sorts of things, such as...
the fact that the bosons don't get any self-energy.
Why not?
Because the fermions don't get any divergent self-energy.
Don't get any divergent self-energy.
You can prove all sorts of things, uh...
that are rather magical and mysterious, coming
from the symmetry between fermions and bosons.
But in particular, you can
prove to all orders, no, uh...
No, you know, no statement,
this is true for free-field theory,
to all orders in everything,
perturbation theory, non-perturbative, the whole works,
you can prove that if the Lagrangian is supersymmetric,
uh, that there are exact cancellations to all orders,
which make sure that these divergences don't happen.
That's the, that's the punchline, and, uh, I feel like
I've been punched around a little bit too much today.
Two hours of teaching this morning and an hour and
a half of supersymmetry is more than I can deal with.
I'm sorry.
Any questions?
Yeah, good.
How do you spell Chiral?
Chiral, Chiral, C-H-I-R-A-L.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, Chiral, wipe your hand, Chiral.
Hand you this.
Has someone done all this bypassing the Lagrangian
and just going directly to the Feynman rules?
Yeah.
You can derive Feynman rules from,
no, no, you can, can you, well...
No.
The way you get Feynman rules is from a Lagrangian.
Could I tell you what the Feynman rules are?
Sure, but they wouldn't be very interesting.
The inter, look, the interesting thing is here
is that this is a generalization of space-time.
What's interesting here is, uh, that
this is generalizing our ideas of space-time.
It's adding coordinates of space-time.
What do you want the Feynman diagrams for?
You're going to go and
do, have Feynman diagram calculations?
You're going to go and go up to Slack and
say, I'm here, I'm going to do all the Feynman
diagram calculations you want?
There are people who can do that, and they
can do it a lot better than you or me.
Um, what's really interesting here is
that this is a generalization of space-time.
Here, it's just time, a generalization
of time and new coordinates of space.
It's going to be a new generalization of
space-time, a new generalization of the symmetries of
space-time that will generalize a special theory of
relativity to a theory which mixes up the
x's with a bunch of thetas.
That's what's really interesting about it.
It's not just any old set of Feynman diagrams.
It's one which comes out of a
deep, presumably very, very deep, um, space-time symmetry,
generalization of space-time symmetry.
So, why would I want
to give you the Feynman diagrams?
What would you do with them?
Uh, I just sometimes think that
they're more fundamental than the Lagrangian.
I don't think in this case.
No, I really don't think so.
Um, it's not so much the Lagrangian
as the, as the, as the symmetries.
The symmetries appear to be
really, really fundamental, a fundamental generalization
of coordination.
These are kind of rotations that sort of
rotate in a funny way time into anti-commuting
coordinates.
No, I don't think these Feynman
diagrams themselves will tell you very much.
They would be very dull.
I would tell you this coupling constant
has to equal this coupling constant, it would
not be interesting.
Um, and looking at the Feynman diagrams, you
would have no guarantee, just looking at the
Feynman diagrams, you would see no
guaranteed reason why all these perfect cancellations
take place.
You would have to work out diagram by
diagram and see that all the divergent contributions
to the self-energy of bosons cancel, and
it would just be a set of accidents.
Just as, it would be exactly the same as
if I gave you the Feynman rules for, well, I
gave you a set of Feynman rules
and you started calculating Feynman diagrams and discovered
to your amazement that the scattering amplitudes
were always Lorentz invariant, but you had
to go step by step by step by
step, each Feynman diagram, each order of perturbation theory,
you would start to ask, come on, there
must be some reason why these things are happening.
Why is it that the
scattering amplitudes are always the same?
Why is it that the scattering amplitudes are always
the same in any reference frame and so forth?
You would eventually come to the
conclusion that there were some Lorentz transformations,
that the theory was invariant under Lorentz transformations.
I could give you the Feynman diagrams of supersymmetry and
show you all the cancellations, and you would say, why?
I would go back and say, because the theory has
this kind of space-time symmetry, this generalization of space-time symmetry.
So, to me, that's what I'm saying.
That's what's interesting.
I'm not going to take this much further.
I'm going to show you one or two examples of super Lagrangians,
and then I'm going to tell you the implications for particle physics,
a little bit more about the implications for particle physics, which
are not much more than saying that there are all these cancellations
which take place, and there are the superpartners.
They should be there in the experiment.
In the experiment.
Not much more than that.
Yeah.
One of the nice things about this mathematics is
you have to worry about series expansion diverging to infinity.
Right.
Guaranteed.
That's right.
Right?
So you're going to do something similar to the
space coordinate as well as you've done with the time?
No.
What do you do with space coordinates?
And to expand things.
Euphoria transform.
That's a useful thing to do.
It's not particularly useful to
power series expand in coordinates.
It's just not a useful thing to do.
Fourier transform is more interesting, and
it gives you waves and so forth.
Here, power series expansion in the thetas
is the thing to do because it terminates.
The power series expansion in
terms of x's would not terminate.
So it would just be some arbitrary expansion.
If a supersymmetric particle shows up in the LHC, how would we recognize that
it's a supersymmetric particle and not just another particle we didn't know about before?
All of its couplings and its interactions with
the ordinary particles are determined by the supersymmetry.
All right?
So all of the terms in
the Lagrangian involve a much smaller number.
In particular, the interaction terms, the coupling terms, the
phi cubed, the phi fourths, the psi, psi, phi terms,
they're all governed by a smaller number
of coupling constants than what you might have.
In other words, there are
very detailed constraints among the parameters,
of the particles, that have to be respected.
So decay rates, cross sections, are all determined
in terms of a smaller number of constants
than the general theory that you would
write down of that same set of particles.
It'll be clear. It'll be clear that they're superpartners.
So the superpartners actually, the protons,
don't have the same mass, right?
That's right.
You know, we've been talking about the...
The superpartners having the same
mass with the permanent ones.
That we have to change.
And we don't expect them
to have the same mass, right?
So how does that complicate the theory?
A lot.
We have to talk about
the spontaneous breaking of supersymmetry.
And we have...
We have to talk about
spontaneous symmetry breaking of supersymmetry,
which itself is a hellishly complicated story.
Next lecture.
Hm?
Well, we'll see.
We'll talk about it a little bit.
Um...
No, it's an extremely involved story, and...
It's extremely frustrating.
For somebody who likes to teach
physics, and likes to explain physics,
this is incredibly frustrating.
It's frustrating because it's just, as I
said, it's just a bunch of formalism,
and index manipulation, and symbol manipulation,
and in the end, you...
In the end of the day,
even after you're finished with it,
you have to break the symmetry.
That involves a whole theory of its own.
And then you have to put it together with gravity.
It's enormously complicated.
Enormously complicated.
And, um...
I find it extremely frustrating.
Very, very frustrating that...
something which seems very, very simple,
the idea of a symmetry between fermions and bosons,
becomes so complicated so
quickly that it becomes unexplainable,
even to people who have learned all about quantum mechanics,
learned a bit about quantum field theory,
learned about relativity,
and still, to go through this stuff,
would...
It really takes a quarter of...
Not a quarter of this class,
but a quarter of a...
of a...
twice a week supersymmetry class to go through this.
And even then, it wouldn't be finished.
So it's a big subject, and it's a difficult subject,
and it's a technical subject,
and yet, at some level,
it's probably saying something very simple.
And we don't know what it is.
Are there any layers of abstraction
that keeps piling on and on,
or does it just keep going?
So far, no.
So far, this has reached the point of abstraction
where I think it becomes unexplainable,
except to those initiates,
people who have initiated themselves,
by going through...
You know how you learn the subject?
You learn the subject by going through detail by detail
by detail by detail,
and doing it over and over again
until it becomes second nature.
And everybody I know who has learned it
has complained bitterly about having to go through detail...
You don't go through details like that
when you're learning general relativity.
You don't go through details of index, you know,
index and keeping track of signs
and keeping track of details.
The way this subject was learned
by the people who learned it
was by going through the details
over and over and over again,
and it's extremely tedious.
Extremely tedious.
What is it saying?
I think it's saying,
look, there was no guarantee that
the rules of nature wouldn't be tedious,
that they wouldn't be tedious having
to keep track of detail and detail.
It's just what we impose on what we would like
when we say that a
theory should be simple and comprehensible
and composed out of pieces that we can understand,
and that's what we're trying to do.
Instead it's saying it's not very complicated,
there's some simple rules,
but to follow through on the simple rules,
to follow through on the simple rules,
to use them, to construct them,
is just an exercise in the
frustration of enormous amounts of tedium.
The people who did this work
really did immerse themselves
in a kind of
detailed tedium until they got good at it.
Once they got good at
it, they could look at it
and do it much easier than I can.
I'm not good at it.
Can you infer something about
the structure of fermions and bosons
through these transformations
that dictates their activities?
What do you mean by their structure?
Well, the fermions and the bosons,
they interact quite differently with each other.
But we're seeing in this theory that they are swabbing.
You have the fermion and boson pair
that are somewhat the same thing,
in some regards just two
different sides of the same thing.
Well, they're images of
each other under these transformations.
So does that tell us
something about what the differences are,
the characteristics of...
the fermion and the boson?
Does it help for me to say
that a fermion is what you get
when you take a boson
and act with the generator Q?
No.
Well, does it? I don't know.
In some sense, to go from a fermion to boson
is the process of shifting theta a little bit.
The shift in theta from one...
You can't really speak about the values of theta.
They don't take on values in the usual sense.
But this shift operation,
which shifts theta a little bit
and at the same time does this over here,
that is the operation which takes
you from a fermion to a boson.
So it's a little motion in this super space.
A little motion, roughly speaking,
from one point of super space
to another point of super space
takes you from fermion to boson.
It is analogous to
the way rotation of coordinates
will take the X component of a
vector to a Y component of a vector.
Right?
The X and Y components of
vectors you can visualize in your head.
The fermions and bosons can be...
are often called components of a super field.
That super field up there,
the phi, the psi, the psi bar and the D
are the components of the super field.
They're called the components of the super field.
And the supersymmetry transformation sort
of mixes one into the other,
takes one into the other.
In particular, it always takes a phi to a psi
and a psi to a combination of phi and D.
So it just is a motion in the super space
which takes a fermion to a boson.
Can you picture it?
Can I say what that means about these particles
in any language that you can understand?
No.
The language is not English.
The language is Grassmann variables and...
and...
This is why you don't...
you...
um...
I was going to say this is why
we don't teach it in courses like this.
But there are no other
courses like this, so I think...
But this is why I have hesitated
and sort of worked around it and avoided it.
But you asked for it.
All right?
So I'm not going to stop until...
until it's finished.
And, uh...
String theory is not as bad as this, incidentally.
String theory is...
is much easier to understand.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.