Stanford University
Alright, so let me just tell you a
little bit about the origins of string theory.
The origins of string theory really were in hadron physics.
They did not have to do with quantum gravity.
They had to do with
protons, neutrons, mesons, particularly mesons.
In fact, the theory was put forward at a
time when it really wasn't even known that for sure,
it was suspected, but it wasn't known for
sure that protons and neutrons, mesons and so forth,
had a quark content to them.
It was suspected that a
meson was a pair of quarks.
The idea of gluons did not yet exist.
The idea of gluons...
Well, and...
Well, in fact, it actually did.
But nobody paid too much attention to it.
Nembou had postulated something like it.
But gluons were not part of the standard discussion
of hadrons in, let's say, around 1969, 1968, 1970.
What was part of standard
hadron physics was an interesting fact
that the number of particles...
The number of particle states was large.
There was the proton and the neutron, of course.
I'm not interested in the
difference between proton and neutron.
Just think of them as one thing, the nucleon.
And then there was another particle which
was very similar to the proton and neutron,
had a little more spin
and a little bit heavier mass.
And then there was another one above that with a
little bit heavier mass and a little bit larger spin.
People drew pictures, diagrams.
They were called Choufrouchi plots.
Plots, not plots.
Plots, plots, plots.
And they were diagrams which indicated the
spectrum of objects like a proton, for example.
And they plotted horizontally here...
Let's see.
They plotted vertically angular momentum and
horizontally the square of the mass.
Who decided to put the square of
the mass there instead of the mass?
Nobody.
The diagrams had a nicer look
to them if you plotted mass squared.
And what was discovered experimentally...
This is an experimental fact...
I'm getting my P's and my F's screwed up today.
An experimental fact that the spectrum of particles...
Okay, let's start with the proton.
That has half a unit of
spin and a mass of one.
Okay.
And a mass of one in certain units, namely the
unit in which the mass of the proton is one.
That's approximately one GeV.
Incidentally, at that time, the GeV didn't exist.
It was the BeV for billion.
Now it's giga.
Okay.
And so the proton and the neutron were over here.
A mass of one, mass squared of
one, and an angular momentum of a half.
Then there's another particle
with angular momentum three halves.
These were fermions, and so their
angular momentum was quantized in half integers.
And so there was another one up
here with a little bit bigger mass.
Another one, another one, and another one.
And rather remarkably, these particles
all formed a straight line.
A straight line in the plot of L versus M.
Now I should tell you, when
Chu and Frouchi first put this forward,
the logic of drawing a straight line,
there were only two points on this plot.
And they thought it was a theorem that through
any two points, you could draw a straight line.
Well, it is a theorem, but
these guys were not the smartest.
Well, they were pretty smart, but they...
And so they said, oh, there's two points.
Let's draw a straight line through them.
And miraculously, as experiment went on, the
additional particles all landed on the same line.
In M squared.
In M squared, yes, they actually said in M squared.
They plotted it as a function of M squared and
L, and said, two points, let's draw a straight line.
And that worked out just fine.
But I mean, that explains why M squared is the axis
there, because they're hypothesizing L is proportional to M squared somehow.
They were.
Why did they postulate that?
Because L is proportional to M.
They were lucky.
They were lucky, or else they had some deep...
No, it wasn't entirely luck, and it wasn't
entirely, and it wasn't a stupid guess either.
There were some interesting reasons for it.
But the same pattern held true for all hadrons, or
at least for all hadrons that have been studied in detail.
For example, the pi meson.
The pi meson also exists on a trajectory.
These are known as Regge trajectories,
R-E-G-G-E, for the Italian physicist Tullio Regge.
They're called Regge trajectories.
And if you plotted the meson spectrum, the meson
spectrum, mesons are bosons, so the angular momenta were integers.
For example, the pi meson has almost zero mass.
Its mass squared is even smaller than its mass.
It's true.
In units of a GeV.
Alright, so the pi meson was
almost massless with almost zero angular momentum.
And then there's the next one
up, I forget what it's called.
I don't remember what the next one is called.
I used to know, but I don't remember anymore.
The next one up, and the next one
up, and five, six, seven particles along a trajectory.
Like that.
The rho meson, which was another
meson, which starts with angular momentum one.
Also same pattern.
And what's more, all of these
trajectories were parallel to each other.
They were parallel to each other, which said, whatever this
M squared thing is, it takes exactly the same energy.
Well, not exactly, but approximately the
same energy to increase the M squared
by when you, to increase M
squared when you increase the angular momentum.
In other words, the spectrum was quantized.
Of course it was quantized.
These were particles, and this is quantum mechanics.
The spectrum was quantized, but in each case,
the same relationship between L and M squared
and the same quantum jump in M
squared when you increased L by one unit.
One unit now means in
units of Planck's constant, of course.
Okay.
So there's something going on that was giving rise to
large numbers of particles of higher and higher angular momentum.
Higher angular momentum is not that uncommon.
You take a basketball.
You leave it at rest.
That basketball has a certain energy and therefore
a certain mass, and you could plot it someplace.
And now you spin the basketball.
Give it one unit of Planck's angular momentum.
That's not easy to do, incidentally.
But when it has some
angular momentum, it will be rotating.
It will have some rotational energy.
So if you increase its angular momentum by one unit,
you will have to increase its energy by a little bit.
Tiny, tiny bit for a basketball.
And you can keep increasing
the angular momentum of the basketball.
As you do so, the energy will increase.
In fact, it will not look like a straight line.
It will look like a curve.
And it will end somewheres.
Why does the curve end?
The curve ends simply because at some angular velocity, the centrifugal
forces are so large that the basketball will just be torn apart.
So it ends someplace at some high
angular momentum, which represents the strength of materials.
How strong is whatever basketballs are made out of.
So trajectories like that were not unusual.
You can plot them for atoms.
Atoms also have the property that as you increase
their angular momentum, you increase their energy, their mass.
Energy and mass being the same thing.
But again, for an atom, there's only so much
mass you can give it before you ionize the atom.
So what was unusual, particularly unusual, and again,
incidentally, factually, I'm not going to go into that.
But what was unusual, particularly unusual, and again,
And again, incidentally, for atoms,
they would not be straight lines.
But what was unusual here was the simplicity
of the formula or the simplicity of the observation.
Rather straight lines.
I mean they were all
straight and parallel to each other.
And...
When you say parallel, I mean, how do you mean?
I mean that if you were to plot the
meson, or the baryon, or the proton, or the neutron,
I mean, how do you mean...
the limazon or the romezon, its
excited states would form the same line.
In other words, you take a set of
particles, a family of particles, same slope, same slope,
and it was called the universal regeslope.
Same for bosons and fermions, same
for different families of bosons and fermions.
Now this is strictly for those objects which
are hadrons, those things made up out of quarks
and gluons, which we now today recognize
as being made up of quarks and gluons.
That was one observation.
The implication of this observation was fairly
clear, even though it was misinterpreted at
the time in many quarters.
It was fairly clear.
It said that hadrons were composite.
That you could spin them up.
This is not something you can do with an electron.
There is no excited state of an electron
with higher angular momentum, at least not within
current experimental bounds.
So electrons are like points.
You can't spin a point.
Spinning a point doesn't mean anything.
Turning a point, you can spin a lump.
So somehow these objects were not simple point particles.
That was the message that should have been,
and in many quarters was taken from this.
And in fact that they had a stretchability
that from this picture you could deduce if
you wanted, and we will, we will, you could
deduce the fact that they deform as they spin.
You wouldn't, it's not obvious from here, but you can.
All right, but there was something else.
There was another observation, which
was a very bizarre observation.
Let's see.
Let me describe it to
you in terms of meson-meson scattering.
Let's take meson-meson, and for
particular let's take pi-meson, pi-meson scattering.
Here's a pion coming in.
A pi-meson, let's call it pi.
It doesn't matter whether
it's pi-plus, pi-minus, doesn't matter.
And it scatters off another pi-meson.
There is a particle called the romezon,
which, while it's not a composite, it's a
composite of two pi-mesons.
Two pi-mesons can come together at a vertex
in a Feynman diagram and make a romezon.
Let's make the romezon like that.
We're going to talk, we may or
may not talk more about these mesons.
It's not important, the idea is important,
but the particular names are not important.
Romezon.
And then that pi-meson could, then that romezon
could materialize as a pair of pi-mesons again,
this being a Feynman diagram.
A conventional Feynman diagram.
And it would govern the
properties of pion-pion scattering probabilities.
That was the first thing.
Now, these are all pions here.
Any quantum field theorist would immediately tell
you, if you have this diagram here, where
the two pions come in this way and make
a romezon and then go off as two pions, there
will be another diagram.
Which looks like this.
It's just the same diagram turned on its
side, where a romezon is exchanged between two pi-mesons.
In this case, a romezon jumps from here
to here, and this, without the pions ever annihilating.
But this is just the same diagram turned on
its side, and if one exists, the other has
to exist.
That's a consequence of principles of quantum field theory.
So, that's something that everybody believed.
But then, once it was recognized that this
romezon was not a unique creature, but came
along with this whole family, this
whole regitrajectory of excited states, it became
clear that there was no reason
to only have a romezon in here.
So, you could add together all the various,
you could add, pi-mesons come in, form not
the romezon, but the next excited state of
the romezon, or the next excited state of
the romezon.
And so, actually, when you draw this diagram,
you're really committed to adding up the contribution
of all the mesons along here.
Likewise, here.
If you can exchange a romezon, you
can also exchange all the other mesons.
So, you can add up all the mesons.
What is the next excited state?
Well, there was something very, very
suspicious, very, very peculiar, when people numerically
went to do this.
They actually added up from known experimental
data the contributions of the romezon, the
rho prime meson, the rho double prime
meson, and so forth and so on.
They did that and they did the
same thing for the exchange of the romezon.
And they found something rather remarkable.
they found that to some approximation
the sum over all the Romezons going this way
gave rise to about the same thing
as the sum over all the Romezons
and its partners going in the opposite there
and the other channel it was called
in other words it appeared to be over counting
all you needed to represent the data and
all that you needed to represent the physics
of pi-pi scattering
was summing over rho, rho prime, rho double prime
in this annihilation process
annihilation and recreation process
and in fact you didn't need to add this in
because
this already seemed to contain it numerically numerically
on the other hand it was also
true that you could ignore this altogether
and add all this up
and again get the right answer get
something which looked pretty much like experimental
data
that was very peculiar any quantum field theory
would look at this and
say complete how rubbish you cave
you know if you have
this you have to add that
you have to add it
you don't get to say it's this or
this you get to say is this and this
okay
But, peculiarly, when you added up all these contributions
it simply gave you for free
the effects of another diagram
here
for that reason I another people began to draw diagrams
which looked not so
much like paletteattedMUSICI food unexpected
Feynman diagrams which looked more like this.
We didn't know what we were doing, we
were just saying, look, something's going on here.
First of all, we had
the idea that they were quarks.
Quarks were not a new idea.
And we said, what must be going on is
there must be a picture which looks something like this.
Replacing the Feynman diagram, this would be
a quark, this would be an anti-quark,
this would be a quark going this way,
an anti-quark going this way, and likewise over here.
We drew diagrams like that.
Now, it took some time for us to
think about filling in what goes on in here.
We just drew pictures like this,
and we said, look at this.
If you think about somehow what's going on has a
topology, let's call it a topology, which looks like this,
then look, if you cut it this way,
if you imagine something like this,
slicing it in an instant of
time, time is running upward, of course,
in all pictures, Feynman diagrams,
time we're allowing to run upward.
If you slice this right through the
middle, then you see something that looks like
a Feynman diagram in which two particles
come together and join and make another particle.
If we think of particles as pairs of quarks,
then
this figure here can represent a picture like this.
On the other hand, if we take
that same picture and slice it this way,
it looks like a picture
in which something is jumping across.
Slice it the other way, it looks like these two particles
produced a thing which jumped from this side to this side.
So this was kind of the origin of pictures.
One more ingredient was added.
It was just added for fun.
Just a curious question.
If there are these quarks,
what's holding those quarks together?
Well, maybe it's something in here.
These are space-time diagrams, of course.
Maybe something is bridging between the quarks.
And if so,
then when you slice through these diagrams,
then what you would see is
two quarks with something bridging between them.
And that something, of course, would
have the structure of something one-dimensional
connecting a quark and an anti-quark.
A string and a pair of quarks.
If you cut it the other way,
that same two-dimensional sheet here
could be sliced into a picture
where a string was exchanged from one side to another.
This was the very crude origins
of the idea of string theory.
In fact, it isn't exactly where
it came from, but it could have.
It did, to some extent.
Different people thought of it different ways.
So...
What's more,
what's more,
once a hadron is a string
with two quarks connected to it,
you can spin it.
Something you can't do to an electron.
You can spin it.
You can try to calculate,
with some assumptions, about the nature
of the material forming the string,
its elasticity, its various properties,
you can start asking how the energy of it,
what kind of energy is there, incidentally,
first of all is kinetic energy,
and second of all is stretching energy.
So with some kind of assumptions
about the nature of these strings,
or this material in here,
you can start asking questions
about how the energy increases
as a function of the angular momentum.
Surprisingly, with a relatively simple
assumption that we're going to do,
and we may get to it today,
I hope we get to it today,
we'll see that these pictures are
not as arbitrary as they might seem.
L versus m squared, or linear
function of L versus m squared,
is exactly what you need.
Now, I...
Yeah?
Why did you suggest that
it was something like a string,
something new, rather than a normal particle that changed
between the two quarks?
Well, this is not a particle exchange.
This is something that's sitting
at all the points of it
between the quarks.
This is...
If you were to slice it at an instant,
in other words, take a
look at it at an instant.
Here it is at an instant.
It consists of a quark, an anti-quark,
and a whole bunch of stuff in between.
Now, that bunch of stuff in between
might have been a collection of
particles that are forming a string,
you know, that are forming a string-like thing.
They might...
No prejudice about whether it was truly continuous
or whether it was just something
which was approximating something continuous in between.
But there was one thing that made you think
there might be something more fundamental about it
than just a shoelace.
And that was that, as far as we could tell,
these trajectories didn't end.
If you take a shoelace and
put a pair of golf balls
at the opposite ends of it and spin it around,
eventually you'll come to the point where it breaks.
And as far as could be told,
these rigid trajectories did not break.
So it seemed maybe that
there was something new going on.
Yeah?
Can the standard model accurately describe pylon scattering?
Uh...
To the extent...
that the standard model gives rise
to a string-like behavior,
it can.
Um...
Yeah, the standard model can describe a
great deal about pylon scattering these days.
Yeah.
Depending on the energy.
At very low energies,
the standard model has a
very good description of pylon scattering.
As the energy goes up,
where you start getting into the issues of these
particles being exchanged back and forth,
the standard model begins to get a
little bit more difficult to deal with,
and a string-like picture becomes more useful.
Yeah.
Did they know that the trajectory did not end?
No, of course not.
No.
But it didn't give any sign of giving out.
Uh...
So what that meant, what it appeared,
is this thing could be stretched more or less indefinitely
without much happening to it.
Uh...
We'll...
We'll come back to this point.
These are something entirely different
from the gluons, which, uh...
Well, in fact, they're not entirely different than gluons.
In some sense, they may be collections of gluons.
In fact, they have to be collections of gluons.
The present understanding of it
today is something like this,
that, um...
that the gluon field is like the metal.
The metal field is like the Maxwell field.
All right?
Uh...
The quarks...
You asked me about bar magnets.
Okay.
So the quarks are like poles of the, uh...
North pole and south pole of a bar magnet.
North pole, south pole.
You can't have monopoles.
The only way you can have
a north pole or a south pole
is to have it as
the end of a bar magnet.
Okay?
Or you could say it a different way.
You can have dipoles.
You could have magnetic fields which look like this.
Here it looks like...
There's a magnetic monopole, lines of flux spreading out.
Here it looks like there
are lines of flux spreading out.
And there might be some
reason why the lines of flux
form a narrow tube in between.
The current understanding of
the connection between
gluons and these strings goes something like this.
Quantum mechanically fields can be
described as either particles or fields.
Let's take the field description.
In the field description,
the gluon field
between two quarks,
a quark and an anti-quark,
would be like the field configuration between
a particle between a charge and an opposite charge.
It would look like this.
That's what the field between a positive
charge and a negative charge looks like.
The energy as you separate them
is the energy stored in the field in between.
Now for ordinary electrodynamics,
those field lines spread out,
and because they spread out,
the field diminishes in between them
as you separate the field,
as you separate the charge lines.
The field lines spread out,
the field diminishes in between,
and that's the usual pattern.
Our understanding today is that the non-linearities,
we've talked about this before,
but I'll just mention it again,
that the non-linearities
in quantum chromodynamics
have the effect of causing these field
lines to attract in a certain way,
and the effect of it is
that the field lines form strings
that look like that.
As you pull these apart,
the string doesn't spread this way,
it just gets longer and longer and longer.
That's our current understanding,
and if you like,
it's permissible to think of the string
as being made up out of gluons.
As you pull it apart,
it's not like a shoelace or a rubber band.
As you stretch a rubber band,
the number of molecules in it doesn't change.
The number of molecules in it,
and they just stretch,
and eventually, because the
number of molecules doesn't change,
eventually they get too far from each other,
and bang, the rubber band breaks.
But imagine a rubber band
in which as you stretched it,
every time there was a gap opening up between atoms,
a new atom was inserted in between.
In that case, you could imagine that
you could stretch this ad infinitum forever
without breaking it,
and that's the nature of the goal.
So, if you stretch the gluon
field between a quark and an anti-quark,
as you stretch it,
the energy of stretching goes
into creating more gluons in between.
And you can just stretch
the hell out of that system,
and it won't break.
Yeah?
Can you extend that analogy to say that
the string that makes up, say, an electron
is somehow composed of gluons as well?
It's composed of...
First of all, we don't know that string...
that electrons really are made of strings.
No.
This...
All of this physics was
taking place on a length scale
of the size of a proton.
This is an enormous length scale
by comparison with the scales of...
quantum gravity, which take place at the Planck length.
It's a more or less, perhaps accidental,
fact that the mathematics of
string theory has described both things.
They're quite different.
They occur at completely different length scales.
But through these considerations,
I, other people, began to work
out the mathematics of interacting strings.
Can you really quantify this?
Can you really make a theory of this?
I think that a theory of interacting strings,
which will give you all of
the physics of the interacting hadrons.
The answer at the time is, it looked promising.
It looked very promising.
In fact, it kept promising and promising and promising,
like string theory today.
Huge promise, but never quite did it right.
Okay?
For reasons that, in hindsight,
are fairly clear.
The precise mathematics that we were using
was not quite the right mathematics for studying hadrons.
It was the right mathematics for studying quantum gravity.
And so we kept getting, as
much as we didn't want it,
we kept getting particles in the
theory with zero mass and spin two.
What is that?
A graviton.
Nobody wanted a graviton.
This was a nuisance.
Go away, graviton.
We couldn't make it go away.
Nothing we could do could make it go away.
And eventually, some smart guy named
John Schwartz and Joel Schurk said,
wait a minute, wait a minute, maybe we're being dumb.
Maybe this is a theory of quantum
gravity and not a theory of hadrons.
Incidentally, string theory of hadrons has been put together
with the proper mathematics.
It does work, but it's a little bit different.
Okay, let's talk about...
Well, okay.
Before talking about strings, the mathematics of strings,
let's talk about
relativity versus non-relativistic kinematics.
Oh, incidentally, just a buzzword.
This two-dimensional structure in here,
which is, what is it?
It's replacing kinematics.
It's replacing the idea of a world line.
A world line is being replaced by a two-dimensional sheet.
Such a sheet, I think the
term actually goes back to me,
was called a world sheet.
Today, it's the standard terminology.
So strings are world sheets looked at at an instant
in the same sense that particles are
world lines looked at at an instant.
So that's the jargon.
World sheets and world lines.
Sir, could I go back to that diagram?
Okay.
See that there's a string in there, as it stretches,
and that put the glue on to tension?
No.
And so how do you get
from a plus to a minus?
Well, the lines of flux come out
one side and go in the other side.
Same way you go from a north
pole to a south pole in a magnet.
And a magnet?
No, any magnet.
Any magnet has two poles.
There's always two poles of opposite sign.
No magnet has two north poles.
No magnet has two south poles.
Every magnet has one north pole and one south pole.
North and south are like plus and minus.
Is there a block wall in there?
What?
A black wall?
A block?
I don't know what a block wall is.
Despite the fact that I'm
going to feel it's an object.
It's not a block wall.
So it's a block.
I'm going to get rid of that.
So you have to do a block wall.
It's a square, right?
Yeah.
Despite the fact that I'm the Felix
Bloch professor of physics, I don't know.
Yeah?
Could the string be considered either continuous
or discrete, or does it make any
difference?
Well, you see, now you're running
into the subtleties of quantum mechanics.
Is the electromagnetic field a continuum?
Well, in some ways, yes.
Is the electromagnetic field made of discrete quanta?
Yes, in some way, yes.
And quantum mechanics tells you that
that distinction between continuum and discrete
is a very subtle one, and I
won't try to answer it right now.
I think both are true.
It's continuum and it's discrete, depending
on the way you think about it.
All right.
Next question.
Nonrelativistic versus relativistic kinematics.
So kinematics are simple ideas about
particles, energy, momentum, the symmetries of motion.
On the face of it, relativistic
and nonrelativistic physics look very, very different.
Right?
Of course, we know that they're connected
to each other, but let's quantify or discuss
that difference.
Yes?
Yes.
Michael, you can always ask your question.
As long as you keep bringing me cookies.
The string being a point
in time at the wall sheet.
Yeah.
Okay.
If you change the angle of
that cross-section of space-time, what happens?
Well, the point in time is the
point in time of the wall sheet.
So if you change the angle of the wall
sheet, you still describe what you get as something
like a string.
Yes.
The Lorentz transformation of us, what
you're talking about is the Lorentz transformation,
of course.
The Lorentz transformation is a moving
string, but it's still a string.
Absolutely.
Right.
So if you were to consider a frame
in which simultaneity was this line here, you would
still be seeing a string, but you
would be seeing a string in motion.
As opposed to standing still.
Right.
When I say standing still, incidentally, I mean
the center of mass of it standing still.
Strings wiggle a lot.
They've got a lot of tension and they
vibrate a lot, so they don't stand still.
But the center of mass can stand still.
All right.
Let's come now to the
issue of relativity versus non-relativity.
How do you describe a relativistic string?
Well, that's awfully complicated.
Describing anything relativistically is complicated.
For example, just the, let's begin
with the energy of a particle.
The energy of a particle, non-relativistically,
point particle, is p squared over 2m.
Momentum squared, depending on the number of
dimensions, we would have to add up the
various components of momentum, divided by twice the mass.
That's a nice simple algebraic quantity.
The square of a function is easy to compute.
And so forth.
You might add to this a constant.
And the constant you would think of as the
binding energy or just the energy of the particle
because it's there.
So you might put something else there.
Let's call it B, the energy that it
takes to assemble a particle, whatever it is.
The characteristic of it is that it
does not depend on the state of motion.
It doesn't depend on p.
In a relativistic theory, there's a
natural candidate for what this B is.
It's the energy of a thing
when p is equal to zero, right?
I mean, relativity or not relativity.
It's the energy of the particle at rest.
What is, what are we, in the special
theory of relativity, what do we put there?
mc squared, of course.
So there's a natural thing to
put there, which would be mc squared.
But let's just think of it as an additive constant.
And it's constant.
Only.
But the idea is that the energy of the
particle is not dependent on the state of motion.
What it's doing so far is
it does not depend on p.
It might vary from different kind
of particle to different kind of particle.
It could be the binding energy holding together an atom.
It could be whatever.
But it doesn't depend on the overall motion.
And for many purposes, you could
just drop this because it's always there.
And energy differences don't depend on it.
So p squared over 2m.
It's just quadratic.
Of course, if you have many particles in a
system, then what you do is you add up the
energy, if they're not interacting.
And you also add up the internal
binding energy, internal energy you could call it.
You add them all up.
Again, this doesn't matter because energy
differences don't, are insensitive to it.
Now how do we get this from relativity?
Let's remind ourselves of the energy differences.
Let's remind ourselves what the formula
for the energy of a particle is.
The energy of a particle, this is E. All right.
In relativity, it's equal to the square
root of p squared plus m squared.
It's of course, I'm going to correct this in
a minute, but it's of course equal to the
sum over all the particles.
Let's just write it as E equals the sum
over all the particles in the system of p squared
plus m squared.
Where p squared equals the sum over all the particles.
p squared is px squared plus py squared
plus pz squared or however many dimensions we
wish to take into account.
Well, why take into account?
However many dimensions are appropriate to the problem.
So this would be pi and mi for the ith
particle and also x, y, and z and whatever else.
Okay.
How do we go from here to here?
Well first of all, I left something out.
I left out c to the fourth.
That's the fourth power of the speed of light.
And m squared, c squared here.
As soon as I finish this one little
demonstration, I'm going to set c equal to one.
Maybe four and two are switched.
Four and two are switched?
Do I have it wrong?
You're right.
Sorry.
mc squared.
Yeah, c to the fourth.
Very good.
C squared.
p squared, c squared, m squared, c to the fourth.
Good.
Boy, I would have been in trouble.
Okay.
The nonrelativistic limit is appropriate for problems
where a particle is moving very slowly,
which means its momentum is very small, and
in particular in which p squared, c squared
is much smaller than m squared, c to the fourth.
Under those circumstances, you can take the square
root of p squared plus m squared and
write it first in the form m squared, c
squared, m squared, c squared, c to the fourth.
Okay.
So, you have m squared, c squared, c to
the fourth, times one plus p squared, c squared,
over m squared, c to the fourth.
You can factor out of the square root the
m squared, c to the fourth, and that gives
you mc squared on the outside.
That's a good sign.
But with a correction.
And the correction is this over here.
What do you do with it?
You expand out the square root.
You use the formula that the square root of
one plus a small quantity is one plus the
small quantity divided by two.
Square root of one plus a small quantity is
equal to the one plus the small quantity over
two.
That's an approximation, of course.
It's not exact.
But as the small quantity gets smaller
and smaller, it becomes better and better.
So what do you get?
You get mc squared plus m squared.
Plus p squared, c squared, over mc squared,
mc to the fourth, divided by two, all times
mc squared here.
Okay.
So let's see what cancels.
mc squared, that's familiar.
That's the relativistic rest energy.
But this here has four powers of c in
the numerator, four powers of c in the denominator.
c goes away.
It has one power of m in the
numerator, two powers of m in the denominator.
Cancel them.
Then you get the good old nonrelativistic formula.
But it's an approximation.
It's an approximation.
And when is it good?
It's good when all particles are moving slowly.
It's not just that.
It's not just the whole system which
has to be moving slowly to use nonrelativistic
physics.
You might, for example, have a box of particles.
And the box may be moving slowly, but
inside the box, the particles may be moving with
close to the speed of light.
You cannot use pure nonrelativistic physics for
all of these particles because they have
relative motions which are up near the speed of light.
So strictly speaking, the nonrelativistic limit is a
good thing to do when all of the
particles are moving slowly, and it is an approximation.
Now, there's another sense in which nonrelativistic
physics is an exact description of relativistic
physics.
So I'm going to show you this.
This is something that goes back
a long ways in particle physics.
When I worked on it in 1968.
Or 67 or some time, it
was called the infinite momentum frame.
Now it's called the light cone frame.
So if you look up light cone
frame, you will see these things described.
Okay, but it's easy.
It's easy.
If I don't want to do it
in great and enormous generality, it's easy.
And here's what the trick is.
Instead of thinking of a system in its rest frame,
when we said, or near the rest frame, in
other words, a frame in which every momentum is slow,
we're going to do a different trick.
We're going to look at it from the point
of view of a frame where everything, the entire system,
has been boosted up to
have huge momentum along one axis.
In other words, boost it up
so that it's moving down the z-axis.
Let's take that to be the z-axis.
So that it has humongously large momentum along the z-axis.
There's no loss in generality there.
We can take any system and just
boost it so that it's along the z-axis.
And then rewrite what this formula looks like.
Okay, so I'm going to, you know what I'm going
to do, I'm going to set c equal to one now.
I'm not going to bother keeping c.
The energy is the sum of all the particles
of, again, square root of p squared plus m squared,
which is equal to square root,
of pz squared plus px squared
plus py squared plus m squared.
But now we're boosting the hell
out of this system along the z-axis
until every single particle has
a huge momentum along the z-axis.
Every single one of them.
If there's any particle which
is going backward on the z-axis,
you just haven't boosted it enough.
Just boost it more until it's
going forward with a large momentum.
In that case, all of the pz's are very large.
What happens to px, py,
and m when you boost something?
Nothing.
That's the rest mass.
We don't even speak about moving mass anymore.
The rest mass.
And the components of momentum perpendicular to
the boost don't change when you boost something.
Okay, so now the big quantity is pz.
And px, py, and m.
Are kept fixed.
And are much smaller than pz.
So the appropriate thing to do here,
in taking the limit,
is expand it for large pz.
Expand it for this being small.
The way to do that is
to write this in the form
square root of one plus,
let's just call it px squared plus py squared,
plus m squared,
divided by pz squared,
all times pz on the outside, right?
pz on the outside.
If I brought the pz inside the square root,
it would have to be squared.
It would be pz squared,
and then it would cancel this pz squared here.
Okay.
What's the next step?
Expand.
Use the binomial expansion, the binomial approximation,
and then you'll see that
this is exactly the same thing
we did over here.
This is now the small quantity.
And so this becomes pz times one plus
px squared plus py squared plus m squared
over twice pz.
Twice pz squared, excuse me,
pz squared.
Or to summarize it all,
the energy is the sum over all the particles
of pz of the ith particle
plus the sum of, let's call it,
p, uh,
p will now stand for px and py.
Let's use little p.
Little p stands for px and py.
Little p squared over twice big Pz
plus m squared over twice big Pz.
No.
It was a Pz up here
and a Pz squared down here.
Okay?
Good.
I don't need to put brackets in.
Okay, first observation.
If we believe in momentum conservation,
which we do in this class,
if we believe in momentum conservation,
then first of all, this is
just the total momentum of the system.
The first term here is
the total z component of momentum
going down the z axis.
It's huge, very large,
but it's a constant.
It's a constant, and as various things go on,
in this system,
the total momentum never changes.
If you have a constant term in the energy,
which doesn't change in any
way during the course of a,
you know, a constant additive thing,
adding it to the energy
or subtracting it from the energy doesn't do anything.
For example, if you added
the electric charge to the energy,
since electric charge is conserved,
then the only thing that's ever important in physics
is differences of energy,
and that's the same thing with energy conservation.
You can just drop it or keep it.
It doesn't matter.
The same is true here.
You have a conserved quantity,
which is conserved for
other reasons than energy conservation.
Energy, of course, is also conserved,
but Pz is conserved for other reasons.
Here's something which never changes.
You can just drop it.
If you were to think of the
energy as being the Hamiltonian of a system,
it would make no difference whether
you drop it or don't drop it,
because it's a conserved quantity which never changes.
So you can drop this.
It will make no difference.
The rest of the energy here is this thing here.
Now, first of all,
notice that Pz is in the denominator.
What does that mean?
Why is the energy so small?
In particular, energy differences,
for example, differences depending on the
state of motion in the xy plane,
they will be tiny.
Why are they tiny?
Anybody know?
Why are the energy diff...
Okay, I will tell you.
For this, it's useful to
remember a bit of quantum mechanics,
even though we don't need to be doing quantum mechanics.
What is the meaning of the energy?
The energy, of course, in quantum
mechanics is the same as the Hamiltonian.
It is also in classical mechanics.
But what's the meaning of
the Hamiltonian in quantum mechanics?
Do you remember your quantum mechanics?
It is an operator.
It's a Hermitian operator.
But it's also the oper...
Hmm?
It's an eigenvalue of the energy,
but it's also associated with something else.
It's also associated with time evolution.
All right?
Remember that this is the
same as I d by dt.
Namely, I h bar, probably, d by dt.
This is...
It's action as an operator on a state.
That what it means to say energies are very small
is that systems are changing very slowly.
This is also true, incidentally, in classical mechanics.
I just point this out in quantum mechanics.
If the energies of a system are very, very small,
it means changes take place very, very slowly.
So, if the energy of
a system is very, very small,
it means changes take place very, very slowly.
The smaller the energy,
if the energy scales with
some 1 over p z here,
it means that the larger that p z is,
the slower things take place in the system.
What's going on here?
Very simple.
It's time dilation.
The more you boost the system
up to higher and higher momentum,
in your reference frame, the slower things take place.
Okay, that's interesting.
So, we have all the time in the world,
a system moving.
We can wait as long as
we like to see things take place.
If we're trying to make a theory of radioactive decay,
sure, boosting it up will
make the radioactive decay go slower,
but we can rescale that out.
We can say instead of
working on a scale of microseconds,
we'll work on a scale of millions of years,
and we'll also see the nucleus decay.
Everything just has to be rescaled.
So this 1 over p z there,
the total of this is 1 over p z,
this is incidentally for the i-th particle,
and we add them all up.
So the fact that all the p z's get large,
incidentally, in fixed proportion,
they all get large in fixed proportion,
that said the energy got smaller.
That's a completely expected phenomenon.
Apart from that, if we rescale
all the p z's,
ignore the fact that they get big,
or just rescale the evolution of the system,
this Hamiltonian, or this expression for energy,
really does look like the non-relativistic expression
with respect to the motion in the x-y plane.
For the motion in the x-y plane,
the energy is proportional to
the square of the x-y momentum,
just as it is for the non-relativistic particle,
but notice that the role
of the mass of the particle
in this non-relativistic analogy
is not the rest mass,
it's the momentum along the z-axis.
What this means, what is mass?
Mass is inertia, right?
It's got to do with the difficulty of deflecting something.
What this is saying is
that the momentum along the z-axis
is functioning as a kind of inertia
with respect to forces in the perpendicular direction,
and the whole thing is looking very, very much like,
if we think of p z as a constant,
then all this is is the non-relativistic formula
for the energy of a two-dimensional particle now.
Notice we now have only two dimensions of motion,
and what about this term over here?
How should we interpret that?
Again, remember that we think of p z
as being independent of the state of motion,
at least the two-dimensional motion,
so with respect to this two-dimensional analogy,
analogy between relativistic and non-relativistic physics,
it's an analogy between relativistic physics
and two-dimensional motion,
in which p z plays the role of the mass,
and how about this object over here?
It plays the role of the binding energy.
Does it have the right
properties to be a binding energy?
The only thing about a binding energy
is that it should be
independent of the state of motion.
It should not depend on...
This does not depend on the two-dimensional motion.
So this is kind of interesting,
and it's not only interesting,
but incredibly useful in studying particle dynamics,
and absolutely central to studying strings,
is that in a very precise and exact way,
the motion of a relativistic system,
when it's boosted up to enormously large momentum,
behaves completely non-relativistically
with respect to the motion in
the plane perpendicular to the boost.
Okay?
It's for this reason
that string theory is also often
described in terms of mathematics,
which is the mathematics of a non-relativistic string.
A non-relativistic string...
A non-relativistic string is a collection of point particles
in some limit in which you let
the point particles get more and more continuous,
all moving non-relativistically,
and then you let the point
particles get more and more continuous.
And so,
by what chutzpah do we use non-relativistic physics
to describe anything as
complicated as a relativistic string?
Well, the answer is that in the infinite momentum frame,
which these days is called the light cone frame,
mostly because it has nothing to do with cones,
nothing whatever to do with cones,
I'll tell you another time why
it's called the light cone frame.
Not important.
But in the infinite momentum frame,
you have a chance that
perhaps the motion of a string,
when it's boosted up,
may be described by a
kind of non-relativistic quantum mechanics.
And this seems to be
borne out, not seems to be,
this has been the techniques that have been used for
since the very beginning of string theory
to analyze relativistic strings.
Let me show you the simplest fact...
Yeah, no, okay.
Let me show you one of the very simple questions
that I've been asked.
So, let's say that we have two connections
that follow from thinking this way.
Let's now hypothesize or postulate
that we can think of particles
as strings using the two-dimensional analogy
with non-relativistic physics
to explore those strings as if they were conventional,
non-relativistic, not shoelaces,
but something closer to rubber bands.
Stretchable, they can move, they can flap,
they can do all the things that a rubber band,
an ideal rubber band can do.
What's the mathematical description
of a two-dimensional rubber band
which is moving around in two dimensions?
Let's take our rubber band
to be an open rubber band.
That means somebody took a scissor,
cut it, and opened it up.
Let's begin with open strings.
Open strings means strings with two ends.
There may or may not be something interesting
attached to the ends,
but we're interested more in the strings.
Let's write the physics of a string.
What is the energy stored in a string?
We can think of the
string as a collection of points,
point particles, which later on we will take limits.
One of the things we will
do when we take a limit
is we'll let the mass
of each point go to zero.
That's because the whole string has a finite mass.
We're going to think of it as being a collection
of a virtual infinity of point masses,
and it had better be that in taking the limit,
we let the mass of each point go to zero.
All right, but what's the energy of this?
The energy is going to be proportional
to the kinetic energy.
It'll be the sum of all the points
of x i dot squared.
These are two-dimensional now,
so we could write this
as x plus y dot squared.
That's the i-th point.
Divide it by two,
and we might put here
a mass of the i-th particle,
which later on we're going to let go to zero.
But let's not be too...
I'll just tell you how to do the continuum limit.
I'll show you how to do it.
I'll just tell you how to do it.
All right, what are we missing out of this formula?
Interactions.
Interactions, yeah.
These points are attracting each other.
If they weren't attracting each other,
they'd just fly apart.
They're forming a string.
They are, in addition to the points,
we have to put in
the little springs that connect them.
So think of it as a
chain of little balls and little springs.
Can you see the springs?
All right, little balls and little springs.
Let's just call this x sub i squared.
x sub i squared now stands for x squared.
x dot squared plus y dot squared.
Okay, what is the potential energy between the points?
The potential energy is a
sum also over all neighboring pairs.
So there's another sum of i here.
There's a spring constant.
Let's just call it k.
All the mass points have the same mass.
There's a spring constant there.
And what is the potential energy
between a pair of points?
It'll be proportional to the distance between them,
xi minus xi plus one squared.
Probably a two there.
This is Hooke's Law.
The energy stored in a stretched spring
is proportional to the distance of stretching squared.
That's the Hooke's Law.
The formula for the...
Now, what happens when you go to the continuum limit?
In other words, you let the
points get denser and denser and denser,
more and more of them.
You have to do two things.
You have to let the mass
of each one go to zero,
and you have to also let the spring constant...
What is this?
You want the spring constant to get big or small?
Big.
Do you know why?
Supposing you take a rubber band.
You take a rubber band, a
big, long piece of rubber band,
and you stretch it.
It's easy to stretch.
Now take two points very close to each other
and try to stretch them that same distance,
much harder.
Okay?
So the spring constant gets big,
and the mass gets small,
but in the end what you get...
Just take it from me.
What you get is, of course, an integral represent...
an integral replacing the sum,
the integral is over a parameter along the string.
You have to introduce a
mathematical parameter along the string.
We can call that parameter, we'll give it a name,
sigma.
Sigma goes from one end of the
string where we can arbitrarily say it's zero.
So sigma is zero at this end,
and at the other end we can
arbitrarily say sigma is equal to pi.
I could have taken it to be one,
I could have taken it to be seven,
it doesn't matter.
It will be useful to call it pi.
The reason is later on
we're going to study closed strings,
which go all the ways around in a loop,
and it's nice to say they go
from zero to two pi, that's all.
But they go from zero to pi.
So this sum over the mass
points is going to be an integral
from zero to pi, d sigma.
This is adding up.
This is adding them all up.
And we're going to have the kinetic energy
of the little element of string at point sigma.
We have a continuous string now.
We take a little element at point sigma.
We take its velocity squared and divide by two.
And what about this term over here?
I've chosen the mass to go
in the appropriate way of dropping the mass here.
By the time you're finished,
you can absorb the mass into something else.
It doesn't matter what.
It's just x dot squared.
It's clearly kinetic energy.
What about this term here?
What's that going to look like?
How about xi minus xi plus one?
What do you replace that with?
Derivative.
This is like the derivative
of x with respect to sigma.
So, the other term here will be
derivative of x with respect to sigma.
This is derivative of x with respect to time.
This is derivative of x with respect to sigma squared.
This is the energy of the string.
If I wanted to write the Lagrangian,
you all remember what a Lagrangian is.
Energy is kinetic energy plus potential energy
plus potential energy plus potential energy.
So, this is the energy of the string.
This is potential energy.
Lagrangian is kinetic energy minus.
So, if I wanted the Lagrangian,
it would be this.
If I wanted the energy,
it would be with a plus sign.
I'll write the energy.
We'll write the energy.
Hamiltonian plus.
Let's focus for a little bit.
I'm going to stop in a
few minutes and we'll take a rest.
But let's focus a little bit on a string
which happens to have no overall center of mass motion
in the two dimensions in the xy plane.
We're coming back now to here.
What we're going to do is use a model
of a relativistic string
which is simply based on
this kind of infinite momentum thinking
but in which there are only two x's.
The two x's moving in
the direction perpendicular to the motion.
So, this could be called x and y,
but I'll just call it x dot squared.
It really consists of x
dot squared plus y dot squared.
This one consists of dx by d sigma squared
plus dy by d sigma squared.
Is that clear?
Yeah, okay.
Oh, I just absorbed it.
I just chose...
Oh, sorry, there is a two.
Two is important.
I chose k in such a way to make sure
that when I got to the final continuum limit,
the coefficient was one.
Remember, it's something that has to vary
as you vary the spacing,
and it can be chosen in such a way
as to make this...
And this is the conventional energy of a vibrating string.
It has two terms, kinetic and potential.
Potential proportional to the stretching.
This is the x d sigma
is the stretching of the string.
Okay, I want to point out one interesting fact.
This Hamiltonian here,
or this expression for energy,
is the generalization of this expression here
for a system of particles
which also has an interaction between them.
But the whole thing, the whole object,
it may be vibrating and doing things,
but the whole object is an object.
We can call it a particle.
Who's to say it's not a particle?
Protons and neutrons have spin.
They rotate.
There's all sorts of internal motions in particles.
We know there are internal motions of particles,
internal motions of atoms,
internal motions of quarks inside protons and neutrons.
The best bet would be there
are all sorts of internal motions
in every particle.
So this stringy vibrations and
internal motions and so forth,
that perhaps, not perhaps,
but would add up to all
the internal motion in the particle.
All the internal energy in the particle.
The internal energy would be the contributions to the energy
from the potential stretching
and from the relative motion of the different parts.
The overall motion,
we'll separate that out soon enough,
but the overall motion of the string,
the center of mass of it,
that would just be treated
as the position of the particle.
But the relative stretching
and the relative vibration,
that's internal energy.
So, when we calculate the internal energy of this particle,
what should we relate it to?
We should relate it not to the mass,
but to the mass squared.
In this correspondence,
it's not an analogy,
it's an exact statement about the properties of relativity.
It's a very precise statement.
It's a very precise mathematical statement,
which I won't make now,
but there is an exact sense
in which fast-moving systems
are completely non-relativistic
in the two-dimensional sense.
What would the internal energy correspond to?
It would correspond not to the mass of the particle,
but to the mass squared.
So, for a string at rest,
think of a string which has no motion
in the x-axis,
but is in a x-y plane.
All it's doing is vibrating,
and it has internal energy.
That internal energy has to be identified
with the square of the mass
of the entire assembly of constituents of the string.
If the constituents of the string
are adding up to something
that we want to call a particle,
then that particle has a mass squared,
which is the sum of all of the internal energies
of the particle.
Now, this is an interesting fact.
We get mass squared
for the energy of a particle
in this framework.
There are some C's around,
which I haven't tried to keep track of.
There are C's,
and, yeah, there are C's,
and, right.
Yeah, I haven't tried to keep track of them.
But,
this connection was something I knew
that nobody else knew at the time.
I worked on both these things.
And, so,
this is interesting.
This is exciting.
Another fact.
Another fact is that a string
is not so different than a spring.
If you look at the spectrum of energy,
the spectrum of energies of a string,
it's quantized in pretty much the same way.
We're going to do the quantization of it carefully,
but the basic fact about the quantization of it
is that the string is a collection of springs,
and springs have quantized energy.
And what's the formula for the energy
of a quantum mechanical oscillator?
An integer multiple of something.
Each time,
you increase the energy of a spring or a string,
the internal energy,
by one unit,
it increases the mass squared by one unit.
Increases the mass squared by one unit.
A quick question.
Yeah.
The m, m, energy is m squared.
The m is,
this is a simple confusion,
is m the mass of the string?
Yeah, it's the mass of the whole string.
The whole string.
So she doubled the size
of the mass of the string
four times the energy of the general,
because m squared would be,
is that correct?
Yeah.
You've stolen my thunder.
Well, I,
I'm confused.
Okay, but now,
well, okay, let's look at this formula
a little bit carefully now,
and see if we can see anything interesting.
Good question.
The right side,
you have m squared there.
That would kind of,
kind of connote the rest mass of the system, correct?
It is in fact the rest mass of the string
in a frame of reference where it's not zipping along,
but where it was really stationary.
But the equation seems to be,
seems to be not well describing a photon.
It, well,
that's right, because a photon is massless.
Yeah.
Well, that just corresponds to m equals zero
on the right-hand side.
And you're going to ask me,
how can this thing be zero?
Well, we're going to come to that.
That is a very significant and interesting point.
We're going to come to it.
For the moment,
it's just the mass of the entire string.
The entire, including its internal energy,
including its stretching energy,
all of the energies that you would normally add up
to find m c squared,
to find the rest mass,
that's what this is here.
Okay?
It's just a, yeah.
This is just a classical mechanics
and relativity applied so far.
We haven't invented any other?
We haven't introduced quantum mechanics yet.
Do things like that.
Nope.
Okay.
But if we did introduce quantum mechanics,
we would know that this string would be,
would have quantized energy levels,
and therefore quantized mass squares.
In fact, if we increase the angular momentum
by one quantum,
then the quantized energy,
the quantum of energy that would be introduced
would be a quantum of m squared,
not a quantum of m.
All right.
So.
This was an immediate piece of evidence that,
that moreover,
yeah, okay.
This was, this was one of the hints that,
one of the hints.
There's another interesting fact here.
Supposing you took a string
which was not moving,
but which you stretched out,
which you stretched out to a certain length,
okay,
how much energy would it have?
Well, then all of its energy would be
potential energy, not kinetic energy.
Let's calculate what it would be.
How big is the x d sigma?
Well, if you stretched it out uniformly,
then the change in x along the length of it
would just be the length of the string.
L would just be,
we're stretching it out
to a physical distance L.
We stretch it out to a physical distance L
over a distance from zero to pi, right?
All right.
So the derivative of x with respect to sigma
would be something like L divided by pi.
I don't care about the pi's right now.
They're not what's, what's interesting.
The x by d sigma would just be proportional
to the length of the string.
Okay.
If you stretched it out by distance L,
and divided it by the range of sigma
from zero to pi,
that would give you the x by d sigma.
And so we can say
that the x by d sigma
is proportional to the length of the string.
And the x by d sigma squared
would just be the square of
the length of the string, right?
This is Hooke's law.
This is Hooke's law for a string.
If you stretch it out to distance L,
the energy stored in it,
nonrelativistically,
will be L squared.
But that's what has to equal the mass of it.
That's what has to equal the mass squared.
Now we know something interesting
about how, about the energetics of the string
if we were to study it in the rest frame.
In the rest frame of the string,
the energy of the string is the mass.
We got from mass to mass squared
by boosting the string.
But if we went back now,
and we said, look, wait a minute.
We know E equals mc squared.
That's rest mass.
What is the rest mass?
The rest mass of the string.
And the answer is that the rest mass
is proportional to,
is a proportionality factor,
proportional to its length.
In other words,
this string has the property
that the energy,
if you think about it in its rest frame,
if you stretch it out to distance L,
it will have an energy
which will grow with L
and be proportional to L.
In the rest frame,
it doesn't look like a Hooke's law string at all.
It looks like a different kind of string
whose energy is proportional to its length.
Well, that's very interesting
because it fits with another picture.
It fits with the picture
which I described before
of lines of,
lines of flux connecting quarks and anti-quarks.
Lines of flux would produce,
if I slice them through like this,
they would produce a patch
of electric or magnetic field here.
It doesn't matter whether it's electric or magnetic.
Lines of flux in a tube like this
would produce a magnetic or an electric field in here.
Electric fields have energy,
and the energy density in them depends on the field.
The energy density along the field,
along this long tube of flux,
would be uniform.
If the number of flux
lines passing through this little area
is the same as the
number passing through this little area,
and so forth,
the field strength would be uniform
along this tube of flux here.
This is, in fact, a
property of tubes of magnetic flux
and superconductors and so forth.
And superconductors are,
and superconductors are,
superconductors, you don't have, of course,
monopoles in superconductors,
but you can have long lines of magnetic flux,
and they have the property
that the magnetic field is uniform along them,
and therefore the energy density is uniform along them.
That means that the energy is proportional to their length.
This is a common thing in field theory
and condensed matter physics
and a variety of different contexts
where field energy,
in a field forming a long string,
is proportional to the length of the string,
not the length squared.
It's a different kind of string.
Another way to think about it
is that the string is made
up of a lot of little particles,
but as you pull on it
and separate the distances here,
new particles form in between
so as to keep the number
of particles per unit length fixed.
That's another way to think about these long flux lines,
that they're uniform along their length,
and as you pull them apart,
more particles form to fill the gaps.
Then, in that situation,
it would also be true
that the energy per unit length would be fixed,
and the energy would be proportional to the length.
This is, by now,
actually an experimental fact about hadrons,
that you can spin them up,
you can stretch them,
and they have the property
that the energy per unit length is fixed.
It's called the string tension.
The string tension is a constant.
That would not be the
case in an ordinary Hooke's law,
if you stretch them.
But this is the picture in the rest frame.
In the rest frame,
the energy of the string is proportional to its length.
In the infinite momentum frame,
where the physics is all non-relativistic,
the energy is proportional to the square of the length,
like Hooke's law.
So these two kinds of strings,
Hooke's law and flux tube,
are related to each other.
In some sense,
they're just the same object
being described in two different reference frames,
one at rest and one...
Just to amplify that,
if you had an ordinary rubber band,
and it was vibrating at almost relativistic speeds in one...
No, no, no, wait.
Ordinary rubber bands,
if they vibrate with relativistic speed,
we haven't got the vaguest idea how to describe them.
We don't want to do that.
No.
We've made an indirect deduction.
First half of the deduction was,
in the infinite momentum frame,
everything is non-relativistic,
at least in two dimensions.
We use that to discover the fact
that the stretched energy of a string
which is L squared,
because it's described non-relativistically
like a Hooke's law spring,
is L squared.
That is to be related to M squared.
Indirectly from that,
we conclude that if we were in the rest frame,
the energy of the string
would be proportional to its length.
And that's interesting,
because there's a wide variety of interesting
string-like objects that occur in field theory,
and they're called field theories,
not made out of atoms,
but made out of field configurations,
which have exactly the same property.
All right, let's come back in a few minutes.
I think I probably exhausted your attention for today.
But let me summarize.
Let me summarize.
Experimental properties of,
of hadrons indicated this kind of
excitations along a line.
Had we been smart at the time,
we probably would have realized
that this pattern here
is the appropriate pattern for strings
whose potential energy is proportional to their length.
That's something we actually could
have deduced directly from here.
In fact, why am I saying we could have?
I mean, we could have deduced that
the energy grew as the length of such a string.
That was the consequence of this relationship here.
All right, that was one fact.
Next fact.
Relativistic physics in a frame
in which everything is moving fast
is the same as non-relativistic physics,
except in one less dimension.
In one less dimension.
And so we can say that,
and so we can try to
build a simple theory of relativistic strings
by going to such a
frame and just using non-relativistic physics,
but in one less dimension.
Here it is.
Here's the non-relativistic string in two-dimensional space.
The only thing we have to remember
is that wherever we saw energy,
we have to think of
it, or internal energy in particular,
internal energy should be really identified
with the square of the mass,
not the mass.
Okay?
That, if you remember, came
from the two different expansions.
If you like, one of them was an expansion
in which this was the big term,
and then the whole thing
is approximately of order mc squared,
square root of this thing in here.
The other expansion was a
term in which this was big,
and then the excess energy was
proportional to m squared, not m.
So when you do that, and
you go through this little exercise,
your conclusion is that the Hooke's law energy
of the effective non-relativistic string
should be identified with the mass squared,
which indirectly tells you that
the rest mass of the string
is proportional to its length.
And finally, there are lots and lots of field theory
and condensed matter systems which have the same property,
so that was something.
Encouraging, if you like.
Okay, let's take a rest,
and then we can come back
and either ask some questions or...
I don't think I'll discuss
the quantization of the string today.
The quantization is easy.
We've done most of the things
that are necessary to figure it out.
It's just a collection of harmonic oscillators.
But I think we can take a rest first.
Just to help my comprehension here,
it seems you start with a classic string,
then you boost the hell out
of it in the z direction,
and you basically do a Lorentz transform.
Shouldn't you get the same physics when you go back?
Shouldn't you get back the physics that you started with?
You do.
You do, it's just easier this way.
No, but you don't have the same physics.
No?
At first, you start with a string that had a...
a length proportional to its mass squared.
In both cases, the mass is proportional to the length,
and the mass squared is proportional to the length squared,
in both cases.
But in one case, you call the energy the mass,
in the other case, you
call the energy the mass squared.
Let's go through that.
I'll come back to your question in a minute.
Let me just go through it again,
because there was some sleight of hand.
There was some tricky business there.
We wrote that energy is equal to...
square root of p squared plus m squared.
Let's, for the moment, forget
the motion in the xy plane.
Let's just concentrate on the
z direction and the time direction.
Energy is related to time, p is related to space.
There's two ways I could expand this.
One of them is good when
p is small and m is large.
In other words, when I'm in a...
and when the particle is moving
slowly in my frame of reference.
In that case, let's see what we do.
Then we write that this is equal
to p times the square root of
1 plus m squared over p squared, right?
Sorry, I want to start in the situation
where p is small and m is large.
Good.
p is small and m is
large, so I write this then as
m squared times 1 plus p squared over m squared.
p is small.
p is small and m is large, so
p squared over m squared is a small quantity.
Okay?
Nod.
Good. Okay.
The m can come out and this becomes m times
the square root of 1 plus p squared plus m squared,
but that's approximately 1 plus p squared over 2m.
Okay?
Squared.
Which is equal to m, which really means mc squared,
plus p squared over 2m.
So, in that context, the internal energy
when the particle is at rest in space
is proportional to the mass.
That's your good old e equals mc squared.
Okay.
And that tells you that for
a particle at rest, it's inertia.
A particle at rest, it's inertia.
In other words, its usual resistance to acceleration
is the same as its mass and its energy.
It's mass meaning inertia, and its
energy are proportional to each other.
Okay.
Now, let's do the other expansion.
The other expansion, we boost like hell
so that the momentum is very large.
Okay?
And then we expand it in the other way.
Let's see, p is very large now.
So, this is the square root of p
squared times 1 plus m squared over p squared,
which is p plus...
Did I do that right?
Yeah.
p plus m squared, I think, over 2p.
Okay.
All right.
Now, this is the momentum along
the direction that we did the boost.
There are two other directions of momentum,
and we can put them in here.
But notice that the energy, apart from this
fact, this piece, which is just total momentum,
which we can drop because it
drops out of all interesting things,
is proportional to the square of the mass.
So, in this form, the
energy is proportional to the square.
It's proportional to the square of the mass.
And what that says is that
if a particle or a system,
a system of particles is moving
down the axis with an enormous momentum,
that its inertia, that its
inertia relative to this direction here...
Well, let me go back.
Let me go back.
Let me put in here the other
terms, plus px squared plus py squared.
They just went together with m squared.
This was pz squared plus m
squared plus px squared plus py squared.
We're taking this to be
small and pz to be large.
Okay?
One of the things that this says is that
the inertia is now not the mass of the particle.
It's the momentum along the z axis.
And that actually makes a lot of sense.
It's not true nonrelativistically,
but relativistically, it's true.
That a given force perpendicular to the direction of motion
will produce a smaller acceleration the larger the momentum.
So this, that's the first thing.
This p here is the inertia.
And the m squared is playing
the role of an internal energy.
Or m squared over 2p is
playing the role of an internal energy.
So internal energy becomes mass squared in this frame,
and inertia just becomes...
pz.
Oops, that doesn't look good, but...
Alright, now somebody asked me about the connection
between these kind of strings which have this
property of having an energy per unit length
and superconductors.
I think I mentioned it as we were talking.
I will spell it out.
Superconductors have the property
of repelling a magnetic field.
They repel, they don't want to
accept magnetic field penetrating through them.
They actually repel the magnetic field.
Because they repel the magnetic field,
it's kind of a pressure that was
pushing magnetic field out of the way,
but if you somehow push a magnetic field,
I'm going to tell you how
to do that in a minute,
if you push a magnetic field into the superconductor
in such a way that the lines of force,
the lines of force are
passing from one side of the...
Here's a big piece of superconductor.
Lines of force are passing through it, like that.
What it will do will be to squeeze, will
push those lines of force out of the way
and push them into a narrow...
string-like thing, like that.
That's called a fluxoid.
It's called a fluxoid,
or a superconducting flux line.
Superconducting, yeah, superconducting flux line.
Magnetic flux, not electric flux.
Magnetic flux.
And how can you make
one in principle in a superconductor?
Here's what you might do.
I doubt very much, well, this is probably
not the way it's done in real life,
but you take a piece of superconductor,
you drill an incredibly narrow hole through it.
This is a Gedanken experiment.
This is not something that I want you
to go away with as a practical experiment.
You drill through it an incredibly small...
Let's see, am I going to get this right?
Ah.
Before you cool down the superconductor,
you take a long bar magnet
and you stick it through the hole.
Like that.
Flux lines come out this way
from the bar magnet
and this way.
Now you cool it down
so that it becomes a superconductor
and you draw out the magnet.
These lines of flux here
will get pulled into the magnet.
Even after you've pulled out the magnet,
the lines of flux will go through that magnet
and they will form a thin tube through that magnet.
The field along the tube will be uniform.
And because the field is uniform,
that means the energy per unit length is fixed.
Okay, now, let's go a little bit further.
Imagine that we had magnetic monopoles.
We can actually simulate magnetic monopoles,
but let's suppose we really did have magnetic monopoles,
that there really were magnetic monopoles in the world.
And there may well be,
but we haven't discovered them yet.
But let's suppose we have discovered them
and we can manipulate them.
Okay, then we could take a monopole and an antimonopole,
put them right on top of each other,
don't let them annihilate, keep them a little bit apart.
Take them and put them into the superconductor.
Monopole and antimonopole.
I'm not going to tell you which one is which,
I'm just going to draw two of them.
And of course the monopole and the antimonopole
have some flux lines between them.
Now cool down the superconductor.
And take the monopole and the antimonopole
and start to separate them.
What happens?
Exactly the same thing that we think happens
between a pair of quarks.
Except that this is just an ordinary magnetic field
between the monopole and the antimonopole.
So inside a superconductor,
a monopole and an antimonopole would have an energy
which would be proportional to the distance between them.
Why the distance between them?
Because the string between them has
an energy proportional to its length.
Okay.
The monopole and the antimonopole
could not separate from each other,
they would be confined,
because as you start to separate them,
the energy goes up with the length,
and that's the character of what happens to hadrons,
or quarks in a hadron,
you separate them and their energy goes up.
So okay, so this is a system
where the energy is proportional to the length,
and it has the characteristics
of the same kind of string.
Does that answer your question?
Did you ever ask me?
I don't know who asked me.
Oh well, I guess he's gone.
The question was,
what's taking the role of the superfluid for the hadrons?
What is the superconducting fluid?
Virtual monopoles.
That's what it's thought to be, virtual monopoles,
but not these different monopoles.
These are called chromodynamic monopoles.
In the superconductor here,
the condensate, the superconducting condensate,
is made out of electric charge,
and it causes confinement of magnetic charge.
In quantum chromodynamics,
quarks are confined,
and they are kind of the electric charges
of quantum chromodynamics.
The things which condense are magnetic charges.
You say, where are those magnetic charges?
Why don't we see them?
Because they're always condensed in the vacuum.
But this is beyond what
I intended to talk about today.
Okay, what other questions come up?
Oh, it's almost 9 o'clock.
Okay, yeah.
So the energy being proportional to the length,
is the rule for highly relativistic string?
Well, a superconductor is not a highly relativistic,
it's a...
It's also not a string.
No, no, but it's string-like.
So if you took a regular Hooke's law,
string made of springs,
and had it going relativistically inside,
Assuming you could...
You'll have to make up some theory, I don't know.
You'll have to make up some theory.
But that construction would then have
an energy proportional to its length.
I don't know what it would do.
Depends on the details.
No, there's something special about
energy that grows at length.
As I said, what it really means in particle language
is that as you separate the constituents of the string,
as you pull it apart,
the energy of pulling it apart,
instead of just separating and making larger distances,
makes more particles.
So that the density of them
along the string always stays the same.
That's the character of these kind of strings.
And the other way to think about it
is there are strings made up out of field,
where because field lines are not allowed to end,
field lines are not allowed to end,
as long as the field doesn't spread out this way,
it has to remain uniform in the other direction.
So it's a characteristic of flux lines.
Flux lines which are confined to a tube.
If you had any kind
of situation where an electric field
were confined and prevented from
spreading out in the perpendicular direction,
the energy per unit length of it would be constant.
Yeah.
What about the kind of
residual motion along the p-z direction?
Along the z?
Ah, that's a very good question.
Yeah.
Remarkably, the way string theory works
is there are not independent degrees of freedom
for motion along the other direction.
This is a remarkable and strange fact
that in string theory you do
not include directly degrees of freedom
for the motion of the string along the direction
of the boost here.
It is thought that that's connected
with something called the holographic principle,
that really in a gravitating system you
need one less direct dimension to describe it,
but it's one of the
very remarkable features of string theory
that you don't describe the string in,
let's say in three-dimensional space,
in this limit you describe
it only by the two-dimensional motion,
and yet, as we will see,
it's consistent with Lorentz invariance.
Yeah.
How many data points do
we have on the Regiflots now?
Five or ten or?
I don't know what the maximum number is now.
Seven, something like that.
It's not endless,
but it doesn't give any evidence of giving out.
I'll talk about it another time,
but the evidence for that.
But remember,
that we're not really interested in hadrons.
I was just giving you a historical perspective
of where the whole thing came from.
But now we want to study this mathematical theory
and not insist that it looks like hadrons,
but just ask what it does look like.
And what we'll find out is
that it looks more like gravity
than it does hadrons.
Well, what if it was a electron?
What if it was something that is...
What if what was an electron?
Well, the idea that we
had some kind of spatial element
of the particle, the compositeness of the particle,
for a particle that doesn't seem to be composite...
Well, okay, let's be...
All right, so the question is...
can be expressed in two different ways.
Let's see.
It can be expressed...
or the answer to your question can be expressed
in terms of the smallness of the particle
or in terms of the energy that it takes
to increase the particle by one unit.
All right, so let's...
Do you remember the formula for the energy
of a rotating system as
a function of its angular momentum?
L squared, that's the angular momentum,
divided by two times something.
Remember what it is?
Moment of inertia.
And what's the moment of inertia related to?
The mass and the square
of the size of the system.
Right?
M R squared, not M squared, R squared.
M R squared.
But the point is that for a given mass,
the moment of inertia gets smaller and smaller
as the system gets...
Sorry, yes, the moment of inertia gets very small
when the system is very small.
Now, what is L?
L is angular momentum.
And it comes in quanta.
So this is proportional to N squared,
H bar squared, or something like that.
And now you can ask,
how much energy does it take
to go from N equals zero to N equals one?
N equals zero, the energy...
It might be a little bit of energy,
but the energy, this piece of the energy is zero.
The first excited state would have an energy
H bar squared over two,
one divided by the moment of inertia.
And if the object is very, very small,
the moment of inertia is very large.
No.
One over the moment of inertia is very large.
So the excitation energy,
the energy that it takes to increase the angular momentum
by one unit becomes very, very big
if the object is small.
Well, hadrons are big objects.
They have small moments of inertia
on the scale of quantum gravity.
Hadrons are just enormous.
I mean, they're, you know, they're big blobs.
They have large moments of inertia.
The energy taken to excite one is not very big.
Electrons are known to be much smaller.
The expectation is that they're exceedingly small,
maybe 10 to the 16th times smaller than a proton.
You square their radius to get the moment of inertia,
so that could mean 10 to
the 32 times smaller moment of inertia,
and that means that the energy of excitation
would be 10 to the 32 times bigger.
Well, maybe that's probably too much.
So if electrons have excited states,
because they're so small,
if they have rotational excitations,
those rotational excitations,
well, I think I lost my true Frouchy plot,
but the mass necessary to increase the angular momentum
by one unit would be way off on the,
no, that end of the plot.
Just too much, it just takes
too much energy to spin it up.
When I say too much, I
mean too much compared to the energies
that are available in particle collisions.
Okay?
So the energy needed to
excite a hadron by one unit
is less, is roughly of order of GeV.
You collide particles at a distance
of GeV or whatever it is,
you see these excitations.
The energy needed to spin up an electron
is very much higher.
You don't see them.
How about the energy needed to spin up a basketball
by one unit of angular momentum?
Very small, very small.
In fact, you can't even see that it's quantized.
All right.
An atom would be, okay.
Whatever it is,
first there, you know, a couple of electron volts.
You mean to spin up an atom by one unit?
A couple of electron volts.
Uh, all right.
Good.
Okay.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.