Stanford University
Okay, let's go to the space-time view of string theory.
What other kind of view could there be but space-time?
But I mean, let's think of the blackboard
as space-time and view what string theory looks like.
First, let's do something simpler first.
Let's just talk about an ordinary particle.
An ordinary particle in
classical mechanics has a trajectory.
Both in non-relativistic physics and relativistic physics, the
trajectory can be described by the three-dimensional position x
as a function of t.
But if you're doing relativity,
there's something which is more convenient,
and that's to take all four components,
space components and time components of position,
call them x mu, and think of
them as a function of a variable
which just denotes and demarks, let's say,
proper time along the trajectory of tau.
Let tau be the proper time along the trajectory.
And then clearly, if you know
the four-dimensional position at every proper time,
or every value of this parameter here, then
you can say exactly where the trajectory went.
So there's a slight, well, maybe more than a
slight, there's a difference of emphasis in non-relativistic physics
where you think of x as a function of time, and in
relativistic physics where you might be inclined to think of x mu,
the four components of position, as a
function of a parameter along the trajectory,
a kind of scalar parameter along the trajectory.
In each case, the motion of a particle is
defined by an action, by a principle of least action.
In the case of a non-relativistic system,
for a free particle, forget potentials, nothing else,
the action, which is usually called s,
I don't know why it's called s,
it's the same label as we use for
entropy, and to make matters worse, in many cases,
entropy and action turn out
to be the same thing, numerically.
But s is action, and for a non-relativistic particle,
it's the integral over time along
the trajectory of the kinetic energy.
One half x dot squared, and I've chosen
the mass of the particle arbitrarily to be one,
because I get tired of writing it.
That's the action, and what do you do with it?
You minimize it. You minimize it
to find the trajectory of the particle.
You minimize it, subject to some end positions,
holding down the end points, you minimize it.
Now that's not what you do in quantum mechanics.
Before we do that, let me discuss the relativistic case.
In the relativistic case, something very similar,
the thing is the action can be taken
to be the integral over tau,
the proper time along the trajectory,
of dx mu by d
tau, dx mu by d tau.
Notice there's one upper index and one lower
index, and you can figure out what that means.
In other words, it looks very, very
much like the non-relativistic kinetic energy formula,
but it means something different.
There are four components of position,
and the time is the proper time,
and what's more,
the time components and the space
components of this expression have different sign.
But apart from that, they look very similar.
And again, what do you do with it?
You minimize it. You minimize it, subject to
the constraint that at the ends of the period,
the particle is at this
space-time point and that space-time point.
So there's a sort of parallel structure,
and basic principle is a principle of least-division.
So you have the first action.
Now in quantum mechanics, you do
something totally different with the action.
What you do with the
action, you ask a different question.
You don't ask, what is the trajectory given to endpoints?
Here you ask, what is the trajectory given to endpoints?
The answer is, of course, a straight line.
In either case, it's a straight line.
It's a straight line through
space and time with constant velocity.
You ask a different question.
You ask, what is the amplitude that
a particle that started at this point,
at time zero or at the beginning of
time, at the start of the time interval,
is detected at that point at a later time?
That's the question you ask.
You don't ask, what's the trajectory in between?
You ask, what's the amplitude for the
particle to go from here to here?
And the answer is,
the amplitude to go from point one to point two,
is the same as the amplitude
of the particle to the point three.
So in either case, you write the action,
you write the exponential of the action,
e to the i, not just any
exponential, but exponential with an i in it,
e to the i times the action,
let's write it out explicitly,
d by dt over one half,
dt dx by dt squared.
This is the equation.
This integral here goes from t1 to t2,
but then you're not finished.
You're not finished.
This expression depends not only on the position
of the particle over here and over here,
but it depends on the position
of the particle everywhere in between.
So what do you do
with it to find the amplitude?
You integrate or you sum over all possible trajectories.
Sum over all trajectories.
Or,
integral, strictly speaking,
over all trajectories.
This is a monstrously complicated thing.
It's not a simple integral that you can put on,
what's his name,
yeah, Mathematica.
It's an infinite dimensional integral,
a continuously infinite dimensional integral.
So it's a mathematical monstrosity.
I mean,
but,
this integral over here is
just the integral along the trajectory.
That's easy.
That's just the action.
But this integral over here
is the sum over all trajectories.
So the particle feels out all trajectories.
It doesn't sample the one of least action.
You integrate over all of them
this expression
to find the amplitude to go from one to two.
That's the quantum mechanical version
of the principle of least action.
It's Feynman path integral.
You do the same thing in either classical mechan-
in either non-relativistic physics
with this expression
or relativistic physics with that expression.
When you calculate in relativistic physics,
the amplitude to go from one
to two is called the propagator.
It's called the propagator for the
particle to go from one to two.
And you do some fancier things with it.
You, for example, consider processes where
particles come in, join, split, and go out.
A similar kind of action
is defined in terms of the action
for each one of these,
what should we call these, each one of these segments.
You add the action together for each segment
and then you don't sum over just a single trajectory.
You sum over all of these trajectories
and on top of everything else,
you integrate over the points
where the trajectories came together.
So you do the same kind of thing
and it gives you a Feynman diagram.
And then at the end,
to make the whole thing even more complicated,
you sum over all Feynman diagrams for a given process
and that gives you the amplitude,
not for a particle to
go from one point to another,
but for a pair of particles
to come in and go out.
All right.
That's the basic setup of Feynman path integrals.
Before we go into string theory,
let me teach you a trick
that physicists use over and over again.
It's a cheat.
Can it be justified?
In some special cases, it can be justified.
It turns out it can be more easily justified
in string theory
than in quantum field theory.
But I'll tell you what the trick is.
This kind of integral,
this one, this integral,
is sum over trajectories.
It feels out all trajectories.
Let's even concentrate on the nonrelativistic case.
It feels out trajectories which go like this.
It feels out straight trajectories.
And it feels out some wild, wild,
insane trajectories.
Are some of them somehow more important than others?
Of course they are.
The ones which correspond to the classical motion,
the straight line ones,
must be the most important ones.
Otherwise, classical physics wouldn't make sense.
But when you look at the integrand here,
e to the i times anything
always has magnitude what?
One.
So whatever the trajectory is,
they all have equal numerical weight.
They come in with different phases.
The different phases can cancel each other.
If you're adding up numbers on the complex plane,
and all those numbers happen to have unit magnitude,
that doesn't mean they can't cancel.
They can cancel, they can
give rise to a real number,
they can give rise to an imaginary number,
they can do all sorts of things.
But each one of their contributions
is as big as every other contribution.
In that case,
a normal definition of an integral doesn't make sense.
It doesn't converge.
It doesn't converge because the trajectories
which are wildly way out there
and correspond to some very, very distant trajectories,
in some sense,
don't have smaller and smaller amplitude
as the trajectory gets more and more wild.
So, strictly speaking,
these path integrals,
don't really exist as any well-studied mathematical objects.
Okay, so how do we deal with them?
Well, one way of dealing with them
is to be extremely careful,
define integrals in an extremely precise way,
all sorts of reservations and things that are too hard
even for the people who do them to think about.
Really hard.
There's a trick.
There's a trick, and the trick always works.
The trick is one which, to justify it,
is as hard as trying to understand the original integral.
But once you've justified it,
it's the trick which always works
and always gives you the right answer.
So I'm going to tell you what the trick is.
Which shall we take?
Let's take this case here, the relativistic case.
You change the tau variable.
And how do you change it?
You change it very, very simply.
You invent a new variable called s.
And s is just any number times tau.
We'll choose the number alpha later,
to our convenience.
It's just a change of variables.
This is an integration variable.
Incidentally, it goes from tau one to tau two,
and tau one and tau two
are the end points of the trajectory.
But we change variables.
Oh, this s, we shouldn't
confuse this s with the action.
I'm sorry I even called...
Let's call the action, let's give the action another name,
in order to avoid confusion.
You have a little s and
a big S. What's the difference?
You're right.
Little s. Okay?
Little s.
Little s is by definition alpha t.
And what is alpha?
Whatever you want it to be.
We'll pick it later.
Alright, so let's see what we get then.
Dt...
Did I want...
No, I think I'm going to be smarter.
I'm going to set tau equal to alpha times s.
Tau is equal to alpha.
Then I don't have to invert the equation.
Alright, so what does this give us?
This gives us integral n
from s one to s two.
The end points now are...
The end points of the s interval...
The end points of the s interval are of course
just alpha times the end point values for the tau integration.
Okay?
Now we have d tau.
d tau is alpha ds.
And then we have dx.
What's dx by d tau
in terms of dx by ds?
Wherever you see a tau, you stick alpha times s.
That's all.
So this becomes dx by ds squared.
I won't bother writing all the indices mu.
But one over alpha squared.
For each tau, I have to put in alpha s.
So that gives me a one over alpha squared.
So there's alpha squared downstairs.
That's the action.
Alpha downstairs.
Now what do we do with that action?
We put it up into the exponent with an i.
Can you read this?
e to the i one half, I
suppose, if I want to get it right.
Let's just put the one half out here.
We'll keep it out of the way.
The i, of course, is just a
constant that can be brought inside the integral.
And it's i over alpha.
Now it's complete nonsense.
Or at least it needs a
major justification to do this trick.
But what do you think we're
going to choose alpha to be?
i.
i or minus i?
Let's see.
i over i is one, right?
I think I want it to be minus i.
That sounds right.
i over i.
Yeah.
I think I want alpha equals.
I choose it to be minus i.
This becomes i over minus i,
which is also called minus one.
And the whole exponential magically loses its i.
It becomes e to the integral minus.
That's this minus sign from i over minus i.
One half.
So we've got i over minus i.
And here we've got something called the integral.
And this is what we're going to call it.
We're going to call it x by ds squared ds.
The only place that we have to be
a little bit careful is we have to remember
the end points of the interval here
are not really real values of s.
even though the endpoints of
the integral are not real numbers.
Why aren't they real numbers?
Because tau is equal to minus is,
and the endpoints of the original
integral were real values of tau.
But let's forget that.
Let's just call it from s1 to s2.
And later on, we'll remember that
s1 and s2 were imaginary values.
Later on.
For the moment, just leave it this way.
Now we're going to integrate this over all trajectories.
Over all trajectories.
This is much better than the original integral.
In the original integral, no
matter how wild the trajectory was,
the amplitude for that particular
trajectory was in magnitude 1.
Now let's take some wild trajectory.
And stick it in here.
If the trajectory is wild, if it goes off and
extends off to some large spatial separation and comes back,
then there's going to be places where the x
by the s is going to be very large.
If the trajectory is wild in any form whatever,
maybe just because it doesn't even go very far,
maybe it just wiggles extremely rapidly.
Well, that's okay.
That's okay.
The x by the s.
It's going to be very, very large.
It's going to oscillate, but it's
going to be very, very large.
Or maybe it goes off and
then comes back a long distance.
Still, the x by the s will be very, very
large along the orbits where it goes out and comes back.
So for any kind of trajectory that's far
from just the simplest trajectory, namely the straight line,
the action is going to be huge.
it's going to be huge and
it comes in with a negative sign
e to the minus a
large number is a small number
so
in this form
wild trajectories don't contribute very much
only trajectories near the straight trajectory
are important
this is a form of path integral
that is used
in statistical mechanics it's called the wiener integral
it was invented before the finding path integral
and it's perfectly convergent
mathematicians know how to define it in a serious way
and it's a good quantity
so this is what we are always
doing we are always making this trick
of turning a time variable
on its side by making it
i times some time interval, time variable
and then using it in integrals. Now what's the trick?
at the end of the day
this whole thing is going to be some function
of
the end points of the integral
you evaluate this
not paying any attention
to the fact that the
end points of the interval are
imaginary numbers
but then after you have evaluated it
you then
the right word is
I should have said
you can analytically continue it
or extrapolate it to imaginary values of of s
this is something that we know how to do
it's a straightforward procedure if
you actually evaluate these things
for the experts there are analytic functions of s
and you can extrapolate them or analytically continue them
to the desired complex points
this is the only real way
that physicists ever really do path integrals
hear people talking about path integrals,
either they're just talking or if
they're actually trying to perform them,
they're doing them this way by turning
the time variable on its side. All right,
I thought I would tell you that once and
for all, because we're going
to do that in string theory.
So let's come to string theory now. Same kind of setup,
but now a particle is not a point, it's a string.
Its world history is not a world line.
It's a surface. It could be open strings,
in which case it's a surface, a ribbon,
kind of ribbon, a ribbon that can
change its length and change its way it's
embedded in space, but it's a ribbon.
Closed strings, it's not a ribbon, it's a
tube. You can call it a world
tube, usually called a world sheet. That's the
motion of a particle.
Let's talk about the motion of a particle.
Let's talk about its action. We're interested in its action.
Now the kind of question we're going to ask is,
given the location of all of the points on
the string at some initial time and some later
time, what's the amplitude to go from the
initial state to the final state? What's the
amplitude that if you set the string up
in a certain configuration and then let it go,
that you would find it at
a later time at some other configuration?
Now, the location of a point on the
world sheet is a function x of two variables.
One of them is a kind of time
variable along the sheet. We'll call it tau. It's
not real time. It's real time, no
more real time than the tau variable up
here was more like proper time, but
now it's just a parameter. It's just a
parameter. You take the sheet, you coordinate
it with two coordinates, sigma and tau, and
you write x of tau and sigma. We've
done that before. It's a function of two variables.
If you know x mu for each sigma and tau,
then you know where that point on the string is.
And if you're given the whole history of the string
as a x mu of sigma and tau, that does
it. That's the whole history.
Again, you construct an action. Again, you
construct an action, and this time the action
is the immediate generalization of that,
but with two independent variables here. It's
s is equal to integral from, I'm not going
to try to label the starting, it's too complicated
to label the start and the finish. We'll just write what
it is. It's the integral d tau, d sigma, and d tau.
So, you're going to have a function of two
variables. You're going to have a function of two variables.
You're going to have a function of two variables.
Now, what's the integral over the two-dimensional world sheet
of d x mu by d tau squared minus
the x mu by d sigma squared.
I think I have it right.
d x mu by d tau squared minus d x
mu by d sigma squared. That's the action for the string.
And notice this is the action of a field
moving in tau and sigma space. It's just the action
of the wiggles moving up and down the tau
and sigma, but it is also the action for a
tube moving through space-time.
It comes from the fact that tau is, it
comes from the same place, okay, it comes from kinetic
energy minus potential energy.
Kinetic energy minus potential energy.
This is kinetic.
It's like a time derivative.
This is potential energy.
It's like a space derivative.
So it's the fact that the action, the
Lagrangian, has a minus sign, t minus v. Okay.
What do you do with this action?
You exponentiate it.
E to the i.
And then you integrate it over all possible surfaces.
I'm not going to try to draw a complicated surface.
Well, I tried.
I failed.
You integrate it or sum it over all possible surfaces.
Incidentally, .
There's a classical version where you don't
do the path integral, which just tells you
if you start the string in a certain fashion
and end it in a certain fashion, how it has
to move in between to satisfy classical equations of
motion to go from the initial to the final.
But we're not interested in that.
We're interested in quantum mechanics.
This is the amplitude for the string to
go from an initial configuration to a final configuration.
That's the setup.
That's the, if you like,
after all is said and done.
This can pretty much be defined
to be the definition of string theory.
Well, no, it's too simple.
You can generalize the idea.
You say, supposing I'm not interested in a string going to a string,
but two strings going to two strings, or two strings going to three strings.
Then you can generalize it by saying, .
You can generalize it by starting with two strings, ending with three
strings, and drawing all the possible surfaces that can interpolate in between them.
There's a surface that interpolates between them.
There are other surfaces which
interpolate between them with different topology.
You can put a hole in here.
Perfectly legitimate.
But let's concentrate on the ones
without holes in them for the moment.
You can then ask the question, what is the amplitude to start with two strings, each
one in its own given configuration, and end up with three strings also in particular configuration?
The answer is the same.
The answer is e to the i times the integral over
all surfaces which connect the initial state to the final state.
e to the i integral over all
surfaces of the action for that surface.
In a simple case, say an electron going from
one point to another, is vx d sigma zero?
You mean a point electron?
Yeah.
Well, a point electron, if you were dealing with it by finding
integrals before anybody heard of string theory, you wouldn't have any sigma.
You would just have tau.
I think maybe you're asking whether in
some limit or other this reduces to the...
Yeah.
Yeah, that is a good question.
The answer is yes.
As long as the electron is very much lighter than the string scale, and as long as
the energies of the processes are low, then yeah, these things will reproduce Feynman diagrams, ordinary Feynman diagrams.
So, yeah.
They are connected.
That would take us more than a little bit.
Okay, so that's the...
That's practically the definition of string theory.
Incidentally, if you really mean sum over all surfaces that connect
them, including the surfaces that have holes in them of various kinds,
then that's pretty much the analog
of summing over all Feynman diagrams,
with all possible topologies and all
possible number of loops and so forth.
So you're having one simple expression or one simple idea, the
sum over surfaces, you have something which is as complex or as...
Complex is perhaps not the right word.
It's much simpler than Feynman diagrams in many ways.
But it contains as much...the same kind of
information as the sum over all Feynman diagrams.
Okay, but let's forget these holes for the moment and
just concentrate on the structure of this path integral here.
This is a path integral for strings.
Again, it's a monstrosity for the same reason.
Wildly varying surfaces contribute as heavily
as straight surfaces and so forth.
The integral doesn't converge in any meaningful sense,
because again, surfaces which stretch out
to alpha centauri and come back
are no less numerically large in
the amplitude than a nice simple tube.
Alright, so that means we've got to
do something to make this integral make sense.
You can do what a serious mathematician would do, would
be to try to define a new kind of integral.
People have studied that.
Or you can do what a physicist...
would do and say, analytically continue.
Analytically continue.
Last refuge of scoundrels.
And we are going to be scoundrels.
What do we do?
Not...we don't worry about sigma.
Sigma is...is...um...not our problem.
It's actually tau which is
our problem, as we will see.
Let's do the same thing.
Let's let tau go to i tau.
No, I'm not going to call it s.
I'm not going to call it s.
It will just get too many variables.
I'm just going to tell you.
We now make a transformation of
variables from tau to i tau.
Same trick.
When you do, you will
pick up an i from here,
and you will pick up two i's from here.
You won't pick up any i's over here.
So let's follow it.
Each time you see a tau,
you write i tau.
Really, tau is becoming s,
but I don't want to introduce another variable.
So I'm just going to
say tau goes to i tau.
We change variables to i tau.
Then, the first thing that happens is
we pick up an i over here.
That's good because it will get rid of this i.
But then we pick up two i's down here.
What is two i's?
Minus.
So that turns this into minus here.
Same as the minus here.
And gets rid of the i over here.
Now unfortunately, I didn't really mean it
when I said tau goes to i tau.
I meant tau goes to minus i tau.
In which case, we have an extra minus sign here.
Same as for the particle case.
Now look at what we have.
We have something...
Oh, no, I...
No, I have too many minus signs.
Too many minus signs.
I've lost control of the calculation.
No, no, you had i squared.
Is that okay?
That gives you one minus one.
Oh yeah, you had minus i squared.
So you end up with plus signs over there.
And plus sign here.
Minus i squared.
Minus sign here.
Right here?
Oh, no.
Right in front of you.
Whichever one you want, you can get it.
So let's get this one.
Let's get that one.
It's either tau goes to minus i
tau or tau goes to plus i tau.
The reason I want the plus sign here and the minus signs here is
because that allows me to remove the minus signs here and put it out here.
Now why is that?
Now why is that a good thing to do?
It's a good thing to do
because what appears in here is positive.
The more wild the surface is,
the bigger it's going to be.
Even if the surface doesn't fluctuate out to far distances but it just vibrates a lot, then
the xd tau or wiggles too much, if it wiggles too much, the xd sigma will be large.
If it vibrates too much,
the xd tau will be large.
If it stretches out to alpha centauri, both
of them are going to be large and positive.
So one good thing of this trick is it
made these both of the same sign and both positive.
And then e to a minus a positive
number is small or a large positive number.
So what does this do?
It does the same thing that
it did in the particle case.
It suppresses the wildly varying surfaces.
And it allows you to actually calculate the path integral.
I should tell you there's another form of string theory in which
what you put in for the action is more complicated but quite beautiful.
It's actually for both the particle and the string.
There are other forms of the action.
Which are mathematically harder to deal with but
in a certain sense geometrically very, very highly motivated.
For the case of the particle, what you put
in is the proper path length as the action.
The action is just the proper path length
between the initial point and the final point.
The proper path length itself.
And for the string, what you
put in is the space time x.
The space time area of the world sheet.
That's another set up.
Another formal way to do it.
It gives you the same answers but it is
more complicated so I'm not going to do it.
If you ever come across the term Nambu-Goto action, the Nambu-Goto action is the
action which just says stick in for the action the area of the world sheet.
Right.
The other form is sometimes called the particle.
The other form is sometimes called the Polyakov action.
Although it had nothing to do with Polyakov.
It was invented by me.
Which Polyakov constantly keeps telling people.
People like to get credit but they
like to get credit for what they did.
So.
Anyway, it's called the Polyakov action.
And this action here.
Things are named after people who
didn't do them much more often.
Oh.
He did do something else which is related to this.
But that's, the other thing he
did which is closely related to this.
There's some other factors in
it which is also quite beautiful.
Which was invented by Polyakov.
It's called the Leoville action.
Leoville was a mathematician who died
long, long before even classical mechanics.
So don't ask.
The same reason that Polchinski
brains are called Dirichlet brains.
I don't know.
I guess Dirichlet strings were around a long time.
Dirichlet boundary conditions on ordinary
strings were around a long time.
Yeah.
Right.
That's correct.
Okay.
That is the idea of
a path integral for string theory.
Now I want to explain some mathematics.
Some trivial math, not trivial.
It's nice mathematics.
Many of you have seen it before.
Let's see.
Oh.
I forgot.
Yeah.
Let's take a look at this action and
ask what are the things that it's invariant under.
What are the things that it's invariant under?
What kind of transformations in particular of
sigma and tau into new variables is it
invariant under?
Why am I interested in that?
Well, I never told you exactly what
the choice of sigma and tau is.
I didn't tell you how to
choose sigma and tau on here.
You can just draw it any way we please.
Surely, the answer can't be the same
for any choice of sigma and tau.
There must be some rules about what kind
of coordinates I can use on the world sheet.
But are those rules rigid?
They tell you you have to use
these particular coordinates, or is there some invariance,
which allows you to have a
variety of different combinations of coordinates?
Well, the answer is no.
It's just the same thing.
It's just a combination of these two things.
So, the answer is no.
Well, the answer is no.
But are those rules rigid?
They tell you you have to use
these particular coordinates, or is there some invariance,
which allows you to have a variety of
different sets of coordinates, which will all give you
the same answer?
That's the classic problem of
the invariances of a Lagrangian.
What are the invariances of this Lagrangian,
but in particular, what are the invariances
with respect to coordinate transformations?
of the Sigma Tau surface, of the
Sigma Tau parameters. Sigma Tau's are just labels
of points. They don't have
any independent meaning other than just
labels of points. This one is called
George, this one's called Fred, this one's
called Harvey. Clearly the answer can't
depend on whether I rename the points
to Melvin whatever. Okay so what
are the invariances that that are allowed?
So we look at this action and we
ask what kind of what kind of transformations can
we make. Let's look at it a little
more detail here it is the x by
n,
In fact, instead of looking at the action
itself, let's look at the equation of motion,
which would come by varying this action.
Why?
It's just, it's as good as looking at the action.
The equation of motion that would come from
varying this action would look like a wave
equation.
This is basically the action for
a wave equation with one exception.
What's the exception?
The sign here.
Yeah, two positive signs.
Okay.
What's a wave equation?
A wave equation would be d second x by d
tau squared minus d second x by d sigma squared
equals zero.
What do you think the equation
of motion coming from this would be?
Look.
X is some field.
It's a little bit more complex.
It's called the wave equation.
What does it mean?
It's the equation of motion.
It's the equation of motion that's
applied on the tau sigma coordinate space.
Do you know the name of this equation?
It's not called the wave equation.
The Laplace equation.
Two dimensional Laplace equation.
It's the two dimensional Laplace equation.
D second of something with respect
to one variable squared plus d second.
Usually you see it in a different form.
You see the variable x would be replaced
by phi, some function, maybe just f function,
and tau and sigma.
be called x and y. So you'd have an
equation like d second f, or d second phi actually,
yeah, by dx squared plus d second phi
by dy squared equals zero in two dimensions.
In three dimensions you would add another one,
d second phi by dz squared. I'm talking
now not about physics, I'm talking about
the formal structure of equations. You recognize
this equation? Vibrating drum? No, no, okay, I
don't want to get into it. Yeah, you're
partly right, but a vibrating drum also has a
time variable in it. Okay, so I don't want
to get into vibrating drums, but you're
not completely wrong. This equation for the electrostatic
potential, except in the electrostatic potential you
would have a charge density on the right
hand side.
Okay, it's called the Laplace equation, and
now it's a Laplace equation in two dimensions,
except now the variable phi is replaced by x,
and the variable x and y are replaced by
tau and sigma. But otherwise the mathematical
structure of this equation is the same.
Another question? Yeah, question?
Here you have second derivatives,
here you have first derivatives.
Here you have first derivatives, yeah.
But when you have first derivatives in
an action, it gives you second derivatives in
the equation of motion. Just like having x
dot squared in an action gives you x double
dot in the equation. So that's a good question.
Okay, and whether I work with the action or
the equation of motion, it doesn't matter. You get
six of one, half a dozen of the other.
Alright, I just like this form better because
it helps me illustrate a point. Alright, now
let's, what is a second derivative?
Yeah.
Yeah, okay.
Second derivative of x, think of the tau axis as being discrete
now. Just to give you a geometric picture of what this equation means.
Think of the tau axis as being
discrete with little separations epsilon between neighboring points.
What is a first derivative? A first derivative is, let's
call this point one, let's call one, two, and three.
A first derivative is called a second derivative.
A second derivative is called a second derivative.
Because it represents a number of points
and also its derivative is closely related to
the difference of a quantity at neighboring points.
Alright, so the first derivative would be like
x of three minus x of two. You divide
it by epsilon, but the, this, this is
not the important thing. Let's divide it by epsilon.
Epsilon is the distance between the points, and
then you let the epsilon go to zero. And
that gives you the first derivative. Let's
not worry about the epsilons right now. That's
not the point. A first derivative
is like the difference of something at
neighboring points. If that's what a
first derivative is, what is a second
derivative? A second derivative is
difference of first derivatives. Alright,
so a second derivative is x3
minus x2, that's the first derivative evaluated
between these two points, minus the
first derivative evaluated one step over. So
that's minus x of 2 minus x of
1. That's the analog, the discrete analog of the
second derivative. Let's see what it is. It's x3,
x of 3 plus x of 1 minus twice x
of 2.
So what is x of 2?
It's the sum of the quantities on
the outer edges minus twice the quantity in
the center. That's a second derivative.
Let's look at the thing which occurs
in the Laplace equation here. Instead of
taking the tau axis to be discrete,
let's take the tau sigma plane to be
discrete. The tau sigma plane is discrete now.
And let's see if we can
geometrically identify what this equation means.
Let's go to a point over here. A
point over here, the second derivative of x
with respect to tau is x at this point
plus x at this point minus twice x at
the center. That's what we just figured out. Let's label the
points. 1, 2, 3, 4, and at the center we'll call 5.
1, 2, 3, 4, and
at the center we'll call 5.
So d second x by d tau squared, that's x of
1 plus x of 3 minus twice x at 5, right?
How about d second x with respect to sigma squared?
Oh, sorry, did I make a mistake here?
Well, okay, it depends on which way I think of
tau and sigma. I guess I have in this picture here.
I guess I have tau
going horizontally and sigma going vertically.
I don't usually think about it
that way, but that's all right.
So x of the second derivative with respect to
tau is this one plus this one minus this one.
How about the second derivative with respect to sigma?
That's going to be this one plus
this one minus twice x of 5.
So we get to add in plus.
We get to add in plus x of 2 plus
x of 4 minus twice x of 5 equals 0.
Well, that's not so bad.
x of 1 plus x of 3
plus x of 4 plus x of 2.
x of 1, 3, 2, and 4.
So we get the sum of the x's on the points surrounding x of
5 minus 4 times the sum, sorry, 4 times x at 5 equals 0.
Another way to say it is that x of 1 plus
x of 2 plus x of 3 plus x of 4.
equals 4x at 5.
4x at 5.
Or yet another way to say it is that
x at 5 is the average of the x's on.
That's what the Laplace equation says.
It's true in higher dimensions also.
That's what the Laplace equation says, that at
any point if you're surrounded by a square,
and even though this thing is
on its side, it is a square,
any square, any small square, any infinitesimal square,
that if you evaluate the field,
at the sum of the field at the corners,
that the field at the center
is the average at the corners.
Now, the square doesn't have to be oriented this way.
It's well known that this equation is
invariant under rotations of the sigma-tau plane.
So, you can say it even more geometrically.
Take any square, any square oriented
in any way, any small square.
This is of course only true for infinitesimal squares.
For any small infinitesimal square,
the field at the center is the
average of the field at the corners.
That's an invariant way,
apart from the fact that
you have to think about limits,
which makes it a little more complicated,
apart from that limiting procedure that you have to do,
that's an invariant way to
say what the Laplace equation is,
and it's an invariant way
to describe the equation of motion,
the classical equation of motion of this thing here.
Okay, so now I can tell
you exactly what the invariance structure
of the Laplace equation or of this action is.
It's the class of transformations of the sigma-tau plane
which take every infinitesimal
square into an infinitesimal square.
If under coordinate transformations of the sigma-tau plane,
squeezings and mappings of the sigma-tau plane,
if it takes every small square
into a small square,
then the Laplace equation will
be unchanged in the new coordinates.
So, if we have some new coordinates,
let's call it sigma prime,
which is a function of sigma and tau,
and tau prime, which are functions of sigma and tau.
If it is true that any small sigma-tau square
maps into, this is the sigma plane,
sigma-tau plane,
we map it now to the sigma prime-tau plane,
most mappings will not take squares to squares.
They'll take squares to something else.
But there's a special class of mappings
which take squares to squares.
Anybody know the name of such mappings?
Conformal mappings.
Now, let me express it another way.
If I have a transformation which preserves angles,
if all angles are preserved,
then it will be a conformal transformation.
It will take squares to squares.
Why?
Well, first of all,
let's take the diagonals
and map them to the sigma-tau plane,
so to the sigma prime-tau prime plane.
There'll be little short segments
oriented in some other direction.
And let's suppose that all angles are preserved
under this mapping.
Any angle between two curves
becomes the same angle
among the sigma prime,
the prime plane.
Then, first of all,
orthogonal angles here
will go to orthogonal angles here.
This is not true of any whole transformation.
It's true of some class of transformations,
the angle-preserving transformations.
Now, we can say something else.
Supposing that it had this property
of taking perpendiculars in here
to perpendiculars,
but it stretched things out in one direction.
In other words,
it made a kind of an elongated kite
out of a little square.
Then there would be other angles
which weren't preserved.
These angles over here would be changed.
This angle at this corner would not...
If this is a 45-degree angle,
if it stretched the square in some way,
it would not remain a 45-degree angle.
So, conclusion.
Angle-preserving transformations
preserve little squares,
take little squares to little squares.
Wouldn't that just be basically rotational?
What's that?
Wouldn't that just be basically a rotation?
Locally, it's only a rotation,
but it can bend the coordinates.
No, it's not just rotations.
Remember, we're only demanding
that infinitesimal little squares
remain infinitesimal little squares.
But now we can say it
without using the word infinitesimal.
If the transformation has the property
that the angle between any intersecting...
pair of curves on the sigma-tau plane
maps into the same angle
on the sigma-prime-tau-prime plane,
then that mapping is conformal.
Conformal mappings preserve...
They preserve angles,
but since they preserve all angles,
for sufficiently small shapes...
For sufficiently small shapes,
you can think of the curves as being straight lines.
And it's easy to prove
for sufficiently small shapes,
that shapes themselves are preserved.
Sizes are not preserved.
A small square over here
can map to a bigger square over here.
No, I didn't draw.
You know what I mean.
Sizes can be preserved.
Sizes can be...
Can also be preserved in addition.
Then we're talking about
the rotations and translations.
Yeah.
Right.
That's our much, much smaller class of transformations.
Now, here we're talking just about
the angle-preserving transformations,
and they can expand and contract shapes.
In fact, they can expand and contract differently
in different regions of the plane.
Over here, a shape might
get stretched to a bigger shape.
get squashed to a smaller shape.
Question.
Yeah.
Would this conformal mapping be equivalent to saying
the coordinate system is flat?
No.
Nope.
Conformally flat, no.
I don't know.
What do you mean by coordinate system being flat?
You mean Cartesian?
That it's not curved,
otherwise the angles wouldn't be preserved.
No.
Where is this trick of conformal mappings used?
Mercator projection.
Well, any projection,
any projection of a map,
which is intended to preserve the shape of islands,
continents, and so forth, small ones,
but doesn't care about the sizes of things,
that's a conformal mapping.
So the relationship between different maps,
different projections,
both of which preserve shapes,
but not sizes,
is always a conformal mapping.
Yeah.
Last week you said,
when we were looking at the stream scattering,
that at the end you had enough freedom
to assume that the stream when it's split again
was kind of in half.
And is that related to this?
Yeah.
We will.
All right, since you asked me,
I will tell you right now what the relationship is.
Okay.
I was going to tell you
a little bit about analytic functions,
but maybe we'll come back to that.
Coordinate transformations,
which are defined by analytic functions
of complex variables,
are angle preserving.
We may come back to that.
Okay.
Oh, incidentally,
there is one situation
where angles are not necessarily preserved.
It's a curious one.
You can take any figure with a boundary,
let's say a square,
a big square now,
not an infinitesimal square,
a finite size square,
and map it by conformal mapping
to any shape you like.
But in particular,
you could map it to a,
this doesn't look very square,
you can map it to a,
let's say,
this is a square.
And you can map it to a,
let's say,
to a,
something like that.
So wait a minute,
you said that they have to preserve angles.
This doesn't look like it preserves the angles.
Well, first of all,
it only preserves infinitely small shapes.
You can map this to this by conformal mapping,
but the corners will not go to the corners.
The corners here will perhaps go to these points.
Okay, so conformal mappings are tricky.
You can map any shape with a boundary
to any other shape with the same boundary.
This is a theorem about analytic mappings.
And inside the region,
any small shape will map to
a shape of the same kind.
Any small shape here will map
to a shape of the same kind here,
in the interior of the mapping.
So this is something to know,
that you can do some things
with changing the shapes of boundaries of regions.
Okay, having said that now,
let me come to what the point is.
Last time,
we talked about strings splitting and joining.
I drew a picture for you
where two strings came in,
and I indicated that by making a slit.
Take a ribbon,
make a slit down the ribbon,
until that slit comes to an end point.
Those are two separate strings
joining at this point
and making one long string.
And then continuing again
after it splits again like that.
There's a one-parameter family
of such splittings and joinings,
characterized by the time interval,
or the tau interval,
between this point and that point.
In the end,
if you're calculating a scattering amplitude,
you'll integrate over it.
You get some integral,
and that integral gave you
the beta function,
the Euler beta function,
or the Veniziano amplitude,
however you want to call it.
We wrote,
I described it for you last time,
and it gives you the scattering amplitude
in string theory.
Important fact,
but,
not really terribly central right now.
Okay, what's going on in here?
What's going on in here
is we have a two-dimensional space,
we can call it sigma tau.
There's sigma tau.
And we have at each point in this space
we have an x,
not just one x,
but several x,
a family of x's,
x mu of sigma and tau.
And they satisfy some kind of equations.
In fact,
we have a series of equations
that we call sigma tau.
And they're called sigma tau.
And they satisfy some kind of equations.
In fact,
what kind of equations do they satisfy?
They satisfy the Laplace equation.
Now actually,
technically they satisfy the wave equation.
But if you do this trick
and carry out the path integrals
by letting tau go to i tau,
then the x's in here satisfy the Laplace equation.
What does that tell you?
It tells you that you can map,
here we have a shape,
here we have a piece of a plane.
It goes out to infinity along here.
Think of it as being slit down the center here.
And think of it as
being slit down the center here.
What's the topology of this region here?
I'll tell you what the topology of this region is.
The topology of this region is a circle,
but with some special,
why is it a circle?
Let's start at the center of a circle
and work outward with a series of circles.
It's a bull's eye.
Let's start at the center of this and work outward.
I can do this in such a way
as to cover the whole space
by a sequence of closed curves
which are isomorphic to the circles.
In other words, I have taken the bull's eye
and deformed it,
but without changing its topology,
I have changed it into this double strip,
a line,
with these points over here.
It depends on what happens out there.
There's some exceptional points
in the exceptional points
are the infinite endpoints there and there.
You can do this mapping.
This mapping exists.
You'll have to remember that
there were some exceptional points
which have to be...
We have to know what
to do with those exceptional points.
But the answer is that the, I don't know
what to call this shape, what should we call it?
The slit strip, the doubly
slit strip, okay that's a mouthful.
Band-aid.
The what?
The band-aid.
No, no, no, no, it's cut down the
middle there so it's not quite a band-aid.
No, the sports band-aid where they have the wing.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, the sports
band-aid shape, yeah, good, right, good.
Except that it's the infinite sports band-aid shape.
Okay, that's not much better than the doubly slit strip.
The infinite sports band-aid.
The infinite sports band-aid can be
conformally mapped, conformally mapped to the circle,
or to the disc, to the disc.
The disc is a circle.
It's the disc.
It's the interior of a circle.
So, that means in principle we can take the
wave equation or we can take the Laplace equation
or the action even of the action of the
string, the path integral for the string, the entire setup,
and rewrite it in a form in which
the x's all live on a unit circle.
Where the x's all live on a unit circle.
There's something special about these four points here
where the particles came in and went out.
And I'm going to eventually tell
you what that special thing is.
You can map it to here.
Of course you can map it to here.
But you can map it to here
without changing the form of the equation.
It's still just a Laplace equation.
The Laplace equation for the x's in here
is the transform of the Laplace
equation for the x's in here.
Okay.
And that's because of the
conformal invariance of the Laplace equation.
Yeah, because of the conformal
invariance of the Laplace equation.
So, you could set up the string path integral
in a new way by taking a unit disc,
thinking of a set of x's
which live in the unit disc,
and integrating over all ways, all
x's that live on this unit disc.
In other words, yeah, I think you understand.
x of sigma and tau,
where sigma and tau are not on the
sports band aid, but they're on the disc.
Writing the action as the same kind of action,
the path integrating over the x's in here,
with some special things going
on at these four exceptional points.
I think I won't get into what the exception...
There's nothing very complicated about it,
and we will get to it,
we will certainly get to it.
Technically, or in the jargon is,
you have to put some vertex
operators at the point over here,
but we'll come to that, alright?
But you could also have stretched that out into other
shapes. You could have stretched that out into a shape
which looked like this
which went off to infinity
So it looks actually more like a scattering process
There are many things you
could have stretched it out into
Now
Let's take a break
All right, now
In mapping this problem to this problem
Now by this problem, I mean
the problem of calculating the scattering amplitudes
There is something that you have to
do out at these infinite points here
to set up and specify the initial and
final states of the particles that are coming in
Their momenta, their particle types
Are they the ground states?
Are they the first excited states?
Somewhere in here
There's some input of information that's above and beyond
just saying that there's a Laplace equation in here
That input of information has to do with
something or other that we do out near the
Out near the ends here
I'm not sure how to draw that
Just some input at the end flaps of the
Of the band-aid
That same input has to be put into this diagram
We have to say what kind
of particles, what is their momentum
I'm not going to tell you exactly
how to do that at the moment
I will tell you eventually
But it's some operation that you do on each one
of these points to inject in a certain amount of momentum
And some information about the particle type
So keep that in mind
Alright, now where exactly do we
put those points, those four points?
In this diagram it's clear where we put them
We put them out at
the end flaps of the band-aid
In this diagram it's less clear
And I will tell you what is correct
In mapping this to here
You forget for a moment the ends
You have some ambiguity
For example you could rotate it
You can do some other things to it
But you also have enough ambiguity
That you can arbitrarily choose
That there's really only one parameter
In the relationship between the four points on here
One parameter, all the other
It looks like there are really several parameters
You could arbitrarily pick by rotating
the angles the position of this point
But then there would be the
length or the distance to here
The angular distance to here
And the angular distance to here
No
You can find conformal transformations
Which will move the boundary points around in various ways
And the end result is there is really only
Up to a conformal transformation
There's only a one parameter family of such configurations
And we could describe the parameters by saying
I'll arbitrarily choose left-right symmetry
That's a choice
And I'll also choose
Vertical symmetry
And I can choose this point over here
Since I've used
Since I've decided to make the
diagram both left-right and up-down symmetric
I have to choose the other point over here
Over here and over here
In a completely symmetric way
But that still allows a freedom
Here's one extreme situation
Here's another extreme situation
What determines where you put the points
Whether it looks like this, like this, or like that
The answer is the time interval between here and here
Which is also a one parameter family of figures
Right?
The time interval over here
is one parameter family of figures
The time interval or really strictly speaking
The ratio of the time
interval to the separation along here
Or the time interval between the
tau interval between here and here
Is the one parameter that
governs where you put these points
You have to integrate over it
Just as we integrated over the time separation
This is part of the path integral
We integrated over the time separation
Between the joining and the splitting
That translates into a one parameter integral
Over, we can choose it in many ways
But in this case, with this particular setup
It's a one parameter integral
over how we choose these points
My fingers aren't big enough
to stretch to this configuration here
But if we had two of us up here
I would move my fingers like that
And you would move your fingers like that
And then we'd spread them
out and go the other way
That integral is still to be done
And it's that integral
When you work out
The path integral
And then integrate over the positions
of the points in the right way
That's what gives you the beta function
In this language, the beta
function comes from integrating the positions
Of the injection points
Let's call them injection points
Positions of the injection points
Over a one parameter family
There are two extreme situations
One extreme situation
Is this
The other extreme situation is like this
In this extreme situation
The two input points on the left
Are close together
In the other configuration over here
This one and this one are close together
Now, this, these two extremes
Must translate to some extremes on the band-aid
It does
The extreme where the two incident particles
Appear adjacent to each other
And the two outgoing particles appear adjacent to each other
That
Is the conformal mapping
Of the configuration where the time interval here
Is very, very long
And so it looks like these
two points are much, much closer
Uh, than the distance between here and here
That's the, if you like, the mapping
From the band-aid to the circle
Of the configuration
Where the intermediate state lasts a long time
It's the same thing
But it's a situation that manifestly looks like
Two particles coming in
Forming a string that vibrates many vibrations
And then goes off again
That's this limit
What's the other limit?
Well, the other limit is exactly the other limit
Where the time interval is very, very short
The intermediate state lasts a very short time
But the course of time changes
And that's this shouting
Yep
Well, that's better
Here the mistake on the over-line
O-line
There's no integration
This basically looks like the transverse
So, in this case
You have one on the x-axis
Okay
Which should be enough
Oh, you have an Janel
Ok
This should understand
I've earmarked some words
If I hit that
Okay
So this, it's very very easy
symmetry, that there's some symmetry. From this
picture over here, it's hard to see that
there's any symmetry between these two
extreme limits. Two physically totally different pictures.
One, an intermediate state lasts a long
time, and the other, an intermediate state lasts
a very short time. It doesn't look like
there's much symmetry. But from this picture here,
you see that somehow there is a symmetry,
that they must be related to each other in
some way. How are they related to each other?
The rotation of sigma and tau.
Well, that's not the point though. They're
related by the interchange of what we called
last time the s variable and the t variable.
Remember what the s variable was? It was the
sum of the four momenta coming in squared,
or the center of mass energy squared. If we
label these with momenta, then the s
variable, k1, k2, and k3, are the same.
k2, k3, k4.
Then the Mandelstam variable. The Mandelstam s
variable was k1 plus k2 squared, and it
corresponded to the square of the center of mass energy.
Well, let's write that it's equal to the
Mandelstam s variable. This is not the action, and
it's not any other s that I used
tonight. It's the Mandelstam s variable, s. And it's
also equal to the square of the
center of mass energy, center of mass.
On the other hand, it's quite clear that we've
done what we've done in going from here to
here.
We started to use the sh desk term. We
used the sh desk term all the time and Problem
Adam gave me one time ago so
I might have given you two times.
All we're doing isたpositivelyありparogam Come
forward and leave the form form.
We're all right will there be some arguing.
So it's not to be anxious about that.
So okay.
Okay.
center of mass energy, it's some
combination of center of mass energy,
E center of mass squared minus M squared
times I think 1 minus the cosine of the
angle of scattering or something. But it
is just k1 plus k3 squared, where all
moment there are counted as coming in.
In this form, it's manifestly clear that
these diagrams have symmetry between the S
channel and the T channel. It's also clear
that if they have, if they describe
particles forming and decaying in the S
channel, two particles coming in, forming
and decaying, they must also describe a
process where the two incoming particles
are replaced now by one incoming one
and two incoming ones. And then they have
a symmetry between the two. And so, if you
have one outgoing and a particle is
exchanged, not the creation and annihilation of a
particle, but an emission and reabsorption at
the other side of the diagram. So, that's
what was so fascinating about these
structures, is that one structure, one simple
structure, one integral, but one basic principle
was accounting for both the S channel
and the T channel particles. The S
channel particles were somehow associated with long
diagrams like this, and the T channel ones
were short ones. But we don't have to interpret,
we just say the integral was symmetric under S
goes to T. And so, whatever was there in
the form of S particles formed
by k1 plus k2 coming together,
there was also T channel objects which were formed
by k1 and k3 coming together. That was called
duality. That was the first duality, the duality
between the S channel and the T channel. Now,
these days, it's called channel duality. Channel,
in this case, means either, it's clear what
it means. It's called channel duality, and it was the first sort of, at
first it was a miracle. At first, when thought about in terms of band-based
diagrams, it was a miracle that there was a symmetry between S channel and T
channel. It was very quick that it was realized that this was because of conformal symmetry,
and that you could map it to this more symmetric situation. But at first, at first sight, it just
looked like a miracle. The trouble with understanding miracles is it always has the same effect. You know, you're
you may now understand it, but
you no longer go gaga over it.
When was it?
Hm? 1969.
If you were to draw that second one, the one that goes down, I can understand how
the top one corresponds to the band-aid. Is there a band-aid that corresponds to the second one?
Well, yeah, you could have drawn the diagram the
other way. You could have drawn it this way.
It would still be going?
Okay.
Horizontally?
No.
Yeah, you could have, well, yes.
How would that?
Well, no, time comes in here. Well, no, no, no, no, no, no, no. In that case, you could not have thought of time as running horizontally. You
would have to say this was the deep remote past over here, and this was the deep remote future over here. But you could have drawn it that way.
For some reason, I think of the time
that they're together being related to the coupling constant.
Okay.
No, no, no, no. The time that they're together, you have to integrate over. That's something you integrate over. I think what you're trying to say is that the probability for
it to decay is related to the coupling constant. Yeah. But in either case, no matter what, you still, that just means you have to put into the integral the coupling constant.
And, but no, it, these diagrams are not the same.
I think the coupling constant just
comes in as a multiplicative factor.
And, right. Okay, I think that's enough for tonight.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.