Stanford University
Let's talk more about conformal mappings.
These are very interesting in their own right.
They are widely applicable to
all kinds of mathematical physics problems.
The most direct is electrostatic
problems, electrostatic problems in two dimensions.
There are problems in theoretical physics which are
mathematically equivalent to the electrostatic problem in two dimensions.
When I say incidentally the electrostatic problem in two dimensions, I
don't mean that you have particles, charges moving in two dimensions
which interact with each
other with three-dimensional Coulomb forces.
I mean particles which move around, electric charges which
interact with each other with mathematical two-dimensional Coulomb forces.
Does anybody know what the Coulomb
force between particles is in two dimensions?
One over r?
One over r, not one over r squared.
How about the potential energy between a pair of particles?
You'd have to integrate that.
Logarithm.
Logarithm because the derivative of logarithm is one over r.
So in a world, a literal world,
where the lines of flux can't escape out into the
third dimension, which are really forced to lie in the plane,
in such a world electrostatic problems would have Coulomb forces
which were one over r instead of one over r squared,
and the equations of electrostatics would be two-dimensional
versions of the corresponding equations in three dimensions.
What are the equations of electrostatics?
Let's just write them down
on the blackboard for a moment.
What do you describe an electrostatics problem by?
You describe it of course by an electric field.
But there's something simpler than
the electric field. What is it?
Electric field is a vector. What's simpler than a vector?
Charges.
Well, charges, but a scalar.
A scalar.
The electrostatic potential,
the electrostatic potential, which is
sometimes, it goes under different names,
but let's call it phi.
What's the connection between phi and the electric field?
The gradient of phi is the electric field.
Alright, so the gradient of phi is the electric field.
And what's the equation for
the electric field in electrostatics?
Divergence of the electric field is?
The charge density.
The charge density, right.
Charge density on the right-hand side,
or rho.
And we can rewrite that in terms of phi
by writing that it's, I'll write
this out in detail in a moment,
del squared phi equals rho.
Del dot phi is e.
Del dot e equals rho.
So del squared phi.
And what does del squared phi mean?
If we're in a two-dimensional world,
literally a two-dimensional world,
let's say with coordinates little x and little y,
then what is del squared?
Del squared is the second derivative
of phi with respect to x squared,
plus the second derivative of
phi with respect to y squared.
And that on the right-hand side is rho.
If there's charge density, it's not zero,
but in places where there is no charge density,
in places where there is
no charge density, it's just zero.
You remember last time, I think it was last time,
we talked about this equation and its invariances.
Conformal invariance.
This equation,
this equation is invariant or unchanged
by any change in the x, y coordinates,
any transformation to new coordinates,
x, y coordinates,
such that that transformation is conformal.
Conformal means?
Angle-preserving.
In other words, that when you make a transformation,
when you, the angles,
well, let's just say the
angles in the new coordinate system
are perpendicular,
and that angles in new coordinates are exactly the same.
Angles between curves in new coordinates
are the same as between the old coordinates.
Conformal mappings.
Those are conformal mappings,
and they are the kind of mappings that cartographers use
in order to preserve the shapes
and the angles on a map,
although they cannot in general
preserve the sizes of things.
Okay, so that's an example of a,
of a place where conformal mappings occur.
Other places?
Fluid flow in two dimensions.
These are also equations of fluid flow.
All kinds of problems,
at least approximately,
are described by Laplace's equation.
When the Laplacian is zero, you have a standing wave?
No, no, this is not wave equations.
These are not wave equations because
they have a plus sign there.
These are electrostatic equations,
and they don't describe wave motion.
You have to add, if you want waves,
you've got to add in the T dependence.
So there's a reason
why we call electrostatics electrostatics.
Because nothing is moving, right, including the waves.
Can you have, is there
a curl in two dimensions also?
There is a curl in two dimensions.
It's a good question.
Let's come back to it when,
well, yes, there is a curl in two dimensions.
The curl in two dimensions is
if you have a field like E,
which has two components,
let's say E sub x and E sub y,
the curl only has one component.
In a two-dimensional world, the curl has one component,
and it is derivative of
E x with respect to y
minus the derivative of E y with respect to x.
That's the component of the curl.
You could think of it
as the component of the curl
in the direction perpendicular to the blackboard.
But, you know, you can be in two-dimensional worlds
where there is no direction perpendicular to the blackboard.
So just think of it as the curl.
The curl becomes a one-component object
in kind of scalar in two dimensions.
It's only in three dimensions
that the curl is a vector.
In higher dimensions, it's a vector.
In higher dimensions, it's something else.
It's a two-form.
Okay, let's talk a little bit more about conformal mappings.
As I said, they are very interesting.
What they allow you to do, incidentally,
is from the solution of a problem,
an electrostatics problem, for example,
on some kind of space,
some sort of space perhaps with boundaries,
with some boundary conditions,
you can derive an infinite number of other solutions
with problems with other boundary conditions
just by mapping the surface
and taking the solution with you
and mapping the solution to
a new solution by conformal mapping.
So, as I say, there's all sorts of applications
of conformal mapping to electrostatics problems.
We're going to come back
to electrostatics tonight at some point,
but let's talk more about conformal mappings.
A conformal mapping is a mapping of the plane,
the xy plane, or the plane to itself.
So here's a Cartesian plane described by x and y,
and let's use a complex coordinate,
z equals x plus iy.
Okay.
So this is our usual complex plane,
or our usual complex notation representing the plane.
Now, we want to do a
mapping of the plane to itself,
or a coordinate transformation of the plane.
Here's the w plane over here.
w is equal to u plus iv.
This is u and this is v.
Incidentally, for obvious reasons,
x is called the real part of z,
and z is called the imaginary part,
likewise for u and v.
And a mapping from the
x plane to the w plane
is just a rule given
any point in x and y
assigned to it a unique,
and let's assume the mappings are one to one,
in other words, for every point on the x plane,
there is a unique point on the w plane,
and likewise,
for each point in the w plane,
there is a unique point in the x plane.
That means any point,
Hm?
Did I say it wrong?
No, no, you know what I meant.
For any point on the w plane,
there's a unique point on the z plane,
and for any point on the z plane,
there's a unique point on the .
Okay.
This means you can take any point
and represent it either by coordinates x and y,
or by coordinates u and v,
and in that sense it's just a coordinate transformation.
U and v are functions of x and y,
or you can say that
w is a function of z.
So let's think of it, and vice versa,
but for today I'm going to think
of w as a function of z.
Given a point z on the complex plane,
it uniquely picks out a point w.
These are complex functions,
both the argument of a function z,
and the function itself w,
are complex numbers.
Alright.
Now there is a calculus of complex functions like this,
called complex variable theory,
and let's just spend a few moments on it.
There's both an integral and a differential calculus,
but we're going to concentrate on the differential calculus.
Given a function w,
we can try to define a derivative,
w of z.
We can try to define a unique derivative,
and here's the way we would do it.
Start at a point z,
and at every point z,
that corresponds to some point over here, w.
Let's move the point z a little bit,
to z plus delta z.
Here's z,
and move the point to z plus delta z.
When you do so,
w will move to w plus delta w.
Here's w,
here's w plus delta w.
What is the derivative of w with respect to z,
at the point z?
Well, the answer is obvious.
It is delta w,
divided by delta z,
in the limit that delta z goes to zero.
Usual logic of what a derivative is,
it's the difference between
the function at neighboring points,
divided by the difference between
the coordinates at neighboring points.
There's only one problem,
something new.
You can approach the point z
from any direction,
and it's not at all clear that in general,
even if the function is nice and continuous,
and has all sorts of good continuity properties,
it's not obvious that when you calculate the ratio,
delta w by delta z,
and then shrink the size of this,
that the answer will be independent
of which direction you're coming in from.
You might get one answer
if you come in from here,
you might get another answer
if you come in from here.
So the question then is,
what is the condition?
If you want to have a nice mathematical framework
for complex functions,
and you want to have
the notion of a unique derivative,
maybe there is no good definition of the derivative,
but let's see what the conditions are
that the derivative,
the limit of delta w over delta z,
exists and is independent of
which direction you come in from.
Now I'm going to show you a sufficient condition,
you can go home and prove it's a necessary condition,
it is a necessary condition,
and it's almost as easy to
prove as what we will do,
but I'll leave it to you for homework.
To prove, what I'm going to do
is work out the necessary condition
by asking that the ratio,
delta w over delta z,
is the same if you come in from the x-axis
along the x-axis,
or if you come in along the y-axis.
In other words, if your delta z
is along the x-axis or along the y-axis,
that you get the same answer.
It is then not hard to prove
that if that's satisfied,
that no matter what direction you come in from,
you get the same answer.
So I'll do the simple thing,
you can do the slightly more complicated thing,
it's only a little bit of algebra,
but I don't like doing
too much algebra on the blackboard.
Okay, let's calculate
delta w by delta z.
Now first of all, what is delta w?
w is u plus iv.
Why don't we, let's not be babies,
let's call it dw by dz.
Whenever I teach pre-meds,
I'm not allowed to use calculus.
And so every time there's a derivative,
we call it delta w by delta z or whatever,
and then we're not officially using calculus,
and that's illegal.
But then I secretly tell them,
you realize that's a derivative,
and they say, yeah, yeah, we know.
But I'm always afraid if I use it
that they'll tell ombudsmen that I'm using calculus,
and I'm not going to use calculus in class.
Okay, so the change in w
divided by the change of z,
and what of course is that?
That's equal to the derivative of,
or the change, the small change in u
plus the small i times the small change in v
as you go from here to here.
Derivative of the differential of u plus iv
divided by the differential of x plus i.
Okay.
dy.
Okay, that's very straightforward.
Now let's calculate it if
I come in along the x-axis.
If I come in along the x-axis,
then dy is equal to zero.
Okay?
dy is equal to zero if
I come in along the x-axis,
and so this must equal,
coming in along the x-axis,
it must equal du by dx plus i d.
Okay?
So I'm going to calculate the derivative of u
plus i dv by dx.
Since we're keeping y fixed and not varying y,
this is the same as the partial derivative of u
with respect to x
plus i times the partial derivative of v
with respect to x.
Oops.
With respect to x.
Okay, is that clear?
Good.
Now let's come in along the y-axis.
dx is equal to zero.
dy is not zero.
And the partial derivatives are
partial derivatives with respect to y.
So let's see what that has to equal.
If, under the presumption,
that dw by dz doesn't depend
on which direction you come in from.
Okay, so let's see what we have to have.
Then we have to have
1 over i.
The 1 over i comes from the i.
dx is going to be zero.
There's a 1 over i from the 1 over i.
multiplying dy.
And then we'll have partial
of u with respect to y.
And then i over i
will just give you derivative
of v with respect to y.
u and v are real.
I neglected to say so.
It may have been obvious.
u and v are real.
It's w which is complex.
x and y are real.
z is complex.
It's at least a necessary condition.
It happens to be sufficient also.
But it's at least a necessary condition
that this expression equals this expression.
Necessary for what?
Necessary that the derivative
not depend on which direction you're coming in from.
Okay?
Now, so let's take the real and imaginary part.
Whenever you have an equation,
that involves real and imaginary parts,
it really stands for two equations.
Equating the real part and equating the imaginary part.
So, let's start with the real part.
Here's a real part.
That's got to equal this.
du by dx must equal bv by dy.
And what about the other one?
The other one says,
let's see,
that's the real part.
Here's the imaginary part.
Let's put it over here.
idv by dx equals 1 over i du by dy.
idv by dx has to be
1 over i du by dy.
That's equating the imaginary parts.
Let's multiply both sides by i
and use the fact that i squared is minus 1.
So we get two equations.
There are two,
they're not the same incidentally,
look at them.
One says du by dx equals dv by dy.
And the other says du
by dy equals dv by dx.
No, minus dv by dx.
One of them has a minus sign,
the other doesn't.
If these equations are not true,
then the derivative doesn't exist
in a meaningful and unique way.
If they are both true,
then the function w of z has a derivative,
and the derivative is well defined,
and the function is called analytic.
Just a name.
When a function,
on a complex function of a complex variable,
has a unique derivative from every direction,
it's called analytic at that point.
If it's analytic everywhere,
then it's called entire.
All sorts of names,
meromorphic, holomorphic,
I never understood what they meant.
Holomorphic is analytic.
No, meromorphic allows poles and...
Holomorphic is the same as analytic.
Yeah, holomorphic is the same as analytic.
I think that's right,
I don't remember.
There's fancy names for everything.
I've learned recently that a mapping
which takes a point to a point
is called a bijection or something.
That's right.
Well, we do diffeomorphisms and all that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
these coordinate transformations of diffeomorphisms.
Right, but all they are is coordinate transformations.
Nice smooth ones.
Okay, so we have now the necessary and sufficient conditions
for a function to be analytic,
every place where these are satisfied.
Let's look at these equations a little more,
just for fun,
see what they say.
They're coupled equations for u and v.
Can we uncouple them and
write an equation just for u
and an equation just for v?
Yes, we can.
Here's the trick.
Let's differentiate this equation with respect to x.
That gives us d second u,
by dx squared,
the second partial derivative with respect to x,
and that's equal to dv,
that's equal to the second derivative of v
with respect to x,
with respect to y.
The mixed partial derivative with respect to x and y.
Let's differentiate this one with respect to y.
That's d second u,
by dy squared.
That's equal to minus
d second v,
by dx by dy.
That's the same as that except for a minus sign,
so it follows that we can eliminate it,
and one equation is d second u,
by dx squared,
minus, sorry,
this is u.
Yeah, no, no, we just, we have to,
just add them.
Add them and the right hand side will go away.
Well, that's a familiar equation.
That's just Laplace's equation in two dimensions.
So, a necessary condition.
Well, something looks a little like your curl equation, too.
It does.
So it's something, sort of, curl-ish.
Well, that's,
this one,
yeah, that sort of is it,
is it, is it the derivative is curl-free,
in some sense.
Yeah.
One of them is curl and the other is divergence,
depending on which way you define the components.
Uh,
yeah, if you think of u
and v as components of a vector,
actually you have to think of u and minus v
as the components of a vector,
then what it says is
that the curl and the divergence,
and the divergence of the vector vanishes.
Okay, so that's this equation,
and if you do exactly the same thing,
we differentiate this one now,
instead of with respect to x,
we differentiate it with respect to y,
and differentiate this one with respect to x,
what we get is exactly the same equation for v,
d second v by dx squared,
plus d second v by dy squared,
equals zero.
So first of all, an analytic function,
w of z,
contains two real solutions of the Laplace equation.
That's interesting to know.
Every analytic function,
every function which has a derivative,
and incidentally,
most of the simple functions that you write down,
I'll give you some examples as we go along,
most of the simple functions that
you would be likely to write down,
are analytic.
So in this way,
you can generate a large family
of solutions of the Laplace equation.
Now it's not sufficient to have
two solutions of the Laplace equation.
Two solutions of the Laplace equation
are just two solutions of the Laplace equation.
These equations link them together.
So in fact,
it's not every pair of Laplace functions
define an analytic function.
Really, it's just one of them,
and you can deduce the other one by a trick,
but we don't need to go there.
Okay, so that's something about...
These equations have a name, incidentally.
They were first, to my knowledge,
they were first discovered by the mathematician Cauchy,
and they're called...
Oh, Cauchy and Riemann.
I don't know who discovered them first,
Cauchy and Riemann,
and they're called the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
Hmm?
Yeah, Cauchy was first, but sort of...
But Riemann was more famous.
Popularized by Riemann.
Cauchy-Riemann.
Well, isn't that often how it goes?
Yeah.
You know, somebody's...
Usually the first guy doesn't get any credit,
but in this case,
Cauchy was a rather famous mathematician,
and...
But not as famous as Riemann.
So physicists never heard of him.
Except in this context.
Yeah.
In math, he's got many other...
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, but not as much as Riemann.
I don't think.
Tell me something else that Cauchy did.
Cauchy sequences.
Oh, yeah.
I've heard of that.
He made calculus rigorous.
What's that?
Made calculus rigorous.
That you don't get credit for.
Okay.
Okay, the Cauchy-Riemann equations
are related to Laplace's equation in this way.
Now I want to prove that these mappings are conformal.
That was the whole point here.
That conformal mappings are the same
as these analytic functions.
These are not mappings or coordinate transformations
generated by analytic functions.
They are the same thing.
But let's just prove...
Let's see how we prove that.
Yeah, let's just remind ourselves one or two...
One small point about complex numbers.
Let's suppose we have a complex number.
Let's...
I'll call it Z.
I'll call it ScribZ here.
It's meant to be a small complex number,
but it doesn't need to be small.
But a small complex number.
But it doesn't need to be small for this purpose.
It can be represented as X plus IY,
but it can also be represented as another way
in polar coordinates as a radius,
let's call it rho times E
to the I times an angle.
That's another form of a complex number.
Now supposing we have two complex numbers.
Let's call this delta Z,
because I really do mean it
to be a small little displacement.
Let's suppose I have another one.
Let's call it capital delta Z.
Each one of these are intended to be
small displacements,
but for the moment they're just complex numbers.
And this one is called rho
prime E to the I theta prime.
Think about the ratio of these two.
The ratio of these two,
delta Z over delta Z,
first of all has rho over rho prime.
We could make it simple and set
rho and rho prime to be equal,
and that's because rho and rho
prime are not the issue here.
What I'm interested in is these angles.
What do I get for the angle?
I get E to the I theta minus theta prime.
The important thing here is that
the angle associated with a ratio
is the difference of angles.
If I have a ratio of two complex numbers,
the angular part of it
is the difference of the angles.
Keep that in mind.
Now what we're going to do
is go back to the Z and W planes.
Here's the Z plane.
Here's the W plane.
And let's take,
starting at that point,
let's construct two little intervals.
One of them I'll call delta Z.
It's the same as this over here.
Incidentally, my script Zs and my
square Zs are the same variable.
Delta Z and delta Z.
We construct two of them here.
There's an angle between them,
which is the difference of the
angles of the two variables themselves,
or the two little intervals themselves.
Now,
I can map every point on this
plane to a point on this plane.
In particular,
this point here goes to here.
The endpoints also get transformed.
So little delta Z gets mapped
to little delta W.
You take the two endpoints,
and you map them to here,
and that defines a little delta W.
Same likewise with little delta Z.
Okay?
Sorry, delta big Z.
W.
Delta W.
Good.
Now what do we know,
assuming it's an analytic mapping?
In other words, assuming that
the Cauchy-Riemann equations are satisfied,
assuming that the function W is an analytic function.
What we know,
is that the derivative is well defined,
and doesn't matter which direction you come in along.
What is the derivative if I
come in along the delta direction?
If I come in along the delta direction,
it's just delta W over delta Z, right?
That's the derivative if I come
in delta W divided by delta Z.
But supposing I come along this direction here,
then what is the derivative?
Big delta W.
Big delta W over big delta Z.
Now if W is really an analytic function,
it means that this ratio doesn't depend
on which direction you come in along.
So it says that these two are equal.
The derivative is calculated along the delta axis,
or the little delta axis,
so the big delta axis should be the same,
if they're analytic functions.
We can rewrite this.
Let's multiply this by big delta Z,
and divide it by big delta W.
Sorry, little delta W.
We can write this in another way.
It's big delta Z divided by little delta Z,
multiplied,
now I'm going to divide by this one,
is equal to big delta W over little delta W.
Everybody see what I did?
I put this one upstairs,
and this one downstairs.
That's all.
But now what does this say?
This says the ratio of big
delta Z to little delta Z
is the same as the ratio of
big delta W to little delta W.
What does that say about the angles here?
Let's call that angle theta,
and this angle over here.
The angle associated with the ratio
is the difference of angles,
which just means the angle associated with the number,
where is it?
delta Z over little delta Z
is just the angle between them.
The angle associated with big
delta W over little delta W
is the angle between here.
What does this tell us?
This tells us the angles are equal.
In other words, the mapping is a conformal mapping.
Every angle on here,
when you make the mapping,
maps to the same angle on here.
It doesn't say it doesn't reorient.
It says the angle between curves,
take any curve, map it to here,
and the angle that they
intersect that will be the same.
That's the defining property of a conformal mapping.
So the coordinate changes that
are associated with analytic functions
are exactly the coordinate transformations
which are the invariances of Laplace equation,
or the coordinate transformation that
the Laplace equation doesn't change
when you do those coordinate transformations.
That's why in string theory, analytic functions,
or coordinate, or conformal mappings,
are so important.
Because they're the invariance of the
equations of motion of the string.
Okay, let's do a couple of examples.
I'm going to show you two interesting examples.
Well, let's first check a couple of simple functions
and see if it's really true that...
Let's take Z equals XZ.
W equals Z squared.
That's a really easy one.
Let's check if it's analytic.
Okay.
Z is X plus IY.
X plus IY squared is equal
to X squared minus Y squared
plus twice IXY.
And this must be equal to U plus IV.
W is equal to Z squared.
All right, so first of all, what is U?
U is equal to X squared minus Y squared.
The real part of this side is the
same as the real part of this side.
So that's X squared minus Y squared.
What about V?
Just two X, Y.
U equals... there's a square missing in V.
Yeah.
Good.
Right? That's what you meant, right?
Okay, let's check whether these satisfy Laplace's equations.
Laplace's equations say that the second derivative
of U with respect to X squared...
What is that?
The second derivative of U
with respect to X squared is?
Two.
Second derivative.
Second derivative of U with respect to Y squared?
Minus two.
So second of U with respect to X
squared plus second derivative of Y squared is zero.
Okay.
What about second derivative of
U with respect to X squared?
Zero.
If you differentiate it once, you get Y,
and then you can't differentiate it with X again.
Likewise, second derivative...
This one also is a good solution of Laplace's equation.
All right, now, that proves that every function that
you'd ever be likely to write down is analytic.
Let's write one down, which is not analytic.
Okay?
One over Z.
Hmm?
Well, that only fails to be analytic at
one lousy point, so let's not worry about that.
No, let's make a really bad one.
First of all, W equals Z.
That's very analytic.
That's a very simple one.
But what about W equals complex conjugate of Z?
W equals complex conjugate.
Remember what a complex conjugate is?
You reverse the sign of the I.
This would say that W is equal to X minus IY,
or U is equal to X, and V is equal to Z.
I will leave it to you to
prove that the Cauchy-Riemann equations don't work.
I'm not going to do it.
You do it.
You get a wrong sign.
You can see you couldn't possibly get
the right sign for both plus and minus.
One of them would say U equals X, V equals Y,
and the other says V equals X, V equals minus Y.
Can't both satisfy the complex.
I'll leave it to you.
I don't want to do it now.
That's because I can't
remember the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
Oh, there they are.
The U by the X
equals the V by the Y.
Nah, the minus sign gets in the way.
Right?
So the answer is no.
Okay.
But analytic functions are written
without ever having a function.
Without ever invoking the complex conjugate.
Complex conjugates are not analytic functions.
W equals Z, W equals Z squared, W equals Z
cubed, W equals Z to any power is an analytic function.
Let's do another one for fun.
Let's do W equals log...
Oh, let's, let's...
No, let's do...
Um...
Yeah, let me see what I was going to do.
Yeah.
W equals...
No.
Z equals...
Z equals E to the W.
Let's do W equals E to the Z.
That's a more complicated thing.
Let's just check it and see that it's really analytic.
You could also do logarithm.
We don't have to do both logarithm and exponential.
Why is that?
Because it's the inverse of the other.
What is the inverse of the other?
Um, if we come back, how do we know that if
a function is analytic, that the inverse of it is analytic?
The angles match.
The angles have to match.
Going one way, they have to match the other way.
If the angles are preserved one way,
they have to be preserved in their terms.
Exactly.
So if they're going one way, they
have to be equal going the other way.
So, uh...
It's also true that derivatives of inverse functions are
just one over the derivatives of the functions themselves.
And so if they're independent of which
way you come in, it's still true.
Okay, but let's try W equals...
Just to learn the experiment around and
to unrust your use of complex numbers.
All right.
So what is E to the z?
E to the z is u plus iv, right?
What is E to the z?
E to the z is
e to the x plus iy.
All right.
E to the x plus iy is the
same as e to the x, which is real.
E to the x is real.
And what about e to the iy?
Is there another way to write e to the iy?
Cosine of y.
Cosine of y plus i sine of y.
Okay, so can you read off u from this?
u is equal to...
Let's put it up here.
u is equal to e
to the x times cosine y.
And v is equal to e
to the x times sine of y.
So we check the Cauchy-Riemann equations?
Let's check them.
The u by dx, what is the u by dx?
What happens when you differentiate e
to the x with respect to x?
You get u again.
So the u by dx is the same thing.
The u by dx is equal
to e to the x cosine y.
What about dv by dy?
All right, what do we get when
we differentiate this with respect to y?
Derivative of sine is cosine.
Okay, so this is again equal
to e to the x cosine y.
Yep, so the first Cauchy-Riemann equation is
correct, and you can check the other one.
It's also correct.
All right, so we check that e
to the z is a good analytic function.
Sums of analytic functions are analytic.
Ratios of analytic functions are analytic,
except at points where the denominator vanishes.
At points where the denominator vanishes, something is infinite,
and those are nasty points where everything breaks down.
Okay, let's take, I took
w equals e to the z.
Let's take w equals logarithm of z.
That's the inverse function.
w equals logarithm of z.
And let's see if we
can see how this mapping works.
This is an important mapping in string theory.
w equals logarithm of z.
Let's see if we can see how it works.
In particular, I'm going to apply
this mapping to the half plane.
The half plane now means, take
the half plane, which has a boundary.
It's the half plane to the right.
I'm not going to, let's not mark it.
We're interested in the half plane to the right here.
Here's the origin.
And let's see if we can see.
When we do the mapping, where
the points of the half plane go.
Here's the w plane.
This is the z plane.
And here's the w plane.
Okay.
First of all, what about
the origin of the z plane?
What happens to the origin of the z plane?
The origin of the z
plane goes to logarithm of zero.
Where is logarithm of zero?
Logarithm of zero is of course not a number.
But we can take logarithm
of a tiny, tiny, tiny number.
And the logarithm of a tiny
number is a very negative number.
So this point out here maps to some place
out at infinity, way off to the left here.
Let's not try to figure out exactly where
it goes, because it doesn't go anywhere really.
It goes out to minus infinity.
What about logarithm of plus infinity?
That's way out here.
But that's not very illuminating.
Let's take this plane and
write it in the other form.
z is equal to r e to the i theta.
Then what is this half line down here?
That's the line theta equals what?
Theta equals minus pi over 2.
Here is theta equals plus pi over 2.
Here is r e to the i theta.
What is the logarithm of
r e to the i theta?
The logarithm of r e to the i theta is log
of r log of z is equal to log of z.
That's the logarithm of r e to the i theta.
That's the logarithm of r plus i theta.
So where does a general point go?
It goes to some real number plus i theta.
And what does theta go between?
Theta goes from minus pi over
2 to plus pi over 2.
Here is minus pi over 2.
Theta equals minus i theta.
Minus i pi over 2.
And the upper end here goes
to plus i pi over 2.
An infinite line, in other words, this infinite
line here gets mapped to this infinite line.
And this infinite, the infinite half line.
The other infinite half line gets mapped down to here.
The origin being way out here.
So what we've done is we've taken this whole space and we've kind
of bent the axes and squashed the whole space on a narrow ribbon.
The ribbon between minus i pi over
2 and plus i pi over 2.
We could draw some curves to see
if we can see what's going on.
We could first draw some curves.
We could first draw some straight lines like this.
Straight lines coming out of the origin here.
They have to go to the origin.
They also have to go out to infinity.
And those lines map to straight lines like this.
It just bands at constant angle.
At constant angle.
Okay.
Next, what about the radial circles which look like this?
Where do they go?
Vertical lines.
Why is this strip description interesting from
the point of view of string theory?
This was the way I described the world sheet of a
string in terms of a coordinate, what do we call it, sigma?
Sigma which went from minus pi
over 2 to pi over 2.
That was, if you like, the parameter along the string.
And the other direction was the time direction.
This was the world sheet of a string where the string went from minus
pi over 2 to pi over 2 in the coordinates and swept out time.
Uniformly.
Everything was translationally invariant in time.
No special time.
And you can see from this picture here.
That everything has a nice symmetry along this axis.
How does the symmetry along this axis,
let's say we push everything to the left.
What happens here?
On the z plane.
Let's take the w plane
and shift everything to the left.
What happens?
It shrinks.
It shrinks by a uniform factor.
If you push to the left a
certain amount, it shrinks by a uniform factor.
If you push to the right, it expands.
So these are called dilations.
Dilations are transformations which expand and contract.
They transform into the time translations.
Curious.
All right.
This is one mapping which is of interest.
This means that the string world sheet could be
described as living on a half plane like that.
With the incoming string coming in at that point.
Right?
And then the string world sheet.
Coming in at that point.
Right?
They're being injected in right there.
The incoming string at a time in the remote past can be
thought of as being injected onto the world sheet right at this point.
Let's do another mapping.
I have a quick question for you.
So you let r equal to b1.
Is that it?
No, no, no.
No.
I was asking if you could say that the
r equal to b1 is some particular line here.
These lines are lines of constant r.
Right.
r equal to 1 is right at the center here.
No, I did not.
Yeah.
R is those circles.
Hmm?
R is those circles that you.
Yeah.
R of the various circles here.
This is r equal to 0, r
equals 1, r equals 2, r equals 3.
Sorry.
R is not 0 over here.
But r is 0 out there.
If I can clarify something.
If I can clarify, you say that the left one is like polar coordinates, but
on the right it's not polar coordinates, it's the old x, y, left, right coordinates
Yeah, but it's a mapping from one to the
other, it's a mapping from one to the other
and the one thing you can be sure of is that angles
on here, when they map to here, they cross at the same angle
That means, among other things, that if the Laplace equation for
x, x now being x of the x coordinate of the string
if the Laplace equation is satisfied for a field, for a
degree of freedom living on here, it's also satisfied on here
So that's the symmetry of string theory
You can stretch, deform
the coordinate space to fit whatever particular
reason you may want for redrawing it
Here's another form
Another mapping of the half plane
Oh, before I do that,
let me tell you what happens
if you map the whole of the Laplace equation
if you map the whole plane by the same transformation
If you map the whole plane from the same transformation,
the angle goes from minus pi over 2 to what?
Minus pi over 2 plus 2 pi
We could also let it go, let's see, we
could also let it go from, let's, yeah, okay
It goes from minus pi
over 2 to pi over 2
So it's from minus pi over 2
to pi over 2 plus 2 pi
2 pi is, add 2 pi
And it becomes a fatter strip
but there's something new, what's new, what's
different about this strip than the original strip?
is it wraps around?
Yeah
When you go all the ways around the
angular direction you come back to the same point
that means starting here
when you go all the ways around
you come back to the same thing.
In other words, what happens
if you map the whole plane,
what do you get?
Cylinder.
Cylinder, not a torus,
because this end is not identified with this end,
but the top is identified with the bottom,
you get a cylinder.
Yeah, it's a cylinder.
An infinite cylinder.
This is the space that you would use
to describe an open string with two ends.
How about this one?
Closed string.
Right.
So it's natural to think of, well,
open strings you can describe on the half plane,
closed strings on the whole plane,
with no boundaries.
That's a, that's...
Yeah.
Useful mathematical fact.
Now let's come to another mapping.
Let's take the, let's forget this W plane,
and map to another W plane.
Different mapping.
We're starting again with the same Z plane.
X, Y, and so forth.
How about this one?
W equals Z plus 1 over Z minus 1.
Let's see if we can see where it goes.
Oops.
Is that what I want?
Yes.
Let's see.
Well do I want Z equals
W plus 1 over W minus 1,
one or the other?
Well let's try it.
Let's see if we can see what it does.
Z equals 0.
Where does Z equal 0 go?
Well, let's try it.
Let's see if we can see what it does.
We have a problem here.
where does z equals zero go? Minus one, right? When
z is equal to w, I'm sorry, when z is
equal to zero, w goes to minus one. Here's
the w plane, w goes to minus one. How
about when z is equal to, ah, when
z is equal to infinity, way out here.
W goes to one. When z
is equal to infinity, or in other
words when z is very, very
large. It goes to plus one.
It goes to plus one.
How about when z is pure imaginary
up here? When it's pure imaginary, in other
words when it lies on the boundary of
the half plane, where does it go? That
means that z is equal to some real
number times i, r times i. What happens
to w? w becomes one
plus ir over one plus i.
W becomes one plus ir over one plus i.
W becomes one minus ir, I think with a
minus sign. How about one plus ir over one minus
ir? Anything special about that? Magnitude one,
right? Magnitude one. The sums of the
squares of the real and imaginary parts are the
same. So the ratio of these two has magnitude
one. So where is this upper half
line here? It lies on the unit circle.
It lies on the unit circle because it has magnitude one. How
about the lower half line here? It also lies on the unit circle.
So when x varies over the entire half plane
here, not x, but when z varies over the entire
half plane, w varies over the unit disc.
This is called a disc, over the unit disc.
What is this useful for? Well, in
practice it is useful for solving Laplace's equation
in various contexts. You put in various charges,
for example, in various places, and you want
to calculate the electric field. If you can
do it in this geometry, then you can transform
the same problem to this geometry.
And solve a whole slew of problems. So one
of the things it's good for is mapping back
and forth electrostatics problems. And it
is used that way quite frequently.
Let's see, let's do one other thing before
we finish. Not before we finish, but before
we finish with this. We started with these
circles and these lines here. What do they
look like on the unit disc
here? Well, they look roughly like this.
The radial lines start at one end and go
out to infinity, but infinity was over here. So
the radial lines look like this. They
are actually circles. They are actually circles.
Circles of different radii.
And the lines of constant radius here...
1 over 0 in the radial line.
So there is an infinite number. The radius
looks like this. And this is always one of
they look like this
and they bunch up as you
get closer and closer to the
do you remember the transformations on the ribbon here?
there were transformations on the ribbon which moved
which translated the ribbon back and forth in this direction
they corresponded to dilatations or dilations
expansions and contractions here
they correspond to some complicated kind of motions here
when you said that those
arcs that you drew are circles
are there circles in the arcs in the circle?
they're circles but their centers are in various places
this one is not a
circle clearly, it's a straight line
but it's the limit of a circle
this one is a circle
with a center way down here
this one has its center somewhere here
and of course this one
has its center right over here
would cartographers like that transformation?
it kind of looks like
well of course that's not a sphere, it's a disk
don't confuse it with a sphere
now, if you did the
same thing with the full plane
you would get a sphere
but that's, I didn't want to do that now
it's the optical illusion anyway
those are circles in a sphere
yeah it looks like a sphere but
it's not intended to be a sphere
it's just intended to be a mapping
from the plane to the disk
alright so we have now
another representation of the same picture
question
where does the left half go?
the left half plane goes
to the outside of the disk
left half plane, right half plane is here
that's the inside of the disk
the left half plane goes
to the outside of the disk
it didn't disappear, it just went
I don't know who asked the question
it's a sphere because
when you take the limits, things go around
and they fold up, right?
you mean when you take the full plane
the full plane, it's a little bit complicated
it's a stereographic mapping of a sphere
I think there's a single point
at infinity and there's a mapping directly
yeah
and it can be mapped stereographically
which was the radius?
the radius on the left, the spokes going out,
which set occurs when they go through the line?
the spokes going out here, they begin
at the left side of the disk, right?
they begin at this point
this point is that point
infinity, let's see, z equals infinity,
that's w equals 1, that's over here
so every one of these lines, let's take the one which is first
of all completely symmetric between the upper half plane and the lower half plane
that's the x-axis
the x-axis, that's just this line
the radial lines above the x-axis are like that
radial lines below the x-axis are like that
then there's the circles on here
here's a circle, every one of these circles sort
of surrounds this point here, sort of, half surrounds it
they start, well let's see, they start on the boundary
they surround this point and
they come back to the boundary
so they start on the boundary of the
disk, they go around and they come back
but as you move out
they go like that
they sort of get turned a little bit inside out as
you go from here to here so they go like that
their curvature is in the opposite direction
Are they circles too?
Yeah, yeah, they are also circles
It's an interesting fact, under these mappings, well
under this mapping, under this kind of mapping
this is called a linear fractional mapping
it's a fraction made out of two linear functions
under linear fractional mappings, the collection of circles and
lines transform into a collection of circles and lines
so here's a line
it transformed to a circle
here's a line
it transformed to a certain circle
circles and lines transform, the collection of
circles plus lines transform to circles plus lines
not under every conformal mapping
under linear fractional transformations, and
that's what these are called
sometimes called Mebius transformations and they
have nothing to do with Mebius strips
at least I don't think they do
same Mebius though
okay
let's take a break for five minutes or so
What about that point at halfway infinity?
The point where?
The point at halfway infinity is a straight line
The point at halfway infinity,
what is a half way infinity?
It's on the basketball
What is halfway infinity?
Isn't that straight line in the
vertical line in the middle there?
That one, yeah
That's some particular radius
probably radius one
I'm not sure
It goes through the origin
Yeah
It passes through the origin on the w plane
So where is the origin on the w plane?
It's the thing whose logarithm is zero
One
Right
Now I'm going to try to give you a
fairly complete definition of what string theory is
We've set up a lot of the mathematics
The problem of course is proving
that these things work in detail
and that of course is where the real
difficult stuff comes in
but um
Let's go back
You may recall that we talked a
little bit about what scattering amplitudes look like
and how you derive them in string theory
We started with a simple example
where two particles collided, came
in and two particles went out
We said okay, let's just take
the world sheet of the whole process
and we're going to take the whole process
and we're going to make the
world sheet of the whole process
to be an infinite strip like this
but since two particles are coming in
let's slit it down the middle like that
Two particles are going to go out
Time goes from left to right
Two strings come in
Two strings go out
So here's the two initial strings
I don't want to draw on
this, at least not with black
Here's the incoming string and it propagates
Here's the other incoming string and it propagates
The two strings join
form a single string
There it is in here
And then after a period of time
How much time?
The answer is you integrate over the time
As in quantum mechanics you
always integrate over all possible paths
from beginning to end
In other words you just
sum up the amplitudes for all possible histories
and then the end what
goes out is two strings again
What do you calculate?
I'll remind you what you calculate
Well, we talked about it in several different versions
But in one version you think of a path integral
In the path integral
the degrees of freedom
are the coordinate positions
We could define a sigma variable and a tau variable
or two coordinates on this
two coordinates on this world sheet
But the degrees of freedom are the space-time positions
the space-time coordinates
of a point on the world sheet
So what are they?
They're x mu
where mu goes from one or from zero
zero being time
What's the last one?
25 if it's in 26 dimensions
9 if it's in 10 dimensions
But whatever the collection of coordinates are
that describe the location of a point on the string
And we call that x mu of
sigma and tau let's say
Sigma and tau could be the
two coordinates on this world sheet
They're of course the same as
these little x's and y's here
They're the coordinates in a two-dimensional space
And those coordinates, the sigma and tau are
The x's are coordinates in real space-time
The sigma and taus are just labels
which label points on the world sheet
The x's are their real space-time location
And if I know the space-time location
of every point on the world sheet
then I know how the world
sheet is spread out over space
What do you do?
We calculate a certain path integral
And the path integral that we calculate
is e to the minus
the action
We did a little trick
I'm just reminding you now of a trick
We did a little trick of
letting tau go to i tau
in order to get rid of various factors of i
We talked about it, I'm not
going to do it over again
And there was an action
The action was the integral of
the integral over d sigma and d tau
of what?
It was the x mu d tau squared
minus the x mu d sigma squared
plus the x mu d sigma squared
What exactly does this mean?
The x mu by d tau squared means
the sum of 26 terms
The x1 by d tau squared
The x2 by d tau squared
The x3 up to the last one
That's what these things mean
This is the exponential of the action
And what do we do with it?
We integrate it
Path integral over all possible ways
of filling up the surface
It's often written delta x of sigma and tau
This means path integral
And it means integrate it or sum it up
over all possible configurations of the world sheet
in space-time, the way the world sheet fills up space-time
But how does this formula here
First of all, how does this formula know about
the momenta of the incoming particles?
The momenta of the incoming particles
we have to add in by hand
And it's inconvenient in this picture
to say how we do it
I'm going to tell you in another picture
exactly how we do it
But for the moment, let's just suppose
somehow we have put in the momenta
of the incoming and outgoing particles
that's somehow embedded in this calculation
And we integrate over all x's
Now, there's one more thing
What about the time interval between here and here?
We integrate over it
And we have to do it in a way
that's not going to be a problem
So what we're doing in effect
is summing up all possible ways
all possible histories
of these two particles
oscillating, then forming a single particle
and then forming two particles again
All possible histories
All possible ways that the world sheet fluctuates
That's this integral over here
It's an integral of the action
And it's a complicated thing
And we haven't even yet put in the rule
I'm going to tell you what the rule is
for the external particles in a moment
But before we do it
What did we call this?
We had a name for this picture
What was it?
Oh, the sports band-aid
Yeah, yeah, the sports band-aid, right
Butterfly bandage or whatever it's called
Right
Well, now we can make use of our freedom
to map this picture to other
sets of coordinates
for the world sheet
Conformal mappings
Conformal mappings is a very wide
variety of analytic functions
And in fact the variety is so large
that you can basically map
This thing has one boundary
The boundary goes from here to here
Now, out at infinity here
What goes on at infinity is subtle
But let's jump to this boundary
It goes all the ways around
Just like the sports bandage
It goes around once
It has one boundary
Apart from the fact that little pieces
of the boundary are off at infinity
We'll worry about that later
You can map anything with one boundary like that
to anything else with one boundary
by a conformal mapping
In particular, if you so choose
Just for symmetry
You can map this whole world sheet
to a circle or to a disk
Exactly the same disk
I showed you how to map this
I showed you how to map
a single strip to a disk
I didn't show you how to
map the sports bandaid to a disk
It's a little more complicated
I once figured it out many years ago
I worked out the mapping in detail
I don't remember it
But you can map it to a disk
And then where are the incoming particles?
Those are points on the boundary
The outgoing particles are also points on the boundary
Let's draw some lines to just indicate how this looks
So if you draw some vertical lines here
Some vertical lines here
They will look like this
Notice that these vertical lines over here
Surround the point at infinity here
That's this one
And then all of a sudden
They come together like that
That's this point
Then they go like this
That's what the mapping from here to here looks like
The horizontal lines
I don't know, they go...
They're a little more complicated
That's what it looks like
The point is, you can do exact...
You don't need to know where these lines are, incidentally
You can forget where they are
They don't play any special role
The point where they split and join
In this diagram here
Is determined by the position
The positions of these ends
The positions of these external points here
As you move them around
These points move
Closer and farther apart
When you move these points together this way
These points get very far apart
When you move them together horizontally
These points move together
So the same picture
The same physics
Different pictures
What do you do here?
You do exactly the same thing
You take the x by the tau squared
You can now call it...
You can now call these coordinates
by different names if you like
You can call them x
and y or u and v
Doesn't matter
The tau and sigma coordinates
You calculate exactly the same quantity
Integrate it over here
But now I can tell you what you do
With the external particles
You have a rule for each external particle
One more factor in the integrand
Anybody know what that factor is?
It's the thing which injects momentum
Delta function of what?
Okay
X's are integration variables
K's are the momenta
K1, K2, K3, K4
These are the momenta coming in and going out
You put in for each external particle
Each particle coming in
You put in a factor into the integrand here
Of
E to the i k x
At the position
Let's call this point z
Approximately
A product for each external particle
One more thing goes in
It's a factor of E to the i k x
Where k is the momentum of
the particular particle that's coming in
So you have an E
to the i k x one
And they're on the boundary
It corresponds to particles being
injected into the diagram like that
That rule
Comes from quantum mechanics
It comes from
Well we can discuss this rule another time
I wanted to lay out the whole set of rules
You do a path integral
Over all possible embeddings
Of the world sheet into space time
All possible ways that this world
sheet can be embedded in space time
E to an action
And for each external particle
An E to the i k x
Where the x
Is at the point
Where the insertion of that particle happened
On the world sheet here
Z here corresponds to the coordinates of this point
On the plane here
One last thing
After you're finished
You have to integrate
Over the positions of these insertions
That's it
That's the whole story
That is what string theory is
This is open string
This is open string theory
That's the whole set of rules
A path integral
A path integral over all world sheets
All embeddings
You can describe it on a disc
You can describe it on a sports bandage
You can describe it however you like
What did you get after you finished all this integration?
The scattering amplitude
The particle of momentum k1, k2
To become k3 and k4
But if those are fixed
How come we integrated over them?
The momenta or the positions?
The momenta
No, we didn't integrate over the momenta
We integrate over the locations on the disc here
Of those
Of the insertions
Okay, so those don't represent the actual values
They just represent where they are
They replace the integration over the separation
Right, okay, so those are fixed
Those are not fixed
No, I mean the k1, 2, 3, 4 are
The k's are fixed
The k's are the momenta of
the particles coming in and going out
So we get basically the scattering amplitude
Scattering amplitude for a particle of momentum 1 and 2
To become a particle of
momentum minus k3 and minus k4
Remember, all momenta are carried
Is that product multiplied by the whole integral?
It's inside the integration
Inside the integration
Is that, you call that the action?
This is the action
And that's part of the action?
This is, no, these are called vertex operators
Vertex operators mean they just bring some
They just deposit momentum into the
Into the diagram
They inject the flow of momentum into the diagram
We'll work that out another time
and see where this comes from
The question is, do they go inside the upper integral?
Yeah, they go inside the integrals
Not inside this integral
No, not inside that integral
No, we could write it out,
let's write it out more clearly
Integral over all possible
Well, let's see
Integral, path integral
Let's just call it path integral,
let's not put any d's there
e to the minus the action
This is the action for a particular configuration
And here it is
This is the action
Times, for each external particle
A factor e to the i k
x of z1
Let's say zi, ki
A factor for each one
k1
z1
Yeah, let me not put it for a moment
e to the i k2
x of z2
dot dot dot
For each external particle
Where z's are the positions
On the disk where the momentum is injected
This is path integrated
And then
Integrated over the locations
Where the momenta are injected
So you integrate over everything, yeah
And use the i k x
Even though we've already done the wick rotation
Yeah
Still e to the i k x
Right
That i is a different i
You should really write k mu x mu
k mu x mu
Okay
There's a k mu
For each component of momentum
And an x mu
There are 26 x's
There are 26 k's
And that's it
That's the whole structure of string theory
Question
In
Where do you
Okay
The momentum is a vector
K mu
That's why there's a mu there
Okay
And the direction
Is the vector
Okay
And then the direction
Is related to the x sub z's
No no
The direction of the momentum is
Here are the components of the momenta
The x's which appear here
Get integrated over
They're part of this path integral here
Integral delta x
They're part of the path integral
Not part of the action
Yeah
They could be
Since they're in the exponent
You could consider them to be part of the action
If you liked
Right
You can just put them into the action
But
You add them
You add them in
A k x for each external particle
So how does this
When you have the bandage
You know the legs can be either swayed or closed
Does that relate to the x's
How that's
The shape
The shape of the bandage
How
The angle of the two legs
The angle
No no no no no
In this drawing
You just draw them
Horizontal
You can draw it any way you want
But
Right
It's not in real space
It's just a parameter space
That all
Right
Okay
The amazing thing
Is
That you can do the integrals
Everything can be
Everything can be done
These are what are called Gaussian integrals
Everything is quadratic
In the exponent
All the integrals
Can be done
That's the good news
infinity
but not if you're in the right number
of dimensions. Now I am not going to tell
you about the wrong number of dimensions
I'm going to tell you what the answer
is like in the right number of dimensions
and it's incredibly simple
it's the solution of an electrostatics problem
you take every one of these x's
and think of it
as an electrostatic potential
there are twenty six of them or ten
of them or however many of them there are
think of them
as separate electrostatics problems
it's a world now where there are
twenty six different kinds of electric charge
twenty six different kinds of electric field
and twenty six different kinds of electrostatic potentials
the electrostatic potentials are these x's
x1, x2, x3, x4
what do you think the charges corresponding to them are?
can you guess?
the components of the momenta
twenty six components of the momenta
are like twenty six
kinds of charges
each one being the source of
its own electrostatic field, the electrostatic field
being called x
okay here's the calculation that you do
and it is really...
easy
it is
obtained by doing these integrals
the integrals
twenty six
not twenty six charges
twenty six different kinds of charge
twenty-six different independent kinds of charge
each
creating its own electrostatic field
here's what you do we have x2 and x3 a series of carbons and those
kinds of negative sign claro here's what you do all right here's what you do
here's what you do cioè a submissions of beta quantываютなんだ
energy terrestris
in the Какhtub???
defined by addition progressive sigh
through the klap tend to a carbon carbon atom.....
take a disk, this disk is, think of it
as a world in two dimensions, on this disk
you have, let's see, I get confused, the
x, um, the x, yeah, the boundary conditions
are that the electric, that the components
of the electric field perpendicular to the
surface of the disk vanish, it's not so
important, the boundary conditions, you have a disk,
a world with these 26 different kinds of
electricity, on the boundary you put charges, little charges
on the boundary, at each boundary point
there are 26 charges to put on.
Okay.
The charges themselves are the components
of the electrostatic potential, are the components
of the momentum. So if this particle comes
in with 26 components of k, those 26 components
of k become the 26 charges that you put
at that point, another 26 charges at that point,
another 26 charges at that point, and another
26 charges at that point. This is a straightforward
electrostatics problem.
26 of them, but it's easy to do 26 of them
as it is to do one of them, well, in principle.
If you can do an electrostatics problem with
one kind of electric charge, you can do the
same electrostatics problem 26 times over
with different values of the charge here.
Alright, so fixing the values of the charge
and fixing these points, what do you calculate?
You calculate the electrostatic potential inside.
Okay.
From that you can calculate the electric
field, and once you know the electric field
you can calculate the electrostatic energy.
You calculate the electrostatic energy of
such a configuration, that's this whole
integral there, the electrostatic energy, and then
you integrate it over the points. You
move the points around, you integrate over them,
and that is the scattering.
Okay.
And that's the scattering amplitude for the 26 dimensional particles to
scatter from one set of momenta to another set of momenta.
So in fact, the final upshot is very easy. It's
just an electrostatics problem with 26 different kinds of charges.
You calculate the electrostatic energy in here.
Is that one energy or 26 energy?
26. There are 26 and you add them up.
That's right. There are 26 different kinds of charges.
26 distinct...
You have 26 potentials.
26 potentials, 26 electric fields.
And you end up ultimately with one energy, right?
One energy. One energy.
And there's no cross terms between the
26. The 26 are just operating orthogonally.
There are no cross terms between them. You take that electrostatic
energy, you exponentiate it, e to the minus the electrostatic energy.
The whole answer depends on the energy.
The whole answer depends on the positions of the charges.
And you integrate it over the positions of the charges.
You calculate the 26 electrostatic energies
for the 26 different kinds of charges.
How do you do that? You calculate the electric field, you square
the electric field, or you can just calculate the electrostatic energies if you're...
And you exponentiate it, you integrate it over the
positions, and that gives you the scattering amplitude for...
Particles whose components of momenta are the same as the
values of the charges that you put on these points.
That's the whole upshot of it. Yeah?
The angular parameter of this disk
has no relation to scattering angle, right?
No. No. No, it has more of
a relationship to the time intervals in here.
Yeah.
Yeah. There are various parameters,
but you integrate over them.
You integrate over them.
And that's the string theory scattering amplitude.
It's a fairly simple prescription.
Could you say this does
not work if it's not 26?
It doesn't.
You get a bunch of infinities from
the path integral which just don't go away.
This is the final answer when it works.
When it doesn't work, it's just infinite.
And 26 and 10.
So I'm... I'm sorry.
I'm sort of short-circuiting it by
telling you what the answer is.
It's a very beautiful and simple final answer.
But once you know that this is the procedure, there's
nothing to prevent you from putting lots more particles in.
You do have to integrate over their locations on here, but basically
that's the answer for the scattering of any number of incoming particles.
The amplitude.
The thing that's coming in.
The thing that you square.
The amplitude for any number of incoming
particles to any number of outgoing particles.
Yeah?
We have three long dimensions and these small ones.
Does the fact that you convert them to this...
Whoa.
Three long dimensions.
Well, we haven't talked about compactification yet.
We have not.
That'll be the next discussion.
Yeah?
You're talking about the connection to the potential again.
It's because of the coordinates satisfying the Laplace?
Yes, it's because the
coordinates satisfy the Laplace equation.
And...
It connects you to the static potential solution.
That's right.
The coordinates satisfy...
Well, yes, they satisfy the Laplace equation.
And the Laplace equation is
the basic equation for electrostatics.
We didn't have to call it electrostatics.
We just said Laplace equation
with some delta function sources here.
But it...
The mathematics is the same
as calculating an electrostatics problem.
You have four degrees of freedom for each
of those four points around the disk, right?
Each angle has an angle.
And then you have...
Yeah.
It's actually simpler than that.
You can use the conformal freedom.
The freedom to reconformally map things to arbitrarily
fix the location of any three of them.
In other words, you should integrate over all of them.
But for any given configuration, you
can always find the conformal mapping,
which will bring this point to here,
this point to here, this point to here.
And then it's only the fourth point.
For the case of two in and two out, it's only the
location of the fourth point which gets integrated from here to here.
That's a technical point.
Place the two points inside the band.
These two points, yeah.
The integral over these two...
Freedom there, right?
No, no, no.
There's really only one integration, which
is the time between these two.
They don't have to exactly break apart in the same...
Ah, that's a good point.
They could break apart at different points, like that.
But you can always find the conformal mapping.
You can always find the conformal
mapping, which will pull them back together.
So you have that freedom.
You have that freedom to pull them back together.
So when you add more points, how does the
number of points map to the number of parameters?
Well, the answer...
Okay, the answer is that
you have a conformal invariance freedom,
a freedom of conformal mapping that allows
you to choose any arbitrary three points
and put them wherever you like.
You fix them, put the first one here,
the second one here, the third one here,
and then all the other ones get integrated over.
So the answer is you have
n minus 3 integrations to do.
Yeah.
How does this procedure relate to n-theory?
To what?
To n-theory.
Doesn't yet.
Not yet.
We'll hopefully come to it.
The other diagram that you had were the...
You had the Swiggy line going vertical.
In other words, you had the two particles coming in.
That would correspond to if
those two points were actually...
If you had a negative...
You want to study it if you use
a coordinates in which it looks like this.
And then the other one goes...
Reaches all of it.
The top one goes further to the left.
Yeah.
Then the integration...
You can pick one of these.
You can hold one of them fixed.
The other one has to go all the ways to...
From plus infinity to minus infinity.
I was just comparing to the path...
The two paths that you
had that you said were equivalent.
That would be equivalent to, say, the top break...
The point at the top break being to
the left of the point at the bottom break.
Yeah.
That's the...
Yep.
You do have to do that.
You have to integrate over.
But in the special case where you have
them at exactly the same height, the integral terminates
when they touch.
And it's the same integral.
The amazing thing is it's the same integral.
And in fact, it's the same integral as integrating
over the points on the boundary of a disk.
So, this is a sort of nice, uniform,
symmetric picture in which all the particles are on
the same footing.
And you can pull...
And you can pull it and you can, you know,
pull it out and push it in in various ways
to make it look like different kinds of processes.
But...
It's nice.
Yeah.
So, this is open string theory.
Open string theory, the particles
are injected on the boundaries.
The boundaries...
And these are the edges of the strings.
The endpoints of the strings.
That's what the boundaries are.
We'll talk about closed string
theory a little bit next time.
So, you can see the mathematics of
it at this level is fairly simple.
It is.
I mean, it's just electrostatics.
Is this...
When you say this is
basically string theory, is this model...
I mean, this matches up with experimental results?
So, when using this formalism, you match
what you get when you run experiments?
Which experiment are you thinking of?
Colliding particles.
It's a reasonable description of hadrons.
Nobody has the vaguest idea what
happens when you collide gravitons together.
So, I mean, we have a good idea.
We have lots of idea.
But the details of it can...
You know, way beyond us.
And there is a zillion versions of this.
Don't get...
This is...
I have described one simple version of a string theory.
There's a zillion versions.
And the zillion versions are connected with
the way the extra dimensions are compactified.
We haven't talked about that.
No, this doesn't agree at all with the experiment.
It has 26 dimensions of space.
How could it compare with the experiment?
It's terrible.
You're talking about the other end.
When you talk about the scalar...
When you talk about the scattering
amplitudes, you're talking about something that is...
They're not things that you can measure in any experiment.
What I'm trying to figure out
is you're calculating a scattering amplitude.
Right.
And you're asking whether it agrees with experiment.
The first thing you would discover if you
took these scattering amplitudes and compared them with experiment
is the number of dimensions was radically wrong.
Immediately.
You can't even get started with it.
We have a lot more to do before
we can make a sensible theory out of this.
Details, details.
What could be worse?
The number of dimensions of space is...
25 of them instead of 3.
It's off by not even an integer.
Oh, it's better in superstring theory.
There the number of dimensions is 9
and it's only 3 times too large.
I just wanted to get
clear that this was pure mathematics.
At the moment.
So does that mean that eventually we'll come
around to a point where you will compactify
these things and then get reasonable numbers
that we see somewhere on the solstice?
Yeah, but the real complexity and
enormous difficulty of this subject, the mathematical
sophistication of it is in the
compactifications and it is really hard.
That's where the difficulties are.
And I can show you some simple examples
of compactification and I can show you how they
lead to information about particles and
about gauge groups and things like that.
But to do the real thing is far, far,
not only beyond me, but it's far, far beyond the
subject.
I mean, nobody knows how to put these
things together to make realistic theories of particles.
So, let's say that we're, this is a machine
for making lots and lots and lots of different
models.
The number of models or the number of constructions that
can be made are in the 10 to the thousands.
So, this is very much a work in progress.
But on the other hand, there is
a very, very definite mathematical subject of constructing
a model.
They are highly rigorous and they
produce an enormous wealth of mathematical information
about gravity, about mathematics.
But there's no question that it has not
succeeded in giving a theory of elementary particles,
or better yet, it has succeeded in giving
about 10 to the 500 theories of elementary
particles.
Which is, you know, that's a lot.
Yeah.
And it's, you know, it may be like that.
I think it's like that.
But we will find out.
This is, you know, I
am not proselytizing for this theory.
I'm simply telling you what it is.
Is there a brief description for how it
came about with 26 dimensions in this model?
Yeah, I thought, yeah, there's a brief description.
And unless, we talked about it, we talked about
1 plus 2 plus 3 plus 4 equals minus
a 12th.
And 12 times 2 is 24.
And 24th plus 2 is 26.
Remember that?
Are these k's quantized in any sense?
Are they what?
Are they quantized or are they considered continuous values?
Which?
The k, the momenta?
Which things?
When you look at the electrostatics, do
you assume that there's a quantization or do
you assume that it's continuous value?
No.
The only thing that's quantized is the sums
of the squares of the momenta, which is the
mass squared of the particle.
Yeah.
No.
Momenta is not quantized.
Most definitely not.
Okay.
Good.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.