Stanford University.
All right, let's try to get to the
heart of some of the aspects of string theory,
which are really very central.
We haven't talked about them, but
we've set up many of the questions.
We've set up many of the ideas.
I want to show you first something which has
both to do with why string theory has gravity
in it, and it has to do with
why there are such unusual constraints on the allowable
kinds of string theories that you can have.
I'm not going to actually get into 26 or 30.
It's 10 dimensions, but I'm going to give
you an example which shows just how tightly
constrained the idea of string theory is
compared to the idea of point particles.
Point particles can move in curved spaces.
A very, very simple example would just be...
This is something you can...
You can look up, I
suspect, in elementary mechanics textbooks.
Ordinary particles moving on a curved surface.
Curved surface could be a sphere.
It doesn't matter.
Some sort of curved surface.
It could be positively curved, negatively curved.
In fact, it doesn't have to be
two-dimensional, but I'm drawing it as two-dimensional.
Let's say a two-dimensional surface and a particle on it.
A particle is described by a point on that space.
A point and a velocity, if you
want to know the future history of it.
And it moves on a trajectory.
Moves on a trajectory.
And it satisfies an equation of motion.
The equation of motion is some form
of Newton's equations projected onto the surface.
How does a point particle move?
I'm thinking now about ordinary particles.
Ordinary non-relativistic particles moving on
a curved surface without any forces.
The forces, of course, are there to hold
it in the surface, but other than the forces
needed to hold it in the surface, no other forces.
How does a point particle move?
Anybody know?
It moves on a geodesic.
Moves on a geodesic, which is another way
of saying it moves as straight as possible.
It doesn't deviate to the left.
Doesn't deviate to the right.
It moves along a geodesic.
That's right.
If there are forces on
it of one kind or another...
Then it may move in a more complicated trajectory.
You could imagine that this wouldn't be consistent.
You could imagine that it might not be consistent.
How could it fail to be consistent to write down...
It's just a differential equation,
just a Newton-type differential equation.
Here's a way that it could be...
Which of course is not inconsistent.
It's perfectly consistent.
As long as it's consistent, it's a good thing.
It's a good thing.
As long as the surface is smooth.
As long as the surface is smooth, differentiable,
all the good things that nice surfaces have.
But what do you really mean by a
motion of a particle satisfying a differential equation?
As always, you mean break up the trajectory
into a lot of little pieces, replace derivatives
by distances, and think of a discrete version of it.
That's the first step.
Derivatives are really differences.
And then take the limit.
Take the limit in the appropriate way
of more and more little time intervals.
How do I know that the limit exists?
Could it be that as I put more and more
points in there, that the limit of whatever it is
you're calculating, the trajectory itself...
How do I know that the trajectory does not exist?
And then you have to figure it out.
Could it be that...
that the limit exists? Well, these
are just described by ordinary differential equations.
People have been studying differential equations
since the mathematician differential was a
young man. And we know that the solutions
of these things are smooth, regular, and have
good limits.
Ordinary.
Okay. Now you could ask a more complicated
question. You could say, wait a minute, I'm
really interested in quantum mechanics. And in
quantum mechanics, we have a more complicated
kind of question. Instead of just looking
for a trajectory, we ask questions, for example,
what's the amplitude that if a particle starts
here, that at a later time we will discover
it here? We find again there is an
action principle, but the action principle is not
to find the trajectory of least action,
which gives a differential equation, but to use
a particle.
So what's the path integral? And the
path integral sums over all trajectories, including
wildly varying ones. Again, a trajectory being
defined in terms of breaking it up into
little pieces and then taking a limit. Now
how do I know that the limit exists? Yeah?
Are those trajectories all inside the surface?
Yeah, they're all inside the surface.
Yeah. Everything takes place inside the surface.
Yes. Good point. Yeah. We're
talking about physics in a surface.
On a surface, whatever you want to
call it. Those features, which are completely independent
of how the surface, that depend on the
geometry of the surface, but not in anything outside
the surface. Yeah. All right. So how do
I know that this very, very complicated path
integral structure exists in the sense that it has
a limit, a limit as you take the grain
structure finer and finer?
There the answer is much, much more
complicated, but it's equivalent to solving the ordinary
Schrodinger equation on the surface. And again,
that's a more complicated kind of equation.
It's a partial differential equation. And
partial differential equations are more difficult,
but partial was a very smart guy, and
he figured out how partial differential equations work.
And we know from 19th century physics and
so forth that the limits do exist. They do
make sense.
String theory is more subtle, infinitely more
subtle. In string theory, we're not talking
about a point particle. We're talking about
an extended object. Now, that's the string
itself. Imagine a string which is constrained to
move in a surface. And this surface does
not have to be two dimensional. But as
I said, I'm going to think about two dimensions.
Here's the string. And it's a quantum
mechanical string, which means it's subject to vibrations.
In fact, just to pick an example, let's
talk about string theory where the space that the
string moves on.
Now, there's real space. The space that the
string moves on is a sphere. And it happens
to be a sphere with radius r. It's a
sphere with radius r. Oh, let's do a point particle
first. In fact, let's do a classical point particle first.
Point particle moves on a sphere. What is
its kinetic energy or its Lagrangian? As always,
it's just 1 half.
So, the velocity vector is 1 half mv
squared, mass times velocity squared, which is also
the momentum squared divided by twice the mass.
Let's write it that way. P squared divided
by twice the mass. But now there's a
constraint. And the constraint is that the particle has
to stay on the sphere. Nevertheless, what that
means is this velocity vector is in the
surface of the sphere. The momentum vector is
also in the surface of the sphere. And
that's the momentum vector. But other
than that, it's just standard classical mechanics.
Now, if we were doing quantum mechanics, then on
a sphere, the motion of a particle on a
sphere moves in a circle, of course, a great
circle, a great circle of size r. The momentum
is quantized. How do you see that the
momentum is quantized? Well, there's various ways to
see it, but let me just give you a very
simple way. If the momentum is p and the radius of
the sphere is r, what is the angular momentum?
PR. PR. PR. So the angular momentum L is equal
to p times r, in magnitude anyway. And
angular momentum we know is quantized. We know that
it's quantized in units of h bar. So,
some quantized angular momentum here. I'm not even
going to bother writing it. Angular
momentum is fundamental because it's quantized. So,
it pays to rewrite the energy in terms of
the angular momentum. Let's write p as L over
r, and stick it into here. Then it becomes
L squared divided by twice m, let's see, what
is it, twice m, and now r squared, right? m
r squared. Do you know what m r squared is
called?
Moment of inertia.
Moment of inertia. The moment of inertia, in
this case, of the point particle over here.
And the symbol for it?
I.
I. L squared over twice the moment of
inertia. So, what characterizes the motion of this
particle is, first of all, its angular momentum,
but the moment of inertia. The moment of inertia
is less than square root of V, it's more
than square root of V. 다양 감 m allη常
Ϡ v attached to the moment of inertia. This
equation, that's got the big
constant that the initial moment
Ts does. T
Okay, so all of that is straightforward.
Now we want to talk about a
string, a string moving on this sphere.
Here it is.
It's constrained to be in the sphere.
The spherical surface is all there is.
There is no outside the spherical surface and inside.
There's only the spherical surface itself.
However, as I said, the spherical surface
could be higher dimensional, but for the moment
just two-dimensional, and it's going to move around.
Good.
How do I know that in the limit that I
think of the string as a collection of little points,
how do I know that the properties
of this little string have good limits?
The answer is they don't.
Spencer, not that we don't know.
The answer is that the limits don't exist.
So let me show you why and what happens.
The first thing is to understand a little
more about the size and shapes of strings.
We want to understand a little more about them.
So let's calculate how big statistically the
string has zero point oscillations, the oscillators
in the string are constantly
vibrating, even in the ground state.
Because they're vibrating, they give
the string a little size.
They give the string a little size.
And I'm interested in trying to figure out
how big that string is when the zero point
oscillations are included.
So how do I do that?
I go back to a formula that we had
on the blackboard, maybe the first or second lecture.
Let's do open strings just for simplicity.
Remember this formula?
The position of a point
on the string, what is sigma?
Sigma is the parameter along the string,
is equal to a sum over oscillators.
Each oscillator has a frequency
associated with it, so an n.
And we have...
Let's call it a plus n plus
a minus n cosine of n sigma.
And there's one other thing,
a square root of n downstairs.
Does everybody remember that?
Probably not.
But if you go back in your notes...
Yes.
Yeah.
There may be factors of
two, I don't remember in detail.
Whether the factor of two is
a factor of n or not.
I don't remember.
But there's a factor of n.
I guess it's a factor of n.
You don't remember that.
It's a factor of n or not.
It's not an odd factor.
It's a factor of n.
It's a factor of 2 that
sits in front of it or not.
But that's not important.
This is the structure of it.
Now what do I want to calculate?
I want to calculate in
the ground state of the string.
Ground state of the string
is a state with no oscillations.
I want to calculate the mean size
of it, the average size of it.
So the average size of it,
let's calculate the average squared size.
x squared at any point sigma, an arbitrary point sigma.
What does that give us?
That gives us sum on
n and a sum on m.
We're going to have a
plus n plus a minus n
times a plus m plus a minus m
over square root of n, square root of m,
cosine n sigma, cosine m sigma.
I've just written down this expression twice.
Once as a sum over n
and once as a sum over m.
I've done nothing special.
Now what I want to calculate is
its average value in the ground state.
Average value in the ground state
in quantum mechanics we represent like this.
O stands for the ground state string.
We want to calculate its average value.
That means we want to calculate the average of this
in the simultaneous ground state of all of the oscillations.
You might think the answer is zero, right?
Well, that's not quite true.
Every oscillator in its
ground state, quantum mechanical oscillator,
has a little bit of zero point energy.
That little bit of zero point
energy gives it an average fluctuation,
in position or in this case in x itself.
And how do we calculate it?
Let's look at the various terms here.
We're going to calculate the
ground state expectation value of this.
O O.
The important pieces are
these creation and annihilation operators.
What happens if I take the
piece with a plus times a plus?
Can that have an expectation value
for in the,
in the ground state
well no it can't
the reason is two A pluses
when they act to the right
create a state
with two extra units of energy
you've raised
the oscillator in twice
and that has no overlap
with the ground state at all
so the term with two
A pluses
that can't contribute to this
how about the term with two A minuses
what does A minus do
when it hits the ground state
it kills it right
it's also true incidentally when A plus
acts to the left it kills this
so the term with A plus
A plus and A minus A minus
give nothing
what about
A plus times A minus
A plus times A minus gives nothing
well you just said it kills
the left kills the right
right so that's not there
but what about the term A minus A plus
sounds good
let's look at it
A minus times A plus that's still there
if it's zero
so be it
but I don't see any
reason why it should be zero
okay
what does this say it says
we create one unit of excitation
for the
the nth oscillator
this says we remove
one unit of excitation
for the nth oscillator
can you remove
a unit
other than the one you put in
no
so this can only be non-zero
if n is the same as m
but if n is the same
as m what do you get
delta
a chronic or delta one
these are all discreet so they're not continuous variables
nth oscillator
You get 1 if n equals m, and 0 otherwise.
In other words, the sum over n
and m is only a single sum.
It's the sum over n of a minus
n, a plus n, over square root of n.
Sorry, not square, n, n.
Square root of n times square
root of m, that's just n,
and then cosine squared of n sigma.
Now, cosine squared is always positive,
and it averages to about a half.
Cosine of n sigma is
a function which looks like this.
If you square it, of course, it's above the axis,
because the square is always positive.
And it averages to about a half.
That's good enough for our purposes.
It's never negative.
You can't get any cancellation, and
it kind of oscillates around a half.
So for most purposes, it's sufficient
just to call this a half.
And that's about right.
O, O.
And what is this thing?
This thing is just 1.
You create a particle, or you
create an excitation of the nth oscillator,
and then you take it out.
That average value is just 1.
So we now have an answer.
The answer is that x squared,
now I'll tell you what
x squared means in a moment.
It's equal, the one half
is not the important thing here,
just sum on n, 1 over n.
Now, first of all, what is x squared?
What is x?
I wrote here x of sigma,
but I left out one term.
Does anybody know what the
term that I left out is?
The center of mass motion.
There's one term which corresponds to zero frequency,
which is just the center of mass.
So really, the thing that I've
calculated was the average of the position,
of the string at point sigma,
minus the position of the center of mass.
Think about that for a moment.
What's it mean?
You have a string, in this case an open string,
and the center of mass may
or may not be on the string.
But different points on the string
are separated from the center of mass.
The average,
the average separation from the center of mass
is a measure of the size of the thing.
The center of mass is
where the center of mass is,
and if the points of the string
are not at the center of mass,
that means that it's been spread out.
If this is non-zero, it means
the string is extended in size.
And here we're calculating it, and we find out
that x squared is this sum of 1 over n.
Okay?
Trouble.
Trouble. Big trouble.
Why is it trouble?
It's infinite.
Now, most of these oscillations are incredibly rapid.
Large n oscillations are very, very rapid oscillations.
Maybe we should just say, really,
all those very, very rapid oscillations are
unphysical,
cut them off,
only take the first n,
the first 25 oscillations into account,
and see what happens.
Well, then we'll only have log of 25, and
log of 25 is not a very big number.
How big is log of 25? Log to
the base e of 25? Not very big.
It's a small number. A moderate number.
But then we're not doing string theory.
We're essentially doing a string of 25 particles.
We're not doing string theory.
We've got to go to the limit n equals 0.
Now, it's an extremely remarkable
thing that this causes no problems
for the scattering of strings in flat space.
In flat space, it's a real magical,
very, very delicate cancellations that
make sure that this string,
which is essentially infinitely big with rapid
fluctuations taking place all over the place,
doesn't bombard other strings far away, even
though it's extended out all over the place.
They're very rapid fluctuations.
It's an amazing set of cancellations which
makes sure that all of this works out.
But those cancellations don't always work.
They work in some geometries and in others.
So I'm going to show you
what goes wrong on the sphere,
and it doesn't go wrong in flat space.
First of all, the message of all of this is,
first step, terminate this sum at some maximum n.
A maximum frequency.
Later on, we're going to have to repair
the damage by letting the maximum frequency get larger.
Now we can ask, how does this string behave?
As a function of n max.
In flat space, well, here's
the way to think about it.
As a function of n max, the
string occupies a certain region of space.
It's the region of space whose x
squared, or r, whose r squared is equal
to the logarithm of n max.
The higher we make n max,
the bigger it seems to spread out.
But very, very slowly.
But nevertheless, it seems to spread out.
Well, if this is moving in flat space, it has a
energy which is just one half its mass times p squared.
It doesn't matter that it's spread out.
The motion of the center
of mass of a billiard ball,
this big, that big,
moves exactly the same way as the motion
of the center of mass of a proton.
It moves the center of mass,
well, of course it's not the
same way, it has a different mass.
But in flat space, the motion of a particle,
the center of mass of a particle,
separates off the fact that it's an extended object.
You don't have to remember the fact that it's extended
if you're just interested in the center of mass motion.
But that's not true in curved space.
In curved space, they don't separate off so easily.
So let's see if we
can figure out what's happening here.
Here's the string.
Let's put the string up at the north pole here.
The string is up at the north pole.
And if I make as my first approximation
that there's only one or two oscillating modes,
well, we could start with no oscillating modes,
if there were no oscillating modes,
then the string would be a point.
It wouldn't be spread out at all.
It would be like a, just be a point.
Then the string would just be a
point, and it would be over here,
and it would move as an ordinary point particle.
How does a point particle move?
It moves with an energy which
is the square of the angular momentum
over the moment of inertia.
And what's the moment of inertia?
It's just proportional to mass times the radius squared,
times the radius squared of the sphere.
If we set m to 1, then it would
just be the square of the radius of the sphere.
So this point here would move
around the sphere on great circles,
and it would move with an energy which
would be controlled by the radius of the sphere.
The radius of the sphere would go into this calculation,
in terms of the moment of inertia.
Okay, now let's take into account that
as we add more modes of oscillation,
the string starts to spread out.
It starts to get a size and grows.
Not grows with time, but grows
with more and more oscillations here.
It starts to get bigger.
It fills up some region, which looks about like that.
Incidentally, if you ask what does
it look like on the average,
it simply looks like a tangle.
The more modes that you add, the
more and the bigger the tangle is.
It's fluctuations on top of
fluctuations on top of fluctuations,
and this thing starts to get bigger.
So if you think about its motion
around the center of mass of it,
think of the center of mass of
it moving on the same great circle.
The center of mass will
still move on the great circle,
but what about its moment of inertia?
Moment of inertia about an axis.
Here's an axis. It's moving. It's going around that axis.
The relevant quantity is the
moment of inertia about that axis,
and it's governed by the square
of the distance to the axis.
The moment of inertia about an
axis is proportional to a sum.
It's an integral over the mass distribution.
Each little piece of the mass distribution,
you take the mass of that little piece,
and you multiply it by the
square of the distance to the axis
that you're rotating about.
Now notice that this point over
here is closer to the axis
than this point up here.
In fact, let's go to extremes.
Let's suppose we include so many modes that...
Let me draw this better.
It droops down to about over here.
It's rotating around the sphere this way.
It's on the sphere. It's not inside the sphere.
It's on the sphere.
The point on the sphere up here,
that is a distance r from the axis.
What about this point over here?
How far from the axis is it?
Is it less than or more than r?
Looks less than, doesn't it?
But that's deceptive because we forgot
that the sphere is really a sphere.
It's really a sphere.
It's like moving the point down to here.
With the axis going in this direction,
it would be the same distance.
This point over here,
which is out here somewhere,
is the same distance from the axis as this point.
But how about this point over here?
It really is closer to the
axis than the point up here.
So what's going to happen when I calculate the...
when I calculate the moment of inertia?
The moment is going to be bigger or
smaller or exactly the same as it was
when I pretended all of the
string was at a single point.
It's going to be smaller.
Right.
The mass of the string is the same, incidentally.
That does not change when you add more modes.
It just oscillates differently, but the mass,
the amount of mass that's there
is just the sum of the masses
of little point particles that make it up.
The mass stays the same,
but the moment of inertia gets smaller.
The meaning of that is that the quantum mechanics behaves...
You can either say
You can say it two ways.
You can say the string is spread out like that
and therefore closer to the axis.
Or you can just say it's as
if the string moved on a smaller sphere.
It's as if all of the quantum mechanics essentially takes...
behaves as if the string was a point,
but was a point on a smaller sphere.
Okay?
But the more modes that you add,
the bigger the string gets.
Eventually, if you add enough modes,
it's going to grow so that it's
almost as big as the entire sphere.
In other words,
well, let's go to some extreme
where it fills up a good fraction of the sphere.
In that case,
the effective moment of inertia
is going to be much smaller
than the moment of inertia
would have been
if it would have been a point particle.
But even worse,
there's no limit.
Or at least as n gets larger and larger,
the string begins to cover the whole sphere
and the effective moment of inertia is actually zero.
The average position of it is right at the center.
If the effective moment of inertia is zero,
well, that's a zero in the denominator here.
That's not a good thing for the motion of anything.
Why is it zero?
I mean, it's still spread around.
It's as if the thing should...
Well, it's...
No, it's not zero.
It's not zero, but...
Okay.
Yeah, yeah, no, no.
You have to be...
It does go to zero,
but you have to think
about it in a different way.
What you do is...
What you do is you say the string behaves...
If you only take into account,
let's say, a dozen normal modes,
then the string behaves as if it were a point
on a closer circle.
But now instead of a dozen normal modes,
let's take two dozen normal modes.
Then what it does is it starts to behave
like a string
on this inner surface here.
This is not obvious.
This is what is called renormalization group.
Renormalization group is a way of following the system
as you add more and more degrees of freedom.
What you can follow it honestly
is for a small change in n max.
But once you follow it for
a small change in n max
and you find out that it's behaving
as if it were a lump,
let's say this big,
now you add more structure,
it begins to behave like a collection of lumps
that also form a string.
And you just do the whole process over again.
You say with a dozen normal modes,
it behaves as if it were
a more or less a point
on an inner region here.
Now you add more of them
and it begins to make itself
into a string of these same lumps.
That has the effect of pushing it in again.
And eventually it just pushes it to zero.
So there is no limit.
There is no limit.
The limit of a string moving on a curved surface,
and this is due to the curvature.
If it weren't due to the curvature,
you wouldn't have this effect.
It's due to the curvature of the sphere.
This happens in any number of dimensions.
And it's not just a number.
It's a number of modes.
That as you add more and more modes,
the behavior does not tend to a finite limit.
It just tends to behave eventually
as the motion of a string on an extremely small
infinitesimal sphere,
which means in the denominator here a zero.
And that's not a good theory.
That's what happens.
So the answer is strings on spheres are not good.
Strings on spheres don't make sense.
What is the condition for a surface,
and a surface I'm using
the term in a general sense.
It doesn't have to be two dimensional.
It could be three, four, ten, twenty-six dimensions,
whatever the number of dimensions
of space.
What we mean by a surface
is a geometry with a metric.
A geometry with a metric.
A Riemannian geometry.
What are the rules?
What you really want is a set of rules
which approach a limit.
If you're near that limit, then,
in other words, by a limit, I mean the limit
that as n max gets bigger and bigger.
You don't want the answers to change
as n max goes from 100
billion to 100 billion plus one.
Or for that matter, from 100 billion to 200 billion.
You want the answer to stabilize.
That's called a fixed point.
You want the answer to stabilize and not to change.
So what you would like
is a situation with a geometry
that when you do exactly the same thing,
the geometry does not seem to change.
In other words, we could define an effective geometry
for a string.
We take the geometry and
now we sort of average over
the properties of an extended object
and that defines the motion on a different surface.
Different surface being the effective surface
that the spread out string moves on.
As long as it keeps changing on us,
as we increase n max,
there will not be a limit.
A limit would mean that at some point,
as you add more and more structure to the string,
the effective geometry stops changing
and tends to some limit.
That limit will be a good geometry
for string theory to make sense on.
Okay, so I'll tell you what one can do
this calculation very precisely
for an arbitrary geometry.
And you can ask,
when you add
additional modes,
let's say you add, you
go up to some n max
and you add one more mode,
how does the effective geometry
that the string moves on,
how does it change?
How do you describe a Riemannian geometry?
What's the variables that you describe
in Riemannian geometry?
The metric, right?
The metric tensor.
That's the description of the geometry.
g mu nu of x.
This, don't think of it now as the gravitational field,
although it is the gravitational field,
it's the metric of space,
g mu nu of x.
We have a geometry,
could be the sphere,
could be anything else,
could be a hyperboloid,
it could be a thing with wiggles in it,
it might be space-time geometry itself.
Okay?
A string moving on such a geometry,
the effective geometry will change a little bit.
Why?
Because the string is spread out a little bit,
the center of it will move in a way
that responds to a slightly different geometry,
and so we can ask what's the change
in the effective geometry
when you add one more mode.
Okay, the answer is, first of all,
that it depends on the curvature.
If the sphere is moving,
if the sphere weren't curved,
this would not have happened.
This has to do with the
fact that the sphere was curved.
So, whatever the change in the geometry is,
if it were flat, it would not change.
But if it's curved, it does change in general.
So, there must be on the right-hand side
something which involves the curvature tensor.
The left-hand side is a tensor,
with a mu and a nu,
a second-rank tensor, symmetric.
So, the right-hand side has to be a tensor.
It's not g mu nu itself,
it's some other tensor that
has to do with the curvature.
If it weren't curved, nothing would happen.
So, it must be that on the right-hand side
is something involving curvature.
Curvature is called capital R,
and the full curvature tensor
has four indices.
It's a thing with four indices.
R, let's say, mu, nu...
No, let's not call it mu and nu.
For the moment, let's just call it
alpha, beta, gamma, delta.
You can put all four downstairs,
upstairs, doesn't matter.
It's often written with one index upstairs
and some indices downstairs.
Okay.
This equation doesn't make sense.
The indices don't match.
But is there a thing that you can make
out of the curvature tensor
which also has only two indices
and which is symmetric?
Anybody know?
The Ricci tensor.
The Ricci tensor is simply
the contraction alpha, alpha, mu, nu.
That's called R mu nu,
and it's the Ricci tensor.
So when a careful calculation...
Let me see, is it plus or minus?
I think it's minus.
Minus.
Minus the Ricci tensor.
It corresponds to the sphere
getting smaller when you add more structure.
That's why there's a minus there.
This is the equation that governs
how the effective geometry of the string changes
as you add more and more
fluctuation to the string.
Mathematicians have a name for this equation.
It's called Ricci flow.
Ricci flow is a tremendously important part of mathematics.
And it's an equation that
if you start with a geometry
and then you change it in accord with this equation,
what happens is it starts to deform,
and it flows.
The geometry flows.
It's called Ricci flow.
It has very important applications in mathematics.
I don't know whether it was discovered by string theorists
or first discovered by mathematicians.
I'm not sure.
But that's what this is.
It's a fuzzing out of the geometry
because the points have gotten fuzzed out.
It's a kind of diffusion of the geometry
which is fuzzing it out.
The points have gotten fuzzed out,
but by the fluctuations of the strings,
and the effective geometry behaves this way.
Is there a function of n max there somehow?
No, this is the change when you add,
it's the logarithmic change.
It's the change when you
change the cutoff by a factor.
Yeah.
Change in the logarithm of the cutoff to be exact.
But it doesn't matter.
It's the change as you change the cutoff.
Now, what we're looking for, though,
is geometries which don't change
when you change the cutoff.
We want something stable.
We want to say we're talking about string theory
on this or that space.
We don't want the description of it
to keep wandering away
as we add more of these modes.
So what we really want
are geometries
which are stable and don't change
when we change the,
when we change things,
when we change the cutoff.
What does that mean?
That means geometries
where the Ricci tensor is zero.
If the Ricci tensor is zero,
that's like saying it's,
well, it's not like saying it's flat.
Flat space is,
does have Ricci tensor zero, of course.
It has all of its
components of curvature equal to zero.
So flat space is,
is an example of this.
Question is,
are there other examples of spaces,
this is called Ricci flat.
If a space has vanishing Ricci tensor,
it's called Ricci flat.
Ricci flatness is essentially the condition
that strings can propagate sensibly
on that geometry.
Okay.
Have good limits
as the number of modes goes to infinity.
All right, so there's,
there's a condition on the geometry.
It's called Ricci flatness.
It could be the space-time geometry
that the string is moving in.
In fact,
that's the way you think about it for the moment.
The space-time geometry
has space directions, time directions.
But anybody know what that equation,
that equation has another meaning?
Relativity?
Yeah.
It's essentially the Einstein field equation
for the gravitational field.
The Einstein field equation for the geometry,
it's the vacuum Einstein field equations.
Einstein in vacuum.
No matter, just gravity and curvature.
I'll write out the Einstein equations for you
and then I'll show you that it's the same as,
as this equation.
Anybody remember the Einstein field equations?
Something equals,
r equals t.
Something like that.
It's a tensor called capital G mu nu.
It's called the Einstein tensor
and the reason it's called capital G is
because it's got something to do with gravity.
But it's also equal to r mu nu
minus one half G mu nu r.
Okay.
Where r, what is r?
r is r alpha alpha.
Or, yeah, r alpha alpha.
And that's equal to t mu nu,
where t mu nu is the energy momentum tensor.
Energy momentum tensor means
the energy momentum of cookies,
the energy momentum of a cup of coffee,
but not the energy momentum of the gravitational field.
Everything is in here other than gravity.
Okay.
The vacuum Einstein field equations mean
the field equations for the gravitational field
when there's nothing on the right hand side.
Zero.
That's called Einstein vacuum equations.
Are there any interesting solutions to this equation?
What are the solutions of this?
Schwarzschild is one,
but Schwarzschild has a nasty singularity in it,
so it's, it's, it's, uh,
No.
Um, well Robinson Walker also has singularities,
but, uh,
Hmm?
No, the, the, the, the, the,
the city of space requires a cosmological,
no, just gravitational waves.
Just gravitational waves.
Just, that's it, gravitational waves.
It's, uh, similar to Maxwell's equations without sources.
Maxwell's equations without charges.
Do they have any solutions?
Yeah.
or just electromagnetic radiation
gravitational radiation also exists the solutions
of this kind of equation here
in four-dimensional space-time
in other words one time direction three space directions
the solutions of this include
all kinds of things like gravitational waves
interacting gravitational waves
gravitational waves can do complicated things
in Einstein gravity but there's a whole family
an infinite parameter family of complicated solutions
of these equations
now
we're interested in Ricci flat
this doesn't say R mu nu equals zero
but let's take
when I put one index upstairs and
one index downstairs that's called the trace
when I sum over alpha and alpha
alright
let's raise one index
let's write it R mu nu
minus one half g mu nu
R alpha alpha equals zero
what's g what is this thing here
one mu g with one mu downstairs and one upstairs
that's a Kronecker delta
right so that's just a
Kronecker delta
delta mu nu
and now set mu equal to nu and sum
call them both alpha
R alpha alpha
equals one half
minus sorry is equal to one half
what happens to this when you set mu
and nu both equal to alpha and sum
I think you get four right
four for the four directions of space
so this becomes either plus or minus a
half and it becomes two R alpha alpha
it doesn't it does not say let's see
two altogether
it's either plus two or minus two I can't remember
but it's quite inconsistent unless R is zero
right
this equation implies that
this is called the Ricci scalar or the curvature scalar
the curvature scalar must vanish
if Einstein's field equations are correct
if they're satisfied
so this is not there
and the Einstein field equations in empty
space is just R mu nu equals zero
what have we learned
we've learned that the only acceptable geometries
in which strings make stable sense
and in which the geometry doesn't
change and change and change and change
as you add more degrees of freedom
are the solutions of Einstein's field equations
you can quantize strings
in background geometries
which satisfy Einstein's equations
and you cannot formulate them
correctly in spaces which don't
satisfy Einstein's equations
that's pretty impressive
that out of the consistency condition
for strings to have a well defined geometry
in the limit that the number
of degrees of freedom becomes infinite
you derive Einstein's field equations for geometry
that's an extremely impressive fact
question
yes
can there be a connection between
the
it is very closely connected to conformal invariance
but not conformal invariance in spacetime
conformal invariance of the worldsheet
is very closely connected with that
non-formal invariants, but they are connected, yes.
But I've showed you the
simplest way to think about it.
That
in general, because the string spreads out, the effective geometry that
it sees is different than the geometry you started with and
in general doesn't approach a limit. If it
does approach a limit, it's because at the limit
the Ricci tensor is zero.
So Ricci tensor being zero are special.
Okay, now we want to come to a subject.
Oh, incidentally, I've
cheated a little. I haven't cheated.
I haven't told you the whole story.
The whole story is that it really doesn't work,
except if you're in the right number of dimensions.
The subtleties of this kind of thing and
are quite subtle and it really
only works that the answers become
independent of N-max if the geometry is Ricci
flat and in the right number of dimensions.
10 for superstring theory,
26 for
So that's the basic principle. The answers should
have finite limits as N-max goes to infinity,
and that is enough to tell you that the geometries
that you move in must be solutions of Einstein field equation.
They must be gravitational waves and other things.
Now we want to come
to the problem of what do we do
with 10 or 26 dimensions? How do we
make sense out of them?
And the answer is called compactification.
Compactification is simply the process of
taking however many dimensions we want to get rid of,
by getting rid of them, we
don't really get rid of them,
but we make them small enough that they become invisible,
except the very very small things.
We want to roll them up into little
manifolds that our coarse-grained apparatuses don't see.
They may affect and they will affect,
they'll have, you know, real serious effect on
the structure of particles and so forth, the structure of
elementary particles, type of elementary particles that you can have,
but they won't be visible as directions
that that you can move around in.
All right, so let's talk about compactification.
We have, let's take the case of superstring theory where
there are 10 dimensions of space-time, which is six too many.
And one good thing is
that the 10 dimensions of space-time have
only one time and six space and
nine space dimensions.
We wouldn't have, we would not know
what to do with two time dimensions.
Physics with some extra space dimensions, that's no problem, things just get to
move and more, but what would mean to have more than one time?
Beats me and
probably doesn't mean anything.
So,
Superspring theory is a theory with
nine spatial dimensions and one time dimension.
It kind of ties into what Jeff's question earlier
was about degrees of freedom versus dimension of space.
In essence what I was trying to say,
never mind whether, you know, there's 12 or only six, the idea is
that the more moving parts you have the more degrees of freedom you have.
Okay, which is not the case for
dimensionality of your core.
You have more coordinates and that's because you're
looking at commonalities of those degrees of freedom
in dimensioning your space.
The more dimensions you have the
more ways the thing can move.
So there, it turns out in
electronics design you can have multiple clocks.
So there are sort of multiple
times
within the design and essentially
what singles out a particular
signal as a clock signal is that it synchronizes a
lot of other signals or ties things together connects to
Which means it really was only one time
and a lot of clocks.
A lot of clocks is not
the same as a lot of times.
What physics would be like if you were new...
Well the question is if you have regions in which
they are effectively independent of one another then they would be...
So the thing is...
Okay, you make a theory with two times.
I don't know how.
When we say two times we mean at
every point of space there are two times.
Not a region way out there where there's one
time and a region out there where there's another time.
I mean every point of space...
Well, I mean, I think the amazing thing about
our universe is that is that the geometry space-time geometry
everywhere seems to be the same.
Yes, and it has only one time.
It also only has the same...
same, you know, whatever...
Let him give the lecture, okay?
It's alright.
I think that there are people that
don't think it's nonsense and that's why.
Yeah, there are.
There are.
People who don't think it's nonsense.
However, it has never...
It has never become any part of mainstream thinking.
And...
More than one time...
More than one time direction.
Not more than one clock. Okay, let's go on.
Yeah.
So we have these six extra dimensions of space.
How do we get rid of them?
And of course, you know the answer.
You roll them up.
The simplest model
would be a world in which
on the large scale
there was one dimension of space.
Time is there.
But let's just freeze time.
One dimension of space.
That's a long line.
We can imagine particles on this line.
Particles move up and down the line.
Maybe they bind together.
Maybe they form molecules.
Maybe they do interesting things.
Who knows?
Maybe even they can form life.
They can signal each other by
launching a particle
from one group to another group.
And you can have some possibly interesting physics.
These people who live
on this line, who are made up
out of these point particles
Well, I always like to
say they have a rather boring
life.
Each one has a friend to the left
and maybe a friend to the right.
But my joke is that
they don't have a social circle.
Because you can't have a circle in one dimension.
Ha ha ha.
Very boring life.
And also they can't
pass through each other.
They bang into each other.
Very boring.
But then they look through a high power microscope
and they discover their line
which is really
the surface of a cylinder.
Now they are too big to feel the cylinder.
They are great big things which move up and down.
But
that doesn't mean that there aren't smaller things.
And the smaller things
now can move
both along the line
and perpendicular to the line.
So there are new degrees of freedom.
There are new distinctions between
particles.
Particles can move this way, they can move this way,
they can even move this way.
And there's a whole new game.
This is the most
elementary and simple example
of compactification.
Another way you could think about it
is
let's try to think about
higher dimensions.
Let's suppose ordinary space
was two dimensional
but
when the creatures who lived in this ordinary space
magnified it
they discovered a tiny third dimension.
What might that look like?
Okay, and
a third dimension in the same sense
that the circle here
provided a third dimension.
So here's what it might look like.
There's the world
that they think they live on.
But now they look under
a microscope and they discover
that there's a direction perpendicular
so there's some thickness there.
There's some thickness there.
We'll call the top thing the ceiling
and the bottom thing the floor.
And there's some
bulk stuff, namely space,
in between.
Okay, now we're going to do something else.
Having edges like this
makes trouble for strings.
The strings start to fluctuate
and eventually they fluctuate out
and get bigger than the
distance between the floor
and the ceiling.
But we're going to do something
the same thing we do when we
well, what we're going to do is
identify the floor
with the ceiling.
We could have done this
let's go back to the cylinder.
The cylinder is really a ribbon
in which you identify
the floor with the ceiling.
You say that if you go out here
you come back here.
In other words,
here's the ribbon
and
the cylinder is obtained from the ribbon
by identifying
one edge with the other edge.
When you go out here, you come back in here.
Same thing here.
The floor and the ceiling are identified
so that when you go
out the ceiling here
you reappear on the floor.
Now this direction
there is no edge.
There's no edge anymore
and this perpendicular direction here
has the topology of a circle.
It's periodically identified.
This would be an example
of compactifying one
out of three
dimensions.
Can you compactify two out of
three dimensions? How many bits
would be left over
if you compactified two out of three?
One.
So we'd be back to the world of one dimension
but with something new.
Two compact dimensions instead of one.
Let me show you what that would look like.
A particular way of doing it.
This is a particular way of doing it.
Take a
well let me make it bigger
this is kind of a prism
an infinitely long
prism. Would you call this a prism?
I thought prism I guess
no prism is the wrong word
Rectangular something or other
Rectangular what?
Rectangular parallelepiped
except that it's infinite in extent.
Okay? Right.
It has edges.
But what we're going to do
with the edges is we're going to
identify
this edge with this edge
and this edge with this edge.
Not just the edges. A point over here
is identified with a point on the floor.
A point on the ceiling
A point on the back wall
is identified with a point
on the front wall. Here's the back wall
here's the front wall.
So anything that goes out through an edge
reappears on the opposite
face at the same spot.
That
now has compactified
and there's no edges left.
Once you make these identifications
there really are no edges anymore.
To draw it
you know to draw it
on a plane
really on a plane
you take the cylinder
you slit it
and you open it up.
Okay so now it looks like
it has a floor and a ceiling
but then keep in mind that the
real geometry is identified
and has no edge.
Same here. There are no edges.
Anybody who walks out one side
reappears at the other and doesn't even notice it.
So this is
compactifying two out of three dimensions.
How about
two out of ten or six out of ten?
Yeah, you can do the same thing.
And
exactly
the same thing.
And this process
is called
toroidal
compactification.
Okay, what does it have to do with a torus?
Let's talk about
a tori because tori
are the simplest
geometries
to use for compactification.
The edge of this here
this face over here
is a torus.
It doesn't look like a torus.
Doesn't look like a donut.
But topologically it's a donut.
So let's talk about tori.
The simplest torus
is a circle.
That's a one dimensional torus.
It's just a circle.
You say a circle doesn't
look like a torus. Well,
don't worry about it. We're going to
define the thing that does look like a torus.
Let's take a torus.
Incidentally, when we talk about a torus,
we're not
talking about a shape
embedded in three dimensional, two dimensional
shape embedded in three dimensions.
What we're talking about
is a topology. We're talking about
the topology of the
boundary.
Not the interior of the
torus. We're not talking about a solid
torus. We're not talking about a donut with
a dough on the inside. We're talking
about the mathematical surface
of the torus.
Okay? And what we're talking
about when we use the word torus is the
topology of the surface.
Okay.
There's a torus. And
let me now do something to it.
I'm going to
cut it
over here.
Well, cut it over here.
I'm going to take a scissor
and slice it around here.
Now remember, we're not talking about the stuff that's
inside the torus. We're only talking about the surface.
Cut it
and open it up. What does it look like?
It looks
like a finite piece of a cylinder,
right?
But I have to remember with
uh, yeah, we've taken it and opened
it up. Alright, it's not the same as
the torus, but it's topologically
the same as the torus as long as
we remember that this point
is identified with this point,
this point is identified with
this point. Anybody
who walks
along here and crosses
this edge, that's over
here, comes back over
here, that's over here.
Alright, so we've done the same game
except we've taken a cylinder now
and identified
the left
cut here with the right cut
through the cylinder over here. That is
now mathematically a torus.
But we can go another step.
We can now take our scissor and cut it
along here.
And now open it up
and it
becomes a rectangle.
So a torus is topologically
the same as a rectangle,
but we have to remember that
the rectangle has identifications.
If this point is called A,
then this is also A.
If this point is called
B, then this is also called B.
Let's follow the
trajectory of a particle as
it moves on a torus.
A hypothetical particle,
a fake particle moving on
a mathematical
torus like this. What happens to
it? Let's see if we can
follow it. Let's suppose it starts over here
moving this way
and assume that it moves in a straight
line. Okay? No forces
on it. What happens when it gets
to here?
It reappears
at the bottom, right?
Now it goes at the same angle because
it hasn't been accelerated and it gets to over
here. It gets to over here,
reappears over here.
Now what?
Goes to here, where does it reappear?
Back over here.
Okay.
Depending on the angle
and depending on the ratio of the
sides of the torus,
it will either, if the ratios of the
sides of the torus are rational
and some other good things,
it will simply
repeat itself
and eventually find itself on the original
line again.
So that there will be a
finite number of bands like this
and then repeat
itself. If the ratios of the
sides are incommensurate or if you have some
incommensurate angle,
then it will just keep going and going and
going, essentially filling up the
entire, or getting arbitrarily close
to any point on the torus.
But this is not the important thing. The important
thing is that a
torus is a way
of compactifying space.
That's exactly what we did over here.
We took this
and identified it with this,
this and identified it with this.
So this would be called
a
compactification
of two
dimensions, keeping the third
one uncompactified
but the compactification would
be a torus.
Tori are especially simple
geometries for compactification.
There are other geometries that you
could try and
people do. I can't
draw it quite the same way,
but you could take a line
times a
sphere,
a line times a two-dimensional
sphere so that every point on
the line, a little fly
moving up and down that
or a little insect moving up and down
that line would be able to
move along the line
or along a sphere
attached to each point on
just as there's a torus
attached to each point here,
you could do a sphere.
For reasons
that I'll come to, spheres are not
good things to compactify on.
Alright, so this is the toroidal
Now, can you do the same
thing with
higher dimensions? Let's suppose we had
Supposing we wanted to get rid of three
dimensions. To get rid of
three dimensions, we want to invent a thing
called a three torus.
A three-dimensional torus. We want to take
three of the dimensions and
make them into a torus. Yes,
that's not hard. You do exactly the same
thing. You take a cube.
Doesn't have to be a cube.
A
parallel a pipette, or whatever you call it.
And now, do the same
kind of identifications.
This face over here, A,
is identified with this face over here, A.
This one over here, B,
with this one, B.
And the backside of a
a
C, this is in the back,
is identified with C
in the front.
That becomes what is called a three torus.
It has the topology of a three torus.
Again, no edges,
although if you try to draw it, you draw it
with edges.
And that would
effectively shrink
three directions, if you made the
torus small in any case. If you made it
physically small, it would hide
three dimensions,
at least from your coarse-grained
measurements. So if you were doing
string theory in ten dimensions,
and you compactify three,
ten space-time dimensions,
compactify three, you would have
seven dimensions left over,
one time and six space.
That's also not what we want.
So what do we want to do?
We want to make a
we want to get rid of six dimensions.
So we make a six torus.
A six torus I can't
draw on the blackboard for you.
I suppose I could draw a four torus,
but we'd clutter up the blackboard terribly.
What's the figure,
the four cube called,
when you,
what?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And then identify faces of that,
but, or volumes of it,
you'd be identifying volumes of it.
But, um,
mathematically, all you're
doing is adding axes,
and keeping, and making identifications.
A torus, yeah?
It seems like all these dimensions,
all these spatial dimensions greater than three
come back on themselves.
Yeah.
They're periodically identified.
They're what?
Yeah. Yeah. They come back on themselves.
Is that, that's fundamental, I guess.
Well.
You can't go infinite like x, y, and z can.
You could have six or ten
or nine, whatever it is,
dimensions which don't come back on themselves.
It just wouldn't be our world.
You ask,
why did nature choose
to, uh, to compactify
some dimensions and not others?
That we haven't got the
vaguest idea, but, uh,
we do know that we live in a world
of three dimensions.
Why do we assume that other dimensions are spatial?
String theory, or no other theory
that I know, quantum field theory,
none of them make sense with more than
one time dimension.
Correct. We know we have one
real time dimension,
but there's no more room for more.
But, why beyond the
four, do we assume that the
remaining dimensions are spatial?
What else could they be?
What else would they be?
I'm not, well, I've got some ideas, but
my point is that just because
we can't identify what they are,
why do we assume they are spatial
and
curled up as opposed to something
that else we just don't understand?
Because we can understand
this.
It doesn't mean it's the real world.
It means it's a thing
we can study,
find out its properties,
see how it behaves,
and compare it with the real world.
If you just say, maybe
it's something and we don't know what it is,
okay, we'll stop. We're dead.
This is
easy,
it's straightforward,
it's not enormously subtle,
not these tori,
these tori are pretty easy,
they're not enormously subtle,
they're solvable,
we can work out
what particle physics is like,
we can work out what the
world on
in such a setup is like,
and we can ask, how close is it,
how similar is it to the real world?
That's the only reason.
It's a setup that we
know and understand,
it has gravity, it has quantum mechanics,
it has particles, it has bosons,
it has fermions, and we can study it.
It also has black holes,
so we can study the black holes and find out
if they do this or that,
that's the reason.
What does it lack?
It's too symmetric.
It has supersymmetry and other symmetries
that are just too symmetric.
Some things it lacks and some
things it has too much of.
When you take the bagel and turn it
into a rectangle,
topologically they're equivalent,
but if you look at the distance
of why on the inside of it...
Yeah, don't think about the distances.
Right.
When a mathematician
speaks about a torus,
or a physicist
for the most part,
he's talking about a topology,
not talking about a geometry.
Now,
in fact,
the torus,
when it's presented as a
rectangle...
Oh, let's talk a little bit about
how many
how many inequivalent tori there are.
What is the...
What are the parameters
of a torus?
Alright, it's a rectangle,
so first of all it has
an overall area.
Or, equivalently,
it has a length and a height,
a width and a height.
There's a width and a height,
which are two parameters.
One of those parameters
is the size of it.
You could take it to be the area.
Call that a size parameter.
The other is the...
And that's the product of the
length times the width
times the height.
There's also the ratio of the width
times the height. You could call it
the aspect ratio or
the shape.
Alright, so here is a
long, thin torus.
Here is a broad,
fat torus.
But these are the same.
These are really the same
torus. That is to say,
they're geometrically identical.
They're geometrically identical.
Every point on here
is equivalent to a point on here.
This
maps to this.
This maps to this.
This is a picture on its side.
And we haven't made a new
kind of torus.
So, one thing we can say is
there's the ratio of the sides
but
the ratio of the sides
does not go from
zero to infinity.
It goes from one to infinity.
Why one to infinity?
Because when it's less than one
The ratio, let's say, of the horizontal to the vertical
This is bigger than 1, this is less than 1
But they're the same torus
So the ratio of the sides can
vary from, basically, from 1 to infinity
But not just 0 to 1?
Well, from 0 to 1, either way
In fact, you usually take from 0 to 1
You can go from 0 to 1
Anything else, is there anything else that
you can do to change the torus?
And the answer is yes
Here's the game that we haven't discussed
Let's go back to our piece of cylinder
We're going to identify the left edge, the left
circle over here with the right circle over here
But before we do it, let's imagine a twist
A twist by an angle
So that you don't identify this
point with this one up here
But you identify it with a displaced angular point
This one over here is identified with here
This one over here, identified with that
You imagine in your mind, before
making the identification, making a little twist
And then making the identification
That's something new
And what it looks like, let's see
Let's do it vertically, let's draw it this way
Make a little twist here before we make the identification
So that slides things along the top edge
If we didn't do the
twist, we would have a rectangle
If we do the twist, then we
don't identify this point with this one
We identify it with that point
This point with that point
And we might as well draw it like this
We might as well draw it
as, well that doesn't look very neat
That's not quite right
Yeah
Alright
Everything in the bottom gets
identified with a point above it
And everything on the left gets identified,
but with this offset, with this angle
So to parameterize tori, there's
the aspect ratio, there's the size
That can be taken to be the overall area
Then, getting rid of the area,
let's say unit things of unit area
There's the aspect ratio and there's the angle
These things are called moduli
These are the moduli of the torus
There are three of them
The three moduli of the torus are the overall
size, the ratio of the height to the width
And the angle, the lean, the angle of leaning
These have technical names
The twist is called a Dehn twist,
D-E-H-N, after a mathematician I suppose named Dehn
The overall volume is called a Kähler moduli
And the aspect ratio is called a complex structure moduli
They have technical meanings
If you see them, you'll know roughly what they mean
Couldn't you flip it as well?
It seems like you could flip the ring as well
Flip it? You mean reflect it?
Then you make a Klein bottle, it's a different topology
You mean if you take...
If you take this point over here
Identify it with a point in the front
This point with that point, this point with that point
And this one with the one in the back
That's a Klein bottle
That's not a torus
It's not an orientable manifold
What about a non-uniform twist?
It has to be a map,
but in our experience it's continuous
Yeah, yeah, yeah
You can...that's right, that's right
You can absorb that kind of
thing into the metric on the torus
You're right, there are other ways of deforming the torus
But those can be absorbed
into the metric on the torus
Um...
These tori are all flat
They have flat geometries
Or they can be given flat geometries
Since they can be drawn
on the blackboard without stretching them
I don't mean the real donut
The real donut is a truly curved surface
It has curvature
On the outer boundary it has positive curvature
On the inner near the
hole here it has negative curvature
I'm talking about this mathematical structure that's
been mapped onto the plane in this way
It's completely flat
Triangles on it have 180 degree sum of their angles
Even on this one
And in particular it's not
only flat, but it's Ricci flat
It's Ricci flat and it's flat
And so string theory on these geometries is well defined
It's a good...
Good mathematical structure for string theory to exist on
It's by far the easiest way to hide other dimensions
And it's called toroidal compactification
It's not good for the real world
The real world is more complex than that
But I thought I would show you
what the simplest form of compactification is
Now I'm gonna...
Let's see, let's take a five minute break
Somebody wanted to make an announcement, I can't remember
Yeah, there you are
Yeah, toroid are all flat
Toroid are all flat
Toroid is the plural of torus you realize
Toroid are all flat in any number of dimensions
And therefore they're also Ricci flat
And because they're Ricci flat
String theory
Strings moving on toroid are...
Good things
They have a sensible well defined mathematics
There are other Ricci flat spaces
Where you can take six dimensions that
you don't like and get rid of them
By compactifying them
Not on a torus
Or not by replacing them by a torus
But by replacing them by other Ricci flat manifolds
In particular
There are a class of Ricci flat manifolds
Which are known as Calabi-Yau manifolds
Which have very special properties
And where string theory is a good theory
These are incredibly complicated
They're far beyond the scope of this course
But they're also the kind of things that string theorists...
Which have enough complexity
And lack of symmetry
That they do look more like the real world
But they don't really involve any really new concepts
Some mathematical concepts to be sure
They're very mathematically difficult objects
But no really new principles come out of...
They just look more like the real world
And I'm not going to try to get into them
But I think a torus is good enough for us
We can see some very interesting things
When we start to explore string theory on a torus
Alright
Okay, let's go...
Let's take as our model for simplicity
Just the infinite one dimensional world
With an extra dimension that goes around in a loop
You see why I call
a circle a one dimensional torus?
It's just a line element periodically identified
Alright, let's start with that
Alright, we can have a
particle which moves around on here
And it can have a component of motion horizontally
Nothing special about that
That's just the momentum along the direction
It would have been there...
Even if you hadn't...
Well, even if you didn't have the extra dimension
You'd have momentum along that direction
But you also have momentum along the other direction
You can have both of them at the same time
A particle moving sort of obliquely
Sort of spiraling around this thing
Would have a component of momentum horizontally
And a component of momentum along the circle
The components of momentum along the circle
Are quantized
Momentum...
Momentum on periodic spaces are always quantized
The easiest way to see it
Is just to say supposing...
Supposing the circumference of this circle
Let's just call the circumference 2 pi r
That's just what I'm calling the circumference
If I take the momentum along the r direction
The momentum along...
Sorry, along the circumference
Let's call that p along the circumference
Pc
P along the circumference
And I multiply it by r
Which is the circumference divided by 2 pi
I get something like this
I get something which looks like an angular momentum
In fact it is a kind of angular momentum
It's...
There's an angle associated with this circle
It's just an angular position along here
And p times r
It's just like...
It is like angular momentum
Okay
That's quantized
In integer multiples
Of Planck's constant
So...
The momentum...
Along the circumference
The momentum along the circumference
Is quantized in units
If we set Planck's constant to 1
Then the unit of momentum is 1 over r
Let's suppose the particle we're talking about is massless
If it happens to be a massless particle
Then its momentum...
Or the magnitude of its momentum
Is the same as the magnitude of its energy
Energy for a massless particle
Is equal to the momentum
Of course there's a factor of the speed of light
Apart from the factor of the speed of light
Energy is equal to the magnitude of the momentum
This component of the momentum
Can be positive or negative
And it's an integer
The implication is
That there is a quantized amount of energy
Even if the particle is not moving
Along the horizontal direction
If it's moving in the circular direction
It has an energy
Which is n units divided by r
Alright?
That energy
It's from our point of view
While we don't see the circular direction
It's just a thing standing still
It's a thing standing still
But the manifestation of the fact
That it's moving in the circular direction
Is a thing standing still
But the manifestation of the fact
That it's moving
Is that it has some energy
It has some mass
This is the mass now
Of the particle
And it comes in integer multiples
Of one over r
The smaller r is
The bigger the spacing
Between mass levels
The bigger the spacing between mass levels
So
By knowing
The spacing
Of course
We don't measure any of this
But in principle
By measuring
The spacing between
The masses of these different particles
How are they different?
They're different from a macroscopic
From our point of view
They look different
They have different masses
From the point of view of a small object
You know, a small detector
Which can see inside this thing
They're just particles
Which have different components
Of momentum in this direction
We call them different particles
Because they have different masses
And the spectrum of them
Namely the spacing between them
Tells us how big
The internal space is
The bigger the internal space
The closer the levels
Let's draw a level diagram
Energy
Energy equals zero or more
Of energy
Energy equals zero or mass
Mass equals zero is right over here
Then we can have
Plus one unit
Of rotational momentum around here
That would give us a particle of
Mass one over r
And so forth
What about if n is negative?
Does that mean it has negative energy?
No
The energy is the absolute value
I think I erased it
The energy is always positive
So there's a particle of mass one over r here
There's a particle of mass one over r here
Two over r minus or two over r
The spacing between the mass levels
Is a direct reflection
Of how big the circle is
The smaller the circle
The larger the spacing
If this circle is very, very big
Then the levels are very, very close together
So if we discovered
Excited states of particles
Which were very, very, very densely spaced
We would say
Oh, it looks like there's an extra big
Rather big dimension
If we find that the spacing
Due to this kind of motion
Is very, very sparse
Then we say that dimension is small
Right?
Okay
So these are the energy levels
For
The components of mass of a
Or the mass of a particle
Where the particle is simply a particle
Moving around this direction
Now you can do something else
In a compact space
You can have a different kind of particle
Which from the outside
Meaning from the big dimensions
Just looks like a particle
But which has an entirely different structure
Oh, incidentally
If all particles are strings
If particles really are strings
Then I might want to draw this
As a little string over here
But just think of it as an almost
Tiny little particle
Let's forget the fact that it spreads out
It's a tiny particle
And it moves around
The whole center of mass of it
Moves around
And gives it a
A series of energies in this way
But there's something else you can do
The other thing you can do with a string
And a compact space like this
Is wind the string around
Like that
Here
This
Band around here
Is once wound around the cylinder of the cup
I can take a rubber band
and wind it around that way
That can also move up and down the axis
First of all, it's localized
It's at a definite place
In the big dimensions
So it has a location from our point of view
It can move
It can move up and down
It's a particle
It's also a particle
It's a particle which is
Wound around the extra dimension
What is its mass?
Its mass now
Is not due to its motion in this direction
It's due to the potential energy
of stretching a string around it
So we can show you
How much energy would we expect
To be in a string stretched around here
The answer, clearly, will be proportional
to the length of the string
There's a certain tension in the energy per unit length
For every string
Let's set it equal to 1
We won't worry about the units tonight
Tonight, I'll ignore units
Set just working units where the string tension is 1
If the string is stretched out to a certain distance
Then the mass will be equal to 1
How does it work?
Then the mass that that string has is
proportional to the length of the stretch string
How about a string which is wrapped around this direction?
What would you expect its mass to be proportional to?
The circumference, R. Yeah, the
radius of the circumference. So
This one will have a mass
equal to R, or proportional to R
But you know you can wrap it around several times
That I can't do with the coffee
cup, but I can draw it I think
No, no, but I want to connect it back
together again. Oh, I know I know I got it
Yeah
It crosses here and connects back here
Can you see it? If I had
a rubber band I could wrap it
You can wrap a rubber band twice around here.
You take it twist it and put it on here
All right. How about this one? What's the
mass of it? How much energy does it have?
2R
twice as much, twice as much stretching
so we have
R, we have energy R, we have energy 2R
3R, 4R
If the string has an orientation
In other words if you think
of the string as having a direction
Then you can wrap it positively or you can wrap
it negatively. Here's one wrapped positively. Here's one wrapped negatively
So this wrapping or winding number, it's called
winding number, the winding number can be positive
Imagine you have a rubber band, but on the rubber band
you draw little arrows to give it a sense of direction
And you're going to wrap it around your wrist
You're going to put it on your wrist
And you're going to wrap it around your wrist. You can wrap it around your
wrist so the arrows are in this way or so that they run this way
So the winding number can be either positive or negative
But whatever the winding number is
The mass of that string is
equal to the absolute as R
Times the absolute value of the winding number
Okay, so there's another spectrum of particles here
And that spectrum of particles has
energy levels whose distance is
not proportional to 1 over R
But it's proportional to R itself.
Let's suppose R is very small
Let's suppose that R is very very small
Then this spacing is large
And this spacing is very small
It takes very little energy
to wrap around a small circle
Okay
But for the particles which are not wrapped
But which are not wound around
But which are moving around
Literally moving and have momentum
The spacing between levels is large if R is small
So we have these two spectra
of two different kinds of particles
One is called
These ones here are called Kaluza-Klein particles
They were this idea has been around
Of particles having momentum and an extra amount of energy
They were this idea has been around of
particles having momentum and an extra amount of energy
They are called Kaluza-Klein particles
They have a very large and compact direction
That goes back to beginnings of general relativity
Kaluza-Klein particles
First had the idea 1917 I think
And it's grown up a great deal since then
But string theory
Introduced the new idea of wound particles
Particles wound around
And they have very complementary kind of spectra
So if you see particles
With a large spacing
You must also see particles with a small spacing
Both combinations together would tell you something
about the nature of the compact directions
But notice
But notice that there is no way
To make the spacing arbitrarily large
Here
Without having very small spacing
Small spacing of course means that it
just takes a little bit of energy
To create one of these things
On the other hand, what happens
if you take R very big?
Now imagine taking R very big.
If you take R very big, then the
spacing of these Kaluza-Klein particles is very small.
These are very close together now.
R is very big. 1 over R is very small.
These become very closely spaced.
And what happens to these?
They get very widely spaced.
Why? Because it just takes a lot of energy
to wrap it around a very, very big cylinder here.
So you have these two complementary kinds of particles.
There's almost a symmetry.
There's almost a symmetry of the spectrum
where you replace R by 1 over R.
You replace R by 1 over R,
and you replace momentum by winding number.
And what happens?
You just interchange these two.
And?
The spectrum stays the same.
That seems to be a symmetry
of the spectrum of string theory.
This only applies to the extra dimensions.
There's no way to wrap
a string around the real x-axis.
It's infinite.
But as applied to the extra dimensions,
there seems to be a symmetry where
you replace R by 1 over R,
winding by momentum around that direction,
and the system comes back to itself.
Is this the same as the vertical versus the horizontal?
No, no, no, no.
This is not the vertical versus the horizontal.
This is the duality between winding number and momentum,
and Kaluza-Klein momentum.
Now, from what I've told you,
it's hardly clear that this is
an exact equivalence in every possible respect.
It's just an equivalence of the
energy spectrum of some simple particles.
In fact, it's an exact symmetry of the theory.
If you take a compact direction,
and you start shrinking it down smaller and smaller,
well, at some point, incidentally,
the spectra will be equal.
There's some radius.
There's some radius where the
spacing between the Kaluza-Klein particles
and the winding particles,
will be the same.
We could call that R equals 1 in some units.
At R equals 1, the spectrum are the same.
Otherwise, they cross.
If you start trying to make
the radius of compactification smaller and smaller,
you eventually get to this point,
where when you cross it,
you can either think of it as
saying that the size is smaller than 1,
or you can interchange winding,
and momentum,
and say it's bigger than 1.
There's no sense,
in a certain sense,
there,
it's not possible to think about string theory
where R is smaller than a certain size.
Oh, you can think of it if you
want to make it smaller than a certain size,
but all that happens is it rearranges itself
so that it looks like
string theory on the larger space.
Yeah.
Does R less than 1,
and R greater than 1,
are those different kinds of particles?
Are they all fermions?
Oh, fermions, bosons, they all do the same thing.
Oh, so there's 10 or 26 dimensions,
it's, it applies to both.
Yeah, yeah, it applies to every compact direction.
Here I've only indicated one compact direction,
circle.
We can apply it to problems with several compact directions,
but this is a kind of freakish, surprising result
that's characteristic, really, of string theory.
It is not characteristic of point
particles moving in enclosed spaces like this.
It's the interchange of winding with momentum.
That hardly seems an obvious thing to do.
Remarkably, the entire theory, the scattering amplitudes,
the spectrum of particles, the whole works,
is symmetric under this interchange.
But one open string and the other closed string?
No, no, no, no, they're both closed strings.
Closed strings, closed strings.
Open strings, it doesn't make any sense to wind around,
they just unwind themselves.
But I'm comparing them to the...
No, no, they're both closed strings.
In a theory, I should have said that,
in a theory of closed strings,
there's this interchange symmetry.
Open strings are a little more complicated.
Yeah, and we'll talk about them.
Would that be similar to the black hole analogy,
where dimensions become time-like,
and time becomes dimension-like?
Nope.
What it is, is it's
saying that there's a certain distance
where when you try to think of
string theory on a space smaller than that,
it's equivalent to string theory
on a space bigger than that.
Trying to shrink the diameter of a compactification
to arbitrarily small distances, you get frustrated.
It just rearranges itself,
so that it looks like
the theory on a bigger space.
Does that help get rid of self-energies?
Well, it does say in some sense
there's a smaller size scale in string theory,
but it keeps things from being infinite, yes.
Well, that's true if you have a winding number, right?
What's to say that there is a winding number?
Is that just a theoretical model, or
is there an analogy to physical space?
In the absence of a winding number, right?
If you have a compact dimension,
then it's possible to think of strings which are round.
Are you asking...
Maybe you're asking how you make them
if you don't have them to begin with.
Well, I'm asking if there is
no existence of a winding number.
A winding number or a particle with a winding number?
A particle with a winding number.
You can make them.
I'll show you how to make them.
We do have to start with something.
So we start with a
particle which has no winding number.
That's a little string that looks like that.
Okay?
Now we take this,
and we pull it around,
we stretch it out.
It's still got no winding number.
It's not wound around the thing.
And now we stretch it all the way around here
so that it comes back the back side
and comes up over here.
Can you see what I've done?
It still has no winding number.
The winding number of this piece is canceled out.
It's canceled out by the winding number of that piece.
So you take your arm,
you take the rubber band,
and you pull it around,
and then take the two pieces here.
And that's what you're left with.
That still has no winding number.
But remember now that in string theory,
the basic process of interaction is for things like this
to become things like this.
Rearrangement.
So if you sit there for a while,
this string will rearrange and form that.
Now what does this have?
It has two particles with opposite winding number.
Okay?
We still have a net zero winding number.
One is wound one way,
one is wound the other way.
But now they're disconnected,
and they're free to separate.
Throw that one away.
Just eject it out of the system.
Give it some velocity.
And when it gets off to alpha centauri,
you forget about it,
and you're left with a particle with winding number.
So whether you like them or not,
you can't forbid them.
Some things you can try to forbid.
You can say if they're not there to begin with,
they'll never be there.
Possibly.
Some things you can't forbid
because you can imagine
that the processes of the theory itself,
the important processes in the theory,
can force them on you,
and these get forced on you.
Of course, they always get forced in pairs.
But you can...
That's...
You throw away half of them
and just do some experiments
with the remaining ones.
And this is with increasing energy,
I guess, then?
The Kaluzik-Klein closed string gets larger?
Does that be more energy?
Yeah, it does.
It gets some energy not only from momentum,
but from being stretched.
It takes energy to do it.
But you know, this is the sort of thing
which would happen if you collided
two particles with no winding number,
just two Kaluzik-Klein particles.
You collide them hard.
Every possible combination of stuff happens.
And among the things which would happen
is these winding and anti-winding things
would go flying off.
And the logic is the same as the logic
of electric charge.
So, if you started with no electric charge,
does that mean there would be no electrons?
No.
Any kind of collision that would take place
would create electrons and positrons,
and then the positrons could go flying off
to some other place,
and you'd be left with electrons.
So the logic is really no different
than electric charge.
You can't not have electric charge
because you can always make it in pairs.
The net charge in the world
might be zero, for all we know.
The net winding number might be zero,
but who cares?
We can do experiments on a region
which contains a winding number.
So, yeah.
This has a name, incidentally.
The equivalence between theories
which look different
usually called a duality.
This is called T-duality.
Capital T-duality.
And the T in this case stands for torus.
T stands for torus.
This is torus duality, or T-duality.
And as I say, it's a duality which relates
compactifications on very small geometries
to compactifications on big geometries.
And it's a rather startling thing.
I mean, when it was first discovered,
it surprised everybody.
Good.
What it means is that geometry defined
in terms of how strings...
Geometry can often be recovered
or partly recovered
from the spectrum of modes on a...
The geometry of a drum head,
the shape of a drum head.
This is a famous mathematical question.
Can the shape of a drum head
be predicted from the sound of it?
The sound that it makes,
from the spectrum of vibrations?
The answer is not quite,
but you can predict a lot of the shape
of the drum head.
The same question applies
to these compactifications.
From the spectrum of particles,
the spectrum of vibrational energies,
vibrational and other kinds of energies,
can you predict the shape
or the size of the compact directions?
And the answer is yes to a large extent.
But...
there are some ambiguities
and some dualities
that you can't tell if it's a tiny geometry
or if it's a big geometry
because these two go into each other.
That would not be the case
with a drum, I assure you.
Uh...
You would not mistake a small drum
for a big drum.
Okay, good.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.
Thank you.