This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Classical mechanics is the basis for all of physics.
It's the basis of all of physics,
not only because it describes the motion
of objects like particles and
mechanical systems and so forth,
but because the
basic framework,
the basic structure of all
of physics is based on the
principles of classical mechanics.
The conservation of energy,
the conservation
of momentum,
the principles by which all systems
evolve in nature is the same set
of rules,
essentially exactly the same set of rules,
and the same set of rules,
and the more abstract and the more general
setting than the rules which govern how a
simple particle moves,
for example,
under the influence of gravity.
But in order to understand it,
we have to understand the principles in a fairly general
context.
Let's begin with the very,
very simplest
kinds of systems that we can think of,
systems that are so simple that in fact they're simpler
than any real systems in nature.
Laws of nature,
let's imagine laws of nature
which are of the most primitive and simple
kind acting on the most primitive and simple
systems that we can imagine.
I want you to first of all suppose that time,
which evolves
continuously under the,
my watch,
I see the second hand
goes around and around and around,
it goes around continuously,
the time can evolve and be any real number,
t,
I want you
to imagine it only occurs in beats.
A stroboscopic world in which you
only have a number of times,
you only look at the world at intervals of
time which we could be a thousandth of a second
or it could be a millionth of a second,
let's just take it to be one second intervals,
and
ask how in the stroboscopic world systems change with time.
Let's also imagine a very,
very simple set of systems,
systems which are so simple
that they only have a handful
of configurations.
Configurations mean
a number of times,
everything we need to know about
the system to characterize it completely.
So the simplest
system I can think of would be
a system that has only two configurations,
heads or tails,
a coin.
Lay a coin down on the table,
I don't have a coin
so we'll take this coffee top
here,
I could put it down heads
or I could put it down tails.
I doubt if you can tell
the difference from where you're sitting
but I can tell the difference,
this is heads,
that's tails.
So we have a system
then that's characterized by two systems,
the first one
is a state,
the second one is a state of being,
and the third one is a state of evolution.
So we have two states,
two states of being and we want
to add to those two states a law,
a law of evolution in going from one
instant of time to the next instant of time,
from
one beat of the stroboscopic light to the next one.
What kind of laws are allowable,
what kind of laws do the basic principles
of physics allow and what kind of laws don't
they allow?
That's going to be our
first kind of question for tonight.
So our first concept is the space of states,
in this case just heads and tails,
it's just
two points,
heads and tails,
so two points in an abstract space,
heads and tails.
It's
called the phase space,
it's called the phase space of a system,
the space of possible states
of a system.
And what do I mean
by a state of a system?
I mean everything that you need
to know in order to predict what happens next,
everything you need to know in order to be
able to say with certainty what the
next state of the system will be.
So that's called the phase space of the system,
in this case just heads and tails.
What kind
of laws can you imagine,
what kind of laws of nature
can you imagine for this extremely
simple world?
It is the simplest—well,
I suppose you could imagine a slightly simpler
world.
You can imagine a world with only one state,
heads.
Not much can happen in that
world.
There's only one law of physics.
Heads go to heads,
and heads go to heads go to heads.
that's extremely boring,
nothing ever happens,
because there's only one state,
so how could
anything happen?
But with two states,
heads and tails,
you can have a richer variety of possible
laws of physics.
One law,
let's take the various varieties of
laws of physics we could have,
one law might just say,
you stay the same.
If the state of the system
is heads at one instant of
time,
then the next instant of time it will be heads.
If it starts tails,
it will stay tails.
That's a very boring law,
and let's graph that law by drawing an arrow.
If it starts heads,
then it stays heads.
Let's just represent that by drawing
an arrow from head to head,
and from tail to tail.
The meaning of this arrow,
you start at the tail end of the arrow,
and you follow it,
and you see that it
comes around to the same point.
That stands for the rule that
says that a heads stays a heads,
and in this case,
a tail stays a tail.
So this is a very dull law of nature.
This stays that way for endless amounts
of time,
and this stays that way for endless amounts of time.
Another possible law of nature
would be a slightly more interesting situation.
If you look at it at one instant of time,
the next instant,
it's the opposite.
Heads goes to tails,
goes to heads,
goes to tails.
These are deterministic laws.
Deterministic laws mean that if you
know what is happening at one
instant,
you know forever after.
You know everything about the system infinitely into
the future.
Completely deterministic.
Classical mechanics has that nature to it,
that it is
completely deterministic.
You know the adversals?
No.
The adversals is in a certain sense always reversible,
but we're coming to that.
All right,
so to draw the graph representing heads
goes to tails and tails goes to heads,
we draw an arrow from heads
to tails and from tails to heads.
And we read that as saying
that if you start at heads,
you go to tails.
If you start at tails,
you go to heads.
What is the evolution of a
system under this law of nature?
If you start with heads,
it's heads,
tails,
heads,
forever after.
These are two consistent laws of physics
in a world of only two states.
Whether we can think of more laws,
yes,
we can,
but for the moment,
these are two interesting
ones.
Now,
how can we generalize this?
We can generalize this,
first of all,
to systems with more states.
Two states is not very many.
We could have a die.
A die isn't dice.
A die has 16 states.
states,
and 6,
and we could represent them as points,
six points.
Now we have a large variety of
different laws of physics that we could have.
For example,
we could simply have,
we could label these 1,
2,
3,
4,
5,
and 6.
Which one is 1 and which
one is 6 is not very important,
but there are six of them.
We could have a law of
physics which is 1 goes to 2,
2 goes to 3,
3 goes to 4,
4 goes to 5,
5 goes to 6,
and 6 goes back to 1.
This would be a complicated motion when
thought of in terms of a die.
You start with a 1 up,
and then it goes to the 2 up,
3 up,
and so forth,
but it's a relatively simple picture
when drawn in this manner here.
You can imagine more complicated
laws of physics with six states.
Well,
whether they're more complicated or not is in the
eye of the beholder,
but first of all we could
have a similar law where instead
of 1 going to 2,
1 could go to 3,
3 could go to 2,
2 could go to 5,
1,
2,
3,
4,
something like that.
That's really not very different than this.
Each one goes
to a neighboring one,
well not to a neighboring one,
each one goes to a next
one.
And they cycle around,
and one characteristic of such systems is they
will just cycle around forever and ever and ever.
Okay,
now you can have more complicated,
I don't know if they're more complicated,
different laws.
For example,
you could
have a law which goes this way.
If you start at 1,
you go to 2,
if you go to 2,
then you go to 3,
and then you go back to 1.
If you happen to start at 3,
no,
this isn't 3,
this is 5,
right?
If you start at 3,
you go to 4,
if you start at 4,
you go to 5,
back to 3.
In this case,
well that's somewhat similar to this,
you have
two disconnected cycles,
two more complicated things.
Here's another one.
In fact,
I think it
would take a long time to draw all the possibilities.
1 goes back to 1,
2 goes
to 3,
3 goes to 4,
4 goes back to 2,
5 goes to 6,
and 6 goes back to 5.
Right?
They're all acceptable laws of physics.
Wherever you happen to be,
you
know exactly where to go next,
so it's deterministic.
It's deterministic into
the future,
meaning to say wherever you start,
you know where you will be arbitrarily into
the future.
If you start here and
you go a hundred thousand times,
you'll just
wind up,
I don't know,
somewhere,
wherever,
wherever.
If you start here,
you stay there.
So these are completely deterministic into the future,
but they're also
completely deterministic into the past,
which means if you know where you are,
you know where you were before.
If you find yourself over here,
then you know
in the previous cycle,
the previous instance,
that you are over here and so
forth.
So you can trace your motion either
into the future or into the past
with complete confidence about where you will be,
no matter how far you go.
That's
the character in principle,
if not in practice.
In practice things
get jumbled up and you can't see them clearly enough,
and you miss
detail.
But you can see the infinite nature of
theили that occurs in the encourage and the
small detail in a system and get
every single bit of physics absolutely right
for any classical system,
they are in this sense exactly deterministic,
both
into the past and into the future.
Now what kind of laws of physics do we not
allow?
The kind of laws of physics that
we don't allow I can best illustrate,
I
think,
by drawing some possibilities and explaining
to you why they are not
allowed.
Here's a law of physics that
is not allowed by the principles of
classical physics.
Three states,
three states is perfectly alright,
nothing
wrong with that,
but let's draw some arrows.
Two,
three,
two goes to three,
and
three goes back to two.
That would be perfectly alright by itself.
What about
one?
Well,
I could have one goes to one,
but I don't want one to go to one.
I want one to go to two.
That's completely deterministic into the future.
If I start at one,
I go to two,
I
go to two,
I go to three,
I go three back to two,
two back to three.
I always know
where to go in the next step,
I just follow the arrow wherever it happens to
be.
But what does it fail?
It fails to be deterministic into the past.
Supposing I
am at one,
then I'm at two,
then where did I come from?
I could have come from one,
or I could have come from three.
So,
I cannot work my way backward with
uniqueness.
I can work my way forward,
I cannot work my way backward.
This is a law
of physics which is irreversible.
It would not allow me
to run the laws of physics
backward,
it would lead to an ambiguity
every time I were at two.
Another law which is,
not allowed by the principles of classical mechanics,
or principles of
classical physics,
would be basically the same thing
but with the arrows turned in
the opposite direction,
all arrows reversed.
Here I have a problem not going
into the past,
but I have a problem going into the future.
Let's see,
yeah,
supposing
now I find myself at two and
I want to go into the future,
I don't know whether to
go into the future by following this
arrow to one or this arrow to three.
There are two
arrows leading out of two over here.
One of them goes to three,
one of them goes to one.
Nothing tells me which arrow to follow,
so it's not deterministic into the future.
I
might randomly decide to go from two to three,
or randomly decide to go from two to one.
These are rules,
each one of which is deterministic into the future.
It's deterministic in one direction,
but not the other.
These are the sorts of things
which are forbidden by
the principles of classical mechanics.
Why are they forbidden by the principles
of,
yeah?
What if you just erased one of those lines,
one of those with .
Which one?
Yeah,
just one of those two lines on the loop there.
That wouldn't come,
I wouldn't know where to go from three.
You get stuck at three.
Yeah.
Yeah,
no good.
Can you ever have,
say,
a dangling one over here?
Well,
you can't have a dangling one.
You've got no way to go next.
No,
you could,
let's
see,
we could try to put something like that in.
Yeah.
Okay,
so that would say we go from one to two,
from two to three,
to three,
to three.
Now,
the problem would be in going backward,
I think.
Right.
Yeah.
You don't know where you come from.
Three or two.
Yeah,
right.
Right.
So one way or the other,
you get stuck with these rules.
All right,
how do we spot
what's allowable and what's not allowable?
Well,
it's very simple.
At every configuration,
two,
three,
we should have one in and one out.
We should have a unique one in,
a unique
arrow in,
and a unique arrow out.
One arrow in to tell us where we came from,
and one
arrow out to tell us where we're going.
That's the character of class.
Classical physics.
Uniqueness into the future,
uniqueness into the past,
when represented
in terms of this very simple and analog world,
analog digital world of a finite number of
states,
then the rules of physics as we
know them would say every configuration has one
in arrow and one out arrow.
Now,
with this rule,
of course,
life is very boring.
I mean,
it's boring because if you only
have a finite number of states,
all that can happen to you
is you cycle around endlessly among those number of states,
always in the same order.
You can have slightly more interesting situations.
There's no reason why the number of states
has to be finite.
You could have a situation where
there's an infinite number of possible
states.
A state corresponding to every integer.
A state corresponding to every integer,
positive and negative.
A particle on a position on
a line where the position could be any integer value.
And then a simple law of physics would
be you go from one to the next.
Wherever you are,
you go to the next one.
Each point has
one in and one out.
I can't draw them endlessly.
It'll take forever.
But each mark,
one in
and one out.
It's a rather boring law of nature.
You just hop from one to
the next to the next to the
next to the next forever and ever and ever.
But at least you wouldn't be cycling around
endlessly.
Again,
we can add some more states onto this.
We could add this on.
If we start on the line,
we simply move off and keep
going forever and ever and ever.
But if we start over here,
we cycle around.
So we could have mixtures of both kinds of things.
Some states we cycle around in.
Other
states we move off to infinity.
Now,
notice that some of these laws of nature
— the phase-space breaks up into different pieces,
which are connected among themselves,
but not connected to each other.
For example,
still,
even with just two states,
we had two possibilities —
one like this and one like this.
In this case where it
breaks up into more than one
binary,
I could have very different possibilities.
In the Fase-Space- прост microbial law,
we can say there's still a modern imagination
more than one piece,
we have something called the conservation law.
The conservation law is simply
a memory of where we started.
The conservation law means that something
is kept intact for all time.
Some piece of knowledge is kept
intact for all time and doesn't change.
In this case,
we could label this,
we could label a configuration over here with a plus
one and a configuration over here with a minus one,
and then we could call,
we could invent
a variable,
plus one over here and minus one over here.
It never changes.
If it's plus one,
it stays plus one.
If it's minus one,
it stays minus one.
That's a conservation law,
something which doesn't change with time.
On the other hand,
if we hop from plus one to
minus one to plus one to minus one,
we
don't have a conservation law.
Conservation laws are always...
They're always associated with these kind
of closed families of different trajectories
in the phase space which don't mix with each other,
which remember something about the
system which might otherwise get mixed
up if everything got all mixed together.
So there's all kinds of possibilities
that are inherent in these deterministic laws,
but always the condition is one in line.
One in line and one outline for every point.
That can also be called information conservation.
It's information conservation in exactly the sense
that you never lose memory of where
you started,
either into the past or into the future.
If you know where you are at any instant,
you know where you came from and you know
where you'll be,
information about where you are is conserved,
never changes into the past
and the future.
Whereas if you have one of these bad laws,
laws which are forbidden by the rules of classical
mechanics,
then you do lose information.
For example,
if you find yourself over here,
you don't know whether you came from here
or from...
Well,
no,
that's not quite right.
If you find yourself over here,
you don't know whether you
came from here or over here,
so you lose information.
Information conservation is perhaps
the most important thing.
It's the most fundamental law of basic
classical physics that you don't lose information about.
Now,
why is that so?
It's not written into the laws of
physics why they are what they are.
Maybe someday we'll understand hyper laws of
physics or meta laws of physics or deeper
laws of physics which will tell us why
the laws of physics are what they are.
At the moment,
it's more or less an experimental fact
that all the known laws of physics fit
into this class of information.
The laws of physics are
the laws of information conserving laws,
even those which are quantum
mechanical.
But for our subject this quarter,
we're only interested in classical physics.
All right,
so that's the basic setup if
we were interested only in this stroboscopic
world of discrete time intervals.
The real world,
of course,
is more continuous than that.
Supposing...
I'm sorry.
Okay,
so let's make the law something like this.
If the last two states were heads,
heads,
then it stays heads.
If the last two states were heads,
tails,
then it goes to heads.
If the last two were heads,
tails,
heads,
then it goes to tails.
And if the last two were tails,
tails,
then it goes to tails.
I think that's a possible law.
Then you would say,
I can't tell from the fact that it's heads
where it goes next.
And indeed,
I can't.
But that would just be
another way of saying that a
specification of a heads by itself is
not what you would call a state.
What you would call a state
would be the specification of the previous last two entries,
because you need two entries to tell
you what happens next.
Now,
that raises the question that's very,
very important in classical
mechanics.
How much and what exactly do you
need to know to say what happens next?
If the phase
space is the space of things,
space of possibilities,
but always in such a way that
they are not the same,
then you would say that it's
not what you would call a state.
If you can't tell what happens next,
what is it that you do have to know next?
So that brings us
to continuous physics.
Let's take the motion of a particle.
Is it enough to know where a particle
is to say what happens next?
Let's hypothesize that the generalization
to continuous time is that
we need to know the exact
location of a particle along a line.
We've run out of ink,
I'm afraid.
Now,
there it is.
All right,
so let's imagine the motion
of a particle along a line.
Then you might
think that the analog of a state
is just the location of a particle.
Where is it?
But is it
enough to know where a particle is
in order to say what happens next?
No.
What else do you need
to know?
It's velocity.
In order to know where a particle will be next,
you need to know not only
where it is,
but also where it's going to be.
So you need to know where it's going to be.
So you
need to know where it is,
but how fast it's moving.
You need to know its velocity.
So that means the
state,
in the same sense that I used it,
that which you need to know
in order to know what happens
next does not just consist
of the location of a particle,
but you can say it two ways.
You need
to know not just the location of the particle,
but you need to know also the previous location,
or better yet,
what is equivalent to knowing the previous location,
the velocity.
The velocity.
That tells you that the phase space,
the space of states,
the space of
configurations is two-dimensional,
not one-dimensional.
It's not just a line.
It's a line that represents the position of the particle,
and a second line which represents
its velocity,
either to the left or to the right.
Positive velocity means moving to the right.
Negative velocity means moving to the right.
means moving to the left.
Supposing you're over here,
where do you move next?
You stay in the same place.
Why?
You're at the origin and you have no velocity.
What
if you're over here,
so we could just,
we could draw a little loop here to say that
you come back to the same place.
What if you're over here?
You stay the same place because
you're moving with zero velocity.
Vertical axis is velocity,
so you come back to the
same place.
What if you're over here?
Where are you one second later?
Let's chop time
up into one second intervals.
Where are you next?
Somewhere to the right.
Somewhere to the right,
huh?
What if you're over here?
No,
what if you're over here?
Move twice as far,
or roughly twice as far to the right.
What if you're down here?
You
move to the left.
So we could fill up this space
here with little tiny arrows to show
where you move next,
but notice,
to know where you move next,
you have to know not only where
you are in the sense of what x is,
but you also have to know the vertical axis.
So you're
stress gods.
The vertical axis is the vertical component,
namely what the velocity is.
So
that means the analog,
the analog of a point in the phase
space is a point in a space not
only of positions,
but also velocities.
So,
if there's a conceptual issue to that,
I understand,
that is,
you would think that if you were
able to discretize time emphatically it would
not...
Yes?
The two should be the same,
and yet...
Why?
A velocity that came in,
which is readily apparent where
that would take place if we
had these infinitely small
discrete time representation of that.
No,
it means exactly what the gentleman asked me before.
What if you had a law of nature which
tells you in order to know where to move next,
you
had to know your previous two entries?
Now one way of saying it is,
all right,
in that case I need to know the previous two
entries and it just doesn't
fall into this class of things.
Or you could say that the space of configurations
doesn't just consist of a heads or a tails,
but it consists of a pair of entries,
a pair.
So we can model that
with every time the same one.
That's right.
We model that.
We need the last two.
That's right.
We need two axes instead.
We need an axis for the
present configuration and the past one.
Yeah.
That's exactly right.
Also in classical physics,
you can't just say,
well,
I'm going to do this,
and then
you have to really know your state?
Well,
of course not,
because in classical physics,
the position of a particle and so
forth is a real number.
A real number is something
that you can never determine exactly,
and so there's always imprecision,
and that imprecision always represents a degree
of uncertainty in where you will be
next.
Now,
it gets worse and worse in general.
It's likely to get worse and worse as
you try to take larger and larger time intervals.
A given degree of imprecision in what you
actually know can get magnified and get magnified
into worse and worse imprecision as time goes on.
So in practice,
in practice,
classical systems don't really have
the property that you can
predict endlessly.
They don't predict endlessly where they're going
to be and exactly what they're going
to do,
but you can always say,
given a time interval,
I want to be able to predict exactly
for the next 30 seconds where
every molecule in this room will be.
Let's forget quantum mechanics now.
I want to be able to
predict exactly where every molecule will be.
Then there's a certain degree of precision
in the present information at exactly one
instant of time,
which will permit me.
It will not permit me to extrapolate for 30 seconds.
It will not permit me to extrapolate for 40 seconds.
If I try to extrapolate for 40 seconds,
I will find the errors get magnified out of
control.
If I want to predict correctly for 40 seconds,
I will have to do even better in my initial
conditions,
in my knowledge of exactly what
the state of the system is.
So in practice,
this idea of determinism is defective.
It's defective.
It's defective because in order to
determine for a given length of time,
you have to have
precision,
which is so good that it's way,
way beyond anything anybody can do.
But in principle,
given any length of time in classical physics,
there exists a degree
of precision which allows you to
extrapolate for that length of time.
Does that answer the question?
Yeah.
So some systems are very predictable.
Some systems are less predictable and
get out of control very quickly.
They're called chaotic systems.
Okay.
So you can say that the system is very predictable,
but the principles are the same,
that it's
just a degree of precision which you need
to know in the beginning in order to extrapolate
for a given length of time.
You could say the system is still deterministic,
it's just not predictable.
Well,
you could say...
I'm not sure what the difference between predictable and...
The way I use the terms,
I use them interchangeably,
so I can't say that.
I think the conception is quite different.
And you could say that these
are the equations that match reality,
and they are deterministic.
There's just no way out,
except that they don't give you an algorithm to predict,
because
prediction requires...
I can't imagine it.
Okay.
Yeah?
All right.
It's a probability of predictability.
What's that?
Yeah.
Right.
The equations are deterministic.
They're deterministic if you know the initial conditions...
Or deterministic or predictable,
infinitely predictable if you know the initial conditions
with infinite precision.
You never do,
and therefore they're never completely predictable.
Now,
the fact that you need to know
both the position and the velocity in classical
physics in order to predict what happens
next reflects itself in the structure of
the equations of mechanics.
Specifically,
it tells you that the equations of motion,
Newton's equations in this case,
are what are called second-order
equations instead of first-order equations.
Let me illustrate it by
starting with a first-order equation.
A first-order equation...
What a first-order equation means is that...
It only has quantities of
first derivatives with respect to time.
In other words,
only contains velocities.
Second order means it contains not only first derivatives,
but second derivatives means
it contains accelerations,
the equations of motion.
Acceleration is the second derivative of the motion.
We could write...
We know what the real
equations of motion of Newton are.
F equals ma.
It contains acceleration.
Acceleration.
Let's write a phony equation.
Let's write F equals mass times velocity.
Force is F.
Velocity is velocity.
And let's suppose that force
just depends on where you are.
We have a particle that moves along a line.
It's subject to forces which vary along the line.
Force may be big here,
small there,
and so forth.
So the force depends on where you are.
on position,
and let's imagine this fake equation of
motion that it's equal to mass times velocity,
and what is velocity?
Velocity is the time derivative of the position,
the x by dt.
And I will use continuously throughout
this course the notation that time derivative
is just indicated by a dot.
Dot means time derivative.
All right,
what does this tell me?
What do I need to know
in order to predict what happens next?
I say for this equation,
we only need to know the position of a particle.
If we know the position of a particle,
I can tell you what the
velocity is just from the equation.
If I know that the position is a
particular position,
then I know the force on it,
and from the equation that tells me what the
velocity is.
Does it tell me the acceleration?
How about the acceleration?
Let's see if I can
compute the acceleration.
To compute the acceleration,
I'm going to use the equation of the velocity.
To compute the acceleration from this equation,
we just differentiate it once more.
We write that df by dt is equal to mass.
Mass is just a constant times the second derivative
of the position,
or just the acceleration.
So we have over here acceleration.
Acceleration.
What about the f dt,
the time derivative of the force?
The force varies with time
because the position varies with time.
So df by dt is just a reflection
of the fact that the position
of the particle varies with time,
and we can write the f by dt
using standard rules of calculus as just the
change in f with respect to position times the
change in position with respect to time.
In other words,
the velocity.
All right.
But we've already figured out what the velocity is,
knowing the force,
knowing the position.
So we know the velocity,
and we can read off from
this equation what the acceleration is.
We can figure out all of the derivatives of
the motion if we know where the particle is
by multiply differentiating this equation.
So what it tells us,
to make a short story
out of it,
is it tells us that if we know
where the position of the particle at any
instant of time,
then we know where it's going
to be in the next instant,
the next two instants,
the next three instants.
It completely predicts the motion.
But this is not the character
of Newton's equations.
Newton's equations say f is
equal to mass times acceleration,
not mass times velocity.
So let's look at this equation.
F equals mass times acceleration.
Can I predict from this what the velocity is?
No.
There's
just no equation for the velocity.
All right.
If I know what the position is,
I know what
the force is.
That tells me what the acceleration is,
but there's nothing in these equations which tell
me what the velocity is.
That means I have to add in
the velocity as a piece of information
to begin with.
I have no choice.
I have to tell you,
in order to predict,
I have to tell
you the position as well as the velocity.
Then,
if I know the position and the velocity,
I can then predict the acceleration.
The next third derivative,
the fourth derivative,
the
fifth derivative,
and all of them.
So that tells me that in
order to know where I am
and where I'm going to be,
I have to know the position and the velocity.
The phase space
is a two-dimensional space.
So we see then that
classical mechanics does have this character
of a configura—or a phase space of
different configurations with a set of little arrows
which tell you where to go next.
So I can then predict the acceleration,
the acceleration,
and the velocity.
And then,
I can predict the acceleration,
the acceleration,
and the velocity.
But the phase space itself
has a position component to it
and a velocity component to it.
We will go on and study the classical equations
of motion and study them in a variety of different
formulations.
But always,
the connecting link will
always be conservation of information.
The idea that the laws of physics are
completely deterministic and the structure of the equation
are simply described by equations which
tell you where you will be next.
That's the character
of classical physics.
As a result of this bifurcated system—
Bifurcated?
—the hands and tails up,
instead of being one system,
you need two pieces of information
and that's one.
It's one system,
but you need two pieces of information instead of one,
yeah.
If it weren't bifurcated then you wouldn't—
I'm not sure what you mean by bifurcated.
That's separate to two pieces.
The white hands and tails up there.
At the very top.
up here,
here you only need,
no,
here you need one piece of
information to say where you'll be next
if you're here you stay here,
if you're there you stay there
but the system is heads and tails
the rule is complicated but the
states are only one piece of information
all there is is heads and tails,
that's all there is,
and if you know where you are,
you know where you'll be next
you know when there were six
states then you had six rules,
you can have more rules but basically
no,
there's one rule
for the,
what the dice was initial,
so you only had one piece of information
no,
this,
this is one rule,
heads goes to heads,
tails goes to tails,
that's a single rule
and if you know where you are,
you'll be next
if you know that you're at heads,
then you know you'll be next at heads
if you know you're at tails,
you know,
so you only need a
piece of information heads or tails
that does it,
that tells you everything
now,
we,
I suggested a different,
well,
yeah
you don't need to know where you were before,
you only need to know where you are now
to know where you are now
to know where you'll be next
so,
both of these laws require only knowledge of where you
are at one instant to tell you where you'll be next
you simply follow the,
if you start someplace,
you follow the arrow until you come back
or you follow the arrow until
you get to the next place,
and that tells you where you'll be next
you don't need any more information than that
the only question is what
one of these points corresponds to
does one of these points correspond to,
how much information does it correspond
to a point in this space?
is it enough to know heads or
tails to know what you'll do next?
or might you need to know the two previous things?
that's a different,
that's a different setup
um
ok,
if you have a single particle in three space
then that has six phase space coordinates
let's,
let's stay with the heads and tails for a minute
let's suppose that in order to say what happens next
you need to know the previous two configurations
let's do,
let's work out that example
and let's write it in this form
let's make up a law
I think I had one down before
heads,
heads goes to heads
tails goes to what?
tails?
tails,
heads goes to heads
and tails,
tails goes to tails
ok
is there something wrong with that?
yeah
it's an only,
it's an only course
we gotta switch one of yours
it doesn't matter
it only depends on the last state
heads goes to heads
oh this only depends on,
heads goes to your right,
you're right,
you're right
sorry,
heads,
yeah
we want this one to go to tails
uh
second one goes to heads,
good,
yeah
oh no,
there you go
yes
sorry,
that won't work
no,
there's two of them that were in the first one
what,
what?
say it again
then the first,
what happened two times ago
matters but not the last time
that's also true,
yeah,
yeah
see it looks a little hard to work an example,
doesn't it?
um,
let's see
switch the second one and that'll do it
hm?
switch the second one
switch the second one,
this one?
make it tails
make it tails,
ok
I think that's perfectly alright
you lose information,
why?
well,
ok,
here's a setup
if you know the previous two,
then you know what happens next
in fact,
uh,
let's,
let's now see if we can
make a table out of this
not a table,
but a set of points
a set of points,
then there are four possibilities
heads heads,
heads tails,
tails heads,
and tails tails
ok,
let's see,
here's
heads heads
heads tails
tails heads
and tails tails
now,
supposing you go
from heads heads
to heads
heads
that means you go from heads heads
to heads heads
right?
you go from heads heads to heads heads
now,
supposing you go from
let's see what happens
if you start with heads tails
where do you go to?
so you go from heads tails,
to tails tails
ok
ok,
what happens if you go from tails tails
Well,
we're going to run into trouble,
aren't we?
Yes.
Tails,
tails goes to tails?
Yes.
That's no good.
So tails,
tails goes to tails,
tails.
Bad.
Not allowable by the laws of physics.
Yeah.
You could do an XOR.
And now tails,
heads goes where?
Tails,
tails.
tails goes to tails,
tails?
Heads,
tails.
Wait.
Tails,
tails.
heads.
Tails,
heads goes to heads,
tails.
Tails,
heads goes to heads,
tails.
So that goes here.
That goes to tails,
tails.
Change the third one.
It seems to me we should
be able to make a consistent law.
What?
This one?
This one.
Oh,
tails,
tails goes to tails,
tails goes to tails.
Tails,
tails goes to tails,
tails goes to tails.
Tails,
tails goes to heads.
Yeah,
OK.
So then tails,
tails goes to heads.
And that means that tails,
tails,
heads.
So that means tails,
tails goes to tails,
heads.
Ah.
Oh,
OK,
good,
good.
Now we have a workable law.
The only thing we had to do was
to say that what we originally called a configuration,
namely a single heads or tails,
was not a complete specification.
A complete specification of information
involved two pieces of information.
And once we recognized that,
we were able to write this
down as a law of physics,
which is deterministic and reversible.
OK.
So you don't know offhand.
You don't know to begin with what pieces of information you
need to know in order to know what to do next.
But that's what the configuration space,
or that's what the phase space is.
It's the collection of all the things you
need to know to know what happens next.
Now,
of course,
you could go beyond this.
You could say,
I need to know the first three
things in order to know what happens next.
You can do that.
You'll simply need more states
to make a deterministic system.
What would it mean in classical mechanics to
need more information than the positions of the tails?
Or the positions and velocities?
Suppose you needed the positions,
velocities,
and accelerations.
That would mean third order differential equations,
but what would it say about the phase space?
It would mean you would need positions,
velocities,
and accelerations to represent the phase space.
As it happens,
that is not the case for classical mechanics.
That's an experimental fact.
But it wouldn't stop us if we did.
If we did need the accelerations,
we would just write third order equations,
and we would make our phase space three-dimensional.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.