This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Let me review,
first of all,
the idea of initial conditions and
why we need both position and velocity.
Let's just take the case of
one dimensional motion as an example.
And let me begin with a false law of physics.
I think I called it last time Aristotle's Law.
Aristotle thought that in order to keep an object moving,
you had to continuously exert a force on it.
Of course,
we know that's not true.
An object moving through free space
under its own inertia will keep moving
without an external force,
but Aristotle's Law is a consistent mathematical law.
So let me write it down.
What it says,
I don't know that Aristotle,
of course,
ever said it this way.
I'll say it this way.
I would call it my own
law except I know that it's wrong,
so there's not much percentage in it.
Force is equal,
let's put a constant in and call it mass,
times velocity.
And we can make this a vector
equation or we can simply make it
a one dimensional equation along an axis.
It says that without force we have our force.
you can't have any velocity.
If you remove the force,
an object will instantly come to rest.
Wrong equation.
But we can also write this,
of course,
F equals mass times dx dt.
And just to remind you,
I often use the notation dot on top of
a symbol to indicate derivative with respect to time.
So that's Aristotle's law.
Now,
what do you need...oh,
and we'll also assume something else.
We'll assume that the force law is a law which tells you
what the force on the object is if you know where it is.
Where the object is.
So let's write F of x.
F of x is equal to mass...well,
that's fine.
Mass times dx dt.
Now,
I say that in order to follow the system,
all you need to know is,
at the initial starting point,
all you need to know is the position.
You don't need to know the velocity.
How do I know that?
Well,
look at this equation.
Supposing you knew that time t equals zero,
this is x,
the vertical axis doesn't mean anything right now.
Supposing we knew the particle was at x.
Then,
we would instantly know the force on it.
Why?
Because the force is a known function of position.
But from that,
we would instantly read off the velocity.
Just from the equation itself.
So,
with Aristotle's equation,
if we know x at an instant,
we also know the velocity.
Now,
what about the acceleration?
Do we know the acceleration?
Let's prove that we can figure out the velocity.
Let's figure out the acceleration.
To figure out the acceleration,
all we have to do is
differentiate this with respect to time.
We'll assume the mass,
in fact,
from here on in,
forever and ever,
mass is a constant.
It doesn't change with time.
The mass of an object,
just to state that.
Of course,
the mass of an object could change.
We could drop the bottom row off this,
and its mass changes.
But that's only because we ignored
part of the system that fell off.
All right,
so here we are.
F equals m dx dt.
Let's differentiate this with respect to time.
Then on the right-hand side,
we'll of course have the acceleration.
Mass times the acceleration.
What about the left-hand side?
The left-hand side will have
the time derivative of the force.
So let's come over to this blackboard
and calculate the time derivative of the force.
Why does the force change in the first place?
It changes because the particle moves.
And depending on where the particle is,
the force will change.
The force only changes because the particle moves.
So let's calculate the time
rate of change of the force.
That's equal to the derivative of the force.
Let's call it the derivative of
the force with respect to position.
I'm using some crazy mixed notation,
partial and the derivative of
the force with respect to position.
That tells you how much the force changes when you
move from one position to another times how fast you move.
dx dt.
In fact,
if you look at this equation,
you'll notice it's correct because
you can cancel out the dx.
The f dt is the
f by dx dx by dt.
And what it tells you is the force
changes with time because it varies with position,
and position is varying with respect to time.
So this then is the
f by dx times the velocity.
Okay,
let's put it in here.
The f by dt is equal to
the f by dx times the velocity.
Let's forget this for a moment.
Well,
that immediately now tells us the acceleration.
We know the force is a function of position.
We can differentiate it and find out
how it varies with respect to position.
So if we know f of x,
we also know df by dx.
And the first equation up here tells us
what the velocity is if we know the position.
If we know the instantaneous position,
we know the velocity.
If we know the velocity,
then we know the acceleration.
So without any further information,
using the equation,
we can also deduce the acceleration of the object.
We can go further.
What's the derivative of acceleration called?
Jerk.
The time derivative of acceleration.
Let's see if we can
work that out just for fun.
Just...
Supposing we differentiate this
equation with respect to time.
Then we'll have m times the jerk,
the derivative of the acceleration with respect to time.
Let's call it jerk,
j.
Which is derivative of acceleration with respect to time.
Alright,
now we have to differentiate the right-hand side.
The right-hand side is a product.
To differentiate a product,
we use the product rule.
And that says,
first of all,
we have df by dt.
And that's the derivative of f by dx.
Times dv by dt.
But that's just the acceleration.
That's one term.
That's the term coming from differentiating velocity.
And then the other term is
gotten by differentiating df by dx.
We're differentiating with respect to time.
But that's just the second derivative of f
with respect to x squared times the velocity.
Forget this for a moment.
The time derivative of f of the derivative of f is the
second derivative of f with respect to x times the velocity again.
It's exactly the same thing as over here,
except applied to the derivative of f.
Now,
we have to multiply that by another velocity.
Okay.
Derivative of f with respect to
x times the velocity times another velocity.
The upshot is,
in fact,
we do know the jerk.
We,
a moment ago,
convinced ourselves that if we know the initial position,
we also know both the velocity and the acceleration.
Well,
all that goes in here is velocity
and acceleration and knowledge of the force law.
So,
you also know the jerk.
I don't know what the term
for the derivative of the jerk is.
The putz,
the schmuck,
I don't know.
But,
uh...
I don't know what the term is.
I don't know what it's called.
But you can see the pattern differentiated again,
and each time you can deduce the next derivative.
That,
in effect,
says you can build up the entire motion if all
you know is the position at one instant of time.
Now,
as I said,
this is a false law.
So,
let's go to Newton's laws.
And I'm going to ask the same kind of question.
So,
f is now equal to mass times acceleration,
which means mass times the second
derivative of position with respect to time.
Sometimes,
if I use my dot notation,
I'll call that mx double dot.
Each dot means a derivative with respect to time.
Okay.
Let's suppose,
again,
I know where the particle
is at time t equals zero.
That means I know x.
That also means I know the force on it,
because the force is a function of position.
But how on earth am I
going to get the velocity from this?
I can't get the velocity.
What it tells me is the
acceleration in terms of the force,
and there is nothing in this equation
which tells me what the velocity is.
Just doesn't tell me.
So I've got to add in
the velocity as another piece of information.
So,
I've got to add in x and velocity,
or x and x dot,
are what I need to know to get started.
Well,
if I know x and the velocity,
then I can calculate the jerk.
Well,
first of all,
I can calculate the acceleration.
The acceleration I calculate from Newton's equation.
So now what do I know?
I know the position.
I know the velocity,
because I'm assuming that was the velocity.
That was given to us.
And I now deduce the acceleration.
From there on,
I can continue and compute the
jerk in exactly the same way.
If I know the acceleration and the velocity,
I then compute the jerk,
and then the multiple,
all the multiple derivatives.
So,
the lesson is,
in Newton's equations,
which are second order equations,
which involve second derivatives with respect to time,
you need to know,
to get started,
positions and velocities.
You need to know the position and velocity of
every particle and every component of the position and velocity.
If you know that,
then Newton's equations allow you to compute.
And,
of course,
you also need to know the force
law as a function of those positions.
The force law might depend not
only on the position of particles,
but it might depend on the different,
on relative positions and so forth.
But,
if you know all the positions,
then it's assumed that you know the force.
All the positions of all the particles,
then it's assumed that you know the
force on every single one of them,
due to all the others.
That's the assumption of Newton's equations.
Now,
we also talked about conservation of energy.
I think I was getting a little bit tired.
I tend to do that after two hours.
So,
let's just go back quickly
and discuss conservation of energy.
From Newton's equations.
Nothing deep at this point.
I mean,
conservation of energy is clearly
a lot deeper than Newton's equations.
It follows for electromagnetic radiation.
It follows in the theory of electrodynamics.
It works in relativity theory.
It works in general relativity.
It works in quantum mechanics.
There's clearly something much deeper
about the conservation of energy
than just what we're about to demonstrate.
But,
still,
we'll start slow.
Okay.
Now,
I gave you the example,
a couple of examples,
where energy conservation fails.
For example,
if there's friction forces,
of course,
energy conservation really does work.
It works if you were to follow the heat
and everything else that's produced by the sliding eraser.
But if you ignore all that and just
think of friction forces slowing the eraser down,
it would seem that the energy,
the kinetic energy,
the energy of motion,
suddenly goes away,
and it's not compensated for any change in potential energy.
So,
there are options.
There are obviously formulas that you can
write down which would not conserve energy.
I'll give you another example.
The other example was the spiral staircase.
The spiral staircase,
you can think of it this way.
Supposing you have a force law
that always pushes you around
a circle in the same direction.
The force always points around the circle.
Let's not worry for the moment where
the centrifugal force takes you off the circle.
Let's pretend that the force is
always pushing you around the circle.
Let's pretend that there's a good solid barrier,
another force,
which keeps the particle from moving off the circle.
And what's going to happen?
If the force is always pushing you
around the circle in the same direction,
the particle is going to
get faster and faster and faster.
And it's clear,
by the time it comes back to the same position,
it will be going faster.
There's no possibility of a
conservation of potential in kinetic energy
because you've come back to exactly the same spot.
So therefore the potential energy,
if there is any,
will be the same.
But the kinetic energy has increased.
And it'll keep increasing.
A force law like this is,
again,
unphysical.
It never occurs in nature.
The forces that occur in nature are called conservative.
And they are always of the following form.
The components of a force,
I'm speaking about a single particle now,
we'll generalize this to many particles,
in fact we'll generalize it to arbitrary systems,
but let's take the case of a single particle.
The force,
and now think of the force as a vector,
I'm drawing it in two dimensions,
it could be in any number of dimensions,
is equal to minus the derivative,
I'll write a formula and
then I'll explain what it means.
This formula,
this triangle is simply a symbol for derivatives,
partial derivatives.
Imagine that the potential energy is a function of position,
and if the position were two-dimensional,
as it is here,
it would be a function of x and y.
This is the potential energy,
u.
This formula really just means
that each component of the force,
the x component of the force,
and the y component of the force,
are equal to minus the derivative,
in this case with respect to x,
of u of x and y,
and minus the derivative with respect to
y of u of x and y.
That's what this symbol means.
It means the collection of derivatives,
partial derivatives,
with respect to the individual coordinates.
So what it says then,
is the components of force in a given direction
are proportional to how fast the
potential energy is changing along that direction.
Okay.
Alright,
let's use this to prove the conservation
of energy for the motion of a particle.
I did it last time,
but I,
as I said,
I was getting a little bit tired,
so I want to do it again,
and just do it as review.
Okay.
Let's define the quantity of the total energy
as the sum of kinetic energy plus potential energy.
Okay,
what about,
what is kinetic energy?
I'll define it for you now.
By definition,
for a particle moving,
it's one half
the mass of the particle times the velocity squared.
The velocity squared means,
if there's more than one component of velocity,
it means the sums of the
squares of the components of the velocity.
So in this case,
with two dimensions,
it would mean one half
m vx squared plus vy squared.
More generally,
I could write it as one
half the mass of the object
times the sum over the components of vi squared.
Sum,
meaning vx squared plus vy squared plus vz squared,
or whatever the number of directions of space is.
Okay,
that's the kinetic energy.
So that's usually called T.
Again,
just like P stands for momentum,
T stands for kinetic energy.
Don't ask me why.
And then,
the other contribution to the energy...
Is that also why U is potential?
Yeah,
it's also why U is potential.
A lot of people use V for potential.
But that gets mixed up with voltage,
which is potential energy divided by charge.
So I use U and I steer clear of V,
but other people use V.
It also gets confused with velocity.
T plus U.
That is the total energy.
I want to prove that it's
conserved as a consequence of Newton's equation,
F equals m a.
What does it mean that it's conserved?
It means that its time derivative is zero.
So all we have to
do is take its time derivative,
use Newton's equations,
and prove that everything cancels out
when we take the time derivative.
That's the exercise.
And it's not very hard.
Let's do it.
Okay,
so let's calculate the time
derivative of the kinetic energy.
Derivative with respect to time of kinetic energy.
That is...
Here it is right here.
Here's the kinetic energy.
One half mv squared.
m is not changing.
Mass is fixed.
One half is not changing.
The thing which might change is the velocity.
This,
of course,
is the sum of squares of velocities.
So it's a sum.
mv sub i times dv sub i by dt.
Now what I've done is I've
said that the derivative of a square,
namely the derivative of v squared,
is v times the derivative of v.
The derivative of a square of something
is the something times its own derivative.
Whoops.
I forgot a factor of...
I did it right,
but I didn't say it right.
The derivative of the square is twice
the something times the derivative of the something.
All right?
That gets rid of the factor of two.
So the time derivative of the kinetic energy
is the sum over all the directions of space,
the mass,
times the ith component of the velocity,
times...
Now what's dv sub i by dt?
That's the component of the acceleration.
So we might as well call it the acceleration.
a sub i.
Ith component of acceleration.
Let's calculate the time derivative
now of the potential energy.
And the potential energy is also...
It is a function of position.
When I write here that it's a function of x,
it could be a function of x,
y,
z,
all of the coordinates.
What is the derivative of u with respect to time?
Well,
u varies with time for the
same reason that it did before,
because the position varies.
It varies a little bit if
you move in the x direction.
you move in the y direction.
It varies a little bit if
you move in the z direction.
And so in fact,
the derivative of u with respect
to t is the sum of terms,
each term being the derivative of u with
respect to x times the time derivative of x,
plus du by dy.
times the time derivative with respect to y,
and so forth.
Or I can summarize it by
saying it's the derivative of u
with respect to the ith coordinate x
times the velocity in the ith direction,
times the component of the velocity in the ith direction.
Again,
summed over i.
So now let's write down
the total time derivative of u.
It's the sum of these two.
Derivative of kinetic energy,
derivative of potential energy.
And we can write down
that the time derivative of energy
is equal to the summation over all the directions.
Let's take v sub i first,
and then write m a sub i.
That's the first term here.
You can see where this is going.
I'm grouping m with a sub i for a reason.
And then we have to add to that,
again,
a sum over i.
And it is plus du by dx i,
also times vi.
Both these terms have the velocities in them.
So let's take the velocity outside the parentheses.
Like so.
Well,
what do we have?
What's m a sub i?
It's a force.
Mass times acceleration.
So this is the component of
the force in the ith direction.
But what's du by dx i?
That's minus the force in the ith direction.
There's a minus sign here.
So this is just f minus f.
That's what's in the bracket here.
Notice that force is minus
the derivative of potential energy.
All times v.
But if f minus f is 0,
whether it's multiplied by v or not,
so term by term,
all you get is 0.
Upshot.
Energy is conserved.
And now we're only talking about a
single particle moving in a force field.
But we could be talking about any number of particles.
Instead of thinking of the sum as just
a sum over the three directions of space,
it could also include the sum over different particles.
And precisely the same kind of analysis would
say that if you have a system of particles,
that the system of particles will function in
a way that is not a system of particles.
That the system of particles will have a conserved energy.
No matter what the force is,
as long as the rule is
that the force on every particle
is minus the derivative of
u with respect to its position.
Okay.
So that was review.
I don't remember if we talked
about conservation of momentum last time.
Did we?
No.
Okay.
So I will now begin reviewing
what I did not do last time.
But which I had intended to do.
So let's review conservation of momentum.
Now as I said,
this was a little bit of
trickery and a little bit of magic.
And you might say,
yeah,
but why is energy really conserved?
We will come to that.
But for the moment,
we're just observing that Newton's equations
allow you to define a certain thing.
Namely,
T plus V to be called energy.
Okay.
Now let's come to momentum.
Now first of all,
let me rewrite Newton's equation
in a slightly different form.
Nothing very deep.
Now we're talking about a single particle.
The single particle is just,
has the equation.
The force,
again,
we can do it in components.
F sub i is just equal to mass times
the derivative of V sub i with respect to T.
Again,
i simply stands for one
of the three coordinates of space.
So these are the three coordinates.
All right.
Mass doesn't change with time.
So I can bring it into the
time derivative and just write the force.
I'm not going to bother putting indices down here.
Is the derivative with respect
to time of mass times V.
And now give mass times V a name.
The name is momentum.
Mass times velocity,
and it's a vector.
It has components.
It has,
we can write this for each component.
M times V is called momentum.
And so another form of Newton's equations is that force is
equal to the time derivative of the momentum of an object.
Momentum is called P.
And so we have this.
We can make this a vector equation if we like.
Force is simply the time derivative of the momentum.
And wasn't that the original formulation
that was along the way being stated?
I don't know.
I don't think Newton actually defined the
definition of momentum as far as I know.
I'm not sure.
It's been quite a number of
years since I read the Principia.
What assumptions are we making about
time before we can do the Newton's?
What assumptions are we making about time?
Well...
Yeah,
I know we didn't talk about it.
No,
we didn't talk about it.
We're assuming that there's a universal concept
of time at every point in this room.
We could have a watch or a clock,
each one of you has a clock.
They're synchronized.
And we're making the dumbest,
simplest Newtonian assumption that time
is an absolutely universal thing.
At every point of space we can synchronize our
watches so that everybody will agree upon the time.
And that time just flows uniformly
in the most naive kind of sense.
One of the things we have assumed is that
the force law here does not explicitly depend on time.
We could imagine force laws which change with time.
I'm assuming for the moment that that's not the case.
All right,
now let's come to conservation of momentum.
First of all,
even if there were just a single
particle and there was no force on it,
momentum would be conserved because who would say
the time derivative of momentum is equal to zero?
So for a single particle with no forces on it,
out in outer space,
far away in between galaxies,
the momentum is conserved.
At least to the approximation that
we ignore forces on the particle.
But that's hardly a very general example.
So let's think about a more general example.
The basic foundation for the conservation of momentum
is another one of Newton's laws about force.
Here's what Newton said.
He said the forces between objects.
Well,
first of all,
he said the force on every object,
and by every object we can mean particles now,
everything being made out of particles.
The force on every object is the sum
of forces due to all the other objects.
All right,
so if we call this particle one,
then the force on particle one is equal to
the force on particle one due to particle two,
let's call that F12,
plus the force on particle one due to particle three,
we assume that a particle
doesn't exert a force on itself.
Plus F14,
and so forth.
Force on particle one is the sum,
this is one,
two,
three,
four,
five.
Same thing for particle two.
The force on particle two
is the force on particle three,
plus the force on two due to one.
Okay,
so notice what I've,
notice my notation.
My notation is the first entry
is the particle that we're talking about,
who's,
we're talking about the force on the first particle here.
The second entry is,
refers to the particle that the force is due to.
So this is the force on one due to two.
Here's the force on two due to one,
plus the force on two due to three,
plus the force on two due to four,
and so forth.
Let's just take three,
I don't want to write too much.
Let's just truncate it at three particles.
And finally,
the third particle would have a force due to,
a force on three due to one,
plus a force on three due to one.
Plus a force on three due to two.
And that's all.
Now Newton's assumption,
Newton's law,
it's called action and reaction of course,
is that the forces of a particle on another particle,
the forces between a pair of particles,
are equal and opposite.
So the force on one due to two,
might be an attraction for example,
is equal and opposite to the
force on two due to one.
So if two is pulling one upward to the left,
one is pulling two downward to the right,
with the same magnitude of force.
Now there was another element to this,
that the force is along
the line separating the two particles,
but we're going to not worry about that right now.
We'll come back to that.
The important point is that the
force on one due to two,
is minus the force on two due to one.
We can make a vector equations
out of these if we like.
They are vector equations.
And what does Newton's law say?
It says that F12 is minus F21.
F13 is minus F31.
And F32 is minus F23.
Okay,
now let's see if we can explore momentum conservation.
What we'd like to prove is that the time derivative
of the total momentum of a system is zero,
as a consequence of this.
What do I mean by the total momentum?
I mean the total sum of momentum
on all the parts of the system,
all the particles that make it up.
So,
let's write them down,
let's do the three particle case.
dP1 by dt.
I'm not going to bother putting vector signs above the,
think vector.
dP1 by dt is equal to F1,
which means F12 plus F13.
Plus all the others,
if there were more.
What about dP2 by dt?
That's equal to F21 plus F23.
And finally,
dP3 by dt is equal to F31 plus F32.
Now let's add them up.
dP1 by dt,
dP2 by dt,
and dP3 by dt.
That gives us the total
time derivative of the total momentum.
So,
the time derivative of the total momentum,
dP by dt,
is just the sum of
everything in the right hand corner.
The left hand side.
But they cancel in pairs.
F12 is minus F21.
This is just saying the forces cancel.
F13 is minus F31,
and F23 is minus F23.
They all add up to zero.
And it says that the
total momentum of any closed system
means a system with no external forces on it.
Of course,
we might have other forces,
due to some other object in the system.
Then we would have to take it into account also.
But if we have a closed system,
a closed system means we've
accounted for everything in the system
that can exert forces.
Then the time rate of change of momentum is zero,
and momentum is conserved.
Again,
it comes from a rather special assumption
about Newtonian forces,
but it's far more general.
It applies to light.
If a light ray bangs into the wall,
it'll give the wall a little bit of push.
It'll change the momentum of the wall.
Why?
Because the light ray has some momentum.
It applies in quantum mechanics.
It applies in the general theory of relativity.
So it's far,
far more general than this little example shows.
And our object will eventually be
to write the laws of physics,
in particular mechanics,
in a form which is so general
that we can see why these things had to happen.
Okay,
any questions?
Yes?
Is action and reaction instant?
Loud.
In Newtonian physics,
it is.
All right?
In classical mechanics,
Newtonian physics,
and Newtonian physics means forget relativity.
In Newtonian,
let's put it this way.
In Newtonian physics,
the speed of light is infinite.
You turn on the lights
and the room lights up instantaneously.
There's no lag.
In the real world,
of course,
forces do not act instantaneously.
It takes time for a force,
when you do something to a particle over here,
it takes time for it to,
for a force to respond over there.
That's because of relativity,
special relativity.
We're assuming Newtonian physics,
and Newtonian physics means that forces are instantaneous.
So yes,
we're assuming they're instantaneous.
Again,
what's curious is that special relativity
undermines that instantaneousness of forces,
but it does not undermine
the conservation of momentum.
So it's somehow much deeper
than our examples indicate.
The momentum law seems a little more deeper
than the energy law,
in the sense that...
It's easier to derive.
Also,
you can choose any direction,
and momentum,
the component of momentum,
will be conserved in that direction.
It seems like there are more laws...
Right,
there are more momentum laws
than there is energy law.
How many momentum laws are there
for a single particle,
for example?
Well,
how many momentum laws are there altogether
for a combined system?
Three.
One for each direction of space.
How many energy laws?
One.
So altogether,
there are four conservation laws.
Three for the three directions of space,
and one for the direction of time.
And in the special theory of relativity,
they form a complex of four related conservation laws,
but this...
It's more general than that.
Okay.
Now,
it's my usual...
Yeah.
We're going to need a little bit of mathematics,
not heavy-duty mathematics,
fairly light,
but let's spend a little bit of time...
What we're going to do next
is we're going to go on
to what really is the deep law of classical physics.
It's called the principle or the law of least action.
And it contains all this junk.
The law of least action,
has all of this stuck into it,
plus a lot more.
But before we do,
we need some math.
Elementary mathematics,
extremely simple.
Math that you know very well.
I just want to spell it out
and remind some of you who haven't done calculus
for a couple of years,
so that we're all on the same playing field.
Okay.
The first thing has to do with minimizing functions.
This is very elementary.
I'm not telling you anything you don't know.
If you have a function of several variables,
let's start with a function of one variable.
Function of y.
Some known...
Not force.
F does not stand for force now.
It just stands for function.
F of y.
And y is just some generic independent variable.
Okay.
Here it is.
Here's the function.
It's plotted.
Vertically,
I plot f.
Horizontally,
I plot the independent variable y.
And it has some shape,
something.
The first fact is,
if you want to find the local minima,
the local minima of the function
mean the places where,
if you're there,
if you go in either direction,
the function increases.
A global minimum
would mean the absolute minimum,
the lowest possible minimum.
But we're going to speak about local minima.
Local minima mean that if
you are confined to that region,
you would think that the function
was minimum right at that point.
What is the mathematical condition for searching for minima?
Well...
The derivative of a function should be equal to zero.
Right.
That's not sufficient.
Yeah.
Right.
So the first condition,
and the easiest one,
is that at a minimum,
the slope of the function is zero.
That says that the derivative of the
function is equal to zero at minima.
It's also zero at maxima,
notice.
Right.
The first condition is that df by dx,
or df by dy,
total derivative,
in this case,
if it's only a function of one variable,
is equal to zero.
Now,
there are other conditions.
The other conditions are basically there to sort out
two other cases.
The maximum,
the f by dy is also zero at maxima,
but,
you can check
whether it's a maximum or a minimum
by looking at the second derivative.
The second derivative is positive at a minimum
and negative at a maximum.
But we're not going to worry about that distinction.
The principle of...
What's the generic term
for a function which is either maximum or minimum,
and you may not know which?
Extremum.
Extremum is one word.
In fact,
there's even another possibility,
an inflection point where the function is flat
and then goes down like that.
Again,
zero derivative at that point.
X cubed is a function which has a...
an inflection point like that at the origin.
Its derivative is also zero at the origin.
Knowing that the derivative is zero
doesn't sort out these three cases of
minimum,
maximum,
or inflection point.
So,
the word for either minimum or maximum
is extremal,
extremum point,
but what's the word for
any one of these three?
Stationary,
stationary.
Stationary.
The function is stationary at those points.
Which means
that if you move a little to the left
or move it to the right,
it neither increases nor decreases.
Well,
it may increase
to second order,
but it doesn't increase to first order.
The derivative is zero there.
It's said to be stationary.
The real principle of least action
is really the principle of stationary action.
We'll call it the principle of least action
and always pretend that we're looking for
minima of things,
but in fact,
it's more general.
The principle of action
is the principle of stationary action.
But I'm not going to draw that distinction
after this point now.
The condition for a stationary point
is that the derivative of f with respect to y
is equal to zero.
And I'll often say minimum,
but I will mean stationary point.
Now,
supposing we have a function
which is a function of several variables,
f of x and y.
And let's think about it.
Let's draw the xy plane.
At every point on this plane,
the function takes on some value.
We could describe the function
by a sort of contour map.
You've all seen contour maps.
You know what they look like.
Each contour describing
a particular value of the function.
And as you move from one point,
one contour point to another contour point,
the function changes.
Well,
all right,
I don't need the contour map.
All we need to do is draw the xy plane.
All we need to do is to remember
that the function has some value
at every point on this two-dimensional plane.
Now,
supposing what I want
is the minimum,
local minimum,
with respect to two variables.
What that means is a point
where the function is minimum
no matter what direction you move off in.
It could be any number of dimensions.
I'm interested in points
where the function
achieves a minimum,
which means that any direction
that you move off in,
the function increases.
However you move.
Think of it as the bottom of a bowl.
Right.
Are you talking stationary again?
Yeah,
strictly speaking,
we're talking stationary.
But I'll use the terminology of minimum.
And if you want to think about it,
think about minimum.
You won't be making any serious
mistakes because in fact,
almost every case in mechanics,
we really are talking about
the minimum action.
I have a question.
I think I read that if forces are conservative,
that it is not a maximum.
If forces are conservative,
it's not a maximum,
but I think that's probably not true
if there are velocity-dependent forces
like magnetic forces,
although I've never checked that.
That would be the non-perturbative case.
Non-perturbative?
Non-conservative.
No,
no,
no.
Magnetic forces are conservative,
but they're different in nature than...
Let's not get into them at the moment.
We'll come back to them.
I believe there are cases in physics
where the action is not minimum,
but they're unusual.
So let's just say minimum.
Minimum,
minimum.
Let's not worry about that subtlety.
All right.
Well,
first of all,
let's suppose we are...
There's a minimum right there,
and let's look at the function...
Whoops,
I meant to go right through that point.
Let's look at the function
as we move to the left or right
away from that point.
Now the function is only a function of one variable.
Think of it as a function of one variable
along this line.
It should achieve a minimum
right at this point.
So that means as you move along this line,
ignoring all the other lines,
the function should be minimum at that point,
and that says that the derivative of f
with respect to x
should be equal to zero.
But we can say exactly the same thing
about moving on the vertical axis.
If the function is minimum at that point,
it will be minimum with respect to a vertical motion.
So that says the function...
should have no derivative with respect to y.
If you have a function
of a whole bunch of variables,
let's give them the generic name x sub i now.
Function of x sub i.
The condition that you're at a local minimum
is that the derivative of f
with respect to every one of the x sub i's,
every single one should be equal to zero.
Let's do an example or two just to...
I think as a function of one variable,
we don't need to do an example.
Let's take a function of two variables
and find its local minimum.
Just,
in fact,
it will be its global minimum.
I'm just arbitrarily making up a silly function now.
All right,
here it is.
x squared plus y squared
plus 3x plus 2y
let's put in plus xy
plus 7.
That's my function.
I want to find out where that function is minimum.
All right?
So I differentiate it with respect to x
and set the derivative equal to zero.
That gives me one equation.
Do the same thing for y.
It gives me a second equation.
What are those equations for?
They're for x and y.
They tell me where the minimum is achieved.
So I have two equations for two unknowns.
Let's work them out just as an example.
The derivative,
the partial derivative of f
with respect to x,
df by dx.
All right,
that's from this term,
we just get y.
From this term,
we get plus 2x.
This term doesn't depend on x altogether.
From this term,
we just get 3.
And there are no other terms which depend on x.
So this is the derivative
of f with respect to x,
pretending that y were just a constant.
All right,
that's the partial derivative.
And our rule is,
set this equal to zero.
That's one equation for x squared.
And we're going to do the
same thing for x and y.
All right,
let's do the same thing df by dy.
df by dy is x
plus 2y plus 2 equals zero.
Here are two linear equations for x and y.
You can sit down and solve them.
Notice that the 7 didn't come into it at all.
Why not?
Because the 7 is just the height,
the overall height of the function,
and it doesn't change where the minimum is.
All right,
so I'll tell you what the answer is.
It's x is equal to minus 8 thirds,
and y is equal to minus 1 third.
And if that's not correct,
it's not important.
Is it minus 1 third?
I lost the paper that I did it on.
But it's not important.
There is an answer to the problem,
as you can see.
It's just two equations for two unknowns.
If you have n unknowns,
in other words,
if you have a function of n variables,
then there are n equations like this.
n equations for n unknowns typically will have a solution.
Not always.
Some functions don't have minima.
For example,
if I took a function that just was like that,
forever and ever,
it wouldn't have a minimum.
There would just be no solution.
There would be no point at which the derivative vanished.
Sometimes there's more than one solution.
For example,
if I took a function
with a few minima in it.
But you have enough equations
for enough unknowns to locate solutions.
All right,
that's mathematical point number one.
You find stationary points or minima
by different equations.
You're differentiating the function.
Or another way of saying it is finding points
where if you vary the function a little bit,
it doesn't change.
It doesn't change the first order in the variation,
basically.
All right,
so that's the principle of stationary functions.
Now,
we're not going to be interested in minimizing functions
of a finite number of variables.
We're going to be interested in something
which,
at the face of it,
seems far more complicated.
It's minimizing expressions which depend
not on some finite set of variables,
but which themselves depend on whole functions,
whole trajectories,
minimizing quantities which depend on a whole trajectory.
Before I give you an example,
let me just say some words about
what the basic principle of stationary functions is.
And what the basic problem of mechanics is.
And more than that,
the basic problem of classical physics,
but let's say mechanics.
The basic problem of mechanics is to determine
the trajectory of a system
from its initial starting conditions.
That's the mathematical problem.
Now,
of course,
in every case,
we may not really be interested in determining
if we have 10 to the 23rd particles,
determining the trajectory of that system
is equivalent to determining the trajectories
of all 10 to the 23rd particles.
Nobody tries to do that.
Instead,
we may make some statistical statements about it,
or some approximate statements.
But the very precise question of classical mechanics
is determining the trajectory of a system.
Now,
what does it mean?
We spoke last time a little bit
about generalized coordinates.
Generalized coordinates are simply
the coordinates of a system.
They could be the Cartesian coordinates
of the positions of a system of particles.
They could be angles.
They could be the orientation of this eraser.
They could be any number of different kinds
of coordinates that we might use.
For example,
on the surface of the Earth,
we might use latitude and longitude
to locate an object.
Those are all generalized coordinates,
and they may not be Cartesian coordinates.
They may be angles or other funny kinds of variables.
But they do serve to locate an object in space,
or locate a system in space.
Those are called the generalized coordinates,
and they're often labeled by Q.
Q1 dot dot dot through Qn.
For a single particle,
there are three Qs.
X,
Y,
and Z.
For two particles,
there are six Qs.
The X,
Y,
and Z of one particle
and the X,
Y,
and Z of the other particle.
If there are 10 to the 23rd particles,
there are three times 10 to the 23rd Qs.
But as we've seen already,
the Qs are not enough
to be able to predict the future.
If you want to predict the future,
you also need the velocities.
So in a more general abstract language,
it also means that you need the Q dots,
the time derivatives.
You need six n pieces of information
for n particles to predict the future.
Now what does it mean to predict the future?
It means to determine
the trajectory of the system,
which means Q1 of t,
Q2 of t,
Q3 of t.
It means to determine all of the coordinates
as a function of time.
All of the particle coordinates
or the angles or the orientation angles
or whatever it is to determine all of them,
not just one of them as a function of time,
but all of them.
Such a system of functions
as a function of time,
we can call a generalized trajectory.
A generalized trajectory,
we can imagine horizontally
plotting all of the Qs.
Now horizontally,
I've just drawn two dimensions here.
Two dimensions will be a stand-in
for any number of dimensions,
Q1 through Qn.
And vertically,
we plot the time.
A trajectory simply means exactly what it says.
Because a trajectory through the space
and a trajectory through the space
is a system of Qs at every value of time.
That's the mathematical problem
that's put in front of us
by the questions of classical mechanics.
To what extent can we determine
the trajectory from the starting point?
All right,
the answer of course is,
given Newton's equations,
we can predict the Q of t,
not just from the starting point,
we need the Qs and
the Q dots to start with.
If we know the Qs and the Q dots,
we can determine the trajectory.
The equations of motion,
the Newton's equations of motion,
what they tell us is,
every point along this trajectory,
they kind of tell us,
if we're moving in a certain way,
how to move next.
They tell us that if
we know the velocity along here,
or sorry,
if we know where we are along here
and we know the forces,
then we know the acceleration.
So that tells us if we know where we are
and we know where we're moving,
we know where we'll be next
and we know where we'll be moving next.
The way to say this is that
Newton's equations are local equations
along the trajectory,
and they tell us information,
they tell us how to proceed from one point
to the next along the trajectory.
You don't need to know anything
about the rest of the trajectory.
If you know where you are over here,
and you know which way you're going,
then you know where you'll be next
and you know where you'll be going next.
So they're local equations,
and that's why they're differential equations.
Differential equations are equations
among the positions and the derivatives and so forth,
and that's the kind of
information that they have in them.
Now,
of course,
if you know this information
all along the trajectory,
then you can build up the whole trajectory.
But the equation itself is an equation
which tells you local information.
The principle of least action
is another formulation of the same physics
which looks at the trajectory as a whole.
Instead of being given the position
and the velocity at a single time,
what you're given is different kind of information.
You're given the position
at the beginning of a trajectory,
it could be the position of this eraser
at time t equals zero,
and after a certain specified amount of time,
you're given the position of the system
at the end of the trajectory.
In other words,
you're given the two endpoints
of the trajectory.
So,
for example,
here's an example,
here's the eraser.
I tell you at time t equals zero,
it's over here.
I'm not going to tell you how it's moving,
so I can't tell you
what it's going to do next,
but what I will tell
you is that after one second,
it will be over here.
There's only one trajectory
which goes from here to here in one second.
There it is.
If I throw it with the wrong velocity,
it won't get there.
So it's just as good to
know two points along the trajectory
as to know the two pieces of information
at a single point along the trajectory.
Same amount of information.
Instead of giving the position and velocity at one point,
I give you the positions at two separate times.
That's the problem,
that's another formulation of the question of mechanics.
Question of mechanics,
instead of the initial data problem,
the problem of finding a unique trajectory
which connects two points.
In this form,
the principle of nature that governs trajectories
is called the principle of least action.
And what it says is there's some quantity
associated with this trajectory,
the whole trajectory,
not just little pieces of local information,
but the whole trajectory,
there's some quantity about that trajectory
which is minimum for the true trajectory,
for the true trajectory,
and will be larger
for every deviation of the trajectory
from the true trajectory.
True trajectory.
Correct trajectory.
Here's an example.
Take two points.
For simplicity,
we could take them in two dimensions.
Calculate the distance between them
and ask what is the line,
well,
not the distance,
draw a line,
draw a curve between them.
Draw any curve between them.
Calculate the length of that curve
and then ask what curve minimizes the length.
What curve gives you the smallest distance
along the curve between those two points?
Of course,
we all know the answer,
it's a straight line.
But what's the mathematics that goes into it?
The mathematics that goes into it
is minimizing a certain quantity,
but that quantity is not a function
of a finite number of variables.
It's a function of every point along this curve.
So it's a much more complicated object
than calculating the minimum
of a function of a few variables.
There's two approaches to it.
One is the local approach,
which I'll show you what it means in a moment,
and one is the global approach.
Yeah,
let's talk about the local and the global approach.
The global approach is just what I said.
You pick your two points,
you calculate the distance along the curve,
that's some quantity that depends on the entire curve,
and then you ask what
minimizes the length along that curve.
That's something,
that's a very global view
where you minimize something
associated with the entire curve.
Now,
the local point of the curve
in the view goes as follows.
All right,
supposing we know,
let's focus,
let's take our little microscope here
and focus along,
somewhere along the trajectory over here.
In fact,
for our purposes,
let's imagine breaking up the trajectory
into a lot of little pieces,
each of some small length.
And let's focus right in here.
The curve comes in over here,
so it's pinned down over here,
it goes out over here,
and I'm interested in where it goes between them.
Let's just suppose in breaking it up into pieces
as an approximation.
As an approximation,
break up the curve into little pieces,
and now take two of those little pieces
and ask where should you locate the midpoint
in order that the curve be as short as possible.
Now,
the answer doesn't depend
where you put this point
does not depend on the rest of the curve
if you happen to know this point and that point.
If you know the point over here
and the point over here,
then the rest of the curve doesn't matter.
You will have to,
in any case,
if you want to make
the curve as short as possible
and you know that it passes through here and here,
then all you have to do is ask
how do you make that little segment between them
as short as possible.
What's the answer?
The answer is obvious,
but it's a local version of the same question.
It just depends on this little region over here.
The answer is obvious.
Just go straight ahead.
Move this point until this little piece of the curve
is as short as possible.
Right?
And go straight ahead.
We could express this as a differential equation.
We will.
As a differential equation,
which basically says that the difference in the slope
from one point to the next is zero.
But it's quite obvious that what it says
within this little red region here
is just go straight ahead.
If you generalize that all along the curve,
it will tell you at every point,
just go straight ahead.
So this is the local version,
which says go to each point on the curve
and make sure it's just going straight ahead.
That's enough to tell you that the shortest distance
between here and here is a straight line.
So there are these two different versions
of thinking about the principle of least distance.
This would be the principle of least distance
between these two points.
Let's see.
Just for future reference,
let's work out
Let's try to define our problem mathematically,
even if we won't solve it yet.
Let's try to define it mathematically.
I've solved it for you.
I've told you what the answer is,
a straight line.
Of course,
you knew that anyway.
But let's do a little bit of mathematics
and state the problem in a mathematical form.
Okay,
let's...
Let's take our curve,
and I think I'd like to get a better pen.
Let's think of our curve
as existing in the xy plane.
And let's suppose we know
that it goes through this point.
That's a point at x1,
and another point at x2.
And let's think of y as a function of x.
So there's some curve,
and what we know
is the value of y at x1,
and we know the value of y at x2.
In other words,
I tell you where the endpoints are,
and I ask you to find the shortest curve.
Well,
the first thing we're going to have to do
is calculate the distance along the curve
for any curve,
and then minimize it.
So let's imagine...
Let's not imagine,
let's calculate the distance along this curve.
We'll call this function y .
So if you like,
this is a problem of minimizing something
with respect to a whole function.
Finding the function which minimizes something.
Alright,
let's calculate the distance along this curve
if we know y .
First begin with a little segment.
A little segment,
of...
size dx along the x-axis.
Alright,
so it's a little gap in the function,
it's a little segment in the function
going over the interval dx.
Alright,
let's draw it over here.
Here it is.
It goes over distance dx.
There's y .
And we can also speak of dy.
Here's dy.
As we go from point x to x plus dx,
the function goes from y to y plus dy.
What is the length of the hypotenuse of the triangle?
If we add up all these little triangles
and add up all the hypotenuse...
What's the plural of hypotenuse?
I don't know.
A couple of problems?
I guess so.
If we add up all the hypotenuses,
we'll then compute the entire curve.
So let's compute it.
Well,
this side is dy,
this side is dx.
The distance along here,
we'll call that ds squared.
This is square of the distance.
S stands for distance.
Again,
one of these letters that has
nothing to do with the word.
S stands for distance.
The square of the distance along this hypotenuse here
is clearly dx squared plus dy squared.
Or if I take the square root,
it tells me the distance along the hypotenuse.
Let me write this in the following way.
Let me write ds.
I'm going to take it over here.
I'll rewrite it over here.
ds is equal to dx,
I'm factoring out dx,
times the square root of
1 plus dy by dx squared.
Where did I get that from?
If I bring the dx inside the square root,
I have to square it to
bring it inside the square root,
then the 1 will become dx squared,
and this term here will just become dy.
So I've just factored out dx.
I want to think of x as the independent variable.
dy by dx,
that's just the derivative of the function y of x.
So that's nothing but the derivative of the function.
If I gave you a function y,
you could differentiate it,
and this would be dy by dx.
Now let's add up all of the little intervals.
Adding up all the intervals means doing an integral.
So,
the total length of the curve
from point x1 to point x2,
let's call it s between 1 and 2,
is equal to the integral from x1 to x2
of just this quantity here,
square root of 1 plus dy by dx,
squared dx.
Now I'm not going to
do anything with this right now.
I just wanted to work out for you,
in terms of y of x,
if you know,
if somebody gives you the function y of x,
this is the way you
calculate the total length along here.
What is our problem?
Our problem is to find that function,
y of x,
which makes this integral as small as possible.
Now remember,
when I say that it's as small as possible,
what's inside the square root is bigger than 1.
It's 1 plus something positive.
You might say,
okay,
look,
if I want to make this as small as possible,
I will just make what's inside the square root here
as small as possible,
and make dy dx equal to 0.
No,
that's not the answer to this problem,
because we're making an assumption.
The assumption is that the
curve goes between these two points.
If dy by dx was 0 everywhere,
it would just be flat.
It wouldn't go between these two points.
So it's given that the
curve goes between these two points,
we want to find the minimum value of this integral,
the minimum value of this integral,
and that means the curve,
y of x,
which does that for us,
or the function,
y of x.
In this case,
if we thought of x as kind of like
time,
and y as the coordinate of a system,
this might be determining a trajectory
by some funny principle of
least distance in space and time.
But for the moment,
just all this is,
is how to find the shortest distance between two points.
Now,
I haven't told you how to do it.
We'll get to actually how you do it,
but that's the mathematical problem.
Find the function which minimizes this expression.
Okay.
Um,
this s here depends on y of x.
You can sort of think of
it as a function of a function.
Given y of x,
here's a rule for calculating a number from it.
It's a function of a function.
It's not a function of a few variables.
It's a function of an entire other function.
It's a number which depends on an entire function.
There's a name for a number.
It's called a functional.
A functional is a function of a function.
The result is a number,
but the input is a whole function.
So the distance between two points
is a functional of y of x,
and our problem is to find
the minimum value of that functional,
subject to some constraints that it passes through,
whoops,
that it passes through two points.
Let me give you another example,
a couple of other examples,
in physics,
where you might want to minimize
a functional with respect to a function.
A principle of optics is the principle of least time.
A light ray goes from one point to another point,
along a path that minimizes the amount of time
that it takes for the light ray
to go from that point to another.
That's Fermat's principle.
How we figured it out,
I don't know.
But it is a correct principle.
Now,
you say that just means the
light goes in a straight line.
If it minimizes the time that
it goes from one place to another,
and light goes with the speed of light,
that must mean it minimizes
the distance between the two points.
Yes,
that would be correct if the
speed of light was everywhere's constant.
But we're actually interested in a more
general and more interesting kind of setup,
where you might have a material of some sort,
with an index of refraction,
which means the speed of light,
which changes from point to point in the material.
All right?
Then it's not so clear
what trajectory we're going to get.
But we're going to have
a very interesting theory to take
in order to minimize the time that it takes.
So let me give you an example.
Let's suppose we have a material,
two-dimensional material.
There it is.
And the speed of light varies for simplicity.
There's nothing special about this.
But for simplicity,
let's suppose the speed of light
just varies with the vertical axis here.
So we can divide this up into a little thin...
ribbons.
And in each ribbon,
the speed of light is different.
For example,
the speed of light might vary from some minimum
to some large value up at the top.
Light goes slow down here.
And incidentally,
it goes the same velocity no
matter what direction it's going in.
That's an assumption.
There are materials where light moves
with different velocity in different directions,
but I'm not doing that.
All right.
So if the light is going this way,
it moves with a certain velocity.
If it's going this way,
it moves with the same velocity.
But the velocity does vary from strip to strip.
Okay.
Now I want to know,
what's the path so that the time
between this point and that point is minimum?
That's the true trajectory of the light ray.
Well,
if you take a straight line,
then that's not as efficient.
There may be a path which takes less time.
For example,
if I curve the path up a little bit,
I didn't mean to curve it quite that much,
but let's curve it up that much anyway,
then it's going to spend more of
its path moving where the speed is faster.
So it'll want to get to regions,
want to get,
light doesn't want to do anything,
but in order to minimize the speed,
to minimize the time that it
takes to go from here to here,
it might want to get to a
region quickly where the velocity is larger,
and then make most of
the path with a larger velocity.
So it's not obvious that
it goes in a straight line,
and it doesn't go in a straight line.
In fact,
it would go in a trajectory something like that
if the velocity of light increased as you moved vertically.
You might think,
well,
maybe the best thing to
do is to jump straight up
and then straight across,
but no,
that's not as good because the upward
part of the journey doesn't get you anywhere.
So it's not as good to just
go straight up and go straight across.
There's some compromise where you curve the
trajectory to get it into regions quickly
where the velocity of light is faster,
but not straight up and straight across.
Alright,
so what is then the
quantity which you're trying to minimize
when you speak about the principle of least time?
So I'll work it out for you.
Just for fun,
we'll work it out.
Again,
we have some solution,
which is y of x.
So we want to find the y of x,
the path,
which minimizes the time between two known points.
And notice,
there's a theme here.
We're always talking about two known points
and asking for the trajectory or the function
which interpolates between those two points.
Okay,
let's find,
let's see if we can calculate the time that
it takes to go from one point to another.
First of all,
again,
we'll break up the trajectory into small little intervals.
Each interval has a distance which we've already calculated.
Here's the distance.
Alright,
so let's write that down again over here.
The distance ds is equal to dx times
the square root of one plus dy by dx,
the derivative squared.
Alright.
But on the other hand,
what is the speed of light?
The speed of light is the distance
that it goes divided by the time.
So each one of these little segments
will take a certain amount of time.
Alright.
The rule is that ds by
dt is equal to the velocity,
is equal to the speed.
Let's call that c.
But c is not a constant.
It depends on y.
I could also take it to depend on x,
but just for simplicity,
I'm imagining this material which
is a kind of layered material
with different speeds at different heights.
So c is a function of y.
Well,
that allows me now to determine how long
the light ray spins in each little interval dx.
Alright.
We just solve for dt.
So dt is equal to
ds divided by c of y.
All I've done is solve for dt.
Multiply by dt and divide by c of y.
Okay.
So that's how much time the light ray takes
to go from one point to a neighboring point
where they're separated by distance ds.
But now,
here's ds.
So we can also write this as dx
square root of 1 plus dy by dx squared,
all divided by c of y.
That's the time,
in terms of the function y of x,
remember now what we're doing.
We have some function y of x,
and we want to see how long
it takes light to go along that function.
dy by dx is just a derivative.
If I gave you a function,
you could differentiate it.
dx,
that's just a little x interval from here to here.
And c of y is the velocity
of light along the curve at height y.
What's the total time that it
takes to get from here to here?
We add up all these little line,
all these little intervals of time.
We add them up,
which obviously means we do an integral.
And so the total time between 1 and 2,
let's call it t12,
is equal to the integral dx from the
starting point x1 to the end point x2,
start to end,
of,
here it is,
square root of 1.
1 plus dy by dx squared
divided by c of y.
If I told you what c of y was,
and I gave you the function y of x,
we could determine how long it takes the
light rate to go from here to here.
Now that doesn't solve our problem.
That just sets up our problem.
It tells us for every curve y of x,
how long it takes to
go from point 1 to 2.
Then our problem is to find
the curve which minimizes the time.
That's obviously harder.
Alright?
So find the curve.
Search through all possible curves
that you could search through,
and find out what curve minimizes the time.
I'll give you another example.
Some other examples where,
for one reason or another,
you might want to minimize something
with respect to an entire function.
Well,
here's a famous example
that everybody who builds bridges knows about.
If you have a chain or
a cable or a string or whatever,
a weighted string,
a weighted string or a weighted cable
hung between two points,
you can see that the
length of the chain is fixed.
Now we're assuming that we
know the length of the chain.
The length of the chain is fixed.
We might ask,
what configuration does the chain take?
And the answer always is,
it minimizes the potential energy.
I'll just tell you that as a fact now.
It minimizes the potential energy.
That means effectively it gets
as low as it possibly can,
because the potential energy is just a function of height.
Potential energy increases as you go up.
It tries to get as low as it can.
Well,
it can't drop down through the floor,
because the chain has a fixed length.
This sort of configuration will not be terribly efficient,
because we can gain some,
or we can lower the potential energy in the middle
by letting it hang down deeper here.
So there's some curve,
some function,
of fixed length,
which minimizes the potential energy.
I'm not going to tell you what the function is,
I'm going to remember,
what is it?
It's a catenary,
right?
Yeah,
it's a catenary.
But if you ask me what a catenary is,
I can't remember.
Hmm?
Yeah.
So that's another example of a problem
in which you might want to minimize a certain function,
which depends on the whole curve,
you might want to minimize it
with respect to the curve itself.
What's the definition of the potential energy in that case?
Is it relative to the...
Oh,
it's just the height of each,
basically the height of each molecule.
You mean from the fixed points,
or...
It doesn't matter,
because,
because you can take it from the fixed points,
yeah.
But if you were to
change the zero of potential energy,
it would just add a constant,
and it wouldn't change the answer.
But right now,
I don't want to set up this problem.
All I wanted to do is show you some examples
where physics requires that you minimize something,
not with respect to a few variables,
but basically with respect to
an infinite number of variables,
the values of y at every point x.
The mathematics is called the calculus of variations.
It's the problem of minimizing a functional
with respect to a function.
The principle of least action is this kind of thing.
It is minimizing something that is defined
for the whole trajectory now,
trajectory of a mechanical system.
In other words,
a system...
Where did I write them?
Did I write them down here somewhere?
Yeah.
Okay.
Not one function,
but a whole collection of functions,
q1 of t,
q2 of t.
Remember what the q's are.
They're the generalized coordinates of a system.
q3 of t.
They're the whole collection of functions
which define a trajectory...
of a system.
Find the trajectory,
which means find the collection of functions,
q1 through q2,
q2n of t,
which minimize something.
What is it minimizing?
What is the quantity?
The quantity is called the action.
That's the principle of least action,
that there exists a quantity called an action,
which minimizing it with respect to the trajectory
is equivalent to the usual rules of mechanics.
In particular,
equivalent to Newton's laws of mechanics,
but is in many,
many situations far more efficient
and a far better tool
than just writing down Newton's equations.
So...
I'm sorry,
did you say there are
equivalent formulations of the same thing?
There are equivalent formulations of the same thing,
and which one is easier and
more useful depends on the system.
But believe me,
there are systems where the principle of least action
is a lot more efficient than...
In particular,
if I were to take this eraser,
which is composed of 10 to the 30th particles,
and I had to write down
all 10 to the 30th force laws
between all 3 times 10 to the 30th coordinates,
it would take me a long
time to write down those equations.
If I tell you,
on the other hand,
that the trajectory that this object takes
in moving through space and rotating
minimizes some action,
and that I know how to write down the action,
it is a much,
much more efficient tool for many purposes.
Intuitively,
for me,
it seems like the principle of least action
might apply to Newton's laws.
Yes.
But not necessarily the other direction.
Yeah.
That's...yeah.
That...
It implies Newton's laws in all cases
where Newton's laws would be the underlying description
or one underlying...
In any case where Newton's laws apply,
it is equivalent to Newton's laws.
But it's much more general.
It's more general.
For example,
it applies to problems in special relativity,
to the motion of objects in special relativity.
It applies to fields.
It applies to the electromagnetic field.
It applies to basically every classical problem in physics.
Not just motion of particles,
but motion of waves,
fields,
the whole works.
The principle of least action
is the most general formulation of mechanics
or of classical physics that we have.
So all systems in classical physics
that I can think of
have a formulation in terms
of the principle of least action.
Now,
if it's not particles,
but it's something more complicated,
the principle of least action might not...
You know,
we have to generalize it.
But the little steps,
and the little steps,
the little step we're taking now
is to think about trajectories for a system of particles.
Could you divide action?
No.
I wonder...
Not yet.
Yeah.
I remember a test where...
an exam where the problem was a frictionless block
sliding down a frictionless wedge on a frictionless table,
and I remember that most of the students spent...
three quarters of their test time
trying to write the force equation,
which was like an introductory physics class.
Right.
And the people that got that
in a reasonable amount of time
were the ones who applied conservation of energy
and equated it to...
Yeah.
...conservation of momentum.
But there are...
Yes,
yes.
And of course,
that is an example
of using more general principles.
But there are mechanical systems
where you wouldn't get too far with that either,
and where the more general principle of least action
would be the most efficient way to go about it.
All right.
So I will tell you
right now what the action is.
All right?
Now,
this action is going to seem bizarre.
It's going to seem strange.
It's going to be a little bit surprising.
But it's going to be a little bit more interesting.
But the final acid test
of whether it's the right action
is to test it out for all Newtonian problems
and see that the principle of least action
gives the same rules as Newton's equations.
All right?
Once we do that,
we will then have a reason to believe
that this is the right action.
So I'll tell you what it is.
It's an integral over the trajectory.
So it's...
It's now the independent variable is time,
not x.
The independent variable is time.
We have a whole bunch of q's of t,
or x's of t,
or whatever we like.
We calculate the kinetic energy
and the potential energy,
and we integrate it over time.
Integral...
of the kinetic energy,
which is what?
One half...
For an ordinary mechanical system
composed of ordinary particles.
Let's just...
Let's just think of it for one particle.
Well,
the simplest thing.
One particle in one dimension,
and then I'll tell you what the generalization is.
One particle moving up and down an axis.
All right?
So the problem then is to find x of t.
Find the curve,
or find the function x of t,
which minimizes a certain thing,
which I will now tell you what it is.
It's called the action.
You might expect...
If I tell you that it
has to do with the energies,
you might expect that it has
to do with the kinetic energy,
one half mv squared,
which is one half dx dt squared,
plus the potential energy...
integrated over time,
dt.
In other words,
at every point along the trajectory,
you might write down the...
the action
for a small interval of time
would be the total energy times dt.
Now,
this is wrong.
Bizarrely,
the answer is almost this,
but not quite.
Minus.
The kinetic energy minus the potential energy.
That's called the action.
Bizarre.
That's a good explanation.
The final...
In the final analysis,
whether you call this plus something or minus something
is of course a matter of definition.
You can...
You can redefine a new variable,
and you can call it w,
which is minus u,
and put in plus w here,
if you like.
But then...
Fine,
you can do that.
Then we have to find out
what the solution of the problem
of minimizing the trajectory
with respect to this thing
that you've written down is.
What you'll find is Newton's equations,
but you'll find Newton's equations
instead of finding the force being
minus w,
dw,
dx,
you'll find it plus dw,
and you'll find out that
the thing that you call w
is behaving like the negative of the potential energy.
So,
you can call it anything you want.
I will call it minus u of x here,
but this is the thing which is called the action.
Sometimes action is called i.
Sometimes it's called s.
I don't want to use s
because we've already used s for path length.
And sometimes it's called a for action.
This is the one case
where I will use a variable
which is linguistically or phonetically
or whatever the word is...
Sensible.
What I suggest is we
go through a bunch of examples.
I'm throwing something at you now,
and it is not easy to explain
where this comes from and why this is the answer.
The best thing to do,
I think,
is to examine it and find out
that it is the same as Newton's equations.
And then we can go back and say,
why did it have to
be this to get Newton's equations?
I'd rather not try to motivate it at this point
than just examine it and see what we get.
So let's hold in suspension our questions
about why this is the right thing.
But let me notice some things about it.
First of all,
let's compare it
with the principle of least distance
or the principle of least time.
The principle of least time also had integrals.
Now,
in those cases,
I used x as the integral.
So I used x as the independent variable,
and y as the dependent variable.
Now I'm using time as the independent variable
and x as the dependent variable.
So I've pulled a switch on you of notation.
The independent variable,
which is like x
in the previous example,
is now t.
Instead of trying to calculate y of x,
I'm trying to calculate x of t.
So the dependent variable is x,
the independent variable is t,
but let's just compare it
with the principle of least distance,
for example,
or the principle of least time.
The principle of least distance told us to compute
1 plus dy by dx squared,
integrated dx.
If we wanted the principle of least time,
the optical principle,
we would also throw in here
a 1 over c of...
of x,
I guess.
y,
sorry.
All right.
First of all,
the thing which I'm computing here depends on two things.
It depends on y of x,
and it depends on dy by dx.
All right?
So it depends on the function
and the derivative of the function with respect to the...
independent variable.
That's also true here.
This depends on the function,
x of t,
and also on the first derivative of the function
with respect to the independent variable.
So it has the same kind of depend...
It doesn't have a square root in it,
but still,
the thing in the...
in the integrand here depends both on the first derivative
of the function and the function itself.
It depends on y of x,
and it depends on dy by dx.
Likewise here,
it depends on x of t
through the function u,
and on dx by dt.
So it's a similar kind of thing.
It's an integral along the independent variable
from one time to another,
and we will also put in an assumption
which is very similar to what we put in
in the principle of least time,
namely,
we said that the integral is between two fixed points
which we don't vary.
We hold the two points fixed,
and we ask what's the trajectory
which takes the least time between these.
Likewise,
in the principle of least action,
we assume that we know what x
at the beginning of the trajectory is,
let's call that t0,
and x at the end of the trajectory.
t1,
given,
not to be changed.
So it's a trajectory between
two points in space and time.
If you like,
well,
you can see what the analogy is.
As I said,
the basic idea is
instead of giving the position and velocity,
you're giving the position at two distinct times.
Find the trajectory which minimizes
this integral of the kinetic energy
minus the potential energy.
That's very surprising.
It's even still surprising to me
after 40 years of having studied this,
more than 40 years,
and I know the reason why it is,
I'm still always surprised
that it's the kinetic energy minus the potential energy.
So you should also be surprised
that it's the kinetic minus the potential,
but it is.
That's the action.
The thing in the integral here,
the integrand,
is called the Lagrangian.
The kinetic energy minus the potential energy
And in a general form,
a script L,
it's a function
of all of the q's,
it's a function of the q of t's
and the q dots of t's.
And you can use it to calculate
So the velocity of the energy
is always the integral over time
from the beginning of the trajectory
to the end of the trajectory.
The integrand depends on the coordinates,
x,
and the velocities,
x dot,
or q and q dot.
That's the most general version
of the principle of least action,
namely that there exists something,
here's the law of physics,
the law of physics says that for every mechanical system
there exists a quantity called the Lagrangian,
out of which you build the action,
and then you find the path,
or the trajectory,
which minimizes that action.
In simple cases,
in fact in all cases that correspond
to Newtonian physics of one kind or another,
this Lagrangian is always
the difference between the kinetic energy
and the potential energy.
In more general systems,
which don't have a Newtonian analog,
this Lagrangian may well be something
totally different and peculiar,
but it will still depend on q and q dot,
and the principle of least action,
will be more fundamental than any kind of
Newtonian laws of physics.
In particular,
this is a Newtonian rule,
the motion of a particle
in the special theory of relativity
is quite different than this,
but it still has this form.
Okay?
So,
what we're going to have to do next time,
we won't do it tonight,
is learn how to find,
given a Lagrangian,
and given an action like this,
how do we convert the rule
of the principle of least action
into equations of motion
that look like Newtonian equations of motion?
How do we go back and forth
from a Lagrangian to Newton's equations of motion?
And if it's not Newton's equations of motion,
what are the equations of motion
that follow from a given Lagrangian?
Notice that this,
if we knew how to do this,
if we knew how to solve such problems,
we would solve,
among other problems,
by the same rules,
the optical problem of finding the path of least time.
So there's a close analogy between optics
and classical mechanics.
Principle of least action in mechanics,
principle of least time in optics,
but the methods,
the techniques,
are exactly the same.
So the next time we'll work out
what are the equations of motion
which follow from a particular action principle.
The preceding program is copyrighted
by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.