This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
We're going to plunge deeply,
deeply,
deeply into the Hamiltonian method of mechanics,
not quantum mechanics.
We've studied the Lebrangian method.
We've studied the principle of least action.
We've even gone to the
extremely advanced study of Newton's equations.
Tonight is Hamilton's night.
Part of the point,
in fact maybe the main point,
of the Hamiltonian formulation of mechanics
goes back to something that I talked about earlier.
I talked about it at the very first lecture.
We talked about the basic structure of classical thinking,
classical mechanics,
but not classical
mechanics quite,
but something even a little more primitive.
We talked about discrete systems,
the coin,
which could either be heads or tails.
That's a two-state system,
two simple states.
Then we talked about possible laws of evolution.
One simple law of evolution is nothing happens.
Evolution now might mean a sequence of
states separated by a small time interval,
a discrete
time interval,
a tenth of a second or whatever.
We update every tenth of a second.
Then we spoke about a simple law of nature,
which was a simple law of coin flipping or
coin changing,
which would be no change at all.
Here.
Without doing anything.
That's a simple law of evolution.
Another less simple law of evolution is if it heads,
then the next time it's tails.
If it's tails,
the next time it's heads.
Tails,
heads,
tails,
heads.
Both of these rules have the feature that if
you know the state of the system in any
instant of time,
you know it at the next instant of time.
In other words,
the updating rule is precise.
But also,
the backdating rule is also precise.
If you know where you are in any instant,
you know where you were.
We even talked about the
general structure of such simple theories.
Instead of just two states,
we could imagine a system with many states.
We could imagine a system with many states.
Each one being represented by a point in a space.
We might as well now call that space phase space.
It's the phase space of a simple discrete system.
In this case,
it's got one,
two,
three,
four,
five,
six.
If I stop there with only six states,
then we could be talking about a die.
A die isn't dice.
Six possible configurations.
All right.
Add two more.
I don't know.
We could be talking.
What system has eight states?
Three pennies.
Three coins.
Precisely.
So this is a general kind of situation.
And the basic setup,
in fact,
the definition of a phase space
is if you know where you
are in the system,
you know where you are in the space.
You know where you'll be next.
And you know where you came from.
So there's a rule which could be represented
simply by a set of arrows which tells you
where to go next.
Oh,
look,
you can't come back because you've already been there.
Here.
And then back to here.
For example,
you can have other kinds of laws.
Not different than in kind,
but different in type.
And different in detail.
For example,
you could have some closed loops like this.
So,
wherever you are,
you go to the next place.
But now there's some closed sort of
cycles so that if you're on this cycle,
you will
stay there.
And if you're on this cycle,
you will stay there.
This corresponds to the existence of a conservation law.
We can imagine that these three states
over here are labeled as having property equal
to plus one.
And over here,
property,
the same property,
minus one.
Well,
if you've got plus one,
you stay plus one.
Plus one never becomes minus one.
And minus one never becomes plus one because
all of the configurations with the state of
number minus one go to configurations
with number minus one and so forth.
But both of these kinds of laws have
the property that if you know where you are,
you know where
you'll be.
And you know where you are.
That's to be contrasted with a
law which might look something like this.
If you're over here,
you go to here.
And if you're over here,
That's a very definite updating rule.
Wherever you are,
you know where to go next.
But there's something funny about it.
Namely,
in particular,
you can't go backward in a unique way.
You can go backward from this point.
From this point,
you know that you must have come from here.
But if you're over here,
you don't know whether you came
from here or whether you came from
here.
What's going on here is point-based.
And the points are running into each other.
There's yet another way to think of it.
Imagine the phase space being populated.
Populated with points.
And the point,
in fact,
let's imagine the entire phase
space is populated with red dots.
And the red dots all move.
They do a dance.
The dance is simply to follow the
trajectories as they're prescribed by the law,
whatever
the law is.
So this red dot goes to here.
This red dot goes to here.
Notice,
every red dot knows where to go,
knows where to come from.
And there's a kind of rigidity to the red dots.
None disappear,
none spontaneously appear.
none appear.
They simply just rigidly or what's
an even better word than rigidly?
A fluid,
an incompressible.
A kind of incompressible motion where
points don't run into each other.
Same thing here.
If we populate the point.
points with red dots and we allow them to move
along the arrows
instant by instant by instant
each instant
the number of red dots is the same
they don't run into each other
they don't bifurcate
the whole thing just moves in an incompressible way
on the other hand with this law
we could start a red point
at each place
twice
but then after one motion
this one would have disappeared,
never to reappear
and we would have only two places which were occupied
going back and forth back and forth
there would be some loss in a sense
of points
in the phase space
phase space points would not be conserved
the whole point of Hamilton's mechanics
Hamilton's form of mechanics
is number one,
it's a form in which every point
knows where to go next
and knows where it came from
without points ever being lost or gained
in other words a kind of
rigid motion in a phase space
or an incompressible motion
of the points in phase space
which may also be considered a form of motion
but it can also be called information conservation
we'll see,
we'll talk about that
a little bit further in the future
okay,
another point of Hamilton's equations
let's think about ordinary F equals M A type equations
they're not of this form
why not?
well,
let's suppose you know where you are
let's make a plot
here's the positions of a particle
possible positions of a particle
here's the particle x,
y,
and z
supposing I know the particle is over here
do I know where it will be next?
no,
I need to know something else
I need to know not only where it is now
but I need to know
where it was an instant back
in other words,
I need to know the position and the velocity
knowing the position and the velocity of the
particle is a very important part of the equation
the velocity is the same thing
as knowing the position and the instant
and knowing the position a slight bit earlier
so I need two pieces of information
I need to know where the object is
and I also need a
kind of ghost piece of information
which is where it was an instant ago
and that's enough to tell
me where it will be next
next means after a short prescribed period of time
so specifying the locations of a system
by now we can simply call
them the cues of a system
does not constitute a phase space
the phase space constitutes everything you need to know
in order to tell where you'll be next
but in such a way that
there's a rigidity to the motion
a rigidity to the motion
points never gained nor lost
that's what phase space is
phase space is a way of
representing the configurations of a mechanical system
so that the motions are described
much as I've described these discrete motions
we'll come back to it in detail
may I ask a question here before we move on?
yeah
and I wonder if you can
talk about what some of the
insights or pressures or motivations were
for this reformulation of Newtonian mechanics
well
yeah I think
the Lagrangian formulation was formulated
by people for practical reasons
the practical reasons being
most systems were awfully complicated
and difficult to apply if people's M.A.
and so a more general formulation
which was not dependent on particular sets of coordinates
in many many contexts
rectilinear coordinates are simply
not appropriate for a problem
components of vectors are not appropriate to a problem
or not particularly useful
motion,
for example
motion of a particle on the flat blackboard
can be nicely described by X's and Y's
and we can use X and Y components
and write F equals M.A.
motion on the surface of a sphere
an object moving around on the surface of a sphere
it's not natural in any
special sense to introduce rectangular coordinates
you can't introduce rectangular coordinates onto the sphere
you can introduce coordinates
latitude and longitude
but you can't introduce rectangular coordinates
and the naive idea of components
the naive idea of components
rectangular Cartesian coordinates is not useful
so it's more useful to define mechanics in a
way that doesn't depend on any specific set of coordinates
that was the that was Lagrange's motivation
what Hamilton was smoking I don't know
but what he developed was an
extremely beautiful elegant formulation of mechanics
which turned out which I don't
think he ever really used for anything
he simply admired it
and physicists admired it afterwards
it turned out to be very useful
part of the usefulness of it
was because it does conserve information in
the same sense that I described over here
I'm sure he was aware of that
but I don't know if
it was foremost in his mind
but ultimately
the real power of it
came when quantum mechanics was developed
so
it's hard for me to put myself in Hamilton's position
I mean it was one of these brilliant mathematical insights
that kind of came from nowhere
just
somehow he saw the structures there
in ways that I think
most of us would not have
and so no I can't really give you
his intuitions
what we can do is do it
and after we've done it
go out back and talk about why it's so useful
and why it's of such power
I'm not particularly sure that anybody
realized how powerful and useful it was
until quantum mechanics was developed
I think that really was the
time when people first really began
feeling they had to learn what Hamilton had to say
because he was long dead by that time
alright
another way
another observation about it
is
it takes
a certain number of second order differential equations
F equals m a is a second order differential equation
for each component
second order means that it involves second derivatives
not first derivatives but second derivatives
so it may also involve
a first derivative here and there
but it contains second derivatives
it contains accelerations
second derivatives with respect to time or something
how many equations are there?
well if there are a certain number of particles
in a certain number of dimensions
that tells you how many equations there are
one particle there are three equations
two particles there are six equations
and so forth
each one being a second order differential equation
what Hamilton's equations are in general
you can always take a
system of second order differential equations
let's say n of them
and replace them by twice as many first order equations
that only contain first derivatives
it's very easy
it's so easy it's almost stupid
so let's discuss
how you take n second order equations
and how you take n of them
the method is completely general
but I'll just illustrate it for Newton's equations
supposing we have a certain
number of equations of the form
derivative,
second derivative
of some i-th component of x
by dt squared
is equal to the i-th component of force
divided by the mass
I've written acceleration is equal to f
over n
I don't know why exactly
I just wanted to write the
acceleration on the left hand side
let's suppose now that there
are n such differential equations
let's take that and make two n equations
each of which only contains a first time derivative
to do that first of all define
now we can do it many ways
but I'm going to do it
in a particular way that will be
in order to get familiar
with the terminology
first of all let's define
the x i by dt
and let's throw in a factor of the mass
the mass of the i-th
that's one mass
everybody has the same mass
let's take n times the x sub i by dt
and give it a name
what do we call it?
we call it p sub i
now
let's write
I don't know why I
put m on the left hand
on the right hand side of the equation
why did I do that?
let's put it backwards and wrongs
f equals m a
now let's write f equals m a
in the form
m i
in fact let's just make one m
alright now let's take
this is of course a first order equation
it only contains first time derivatives
but now let's write f equals m a
in the form dp by dt
is equal to f i i
both of these equations
are only first order equations
but there are twice as many of them
there are twice as many equations
but each one only contains first time derivatives
they become a 2n
a system of 2n differential equations
for twice as many variables
and now what are the twice as many variables?
x sub i
and p sub i
first order equations are the kind which tell you
where to go
if you know where you are
without knowing where you were
a first order equation tells you
how to update to the next position
if you know where you are
but knowing where you are now
means knowing where you are in the phase space
it's equivalent to the old view
you again need to know two things
a position and something equivalent to a velocity
but it's just a different mindset
thinking about the phase space
gives you a picture
x and p
in which wherever you are
you know where to go next
so there's no new form of this equation
no new physics in it
no new laws of nature
just a different mindset
thinking about the state of a system
not as a configuration
but as a combination of a position and a momentum
or not just one position and momentum
but a position and a momentum
for each degree of freedom
for each coordinate
more generally of course we would talk about
q's and p's or q's and pi's
I think I'm going to give up the notation pi
I get that
we'll just call canonical momentum p's
and be done with it
but those are the various
motivations,
various properties
of the Hamiltonian description
it's the equation of
the Hamiltonian description of mechanics
is the equations
for how things move around on a phase space
knowing where you are
they tell you where you move next
in fact you can almost think of it
just as
did I erase what I had to do?
yeah I did erase what I had to do
we have it but let's put it back
we
the thought of a law
as being a kind of flow
a flow of the points in phase space
we're going to see
that there's a natural sense
in which mechanics constitutes
a flow in the phase space
wherever you are
you know where to go next
and if you were to imagine
a populating the phase space
populating the phase space
would mean taking a lot of identical systems
and starting each one
at a different point in the phase space
and watching them as they evolve
that would define a flow in the phase space
and it's that flow in the phase space
that Hamiltonian mechanics is all about
it's almost as if
the points in phase space were all the same
they're all kind of fluid
and we're studying how that fluid moves
if we're interested in any specific system
then we think of it
as a little particle moving along with the flow
we start at some place
we allow it to move along with the flow
and follow its coordinates and its momentum
alright now we need a small piece of mathematics
it's an easy piece of mathematics
but it's a rather formal piece
ありがとうございました
It's the mathematics that's
called the Legendre transformation.
We'll do it first in the simplest possible case.
Suppose there are two variables.
Let me call them V and P.
Just secretly,
between you and me,
V stands for velocity and P stands for momentum.
But now forget I told you that because we're going to
think about the Legendre transformation as a mathematical trick in many,
many different contexts.
There are two variables.
And let's suppose...
Whoops.
It's a funny P,
isn't it?
V and P.
But they're not independent variables.
In fact,
there's really only one variable.
They're functions of each other.
They're functions of each other,
and for simplicity...
Not for simplicity.
This is important.
Let's suppose they're single-valued functions of each other.
Single-valued function means that if you know P,
you know V,
and if you know V,
you know P.
No ambiguity.
That means the graph of P versus V...
Looks something like that.
What it can't do is
it's not allowed to do that.
Why not?
Because if it did this,
there would be certain values of P where
you would have an ambiguity about what V is.
It's also not allowed to do this.
Because then there would be certain values of
V where you wouldn't know what P was.
Single-valued means that the graph of...
Function P versus V looks like this.
Any point on it,
or for any value of V,
is a unique P.
And for any value of P,
is a unique V.
Actually,
just for simplicity,
although this is not important,
let's just draw the graph so
that it goes to the origin.
Okay.
Then if we have such a single-valued function,
not just a single-valued function,
but a one-to-one function,
meaning it's single-valued whether you think about it as P as
a function of V or V as a function of P,
then it's possible to invent a pair of functions,
one which I'll call L,
and one which I'll call P.
Secretly the Lagrangian.
And the Lagrangian is a function of V.
And it has the property
that the derivative of the Lagrangian,
with respect to V,
defines P.
P.
Why would I bother inventing a function L
L
whose derivative with respect to V is P?
Well,
I'll come to Y.
But I can always do it.
This is just ordinary derivative for the moment.
This is only one variable V.
We don't have to make it a partial derivative.
D L by D V.
We're going to find that,
given L,
we're going to find that,
we can construct a symmetrically related function
that we're going to call H.
H is to be regarded as a function of P.
When we think about L,
we will think about V as the independent variable.
When we think about H,
we will think about P as the independent variable.
Of course,
L is also a function of P
because V is a function of P.
Of course,
H is also a function of V,
because P is a function of P.
But each one is thought of
as a function of its own variable,
L of V or H of P.
And the relationship is,
H and L are connected by the derivative
of H with respect to P is V.
This is a completely symmetrical relation between P and V
and between L and H.
So,
this is a very,
very similar relationship.
The derivative with respect to V of L is P.
The derivative of P of H is V.
Now,
let me show you why that's always possible to do
and to show you the relationship between L and H.
Okay,
let's take our function,
which the simplicity I just had passed through the origin,
but you can work it out whether
it passes through the origin or not.
Notice the derivative of L with
respect to V is equal to P.
Think of that as P as a function of V,
of course.
V is the independent variable in the top equation.
So,
P is really a function of V,
as it is over here,
P of V.
Remember,
the P is a function of V.
I've just re-tried it already.
P of V.
We can also think of
V as a function of P.
And now,
we're going to do the same thing.
We're going to do the same thing over here.
Let's solve this equation for L
by just writing that L is equal
to the integral of P of V,
dV.
Does everybody recognize that?
If the derivative of L is P,
then L is the integral of P.
Okay?
We can write this as dL.
Does everybody recognize what I've done here?
Is that a definite and indefinite?
Okay.
That can be taken to be a definite integral.
And for definiteness,
let's take it to be the integral from 0.
But it doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter where we take the integral from,
but let's for definiteness take it from 0,
from V equals 0.
If we differentiate an integral,
then we get the integral from 0.
We just get the integrand.
So if we differentiate L with respect to,
let's put V up here,
definite integral from 0 to V,
P of V,
dV.
If you differentiate an integral
with respect to the endpoint
of integration,
you just get the integrand.
So that's this relationship here.
Derivative of L is equal to P.
We can always do this.
Here,
that's L of the endpoint.
If you like.
All right.
We can now draw a picture of what L means,
at least on this graph.
L is the area,
L of V,
or let's say L of V
is constructed in the following way.
You go to your point V,
and you draw that line,
and then you consider all the area.
Okay.
Underneath the curve here.
This is not a triangle,
it's a curve.
That's the integral of P of V,
dV,
and it's the L at point V.
L of V.
It has the property that if
you differentiate it with respect to V,
you get P.
Now,
what about H?
Well,
we can do the same thing with H.
H must be the integral of V,
dP,
just by symmetry.
The other equation is that
H of P is the integral,
we can again start at zero,
and go to P of V of P,
dP.
Notice that if we differentiate H with respect to P,
we just get the integral of V of P,
dP.
That's the other defining equation here,
derivative of H with respect
to P is equal to V.
All right,
so the geometry of that then,
is that H,
the area in here is H,
H of P.
And the area in here is L of V.
This is,
this is an integral,
yeah.
this area in here
is the integral of v of p dp
does that need further explanation?
well,
now we know the relationship between h and l
take h and add it to l
h plus l
is the area of this whole rectangle
what's the area of the rectangle?
it's p times v
this is usually written as
h is equal to pv minus l
but it's clearly the same thing
for some reason
we tend to write
we tend to think of l first
and then try to figure out what h is
alright,
so now let's write our system of equations
that are called a Legendre transformation
you start with an l of v
you differentiate l of v
ordinary derivative we'll do here
and then you write the equation of the triangle
derivative of l with respect to v
defines p
and gives you p as a function of v
then you construct h
by multiplying p times v
and subtracting l
now l of course is a function of v
but wherever you see v
substitute its value of l
in terms of p
so we can think of this as
l,
same script for branching
l of v
but v is a function of p
so,
v is also a function of p here
so h gets to be thought
of as a function of p
l is a function of v
and when we do this
we'll now prove,
I'll now prove
although it's clear from the geometry here
that the derivative of h
with respect to p is v
let's do a little manipulation algebraically
here's what we do
we consider a small change of p
and ask how much h changes
how much does h change when we change p
let's work it out
the change in h
let's just call it p
delta h
small change in h
is first of all
what's the change in a product
if we change
if we make a small change
in the values of some variables
what's the change in a product
it's the sum of two terms
the sum of two terms
one term being
the first factor times the change in the second
and vice versa
alright,
so first of all we get a term
which is p times the smaller value of p
the small change in v
the second term is v
plus the small change in p
and finally
minus
the derivative of a Lagrangian
the derivative of l
with respect to v
remember that l depends only on v
times the change in v
so we're going to have
v times the change in v
well wait a minute
I defined the l by dv
to be called p
that was
the way that I constructed p
from l
the l by dv
is equal to p
so what do I really have
the l by dv
I'm sorry I sometimes write partial derivatives
and sometimes total derivatives
it doesn't matter
there's only one variable
partial and total are the same
alright
so this thing is
はい
here I have pdv.
Here I have minus pdv.
So these two cancel completely.
These two are the same,
and therefore cancel.
Not the same,
but not the same.
And that just leaves the change in
h is v times the change in p.
That's the same thing as saying that
the h by dp is equal to v.
The h by dp is equal to v.
In other words,
the change in h,
when I change p a little bit,
is just equal to v.
Okay,
that is the Legendre transformation.
So l,
define dl,
dv to be p.
Then construct h,
which is pv minus l.
And now you have a reciprocal relationship.
Where the h by dp is equal to v.
So if we interchange l
and we interchange l and h,
and we also interchange p and v,
it's completely symmetric.
They're completely symmetrically related to each other.
This little demonstration over here is nothing
but the geometry of that rectangle being divided.
That's a mathematical construction.
Which is not only,
which is at the heart of many,
many things,
in particular,
mechanics,
but also thermodynamics.
Thermodynamics is just filled with
Legendre transformations all over the place.
And variables are related in pairs,
Legendre pairs.
Now what happens if there are many v's?
Instead of just one v,
supposing there are many of them.
Then the definitions go as follows.
The derivative of l with respect to the i,
v,
is the i,
p.
Now just keep,
you should probably remember what v is.
v is some velocity.
And in Hamiltonian,
sorry,
in Lagrangian mechanics,
keep in mind that the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to a velocity is a momentum.
This is just,
alright,
let's,
let's.
Okay.
Apply this to Lagrangian mechanics in a few minutes.
But this is not a new relationship for us.
Now of course we should use
partial derivatives because I'm imagining many variables.
Partial of l with respect to v sub i.
That's p sub i.
Definition at this point.
Okay.
Now we construct h of p.
Now of a series.
Now we have a single momentum
but of a collection of p's.
h of p meaning h of all of the p's.
And this becomes summation over all of the i's,
p sub i,
v sub i,
minus l.
This may start to look familiar to you.
Let's go through the same little derivation here.
Now,
the change in h is a
sum of terms of p sub i,
v sub i.
I'm not going to write summation signs.
Whenever I write a p sub i and
a v sub i like that and so forth,
think sum over the i's.
Alright,
so first of all,
a p sub i,
delta v sub i.
A v sub i,
delta p.
A p sub i.
And then a derivative of l with respect
to v sub i times delta v sub i.
When I change things a little bit,
this is what happens to h.
Again,
exactly the same pattern.
The l by d v sub i
is the same as p sub i.
So they cancel.
The things inside rate cancel.
And all I'm left with is that the
change in h is equal to the i-th.
The v variable times the
change in the i-th p variable.
From this,
you could easily read off that the derivative of h,
the partial derivative of h,
with respect to p sub i
is equal to v sub i.
In other words,
the change in h,
if you only change one of the p's,
say the third p,
the change in h,
if you change p sub 3 a little bit,
is just v sub 3,
keeping all the other p's fixed.
So the derivative of h with respect to
p sub i is just v sub i.
Okay,
so again,
same kind of reciprocity.
The l by d v
sub i is p sub i.
The h by d p
sub i is v sub i.
Completely symmetrically related to each other.
Now at the moment,
these are just abstract equations.
They're abstract variables.
Sometimes I've called one of them a momentum.
Sometimes I've called one of them a velocity.
But they could be just abstract variables.
And as I said,
there are many applications of the change of variables
from a v-type variable to a p-type variable
that's kept track of by what I usually call
generating functions,
l and h.
But our interest is in mechanics.
In mechanics,
the Lagrangian is not only a function of velocities.
It's also a function of positions.
We haven't talked about positions at all.
We have velocities here,
things I call v,
and we have things I call p.
The relationship between p's and v's and
Lagrangians and Hamiltonians is exactly what I've written.
But with the coordinates q,
just going along for the ride.
Just going along as if they,
as if you didn't care about them.
As if they were just passive.
So let me show you how the relationship between Hamiltonians and
Lagrangians is nothing but a Legendre transformation of the Zachariah's type.
With the extra added ingredient that there's some
more variables that go along for the ride.
Alright,
now we're doing mechanics.
We have a Lagrangian.
The Lagrangian is a function of what?
It's a function of the q-dots.
But let's call the q-dots v's.
Velocities,
generalized velocities,
v sub i.
q sub i dot is by definition v sub i.
So then the Lagrangian is a
function of the v's and the q's.
Don't confuse q's with p's.
v sub i is equal to q dot.
Let me write up here another
equation of mechanics that you're familiar with.
p sub i.
v sub i is the derivative of
the Lagrangian with respect to q dot.
Remember that?
The L by the q dot defines p.
But that's the same as saying the L by dv.
Uh huh.
The L by dv equals p sub i.
That's right.
The first of our equations over here.
So we start to see the Legendre transformation
between p's and velocities beginning to shape up.
And it's simply the definition of canonical momentum as
the derivative of Lagrangian with respect to q dot.
Next,
let's define the Hamiltonian.
I'm absolutely repeating myself now.
But I'm repeating myself in the language of mechanics.
Let's define the Hamiltonian h to
be the sum of p sub i.
p sub i what?
p sub i v sub i.
Usually we write p sub i q sub i dot.
Right?
That's the language that we've done previously.
But q sub i dot
is the derivative of q dot.
It's nothing but v sub i.
So let's put v sub i.
Minus Lagrangian.
That's precisely the same definition
that we had for the Hamiltonian,
I think,
in the last two lectures.
So,
you see,
we see the pattern shaping up.
But now let's calculate the small change in h.
When we change things.
What things?
We're going to change the p's and the q's.
What happens if we make
small changes in p's and q's?
How does the Hamiltonian change?
Let's calculate that.
You're taking the velocity to be
a function of p and q.
It is a function of p and q.
Generally,
that's right.
In general,
you can think of q as just going
along for a ride as a set of parameters.
Right.
So the velocity depends on the point p.
The whole thing.
Yeah.
That's right.
So that's correct.
Now,
what was said was correct.
Let me rephrase it.
Let me not rephrase it,
but let me just restate it.
Now,
the relationship between the p's and the v's is
such that p is a function not just of v,
but also the q's.
And v is a function
of the p's and the q's.
But you can simply think of the
q's as a function of the v's.
So you can think of the
q's as being parameters at this point,
which,
as I said,
go along for the ride for the moment.
The point is,
of course,
when you calculate the L by the v sub i,
in general,
it might contain some q
dependence and not just v dependence.
But that's okay.
Just pursue it.
Okay.
Let's calculate the change in h
when you change things a little bit.
Change things means change everything a little bit.
P's and q's.
All right.
The change in h.
Same thing as before.
First of all,
the sum,
which I won't write the summation sign.
P sub i delta v sub i
plus v sub i delta p sub i.
Now I have minus the derivative of the Lagrangian.
We have two things that the Lagrangian depends on.
Let's see which way I wrote it.
The L by the q
sub i delta q sub i.
And minus the L by the
v sub i delta v sub i.
Lagrangians depend on q's and v's.
And now we're varying everything in sight.
P's and q's.
You don't have to separately vary the velocities.
Because you know the velocities if
you know the p's and q's.
Okay.
So there we are.
That's the formula for changing h a little bit.
It has several terms.
P sub i delta v sub i.
v sub i delta p sub i.
Okay.
So we have the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to q times the change in q.
Derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to v delta v.
Okay.
It's a little bit complicated.
But fortunately big pieces of it just cancel.
Just as they did over here.
In fact,
the same rate cancellation takes place over here.
Remember that the L by the
v sub i is p sub i.
Here is p sub i.
Things in the red squares cancel again.
They're gone.
The other two terms can't cancel each other.
One involves delta p.
The other involves delta q.
Those are independent variations.
They can't cancel each other.
But what we can write down now is
that the derivative of the Hamiltonian with respect
respect for p sub i.
That's a small change in h
when you change p sub i a little bit,
keeping q sub i fixed.
The h by the p sub i,
keeping the q's fixed,
is just what?
What do you read off this?
v sub i.
And the h by the q sub i,
what's that?
What's this?
It's minus
dL by the q sub i.
So,
okay,
that's not bad.
It's nice equations.
But they get a little bit nice,
right?
Yeah.
要改變
dL by dv sub i,
right?
Well,
no,
sorry,
dL by dq sub i,
right?
That's it.
Do you remember Lagrange's equations?
dL by dq sub i,
what's that?
Okay,
let's write down Lagrange's equations over here.
d by dt
of dL by dq sub i
dot
is equal to dL by dq sub i.
That's Lagrange's equations.
What's dL by dq dot?
P.
So this is,
the left-hand side is P dot
i
is equal to dL by dq sub i.
That's all that says.
That the time derivative of the constant
of the canonical momentum is dL by dq.
Well,
let's look at what we have here.
We have dL by dq,
right?
That's just equal to minus P dot.
That's Lagrange's equations.
P dot is dL by dq.
So we have one equation.
Let's get rid of the middle man here.
We don't need him.
The H by dq
is minus the time derivative of P.
Well,
what is dI?
Q dot.
I'm going to go through this again.
I'm going to do it again.
Well,
these,
of course,
are Hamilton's equations.
They're quite beautiful.
H is a function of P's and Q's.
That's the way you think about it.
The Hamiltonian is a function of P's and Q's,
momenta and coordinates.
You get rid of the velocities.
You replace them by P's.
And then the derivative of the Hamiltonian
with respect to P's defines the Q dots.
And the derivative of the Hamiltonian
with respect to Q's is minus the P dots.
That's the story of the Hamiltonian.
So you can see the structure of mechanics
in the Hamiltonian nutshell,
if you like.
Let's go through it again,
just since it was a series of steps,
all of which are abstract,
none of which are highly intuitive.
Let's go through it again.
Here we have H is
equal to summation P sub i,
V sub i,
minus L.
L being a function of Q and V.
Now let's make a little variation.
That's going to be equal
P sub i delta V sub i
of V sub i delta P sub i
minus
the change in the Lagrangian.
What's that?
Oh,
sorry,
excuse me.
Minus V sub i delta P sub i.
But now we have to calculate
the change in L.
The change in L
is minus the derivative of L
with respect to whatever it depends on.
But it depends on Q's,
delta Q's,
and it depends on V's.
Everybody gets an i.
And there should be a summation sign
which I'm too lazy to write.
Okay,
now,
first of all,
what cancels?
The things multiplying
delta V cancel.
Why?
Here you have P sub i,
and here,
sorry,
did I say that right?
Yes?
Yeah.
Um...
That's it.
P sub i.
Yeah.
The L by D V sub i,
that's P sub i.
Definition of P sub i.
نهاية
الدرس
That's how we define canonical momentum.
Gone,
gone.
And then we look at what's left over
and we see that the derivative of
h with respect to p sub i
is v sub i
but v sub i is q dot.
Then we look at the other one
that says the derivative of h
with respect to
q sub i
is equal to minus the
l by the q sub i,
minus
but then we use Lagrange's equations.
The l by the q sub i
is d by dt
of p sub i.
That's Lagrange's equation.
Or just minus p dot.
So we see that mechanics
in great generality
gets repackaged
as a system of first order equations
of very great simplicity.
You need to know one function of p's and q's.
Knowing that function of p's
and q's immediately by differentiation
tells you
how the point moves through phase space.
It tells you the velocity through phase space.
So here's the next part.
Q dot,
of course,
is just the ordinary velocity,
but the combination Q dot and P dot,
let's put the sign on the other side over here.
The combination Q dot and P dot
is a kind of velocity through the phase space.
It tells you if you know P and Q,
you plug it in to H,
calculate the H dP,
the H dQ.
If you know P and Q,
then you immediately know P dot and Q dot.
So it reduces mechanics from
the system of first-order equations
for P's and Q's.
Every P has a partner called Q.
Every Q has a partner called P.
They come in pairs.
And the Hamilton equations are two for each I.
A pair of equations for each I.
Let's do it,
just for simplicity,
for...
for F equals M.A.
Let's just check that it really is correct
As I said,
I have no idea what motivated Hamilton
to write these things down,
but they certainly do have a very,
very simple structure.
And one of the things they show you
is that suppose you have a P,
we have a Driver's function.
But surprisingly,
with very,
very different physical
interpretation,
P's and Q's seem to be very,
very different things.
Q's in our coordinates,
P's are velocities,
connected to velocities,
and yet,
there's this enormous symmetry between P's and Q's.
they seem to come into the equations
in an extremely parallel and symmetric way,
apart from a single minus sign over here.
They seem to enter in a symmetric way into mechanics.
Now,
it's the study of these
equations which really defines modern mechanics,
modern classical mechanics.
Let's draw a picture to indicate what's going on.
Here's general phase space,
P and Q.
It's not just one variable,
there's many variables.
Some subset are called P's,
half of them are called P's,
half of them are called Q's.
I can't draw them all on the blackboard,
so I'll draw just one P and one Q.
At every point,
where's my equations?
Here they are.
At every point,
I could calculate the H by
P and the H by PQ
and tell you exactly what
Q dot and P dot are.
That defines a kind of
velocity vector through the phase space.
Not an ordinary velocity,
but a phase space velocity.
Let's draw that phase space velocity as an arrow.
It's showing which way that point
is moving in the phase space.
And the length of the arrow we can take
to represent how fast you're moving through the phase space.
And so what the Hamiltonian gives you is
a kind of flow through the phase space.
Where the arrows are long,
you're moving fast.
Where the arrows are small,
you move slowly.
And the velocity,
as I said,
is related to derivatives.
Notice one funny thing.
That the Q velocity is a P derivative
and the P velocity is minus a Q derivative.
So it's not that Q dot is the derivative of H with respect
to Q and P dot is the derivative of H with respect to P.
They get crossed here.
They get crossed in the equations.
That has a profound implication
as we'll see in a moment.
Any questions about Hamilton's equations?
Up the mountain.
Any second order system?
Any second order system can always be.
Just by defining the first derivatives to be new variables.
Then that simply defines a set
of twice as many first order equations.
That's trivial.
But this elegant structure.
This structure here is far more than that.
It has some properties that we'll see in a moment.
Yeah.
Are there any systems where P and
B are not one to one relationships?
When it happens,
they usually badly define systems for
which the evolution is not well defined.
And usually rejected as being.
You mean are there any systems in nature which require?
No.
We don't have any systems.
Circular systems with friction.
Doesn't that be slowly?
Well,
first of all,
friction is outside the boundaries
of Lebrangian and Hamiltonian mechanics.
Now,
not really because all systems
in nature are of this type.
And friction is a part of nature.
But as I've emphasized over and over again,
you don't really see friction in
a system unless you ignore a large,
large number of coordinates.
Friction is simply the excitation and the moving around
of microscopic coordinates that you don't keep track of.
So,
yeah.
Let me see.
I'm trying to think.
Are there any systems that I can
think of where you can't invert the system?
The relation between coordinates and momentum.
Yeah,
I can think of one.
No,
I can't think of any.
I'm sorry.
I was going to say something else.
No,
I can't think of any offhand that make physical sense.
We'll talk about why and talk about
the importance of this one-to-one sort of law.
How about the Fallen and Terminal Velocity?
What?
No,
that's friction.
That's friction.
What's happening is,
right.
You cannot write equations with friction in this form.
Friction outside the boundaries of this formulation.
In the sense that if you wrote the
equations that you normally write down for friction,
they won't be of this form.
If you write the equations governing all of the molecules,
every single one of them
and keep track of them all,
then there's simply a huge number
of equations which do have this form.
So introducing friction is a way of approximating a very,
very large number of equations of
this form by a very small number of equations
and ignoring the motion of most of the degrees
of freedom.
Energy is leaking off into other degrees of freedom.
Okay.
So friction we don't want to deal with now.
No.
Friction is exceedingly complicated.
If we define H as that lower left-hand corner.
Yes.
And then take the delta H.
And we apply the,
equate the oil of Lagrange equations.
Then we get how many of these equations?
That's correct.
Okay.
Now,
but that's,
but where is this Le Genre thing coming in here?
I mean,
what I,
I mean.
Well,
here,
we did the L by dv is P.
Okay.
And the H by the…
Here,
this is the Lagrange and transformation.
What is the,
what is the equation,
is it the,
is it the right hand side,
is it the?
It's taking a fun,
it's taking a function of V,
or what is it?
It's a procedure.
It's a procedure of changing the function of,
of the rotation,
right?
changing variables
changing variables for the set called the
it's
except for
was on the transmission of the whole bunch of arithmetic
if you like
this is the clearest definition of
so
you have a pair of variables the mp
the connect to each other
if they're connected in one-to-one way
then you can
find a lovely
and he should be
elvi
the world under this curve
out this week
h of p is the integral over this curve
up to p
the rebel l with respect to speak
the river of our
age with respect to
he
he has the
is a little bit
that's the simple geometry
why is it so useful
you get used to it that you were you do
it over and over again to get to see why it's
useful
but though
what i would suggest we just go with it
and we will find out just how useful it is
there's no use of it
they're all
there
and
by
it's
not
uh...
output
position
here April
Can you identify a typical situation
of a grump that's not bad?
Sure enough.
Oh,
okay.
We could write down some Lagrangians and Hamiltonians which
are bad and try to see why they're bad.
I think that's a good thing to do.
I'm not going to do it tonight.
Somebody send me an email.
Just send me an email
saying write down some bad systems.
And we'll write down some examples when things don't work out well
and try to follow them and see where the motion breaks down.
See what happens to the motion,
how it tells you.
All of a sudden you
don't know which way to go.
It usually means at some point
the equation of motion simply is singular.
There's some infinity in it.
And something breaks down that
doesn't tell you where to go.
Something in the equation comes into it.
As a general rule.
Presumably it means that your
physics is wrong at some point.
I think it usually,
it always means your physics is wrong.
Yeah.
I know at least one example where
it means something can travel with infinite velocity.
All kinds of things can go wrong.
But I think it's a good idea
to take an example or two which,
where you cannot invert the relationship between velocity
and momentum and see exactly what goes wrong.
And I will do that.
I will do that for you.
Send me an email message,
we can do it.
A strange question.
Why is it ok to have an infinite
number of degrees of freedom in quantum mechanics when
we're frightened of many degrees of freedom in friction?
It's not...
Well,
first of all we can have infinite
number of degrees of freedom in classical mechanics.
Infinite doesn't have to do with the
difference between quantum mechanics and classical mechanics.
A field has an infinite number of degrees of freedom.
Are we frightened of it?
It can get pretty frightening.
Having a field can lead to friction,
for example.
An electron accelerating radiates.
It radiates photons.
The radiation of those photons tend
to act like a kind of friction.
And it can get very,
very complicated to follow the motion of an electron,
including radiation reactions and so forth.
Why are we afraid?
We're not afraid of the many degrees of freedom.
We just have to remember that they're there.
I think you're asking me why it's so terribly difficult
to derive the laws of friction from the laws of mechanics.
Well,
that is hard.
But it's also hard to
derive the laws of radiation reaction.
It is hard to derive the laws of friction.
But that's not for tonight,
in any case.
For tonight,
we want to discuss energy conservation,
among other things.
We've already discussed energy conservation several times.
But it's interesting.
It's interesting to see how these equations,
from the present perspective,
these now become the equations of mechanics.
This is a new formulation of mechanics
based on H of P and Q.
Given an H of P and Q,
you now have a phase space.
You have a motion through the phase space.
You can imagine dots in the phase space.
A fluid of points in the phase space moving each point
with a velocity that depends on its position according to these equations.
And so it's a flow of a fluid.
And it's simply a new way of formulating mechanics.
Let's forget about all the old ways.
Oh,
I said I would work that
out for you for the ordinary particle.
Let's do that first.
Ordinary particle,
again,
one half m d squared.
Minus u of x.
That's the Lagrangian.
One half m x dot squared.
Now I've replaced Q by x.
We've done this before.
I just want to check these equations.
So what is the hand of comedy?
We've done that before.
Everybody remember that it's p squared
over 2m plus u of x?
p squared over 2m plus
u of x is the Hamiltonian.
Let's just check Hamilton's equations.
The h by dp,
differentiate that.
That's p over m.
That's what it is.
Is p over m equal to Q dot?
Or in other words,
is it equal to x dot?
Yes,
it is.
m x dot is equal to p.
So the first of Hamilton's equations,
the h by dp is equal to Q dot.
That's nothing but the definition
of momentum in terms of velocity.
And what about the other equation?
The h by dx minus the
h by dx should equal p dot.
The h by dx,
that's just the u by dx.
Minus the u by dx.
That's equal to p dot.
Well,
that's just Newton's equations.
Mass times acceleration is equal to force.
So the second equation,
typically the way it works,
is the first equation is
the relationship between velocity and momentum.
Okay.
It's just p over m equals
x dot in the sequence here.
It's the second equation which really
looks more like f equals m a.
This is mass times acceleration.
And this is force.
Okay.
So it does work.
It is correct.
It is true.
And it is equivalent to all the other formulations.
ありがとうございました。
we could work out some more complicated examples,
and maybe we will.
ありがとうございました
first let's concentrate on,
in this new form,
let's concentrate on energy conservation.
Let's see if we can
prove directly that energy is conserved.
Let's calculate the H dt.
Time derivative of the Hamiltonian.
If the Hamiltonian is energy,
which it is,
then it should be conserved.
Its time derivative should be zero.
Let's calculate it.
It's equal to the derivative of H with respect to P times P
dot plus the derivative of H with respect to Q times Q dot.
Sum number I.
The change in H when you change P times P
dot plus the change in H when you change Q.
That's the change in the Hamiltonian per unit time.
But now let's use Hamilton's equations
for P dot and Q dot.
What is P dot?
P dot,
this is equal to the sum I,
the H by the P sub I.
That's this.
But what is P sub I dot?
Can somebody read it to me?
It's just a sign that I don't remember.
That's minus.
So minus the H by the Q.
Right?
And how about this one?
This is plus the H by the Q.
The H by the P sub I.
And they cancel.
That's what the minus sign is doing there.
Is that equation if and only if,
so if we have the conservation of energy,
we get balance equations?
I think it's possible to imagine equations which have a
conservation of energy which are not of the Hamilton form.
If you have Hamilton's equations,
with a time independent Hamiltonian,
I've assumed the time,
I've assumed there's no explicit
dependence on the Hamiltonian time.
Then you do get energy conservation.
The other way,
no.
I think you can.
No,
you can certainly have
equations which have conservation laws,
conservation of an energy,
without them being of Hamilton's form.
So it's not if and only if.
All right,
so we see that these
two terms simply cancel each other.
And energy conservation is a very,
very simple equation.
It's a very simple consequence of Hamilton's equations.
It's kind of interesting.
What this says is that if you
take a point and you follow it.
Now,
from now on,
I want you to think about this phase space as
a collection of points that you can follow in time.
As you follow them in time,
you stay on a contour of constant energy.
Imagine the space space.
And imagine it being filled with energy.
Filled with contours of energy.
In other words,
surfaces on which the energy is constant.
It's simply filled up with surfaces
on which the energy is constant.
The phase point,
meaning a point in this
phase space as you follow it,
stays on the same surface of constant energy.
That's just energy conservation.
And the fluid flows.
The fluid defined by the phase space dust.
Think of a dust in phase space.
Flows along these lines,
which are lines of constant energy.
The lines of constant energy,
in general,
could be closed.
They don't have to look like this.
They could be closed curves.
For example,
we studied a case last time called the harmonic oscillator.
In which h was proportional
to p squared plus x squared.
Let's forget the constants.
Forgetting the constants,
it was essentially p squared plus x squared.
So in that case,
the contours of constant energy
were just circles around the origin.
The contours could be open or off to infinity.
They could be closed curves.
They could even be closed curves.
So the velocity of dot.
That corresponds to a motion which doesn't go anywhere.
It just sits there.
For example,
the harmonic oscillator,
which is at the origin with no velocity.
It simply sits there.
It doesn't move.
That's a kind of degenerate circle.
Right at the origin.
So the phase point moves on these surfaces.
This is very much like the discrete situation.
But it's not.
Where you have different closed pieces of the phase space.
And that defines a conservation law.
Which one of the cycles you are.
Well,
in phase space it's very similar.
Every point is on some contour of constant energy.
And you move along those contours.
Yeah?
The density of points is constant.
We're going to talk about that.
Yeah.
Because if the density of points is constant,
how do you get these diverging lines?
Oh.
Well,
that's easy actually.
We haven't discussed the fact yet
that the density of points is constant.
But let me answer your question.
So let's...
Let's imagine lines that look like this.
So the fluid comes in
and goes through a narrow channel.
What happens when fluid goes through a narrow channel?
Suspension.
It moves faster.
It moves faster just so that the density doesn't change.
A big lump of fluid comes in
and it doesn't want to change its volume.
So it has to squeeze between these lines faster.
The lesson is where the
lines clump up and get close.
Where the contours get close.
The fluid is moving fast.
That's in fact what Maxwell's...
What Hamilton's equations say.
When the contours are close together...
Think about a contour map.
What does it mean in a contour
map that the contours are very close?
Steep.
It's steep.
It means the altitude is changing very fast.
What does it mean on the contours of
constant energy that the contours are very close together?
It means that H is changing rapidly with respect to
either P or Q or some combination of P and Q.
So where the lines clump up is where the H by P and
the H by Q is large and it's where the fluid is moving fast.
So the lines can diverge alright.
It's just that the places where they diverge like that,
the fluid slows down.
And we're going to study that behavior a little bit.
Question.
You have closed curves and
open ones at the same time.
What's that?
You have closed curves together with open ones.
Absolutely.
Let me give you an example.
The pendulum.
In the pendulum...
Small oscillations at the bottom are closed curves.
The system just goes back and forth,
back and forth,
just cycles over the same defined closed curves.
When it swings over the top like this,
they sort of correspond to open curves.
Well,
let me give you...
Let's sit it there.
Forget the pendulum.
Take a particle that's moving
on a washboard potential like that.
Okay.
Potential which is just a sine wave.
Alright.
If you start down near the bottom here and
you give the particle a little bit of energy,
all it does is oscillate back and forth.
So it looks like a harmonic oscillator.
In fact,
it is a harmonic oscillator
plus a little bit of extra.
Alright.
So it just oscillates back and
forth and the contours are closed curves.
So for small energy,
the contours are closed curves.
Give it a big energy and it just
goes whistling off over the top of the washboard.
If it has enough energy to
climb over the top and keep going,
then the curves are open.
The system doesn't come back to itself.
It just keeps going off forever and ever.
So yes,
you can certainly have both closed and
open curves in the same phase space.
It would be interesting to try to...
I'm not going to do it,
but it would be interesting to try to plot what the
contours of constant energy look like here on the phase space.
Alright.
Any other questions?
Is there anything you want me to go back over?
Yes.
In general,
is PI always a constant marketable of QI prime?
Say it again.
QI dot.
Say it again extremely clearly.
In general,
in generalized coordinates.
In generalized coordinates.
Yeah.
Is PI always a constant marketable of QI dot?
No.
Definitely not.
It can...
No,
no,
not at all.
No.
It's just...
We can invent all sorts of Hamiltonians.
Here's a Hamiltonian.
H is equal...
Instead of P squared plus Q squared,
let's take P cubed plus...
X cubed instead of P squared plus X squared.
This doesn't correspond to any system
that I know about in nature,
but there's nothing wrong with it from
the point of view of the Hamiltonian.
Now,
what are the equations?
The equations are that derivative of H with
respect to P is equal to X dot,
and that's 3P squared is equal to X dot.
Well,
that does not say that the relation between P and X
dot is that P is a constant multiple of X dot.
So the answer is no,
not in general.
Other...
This is sort of unusual,
but you could have an X here.
That would be less unusual.
No,
sorry,
X times P squared.
Also X times P occurs in Hamiltonians.
But X times P squared.
So you would have the H
by dP is X times P.
And you would have P and X,
the relationship between them having an extra factor of X.
So no.
No.
There's no reason for such a simple relationship.
Yeah?
It sounds like we're describing sort
of a perpetual motion of sorts.
Really?
No.
Yeah.
Motion is perpetual.
That's why energy is concerned.
But I'm not sure what you're getting at.
No,
it's the idea that when you factor in friction,
that you're actually transferring the
energy into another part of the...
Yeah,
okay.
Before we can address the real meaning of perpetual motion
and the pros and cons of it and so forth,
we have to understand something about thermal motion.
And we have to understand the
difference between usable and non-usable energy
and entropy and all that sort of stuff.
So we're now at a more basic level
studying the individual degrees of freedom of a system.
Microscope,
for example,
if it's this table with all the
molecules moving around in it and so forth,
with the air in the room,
these are the equations that
really do govern the entire system.
In various kinds of approximations,
you divide energy into usable energy
or available energy and unavailable energy.
Heat is unavailable energy,
but that's got to do
with the second law of thermodynamics,
which we haven't got to yet.
I hope to get to it.
It would be nice to
be able to get to it.
It's deeply connected with these equations,
and it's deeply connected with the
structure of motion and phase space.
But we're not there yet.
Okay.
Before we understand thermodynamics,
we have to understand chaos.
And we are not ready to do that tonight.
Hopefully we'll get to it.
Maybe.
Okay.
So let's discuss other conservation laws.
Energy is a conservation law that
follows just from Hamilton's equations here.
There are other conservation laws,
but let's look at the general form of conservation.
We know from the Lagrangian point of view
that conservation laws have to do with symmetries.
I'm going to suppress that now.
Later on,
we'll come back to it and
discuss symmetries from the Hamiltonian equations.
But now let's not worry about
why there might be a conservation law.
Just let's see what it
means to have a conservation law.
What the necessary and sufficient
conditions for a conservation law are.
Let's ask whether the quantity A is conserved or not.
What is A?
A is a function of the phase space.
Wherever you are in the phase space,
A has some value.
It's a function of the p's and the q's.
Or equivalently a function of position and velocity.
Let me give you an example.
We worked out a number of times ago that
the angular momentum of a particle moving in a plane
is given by x times py minus y times px.
It's a function of the p's and the q's.
In general,
all quantities that we might be interested
in are functions of positions and momentum.
If we know the position and momentum of something,
we know everything about it.
So in particular,
we know the value of its various quantities.
Let's ask whether A of
p and q might be conserved.
Might it be conserved?
Under what conditions?
What mathematical conditions?
Now I want to express
those conditions in some other way.
In terms of Hamilton's equations.
That's going to introduce for
us a new set of quantities.
Called Poisson brackets.
Fish brackets.
For those who don't speak French.
Okay.
This is easy.
All we want to know is whether the
time derivative of A is zero or not.
In fact,
let's just calculate the time derivative of A.
dA by dt.
Let's just do it.
Bruce Borse will calculate it.
It's the derivative of A with respect to p sub i times p sub i dot
plus the derivative of A with respect to q sub i times q sub i dot.
I'm going to write the summation sign.
Explicitly now for a little while.
Summation over i.
But now let's substitute in for p
sub i dot and q sub i dot.
Their value in terms of Hamiltonian.
So,
this is sum over i.
Derivative of A with respect to p sub i.
What's p sub i dot?
Again,
the sign.
I can never remember the sign.
It's minus,
right?
Minus dH by dq sub i.
So we have dA by dp
sub i dH by dq sub i.
Now what's this one?
Plus dA by dq sub i.
And q dot.
That's dH by dp,
right?
Well,
look at that.
That's kind of interesting.
We find out that the time derivative of any
quantity is given by the sum of two terms.
Let me start with this one.
dA by dq dH by dp.
And q.
So if you know what A is,
and you also know what the Hamiltonian is,
you can compute these things.
dA by dq dH by dp
minus dA by dp dH by dq.
A very symmetric looking construction,
a very symmetric looking expression,
mathematical expression,
that tells you what the time derivative of A is.
This mathematical construction,
let's generalize it.
Take any two functions of P and Q.
A of P and Q
and B of P and Q.
Any two.
How do you get these diverging lines?
Then you define something called the Poisson bracket.
That's the symbol for the Poisson bracket.
You take A and B,
put them inside the bracket,
and put a comma between them.
That's the symbol for the Poisson bracket.
Its definition is
sum over I of all the
coordinates of dA by dq dI
dB by dq dI
minus dA by dP dI
b by bq sub i.
You can see the symmetry of it.
It's composed of two terms,
one in which a gets differentiated with q,
one in which b gets differentiated with p,
and vice versa.
That's called the Poisson bracket of a and b.
We will see that another formulation
of classical mechanics
is to write everything in terms of these Poisson brackets.
But here we are,
let's rewrite.
This tells us that any quantity,
the time derivative of any quantity,
any quantity at all,
whether it's conserved or not,
in fact,
what I'm talking about now is not conservation,
but the time derivative of any quantity,
and that's equal to the Poisson bracket
of a with the Hamiltonian.
The Poisson bracket of any quantity
with the Hamiltonian is its time derivative.
That's another formulation of mechanics,
closely related to Hamilton's.
But if you're interested in whatever it happens to be,
if you can express it
in terms of positions and momenta,
then its time derivative is given by the Poisson bracket
with the Hamiltonian.
The Hamiltonian is a special equation,
but it's not a time derivative.
It's a special object which generates velocities,
generates time derivatives by taking Poisson brackets.
So as I said,
this is another,
yet another formulation of quantum mechanics,
sorry,
classical mechanics,
where the motion of any quantity is expressed
in terms of Poisson bracket perspective,
the Hamiltonian.
Let's just check it.
Let's do one or two examples.
If you like,
this is a generalization
of Hamilton's equations.
It includes Hamilton's equations.
For example,
let's check q dot.
q dot must be the
Poisson bracket of q with h,
according to those equations.
Let's see what that says.
That says one variable now,
one p and one q.
That says dq by dq,
dh by dp,
minus dq by dp,
dh by dq.
I've now just substituted for a,
just good old q.
q dot is the Poisson bracket of q with h.
That's q dot.
The Poisson bracket of q
with h is dq by dq.
What's that?
One.
All right,
so this is just one.
What's dq by dp?
Zero.
q and p are independent variables.
This goes away.
And this just says that
q dot is dh by dp.
No,
that's Hamilton's equations.
What about p dot?
P dot is the Poisson bracket of p with h.
That's dp by dq,
dh by dp,
minus dp by dp,
dh by dq.
What's dp by dq?
Zero.
Zero?
And dp by dp?
One.
I think I just erased the minus sign.
It's not going to work.
One.
So that's the other of Hamilton's equations.
So the two Hamilton equations are special cases
of a much more general rule that the
time derivative of anything is the Poisson
bracket of the anything with the Hamiltonian.
This gives a new view of Hamiltonians as
generating time dependence by the action of Poisson brackets.
The action of taking the Poisson bracket,
that's the Poisson bracket.
The Hamiltonian tells you how systems change with time.
That's yet another representation of classical mechanics.
I think that's probably...
Let's stop the questions and not
go any further at this point.
Is a carbon tax a conservation law?
What's that?
Yeah.
Oh.
Well,
since I started talking about conservation laws,
now we see that it's a necessary and
sufficient condition to have a conservation law
that the quantity in question have zero
Poisson bracket with the Hamiltonian.
Now,
that may seem like an incredibly abstract view of things,
and it is,
but it's also a
very powerful and very general formulation.
If you want to know whether something's conserved,
you Poisson bracket it,
and you can't do anything
I mentioned the Poisson needed,
or the Hamiltonian.
And if it's zero,
then it's conserved.
If it's not zero,
then whatever it is gives you the time derivative.
Try it out for angular momentum for example.
Try to take just the preparation,
and see if the angular momentum is conserved by taking
the Poisson bracket with p squared over 2m,
and so forth.
Let's just take some questions
now and stop for the B.
Okay.
I think we've probably done enough for tonight.
This is very abstract,
but it is very powerful.
Powerful means that apart from the fact
that you can use it to calculate,
which you can,
or .
We haven't discussed the fact yet,
but it depends on your points as a concept.
Not only the structure of classical mechanics,
but quantum mechanics reoccurs and reoccurs and reoccurs
all over the place.
Yeah?
How did Pisan come up with that?
What's that?
I really don't know.
I wouldn't be surprised if
he came up with it exactly
this way,
by calculating small changes in things.
My guess is he came
up with it exactly this way.
Yeah.
What did he do by this practice?
By when did he find the bracket?
Because the chain rule is there.
Well,
he just found this structure
recurring in many contexts.
I mean,
that's when the,
now we're
going to study more general plus-sum brackets,
not just with the Hamiltonian,
but between any pairs
of things.
さっきの
mathematicians,
good mathematicians,
and theoretical physicists,
are people who tend to see patterns.
They see the same thing a
couple of times and they say,
ah,
a pattern,
I see a pattern.
And you saw the same pattern occurring
in a couple of places and you said,
ah,
I'm going to call it a key practice.
What are some other examples
where B and it's not H?
I don't think we ever really got back to that.
Oh,
wait,
you're talking about the non-conservation of energy?
Right.
Yeah,
good.
I would assume that both the Lagrangian and
the Hamiltonian do not explicitly depend on time.
Now if I explicitly depend on time,
in the case of the Lagrangian,
it means that there's some time dependence above and beyond the fact that the
Q's and the P's or the Q's and the Q dots depend on time.
Let's go and ask what happens
if the Hamiltonian really does depend on time.
How can that happen?
Well,
it's dumping in energy,
right?
Yeah.
Let's suppose there's a big lump of energy,
a freaking lump of matter over here.
Our system is over here.
We're not going to include this as
part of the mathematics of our system,
but it exerts forces on here.
And it's moving.
It moves from here to here in a certain way.
That will mean the forces on
this system will depend on time.
In fact,
there will be a term in the energy.
Let's just pick a single particle.
There'll be a term in
the energy that becomes the force.
the energy of this particle,
u of its position,
which also depends on the position of this big lump.
But the position of the big lump depends on time.
So that means the potential energy
depends on x
and also explicitly time.
It means it depends on time
even if the particle doesn't move.
It certainly depends on time just
because x may depend on time,
but that's an implicit dependence on time.
There's also an explicit dependence on time
corresponding to the fact that the source
of the force happens to be moving.
If the Hamiltonian depends explicitly on time,
it's calculating the time derivative of the energy itself.
This was our equation that
we had a few minutes ago,
and these two things cancelled
because p dot and q
dot are also derivatives of h.
But there's just another term.
If h also depends on t,
then we have to write that the time
derivative of h is the h by dp,
which is the time derivative of h,
times p dot plus the h
by dq times q dot plus...
エクストラセイト
derivative of H with respect to T.
In other words,
the change in the Hamiltonian,
even if P and Q are standing still,
if P dot and Q dot are equal to zero.
That's what happens if the potential energy,
for example,
depends explicitly on time.
Then this would of course be
just the U by the T.
That's what it would be.
All right,
so in that case,
even though these two terms
completely cancel each other by virtue
of Hamilton's equations,
there's another term left over.
Just the explicit derivative of H with respect to T.
And that's in general not zero.
It won't be zero if the Hamiltonian,
it says what it says,
if the Hamiltonian
explicitly depends on time,
then that will appear
in the equation for the time derivative
of the total energy.
So that's as simple as that.
We can do some examples.
It's getting a little bit late.
I don't want to do an example now,
but let's come back to it.
An example of a time-dependent Hamiltonian.
Just a little definition in the Poisson bracket.
Is there a convention in
terms of which order there is?
Because there's a minus between the two.
I hope my convention is the same as Poisson's.
And I'm not sure it is.
Let's see,
I always define it this way.
A comma B is the A by BQ,
the B by BP,
minus the A by BP,
the B by BQ.
And you know,
I don't think I've ever looked that up.
But my question was,
since you said this,
that's general,
not just Q's and P's being these variables.
Is it A of Q comma
B or A of P comma Q?
As just a mathematical definition.
A just looks like a machine.
E or Q,
which is the first variable,
which is the second?
He said this was just an abstract definition.
You see what I'm saying?
I don't think that means anything.
You can write it either way.
I mean.
You make a convention.
Let's make a convention.
Isn't one minus the other?
Hm?
Could it be the A,
B,
the B,
BQ?
We could define it by the A by BP,
the B by BQ,
minus the other one.
But this is the way it's defined.
That's not my question.
Since you said you have a function A of P,
you can't just say A of P and Q.
Does that mean that Q is the second variable?
When you say A of Q is
the same as A of Q and B.
Are you taking the derivative of A with respect
to the first variable or to the second variable
in your capital letter?
Which one is first and which one is second?
You choose.
No,
no,
no.
There's no first and second.
There's P's and Q's.
That's all.
Normally,
you'll get the first and second.
But you put Q position first before momentum.
It doesn't make any difference.
Well,
remember,
they're different.
You're just going to end up with one variation
of the Poisson bracket and then minus of the other.
Right.
You just want to know what the convention is.
If I write that the Hamiltonian
is P squared over 2m plus 1
over x plus gx.
And then you get m over x.
Will you please tell me which is the first one
and which is the second one?
It's just two variables.
But it will reverse the sign.
You'll get a reversal of the sign.
No,
no,
no.
I'm never going to tell you
whether x is the first variable.
I don't want to differentiate something.
It's a domino effect.
Please don't force me.
I understand what you mean.
I understand what you mean,
momentum and position,
that there's only one way of saying it.
That's not my question.
You said as an abstract math,
you said that this Poisson bracket
is going to come up in all kinds of places.
So maybe that's not momentum and position,
in which case it doesn't matter which is which variable.
And I was wondering if there
was a definition of that convention.
As to the sign of mu,
I don't think you have to go into detail.
This particular structure doesn't come up anywhere
that I know of except in mechanics.
But some people seem to be under the impression
that it's important to describe
whether x is the first variable
or the second variable.
It's not.
It's just the x variable.
And p is the p variable.
When I calculate the h by the p,
I don't have to ask whether p comes first,
and x second,
and so forth.
Now,
you could have defined the Poisson bracket
in the opposite way.
In fact,
you could have defined the Hamiltonian
with the opposite sign.
All kinds of things we could have done differently.
We made some conventions.
This is one of the conventions.
I don't know what else to say about it.
Let me answer your question.
So that's...
You're not satisfied.
The only question I had was,
you didn't know what p was,
you didn't know what q was,
it wasn't momentum,
it wasn't position.
In which case,
there is a difference of a minus sign.
And the only reason I ask that is you said
Poisson brackets come up all over.
You didn't know that it was always
in the nature of position and momentum.
Yeah,
I don't know any other place
where Poisson brackets come up,
except for positions and momentum.
What I did say comes up all over the place
is Legendre transformations.
Legendre transformations do have this habit
of coming up all over the place.
The equations for Legendre transformations
don't have a funny minus sign in them.
They read the L by the v
and the h by the v is equal to p.
The h by the v is equal to p.
So in that particular case,
there is no...
The preceding program is copyrighted
by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.