This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Now,
Leavill's theorem is really at
the heart of classical mechanics.
It's at the heart of Hamiltonian classical mechanics.
And a quantum mechanical version of it,
which is called unitarity,
is very much at the heart of quantum mechanics.
It will profit us to understand Leavill's theorem because,
as I said,
it is the immediate classical analog of
one of the most fundamental principles of physics,
quantum mechanics.
It can also be thought of...
as the idea,
or generalization of the idea,
of information conservation.
We talked about this,
I think,
in the first lecture,
where...
Let me just remind you,
I think I've done this a couple of times,
but let me remind you again,
that if you have a phase space,
which consists of a collection of points...
By a phase space,
I simply mean the space of possible configurations,
of a system.
In the case of a mechanical system,
it would be positions and velocities.
In the case of just a
system with a finite number of states,
it would be any one
of those finite number of states.
And then the laws of
mechanics for this very simple setup
would simply be expressed as a rule for
going from any configuration to any other configuration.
And I can draw it in a more complex way.
I can draw it in a more complicated way,
but there's not much point.
I could draw it so that the lines cross,
but that doesn't add anything to it.
You could have some disconnected cycles,
but generally that's the pattern.
And you'll notice that each point has one arrow
coming into it and one arrow going out of it.
That's the basic idea of information conservation.
Information conservation,
that nothing gets lost.
There's no,
let's call it convergence or divergence,
of the flow in the phase space.
This can be thought of as a kind of flow.
What's the word for what they do
in discos where they flash lights at you?
Stroboscope.
You can think of it stroboscopically,
where each instant you flash,
and the system moves.
And then it moves to the next configuration.
So it's a sort of stroboscopic flow
of the points in the phase space.
But you could imagine populating each of these points.
Populating means imagine a system
at that point in phase space
undergoing the motion that the system is supposed to have.
So we would have a collection
of systems filling up the phase space,
one at each point in the phase space,
and as time evolves,
the points in the phase space just move.
I've described this.
I think probably the best way to
describe it is that they move incompressibly.
Among other things,
that means that if you start with a separate point,
a separate system at each point in the phase space,
you'll never wind up with two points or two
systems at the same point in the phase space.
It's not like playing Monopoly,
where the Monopoly men can wind up with two points,
and they wind up on the same square.
That never happens.
They stay distinct from each other,
the points in the phase space.
They don't diverge.
They don't converge.
What would diverge mean?
Diverge would be a situation where
an incoming line would split in two.
Now what would that mean?
That would mean there was some
ambiguity in the evolution of the system.
If it went from here to here,
it wouldn't know where to go next.
Sometimes it might go this way,
sometimes it might go that way.
That doesn't happen.
So there's no divergence of the flow,
and there's also no convergence of the flow.
Convergence would mean that from two different phase points,
you come to the same phase point.
Then you would always know where to go,
but you wouldn't know where you came from.
If you found yourself over here,
you wouldn't know if you
came from here or over here.
Those are the two things that would make a difference.
Those are the forbidden kinds of flows.
As I said,
you can think of a lack of
convergence or divergence on a phase space.
Yeah?
Even if you had the word diverges,
but if it diverges under a statistical law?
It's quite thinkable.
It's not that it's not thinkable to have these things.
They don't occur in classical physics.
They don't occur,
except in so far as you ignore things.
Except in so far as you ignore degrees of freedom.
As I've said over and over,
friction is an example where you start
a system in any number of ways.
It's not in many ways.
It comes to the same configuration.
Well,
not quite,
but you get the idea.
Friction just slows things down,
brings them to rest.
No matter how they start,
they come to rest.
Many,
many different configurations can wind up exactly the same.
But that's only because you've ignored things.
You've ignored the molecular structure of a tabletop.
You can take this as an experimental fact,
or you can take it as a
consequence of the basic rules of quantum mechanics,
but all the classical mechanical systems
that are of interest in fundamental physics
have the property that there's no divergence or convergence.
Yeah?
Is that saying something more
than classical mechanics is based on?
Differential equations and there's no solution?
Yes,
it is saying something more than that.
It is saying something more than that.
And we'll see what it says.
It's what Leoville's theorem is what it says.
But we'll come to it.
For example,
the sort of thing that can't happen is,
here's phase space,
okay?
Every point in this phase space is
distinct from every other point in some sense.
Now you could take a group of points,
and follow them,
and they might all squeeze together into a smaller volume.
All right?
That's the kind of convergence that doesn't happen.
Instead,
the flow in phase space
is a kind of incompressible flow.
Both incompressible,
what's the opposite of compression,
and non-divergent.
Well,
phase space doesn't blow up,
it doesn't shrink.
But we'll come to the
precise definition of it soon enough.
So in some sense,
the phase space doesn't pinch together or diverge.
It's as though,
here's the way you can think about it.
In the continuum mechanics case,
you can imagine populating the phase space,
let's call it P and Q,
Q and P.
And of course,
there may be many Ps and Qs,
I simply can't draw them on the blackboard.
And we might imagine,
in the same way,
that we populated each point here with a system,
we can imagine populating the phase space,
with a dust,
with a dust of points.
And follow that dust of points.
Let's assume that the phase space is populated uniformly,
with a constant density,
a uniform density of points,
of dust.
And we follow each point as
it moves through the phase space,
it defines a kind of flow.
But it defines a special kind of flow,
which is called incompressible.
And it basically has the property
that each point in the phase space
can be thought of as
having a little volume around it.
Each one occupies its own little volume.
If we take the density to be uniform,
then each one of these volumes is the same.
And as we follow it,
when we see it later,
each phase point is separated from each other phase point
by the same amount of volume in the phase space.
Or you can say it another way.
If you take a group of points,
there are three ways to say it.
All of them equivalent.
The first is to follow individual
points with little volumes around them,
and watch them move.
The volume of each little point,
or the region occupied by that little volume,
or the little points,
stays the same.
But we can generalize that.
We can say take any region
of the phase space to begin with.
Take any region.
And follow its points.
Follow its points with time.
After time,
that phase space region will change.
It will change its shape.
Some points move faster than other points.
It may spread one way.
It may stretch some direction.
It may compress in another direction.
But the one thing that's true is that
the volume of that region will stay the same.
In other words,
the volume of a fixed set of
points in the phase space will not change.
Will it maintain connectedness?
And it will maintain connectedness.
Absolutely.
They don't disconnect.
The connectedness is simply the predictability.
If it became disconnected,
how could it become disconnected?
A phase point would split somehow.
Which would simply mean it didn't know where to go.
The equations broke down at this point and
didn't tell the phase point where to go properly.
So,
yeah.
Regions maintain their connectivity.
In other words,
a region like this can't break up into two disconnections.
It's a connected region.
And a hole cannot appear.
So it's a very continuous,
smooth,
no holes.
The connectivity is conserved.
But the type of connectivity,
simply connectedness,
multiple connectedness,
whatever it is,
the topology of the chunk of phase space is maintained,
as is its volume.
What is not maintained,
in general,
is the distance in the phase space between points.
Take a pair of points in
the phase space and follow them.
If we follow them,
we may discover later that they're closer together.
Now you say,
how is that consistent?
How is it possible that the
volume of a phase region doesn't change,
but the distance between points can change?
Well,
what's interesting is,
what can happen,
for example,
is a volume can stretch in one
direction and compress in the other direction.
Volume being conserved.
The volume of all of this
collection of points in here is unchanged.
But if you follow each point,
you'll find that the shape changes.
But the shape changes in a
way that leaves the volume unchanged.
But in particular,
this point and this point
are now found here and here,
so they're much further from each other than they were.
On the other hand,
this point and this point are found here and here,
so they're much closer together than they were.
Two points switch places?
Points switch places?
No,
no,
everything is extremely continuous.
But is it conserved orientation?
Conserved orientation.
How do you move past each other?
What does that mean?
Oh.
You mean can one...
Well,
you can certainly have a situation where there's
a point in phase space moving to the right,
and another point in phase space moving to the right,
and they start like this,
and this one is moving faster than this one,
and passes it.
Yes,
that can happen.
No question that that can happen.
For example,
you can have a situation where if
you started with a square in phase space,
that square could evolve into a...
What is that called?
Parallelogram.
Parallelogram of the same area.
That would happen,
for example,
if the top was moving faster than the bottom,
but the width of the whole thing...
That's a sort of shear motion where
the top shears relative to the bottom.
That's perfectly allowed.
That conserves the volume.
If the height and the width stay the same,
it conserves the volume.
So that's possible,
and that would certainly allow a point back
here to get ahead of a point over here.
Yeah,
so...
I guess you did it.
Well,
go ahead,
ask the question.
What's that?
Yeah.
I think you said that was chaotic.
The double pendulum and the gravitational...
Yeah.
So you have a little neighborhood point,
a little point that just spread out lower.
Absolutely.
Absolutely,
but we'll...
Yeah.
Yeah,
we'll talk about that case.
That is not a counterexample to this.
Right.
It's an example of it,
but one which is less smooth and less predictable,
but for reasons we'll come to.
Okay.
Well,
let me just say it very quickly.
I say the phase space
maintains a certain degree of connectivity.
It maintains its connectivity.
All that happens is shape changes.
But the shape continues.
It can change wildly.
For example,
this sphere can evolve into something with...
I'm trying to keep the volume
the same as it was before,
but I'm probably not.
You know,
horrible...
So the...
There's no rule that says that the
shape can't evolve into some wildly extraordinary...
...extravagantly different structure,
which eventually starts to look more and more fractal.
Now,
it never really forms a fractal,
because continuity tells you that things which are close
to each other will stay close to each other.
But in time,
it'll start to get more and more fragmented,
more and more fractured,
but always maintaining its volume.
Okay?
Maintaining its volume so
that distinguishable points remain distinguishable,
and a measure of distinguishability
is the volume surrounding a point.
But we will return to this particular picture.
I ought to leave it there,
because I'll probably wind up drawing it again,
but not right now.
That,
incidentally,
is the basic case of a chaotic system.
Chaotic systems do exactly this kind of thing.
Non-chaotic systems tend to maintain
a greater degree of shape coherence,
we can call it.
Why do you qualify points that are
in close proximity as being in close proximity?
Say it again?
Why do you qualify points that are in close proximity
and end up in close proximity even in wild space?
No,
they don't.
They don't stay in close proximity.
No,
no,
no.
The statement is the volume of
the region in phase space is maintained.
So what that tells you is
that if two points do diverge,
or let's say that if the
phase volume stretches in one direction,
it must compress in the other direction.
So it's not completely without rules,
but the only real rule is that
the phase volume is maintained as time evolves.
What do you mean by volume exactly in this context?
Volume means the same thing that it does in calculus.
It means the integral.
It means break up the region
into a lot of extremely small cells.
Let's talk about area for the moment.
Let's not try to get
to higher dimensions for a minute.
Let's just take the case
of one Q and one P.
Then what I mean by
volume of phase space is that,
is just the area of the region.
Regions have area regardless of whether they're squares.
They don't have to be
squares or rectangles to have area.
You have to use a little bit
of calculus to add all of these up,
but there's a well-defined notion of area.
And as you follow it,
the shape may change,
but the area doesn't.
Now,
if it's a higher dimensional system
with more than one P and Q,
incidentally,
as always,
there's one Q for each P.
They come in pairs.
But we simply have to think,
think about the higher dimensional version of volume,
where we break up the
volume into lots of little cubes,
count the cubes and add them up.
Yes,
Michael.
I think it's really pointing out that
points that are nearby in phase space
have both similar,
close by in position and close by in momentum.
Yes,
absolutely.
That's right.
Nearby means close by in position and momentum.
But it doesn't mean that they stay close by.
And in particular,
the chaotic case is the situation where
there's a great deal of tendency for points
which are close to each
other to diverge from each other,
but always at the expense
of compression in some other direction.
Yes?
I'm thinking of throwing dice.
Yes.
They're traveling free in space,
but then they get a
table and it influences their gravitation,
and one of six possibilities comes up.
Right.
So there's no way of having that happen without friction?
Having which happen now?
Having the free-tumbling system map
into a system of friction.
Oh,
oh,
oh.
Well,
yes,
that's basically friction.
You say there are many ways to start,
and you can wind up
with a six on the table.
Yeah,
right.
If you didn't have friction,
it would just bounce off the table and rebound and...
It wouldn't stop.
Yeah.
Right.
Friction's pretty common.
Friction is incredibly common.
Right.
Yes?
And when you're doing a mechanical system in practice,
if you're an engineer,
you don't want to forget friction.
If you're a physicist,
you often want to forget friction.
You want to pretend it didn't exist.
In fact,
in many situations,
microscopic physics doesn't have friction.
If you really follow every
degree of freedom of a system,
then there's no concept of friction in the equations.
Friction is a collective effect of many variables,
some of which you just decide,
I'm going to ignore.
So it's a thermodynamic idea
rather than an idea of basic mechanics.
Of course,
they have to be consistent with each other.
When you decide not to look
at a collection of degrees of freedom,
the behavior of it may nevertheless reflect the fact
that in some bigger sense,
the phase space volume is conserved.
Energy conservation is one which,
you might not realize if you
were sliding around things on the table.
So energy is lost.
Kinetic energy.
There's no potential energy.
It doesn't go up or down.
Kinetic energy is just lost.
Looks like energy conservation is wrong.
Those who would believe in
energy conservation would make a prediction.
And the prediction would be that
if you very minutely and carefully
measure the temperature of the table,
the temperature of the table
will go up a little bit,
and if you know the specific heat of the table,
then you can find out how
much energy was absorbed by the table,
et cetera,
and the conservation of energy will tell you
that there must have been
degrees of freedom that you ignored.
The same is true of this conservation of information.
If you discover a system which
looks like the phase space is contracting,
it means you've left things out of the system.
Now,
that's an empirical fact.
In the sense that it has
always proven to be the case.
But by now,
it is a fundamental fact derived from quantum mechanics.
But let's take it as a...
Well,
we're not going to take Liouville's theorem as a given.
We're going to prove it.
But we're going to prove it from something.
We're going to prove it from Hamilton's equations.
All right.
So the beauty of the Hamiltonian
form of mechanics is this flow picture.
A flow in phase space,
a very predictable flow in phase space,
where the points move in
a very characteristic kind of way,
and that characteristic way is Hamilton's equations.
The entire flow is determined by a single
function of all of the p's and q's.
If you know that function,
then you know the flow,
and you know the flow on the phase space.
And if you started a
little boat sailing on the flow,
which means you start a system at
a particular point in the phase space,
that Hamiltonian flow will tell you
where it is at any future time.
Okay.
And that flow is incompressible.
But let's first define the flow.
So this is dynamics as a flow in phase space,
as a kind of fluid flow.
All right.
So every point has associated with it a
motion that depends only on where you are.
And a motion means a time derivative.
This is p.
This is q.
It means a p dot and a q dot.
In other words,
a velocity,
but not a usual velocity,
a velocity in phase space,
consisting of the ordinary velocities,
which are the q dots,
plus the p dots,
which are the time derivatives of the p's.
Okay.
So we just write down Hamilton's equations.
p sub i dot is equal
to minus dh by dq sub i.
Notice they come in pairs.
Is plus dh by dp,
dp sub i.
That's it.
That's all of mechanics in a nutshell
in the Hamiltonian form.
Okay.
All right.
Let's consider what it means
for a flow to be incompressible.
What we're ultimately going to prove
is that this flow is incompressible.
What exactly does it mean?
Let's start with a one-dimensional
flow and see what it says.
So a one-dimensional flow just means you have a line,
and let's populate that line
with a uniform distribution of points.
For simplicity,
I'm taking a uniform distribution.
That means that the density of points is the same
everywhere as along the line,
or equivalently,
the little tiny separation between points
is uniform along the line.
What kind of motion constitutes incompressible flow?
Well,
basically,
there's only one kind,
and that's just all the points move together
with exactly the same velocity.
What would happen if the velocity
varied from point to point along here?
For example,
suppose it went faster over here than over here.
Then there would be a
clumping up of points in between.
There would be a clumping up
and an increase in their density.
All right.
But let's consider the mathematics of it.
What's that?
Yes,
yes,
but let's just talk about flows for a minute.
For a minute,
let's forget phase space
and just talk about the
general concept of an incompressible flow.
And we'll come back to
phase space as a special case.
That's right.
No,
you're right.
But nevertheless,
it's possible to think of
incompressible flows in one dimension.
They're very trivial.
You can have any velocity you like,
but the velocity has to be completely uniform
all across the line.
Otherwise,
there's a clumping.
Now,
you can think of it in two ways.
You can either say,
take a set of points and follow them.
Let's take a connected set of
points like this and follow them.
One way of saying incompressibility
is just that the volume of that
particular set of points stays the same.
All right.
That's a view of it following the points.
There's another view of it which
stays at a particular place in space.
Let's say we stay at a
particular space in a place in space.
In other words,
a little volume.
We're not going to move that volume,
but points are going to come into it
and points are going to depart from it.
If the fluid is moving to the right,
of course,
it could be moving to the right in
some places and the left in other places,
but let's count all velocities as positive to the right.
If the fluid is moving,
then some points leave this region,
and some points enter the region.
To say it's incompressible
says that the number of points that enters is the same
as the number of points that leaves in any given time interval.
What is the condition for that?
Well,
it's more or less obvious
that if the velocity,
let's imagine that the velocity is fast over here
and slow over here.
All right.
Then it's quite clear that the number
of points that are exiting the region
is proportional to the velocity at this end.
Let's call this point two and point one.
The number of points exiting
will be proportional to the velocity
of the points to the right,
and that we can just call V2.
That's the number of points exiting.
The number of points entering is the velocity at one.
So the net increase,
shall we take increase or decrease?
Let's talk about the net decrease.
The net decrease in points in this volume here
is going to be proportional to V2 minus V1.
Actually,
it's V2 minus V1 times the density of the points.
But as long as the density is uniform,
then we can just write that the...
Yeah?
If the velocity is higher,
the density's got to be changing.
That's the point.
That's exactly the point.
Wait,
if the velocity...
Yeah.
If the velocity is higher at this end,
or whichever way,
if the velocity is bigger
at one end than the other,
then the density inside has to be changing.
Incompressible means that the density
is not allowed to change.
Okay?
So what it says is that V2
minus V1 must be equal to zero.
That it cannot be a gradient
or a variation of the velocity.
This must be equal to zero.
Now,
if I take a small interval,
let's imagine that this is a small interval,
then the difference of the velocity at 2 and 1,
assuming everything is nice and smooth and differentiable,
the calculus applies,
for a small interval,
we can say that the difference of the velocities
is just proportional to the derivative of the velocity
with respect to x,
times some delta x,
where delta x is the interval here.
And then we would write
that this has to be equal to zero.
Delta x is just a small interval,
it's not zero,
it's just a number,
so it follows then that the derivative of the velocity
with respect to x must be equal to zero
for an incompressible fluid.
Which is what we would intuitively imagine
that the whole fluid has to move together.
Since all of the motion is along the x-axis,
I'm going to write this as the derivative
of the x component of the velocity.
There is only an x component of the velocity.
But just to use a notation which will generalize,
I'll write that this is dvx
by dx is equal to zero.
That's the condition in one dimension
for an incompressible fluid,
and it is very trivial.
Questions?
Good.
Alright,
now let's move on to two dimensions.
I'm going to call the two directions x and y.
Why not?
x and y.
Now let's ask,
in a small interval of time,
what is the increase or the decrease,
I guess v2 minus v1 would be the decrease
in the number of points,
what is the decrease in the number of points
in this little square here?
Let's take this square to be
of size delta x and delta y.
It's not a square,
it's a rectangle.
How many points are in this little square?
So we're entering and leaving
on the various sides of this rectangle.
Alright,
let's start with the number of points coming in here.
Again,
we're imagining that the density is completely uniform,
so the number of points
per unit area to start with
is completely uniform.
If it's incompressible,
then the number of points per unit area
must stay the same,
must be exactly the same afterwards.
So I'll call this dvx by dx.
Okay,
so how many points come in from this side here?
Well,
the number of points coming
in this way per unit time
is clearly going to be proportional
to the x component of velocity,
the y component of velocity,
a velocity in the vertical direction
will not contribute to points crossing this boundary here.
So the x component of motion here,
vx,
at the left-hand end here,
will constitute the incoming points
coming in from the left vertical side of the square.
What about the number going out?
Oh,
there's another factor.
There's another factor.
Anybody know what the other factor is?
Delta y.
Yeah,
the size of the y interval here.
Obviously,
the bigger the y interval for a given velocity,
the more points will enter there.
So there's another factor,
which is just delta y.
Now,
how about the number of
points going out on this side?
That's also proportional to vx,
but vx at the displaced point.
All right,
so we have to move ahead a little bit
and subtract the points coming out on this side,
exactly what we did over here.
The answer is going to be
the derivative of vx with respect to x
times delta y times delta x.
Where does this delta x come from?
The difference of the velocity here and here
is the derivative of v with
respect to x times delta x.
All right?
The difference between the x component of velocity
on the right-hand side of the square
and on the left-hand side of the square
is the derivative of v with
respect to x times delta x.
We have to multiply that by delta y
to find the net number of points
coming into on this side
minus out on this side,
and that's this.
Okay,
so this is the net number of points
coming into the rectangle
through the vertical edges.
Now,
what about the horizontal edges?
The horizontal edges,
things can also move in,
but now the x component of velocity
is not relevant
to particles coming in
in this direction.
Only the y component of the motion
is relevant on the horizontal boundaries.
So,
how many particles come in from the lower end?
Well,
that's going to be
v sub y
at the lower end
times delta x.
But then we have to subtract off
v sub y coming out of the top end here,
in order to find the difference
of the incoming points
and the outgoing points
on the bottom and top.
So that will give us
the derivative of v sub y
with respect to what?
With respect to y,
because we're going from bottom to top,
times delta y.
The whole net change
in the number of points in this rectangle
is simply proportional to delta x delta y,
that's just the area of the little region,
times a quantity which is called
the divergence of the velocity field.
This is the velocity field.
It can vary from place to place,
but it's definite and it's fixed.
And this is the derivative of v sub x
with respect to x
plus the derivative of v sub y
with respect to y.
If this is positive,
it corresponds to a decrease
in the density.
What if it's an incompressible fluid?
If it's an incompressible fluid,
then the net number of points coming in
and going out must add up to zero.
We can forget the delta x times delta y,
that's just a number,
a little area,
and so the condition of
incompressibility
is that the divergence of the velocity field
is equal to zero.
Let's drop this factor here,
it doesn't do anything for us.
dvx by dx plus dvy by dy
is equal to zero.
This is not a general rule
about all possible flows.
This is a rule about
incompressible flows
that start with uniform density
and maintain the uniformity of the density.
Notice that it does not say
that the velocity can't vary
from place to place.
But it does say
that if the velocity is increased,
if the x component of velocity
is increasing in one direction,
then the y component must be decreasing
in the other direction.
So it does not say
that the velocity can't change
from place to place.
It doesn't require the motion
to be just rigid motion.
More complicated kinds of things
can settle here,
but it is constrained in this way.
Questions?
Yes?
Yeah,
but we take
an instantaneous photograph of it
and we ask,
at this instant,
what's the time rate of change
of the number of points in here?
So at any instant,
something which is coming in here,
yes,
it could turn around
and go up here.
That's perfectly fine.
That's perfectly acceptable.
But that will be at a later time
that it will be found going out here.
So we take,
we imagine a snapshot.
Instantaneously right now,
what is the time rate of change
of the number of points in this volume?
Okay?
So if a point is coming through here,
it's not going out there.
Okay.
So that argument applies to any space?
It applies to any number of dimensions.
So in any number of dimensions,
we could write,
there aren't enough letters in the alphabet,
but I,
x,
y,
and z here just refer to a general space
having nothing to do with mechanics,
just a general flow in any number of dimensions.
The general rule for an incompressible flow
would be that the derivative
of the ith component of the velocity
with respect to the ith x
is equal to zero.
All right.
That's also written in the notation.
そう
sum of i,
thank you
that's also written
in the notation that the divergence
of v
is equal to zero
divergence simply means this act
of differentiating the i-th component with
respect to the i-th coordinate and summing them up
it's called the divergence
divergence
i've assumed uniformity of the density,
yes
yeah,
if i hadn't assumed uniformity of the density,
i just did that to make it simpler
had i not assumed uniformity of the density
what you would have to do is invent
the new quantity which is the density at any
point times the velocity
and then that would be the thing which
would have zero divergence but if the density is
uniform
then that factors out
so
just for simplicity i imagined that the uh...
and after all if it's an incompressible fluid
it stands to reason that its density is everywhere
the same since you can't change its density
so
um
let's come back to phase space
what are the x's
the x's are just the coordinates in space
the coordinates are the p's and q's
and the q's and q's are the coordinates
so we should identify the x's not just
with q but with a p and a q
so the number of x's
is twice the number of q's
one x for each p and q
that's the space we're dealing with
if there's only one q
then it's a two dimensioned x
space,
one p and one q,
and so forth.
What are these quantities over here?
p sub i dot
and q sub i dot.
Those are the local velocities in the phase space.
They are the v sub i's.
i now goes from one to two n,
it runs over all of the coordinates in the momenta.
But
these are,
we could call this here,
we could call it v p sub i,
the velocity along the
axis p sub i.
This we could call v q sub i.
So the p dots and
the q dots are the things
that are being called the velocity.
Now let's calculate the divergence of the flow.
We're going to calculate the divergence of the flow,
and of course what we're going to
use is Hamilton's equations to see that
the divergence of the flow is exactly zero.
All right,
so the divergence of the flow,
we take v p sub i and we differentiate it
with respect to p sub i.
So let's write the divergence of the flow over here.
First of
all,
we have
derivative of the p,
I'm not going to bother writing the i.
Well,
maybe I should.
No,
let's
just do it for two dimensions first,
then we'll come back and talk about it for any
number.
Derivative of v p with respect to p,
with only one p and one q,
what is that?
Well,
that is equal to the derivative with respect to p,
times v p,
but v p is minus the
derivative of h with respect to q.
All right,
that's
the first term.
What's the second term in the divergence?
The second term is just dv
q by dq.
All right,
what is v q?
That's over here,
plus dh by dp.
So this becomes dv q,
d by dq of plus dh by dp.
If we have several coordinates in momenta,
then we would put
an i here and sum over i everywhere.
Also in the lower equation here.
I won't bother
with it though.
Well,
now you can see what happens.
So we have a dv q,
and we have a dh by dp.
If we have several of these derivatives,
we have an i,
and we have some of these derivatives.
Partial derivatives can be interchanged.
The derivative with respect to p of the derivative
with respect to q is the same as the
derivative with respect to q of the derivative with respect
to p.
dp dq is the same as dq dp.
It doesn't matter which order you differentiate something
in.
This one has a minus sign,
this one has a plus sign.
So these cancel in pairs.
They
cancel in pairs.
In fact,
it's not just that the divergence is equal to zero,
it's equal to zero in a
special way where they cancel in pairs,
but that's okay.
The divergence,
the sum of these,
dp,
that's exactly equal to zero.
So the sum of these,
add them together,
that's exactly equal to zero.
And that proves that the
flow in phase space is incompressible.
That is quite a profound theorem about mechanics,
the incompressibility of the flow,
the fact that the phase points
can't get squeezed into a smaller volume,
that they maintain sort of,
they have elbows,
and they keep,
for example,
running into each other.
That is probably the most
important fact about Hamiltonian mechanics,
that it is this incompressible kind of flow.
Let's concentrate for a little while on two dimensions,
one p and one q.
Remember,
this does not say that the distance between points,
stays the same.
As I said,
what it says,
is that the volume of a
region of phase space stays the same.
So a region like this could flow
into a region that looks like this,
as long as the volume stays the same,
and in particular two points which are fairly close,
can get fairly far.
So there's no conservation of the
distance between points in the phase space.
Only the volume.
Only the volume of a patch of phase space.
This idea that,
let's take the two dimensional case,
that area is the important thing,
and not distance,
you can see in another way.
Let's take the world of space,
and the world of space,
the world's simplest mechanical system.
A particle moving along one axis,
with an energy which is x dot squared,
a kinetic energy which is x dot squared over two.
I have even gone so far as
to set the mass equal to one,
to make it simple.
There's a canonical momentum,
p sub x,
which is equal to the derivative,
this is the Lagrangian.
Lagrangian is x dot squared over two.
The momentum canonically conjugate to x is the
derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to x dot,
and that's just x dot.
Now,
I could have used another coordinate.
I didn't have to use x to describe this system.
What would have happened had I used 2x?
Suppose I defined a new variable,
let me call it y,
it does not stand for another axis,
it just stands for another
representation of exactly the same physics.
A new coordinate,
I'll define,
and let's call it alpha times x.
Alpha is just any number,
fixed,
it could be two,
it could be a half,
it could be seven,
whatever it is.
This is just another representation of the same system,
where it's been labeled by a different axis,
or an axis with either closer or further away.
So,
it's just a number of points,
different units.
It really comes down to a unit transformation.
Okay,
what is x dot?
x,
first of all,
is equal to y over alpha,
and x dot is just
equal to y dot over alpha.
Let's rewrite the Lagrangian.
The Lagrangian doesn't change.
The Lagrangian is the same numerical
quantity no matter what coordinates we use.
The Lagrangian will now become,
it's still x dot squared over two,
but that becomes now y
dot squared over twice alpha squared.
I've just written that x dot squared
is y dot squared over alpha squared.
That's the new Lagrangian.
It's just another description of exactly the same system.
What is the canonical momentum conjugate to y?
Well,
it's dl.
dL by dy dot.
P sub y is equal
to y dot over alpha squared.
Okay,
let me now write,
right over here we have y equals alpha times x.
We have py equals y dot over alpha squared.
That's also equal to x dot over alpha.
I've used that y dot is equal to x dot,
let's see,
what have I written?
Yes,
y dot is alpha times x dot.
So wherever you see y dot here,
just stick alpha times x dot.
That cancels one factor of alpha.
All right,
but this is also equal
to p sub x over alpha.
All right,
so let me combine that with this equation over here.
P sub y is equal to
p sub x divided by alpha.
Notice what's happened.
When you make a coordinate
transformation that stretches the x axis,
it shrinks the p axis.
Sorry,
p,
yeah.
If you make a transformation which stretches the x axis,
remember now,
p,
x and y are not different directions of space.
They're just different coordinates
describing the same thing.
This is a coordinate transformation.
Y is equal to alpha x.
Along with it goes a
transformation of the canonical momentum,
but in the opposite direction.
If you stretch the x axis,
you shrink the p axis.
Okay.
That means,
for example,
if you take the phase space,
let's,
we can represent it either
in terms of x or y,
and we take a little region,
let's call this x and px.
Suppose we represent that same system in
terms of y and p sub y.
Well,
the width of this box,
as measured in y units,
is alpha times as big
as it was in x units.
But on the other hand,
the height of the region
is one over alpha times
what it was in x units.
So whether the height of this box
and the width of this box,
as measured in either x or y,
are not the same,
but the area of the box,
as measured in x and y,
are the same.
This is a characteristic feature of classical mechanics,
that the various coordinate
transformations that you would do,
if combined,
you do some coordinate transformation,
but you also calculate what
happens to the canonical momenta,
what you'll find is that areas in
the phase space always stay the same.
So the idea of an element of
area in phase space is very fundamental.
It of course comes up in quantum mechanics,
in quantum mechanics it's basically,
roughly speaking,
the statement that there's a smallest area in phase space.
A quantum of area in phase space,
we'll come to that,
but I'll just mention it now,
that things cannot be localized in the phase space
better than that quantum of area.
How big is the quantum of area?
Planck's constant.
No,
no,
not squared.
Not squared.
Planck's constant is not a measure of delta x,
or delta p,
it's a measure of area in the phase space.
And it says that there's a fundamental
unit of area in the phase space,
and that you cannot think of anything smaller than that.
That's the uncertainty principle.
Yeah,
question?
If you consider any possible evolution of a system,
can you use that as a,
if it's convenient,
can you always use that
evolution as a change of coordinates?
Absolutely.
The mathematical statement is that
the time evolution of a system
is a canonical transformation.
Yeah?
What if you were to start with a Hamiltonian
that didn't conserve energy,
like a ball falling to the earth?
That did or did not?
What?
Say it again.
You started with a Hamiltonian
that does not conserve energy,
like a ball falling to the earth,
you ignore the earth's movement.
Why does the,
why does it not conserve energy?
Because the ball takes up energy
as it falls to the earth.
No,
it loses potential energy,
gains kinetic energy.
Yeah,
okay,
that's the same thing.
I don't know why I was thinking that.
Right.
Um.
Good,
okay,
so let's,
all right,
the statement,
the statement that the flow in phase space,
flow in phase space is incompressible,
that's called Liouville's theorem.
So,
what you just said a while ago,
I saw that the alpha
can now represent the time dependence
of the system as a point moves.
Where,
where,
here?
Yeah,
when you.
No,
this wasn't representing the time dependence of anything,
this was just two different sets of coordinates,
that's all.
It could,
and you would conclude it's a point.
No,
well.
Is that,
is that what you call a canonical transformation?
This is a canonical transformation.
Okay.
Yeah,
yeah.
Right.
And we haven't,
we haven't discussed that at the moment,
but,
but the answer is yes,
that is a canonical transformation.
Okay.
All the interesting transformations
of mechanics are called canonical,
but we haven't defined them yet,
so let's,
all right,
let's talk a little bit,
since it's been raised,
about what chaos means.
The系 μelve that we had expected to represent
When it's sticky,
there's something called
What does that mean?
It means the area.
A p dot and a q dot?
Yeah.
A p dot and a q dot.
You want to multiply a
p dot times a q dot?
Well,
let's put two little arrows on it.
Okay,
let's multiply a p dot and a q dot.
That means that's independent of the values that you get.
It doesn't change if you change coordinates.
What doesn't change is delta p times delta q.
The area of a little region of phase space.
It doesn't change.
You have x and p,
p sub x,
and you have some other coordinates,
which you can call y and p sub y.
Okay,
and if you calculate the,
take a little region of area here,
break it up.
And calculate its area by adding up the squares
and giving them and assigning them an area delta p,
sorry,
delta x times delta p sub x.
Or add them up by assigning them
delta y times delta p sub y.
You'll get the same answer.
So it's the area element,
the size of an area,
which will be the same in whatever coordinates you use.
Whatever coordinates in momentum.
If the coordinates in momentum
come from the same Lagrangian.
Okay,
so yeah,
so area has an invariant meaning in the phase space.
It takes on its sharpest physical
meaning when we get to quantum mechanics,
where it really corresponds to the uncertainty principle.
So what would the m-th
product mean before quantum mechanics?
Well,
I don't know.
What does it mean?
The fact that it's conserved means that it's useful.
That,
that...
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Yeah,
it tells you what the right probability is.
What the right probability measure is on the phase space.
That invariant probability measure on the phase space.
And that's useful in statistical mechanics.
I see.
So it's part of the possibilities.
Yeah.
And it...
For example,
for example,
if you have some chaotic system as a phase space,
that means the phase point...
So if the phase point moves around and gets...
If the phase point really
moves around in some wild way...
So if the phase point moves around and gets...
And you ask how often or what is the probability
that it is found in a little region of phase space,
then the answer will depend only on
the area of the region of phase space.
So area would be the thing which would tell you...
And now it's a matter
of time before it does that.
the relative probability
if you are interested in the relative probability
probability could mean
the amount of time spent in this little region here
the phase point moves around
goes crazy
we stand there and watch it
and ask how much time does
it spend in that little volume
that's a measure
of the probability that you would find it
in that volume versus this volume
alright
the answer
is
is that the relative probability
of being in two different volumes
of phase space is simply the ratio of the areas
for a chaotic system,
yeah,
yes
well here I'm defining probability
game probability is not by expectations
your,
your naive expectations
I'm defining it by the amount of time
integrated time that it spends in a region
so that's,
that's a stronger
yeah
right
the,
yeah
the amount of time that it's in here
divided by the total time that you sample the system
tends to
to a finite limit for chaotic systems,
yeah.
No,
yes,
no,
it probably does,
but I have to think about it.
No,
I'm not sure what the word stochastic means,
frankly.
I think it just means an element of randomness.
What does stochastic,
what does the word stochastic mean?
Non-deterministic?
Yeah,
well,
of course,
chaotic systems are secretly deterministic,
but you can't follow them very long in time,
unless you have a degree of precision,
which is far beyond what's reasonable.
I don't want to get
into chaos too much right now.
I will just tell you very
quickly one other thing about chaotic systems,
or the difference between chaotic and not chaotic.
Both of them have the feature...
that the phase-space volume stays the same.
But that seems a little odd,
because you would think that for systems which are chaotic,
you know,
just
systems banging into each other and random collisions,
not random,
really,
but governed by the equations of motion,
but nevertheless complicated enough that they
seem to scatter all over the place,
you would think that the phase-space volume increases.
Increases because you get,
because after a while,
you know less and less about where,
where the system is.
Well,
that's not exactly true.
Here's the way it works.
Supposing you take...
Alright,
so the correct statement is that
this little sphere in phase-space will evolve,
and it will evolve into something which
may look more or less like a sphere,
but it may also look,
you know,
grow all kinds of complicated
fibers and become very fractalated.
I don't know.
Is fractalated a word?
Probably not.
You know,
it'll start to grow...
Okay,
now here's what you do.
You...
I want to put some more in.
Okay,
etc.
Alright,
now,
if I literally,
mathematically follow
the points – incidentally...
this will be just as continuous as this.
If you look at it under a microscope,
you will discover that
this phase-space is completely continuous
Nothing discontinuous
is broken off it or anything like that.
But as time goes on,
it tends to get more and more fractured like this,
so let's just call it fractured.
If you take a look at the screen,
it starts to match.
Take each point,
each point goes to a definite point.
If you follow the volume,
you'll find the volume is the same.
But now you can do
something which is called coarse-graining.
Coarse-graining means a purposeful decision to
draw little circles or spheres around phase
points and,
roughly speaking,
what it corresponds to is saying,
I don't have enough precision
to be able to distinguish points of phase space.
Strictly speaking,
I can only distinguish this
little volume from that little volume
from that little volume and that little volume.
So what we do is draw little spheres
around each phase point and follow the little spheres
rather than the individual phase points.
Follow the spheres and what will happen is this.
The sphere may go over here.
The sphere may go way over here.
This one may go way over here.
But if we were to take
the total area occupied by these spheres,
I think it's pretty obvious
that the total area will be much larger than
the area that you started with if this thing
branches out and fractalizes.
And it is.
So the coarse-grained...
The following of the phase space allows
the area to get bigger and bigger.
And it does get bigger.
Yeah?
Okay,
so that's why I was asking that question
because in order for those areas to stay the
same exactly,
it would have to be in some kind
of a limit as they're known to be random
distribution.
And what you're saying is because of the coarse-graining,
it's effectively random.
Yeah.
Because of the coarse-graining,
it's effectively random.
Yeah.
Because of the coarse-graining,
it's effectively random.
In other words,
if you take the coarse-grained phase space,
the nasty thing that happens
is no matter how small the coarse-graining is,
if you wait long enough,
points within
one coarse grain here will separate
and get far outside a coarse grain.
All right?
If the coarse grain is defined by little spheres.
So...
So what would your second-class sphere say?
What's that?
They're not mapping from the first.
No,
no,
no.
They're not the mapping from the first.
No.
The mapping from the...
No,
no,
no.
They're not the mapping from the first.
They're just spheres in the phase space,
again,
spheres that you can distinguish by the coarse-grained
apparatus that you happen to have.
So,
the coarse-grained apparatus that you happen
to have defines a coarse-graining on
here,
and it's not the same as the
coarse-graining that would inherit by following this coarse-graining.
It's just what you can measure,
what you can distinguish.
Sure.
And of course what you can distinguish depends on
the precision of your measuring apparatuses and so forth
But no matter how precise
your apparatuses and your description is,
no matter how small a coarse graining here
eventually points within a single cell here of
this coarse graining will diverge and get outside
the corresponding coarse grained
description of what happens later
That's what happens to a chaotic system.
Most systems are chaotic of course
The non-chaotic systems which sort of maintain
their integrity in the coarse grained sense,
those are rare and exceptional
Yeah?
The distance between points in a
phase state that's derived by time
Say it again
The distance between points in a
phase state that's derived by time
The distance between points in
the phase state when they change,
are we looking at a change in time?
Yeah,
change in time
Yeah
Would you say the area increases?
The area of the coarse grained,
you take the original region of phase space
you figure out exactly what it does
and then in the original region
of phase space you draw spheres
If the original region
is a nice simple sphere or something like a sphere
then when you add up
all of these coarse grained spheres
you'll get the volume of the original sphere back,
pretty much
But now you take this tree,
this very very finely fractalized tree that it grows into
which may fill up this very big piece of space
which may fill up this
very big piece of this blackboard
with very fine filaments
very very close to each other
Okay?
So for example,
if there are filaments extremely close to each other
so close to each other
that the coarse graining
sort of slops over,
or slops over the
distinction between these different filaments
then the total volume of these coarse grained green spheres
will in general exceed the volume that you started with
Why?
Yeah,
it's basically just going to cover this whole tree there
yeah
You just...
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah
So you just look at this picture with fuzzy eyes
and you see how big this region is
This region can be much much bigger
You can think of the thing
as starting as a solid volume
and then evolving by having
it being invaded by other stuff
Yeah,
lots of ways
Including in your interior
The what?
The coarse grained in the interior
That's right,
yes
Yeah,
you're counting everything within this little sphere here
even though the fiber in here
may be much thinner than the sphere
But the fibers are so thin
that your apparatuses cannot tell exactly
where you are in the sphere
All you know is you're somewhere in the sphere
So at the end of the day,
if you ask where am
I if I start in here
the answer to the question is you're somewhere in here
in a much bigger region
If you have infinite precise control
over either the mathematics or the measurement
then the volume of this fibered
ultra-fine filamentary structure
would be exactly the same as the original ball here
But you don't follow things that way
That's not the way you follow things in an experiment
You say,
okay,
I detect a particle
somewhere in this phase region over here
I can't tell exactly where it is
because it requires too much precision
So in that sense,
the phase space volume does expand
It's called coarse graining
and it is of course the
origin of the second law of thermodynamics
Okay,
there's one other point that I should emphasize
I don't know when and if we'll
come to it in a more thorough way
But the entropy of a system is a measure
of the volume in phase space that the system occupies
the detectable volume in phase space
Meaning to say,
if you know about a
system that it's somewhere in here
you take that volume of phase space
that volume of phase space
which corresponds to the boundaries of the region
that your knowledge tells you that the system
I'm getting tied up
You have some knowledge about the system
The knowledge of the system
is that it's somewhere in here
in this volume of phase space
The entropy is a direct measure of that volume
In fact,
it's the logarithm of that volume
Okay,
essentially that's
Now the system evolves
And what you know afterwards
is that it's somewhere in here
You're not either clever enough or precise enough
to be able to distinguish these fibers
So all you know is that
the system is somewhere in here
The phase space volume is bigger afterwards
than it started in the beginning
because you haven't followed
the details sufficiently carefully
to know precisely to distinguish
this bit of fiber from that bit of fiber
That's why entropy increases
Basically it's a statement that when
the phase space fragments like this
you lose information for
not because information is really lost
but because you have a hard time following the system
It's a technological thing
You can't follow things with sufficient precision
Okay,
that's
That's Leoville's theorem
As I said,
it is extremely fundamental to both classical mechanics
and its evolution into quantum mechanics
What I wanted to do next
Completely different direction
was to work out the equations of a particle
We have not studied very many examples
Incidentally,
you'll notice
I want to study the example of
a particle moving in an electromagnetic field
There's one thing that's new in a magnetic field
that we haven't encountered yet
And it's the existence of velocity dependent forces
So far,
the forces that we've imagined
depend on where you are but not how you're moving
When we said that there's a potential energy function,
u of x
and we differentiate it
to find the force
Well,
the left hand side is just a function of position
So the force on a system
just depends on where you are
There are forces in nature which depend on velocity
Magnetic field acting on a particle is a prime example
Incidentally,
friction is also an example
Friction is an example where the velocity of a
where the force on an
object does depend on its velocity
If it's standing still,
there's no friction force
If it's moving,
there is a friction force
Typically,
the faster it moves,
the larger the force
There's a fundamental difference between
magnetic forces and friction forces
And the simplest way to say it is that
forces due to magnetic fields,
although they're velocity dependent
are derivable from a principle of least action
They have a Lagrangian formulation
There's a conservation of energy
And there's a Hamiltonian formulation
It's just that the Lagrangian and Hamiltonian
have a new little twist to them
that I want to work out now
Forces due to electric fields
are no different
than the forces we've already studied
I think I'll come back to electric fields
I want to concentrate on magnetic fields
because there's a new phenomenon there that's interesting
So what is the force of a
particle if it's in a magnetic field?
Magnetic field is called B
It's a vector and it depends on position
B of X,
the magnetic field
What is the force of a
charged particle on a charged particle?
V cross B
Well,
actually,
Q times V cross B
where Q is the charge of the particle
Velocity cross magnetic field
It's a vector,
the cross product of two vectors
Both of these are vectors
This is the velocity of the particle
This is the magnetic field
And so it says
Everybody know what a cross product is?
I assume everybody knows
That means yes or no?
Something to do with a thumb
Yeah,
right
Right,
let's see
Right
Something to do with a thumb
I'm going to assume everybody
knows what a cross product is
although I will define it
So let's define the cross product right now
The cross product can most
easily be defined through its components
V has three components,
X,
Y,
and Z
B has three components,
X,
Y,
and Z
A cross product has three components
Here's the rule
The Z component
Let's forget Q here and let's just write the rule
The Z component of this
Let's call it the Z component of it
V cross B,
the Z component of it
Is equal to VX BY
minus VY BX
I remember one of them
I remember the Z component
And then if I want any of the other components
I just cycle
Z goes to X goes to Y
So the next one would be X
V cross B,
the X component
And I cycle
X goes to Y,
VY
Y goes to Z
minus minus
VZ BY
And the last one
V cross B
in the Y direction
is equal to
XYZ
YZX
minus VX
BY
Z
Did I get that right?
I think I got it right
That's the definition of a cross product
Now we need one other concept
We need the concept of the vector potential
The vector potential is simply a way
of writing magnetic fields
But you would think,
well
If it's just a way of writing the magnetic field
Why not just use the magnetic field?
And the answer is
You cannot write the mechanics of a charged particle
Just in terms of the magnetic field
You need the vector potential
You can of course write the mechanics
F equals MA
But you cannot write a Hamiltonian
You cannot write a Lagrangian
You cannot write even an expression for canonical momenta
You need an auxiliary quantity called
the vector potential
And the vector potential is just defined
by the condition that the magnetic field
is the curl
of the vector potential
Let's write down what curl means
because we'll need it later
The vector potential is also a vector
The magnetic field is a vector
The vector potential is a vector
What's special about things which
are curls of other things?
They have no divergence
The magnetic field is a thing which has no divergence
And that's why it's convenient to write it this way
But for our purposes
Let's imagine that the vector potential
is something fundamental that we begin with
And that the magnetic field is a derived quantity
We're going to see that
the mechanics of a charged particle
is best written in terms of the vector potential
not the magnetic field
Okay,
let's write down the definition of cross product
The cross product again
can be defined by its components
del cross A,
the z component of it
Now it's basically the same thing
except wherever you see a v up there
wherever you see a b stick an a
and wherever you see a v over there
put an upside down delta
Alright,
so this just says that this is
What does delta mean?
It just means the collection of three derivatives
Delta x,
delta y,
and delta z are just
derivative with respect to x
the derivative with respect to y
and the derivative with respect to z
I assume you all know that kind of thing
A little bit of vector calculus
But let's just write down exactly what this means
This means
derivative with respect to x
of A sub y
minus the derivative with respect to y
of A sub x
And then cycle it down
del cross A,
the x component of it
is the y derivative of A z
minus the z derivative of A y
and just cycle it down
x goes to y,
y goes to z,
z goes back to x
I won't write them all down
So
We can now write that the force
on a charged particle
due to the magnetic field
is the charge times v cross B
which is also the charge times v
cross the curl of A
I'm going to bore you a little more with this
by writing out the individual components
by writing out the z component of force here
It's a little bit tedious
but we'll need it
We'll need the expression for the z component of force
explicitly in terms of the vector potential
So let's write it out
This is just an exercise in substituting
Alright,
I want the z component of the force
F sub z
is equal to the charge
Now,
the cross product
We have the cross product,
where is it?
We have the z component of v cross B
That's v cross B y
minus v cross B y
B cross B x
But now let's just substitute
in for b cross B y
Where is it?
Oh brother
This is q
v cross B x
Now
Go to
b cross B y
b y is d z A
x minus d x A z
That's the first term
minus v y times B x
which is d y A
z minus d z A y
Well,
this is a fairly complicated expression
for the z component of force
But if you know the vector potential
you can work out what this is
It's just some vector field
You can multiply it by the velocities
and you can compute the force,
the z component of force
If you want the other components
again,
you just cycle
The x
x goes to y
y goes to z
You just cycle through
Alright
That's the force on a particle
And the equation is just Newton's equation
F equals m A
But now the new thing
is that the acceleration
doesn't only depend on the position
It does depend on the position
through the position dependence of A
but it also depends on the velocity
So these are called velocity dependent forces
because they depend on velocity
Alright
We want to formulate the theory of
a charged particle moving in a magnetic field
in the Lagrangian or Hamiltonian form
Not obvious that we can do it
It is not obvious that this is of the form
that allows us to have a Hamiltonian
a Lagrangian and so forth
or an action principle
The easiest way to confirm that
is just to make a guess
at what the action is
and then follow it through
The new thing in the action
Well,
first of all
We do expect
that if the electric charge was zero
that there would be the usual terms
Alright
So let's write the action
Let's make a guess for the action
The integral of the Lagrangian dt
Well,
first of all,
guess has the usual
mv squared over 2 dt
where v squared means
the sums of the squares of the x component
y component and z component of the velocities
The usual thing
This is what we would do for a free particle
and if the particle has no electric charge
it doesn't feel the magnetic field
And then there's another term
And the other term is as
simple as it could possibly be
We take the orbit of the charged particle
We break it up
into little segments
Each segment we call dx
also dy and dz
But let's just abbreviate it by calling it dx
Each little segment
defines a differential displacement
in dx,
dy and dz
The added term
that's first of all proportional to the electric charge
If there's no magnetic field
then obviously there is no additional term
even if there is an electric charge
The extra term is related to both the charge
and the magnetic field
But it's related through the vector potential
Where's vector potential?
Oh boy,
did I erase the most important equation?
I did
Okay
I assume you all memorized
what v cross b looks like
in terms of the vector potential
And you'll recognize it when I write it down
I didn't mean to erase it
Alright
What can you write down?
It's going to have the vector potential in it
So let's call it a sub i
The simplest thing you can write down
is the integral of the vector potential
the line integral
of the vector potential
dotted into the differential displacement dx
In other words,
what this means
is every place in space you have a vector potential
As the particle sweeps out through its trajectory
there's a contribution to its action
from each little differential displacement here
And the contribution to the action
is just take the dot product
of the vector potential
with the displacement
In other words,
the component of the vector potential
along the direction of the displacement
and add them all up
Very simple prescription
How do I know that's the answer?
Well,
I know that's the answer because it was written down
in the early parts of the 20th century
and I learned it as a student
Is that dxi?
Yeah,
dxi
Good
Or you can just write a dot dx
where you can think of both a and dx
as little vectors
One is a little vector
the other is just a vector
A dot dx can represent the dot product
of the vector potential
with the differential displacement
It doesn't seem like units are working out right
Is there a time in there?
How do you know what the units are?
Do you know what the units of A are?
Or what the units of Q are?
Well,
you could work out
You could work backwards
and you'd expect to see a time in there
A time?
And b squared
So b squared is
The first integral has a
But how can you tell me what the units are
unless we know what the units of Q are?
Okay
Or A
How do we know what the units of A are?
Well,
the units of A and the units of Q
Obviously,
the combination
Q times A is the important thing
And the combination of Q times A
has units
that are required to make this
have the same units as that
What are the units of an action,
incidentally?
Or momentum times position
Sorry,
momentum
Yeah,
momentum times x
No problem
You can always give Q the right dimensions
This is correct
In some appropriate choice of units
It depends on the conventions
In some conventions
there are pi's floating around
or speeds of light
But you can set them all equal to one
And since I'm trying to describe
a phenomenon rather than a numerical effect
Let's just set all the numerical constants equal to one
in order to absorb them
into the electric charge here
Okay
Now this is
Yeah
Yes
That's exactly what I was about to do
So this does not have the usual form
of an action
which depends on velocities and positions
The a's depend on position as a rule
But what is this dx here?
All we have to do
is divide and multiply by dt
The x by dt
That's just the x component of the velocity
So we can also write this as
a
dotted into the velocity
integral dt
Or I can write it in terms of components
a sub i
x sub i
dot dt
And now we see the usual form
What's that?
Sum over i
Yeah
Alright
So we see,
and this of course is also x sub i
dot squared
Sum over i
I'm not going to write it
Alright so we have then
a typical Lagrangian
We can write out now what the Lagrangian is
And it depends on position and velocity
the way
any respectable Lagrangian would
Lagrangian
for a particle in a magnetic field
is
one half the mass of the particle
times x sub i
dot squared
goes over x,
y,
and z
sum
plus
q
the charge of a particle
x sub i dot
times the vector potential
a sub i
What's the next step?
We have to do the same
The next step is to prove that the equation of motion for
this object is f equals m a with the right hand side being
Where is it?
qv cross b
f
equals
qv cross b
If we can do that
If we can now take the Lagrange equations
Here's the Lagrangian
Take the Lagrange equations
and see if we can prove
that the force on a particle
which is equal to mass times acceleration
that this is equal to qv cross b
If we can do that
then we're finished
We found the Lagrangian formulation of
particle in a magnetic field
So this is now an exercise
in just plugging it through
I could tell you to go home and do it
but let's do it
Let's just carry it out
There's one curious thing coming up
that we'll see in a second
First of all,
what is the canonical momentum
p sub x
Well,
it's the derivative
of the Lagrangian with respect to x dot
So let's take the x component
I now mean the x component
We could write down y and z also
That's going to be
m x dot
from here
Usual thing
Normal momentum
But then there's another term
plus q a sub x
And of course the same kind of thing
for py and pz
So we have a system now
where the canonical momentum
is not just m times v
It's m times v
plus something proportional
to the vector potential
So we have a system now
Sometimes m times x dot
is called the mechanical momentum
It's sometimes called
the mechanical momentum
Meaning to say
nothing other than that it's
mass times velocity
And the whole thing is called
the canonical momentum
So that's one new thing here
We see something new
that there's a discrepancy
between the canonical momentum
and what we naively think of
as momentum
But now let's work out
the equation of motion
Let's work out
the z component
There's three of these
But let's get to pz
is equal to m z dot
plus q a sub z
I'm going to work out
the z component of the equation of motion
What is it?
It's the time derivative of
the momentum
I'll just write it down over here
d by dt
of dl by dz dot
is equal to dl by dz
dL by dz dot
that's just pz
So we have to take
the time derivative
of this thing here
Let's write down the time derivative
It's m z double dot
That's mass times acceleration
And then
there's another term
in the time derivative of pz
It's plus q
times the time derivative
of az
Now in a moment we'll come back
and work out what the time derivative of az is
But let's go to the right hand side
of the equation
The right hand side of the equation
is
the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to z
What is it that depends on z in here?
x dot
or z dot doesn't depend on z
a
And all of the a's
a x,
a y,
and a z
all depend on
on
on z in general
So let's go through them
q
Now the first term here would be
x dot times a sub x
So we would get a term
which would be x dot
times the derivative of a sub x
with respect to z
Remember we're taking the derivative of the Lagrangian
The only thing that depends on z
are the three components of a
Let's start with the x component
x dot times a x
and differentiate it with respect to z
The next one
is plus
y dot
times the derivative of a y
with respect to z
And what's the last one?
z dot
times the derivative of a sub z
with respect to z
Okay,
all I did was differentiate
all three terms here with respect to z
Each one of them depends on z
through the components a
So
What about the left hand side?
What do I do with a sub z dot?
Let's suppose incidentally
that it's just a static magnetic field
Magnetic field not changing with time
It's just a fixed magnetic field
Does that mean that this is zero?
If it's a fixed magnetic field?
No
Because the particle moves
through the magnetic field
I don't mean when I
say it's a fixed magnetic field
I don't mean it's the same everywhere as in space
I mean it doesn't depend on time
Magnetic field varies from place to place
Particle moves through it
And because the particle moves through it
there's a time dependence
of the magnetic field
of the vector potential
at the point of the particle
So how do we calculate that?
Well,
we simply write
m
z double dot plus q
Now
a z
depends on x
the a z by the x
times x dot
plus the a y
Sorry,
what are we doing here?
Yes,
sorry,
the a z
a z,
a z
We're calculating a z dot
which is derivative of a z with respect to x
times the time rate of change of x
plus the a z
by the y
times y dot
plus the a z by the z
times z dot
That's equal
to what's in the bracket over here
equals
this
Okay
I'll let you stare at it for a minute
Remember,
the right hand side
came from explicitly differentiating
the Lagrangian with respect to z
The left hand side
came from
differentiating with respect to t
But notice they have similar form
Each one here
has a velocity times a derivative
of a
on both sides
So maybe they combine together in some nice way
Well,
first of all
you'll see that this term
and this term are the same
z dot times the a z by the z
They're the same
So they cancel
Let's get rid of them
Now what's left
Let's look at what multiplies x dot
x dot
has the a x by the z
and then when we shift
to the other side
it will have what
the a z by the x
So
it's going to have
Let's
Let's move this over
Now I forgot what it was
plus y dot
what was it
the a y by the z
yeah
partial a y with respect to z
partial a y with respect to z,
right?
Yeah
Okay,
now the term which multiplies x dot
When I translate
when I transpose it
it's going to have minus
the a z by the x
Oh,
that's starting to look familiar
And when I transpose the term
that has y dot in it
that will have minus the a z by the y
I've transposed this term over to the right hand side
and I now have
m z double dot
or mass times
the z component of acceleration
is equal to this mess over here
Well what is this mess?
This mess is not so complicated
It's got linear terms in the velocities
and what are these objects?
The magnetic field
The curl of the vector potential
In fact,
this one
is
a x y,
I think this is b y
Is it b y or minus b y?
And this one I think is minus
b x
The x dots and y dots are the components
of the velocity
If you go through it
or just go back in your
notes to where I wrote it down
in the beginning
this is just
the z component of v cross b
velocity
hmm?
Yeah
Okay
Right
v x times d z
a x minus d x a z
and so forth
Yeah
Okay,
so you see
that first of all
there does exist
a Lagrangian formulation
Here it is
for particle in a magnetic field
You need to know the vector potential
First question
Is the vector potential unique
in terms of the magnetic field?
No
You can add things to the vector potential
We'll come to that
But not right now
But if you know the vector potential
or you know a particular expression
for the vector potential
then you can write down the Lagrangian
The Lagrangian depends on the vector potential
but
the equation of motion
only depends on the magnetic field
So even if there is an ambiguity
in the vector potential
it doesn't affect
the equation of motion itself
Okay
Now we have
an example of a velocity dependent force
A force which is
v cross b
It's almost like a
friction force
It is different
The friction force
acts along the direction
of the velocity
Okay
If an object is moving in this direction
the friction force is along the same axis
What about v cross b?
Does v cross b
act along the direction of the velocity?
No
Because v cross b is perpendicular
to the velocity and to b
So
This is a big difference
A big difference
whether the velocity dependent force
acts along the direction of velocity
or perpendicular to it
If it acts along the direction of velocity
it will obviously
have the effect of either slowing it down
or speeding it up
depending on which way it's acting
Alright
But if it acts perpendicular to the velocity
it will simply change the direction of the velocity
if the force is perpendicular
and it won't change the energy
So energy conservation
we can work out now
we can work out what is the expression
for the energy
We do that by calculating the Hamiltonian
and when we've calculated the Hamiltonian
we then have
from previous theorems
the theorem that says that energy is conserved
Alright
So we can work that out
Let's work it out
I think that will just about take
us to the end of the hour
Oh,
excuse me
There's something I need to tell you
I won't be here for the next two lectures
Now
I would like to make up one of them
I think
The question is
What is a good time?
It could be this week yet
But it can't be next week
And it could be the week after
but not on Monday
Yeah,
we can do it this week
Does that work out for people?
If we were to do it,
say,
three weeks
Thursday?
I have something to say,
sure
Friday is a bad day for me
Or we can put it off
We can put it off
until I get back
and
just double up
the week that I come back
I'll be gone for
Should we wait until
Thursday?
How many cannot take it Thursday?
Well,
that's almost half the class
Supposing I were to put it off
I'll be back on the 11th
Now the 11th is probably a Monday
No,
the 11th is a Tuesday
What about Wednesday?
Hmm?
Yeah,
I was thinking about Wednesday
The 12th I think it is
Is it the 12th or 13th?
From Wednesday
No
You're probably not going to get something that works
I know that
Stay on Monday
Hmm?
Well,
we can stay on Monday
but
Yeah
No,
we'll continue
We'll continue
but at some point
we run into the next quarter
You know
Playing,
you know
Points have to move rigidly
You can't
Do you like doing a third hour
or is that just
Well,
we could do that
Another thing I have to do
as I'm supposed to fill in the missing lecture
from the first lecture
I was thinking of doing that this week
but
Did you miss the lecture?
No,
no,
we didn't miss a lecture
but they didn't
They didn't film it
You also talked to us about sexual harassment
Ha
Right
What's that?
Is every 12th going to be the last
lecture of the session?
No,
it doesn't have to be
no
I'm happy to
This is fun for me
I just do it for the fun of it
No,
I intend to keep going
until the
until sometime near Christmas
Um
But we will miss
the next two lectures
so I thought I would try to make up one
What's that?
You're going to skip two Mondays
Yeah
Two Mondays
But then we'll be back on Monday
Well,
we will be back on Monday
and we'll see
if we need to fill in
with another lecture
we'll just figure out at
that point when to fill in
We're already scheduled for the 17th
so the next Monday is
Christmas Eve
Well,
I don't think we'll do
Christmas Eve
Uh
Let's
So that means we sort of run into the wall
Yeah
Well look,
why don't we just decide this
when I get back on the
on the 17th
we'll see when we can fill in
an extra lecture
and I think that will pretty much
bring us to where we want to be
I mean,
I'm pretty comfortable
we just
today I guess or
three weeks
Yes,
three weeks from today
Right
Next lecture is the 17th
Um
Okay,
let's try to just
finish up what I was talking about here
I think I finished
Energy
Yeah,
okay
Let's do energy
So all we have to do is calculate
the Hamiltonian
Incidentally
I'm assuming that the vector potential
has no explicit time dependence
In other words
equivalently that the magnetic field
is constant in time
In that case
the Hamiltonian will be time independent
and there will be a conserved energy
The conserved energy
is surprisingly simple
when expressed in terms of the velocity
is a little more complicated when
expressed in terms of the momenta
So let's work it out
Let's first calculate
uh
P sub x as we saw before
was m x dot
plus
q a
sub x
Same thing for y and z and
I won't bother writing them down separately
Okay
The first thing we have to
do when we calculate the Hamiltonian
Actually we don't need to
We can just
Let's calculate it
not in terms of p
but in terms of x dot
Let's first do it
by calculating it in terms of velocities
to see what the expression for
energy is in terms of velocities
Alright
So what do we have to calculate
We have to calculate
p sub x x dot
plus p sub y y dot
plus p sub z
z dot
minus the Lagrangian,
right?
That's the definition of h
Take each momenta
multiply it by the corresponding velocity
and then subtract it
subtract the Lagrangian
That's a very general rule that we derived
Alright
If I plug in for the p's
their expression in terms of velocities
I'll have an expression for the energy
in terms of velocities
That won't be good for Hamilton's equations
but it will be good
for telling me what the energy is
in terms of velocities
So let's do that,
let's do that first
p sub x times x dot
That is
is
m x dot
plus q
a sub x
times x dot
Likewise for y and z
and I won't write them out
Then we have to subtract off
the Lagrangian
minus L
So subtracting off the Lagrangian means
subtracting off minus
m v squared
or m x dot squared
I'm concentrating on the x term
m x dot squared
divided by 2
and then what else?
minus
q
x dot a sub x
Well
that gives me m x dot squared over 2
the usual thing
no difference there
and look at this
q a x x dot
minus q a x x dot
They cancel
completely
So the expression for the energy
is exactly just the original
kinetic energy
So I'll just do this
just m x dot squared over 2
Likewise for y and z
The magnetic field does not contribute to the energy
when expressed in terms of velocities
It's just one half m v squared
end of story
Now why is that?
Why is that?
That's equivalent to another statement
It's equivalent to the statement
that magnetic fields do no work
What's that?
Yeah,
that's right
It's because the force is perpendicular to the velocity
So when a particle moves
in a magnetic field
the force is
perpendicular to the velocity
The force being perpendicular to the velocity
means that the magnitude of the velocity
doesn't change
A force perpendicular to a velocity
deflects an object
but doesn't change its velocity
and
So
as the particle moves along
its direction may change
but its speed doesn't
So the original expression
for its energy in terms of m x dot squared
is just the full energy
Magnetic fields do no work
which is the same statement
as the statement that the energy
when expressed in terms of velocities and so forth
is exactly the same as
it was in the first place
One half m v squared
is conserved
And you know how particles move in a magnetic field
For example,
if there's a uniform magnetic field
into the blackboard
particles move in circular orbits
with uniform speed
So the kinetic energy is conserved
That's statement number one
But in this form
you cannot use
the Hamiltonian
to write down Hamilton's equations
You have to express it in terms of
in terms of
the momenta
But that's easy.
All we have to do is
solve for the x dots
in terms of the momenta
That's easy
x dot is just
p sub x
minus q a sub x
divided by m
So
we can write down immediately
what the Hamiltonian is in terms of p's
instead of in terms of x dots
And it's just equal
p sub x
minus q a sub x
squared
over m squared
over 2m squared
Excuse me
I've just substituted
for the velocity
their expression in terms of the momenta
Yeah
It accelerates
No it doesn't
Oh it does
It does,
it does,
but radiation is a higher order
effect that's only important
when the particle is
Yeah,
it does
It certainly does radiate
But thus far
we have not even tried
to think about radiation
In order to understand radiation
we will have to formulate
Maxwell's equations
and formulate them in a Hamiltonian form
and discover that the radiation
field itself has energy
Yeah
Right
So
Yeah,
this is the radiationless approximation
You have to put the additional terms on that
to get the
total
You mean these?
Yeah,
sure
Absolutely
Plus
z term
Right
So it's a little bit odd
and a little bit surprising
because when expressed in terms of velocities
the energy just doesn't change
But when expressed in terms of canonical momenta
the expression for the energy does change
and now if we applied
Hamilton's equations
to this expression here
we would again get
precisely the same
equations of motion
What's that?
First x
Yeah
So
Yeah,
all you do is replace
the canonical moment
the momentum
by the momentum minus q a sub x
In other words
this is just a mechanical momentum here
the mx dot term
The mechanical momentum
and the canonical momentum
differ by q times a
The energy is just mx dot squared
so it's just a mechanical
you know,
it's just the square of the mechanical momentum
but you substitute the canonical momentum
if you want to do
Hamilton's equations
So here's an exercise
Take this Hamiltonian
work out Hamilton's equations
and check that you get the same
equations of motion
uh
mass times acceleration
is equal to v cross b
That's a homework assignment
Okay
Good
Music
The program is copyrighted by
Stanford University
Please visit us at
stanford.edu