This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Let's proceed on with Poisson brackets.
Phase space has a structure to it.
It's not just a bunch of P's and Q's,
but it's P's and Q's
with a certain kind of structure.
Spaces have structures.
The structures are the things which are
invariant under the various transformations that you
might want to do.
An example of the structure
that can be on a space,
if you know anything about curved
spaces and differential geometry and so forth,
the metric structure of certain,
of metrical
spaces.
The spaces of Riemann spaces are
part of the structure of those spaces.
They're characterized by a metric on the space,
a distance formula between neighboring
points.
對
Poisson structures are different than metric structures.
They're more abstract.
And they were invented largely to describe
the structure of phase space and its properties.
Its properties under transformations
which change the coordinates.
Now,
the coordinates of a phase
space are not just the q's.
The coordinates of a phase space
are the q's and the p's.
And roughly speaking,
the question,
the kind of question that you might ask is
what are the various transformations that you can do?
For example,
that mix up p's and q's that
preserve the basic structure of classical mechanics.
As I said,
this is the kind of question,
the kind of structural question,
the kind of formal question that the
French mathematicians were awfully damn good at.
It turned out to be very
important to the future of physics.
It wasn't the French who
figured out why it was important.
It was the French who
figured out how the basic structure,
the French and Hamilton basically,
who figured out what the
structure of classical mechanics is.
And it got more and more abstract.
The most concrete version was,
of course,
Newton's version.
The most abstract version,
I don't know how abstract it is.
It probably can get infinitely more abstract
than anything I'm likely to teach you.
But the most abstract end of it for our purposes is the
Poisson formulation of classical mechanics based on the idea of Poisson brackets.
What Poisson brackets do,
or what they're useful for,
is describing flows on phase space.
One kind of flow on phase space is
the motion of the phase space with time,
or the motion of the
points in phase space with time.
How the actual points evolve with time
under the influence of a particular Hamiltonian.
That's one kind of flow on phase space.
But there are other kinds of flows on phase
space that you can imagine with possibly somewhat different purposes.
For example,
we can talk about symmetries.
Now we've talked about symmetries.
The basic symmetry,
the problem for me in explaining symmetries
is not that it's hard to explain.
It's that there aren't too many symmetries.
There are too many examples in classical mechanics that
allow you a wide range of different situations to describe.
The basic symmetries of most classical mechanical
systems are rotations about various axes and translations.
Special systems with particularly simple mathematics sometimes have
some hidden symmetries that you might not have expected.
But the basic symmetries are just those.
The motions of space,
translation,
rotation.
As you move on to more advanced physics,
you discover more symmetries,
different kinds of symmetries,
symmetries among element-t particles and so forth.
But those are not for us now.
What do those symmetries have to do with flows?
Flows in phase space.
Well,
let me begin with flows in just coordinate space.
X-space.
We can think of a rotation.
We can think of rotations in space.
As defining a kind of flow in the space.
Just imagine going from here to here.
Rotating our coordinates in space.
By imagining an infinite
number of intermediate configurations.
And imagine in your head going from
one configuration to another configuration of the axes.
Of the axes of the space continuously.
Or we don't have to imagine motion of the axes.
We can actually imagine motion of a system.
Where we rotate the whole system.
We keep the axes fixed.
And rotate the whole room.
That rotation might not have anything to do
with the actual time dependence of the system.
It simply allows us to
describe mathematically what a rotation is.
A rotation is something which is built
up out of lots of little rotations basically.
And so we can think of
the idea of a coordinate transformation.
Which rotates the coordinates of
space as a kind of flow.
Likewise the translation of space.
The motion from one point moving our coordinate axes.
Not rotating them.
But translating them.
We can also think of that as being built up.
A given translation as being built
up by a lot of little translations.
Which define a flow.
It's those flows in phase space.
Not just in coordinate space.
But transformations which mix together
or potentially could mix together.
Both the P's and the Q's.
Into a richer structure.
Than just the transformations which mix up the coordinates.
I use coordinates to mean Q's or X's.
I use phase space to talk
about the P's and the Q's.
We can become interested and we will become interested.
In transformations which mix the P's and Q's.
And so it's a richer flow.
A family of transformations that we can imagine.
And those flows which move things
around in phase space in various ways.
Are described by the method of Poisson brackets.
So I try to make it a
habit of not beginning in the middle.
Even though I may have covered
something fairly completely in the previous lecture.
So I like to go back over.
Even if it means I
do it two or three times.
Let's just read through.
And review what we know about Poisson brackets.
But let's be French mathematicians.
Let's abstract.
Rather than write down the
concrete definition of a Poisson bracket.
Let's think about it from a more abstract
collection of postulates or axioms about Poisson brackets.
The Poisson brackets.
Between.
What are Poisson brackets.
What go into the Poisson brackets.
A thing that I'll call A
and a thing that I'll call B.
Both A and B are imagined to
be functions of the P's and Q's.
So we can write Poisson bracket of A of
P and Q with B of P and Q.
First of all has the
abstract property that it's anti-symmetric.
Anti-symmetric means that it changes sign
if you interchange A and B.
That's the first abstract property.
Oops.
Minus sign.
Thank you.
Most important thing.
The minus sign.
Right.
So that's abstract property number one.
Abstract property number two I won't write
down in detail unless you ask me to.
It's the linearity.
Oh let me write it down.
Supposing we have the Poisson bracket
of some combination of A and B.
Let's say alpha A,
alpha and beta are numbers.
Any numbers.
Alpha A plus beta B Poisson bracket with C is just
equal to alpha times the Poisson bracket of A with C.
Plus beta times the Poisson bracket of B with C.
So that's the property of linearity.
This is anti-symmetry.
This is linearity.
Then there's the product.
Product rule.
What kinds of things are the A's and the B's?
Capital A.
What kind of what?
Things are the A's.
Functions.
Functions of P's and Q's.
P squared plus Q squared.
Sine of P.
Whatever.
Is it real value?
Not necessarily.
But you can add it.
There's no reason why in these formulas you
can't take alpha and beta to be complex numbers.
But you can't add A's and B's.
That's all it says.
You can add A's.
Oh yes.
You can add A's and B's.
Absolutely.
Just adding the functions.
Yeah.
You can certainly add A's and B's.
They're just functions.
In classical mechanics there isn't much reason
to be thinking about complex valued functions.
But there's no reason that you can't.
And sometimes you do.
Sometimes you do.
Sometimes it's useful.
So they're just general functions
of the coordinates of momenta.
Remember the coordinates when I write down P's and
Q's I don't just mean one P and one Q.
I mean N P's and N Q's where
N is the number of coordinates of the system.
Okay.
So that's the linearity.
Then there's the product rule.
The Poisson bracket of A times B with C is
equal to A times the Poisson bracket of B with C.
Plus B.
A.
Thank you.
B.
Now I've written these formulas in a particular order here.
I've left the A on the left
here and the B on the right.
There's no reason for that.
These are just numbers.
That is to say they're
functions whose values are just numbers.
And it doesn't matter whether you multiply A times
the Poisson bracket or the Poisson bracket times A.
Mathematically speaking these things all commute which
means you can multiply them in any order.
I've written it in a form which won't mean anything to you
now but it will mean next quarter when we study quantum mechanics.
In quantum mechanics things don't commute.
And I've written in a particular order
which is still correct in quantum mechanics.
But for our purposes now A times the Poisson bracket of B and
C is just nothing but the Poisson bracket of B and C times A.
So it doesn't matter whether the B's
come first or the Poisson brackets come first.
It does matter the order that
you write down the Poisson bracket itself.
That order does matter because you have to
change the sign if you want to change them.
Yeah?
So these A's and B's have to be scalar functions?
Scalar has to do with
their properties under rotation of space.
I mean it's not a vector.
They could be components of vectors.
Vectors meaning?
I mean if they were
vectors of our matrix or something.
Oh,
oh,
oh.
We're not talking about matrix
multiplication if that's what you mean.
We're not talking about vector.
We're talking about just numerical multiplication.
Yeah.
Let's not call them scalars.
Let's call them numbers.
Numbers which simply mean that when you multiply two
numbers it doesn't matter which order you multiply them.
Yeah,
mathematicians tend to just use the word scalar.
Oh,
do they?
Yeah.
Well physicists use the word scalar to
represent the property of a system under rotation.
What's the function of these?
The alpha and beta are scalar.
But they're just functions.
Because they depend on the...
We're going to get into linguistic ambiguities here because it
may be that mathematicians use the terminology different than physicists.
Physicist means by a scalar something
which doesn't transform under rotation of space.
Okay.
Mathematicians may use the word scalar to mean a number.
Physicists often use the word
C number meaning a constant number.
It doesn't matter whether it's constant or not.
There's a whole terminology here
that we'll get confused about.
But the important thing is we're
talking about multiplications which are commutative.
But the Poisson bracket process itself is not commutative.
A times B,
A Poisson bracket with B is
not B Poisson bracket with A.
Okay,
I think we know what we mean.
Those are the basic abstract rules.
And then there's some concrete rules.
If the functions A and B are simply
P's and Q's and nothing but P's and Q's,
then we presume that there are some simple laws of Poisson
brackets or simple rules for Poisson brackets for P's with Q's,
P's with P's,
and Q's with Q's.
If we only had one P and one Q,
then we could immediately write down that P with P
with now means Poisson bracket with.
I get tired of saying take the Poisson bracket with.
With simply means take the Poisson bracket.
P with P can only be equal to zero.
That follows from the anti-symmetry P with P is equal to minus
P with P from the top equation if we interchange the order.
But if something is equal to its own negative,
it's got to be equal to zero.
Same is true with Q with...
What?
What's that?
Right.
But that doesn't tell you what the
Poisson bracket of P with Q is.
Let's take Q with P.
For that,
we need to use the definition of the Poisson bracket.
The definition in terms of derivatives.
And then we just find
out that it's equal to one.
Yeah.
Now if we put subscripts in,
we can't be quite as confident that
this is true for every I and J.
Nevertheless,
by the definition of Poisson
brackets in terms of derivatives,
remember that every Poisson bracket has in
it derivatives with respect to P and Q.
So what's the definition of the
Poisson bracket of P with P?
Well,
you can't differentiate a P with respect to Q.
You get zero.
So any time you take a Poisson
bracket of a P with a P,
you must get zero.
A Q with a Q,
But a Q with a P,
you get one or zero,
depending on whether I is equal to J.
Delta IJ.
Delta IJ is the Kronecker symbol.
So you can get a P with respect to Q.
Kronecker.
I don't know if I spelled that right or not.
No C here?
No,
no,
that was right.
I don't know.
Yeah.
It's either zero or one,
depending on whether I equal to J or not.
Namely,
it's equal to 1 if I
is equal to J and 0 otherwise.
That's the Kronecker Delta symbol.
And...
That's the,
these are the Poisson bracket relations for P and Q.
Now,
it's easy to prove that if you take,
well,
in fact,
you can prove,
you can prove almost everything about
Poisson brackets just from these relationships.
But if you also allow yourself to
use the definition of the Poisson bracket,
which can be derived,
incidentally,
from these relations.
But if you use that,
you can also immediately prove that the
Poisson bracket of any function of the Qs,
not the Ps,
with any other function of the Qs,
in other words,
if both functions only have Q in them,
that's automatically zero.
Why?
Because,
again,
every Poisson bracket will have derivatives
with respect to P and derivatives
with respect to Q in its definition.
So at least,
so it will turn out to be zero
if there's nothing to differentiate with respect to P,
so to speak.
So this will be zero.
Likewise,
any function of P with any other function
of P will also be equal to zero.
It's only when you take Poisson
brackets between functions of P with functions,
in which at least one of them
has both P and Q in it.
No,
that's not right.
What do we have to say?
Something on one side has to
mismatch something on the other side.
There's got to be a P on one side and
a Q on the other side to get anything non-zero.
Okay.
So that's a collection of rules.
There are more rules,
but they all follow from these.
There's no independent rules.
For example,
supposing we take the Poisson bracket
of any function of Q with P.
Poisson bracket of any function of Q with P.
What is that equal to?
Well,
I'll tell you right now what it's equal to,
and then we'll try to prove it.
That is equal to the derivative
of F with respect to Q.
So taking a Poisson bracket with P,
is the same as differentiating with respect to Q.
We can see that in a number of ways.
One way of seeing it is just use the definition,
but another way of seeing it is here.
We can prove it by mathematical induction.
Let's prove it for all polynomials,
F of Q.
If we prove something like
this for every conceivable polynomial,
it will be true for every function.
Every function can be arbitrarily well
approximated by a sufficiently complicated polynomial.
So,
the linearity would tell us we
need to only prove it for monomials.
So,
let's prove it for some monomials.
Let's take one.
Let's take F of Q equals one.
What does this equation say
for F of Q equals one?
It says the Poisson bracket of one.
One is a function.
It's a perfectly good function.
It doesn't vary,
but it is a function.
One with P must be equal to
the derivative of one with respect to Q.
What is the derivative of one with respect to Q?
Zero.
Now,
how do I prove this?
I'll tell you how I can prove it.
One is just as good as
F of P is without Q.
Yeah.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
But I didn't prove these,
but let me give you
a simple proof of this one.
The simple proof of this one
is to use the product formula.
one squared with P
is equal to,
one with one P
plus one P with one,
which is equal to twice
Poisson bracket of one with P.
But one squared is just one.
So this says that the Poisson bracket of one with
P is twice the Poisson bracket of one with P.
That proves it's zero.
Okay.
So,
indeed,
the first one is right.
Let's go to the next monomial.
Q with P.
That's the next more complicated monomial for F.
Q with P should be equal to
the derivative of Q with respect to Q,
which is just equal to one.
But that's certainly true.
That is the defining property of Q with P.
Let's just go one more.
Q squared with P.
Q squared with P,
for that we use the product formula again.
And that gives us Q with QP
plus QP with Q.
Plus Poisson bracket of Q with P is just one.
So this just gives us two Q.
And that happens to be the product formula.
And that's the derivative of
Q squared with respect to Q.
All right.
So by a process,
of course,
we use mathematical induction to prove
it for Q to the nth.
Once you've proved it for Q to the nth,
then you use linearity to prove it for every polynomial.
And then to go from
polynomials to arbitrary differentiable smooth functions,
you can use the fact that
any smooth function can be approximated arbitrarily.
And that's done really well by a polynomial.
So,
in fact,
we see that Poisson bracketing with
P is simply another way to differentiate.
Likewise,
differentiating with respect to P is the
same as taking the Poisson bracket with Q.
Notice there's a slight difference in
the order of Poisson brackets here.
To differentiate with respect to Q,
you take the Poisson bracket with
P with P on the right-hand side.
To differentiate with respect to P,
you put the Q first.
All right.
So that's another property.
Yeah?
So are you assuming that Poisson
brackets are continuous in each variable?
Yeah.
So that also...
Assuming everything is continuous,
functions are...
Every function is continuous,
differentiable,
multiply differentiable.
Um...
I'm assuming that.
Yeah.
All right.
So we have our...
One could say we have an algebra of Poisson brackets that
characterize the relationships between P's and Q's in the phase space.
Now,
we add to that another postulate
about the time evolution of a system.
And that postulate,
again,
can be derived...
It can be completely derived from Hamilton's equations.
We've derived it.
We've derived it at least twice,
as I remember.
But let's just write it down.
It can be just added to
these postulates as one more postulate.
And it is that the time derivative,
A dot,
of any function of P and Q...
Now,
let's just remember what that means.
We have the phase space,
which is...
Which is...
Coordinate ties by P's and Q's.
We have points of phase space moving through the
phase space under the equations of motion of a system.
And as they move through the phase space,
the value of A of P and Q
will change along the orbit of the phase point.
That's what A dot means.
The rate of change of A of P and Q...
Because you're moving along the orbit in phase space.
That time derivative is the
Poisson bracket of A with H.
This basically sets the pattern that a flow...
A flow applied to a function...
We have a function on the phase space.
And we apply the flow to it.
I don't know.
We apply the flow to it.
That causes the flow.
We have the function to change
as we move along the flow.
That flow is characterized as
a Poisson bracket with something.
That something happens to be the Hamiltonian if
we're talking about the genuine flow with time.
In other words,
the real flow of the system as time evolves.
But we may just be interested in some mathematical
flow that has nothing to do with the time evolution,
but just has to do with the fact,
for example,
that we're studying some symmetry,
which might correspond to a change of coordinates
through a sequence of intermediate coordinates,
coordinate configurations.
Yeah?
From an abstract standpoint,
without bringing in Hamilton,
does this basically assume that P's
and Q's are functions of time,
basically?
Mm-hmm.
We didn't want to think about...
Yeah.
But of course we could apply...
Yes.
But we could just apply
this to the P's and Q's
and see that they're functions of
time just by saying that P dot...
P dot is Poisson bracket of P with H.
And then if we know H...
If we know what H is
as a function of P and Q,
let's,
for example,
let's just suppose...
Let's just see what happens if our
Hamiltonian happens to be P squared over 2M.
And we apply...
We apply this to P dot.
It tells us that P dot,
time derivative of P,
is the Poisson bracket of
P with P squared over 2M.
Well,
that's zero because of a formula,
which I think I have erased,
which says that the Poisson
bracket of any function of P
with any other function of P is zero.
Okay?
So that's zero.
That tells us momentum conservation.
On the other hand,
Q dot...
is Q with P.
Now we use the product formula.
We use the product formula.
We have P squared here and Q here.
The product formula can be
used to tell us that this...
that this is just P over M.
We have P squared over 2M.
That gives us...
A P with a Q is 1.
Well,
you know how to do it.
You know how to do this.
Just gives us a P over M.
Without ever using anything other
than the algebra of these functions,
the algebra of these Poisson brackets,
we can conclude that the Poisson bracket
of Q with P squared over 2M
is P over M.
And that tells us that Q dot...
Excuse me.
That Q dot is P over M.
And that,
of course,
is the velocity as a function of momentum
for a non-relativistic particle with
Hamiltonian P squared over 2M.
All right.
So without knowing Hamilton's equations,
we could derive the equations,
Hamilton's equations,
from the algebra of these Poisson brackets.
Okay.
Now let's come to a wider class of transformations.
Yes.
Just a little pinch on that.
You said non-relativism.
Does this actually hold up in relativity?
Mm-hmm.
Yep.
But it's a little more complicated.
Yes,
it does.
These basic formulas hold for every
physical system that I know of.
I don't know of any physical
system where these basic formulas don't hold,
including general relativity,
including quantum field theory,
well,
in the appropriate form in quantum mechanics.
The appropriate form in quantum mechanics they hold.
But for all classical systems,
these formulas absolutely hold.
Sorry,
field theory,
electromagnetism,
everything.
Okay.
Now let's move on to symmetries.
What are symmetries?
Symmetries are coordinate,
are transformations,
transformations of a system which don't change the dynamics.
Now,
in the cases we've studied up till now,
symmetries were typically of the
form changes of the variables q
without mixing in the p's.
For example,
rotations of space.
They don't mix up the x's and the y's.
They don't mix in the
momenta with the x's and y's.
Could there be more interesting symmetries of
nature which do mix the p's and q's?
And if they do,
what are the rules and what are the laws
which allow you to mix up p's and q's
and preserve the structure of classical mechanics?
That's the question.
What are the allowable transformations that
don't screw up mechanics so badly
that it becomes unrecognizable?
Recognizable means that it has the Poisson form.
So that's the question we want to ask.
What are the allowable transformations on phase space?
Allowable transformations mean they don't ruin
this Poisson structure that we've written down.
If you were just to take
a bunch of p's and q's,
which satisfy this algebra of Poisson brackets
and make arbitrary transformations
Let's do it this way.
Let's suppose we have a
single p and a single q.
Now,
let me make a transformation.
I'm going to make a new
transformation to new p's and q's,
capital P,
which is going to be twice little p,
and capital Q,
which is twice little q.
Does this preserve the Poisson bracket structure?
It does not.
Let me show you why.
Let's calculate the Poisson bracket
of big P with big Q.
Well,
that's easy.
I don't even have to do any work here.
I just know that this is the Poisson
bracket of twice little p with twice little q.
What's that?
It's the wrong answer.
It does not preserve the
form of the Poisson bracket relations.
Let me try something else.
Instead of big P equals twice little p,
let's take it to be one half little p.
Now what happens?
What's the Poisson bracket of big P with big Q?
This formula has preserved
the structure of Poisson brackets.
If I do this transformation on the p's and q's,
it's not necessarily a symmetry of a physical system,
but it is another set of coordinates
which has exactly the same Poisson bracket relations
as the original p's and q's.
It's kind of interesting.
Well,
I've done that.
So what happens when I turn to the phase space
is I have squeezed it in
one direction by a factor of 2
and stretched it in the other
direction by a factor of 2.
And that has preserved the
structure of the Poisson bracket relations.
Stretching both directions by a factor
of 2 did not preserve the relations.
How about the following?
Supposing I...
Let's try another example.
Let's take...
It seems like conservation of volume and mass.
It's basically conservation of area.
Yeah.
But it's conservation...
It's a little more complicated.
Once you leave the domain of
just one p and one q,
it's more complicated.
But for one p and one q,
the transformations that we're talking about
are the ones that preserve areas.
For more p's and more q's,
it's more complicated.
But let's just do one or two more examples.
Let's take...
Big P is...
Let's rotate p into q.
Rotate p into q.
In other words,
we have the p-q axes and we rotate.
Let's take big P equals cosine theta
little p plus sine theta little q.
And let's take big Q equal minus sine
of theta little p plus cosine theta little q.
This is the form of a rotation in phase space.
It's a rotation in phase
space where you've rotated the axes.
From what I just told you about areas,
it's quite clear that this also
should preserve the structure of Poisson brackets.
Let's check it.
Let's calculate the Poisson bracket
of big P with big Q.
Do I have to check the Poisson
bracket of big P with big P?
Big P with big P.
This is linguistically the hardest part.
I'm sorry,
you're going to have to do this lecture for me.
Though I have to check the
Poisson bracket of big P with...
Too many Bs and Ps.
Big P with big P.
What's that?
By the linearity it all works.
It all just comes by.
Well,
it's just a big P with big P.
Antisymmetry tells me it's zero.
Big P with big P has to be the same
as big P with big P in the opposite order.
That tells me it's zero.
Antisymmetry tells me big P with big P is zero.
It tells me big Q with big Q is zero.
It's only big P with big Q
that I've got to watch out for.
Okay,
so let's just do it.
So that's going to be...
Big Q with big P equals
cosine...
Sorry,
sine...
Sine theta...
Let's begin with Qs.
All right.
Cosine theta Q plus sine theta P.
That's this one here.
There's one of them minus,
one of them is minus,
right?
This one is minus.
And then the other one is cosine theta P.
Plus sine theta Q.
All right,
the only combinations which give me anything are a
Q with a P and a P with a Q.
Let's first take the Q with the P over here.
That's going to have cosine
squared theta in front of it.
Cosine squared theta plus some bracket of Q with P.
Plus some bracket of Q with P is one.
And then we're going to have minus...
Sine squared theta.
That's coming from here.
But what's the plus some bracket of P with Q?
Minus one.
So that corrects this sine here
and makes it plus sine squared.
And gives us a one again.
All right,
so the rotation of coordinates
preserve the plus some bracket structure.
The stretching of one coordinate and the squeezing
of the other coordinate by the same factor...
It didn't have to be two,
incidentally.
That will preserve the plus some bracket structure.
On the other hand,
other kinds of transformations will not preserve it.
In particular,
those that don't preserve the area.
So there are those which do and those which don't.
Those transformations which preserve
the entire class of them...
And they can be much more complicated than this.
In general,
for arbitrary numbers of P's and Q's...
The transformations which preserve
the plus some bracket structure...
Are called canonical transformations.
Canonical.
Canonical transformations are those which keep intact...
The relations between...
The plus some bracket relations between P's and Q's.
If they keep the relation between P's and Q's...
Then they will keep all the
plus some bracket relations between P squared,
Q squared,
P...
Whatever you have.
So what's the equation of motion?
What's that?
The equation of motion should be unchanged.
Yeah,
but you have to remember that when you change...
That the Hamiltonian has to be
expressed in terms of the new variables.
Yes,
that's correct.
So when you generate the...
That's right.
The equation of motion.
These are really examples of gauge transformations?
These are not gauge transformations.
No,
these are canonical transformations.
They're not gauge transformations.
They'reCRIKING
They're not redundancies of a description.
They're just changes of the description to new coordinates.
You're 않을GE ко worrying that you areÖ闪
The
gauge
transformation drags something on to
the existing space … 사용 Those
not called gauge transformations.
Gauge
transformations working to access the cardinal regulars.
Translations
of a definite meaning.
Now,
the point is,
if you start with canonical p's and q's,
and you do canonical transformations
on them,
they stay canonical.
Now,
that's a tautology.
But to make it not a tautology,
what do you mean by canonical?
You mean these Poisson bracket relations.
These are the canonical
Poisson bracket relations.
If after transformation all of
the Poisson bracket relations are kept
intact,
then it's called a canonical transformation.
Okay.
I have a general question about,
must it preserve the Poisson bracket to be a canonical
transformation,
as opposed to the canonical transformation?
I guess.
Well,
let's say if you have
any two sets of p's and,
you know,
small p's and
small q's and big p's and big q's.
With big p's and big q's being
functions of the small p's and small q's.
Okay.
There's changes of coordinates,
is what they are.
There are changes of p-q coordinates.
So you might have two different
sets of coordinates of different systems.
No,
no,
no.
We're talking about different
coordinates for the same system.
That's what we're talking
about.
Different coordinates for the same system.
And by coordinates I now mean coordinates
on phase space.
So we're talking about different representations
of the same system by different
choices of axes or different choices
of coordinates on the same phase space.
So you can't go back and forth?
You can't go from arbitrarily one
phase space to any other phase space?
No,
no,
no.
We're talking about the same system.
All right,
good.
Yeah,
these are changes of description
rather than changes of system.
Okay?
Changes of description
of a given system.
Right,
we must keep that in mind.
It doesn't mean anything,
for example,
to change the coordinates from a harmonic oscillator
to a system of ten-tenths of a second.
Ten-tenths of a second to the twenty-third molecules,
it doesn't mean anything.
You don't necessarily have a canonical
transformation that transforms one totally different system
to another.
It doesn't mean anything.
I mean,
if it does mean something,
we have to make up a definition
for what it means.
Here we're talking about p's and
q's which are really functions of
the original p's and q's,
which means they're just re-descriptions of the same system.
Yeah?
Aren't they just characterized by dimension?
Yes.
I mean,
n is 5,
there's a whole set of
canonical transformations for 5p's and 5q's.
Yeah.
The phase space of n degrees of
freedom are all isomorphic to each other.
But still,
you don't—nevertheless,
when you're talking about canonical transformations,
you're talking about the changes
of description of a given system.
Yeah,
but the different phase spaces,
all with the same number of degrees of freedom,
are isomorphic to each other.
That's correct.
If it works on one,
it works on another.
Yeah,
yeah.
But still,
you don't transform between systems.
Right.
Okay.
All right.
Now we want to come
towards the heart of the discussion,
the subject of symmetries itself.
Can I ask a question?
Mm-hmm.
Is there any way of expressing the
necessary and sufficient conditions for something to
be a canonical transformation,
other than the way you put it,
or are you going to go
for that?
Um.
This is the necessary and sufficient condition,
that the P's and Q's preserve their Poisson
bracket structure.
That is the necessary.
Now,
you're asking if you give me a certain—well,
what are you asking?
I guess is there another way of expressing it
in some way other than that's of some general
purpose?
Yeah.
Yes.
There is another way of expressing
it that is of great general interest,
but is also
not completely general.
We tend to build transformations,
not all of them,
but we tend to build transformations
out of infinitesimal transformations,
out of small steps.
Okay?
If we're talking about an infinitesimal transformation,
I'll explain exactly what I mean by an infinitesimal
transformation in a moment,
but I think you know what I mean,
though.
Yeah.
If we're talking about infinitesimal transformations,
then yes,
there is a way to describe them,
a unique,
special way to describe them,
which we're about to come to now.
So if we can build up
the transformations out of infinitesimal transformations—and
what is an infinitesimal transformation?
It means one—well,
let's just write down what it means.
Okay.
It means q is almost exactly equal to little q,
but with a very small deviation,
and that
small deviation we'll just call delta sub q,
delta of q,
and this,
of course,
is a function
of the q's and the p's.
It just means the deviation from a trivial transformation,
big q equals little q,
is
infinitesimal.
In practice,
what it means is in their formulas,
we will drop things proportional to quadratic
and higher powers of the deltas.
It means that small quantities mean quantities which
are so small that we can drop higher
powers in them.
That's what we'll always mean by an infinitesimal operation,
that we can drop higher powers.
Now.
We can always build transformations out of small quantities.
We can build sequences of little transformations for
each one of which we can drop higher powers,
but then we have to combine them together,
and sometimes that makes something more complicated.
But we can test out very easily
what are the rules for infinitesimal canonical transformations.
Okay.
I won't bother writing down that
it's a function of p and q.
All right.
Let's just remember that
the deltas are themselves functions.
They're functions,
but they're small such that we
can ignore higher powers of them.
All right.
Let's first write down the condition
that this be a canonical transformation.
Incidentally,
of course,
there are some indices here.
I'll suppress the indices up until the last step.
Let's write down the condition
that this be a canonical transformation.
All right.
It just says that...
Let's just do it as if it
was just one p and one q.
And we can fill in the gaps later.
Okay.
Um.
All right,
so let's weigh up y1 plus y2.
Let's do it here.
We'll count all these together.
Okay.
Coming down to,
where on the bar,
what's the characterized from of the scheematical
bege drops and every drop here.
And it says that y is no constant constant.
Walmart mathematical numbers don't just go round and round.
So any hhere,
if we put 100 hundred dollars,
we have nothing,
we haveolutely zero odds
Anything of y is going to get anywhere.
We know the autism or some more Laura Sal's.
Therefore let's also separate into the fairness.
All right.
plus the Poisson bracket of Q with delta P.
I've just stuck in for big Q,
Q plus delta Q.
For big P,
P plus delta P.
And then use linearity to expand it out.
I've left out one term.
I've left out the Poisson bracket
of delta Q with delta P,
but that's already quadratic in small quantities.
Quadratic in small quantities are
too small to be significant.
So this is our formula.
Now,
what do we want to be true?
We want this to be equal to this.
So a necessary and sufficient condition,
then,
is that delta Q with P should
be equal to minus Q with delta P.
Let me show you how to satisfy that.
This actually is necessary and sufficient,
but it's not hard to
show that it's necessary and sufficient.
But let me just show you the construction.
What do we do?
We write that delta Q
is equal to delta P.
It's equal to some small number.
The epsilon is just a small number in the problem.
Delta Q,
delta P are all proportional to the same small number.
I introduced explicitly the small number so that I'll know,
so I'll keep track of it.
Times the Poisson bracket of Q with something.
With what?
With an object that's called
the generator of the canonical transformation.
G of P and Q.
And delta P is equal
to epsilon times P with G.
Another way to say it
is that every infinitesimal canonical transformation
is characterized by a function G of P and Q,
which itself defines a flow.
Is it the same or reverse in order?
Same order.
This is a kind of flow.
A coordinate transformation,
in particular an infinitesimal coordinate transformation,
is a kind of flow on the phase space.
You take every point and
you shift it a little bit.
That's a flow on the phase space.
And flows on the phase
space are characterized by things called
generators.
Generators are functions of P and Q,
and they characterize how the flow takes place.
Let me prove now the theorem.
I'm going to prove the theorem that
says that if delta Q and delta P
are obtained by Poisson brackets with a generator,
then this will always be true.
It goes the other way also.
This is not hard to prove.
First of all,
what is the Poisson bracket of
Q with G of P and Q?
Remember,
taking a Poisson bracket with Q is
the same as differentiating with respect to P.
What is this?
This is dQ by dQ,
dG by dP minus,
yeah,
this is just epsilon dG by dP.
Just using the definition of Poisson bracket now.
dQ by dQ,
dG by dP,
that just gives you dG by dP.
And then dQ by dP,
ah,
that's zero.
What about this one?
This one is equal to minus epsilon dG by dQ.
So now we have specific formulas
for delta P and delta Q.
Here they are.
Let's plug them into this formula over here.
What's delta Q?
Delta Q is epsilon dG by dP.
Epsilon Poisson bracket of dG by dP with P.
And that should equal minus Poisson
bracket of Q with delta P.
What's delta P again?
Delta P is minus dG by dQ,
right?
Epsilon.
All right,
the minus signs cancel themselves out.
I hope.
And what is the Poisson bracket with P?
It just differentiates.
It just differentiates with respect to Q.
So this is just the second derivative
of G with respect to P and Q.
What's Poisson bracket with Q?
Derivative with respect to P.
This is identically,
the left side and the right
side are identically equal to each other.
They're identically equal to each other,
each one being the second derivative of
G with respect to P and Q.
So...
Okay,
so here's what we find.
We find that flows which are generated by Poisson
bracketing with respect to a generator always define canonical transformations.
A special case of this is the Hamiltonian flow.
Let's just look at this equation here.
What does this say?
Supposing we were talking about
the time motion of a system.
The time motion of a system is Q
dot equals Poisson bracket of Q with H.
Well,
if I write that Q dot
is delta Q by delta T,
and I just think of
delta T as a small epsilon.
Let's put epsilon here.
In other words,
I change the time interval by amount epsilon.
Then the Hamiltonian flow is exactly the same.
It's exactly the same as the
sort of thing I've written here.
Hamiltonian evolution of a
system is a canonical transformation.
In other words,
the coordinate transformations of P's and Q's which are generated by the actual
flow of the system is itself a special case of a canonical transformation.
Furthermore,
all canonical transformations can be generated by picking
some generator as if it were the Hamiltonian.
Imagining in our mind,
a Hamiltonian which caused the flow,
which took the points from one to another,
that defines the most
general class of canonical transformations.
Now...
The most general?
Hamiltonian?
I'm sorry,
say that one more time.
Yeah,
the most general...
I think I'm saying something a little too strong.
I'm not sure.
Maybe I'm not.
Every canonical transformation that I know...
Now I know I'm saying something correct.
Every canonical transformation that I know of...
I think it's true...
can be generated
from infinitesimal canonical transformations.
If it can be generated
from an infinitesimal canonical transformation,
then it's got a generator G of P and Q,
which allows it to be constructed in this way.
So,
if you want a small canonical transformation,
which just displaces the points a little bit,
you just take Poisson brackets
of the variables you're interested in
with the generator,
and that gives you the
changes in the phase-space coordinates.
That's the basic idea.
That all motions on the phase-space,
whether they have to do with the actual time evolution,
or whether they just have
to do with coordinate transformations,
moving points around,
are of the form of
canonical transformations generated by generators.
The Hamiltonian being a space,
is a special case.
Yeah?
Are there any restrictions on what the Hamiltonian would be?
It looks like G is
just the Hamiltonian for another system.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
It is.
It's just that it could
be the Hamiltonian for another system.
And the Hamiltonian could just be some arbitrary flow.
That's right.
What the Hamiltonian is,
of course,
is really determined by the physics of a system,
experiment and all that kind of thing.
But the mathematics cannot tell
you whether G is the Hamiltonian
or H is the Hamiltonian.
You do an experiment to find out.
Okay,
now we can discuss,
if the transformations which we are allowed to do,
which preserve the structure of mechanics,
are canonical,
then what is the subclass of those?
For a given system with a given Hamiltonian,
what is the subclass that are called symmetries?
Symmetries are the canonical transformations
which don't change the Hamiltonian.
Just like in the case of Lagrangians,
we said that the
symmetries were the coordinate transformations
which didn't change the Lagrangian,
now,
the more general idea becomes
coordinate transformations in phase space,
which are canonical,
and which don't change the energy.
Those are the symmetries of a mechanical system.
We can actually say that in a somewhat geometric way.
Here's our phase space.
Oh,
incidentally,
I didn't keep track of the little indices i.
You can go home and do the derivation over again.
Keeping track of all the indices i and j,
and see that the construction still works.
It's more or less obvious.
Okay.
But let's imagine here's our phase space,
multidimensional phase space.
Now,
the Hamiltonian corresponds to some flow.
And it's also a canonical transformation.
The infinitesimal small time flow from one point to another
is the canonical trans...
is generated by the Hamiltonian.
And the full transformation over
a period of time is canonical.
Now,
let's imagine there's some other quantity,
a generator g,
that generates another flow.
It's not to be thought of
as the time evolution of the system.
It's just another flow on the phase space.
Just another motion on the phase space,
which moves points through the
phase space in some other way.
In general,
you can see from this picture
that the new flow,
the green flow,
will change the value of the energy along the flow.
But supposing it's true,
supposing it's true
that the green flow,
g,
and the black flow,
h,
the Hamiltonian of the system,
are in just such a way
that the flow along the g direction
doesn't change the energy,
causes the energy not to change at all.
In other words,
flows the system along surfaces of constant energy.
Then it's called a symmetry.
It's a symmetry,
g is a symmetry,
if the flow created by g doesn't change the energy.
What's the condition for that?
This is easy.
Hmm?
Right,
right.
Geometrically the condition,
but in a multidimensional space it's not so obvious.
Alright.
Here's how q and p change under the flow.
Let's take a general function of p and q.
Let's take a general function of p and q
and see how it changes along this flow.
I'm not going to call it,
I'm going to call the function a again.
Let's call it a.
How does a change along the flow?
Well,
it changes dA by dp
times delta p
plus dA by dq
delta q.
But what is delta p and delta q?
Here we have them.
They're proportional dg by dp and dg by dq.
So this is,
let's see,
delta p is dg by dq,
dg by dp.
In other words,
not too surprisingly,
the change in any function of a is just proportional,
there's an epsilon in here,
isn't there,
is just epsilon times the
Poisson bracket of a with g.
This is exactly the same formula
we use for time derivatives of things
when g was the Hamiltonian.
The change of functions along the Hamiltonian flow
is just the Poisson bracket with the Hamiltonian.
The change of an arbitrary function along any flow
is just the Poisson bracket
with the generator of the flow.
That's what these generators do.
Poisson brackets with the generators create the flow
and they give you the derivatives
or the way the functions change along the flow.
All right,
so then,
what does it say
that the energy does not change along the flow g?
It says that the Poisson bracket of
h with g is equal to zero.
It says that h does
not change along the flow g.
All right?
If I were to just plug in here for a,
h,
everywheres,
this would just be the Poisson bracket
of h with g.
So this is the condition that the energy doesn't change
along the symmetry flow g.
But now we can read this the other way also.
This also tells us that g
with h is equal to zero.
h with g and g with h
are just the negative of each other.
And what does this equation say?
This says that the time derivative of g vanishes.
All right?
Remember,
the other equation was that
a with h equals a dot.
The same equation which says that
h doesn't vary along the flow g
says that g doesn't vary along the flow h.
But what does this equation say?
It says that a is conserved.
So if you have a Hamiltonian
and you have a generator g,
a quantity,
a quantity g,
which has the property that the flows created by g
don't change the energy,
then the flows created by the energy,
that's the time dependence of the system,
don't change g.
This is kind of the reciprocal relation,
an interesting reciprocal relationship.
If you have two quantities,
h and g,
and you say h is the
Hamiltonian which generates the time dependence,
and g doesn't change the Hamiltonian,
then if you switch the system
and you said g was the Hamiltonian,
and h was just some arbitrary thing,
I think you get the point.
I'm going to use too many words to say it.
There's a parallel relationship
between quantities which are conserved
and the energy of the system.
Parallel,
symmetrical relationship between them.
I think this would be a good point to stop.
This is a very,
very highly abstract business,
and it does have to do with the fact that,
I don't want to start with
the intrinsic structure of classical mechanics,
but as I said to you time and again,
the place where the real glory of
this comes forth is in quantum mechanics.
It's very abstract in classical mechanics.
It's extremely concrete in quantum mechanics,
much easier to understand in quantum mechanics.
What could be an example?
Of what?
In quantum mechanics.
Angular momentum and energy.
H could be,
let's see,
h could be the energy of a system.
It could be p squared over 2m plus,
I don't know,
function of x squared plus y squared,
let's say.
That could be h.
g could be the angular momentum.
Angular momentum is xpy minus ypx.
If you calculate the Poisson bracket between this and this,
you'll find that it's zero,
corresponding to,
let's do that.
Oh,
yeah,
that's going to be complicated.
Let's do it for a free particle.
It's going to be a little
too complicated to do in general.
Yeah,
let's do it for a free particle.
Okay,
so let's take p squared over 2m,
and that means px squared plus py squared.
Do you mind if I set m equal to 1?
No.
px squared over 2 plus py squared.
That's the Hamiltonian.
g is the angular momentum.
The expression for the angular,
this is two dimensions,
just for simplicity,
two dimensions.
g is the angular momentum.
That's xpy minus ypx.
Okay.
Now we want to start calculating
Poisson brackets between g and h.
This is not too bad.
Remember,
all p's...
All p's.
Hmm?
It's all p's.
No,
this isn't p's.
Oh,
yes.
Right.
I didn't see the q.
Yup.
X's and y's are q's.
Good.
All right.
It wouldn't be true if
I just took xpy or ypx,
but I'm going to do it.
But it's a combination,
xpy minus ypx.
Okay,
so let's do it.
Poisson bracket of g with h.
Okay,
so what is that?
It's going to have xpy with px,
and it's going to have xpy with py.
How about let's do xpy with py first of all.
Do I get anything from that?
The Poisson bracket of an
x with a py is 0.
Remember,
the only non-zero Poisson brackets that you begin with
are x with px and y with py.
When I start calculating xpy with py,
I'm not going to get anything.
py Poisson bracket with py is 0,
x with py is 0.
So there's nothing on this side
which has a non-zero Poisson bracket
with anything over here.
The only non-zero Poisson brackets
are x with px and y with py.
Okay,
so let's begin with x with px.
This is going to be then
Poisson bracket of xpy with px squared over 2.
And then the other term will be minus ypx,
with py squared over 2,
with py squared over 2.
Okay,
how about xpy with px squared over 2?
Well,
we use the product formula here.
We take out one term as just py
with x px squared over 2.
Then there's another term where the x comes out,
and py gets Poisson with px.
But what's Poisson of xpy with px?
So this is the only
term coming from the first bracket.
py times x with px squared.
What's x with px squared?
Remember what Poisson bracketing with a q does.
It differentiates.
So x with px squared gives what?
Just px.
This whole thing is just py px.
It's just py px.
What about this one?
We'll get a px on the outside,
and we'll get y with py squared,
which will be py,
which will just be minus py px.
So this is an example.
This is an example of two generators which have zero...
I keep wanting to use the word commute.
In quantum mechanics,
it would be commute.
But let's not use that terminology.
This is an example of two quantities,
two generators,
which have vanishing Poisson bracket between them.
The implication is the following.
If the Hamiltonian is px squared plus py squared,
then the angular momentum is conserved.
If we invented a new system
where the Hamiltonian happens to be this thing...
Crazy Hamiltonian,
but let's do it anyway.
A new system where the Hamiltonian is this thing,
then this object would be conserved.
The Poisson bracket between them is zero,
so whichever one is the Hamiltonian,
the other one is conserved.
Okay.
And again,
the idea that the Hamiltonian doesn't change
under a transformation,
that is the basic idea of a symmetry,
that a symmetry is an
operation which doesn't change the energy.
Okay.
But we see here there's a
rich structure to the whole thing,
a much richer structure than...
than...
well,
than you might have expected.
Okay,
any questions about this?
And then I want to move on to...
I want to move back and
review what we said the first time.
Yeah?
You said you...
You have a system where g is the Hamiltonian.
Where it said...
yeah,
oh.
What does that mean?
Let's see what it means.
To see what it means,
it means...
it simply means let's find out the
equations of motion that go with it
and ask how a particle would move under the Hamiltonian.
And that's the influence of that Hamiltonian.
Well,
let's see.
I never worked it out.
Here's a Hamiltonian.
New system.
Hamiltonian is x p y minus y p x.
Let's work out Hamilton's equations.
Hamilton's equations say
x dot is equal to
the Poisson bracket of x with h.
What's the Poisson bracket of x with h?
Can anybody read this off?
Where does it come from?
Which term?
The only term in h which can
contribute to a Poisson bracket with x
is a term that has p x in it.
So,
this looks like it's going to be minus y.
x dot equals minus y.
And what about y dot?
y
دارس
اكوت
X
Anybody have any idea what kind of motion this is?
Circle,
circular motion.
It just describes something going in a circle.
So you're saying that h is
equal to what was the generator?
Yeah,
I'm into change now.
So let's make up a new system where the Hamiltonian
just happens to be x p y minus y p x.
And what do I get?
I get a system which just moves
in a circle counterclockwise direction like so.
So if we had some mechanical system
which could only move in a circle,
we would describe it by this Hamiltonian,
but then we would find that p
x squared plus p y squared was conserved.
And in fact that would be true.
You've gone through these with
just a p and a q,
and what one confirms,
my sense is,
you're always talking about the same index.
Well...
And that for each index,
the transformation could be different?
For each index,
the transformation could be different,
yes.
Yeah,
yeah.
I understand,
but it's more complicated than that.
The transformation...
No,
there's one...
Okay.
It's not that there's a transformation for each index.
There's a set of transformations...
Well,
there is a transformation for each index,
I take that back.
q i is a function not
just of q i and p i,
but of all the other functions.
All the q's and p's.
Okay.
So there's a transformation for each index,
but each transformation in general
involves all the q's and p's.
Yeah.
Right.
What's the condition for getting p if you know q?
Say it again.
I remember what it was when we were back in...
in Lagrangian,
but in this form,
what is the momentum that's not canonical with a q?
How do you define it?
Oh,
how do you get the momentum in terms of q's?
I think for this system,
p y is actually equal to x,
and p x is equal to minus y.
Let's see.
Can we see why that is?
I'm talking about the general definition.
I remember...
You mean how do we find
the p's in terms of the velocities?
Yeah,
if you have a q,
how do you know the...
I think the question you're asking is how do
you know the p's in terms of the velocities?
Okay,
yeah.
I think that's the only question I
can think of that you could ask.
It's not always mv.
It's not always mv,
no.
But you go to Hamilton's equations.
You go to Hamilton's equations,
and...
Let's do it for an ordinary case and
see how it works for an ordinary case.
We could have h is equal to
p squared plus some u of x,
okay?
Let's just do it for the...
Excuse me.
Let's just do it for
the good old familiar simple particle,
and we'll see the pattern.
All right,
so we just go to Hamilton's equations.
Hamilton's equations are x dot equals
Poisson bracket of x with h,
and that's just going to give us p over m.
That's it.
That tells us p in terms of x dot.
The other equation is the equation that
p dot is equal to p with h,
and that gives us du by dx.
And that's,
of course,
f equals ma.
Force is equal to...
Force is equal to mass times acceleration.
So one of the Hamilton equations,
typically,
the usual situation is one of the Hamilton equations tells
you the relation between the p's and the x dots,
and the other is like Newton's equations,
involves the acceleration.
Yeah.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.