Stanford University.
I'm going to do something now
I've wanted to do for years.
I've really wanted to do this.
Okay.
Ladies and gentlemen, people out in
the audience viewing this from afar,
we're now going to stop for a commercial break.
I want you all to go out and
buy my book, The Black Hole War.
My battle with Stephen Hawking to
make the world safe for quantum mechanics.
In that book, you will learn
about the cruelty of theoretical physicists.
You will not only learn about Schrodinger's cat,
but you will learn about Susskind's fish
and how he flushed them down the toilet.
Audience, please.
Yeah, I'm sorry.
Come on.
All right, now back to our program.
You may remember that when
we last saw Alice and Bob,
Alice was crying bitterly because the cruel
Bob was forcing her to learn group theory.
Alice, sad to say, is not finished.
Bob is not finished with her.
All right.
Tonight.
Tonight, we will see Alice suffer more.
Okay, are there any questions about group theory for
the moment that now that we're back to the story,
main storyline, any questions about group theory?
We're not finished with it.
We're really not finished with it.
Yeah.
There's two parts of your exposé on groups.
It seems to be some kind of abstract
mathematical object that has some kind of multiplication
table.
And there's also the part on
how those groups act on various objects.
Can we dissociate the two, or is it...
Well, they're completely related.
There's the abstract notion.
Let's take the case of rotation of a spin.
There's a perfect case to study.
There's the abstract, completely abstract
notion of a rotation in space.
And I don't tell you what it acts on.
I just tell you that is
an operation that you can do.
Physics has to respect symmetry
under the rotations of space.
And so we must then say,
how does the rotation of space act
on the quantities which are physically relevant?
If we were talking about classical physics, we
might just say that the rotation of space
rotates the coordinates of a particle.
It might rotate the direction
of a magnet, whatever it does.
We know how to describe that.
We describe that by...
Okay.
In quantum mechanics, the states of a system
are always represented by a linear vector space.
There's the abstract notion of a state of a system,
and there's the concrete representation of
it in terms of column vectors.
How big are those column vectors?
What's the number of entries into the column vector?
Well, that depends on the system.
But basically, it's the number of
mutually orthogonal possibilities for that system.
Okay.
If the system in question
only consists of an electron spin,
then there's only two states, two
mutually orthogonal states, spin up, spin down.
If it's two electrons, and again,
we're only interested in the spin,
then there would be four states, two up, two
down, one up, one down, one down, one up.
If we're talking about a more complex object,
for example, the entire motion of an electron,
its position, as well as its
momentum, it's a very complex object.
It's a very complex object.
And if you're talking about a more complex object,
then you have to think about the
number of states that are in it.
And if you're talking about an electron,
then there are an infinite number of states.
The number of states that it
takes to describe the orbital locat—
the number of mutually orthogonal states of an electron,
speaking now about its position, is infinite.
It could be anywhere in space,
or you could choose to
describe it in terms of momentum.
So the column vectors describing an electron's position
are an amplitude for every possible
location or for every possible momentum.
So there must be representations of the rotation group,
of this group of
rotations, which are infinite-dimensional matrices.
And they are.
They are.
Just how—what are the matrices
which act on the column vectors
which describe the system that you're interested in?
The size of those matrices will depend
on the number of mutually orthogonal states.
All right. So let's come back.
Spin of the electron—throw away
everything else out of your head.
Spin of the electron, 2x2 matrices.
The group elements are the abstract rotations.
They're represented by 2x2 matrices.
A spin-1 particle.
A spin-1 particle has three mutually orthogonal states.
The rotations are represented by 3x3 matrices.
In that case—
Those 3x3 matrices are familiar to some of you.
They are the three-dimensional matrices which
mix up the components of three vectors.
What comes after spin...
after three halves?
Alright, one half, well first
spin zero. What about spin zero?
Spin zero, rotations don't act on
it all. They just leave it alone.
So it's completely trivial.
You can think of it in some very useless sense that
rotations act on a spin zero just to leave it alone.
Okay, that corresponds to one by one matrices.
Just the unit matrix, that's all.
Just the unit matrix, there's nothing.
Two by two, that's spin a half.
Three by three, that's spin one.
Four by four, that's spin three halves, and so forth.
So the same abstract...
group element, the same abstract symmetry operation...
may have many matrix
representations of different dimensionality.
That's an important fact.
And we're gonna spend a little more time on it.
But let's just review for a moment what the...
symmetries... we talked about the
symmetries of rotation of space...
on a spin, on a spin a half
particle, in particular on a spin a half particle.
And we said those rotation operations become
represented by matrices which I called U.
U because they're unitary.
So these are two by two unitary matrices.
I won't bother being more
specific than just putting dots there.
Those two by two unitary matrices act on...
the state vectors...
of a spin a half.
Again, I won't be more specific than writing that.
Let's erase it for the moment.
And this is called a representation of the group.
It's in one-to-one correspondence with the
group elements, matrix multiplication, group multiplication.
They're in one-to-one correspondence.
Let's just flesh it out.
What does it mean for matrix multiplication?
It means that it's inverse is its Hermitian conjugate.
But we know that the number of
degrees of freedom, the number of parameters,
in a unitary two by two matrix is how many?
How many did we say there were?
Eight to begin with.
Four elements, each complex.
That's four elements.
Four elements.
This is four equations.
That cuts you down to four.
But there are only three independent parameters,
the three Euler angles, if you like,
the three angles describing a rotation,
the three things describing a rotation,
namely the rotation angle and the two
parameters which determine the direction of the rotation.
So there are only three
independent parameters of a rotation.
These matrices have one too many parameters.
And to get rid of that one too many parameters,
you have to get rid of the three independent parameters.
There's one extra parameter, one more
condition, and that's the determinant of U.
I'll just represent that.
We could write it as debt.
But I'll just write it as absolute value.
But it's not really absolute value.
It's a symbol for a determinant.
But that is equal to one.
Now a simple fact incidentally, that
when you multiply matrices, the determinants multiply.
So how can you multiply?
You multiply them.
The determinant of the product of A and B
is the determinant of A times the determinant of B.
It is also true that the determinant
of a Hermitian conjugate of an operator
is the complex conjugate of
the determinant of the original operator.
So, here's what we can say. Let's
take the determinant of both sides of this.
The determinant of both sides of this is,
first of all, the determinant of U dagger U,
but that's also equal to the determinant
of U dagger times the determinant of U.
And what's the determinant of 1?
1 is equal to 1.
1 here, of course, means the
unit matrix, all 1s on the diagonal.
All right, now.
Next thing is the determinant of
U dagger is just the determinant of...
Well, is the determinant of...
is the complex conjugate of the determinant of U.
And...
If the determinant of U is 1, the determinant of
U dagger is 1, and the whole thing is consistent.
The only point is that it is consistent.
It's a consistent condition on U's that's...
When I say consistent, I mean that
it's consistent with the law of matrix multiplication.
All right?
If you take a bunch of unitary
matrices, every one of which has determinant 1,
and you multiply them together, you'll
again get a thing with determinant 1.
All right, so it's a mathematical theorem, which
may not be too surprising for many of you,
that the special unitary matrix...
matrices, 2 by 2 matrices, which have 3 parameters
in them, special means that U dagger U equals 1,
that the group of those matrices
is identical to the group of...
of rotations in 3-dimensional space.
Now, it's not quite true.
Go ahead.
Uh, is there...
Is there nothing that says that
the determinant has to be real?
No, the determinant of a...
It just has to be radius 1.
Yeah.
Complex number...
Right.
The determinant of a unitary
matrix must be a pure phase.
Okay?
That's just from the fact that it's unitary.
From the fact that it's unitary.
But you can take any...
All right, here's the point.
You can take any unitary matrix.
Let's suppose its determinant is E to the i theta.
You can then multiply that unitary matrix.
All right.
An put in this unitary matrix by...
Um...
Well you'd multiply it by...
Because when you calculate the determinant, you multiply two
elements together.
All right.
So if you took you and multiplied it...
By E to the minus i theta
over 2, you would construct a special
unitary matrix.
All right.
So the point is, the extra
phase that's in there is almost
you can always get rid of it by
a redefinition of U and in fact the
rotation group doesn't contain this piece
here it's just isomorphic to the
matrices with with determinant one okay I told
you a little fib when I said that
SU is exactly the same as the
rotation groups it's not exactly there's a
two-to-one correspondence instead of
a one-to-one correspondence the unitary
operators U and minus U if U is
a unitary operator U dagger U equals one
so is minus U whatever U is
right in fact is a two-to-one correspondence the
matrices U and minus U both correspond
to the same rotation in space but that's
a fine point that that
I which is not going to play any special
role in in what we say at least for the
time being so a simple statement which
is almost true is that there's a
correspondence certainly there's a
correspondence but that there's a
one-to-one correspondence not quite
true it's two-to-one correspondence between
the unitary matrices two by two
matrices the special unitary matrices those would
get here separately between two and
two but holes simultaneously as we move
along theoped eighty-nine-lerge and the nonunpsy 謝謝
by- could be simply one so
the means is it's aially just a
one-to-one correspondence so there's a
widefting between this and all the
counters with our
And the symmetry is represented by
a set of matrices like this.
Then there's a concept of the generators.
The generators have to do
with infinitesimal elements of the group.
An infinitesimal element of the group means,
in the case of rotation, a rotation about
some axis by a very, very small angle.
In other words, it's an element of
the group which is very close to unity.
Unity means no transformation.
Elements which are very close, which are just
very small shifts of angles and so forth,
are called infinitesimal elements of the group.
And the generators of the group are
very closely related to these infinitesimally small operations.
Now one of the reasons that the
infinitely small elements are important and interesting
is because you can build up any element out of
a set of matrices.
So you can build up any
element out of a set of matrices.
Now, let's look at the sequence of small ones.
In other words, if I want to rotate about
some angle by a finite rotation, I just think
of it as a multiplication
of a bunch of infinitesimal ones.
So if you know the properties of the
infinitesimal generators, you can put together the entire
structure of the group.
We're not going to do that.
We're not going to study that today.
But we are just going to
define the generators of the group.
The reason we're going to define the generators
of the group is because they really are the
conserved quantities.
They are the quantities that are conserved
and which play the role of conservation laws
once you know what the symmetry group is.
Okay, so let's define them.
Incidentally, for what I've written here,
there's nothing specific to SU .
This could be SU .
Where N is the denominator.
The number of elements.
The special unitary N by N matrices.
They're of course not all isomorphic to rotations.
It's only the SU group which
is isomorphic to rotations of space.
SU , SU , SU .
Not so easy to visualize.
Okay, so here we have the definition.
And now let's take an element
which is very close to the identity.
It doesn't have to be SU .
Let's write it.
U is equal to the identity, 1, plus something small.
And let's put an i in for simply notational simplicity.
It'll simplify notations.
A small parameter epsilon and a quantity which is
often, I'm not going to call it g, g for
generator because we've already used g for group element.
And so therefore I will use t.
Yt.
Beats me, I don't know.
So U is 1 plus it.
What is t?
Let's find out what we can learn about t.
We use the fact, first of
all, that U dagger U is 1.
All right, so U dagger U,
that's 1 plus i epsilon t.
Oh, incidentally, it's easy to prove that if U
dagger U is 1, then U U dagger is 1.
I won't prove that for you.
That U and U dagger always commute with each other.
Not for all operators, but for unitaries.
So it doesn't matter which order you multiply.
All right, so it's 1 plus i epsilon
t times 1 minus i epsilon t dagger.
If this is U, then this is U dagger.
i gets changed to minus i when you complex conjugate.
And this is supposed to be equal to 1.
Let's retain things only to the lowest order in epsilon.
Epsilon squared is too small for our interest tonight,
so let's just keep things to order epsilon.
And that says 1 times 1 cancels the 1 there.
And it says that i epsilon times
t minus t dagger is equal to 0.
Or, to simplify, it just says
that t is equal to t dagger.
What's an operator that's equal to its own conjugate?
Hermitian.
And Hermitian operators in
quantum mechanics represent observables.
All right?
Hermitian operators represent observable quantities.
For the case of rotations, what are these t's?
What physical significance do they have?
There are three of them.
First of all, why are there three of them?
There are actually an infinite number of them,
but there are three linearly independent ones.
So let me explain why that is.
The reason is because the
rotation group has only three parameters.
There's only three independent ways that you can rotate.
You can rotate about the x-axis.
So I could have made
an infinitesimal rotation about the x-axis.
I could have made an infinitesimal
rotation about the y-axis or the z-axis.
And in fact, for an infinitesimal rotation,
if I wanted to rotate about some other axis,
what I could first do is
rotate a little about the x-axis
and then a little about the y-axis
and then a little about the z-axis.
Another way to say it is
that the generators behave like vectors.
If I want a vector in an arbitrary direction,
in other words, a vector rotation about some axis,
about an arbitrary direction,
the way I can think of it
is making it up out of the components,
the component rotations about the x, y, and z-axis.
So there are three independent
directions that you can rotate in
and three independent, linearly independent t's.
Oh, we missed one point.
Come back. Back up.
There is this condition here.
The condition that the determinant is one.
All right, so let me tell you before...
We'll get back to it in a moment.
The determinant being one,
the determinant...
of any matrix which is of the form one plus,
let's call it epsilon times a small matrix,
the determinant of m...
is equal to one plus epsilon
times the trace of small m.
The determinant...
of a matrix...
which is close to the identity...
is one.
That's just the identity.
And then the small deviation is epsilon times the trace.
That's something to prove.
I'm going to go home and prove that.
But we can see what that means immediately.
It means that the trace of t...
is zero.
The trace of t has to be zero...
in order for...
the determinant of u to be equal to one.
All right, so that's the second condition.
The trace of t is zero.
And it should be Hermitian.
How many independent Hermitian 2x2 matrices
are there with trace equal to zero?
The answer is three of them.
And they correspond to the rotations about the three axes.
But more abstractly and generally,
the generators of the group of rotations...
are the angular momentum operators for a system.
So that's what angular momentum means in quantum mechanics.
It is the generators of the rotation group.
And you act with the angular momentum,
or one plus i epsilon times the angular momentum,
to rotate a system a small amount.
And then if you want
to rotate it a large amount,
you just do it over and over again.
So everything is contained.
All the information about the structure of the group
is contained in the generators.
In fact, it's contained in
the commutation relations of the generators.
Those are the important things.
I won't go into them again.
We did commutation relations of angular momentum.
I just wanted to connect things
up a little bit for you.
But the important thing is that the conserved quantities
associated with the symmetry are the generators.
And...
So there are three independent 2x2?
Traceless 2x2 Hermitian matrices.
Yeah, they have a name.
The Pauli matrices.
Yeah, the three Pauli matrices.
And then if you went to 3x3 matrices?
3x3 unitary matrices?
Unitary, traceless.
And there are eight.
Like the Gell-Mann?
Yeah, they're the other Gell-Mann matrices.
We're going to do that in a moment.
So, I'm going to go back to the first part.
I'm going to go back to the first part.
I'm going to go back to that in a moment.
All right.
That eight is the same eight as the eight gluons.
Eightfold weight.
Actually, that's a different eight.
Not because it's mathematically the same,
but it's associated with a different SU symmetry than color.
But yeah, mathematics is the same.
Okay, so that was a
little bit about a little review.
The sorrows of Alice.
Let's torture Alice even more.
Let's go to SU .
SU the pattern is exactly the
same, except we're talking about 3x3 matrices.
All right.
So, what is 3x3 matrix?
You can find the 3x3 matrix in the
The 3x3 matrix is a 3x3 matrix.
In fact, I'm not even sure that
there's very much more to say about it.
So, we have nine independent complex numbers.
That's 18.
But then we have U dagger U equals one.
Now, this really is an equation for each element.
This is a product.
This is a matrix product.
So, we can think of it as IJ.
And this is delta IJ over here.
How many equations is this?
This is nine equations.
So, we have 18 minus nine is nine.
But then one additional equation that
the determinant is equal to one.
That's eight equations.
And so, we can guess that there are eight different.
If we start with the unit matrix,
in how many distinct directions in the group
space can we deform away from the identity?
And the answer is eight.
The implication being there are eight
linearly independent 3x3 traceless Hermitian matrices.
Traceless Hermitian matrices, the
number of parameters is eight.
So, we're going to come back to that.
But before we do, let's talk a little
bit about how representations combine to form new representations.
Now, what we're talking about
here is combining systems together.
To form new systems.
In the case of spin, we might be
talking about combining more than one particle together.
To create some sort of composite, for example.
And that composite would also have a spin.
Let's not worry about the motion of the particles.
Let's just think of them as things
that we staple on top of each other.
So, they're nailed down to each other.
But each one has a spin.
So, each one has a spin.
And let's suppose that we take two such particles.
We put them on top
of each other, two half-spin particles.
What do we get?
Well, we get four possible states.
But those four possible states can be thought
of as a basis in that four particle states.
Can be thought of as a spin-zero object.
And the three spin-one objects that two half-spins can make.
If we take two half-spins,
we can certainly make a spin-one.
Why? We can line up
the spins in the same direction.
So, the z-component of spin can be one.
It can be minus one.
And it can be zero, but
it can be zero in two ways.
Alright, but still, a spin-one
particle only has three states.
So, one of those two ways of making zero.
Must not be part of the spin-one multiplet.
What can it be?
It can only be spin-zero.
Why spin-zero?
Because there's nothing for it to transform into.
So, there are three combinations
which form the spin-one multiplet.
And one which forms the spin-zero multiplet.
When you combine spins together that way, there
are two possible total spins you can make.
So, if you were to take an atom.
Made out of two half-spin particles.
And ignore the orbital motion altogether.
One possibility is that the
spins are in the same direction.
That would give you spin-one.
And the other possibility is that
they are in the opposite direction.
In which case, it would be spin-zero.
It's ortho and para-hydrogen.
In particular, for the hydrogen atom.
Where the two spins would
be the proton and the electron.
Right.
So, you combine.
It's important to know how to combine spins.
And to know what you get.
What possibilities you get when you combine them together.
What happens in SU .
Now, we want to jump to SU .
And discuss some very specific representations of SU .
They're the important ones which we will discuss.
First of all, there is the triplet.
The triplet is simply.
If U is a 3x3 matrix.
Then it has to act
on a thing with three components.
In the present context.
The three components represent the three colors of a quark.
So, we're talking now for the moment about one quark.
Not three quarks.
One quark.
And that quark can be red, yellow, red.
Blue or green.
It can be red, blue or green.
This is the amplitude that it's red.
This is the amplitude that it's blue.
This is the amplitude that it's green.
And what does the group do to them?
It mixes them up.
It mixes up red, blue and green.
Takes any particular state.
And sends it to some quantum superposition of states.
Of mixed color, shall we say.
So, if we took a red quark.
And we put it in a 3x3 matrix.
Red quark.
That would be like an up spin.
And we rotated it.
By this SU operation.
We would get something of a mixed character.
Which would have amplitudes for being red, blue or green.
Some quantum superposition.
So, that's the meaning of these operations.
But it's interesting and important.
To know what happens
if you combine representations together.
Let me go back a step.
Now we want to talk about
the various representations of SU .
The representations of SU are the spin states.
Spin 0, 1, 3, 2, 5 and so forth.
Those are the representations of rotations.
We want to know something
about the representations of SU .
And I'm not going to tell you very much.
Just a very little bit.
There are rather 3 important representations.
For our purposes.
One of them is just a 3 dimensional representation.
And it can be thought of as the 3 components.
The 3 things that go here.
Could be thought of as the 3 field operators.
For, let's call them quark, red.
Quark, blue.
Quark, green.
We can either think of these matrices as
mixing up the states of a single quark.
Or we can think of them as a combination.
Of a single quark.
Or we can think of it as mixing
up the field operators that create single quarks.
Red, blue and green.
Alright.
Now.
Next.
This representation.
By 3 by 3 matrices that acts on the quarks.
That representation is called the 3.
In the same language you would.
If you use the same language.
You would call the half spin.
Particle of SU2.
You would call it the 2.
2 for 2 states.
Okay.
So the 3 is a representation that's identified.
With the quark field itself.
Or with quarks.
Now.
There are also anti-quarks.
Anti-quarks.
Their field operators are the
complex conjugates of the quark operators.
So you can ask yourself.
If.
There is a matrix.
Which acts.
On.
Q.
To give some new thing.
We could complex conjugate everything.
And we could say.
Let's write it.
If.
Let's call it U.
U is a 3 by 3 matrix.
If it acts on the column vector Q.
I'm now being a schematic.
U is a 3 by 3 matrix.
Q is a column vector Q.
Okay.
So if it acts on the column vector.
If it acts to give.
Let's call it Q prime.
The rotated Q.
Then what is it that acts on the complex conjugate.
Or the Hermitian conjugate field operator.
That's the object which represents anti-quarks.
Well it's quite obvious.
It's going to be.
The complex conjugate.
The.
Not the Hermitian conjugate.
The set of elements.
If U.
Is a bunch of elements.
Then U star is nothing but the complex conjugate elements.
Let's call it star.
Let's call it star to be consistent.
So there is a second representation of SU three.
Which is the set of matrices.
Which are the complex conjugate represent.
Which are the complex conjugate matrices.
For every matrix U.
There is a complex conjugate.
And that defines a second representation of.
a second representation. It's called a
complex conjugate representation. It is the transformation
property of antiquarks, and that representation is
called the three bar. This is very abstract,
but what is it in the case of electrons?
What does this correspond to in case of electrons?
It is simply the fact that if the electron
wave function gets multiplied by e to the i theta,
then the positron wave function gets multiplied
by e to the minus i theta.
They transform with complex conjugate group elements.
So you would say that the electron
and the positron are complex conjugate representations
of the U1 group. That's the language.
The quark and the antiquark are complex conjugate
representations of the group SU3.
It would be the complex conjugate.
What is the matrix of the Pauli-Split matrices?
For the case SU2. SU2 is a special
degenerate case where the complex conjugate is equivalent
to the original matrices by another matrix. It's
a special case. It's called a real group,
but this is not important for us now.
The three and the three bar representation are
quite different.
They look very similar to each other, but
they are distinct. They should not be thought
of as the same representation
of SU3. They're quite different.
In fact, the generators of the three bar
representation are the negatives of the generators of the
three representation. That's not too hard to
prove. That means they carry the opposite
color.
If a quark carries a red color, then an
antiquark carries a minus red color. It has the opposite
value for the generators.
All right, so these are the quark and the
antiquark. Now what happens if you take a quark
and a quark, two quarks, or a quark and
an antiquark? Just like you could take two electrons
and make a spin one, which was a triplet. Not
got to do with this three, but the spin one.
So you could take two electrons and make a spin one, which was a triplet.
Not got to do with this three, but the three bar representation is the same.
So you could take two quarks and put
them together. You can call that three times three
bar. Sorry, three times three. Two quarks
are three. This is just a notation. Three
times three means two quarks. Sometimes this
is represented by a circle to indicate that
you're not actually multiplying numbers.
You're simply building a space.
Which is now a space of two quarks.
It has nine independent states. Red, red, red, blue,
red, green, and so forth. All nine states.
And if you work out what representations of
SU appear when you multiply three by three, the
answer is, first of all, there is an antiquark
that is the same color as the anti-quark.
That's a little bit odd, don't you think?
But it's true. It's true anyway. And one more
representation called the six-dimensional representation of SU
. We're never going to need the six-dimensional
representation, but there is a six-dimensional representation
of SU . I can tell you what
these things correspond to.
If you think of the quarks as just
indices, color indices, then you can combine the two
quark states symmetrically or anti-symmetrically. You
can combine them symmetrically or anti-symmetrically.
Anti-symmetrically gives you the three bar.
Symmetrically gives you the six. But this
is not terribly important. The point is, if
you make two quarks somehow, in the labyrinth,
in the laboratory, the transformation properties of
the two quark system under this SU there
will be one term, or one way
of combining them together, three independent states of
that system, which will be like an anti-quark,
and the other one will be this mysterious
six, which we don't give a damn
about. We'll see why as we go along.
Now, what happens if we
take a quark and an anti-quark?
If we take a quark and an anti-quark, what
we get is different than what we get when
we get a quark and a quark. We get,
again, six and three is nine states, but it's not
the same nine possibilities. First of all, we
make an object which is a one. What is
a one? That's a thing which
is completely invariant under the color operations.
Roughly speaking, it's a red plus a
red anti-red, a quantum superposition of red anti-red,
blue anti-blue, and green anti-green. That's
one thing. And that's a single representation,
and it simply does not transform under the
SU group. It's called a singlet, an SU
singlet. And one way of saying
it is it's the analog of combining
together the two quarks.
So, you take a quark and an anti-quark,
and you put them together, two electrons to make
a spin zero state. It's like a spin
zero state. It does not transform under the rotations.
It doesn't transform at all. It's just
one state, so how could it transform? There's
nothing for it to transform into. So, when
you take a quark and an anti-quark, there
are nine states, one of which, one
linear combination, red anti-red plus blue anti-blue
plus green anti-green, that just forms a singlet.
And then, there are eight others, and
those eight others are called the eight-dimensional
representation of SU . That eight, incidentally,
think about that eight for a moment.
We've seen eight in another place. It was
the number of generators. Just like the number
of angular momenta. When you rotate space, the
angular momenta rotate into each other. When you rotate
In color space, the eight generators
get mixed up with each other.
The way the eight generators
transform is called the eight-dimensional representation
of SU .
This is sometimes called the adjoint representation.
The words don't matter.
It's just the representation that transforms
the same way as the generators.
And that's what you get when
you multiply 3 cross 3 bar.
Finally, one other operation.
What do you get if you take three quarks?
Three cross three cross three.
You take three quarks, there are 27 states.
Well, you can do it in pieces.
You can say, if I combine together these two
quarks, what I will get is either a one, sorry,
is either a three bar, which
is an anti-quark, or a six.
So, two of these quarks together will necessarily
either transform as an anti-quark or as a six.
A six is a peculiar representation, which
I said we won't care about very much.
Now, what happens if you take this
product and now cross it again with three?
In other words, we see what we get.
When we combine two quarks, here's what we get.
And then we combine it again with another quark.
We will either get what appears if we take
a quark and an anti-quark, but we know what
that is.
That's one plus eight.
The plus here just means or.
You either get a one, the singlet, or an eight.
Just like saying you either
get spin one or spin zero.
That's what this plus means, or.
When you multiply six times three, I
think you get an eight plus a ten.
But this, again, is not very interesting to us.
We don't care very much about that.
The interesting thing, and the most interesting
thing, is when we multiply three quarks together,
we get the possibility again of a
singlet, of a state which is completely colorless.
It has no transformation property.
It's just a combination of a plus charge
and a minus charge, which cancel each other.
We get the singlet, which
has no SU transformation at all.
And it can be thought of as a
combination which simply is invariant under the SU group,
under the SU of the mixing up the quarks.
What is it?
Can we guess what it is like?
I'll tell you what it is.
It's just a red, a green, and a blue quark.
But you have to be careful.
It's a red, green, and blue quark anti-symmetrized.
Not important.
It's a red, green, and blue quark.
A red, green, and blue quark are the singlet.
Then there are other combinations.
Red, red, green, and so forth.
They form the remaining states here.
But the most interesting one for
our purposes will be this singlet here.
So we see that when we take a quark
and an anti-quark, just with regard to the colors,
you can combine the colors in a particular
way to get a singlet plus other stuff.
And when you take three quarks, you can
combine them together to get a singlet plus other
junk.
Is it the probability of these other
things so low that we don't consider it?
The question is what the energy of them is.
And I will tell you.
The energy of them is infinite.
But we will come to that.
The energy of them is infinite, and
so they don't appear in the spectrum.
How can the energy of them be infinite?
That was a great puzzle, which we now understand,
and I'm going to talk about it a little bit.
Right.
But now, ah, there is one
other kind of particle in nature.
Sorry, there's many other kinds of particles in nature.
But there's one other particle in nature.
There's one other particle in quantum chromodynamics.
We're talking about quantum chromodynamics, QCD,
the theory of quarks and gluons.
What of course we've left out is the gluon.
The gluon is an object, which I think I've
told you before, behaves as if it were a quark
and an anti-quark.
With respect to the symmetry, it doesn't behave
like a quark and an anti-quark with respect
to what happens if you hit it or anything.
Just with respect to the colors.
Right.
So the color symmetry, its color properties are
the same as a quark and an anti-quark,
but only the eight.
It transforms as the eight dimensional representation.
It transforms the same way
as the generators of the group.
Right.
So again, it is this octet,
which is separate from the singlet here.
It's the remaining states here.
And that's what a gluon is.
A gluon is a thing with two indices, like
a quark and an anti-quark, except a quark and
an anti-quark arranged into this octet of SU3.
So it's not neutral.
It itself is not neutral.
So let's quark.
Postulates, if you like, of quantum chroma of QCD.
It's got an SU3 symmetry, which I won't write down.
A quark.
It transforms as a three.
Sorry.
The anti-quark transforms as a three bar.
And the gluon or the gluon field as an eight.
Of course, these equations don't really mean anything.
Particles can't equal numbers.
Particles are particles.
Numbers are numbers.
This just means the quark field transforms as a triplet.
Right.
So the anti-quark as the anti-triplet, complex
conjugate, and the gluon as the eight, which
is a piece of a quark anti-quark.
This remaining possible gluon doesn't exist in nature.
Do we know why?
Not completely.
But the important point about it is it doesn't
mix up with the other components, and so throwing
it away is a consistent.
A mathematically consistent thing to do.
Because it doesn't get mixed up with the
other components when you transform the SU group.
That's group theory as applied to quantum
chromodynamics, as applied to quarks and gluons.
Another postulate of quantum chromodynamics, and it's
not really a postulate, it's a dynamical
output of the theory.
But it's a dynamic output of the theory.
But let's take it as a postulate and
then explore what it means in a moment.
And that postulate is all of the particles
of nature, the real particles of nature, not
quarks and gluons, which are never seen singly,
but are always seen in composites, that the
particles which can be separated off and
examined individually, particles of finite mass, the
real things that occur in the laboratory, are all particles.
Real particles.
I don't know, there's nothing not real about a
quark, so I hate to call them the real particles.
The unconfined particles, the free particles,
the liberated particles, or whatever we wish
to call them, free particles
are always transforming under the one.
In other words, they are singlets.
All the real particles in nature are singlets.
There is only two independent ways.
Well, I'll tell you about that.
I'll tell you what the ways of creating singlets are.
This is a mathematical fact now.
There are only two fundamental ways
of making singlets out of quarks.
One of them is to
take a quark and an anti-quark.
That creates a singlet.
The other is to take three quarks.
Now, you can do other things.
You can take a quark and an
anti-quark and juxtapose it with three quarks.
But the elements, the basic...
Or you can take three quarks and another three quarks.
Three quarks in a singlet and
three other quarks in a singlet.
That will also be in a singlet.
But all of the objects that you can
make up have the quantum numbers of combinations of
things made out of three quarks
or a quark and an anti-quark.
What about the gluons themselves?
First of all, before we do
it, let's give these things names.
What is an object made out of three quarks?
It's an object made out of three quarks.
It's a baryon.
Or a baryon.
A baryon.
A baryon, right.
Baryon.
They always have half spin, and half spin, when
I say half spin, that can be one half,
three halves, five halves, seven halves.
Why?
Because they're made out of three half spin particles.
What about the quark anti-quarks?
These are the ones, of course, in the three.
In three cross three cross three,
there's the triple, there's the triplet.
There's the triplet.
Sorry, the singlet are called baryons.
The singlet in three cross
three bar, what are they called?
Quark and an anti-quark?
Mesons.
Now we left out one thing.
Can we make things out of the gluons?
We make things out of the gluons.
Yeah, there's a thing that you
can make just out of gluons.
In fact, if you take an eight cross an eight.
I told you roughly what
happens if you combine quarks together.
You could ask what happens if you
combine gluons together, or gluons with quarks.
I'm not going to go through the whole
list of multiplication tables that you get when
you combine all sorts of things, but
there's certainly at least one more interesting thing,
and that's an eight cross an eight.
This is simply two gluons.
Two gluons.
Now it's not obvious.
You get 63 states altogether.
Eight cross eight.
One of them is a singlet.
What did I say, 63?
64 states.
Did I say 63?
Yeah.
There are 64 states in eight cross eight,
and the rest of them form 63 things which
are a combination of eights and other things.
Eight appears a number of times.
I forget which.
I don't remember which representation.
Those are the two positions.
So, that's the first equation.
The second equation is the number of states
that are together, but there is a number of
states that are together.
These are the two states.
The number of states that are together.
You might have heard of the number of
states that are together, but there are 63 states.
None of them are singlets.
There's one way of combining
together gluons to form singlets.
So, you might ask, is there a
particle which is composed of two gluons?
Just two gluons bound together into an
SU3 singlet, and the answer is yes.
They're called glu-balls.
They're not made of quarks.
They don't have any quark content in them.
They're made of quarks.
They're fundamentally just a pair of gluons.
You can also make three gluons, incidentally.
It's possible also in, it's also
possible to get more complicated things.
But there are gluobals.
So the spectrum of hadrons, the
spectrum of strongly interacting particles which come
from quarks and gluons, consists
of baryons, mesons, and gluobals.
All of them are color singlets.
Color singlets is the watchword.
Now another fact, another fact.
You can check this yourself easily.
I think we've actually checked it before.
Remember now.
All we can make is quark-anti-singlets.
Quark-anti-quark, quark-quark-quark, or gluon-gluon,
and combinations of those.
What kind of electric charges do
we get if we combine three quarks?
Well, I think we can get charge two.
Let's see, we can get zero, one, and two.
We can get two by taking
three up quarks, three down quarks.
Sorry, what were three down quarks?
Three down quarks is minus one.
Three down quarks is minus one, and
you have minus one, zero, one, and two.
But the important point is you cannot
make a fractional charge with three quarks.
There is no way to take
three quarks and make a fractional charge.
What about a quark and an anti-quark?
Well, again, you can take an up,
and an anti-up, or two-thirds, and minus-thirths.
Three quarks.
Two-thirds and one-third.
No, two-thirds and one-third.
You know what the story is.
And you can, again, make integer charges.
I don't remember you telling us
what the charge of a strange was.
It's the same as the charge of a down.
I did tell you because
the way that I grouped them.
I didn't remember.
Yeah, it's the same as a down.
All of the quarks are either up-like
or down-like, and they come in three families.
The up-to-down, the charm, the strange.
Okay.
And the top and the bottom, but
they're three replicas of the same thing.
So all you can make is integer-charged particles.
And so from the point of view of
color, the fact that you only have integer-charged particles
in nature is the same statement as
all the particles combine always into SU3 singlets,
color singlets.
Question about that.
A singlet is like a pair of rectangular electrodes.
It's like a pair of rectangular electrodes.
Yeah.
And is that any significance here?
Other than the way you transform them?
Well, that is the way you make
such states is to entangle them very definitely.
They are certainly entangled.
Does it have any, I'm not sure.
You can't separate them separately and make a
correlation zone like you can in Bell's theory.
Well, you can't separate them
because they get stuck together.
But, you know, you can separate them as far as
you like and it'll just cost you a lot of energy.
So in principle, yes, they're entangled objects.
Not easy to manipulate.
You wouldn't want to try to do
an experiment of that type with them.
Question?
I'm actually having trouble understanding those equations.
Not the details of how you get it, but
what the, you know, the, you know, the, you know,
the, you know, the, you know, the, you know,
what the operations are.
All right.
Good.
So the left-hand side got three cross three.
Yeah.
Which is the group three.
The representation three.
Okay.
So let's, let me, let me tell
you more mathematically what is going on here.
That's sort of my question.
Yeah.
Okay.
Let's take SU first, all right,
and take two spin of halves.
We can think of the two spin of halves.
Okay.
So let's take two spin of halves in
terms of the field operators which create their
particles.
That's the easiest way to
think about it for the moment.
All right.
So let's just call the field operator
psi, and there are two components to it.
The psi which creates a up spin
and the psi which creates a down spin.
Let's call them psi, psi i where i
can take on two values either up or down.
Okay.
Now supposing we want to create two particles.
If psi creates a particle, or psi dagger, doesn't matter.
If psi creates a particle, how do we
create two, psi creates a particle, we can think
of the two components, we can think of it as
psi one and psi two, or psi up and psi
down.
And the SU operations act on this.
Now, that's one particle.
How do we make two particles?
Well, we act twice with psi.
But we can act with psi
up twice, that creates two up particles.
We can act with psi down
twice, that creates two down particles.
Or we can do it one of each.
So let's write psi i, psi j.
In fact, these two operators don't really
have to correspond to the same particle.
Let's even, we could even think
of one of them as a particle.
We could even think of one of them as
being the electron, the other being the proton and
the hydrogen atom, for example.
Let's see, let's even give them different names.
Ah, psi and phi.
They might be the same, they might not be.
But let's, let's allow them
to be different for the moment.
Okay.
So, this now is an object with two indices.
It's an object with two indices.
It's kind of like a tensor, if
we were thinking about vectors in three-dimensional space.
Tensors are objects with two vector indices.
This object is like a tensor,
in that it has repeated indices.
Now, SU can operate on it, because
SU operates on psi and acts on phi.
This is a collection of four objects.
Up, up, up, down, down, up, and down, down.
So we could lay out those four.
Psi up, psi up, psi-phi up, psi up,
phi down, and so forth and so on.
We could lay them out in an array, and then ask,
what happens when you act with SU on this composite object here?
Well, they get mixed up with each other.
They get mixed up with each other for the simple
reason that the sies get mixed up with each other,
and the phis get mixed up with each other.
And so, certainly, these psi times phi,
these sies are going to
get mixed up with each other.
And there's going to be a 4x4 matrix,
which represents the same action as
just going through sies and phis separately
and rotating them by the group action.
Okay.
Now, you look at these, at the
way these things mix up with each other.
You look at the way they mix up
with each other, and you come to a discovery.
You discover that the combination of these two things,
the combination, let's see what it is,
psi up, phi down, minus psi down, phi up,
doesn't mix with anything else under this operation.
It just goes into itself.
This is an easy thing to check.
You just see how SU acts on psi up.
It mixes it with psi down.
You see how it acts on phi down.
And you check what happens to this particular combination.
And the answer is nothing.
So this is a singlet.
This is a 1.
The other three possibilities, what are they?
They are psi up,
phi down, plus psi down, phi up.
This is a, I have not
put in square roots of 2,
but you could put in the
square roots of 2 if you wanted.
This is orthogonal to this.
And then there's psi up, phi up,
and psi down, phi down.
What happens when you do the SU3,
SU2 rotations on these states?
They mix into each other.
In particular ways, they will mix into each other.
This is a,
singlet does not get mixed
with these three states at all.
And these three states mix up among themselves
as if they were a spin 1 object.
They get mixed among each other.
And this is then called the 3.
Spin 1 has three states.
These three mix up among themselves.
This doesn't mix up with anything.
So when you combine two half-spin states,
that's, well,
when you combine two half-spin states,
you make a 1 or you make a 3,
depending on which combination you take.
You make a 1 or you make a 3.
You make spin 1, sorry, you
make spin 0 or spin 1.
That's the sense in which
these equations are being used here.
When you combine together a quark and an anti-quark,
there are nine different ways to do it.
One of the linear combinations behaves in this way here,
and it's a singlet,
and the others transform into each other.
Eight objects, eight additional objects
will transform into each other.
So that's the meaning of these equations here.
How many of each kind of combination you get?
Is that a neat thing?
This multiplication table is neat.
It could be 2 plus 7 if the...
Say it again.
Okay, so...
You have to know some group...
3 plus 3, 2 plus 7, or...
No, no, you have to know
what the representations of SU are.
We did a bit of work to
find out what the representations of SU were,
and they were all the spin half and spin,
and integer spin particles.
We could spend two more
weeks studying SU and find out
what the representations of SU are.
What are...
What matrix representations are there?
There are not matrix
representations of every dimensionality.
There are matrix representations for SU that happen to be,
for every dimensionality,
a matrix representation of SU .
For SU , not so.
There's the singlet, there's the triplet,
there's the antitriplet,
there is the octet, the 8,
there's a 10, there's a 15, there's a 20,
there's a whole bunch of them,
but not every number appears
in the possible matrices
which have the same multiplication table as SU .
So that's a bit of work to prove.
We didn't want to go there.
I just went there by saying,
all right, here's what you get.
And, uh, but the real interesting point
is the singlets that appear.
The ways that you can combine quarks together
to get combinations which don't rotate,
or which are the analog of electrically neutral.
Why do I say electrically neutral?
Because electrically neutral are exactly the same things
as the things that are electrically neutral.
They're exactly the objects which don't transform
under that U1,
the things which the phase cancels out of.
Remember? Go back again to electrodynamics.
The things which are electrically neutral
are the combinations where all the phases cancel out.
If an electron has an e to the i theta,
and a positron an e to the minus i theta,
then an electron and a positron,
are neutral.
Don't transform at all.
Two electrons, that gets an e to the 2i theta.
So it's not called neutral.
Or it's not called, or it transforms under the group.
So singlets are important,
but you should just think of them as neutral objects
with respect to the, uh, to the transformation properties.
And, uh...
I mean, is there a possibility,
that you could just show what that singlet,
uh, that, that transformation?
Uh, just one example there? Is that, uh...
Oh, we can go through it, yeah.
Uh...
Maybe it's too much.
It is a little too much, but, um...
Okay, that's fine.
Yeah.
Uh...
All right, one simple way to see it.
I don't know if this will help you at all.
Uh...
If we write, just write this object here, epsilon.
You know what epsilon is?
What epsilon ij is?
It's the 2x2 matrix, which
is, uh, the anti-symmetric matrix.
Yeah.
Um...
And contract the indices this way.
It's, uh, that, that's equal to this.
That's equal to this.
And it's easy to prove that this is a...
Oh, okay.
This...
Uh, I'll just spend a moment at it.
In every dimensionality,
for matrix dimensionality,
there is always an epsilon symbol,
which has a certain number of indices.
For 2x2 matrices, the epsilon symbol...
And the epsilon symbol is the anti-symmetric,
uh, the fully anti-symmetric matrix
composed out of zeros and ones.
Okay?
All right.
Epsilon ij is the 2x2 matrix.
What about for, what about for, uh, 3x3 matrices
in a three-dimensional?
And it's epsilon ijk.
Requires three indices.
All right?
So I'll tell you right now,
if you take an SU3,
epsilon ijk,
and let's call it...
What did we call the quark fields?
Q?
Qi, qj, qk.
Then you make the three-quark singlet,
which has no color.
ij and k have to
all be different from each other.
Otherwise, this is zero.
So that's why I said a
red, a green, and a blue.
Uh, make a singlet.
Okay.
Well, uh, I, I...
We don't want to make Alice suffer too much tonight.
Um...
For what it's worth,
I just happened to bump
into this in this other book,
uh, that 8 x 8 equals 27.
Oh, let's write it down.
Okay, 8 x 8.
All right, so that means when you,
when you take two 8s and put them together,
in other words, two gluons,
you first of all make a singlet.
What else?
Plus 8 plus 8 plus 10.
Well, say it again.
8 plus 8 plus 8.
Okay, I'll tell you what this means in a minute.
Plus 10 plus 10.
Plus 10 plus 10?
Right.
Okay.
All right, so let's see.
Is that right?
Uh, 10 and 10 is 20,
and 8 and 8, uh, this should make, uh...
Well, well, well, 8 x 8 is 64.
Oh, it's plus 27.
It's not equal, equal to, yeah,
it's plus 27 at the end.
You say there's a plus of 27?
Does that make 63?
I can't tell.
Is that 64?
Yeah.
Okay, good.
All right.
All right, so for your information,
this is a fact I know.
I know the representations of SU up to 27.
I think there's a 35, but I don't remember.
Uh, but...
Another 10?
Uh, we don't, we're not up to 60?
No, okay.
We're not up to 60.
Okay.
All right.
So what this means is, first of
all, there is one and only one combination,
quantum, quantum superposition of states of two gluons,
which makes a singlet.
One and only one.
And that's the glue ball.
Then it turns out there are
two orthogonal ways of making octets.
Two, that's 16 states altogether, but they form two groups,
and the first group mixes into
themselves without mixing into the second.
The second group mixes into
itself without mixing into the first,
and both of them form octets.
Different combinations, different patterns of symmetry
of the wave function of the,
of the state of the two,
of the two, um, gluon system.
Then there's something called a 10.
And again, there are two distinct
ways of combining the gluons together
like tens, but who cares about tens
because they don't appear in nature anyway.
And then there's a 27 dimensional representation.
How about in three cross three cross three?
Okay.
So there's a singlet.
I don't know.
I, I don't know.
We had them written down, but I don't remember.
Can I ask a question?
Is it fair to say that,
that what happens if you change the,
sort of the basis of
the, of the thing to the,
let's go back to the spin two case,
to the, to the singlet and the triplet
and the two up, up, up, down, down.
Wait a second.
Where are we going?
Where are we?
Oh, it may have gotten worse.
Here?
Yeah.
All right.
So you have that and, so, so
use those four things as, as a basis.
Then the matrix which describes
the operation factors into a,
has, has, has one zero, zero, zero, zero.
And then a, a, let's see, yes, and
a, and a, and a lower part that is,
that moves, that moves the, that
exchange, moves the three among themselves.
So the make, you can describe it
in terms of how, how the matrix looks.
If you just work in terms of the basis vectors up, up,
up, down, up, up, up, up, down, down, up, and down, down,
then there's a certain set of four,
four by four matrices which represent the group.
All right.
But if you work in terms of these linear
combinations, this one, this one, this one, and this one,
then the matrices have exactly the property that you say.
There's a one over here and then
a three by three matrices down here.
Right.
And the same thing for this other case here.
There's a one.
Yeah.
That's right.
The matrices, the big eight, the big 64
by 64 dimensional matrices break up into a bunch.
A bunch of blocks.
Block diagonal.
Right.
It's block diagonal in a particular basis.
In the basis.
Right, in the basis.
That's right.
In fact, what you're saying
is that there exists a basis.
Exactly.
In which this complicated matrix.
That's right.
Simplifies into block diagonal.
So there are 64 states.
So the SU three operation has to be
represented on the two, on the two gluons.
Well just to make it simple.
So you're saying that it's 2.
Right.
on the two-gluon system as 64 by 64 dimensional matrices.
But in some basis, those 64 by 64 dimensional matrices
are a 1, an 8 by 8 matrix over here,
another 8 by 8 matrix over here,
then a 10 by 10, I don't have enough room,
another 10 by 10 matrix, and
then a 27 matrix down there.
In a particular basis, that's exactly right.
So each one of those doesn't mix the other ones?
That's right.
In the right basis, they don't get mixed.
This one doesn't get mixed with this
one, doesn't get mixed with this one.
They only get mixed
together as an 8-dimensional representation.
Is there a label or a name for that
type of subset of the total 64 by 64?
Is that basis?
You mean for a piece of it like this?
Yeah, whether that holds that or not.
Well, when you multiply...
I'm not sure what the right buzzword...
I think you're looking for a particular
term which is escaping me right now.
In fact, I don't think such a
term exists, but I know what you mean.
When you say particles...
The 10 particles don't exist in nature,
and the others, it says
that you've declared non-existent natures,
and you don't care about them.
Well, maybe you shouldn't say you shouldn't care about them,
but they won't appear as real particles in the laboratory.
We're going to talk about
what creates this peculiar situation
that you can't have a free quark
by itself, but we'll come to that.
So let's...
Let's talk about it a little bit.
Incidentally, the quantum chromodynamics idea
goes back a long ways.
It goes back a some time.
I know it's due to Nambu, the Yoichiro Nambu.
And Nambu had the idea quite about 1962,
quite maybe a good 10 years before quantum chromodynamics
became the standard theory of quarks and gluons.
In fact, the whole idea
of color goes back to him.
He didn't call it color.
I don't know what he called it.
And the idea of gluons also in the same idea.
And his idea was fairly simple.
He understood that if you made color singlets,
then you would not get fractionally charged particles.
That was his motivation.
What do you have to add into quantum chroma...
into the theory of quarks
in order to have some dynamics
which will forbid particles?
Particles of fractional charge.
So he realized that if the quarks
carried this kind of color quantum number,
and if the color always had to be a singlet,
then you would never get fractionally charged particles.
He had an answer to the question
of why particles should only occur in singlets,
and it went something like this.
He said,
All right, now we need another postulate,
and the other postulate is the connection
or the interaction between quarks and gluons.
The postulate is that gluons play
the same role in quantum chromodynamics
that photons do in electrodynamics,
but photons couple to the electric charge.
The source of the photon field is...
I said consonants, and it's
fun to get rid of them,
there's a new one called cube effect,
and on these chords you do
a sub à plus of add Racian,
with radian and ion allegrological rules.
This way you know that football
players are playing the same issue,
which isification,
wp,
O,
I forgot the slash,
있는데요17OhM buying it.
Take a break.
correspond to fields which are similar in some sense to
to the photons or to the electromagnetic field
the electromagnetic field is sourced by electric charge
what is the source of the gluon field
well what eight quantities do we have available the eight
generators of SU which are
analogous to angular momentum for SU
angular momentum is a conserved quantity
it's additive if you have two objects
you add their angular momentum
and color really means
when you speak of the color of
an object you're speaking about how it transforms
under the group
but the actual thing which radiates
the thing which radiates the gluon field
is the color itself or the color
itself or the generators of the color group
eight of them and each one can emit
the appropriate kind of gluon
the first meaning of this is that if
you take a colored object such as a quark
it's going to be surrounded by a gluon field
so much like electrodynamics
uh... the
the
seeing
quantum chromodynamics
replaces the electromagnetic field
with a quantum chromo
then with a chromodynamic field
but the only thing new about it
is that there are eight such fields
and the eight such fields
transform the same way under that same
eight that's associated with the eight gluons
ok so that's the first thing
now the second thing is to know something about
ah
about the dynamics of electromagnetism
Let's begin with a charge and an anti-charge
A charge and an anti-charge attract each other
The meaning of that is that if you
bring them close together, the energy goes down
So a charge and an anti-charge have less energy if
they're close together than they are if they're far apart
That's why they bind, that's why they bind
Because the energy of a neutral system is
less than the energy of the two charge
Well, the energy of a neutral system is lower
than the energy of a charge system as a rule
For example, the energy of two plus charges is much more
than the energy of a plus charge and a minus charge
How do I know that? Because
the two plus charges repel each other
You have to do work to
push the two plus charges together
You get work out of letting a
plus charge fall towards a minus charge
So here's an example where a system with a net charge
has more energy than a system in which the charges cancel out
Another way to think about it is if you have
two plus charges, the lines of force have to go somewheres
And so there's net field
Out beyond the object
That net field has field energy
Field energy is always positive, it's proportional
to the square of the electric field
And so there's field energy stored in the
fact that there are two plus charges here
If there was a plus charge and a
minus charge, there might be field in between them
And let's suppose you brought them very close together
There might be a little dipole field in there,
but there would be no field on the outside
There would be no large field energy on the outside
And so the field energy stored in a neutral system
is less than the field energy stored in a charge system
The larger the charge of the electron, the more profitable
it is, let's say, to have a neutral system energetically
Or the less profitable or the more expensive it
is in energy to have a neutral system energetically
is in energy to have a net charge system
So the bigger the electric charge, if the electric charge
of the electron was a thousand times bigger than it is
The self energy of the electron, due to the
electromagnetic field, would be much bigger than it is
In fact, the repulsive force between two plus
charges would be much, much stronger than it is
And the amount of energy it would take to
assemble two plus charges would be very much bigger
Than the energy needed for a plus charge system
So the large charge of the
electron would be a minus charge system
The huge charge of the electron would then
make it very, very prohibitive to have net charge
And very, very efficient, low energy,
to have all charges cancel out
So if the coupling constant
of electrodynamics were large, very large
We would be very used to the idea that the
low energy particles, the low mass, mass is energy of course
The low mass particles in nature would be very large
The low mass objects in nature would be electrically neutral
If the charge was big enough, we
might never have discovered individual electrically charged particles
They would be confined
It would just be too prohibitive in energy
to pull them out of an atom, for example
So what Nambu said is, look,
if I have this quantum chromodynamics
And if color, the color generator,
or the color degree of freedom
Is the source of the gluon field
Then if we make the charge, the numerical coupling constant
The analog of electric charge,
if we make it large enough
Then it would be simply impossible to
pull apart these quarks into non-singlet states
A singlet state is the analog of neutral
Pulling them apart, you would be
left over with net amounts of particles
And you would have a color
which would cost you lots of energy
So he understood that when systems
were in the color singlet state
They were fully attractive and pulled themselves together
When they weren't, there was always an element of repulsion
That meant it cost an enormous
amount of energy to pull them together
So that was Nambu's explanation
He said, quantum chromodynamics has
a natural way of making sure
That the real particles in nature are integer charged
And that quarks always come
in either the quark-anti-quark combination
Or the three-quark combination
And this was essentially correct
It turned out to be correct
But the dynamics is a little more interesting than that
So let's talk about the dynamics
and why the dynamics is more interesting
Any questions up until now?
Okay
Why is the dynamics more interesting than that?
And the reason the dynamics is more interesting than that
Is because the analog of the photon, the gluon
Is charged, carries color
The gluon itself is not neutral with respect to the
Remember, the neutral piece was this
ninth member that we threw away
The eight gluons themselves are not neutral
They transform under the eight
It's as if they had a color charge
That is why gluons don't appear in nature as objects
The color, they themselves are colored
And because they're colored, they have
a big color field around them
And they're prohibitive in energy
But this is interesting
What it says is that the gluon itself is
charged in a way that the photon is not
The fact that photons are not charged
Means they don't interact with each other
They're not sources
A photon is not a source of another photon
Electrodynamics, or at least classical electrodynamics
Is a completely linear theory
Meaning to say that electromagnetic waves
just pass right through each other
That's because the electromagnetic
wave itself is not charged
And doesn't influence other electromagnetic waves
So, electrodynamics, the photon
And the electromagnetic wave are very simple and linear
But in quantum chromodynamics it's much more complicated
The analog of the photon itself is charged
That means that the analog of an electromagnetic wave
Intersecting another electromagnetic wave
Will be a serious interacting phenomenon
In fact, even just a single wave of the gluon
One part of it will interact with the other
One part of it may have some color
The other part of it may have some color
Those colors will interact with each other
And the dynamics of gluons is far
And the, not just gluons
But the field
Analogous to the electromagnet, to the Maxwell field
Is far, far more complicated
And dynamically interesting
But also much more difficult to understand
It turned out that the
Pretty much the important thing that happens
Which is new
Can be summarized fairly easily
And I'll summarize it for you on the blackboard
In terms of pictures
The equations that go with this
There are equations
But the pictures I think are better than the equations
There's a quark
And there is, and there is
A quantum chromo dynamical gluons field around it
Now in Electro-dynamics
The different phoetons, or electromagnetic fields
Do not interact with each other
And so there's no sense
In which one field line
Repels or retracts other field lines
They just, they just completely independent
They don't interact with each other
In quantum chromo dynamics
The gluon field itself
is not neutral and therefore the gluon
field interacts with other pieces of gluon field
and the result is very simple.
It turns out to be fairly simple.
The lines of flux basically attract each other.
They attract each other and they
attract each other in a way
which makes...
The rule about lines of flux is
they don't end except on another charge.
The lines of flux coming out of a quark
or coming out of a color charge attract each other
and in the process of attracting each other
energetically they want to form tubes.
They want to form tubes of flux
with the flux running right down the tube.
It is more or less you can either imagine
that the lines of flux are attracting each other
or that empty space is repelling the lines of flux
and pushing them and squeezing them
into the flux.
That's what happens.
That's pretty much the main effect
of the nonlinear interactions between the gluon field
that it makes it energetically favorable
to take those lines of flux and bundle them
and bundle them into tubes.
Let's suppose that's true now.
Now supposing we have a quark and an anti-quark.
We have a quark and an anti-quark
lines of flux come out of
the quark and go into the anti-quark.
If this were electrodynamics, those lines of flux
would separate and form a nice dipole pattern
that we're all familiar with.
Anybody who's ever looked at a magnet and...
Right.
The field energy associated with this
big dipole configuration is relatively small
because the field gets weak far away.
Right.
In this configuration, there's a uniform field,
no matter how far you
take these particles from each other,
there is a uniform field in between,
just exactly as if you
took an electric or magnetic field
and pushed it through a tube.
There would be a uniform field,
the lines of flux don't end,
and because there's a uniform field,
there's a uniform energy per unit length.
What's the result of that?
The result of that is if you
try to separate a quark from an anti-quark,
the energy just grows linearly
with the distance between them.
As you pull this out, it's
like the gluon field was really sticky,
really Turkish taffy,
except Turkish taffy would get thinner
and thinner as you stretched it out.
So it's not quite like chewing gum of Turkish taffy.
It's like a kind of chewing gum that,
as you separated it,
always created more chewing gum in between
so that it never got thinner and thinner.
There's always a fixed number of lines of flux
coming out of every charged object,
and they don't disappear.
So this tube, it's called a flux tube,
or a fluxoid,
and the fluxoid has a uniform charge per unit distance.
Any charged object, which means
any object with non-zero color,
any non-singlet, any object which is not a singlet,
here it is, it puts out lines of flux.
Those lines of flux bundle themselves,
and unless they end on an object of opposite color,
that object is just going to have an infinite charge
because those lines of flux have to go someplace.
They'll end in infinity.
The cost and energy will go up.
That's the difference.
That's the basic dynamics of quantum chromodynamics.
Linear flux tubes like this,
which are the ingredients which keep quarks
from flying around freely.
If you hit a quark real hard inside a meson,
this is a picture of a
sort of extreme picture of a meson,
a quark and an anti-quark.
You hit that quark hard, it goes flying out,
but it simply can't get away.
The field energy just increases,
increases and increases and increases linearly with distance
until you've run out of kinetic
energy and then it gets pulled back.
Or something else happens.
What's the other thing that can happen?
Right.
Yeah, right.
The other thing that can happen
is that the string can break.
If this is a quark and this is an anti-quark,
then spontaneously, it's going to break.
And then spontaneously out of the vacuum,
particle pair production can create an anti-quark over here
and a quark over here.
But you still haven't created a quark.
You've created two mesons.
So you give one quark
in a meson a good shot.
You hit it really hard.
It tries to escape.
And either it can't escape because it
runs out of energy and gets pulled back,
but actually, it can't escape.
But actually, more likely, what will
happen is a quark and an anti-quark
will be created in between
and you'll just create two mesons.
If this quark over here is still going too fast,
it may still try to escape.
It may try to escape this one over here.
What will happen?
And so what happens when you
hit a quark really hard is that,
inside a meson, is that a
whole bunch of mesons go flying off,
forming what is called a jet.
Do you ever get any other hadrons?
Oh, yeah.
Oh, yes, absolutely.
You can get anything as long as it's neutral.
This is the picture of a meson.
The other ingredient that is in quantum chromodynamics
is that three quarks can exist.
This doesn't explain three quarks.
The three quarks are explained by a mathematical fact.
The flux lines can come together in threes.
Quark, quark, quark.
And, uh, but that's not
too surprising because three quarks, again,
make a neutral object.
Three quarks, again, make a neutral object.
And that means that if you have three quarks,
there'll be no net lines coming out of it.
So somehow the lines are forced to
come out of each one of them,
have to...
be able to cancel each other.
That's quantum chromodynamics.
It's based on the SU group.
And it's called a gauge theory.
A gauge theory is simply
any theory where the conserved quantities
are coupled to a Maxwell-like field,
are coupled to a field similar to photons.
It has a deeper meaning
than that, but for our purposes,
any time there is a
conserved quantity analogous to electric charge,
which functions as the source of a photon-like field,
photon-like field, a gluon-like field,
that's called a gauge theory.
The gauge theories are always based on symmetries.
Why are they based on symmetries?
Because they're based on the idea of conserved charge.
And conserved charge means a symmetry of some kind.
Incidentally, why...
What's the connection between conservation and logic?
Between conservation and lines of flux.
Conservation and lines of flux are intimately connected.
If you have a rule, for example, in electrodynamics,
that every charged particle has to
be the source of lines of flux,
and that lines of flux
can only end on charged particles,
then charge has to be conserved.
There's no way...
Remember, these lines of force go off to infinity.
Well, you could say, I
could make this charge suddenly disappear
if I allow the lines
of flux to simultaneously all disappear.
But that would violate the speed of light constraint.
You would be able to
send a message arbitrarily far distance
if, by simply removing that charge,
you suddenly changed the field at infinity.
The fact that you cannot send a
signal faster than the speed of light
tells you that you can't remove this charge.
Why?
Because it's sort of anchored
by the flux lines at infinity,
and if you could remove it,
either one of two things.
Either you would send a sudden signal far away
that the charge wasn't there by removing the field,
or you would be left
over with these lines of flux
that don't end on charges.
So if lines of flux have to end on charges,
then that's tantamount to saying that
the sources of the field are conserved,
which, in another language, says there must be a symmetry.
So some symmetries are connected with photon-like fields
which give rise to lines of flux.
Those theories are called gauge theories.
And you can't even imagine,
without breaking the rules of physics,
without breaking the rules of a theory,
what it would mean for
the charge not to be conserved,
because the rules of a theory attach the charged particles
to the lines of force.
Okay, that's quantum chromodynamics.
Now we've actually gone,
either depending on how you count,
either two-thirds or three-quarters of
the way through the standard model,
we've gone through nine generators, if you like.
The eight generators of SU3,
the electric charge,
the electric charge, which is
not the ninth generator of U3.
The electric charge, those are nine conserved quantities.
They couple to the nine gauge fields,
the eight gluons and the photon.
The standard model has three more generators,
which we will talk about.
So we've got nine out of twelve.
That's three-quarters.
The other way of counting
is to say we studied SU3,
that's quantum chromodynamics.
We've studied U1, that's electrodynamics.
The standard model is SU3 cross SU2 cross U1.
We're missing the SU2.
The SU2, it's not angular momentum.
There's another ingredient in the standard model called SU2.
We'll start to take up SU2 next time.
We've covered a lot of ground,
and I think in about two more lectures,
we can probably finish off the basic structure
of the standard model, SU3 cross SU2 cross U1,
put it together into a package,
and I think the other
element that we need, of course,
is the Higgs field.
The Higgs field plays an important role there.
But I would say within about three lectures,
we will have the working parts of the standard model.
And then we can start to
explore what the puzzles of it are,
why people think we have
to go beyond the standard model,
and why people think there are
going to be interesting new things
discovered at CERN.
I think that's what we want to get.
Okay, good.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.