Stanford University.
All right, we've really studied
two different theories a little bit,
quantum electrodynamics and quantum chromodynamics.
Both of them are gauge theories.
In fact, just about all of nature as
we know it, in one way or another,
is controlled by gauge theories of different kinds.
And so I ought to tell
you what a gauge theory is.
Now, I'm not going to get into
in any depth what gauge symmetry is.
I'm going to tell you what
a gauge theory is in more or
less the minimal mathematical way.
The first and simplest gauge theory is Maxwell's theory.
Maxwell's theory of light,
or Maxwell's theory of electromagnetism,
let's not do that.
Let's not worry about what the word gauge means.
We may go through it later, but not now.
But what it is is a theory
of fields which have all of the properties
of the electromagnetic field.
The electromagnetic field has six
components, three components of electric
field, three components of magnetic field.
You can represent those six components
in terms of a four vector,
called the vector potential.
I'll just write it down for you.
It's not going to play any big role today anyway.
But just to tell you, there's
a four vector that's generally called a,
and it has an index mu.
It has four components, a zero,
that's the time component of it, and
the three space components, a1, 2, and
3, or a x, y, and z.
Let's not write them out in detail.
So it contains a three vector
and a fourth component, a naught.
The significance of a naught
is that it's the electrostatic potential.
It's the thing whose gradient is the electric force.
So for example, the electric force on a charged
particle is just gotten by multiplying the electric force,
the electric charge, by the gradient or the derivative,
fx, derivative of a naught with respect to x.
So it's just the electrostatic potential.
It's measured in volts, or in particle
physics, of course, it's not measured in volts.
Volts per unit charge, excuse me.
Volt, yeah.
It's measured in whatever way you measure electrostatic.
So it's just the electrostatic potential.
That's the meaning of a naught.
Notice first of all, oh, and
of course this is the electric field.
This is the electric field.
It has three components, derivative with
respect to x, y, or z.
So it's the gradient, the gradient of a.
And the gradient of a
is just called the electric field.
So the electric field is determined
by the gradient of a naught.
Okay.
And the magnetic field is determined by
also derivatives, also derivatives of the vector potential.
And in fact, the magnetic field
is the curl of the vector potential.
So one of two ways you can study electrodynamics,
either in terms of the electric and magnetic fields,
of which there are six, or in terms
of the vector potential, of which there are four,
but they're equivalent descriptions of electrodynamics.
And we won't go into maximizing that.
Okay.
We won't go into Maxwell's equations.
But let me just remind you that
Maxwell's equations give rise to electromagnetic waves.
An electromagnetic wave is a
wave of electric and magnetic field.
And a typical electric magnetic wave has
a direction in space that it moves.
Let's just represent it by an arrow.
And it has a polarization.
To understand what the polarization means, you have
to think about the electric and magnetic fields.
And the electric and magnetic fields oscillate.
Okay.
So let's go down the wave.
Here's the electric field, for example.
The whole thing moves with the speed of light.
But at any given instant, the
electric field might look like that.
And the magnetic field is
always perpendicular to the electric field.
Let's try to draw it, see
if I can give a drawing.
I'm imagining the electric field is in the horizontal plane.
And it's always perpendicular to the...
Let's see, is this gonna...
It's always perpendicular.
Like so.
In appropriate units, the electric and magnetic
field are equal to each other and perpendicular.
This would be a plane polarized electromagnetic wave.
In a plane polarized electromagnetic wave, the direction of
polarization, which of course, is a plane, is a wave.
Which of course, is a wave.
Yes, which of course, is always
perpendicular to the direction of motion,
the direction of polarization is
determined by the electric field.
So the electric field determines the
direction of polarization and that's electromagnetism
and lots of electromagnetic waves, in a nutshell.
the other thing, of course, about
electromagnetic waves is that there are sources.
Part ofoin exsules are charges and currents.
But let's particularly focus onthe
sources of the electric field.
Part of the electric field is the
beam of current of the energy of.
theinação of electric current en.
So the electric field, our electric charge, and to
just draw a picture, to put it at the
level of pictures, every electric
charge creates an electric field.
The electric field lines never end except on other charges.
A positive convention, the convention is a
positive electric charge puts out an electric
field which is radially outward, falls
off as 1 over r squared.
You can imagine that the number of electric
field lines coming out of a charge is fixed,
proportional to the charge, and therefore
the number of electric field lines passing
through any sphere is the same
no matter how far the sphere is.
To say that mathematically, the integral of
the electric field over the sphere is the
same wherever you go.
However, if you look at the electric field,
you can see that the electric field is fixed.
It's not as far out as you go.
That's Gauss's law.
And that Gauss's law has a very strong consequence.
If you don't have any other charges in
the system, let's say just a plus charge, then
you can't get, and the rule is electric lines
only end on charges, then there's no way to
get rid of a charge.
No way to get rid of a charge.
If you try to get rid of the
charge, you can't get rid of the charge.
Either the electric field
has to suddenly disappear everywhere.
That would violate the rules of the speed
of light, that you can't send a signal faster
than the speed of light.
So instead, if you said that a wave
moved outward of missing electric field, that also
wouldn't make sense, not unless there were
charges at the end of the charge.
Now what I would do is try to figure
out how you could handle the rich electric field
when there aren't.
If you are trying to get rid of charge,
you can't just sort of take a charge and bring
it around where it kend off, it
spreadsheet of charge could be a lot better.
Where it's blocked out or not.
You can do this.
But this is not necessarily
what I want you to do.
This is not.
The beautiful better way to get
rid of electric field is to 04
to 04.
Why not say I'm right.
Just go through.
There's an old saying.
I'm not going to tell you this story.
Okay, one more time and then we'll get to 00002.
That the electric field is the peak but there are?
That is the essence of a gauge theory.
Essence of a gauge theory, Maxwell-like fields, I'll use the
word Maxwell-like because they're not all truly Maxwell's electromagnetic field.
Maxwell-like fields consisting of
electric-like and magnetic-like fields.
If the gauge field is weakly coupled, and
I will tell you what that means later,
but it basically means that if the interactions between the parts of the
electromagnetic field are weak enough that they don't interact with each other seriously,
then the motion of a gauge field
is exactly the same as a light wave.
It will have a polarization, it will move
down the axis with the speed of light,
unless there's something in the dynamics
that changes that, naively at least,
it's in every way similar to the electromagnetic field.
The only difference is, it also has sources, every
gauge field has sources, analogous to the electric charge,
but it may not be the electric charge.
It might be something else.
Let me give you an
example which is an unphysical example,
unphysical not because it's inconsistent, but because it just
happens not to be true as far as we know.
There is another quantity in
nature called the baryon number.
It's simply the number of
quarks, but it's a conserved quantity.
And you could imagine that
baryon number is the source of,
now baryon number is not electric charge,
why not?
Well, because protons and neutrons have
it, so it is not electric charge,
but it could be the
source of its own gauge field.
If it were, that would mean that there would
be forces between protons, neutrons, protons, protons, neutrons, neutrons,
that would be analogous to
the Coulomb forces between charges,
except it would have nothing to do with electric charge,
they would have only to do with baryon number.
So, for example, two objects with the
same baryon number would repel each other.
A proton and a neutron would repel each
other because they have the same baryon number.
A proton and a proton would repel.
On the other hand, proton and
anti-proton having opposite baryon number would attract.
Now, the only rub in this ointment
is that there is no such gauge field,
coupled to the baryon number.
Baryon number does not come with
a field like this that surrounds it,
and no long-range force associated with it.
So baryon number is not an example.
Color is an example.
And the color forces of quantum chromodynamics also,
oh, before I do that, one or two other points,
one or two other points.
The other point, of course, is this is
a completely classical description of an electromagnetic wave.
The corresponding quantum mechanical description
is in terms of quanta,
but of course if we think of quanta as particles,
at least that's about the only mental picture
that we have to describe these discrete little objects.
The discrete little objects which drawing them, of course,
is always misleading, but let me draw
a photon, there's a photon, a little point.
That little photon has a position,
moves with the speed of light,
but also it has a little flag associated with it,
and that little flag is its polarization.
I won't try to draw a flag on it.
In other words, it has a pointer, which either
points this way, this way, or somewheres in between,
that indicates the polarization of the electromagnetic wave,
of which it is a quantum.
That's a complicated statement, but I think you get it.
So, photons come with polarization,
and that polarization, in principle, can be rotated.
You can rotate it by sending it through a
quarter wave plate, or in any number of ways.
And that's photons, that's
the photon theory of electromagnetism.
And in the quantum theory,
one can think of the Coulomb field as, roughly speaking,
a field set up by
the emission and absorption of photons.
Emission and absorption of these photons.
Okay, so that's, that's electrodynamics in a nutshell.
Electrons are charged, protons are charged, and so forth,
and they interact in this way with the gauge field.
Another aspect of gauge fields,
I've already mentioned it,
that there's a,
there's always conservation laws associated with them,
namely conservation of the sources.
But conservation laws in both
quantum mechanics and classical mechanics
are always associated with symmetries.
Symmetries of some sort or
another are always behind conservation laws.
The conservation of electric
charge, we've talked about that,
and I showed you how,
if you,
study the quantum mechanics of electrons,
in terms, or charged particles in general,
there's a wave field describing those particles,
this could be the electron,
and the symmetry associated with the conservation of charge
is just the multiplication of the field by a phase.
So that was the simplest example of a gauge theory,
a gauge charge, meaning the electric charge,
and a symmetry that goes along
with the conservation of that charge.
Those things go together.
Okay, well, how,
let me just very quickly remind
you how it worked in quantum chromodynamics.
In quantum chromodynamics,
a more complicated structure,
you do have Maxwell-like fields,
let's label them.
The Maxwell-like fields are labeled by indices.
So in quantum chromo, let's continue to call them A.
There is no universal symbol
for the gauge field of quantum chromodynamics.
Sometimes it's called G, sometimes it's called A,
sometimes it's called B, sometimes it's called C.
I'm going to call it A,
but in order to distinguish
it from the electromagnetic field,
we give it some indices,
I and J.
It's a matrix.
Now,
it's a matrix,
and that matrix transforms under a group.
The group was SU3.
So let me just remind you very, very quickly
that we started thinking about SU3
not by thinking about gluons,
this of course would be the gluon field,
but by thinking about quarks.
So a quark was an object which we called Q.
Q could stand for the quantum field of the quark,
and it has an index.
The index, it's not the up-down index,
it's not the charm-strange index,
we'll come to that sooner or later,
it is the color index,
red, green, or blue.
I takes on three values,
and the symmetry operation
is not multiplying by e to the i theta,
but multiplying by a unitary,
special unitary matrix,
Uij,
gives us Q prime i.
That was the symmetry operation,
which is a kind of rotation
in a kind of three-dimensional complex space.
Don't confuse it with a matrix.
Don't confuse it with ordinary three-dimensional space.
This was the symmetry operation,
and one would say that the Qs,
think of them as particles if you like,
the Qs form a representation of SU3
which is called the fundamental representation.
It's called the fundamental representation,
it has three entries, red, green, and blue.
Sometimes it's called the defining representation.
It's the smallest non-trivial representation.
And it just has,
just can be thought of as a three-component vector,
one, two, three,
and the unitary matrices can be thought of as matrices,
three by three matrices.
Okay, we've gone through that.
The other thing that I told you
is that anti-quarks,
or anti-particles in general,
are represented by the complex conjugate fields
fields which are simply the complex conjugates
of the original ones.
The relation, the mathematical relation
between particle and anti-particle,
or the wave functions of particles and anti-particles,
that relationship is complex conjugation.
So, we could ask,
how do anti-particles transform?
Well, we simply realize
that if you want to transform the complex conjugates,
the complex conjugate field,
you should use the complex conjugate matrix.
If you multiply q by u to get q prime,
then you must multiply q star by u star
to get q prime star.
The set of matrices u,
we call the representation of the group.
The set of matrices u star
are a distinct and different representation of the group,
and the language one would use
is that quarks and anti-quarks
are described by the three-dimensional representation
and we could call it three star,
meaning complex conjugate.
It's usually indicated by a bar.
Two different representations of SU .
So there's seven u matrices?
How many?
Seven?
Eight.
Nine, actually.
Well, sorry.
You asked me how many matrices there are?
For u, I guess that's the number of generators.
The number of generators is eight.
Yeah, because these matrices are assumed
to be special unitary matrices.
Now, you can ask, and it's interesting to ask,
what kind of theory would you make
if you didn't insist that they'd be special?
And I'll tell you another time,
maybe later, but not now.
Okay, now what is Aij?
Aij has two indices,
and the way to think about
it is that one of those,
it is mathematically got the same group theory structure,
the same symmetry structure,
as having a quark j and an anti-quark i.
In other words, this is an object
whose indices transform one index
as the three-dimensional representation
and the other index as the three-bar.
Another way to think about it
is it has all of the properties
with respect to the symmetry,
not with respect to all physical properties,
but with respect to the way it transforms.
It transforms as if it
were a quark and an anti-quark
sitting on top of each other.
Not its spin, just its color,
as if it were a quark and an anti-quark.
With one special rule,
namely the trace of Aij vanishes.
The singlet, the singlet that you can make,
the piece which has no transformation property
under the group at all,
that you can kill and forget about.
That's why there are eight Aijs instead of nine.
So Aij is like a thing
with a quark and an anti-quark index.
But because it has a quark and an anti-quark index,
it also transforms when you,
under the SU transformation group.
In that sense, it's different than the photon.
The photon is completely electrically neutral.
Its field, the photon field,
does not get a phase
when you rotate the electron wave function.
Electrons go to e to the i theta,
times electrons.
Positrons go to e to the minus i theta,
times positrons.
Photons do nothing.
That's because they don't have electric charge.
But the gluons,
they do have color.
Now what kind of color do they have?
They have the color of a particle and an anti-particle.
And you say, well, a particle and an anti-particle
shouldn't have any color.
But they do, because you could have a red particle
and a blue anti-particle.
A red, that would make a thing
which was not really neutral,
which knew about color.
So gluons do have color,
and they have color in what is called
the adjoint representation,
which is the representation of the eight generators.
Okay, now,
what about,
what about the interaction between quarks?
Incidentally,
there are many other gauge theories of interest.
They're all pretty similar to each other.
The group might not be SU3,
it might be SU2,
it might be SU4,
it might be SU10,
it might be anything.
And the objects of the group
might not be called quarks.
Nevertheless,
or the fundamental objects of the group,
the analogs of quarks,
might be called something else.
They might have a different name.
But they would be objects which had a single index.
The anti-objects would also have a single index,
but of the complex conjugate kind.
And the analog of the gluons,
which are called gauge bosons,
gauge bosons,
Maxwell-like fields,
always have one index of the particle type
and another index of the index.
So they're all of the same type.
So that means,
let's see,
if we're talking about SU ,
that means how many generators altogether?
Well,
n times n is n
squared minus one for the trace.
So it's n squared minus one distinct gluons.
Now,
what is the connection between the quarks
or more generally,
the
particles which transform like quarks,
perhaps in a more general way?
What's the connection between them and the gauge bosons?
And I've explained that to you before,
but let me just remind you again.
If you have a quark labeled by I,
where I could be red, green, or blue,
and another quark labeled by J,
that the ith quark can become the,
can become the jth quark
if
a gauge boson is emitted.
What kind of gauge boson?
Well,
as I showed you before,
the way to think about it
is just to think about these lines
running through the diagram.
I runs right through,
so that's I,
and J also runs right through,
except when J is pointing downward,
it should be thought of as the,
the analog of an antiparticle.
And so,
an I would become a J
by emitting a quanta,
a quantum of the field A,
is it J I or I J?
I think I J.
No, J I.
Doesn't matter very much.
By emitting a gluon of the I Jth type,
by emitting a gluon of the I Jth type,
an Ith particle becomes a Jth particle,
and that is one of the basic interactions
of quantum,
of gauge theories in general,
of gauge theories in general.
Fundamental objects,
analogous to quarks,
gauge bosons,
analogous to gluons,
and a rule about emission and absorption
that you have to follow the lines
and never lose an index.
Right?
But now,
that raises something new.
If a gluon itself
has the properties
of a quark and an anti-quark,
so let's say this is
the I Jth kind of gluon.
Well, the I Jth kind of gluon
can also emit a gluon.
How would it do it?
The I Jth gluon could become the I Kth gluon.
I J, let's say, red-green gluon
could become the red-blue gluon
as long as the indices make sense
and they're followed, anti-K here.
All right, so this would be an interaction
in which a gluon of type I J
became a gluon of type I K
and a gluon of type I K.
And a gluon of type K J.
A gluon of type K J.
The order of I and K matters.
A K J is not
the same as a J K.
But, um...
All right, that introduces something absolutely new
which is not in electrodynamics.
Namely, that the gluons themselves
are charged particles
and therefore exert forces on each other.
They exert forces in a way that photons do not
exert forces on each other.
The dynamics of gluons is much, much more complicated
than the dynamics of photons.
The last time, what I told you
was that one of the...
And I'm not going to do the mathematics of this.
It's not even fully understood even now.
But the effect...
One of the important effects
is that if you have a source,
a color, a bit of color,
with field lines coming out of it,
again, those field lines are not allowed to end.
They're not allowed to end.
But the effect, let's suppose,
that's a quark, is an anti-quark over here.
Field lines have to come into it.
So the field lines have
to be continuous and so forth.
I don't want...
Let me not draw more than that.
Now, the effect is that the field lines
interact with each other in a way
that they don't in electrodynamics.
And the effect is very simple.
The field lines get pulled into bundles,
which are called flux tubes,
the result of which is...
that no matter how far apart you pull two quarks,
they'll never escape from each other
because the energy stored in this
gooey piece of glue
just increases linearly with the distance between them.
All right, that's a summary of quantum chromodynamics,
but it's also a summary of gauge theory.
It's also a summary,
very, very quick summary of gauge theory.
Maxwell-like fields,
sources,
Gauss's law,
making sure you have conservation,
and symmetries.
Symmetries having to do with the conservation laws,
but more than that,
the symmetries telling you
how the particles interact with each other
in terms of emission and absorption.
There is one other thing in a gauge theory,
and it's the coupling constant.
The coupling constant is the analog
of the charge of the electron.
The charge of the electron,
let's talk about what the charge of the electron means.
It is, of course,
the coefficient in a Feynman diagram
when you emit
a photon from a charged particle,
the amplitude for that,
the quantum mechanical amplitude for that
is the electric charge.
But if you wanted to think about it operationally,
you can imagine an electric charge
slamming into the cathode of a cathode ray tube.
When it slams into it,
it gets accelerated,
and the question is,
what is the probability
that an electron which is stopped suddenly
emits a photon?
The answer is the square of the electric charge.
Okay?
The square,
it's really the square of the electric charge,
there's some pi's in it,
and h-bars and things,
but basically the square of the electric charge
in suitable units
is the probability for emitting a photon.
So that's what,
in quantum mechanics and field theory,
that is what the meaning of the electric charge is.
It's a measure of the,
the square of the electric charge is the probability.
Why?
Because probabilities are always squares of amplitudes.
But that's the,
that's the fundamental significance of the electric charge.
And the electric charge is a dimensionless number.
Just the probability that when you stop an electron,
you emit a photon.
So it's a dimensionless number.
It's a small dimensionless number.
And with appropriate sets of definitions,
the square of the electric charge,
really what tends to come into things
is not quite the square of the electric charge,
it's the square of the electric charge,
divided by some 4 pi.
4 pi's are always floating around in there.
It's called the fine structure constant.
And the fine structure constant,
which is pretty much the probability of a photon emission,
is a number of about 1%.
It's close to being 1 over 137,
a famous number, 1 over 137.
The 137 has no particular significance.
It's just numerically about,
what the fine structure constant is.
And let's just call it 1%.
It says there's a 1% probability of emitting a photon.
So if you had a picture that
when an electron hits a cathode ray tube,
it sends out a spray of photons,
that's not right.
What is right is that if
137 photons hit the cathode ray tube,
on the average, one of
them will give off a photon.
In that sense,
electromagnetism is a weak force,
or a weak process.
The probability of emission is weak.
Alright, that's the quick summary of gauge theory.
What I wanted to do
is give you a very, very briefly
a
rundown on some numbers and orders of magnitude
in various parts of particle and atomic physics.
And then go on to the weak interactions.
Now the reason I'm giving you a rundown about numbers
is to show you how different the weak interactions...
Quantum chromodynamics is the
theory of the strong interactions.
The strong interactions was the word
before quantum chromodynamics was invented
for the interactions between subnuclear particles,
between hadrons,
between protons, neutrons, mesons,
and all the things which are in the atom.
Which are made of quarks and gluons.
So it's the theory of strong interactions.
Um...
And...
There are electromagnetic interactions,
and there are also weak interactions.
So I want to spend a
little bit of time with numbers
to show you where the terminology came from,
why one is called weak, why
the other one is called strong,
why electromagnetism is sort of in
the middle between the two of them.
But let's just review a couple of numbers.
Um...
First of all, in terms of units.
Energy, distance, and time
do not have to be thought of as different units.
They're all related with each other.
First of all, time and distance
really should not be distinguished
in any sensible set of units
that are useful for fundamental physics.
Uh...
We can set the speed of light equal to one,
and if we do, if we fix
the speed of light equal to one,
then time and distance have the same units.
Uh...
And we can use the same units.
And the...
As far as energy goes,
we could also choose to
set Planck's constant equal to one.
That's a useful thing to do in quantum mechanics.
An awful lot of equations get simpler
if you set h-bar equal to one.
Well, they don't get a lot simpler.
It just gets rid of the h-bars.
But you can set h-bar equal to one.
Now let me just remind you,
there's a connection between energy
e equals h frequency, right?
Or h-nu.
Or h-bar omega.
All the same thing.
Uh...
The units of h-bar, well,
we've set h-bar equal to one.
So in units in which h-bar are equal to one,
energy is equal to frequency.
But what's the units of frequency?
One over time.
Number of oscillations per second.
So that means that energy and time
have inverse units to each other.
You don't need to have a
separate unit for time and energy.
Any time you have a unit of energy,
it defines also a unit of time.
Now, of course, the unit of energy
is inverse to the unit of time.
So big energies correspond to small time intervals.
Uh...
And, okay, so let's, uh...
Let's write down some connections.
And since energy and time
are connected to each other,
and time and space have the same
units when c is equal to one,
then time and space
have units which are just inverse
units to the units of energy.
So, for example, here's a
unit of energy, one electron volt.
We've used electron volts before.
One electron volt cannot be thought of
as a unit of distance.
But the inverse, one inverse electron volt,
in other words, one over an electron,
one inverse electron volt is a unit of distance.
And just to have an idea of what it is,
it's about 10 to the minus seventh meters.
One electron volt is about
10 to the minus seventh meters.
So an electron volt is a fairly small distance,
but on the scale of fundamental physics,
it's not a small distance.
10 to the minus seventh meters is what?
Um...
10 to the...
Oh, a atom is 10 to the minus tenth meters,
something like that.
Yeah.
Okay, so it's fairly big.
Uh...
An atomic diameter, yeah, an atomic...
And we can...
Right.
And an atomic diameter,
one atom,
this is the atomic diameter,
that's about 10 to the minus tenth meters.
And so you can convert that to electron volts.
How many electron volts is it?
I don't know, whatever it is.
An inverse of about a thousand electron volts,
a kiloelectron volt.
An inverse kiloelectron volt is an atomic diameter.
Okay, another fact,
just converting distance,
if we know the distance or size of an atom,
then we know the time that
it takes light to go across it.
All right?
So the transit time,
there's another quantity,
transit time,
the time that it takes transit time,
the time for light to cross an atomic diameter,
what is that?
That's about 10 to the minus 18th seconds.
I've used the fact that light goes at
about 10 to the eighth meters per second.
Order of magnitude 10 to the minus 18th seconds.
These are just some numbers that I just wrote down.
But a different time scale,
all right, so this is the
time scale for light to go across,
go across an atom.
The different times,
and by an atom,
I don't mean the nucleus,
I mean the whole atom.
Another time scale is the time scale that
it takes for an electron to orbit an atom.
Now you might think,
why isn't that just about the transit time?
Transit time is about 10 to the minus 18th centimeters.
The reason is because
electromagnetic forces are fairly weak.
Because they are fairly weak,
the force on,
and the ultimate reason that they're weak
is because this fine structure constant is alpha,
which is E squared over 4 pi.
That's a small number of about 1 over 137.
Another way to say it is the
electromagnetic force on an electron is weak.
Because of that,
the acceleration on the electron is not too big,
and the orbit is fairly large.
The weaker the force on an object,
the larger the orbit is going to be.
Sorry,
the slower the electron will move
is what I meant to say.
The slower the electron will move,
and because the electron moves slowly
by comparison with the speed of light,
how much slower?
About 1% slower.
About this much slower.
The electron moves around with only
about 1% the speed of light,
and that means the orbital time,
orbital time,
that's about 10 to the minus,
let's see, it's bigger,
that time is bigger,
10 to the minus 16 seconds.
Another quantity sometimes of interest
is the decay time for an atom.
How long does it take for an atom,
an excited atom,
let's say a hydrogen atom,
with its electron,
one orbital time,
one orbital up from the ground state,
one orbit up from the ground state,
how long does it take to decay?
Now,
that is small,
doubly small,
with two powers of alpha.
What are the two powers of alpha?
First of all,
the acceleration of the electron is small.
Remember,
charges emit radiation when they're accelerated.
The acceleration is small
because the force is small,
so first of all,
the acceleration is small.
The electron moves around
with a relatively small acceleration,
compared to what it could have been
if alpha were bigger.
It moves around with a small acceleration,
but on top of that,
just like the electron plowing into the cathode ray tube,
there's another factor of alpha
when the electron is accelerated
in the probability that it emits,
a photon.
So as the electron goes around here,
first of all,
it's moving with a slow acceleration,
and second of all,
even that acceleration is not very efficient
in producing photons,
just because
the fine structure constant is small.
The net result is that the time scale,
order of magnitude,
decay time,
how long it takes
for an atom to decay,
decay time
is about a nanosecond.
So,
10 to the minus 9 seconds,
much longer
than the orbital time
or the transit time.
So the main thing is
there's a variety of different scales
in the atom,
and they're all related
by the fine structure constant.
They're related by powers of the fine structure constant.
The fine structure constant being a small number,
there are fairly large ratios
between different time scales.
Transit,
orbital,
and decay time.
All right,
now let's come to hadrons.
Hadrons are like atoms.
They're atoms made up out of quarks.
We could ask very much the same kind of questions.
First of all,
we could ask what is the hadronic diameter.
The hadronic diameter of a typical hadron,
it could be a proton,
neutron,
meson,
they're all more or less the same,
there's hadrons.
Hadrons,
hadrons.
The hadronic diameter is a lot smaller than the electron,
sorry,
than the atom.
It's a lot smaller than the atom.
It's not 10 to the minus 10th meters.
It's about five orders of magnitude smaller.
10 to the minus 15th centimeters.
It's also more or less the diameter of a nucleus,
nucleus of course being a few protons
and neutrons is going to be bigger.
Meters.
Sorry,
meters.
Hadron diameter is about 10 to the minus 15th meters,
five orders of magnitude smaller than an atom.
Part of the reason is because,
there's two reasons,
there's two reasons why it's small.
One of them has to do with
the fact that the constituents are heavier,
and heavier things will sit closer to the center.
The other has to do with something else,
that we'll come to in a minute,
but it's about five orders of magnitude smaller.
The transit time,
the transit time is just
gotten from the size straightforwardly.
Transit time,
this is not an independent thing,
it's just another measure of the size of the thing.
Just to get the numbers straight,
it's 10 to the minus 23rd seconds.
So that's a typical time scale for,
well,
it's for light,
it's for light to cross the hadron.
Okay,
but now we can also talk
about the orbital motion of quarks.
How long does it take for a
quark to swing around its wave function,
or swing around the interior of a proton?
And there,
the answer is,
about 10 to the minus 23rd seconds.
What about the decay time
of a typical hadron,
and the typical excited state of a hadron?
A vibrating hadron or an oscillating hadron,
how long does it take for it to decay?
And the answer is,
about,
now I'm talking about particular kinds of decays.
A decay where you hit a proton,
it starts oscillating,
and then emits a pion.
Those decays,
have a lifetime of about
10 to the minus 23rd seconds.
Different than this hierarchy of scales here.
What is the conclusion?
The conclusion is the analog of the fine structure constant
is much bigger,
close to one,
for hadrons.
In other words,
the emission probability,
of a quark,
was to get stopped,
in a fictitious cathode ray,
quirky cathode ray tube,
of quark flying off,
the probability for it to emit a gluon,
would be about one.
That's what these things indicate here.
The hierarchy here is entirely due
to the fine structure constant.
The lack of a hierarchy here,
can only mean that the corresponding quantity,
in quantum chromodynamics,
must be close to one.
By now it's been measured in many ways,
and it is much closer to one.
It's much larger,
than the corresponding quantity for electrodynamics.
One is a little bit, no.
It would seem that,
just special relativity would say,
that the decay time should be much
less than 10 to the minus 23rd,
because that's a computation like,
Yeah, I think that's a fair statement.
It's about as fast as
it could be, in other words.
It's about as fast as it could be.
Nothing's slowing it down.
This is why the strong interactions are called strong.
Now, the facts about the numbers here,
were known before quantum chromodynamics.
And it was understood,
that there was no hierarchy of scales,
and that's why it was called strong interactions.
We now trace it,
to the properties of the charge,
or the fine structure constant.
Incidentally,
for quantum chromodynamics,
the analogous quantity is not really,
one, it's about a fifth,
but much bigger,
than the one over 137 here.
Alright, so that was just,
some numbers,
and some facts about,
So this,
one is the fine structure constant,
and then the other is called what?
The strong,
strong force constant?
It's called alpha QCD.
Right.
So this is called alpha,
and the other one is called alpha,
QCD.
And it's about 0.23,
or something like that.
Or in context of paper,
may write alpha,
QCD.
What's that?
In context of paper,
may write alpha,
QED.
QCD.
I never heard alpha QED,
referred to as alpha QED,
but I think if you were,
writing a paper with both of them,
you might call the top one alpha QED,
yes.
I've never seen it referred to that,
have you?
Well, particularly,
if you're talking about shielding,
or something like that.
No, I can't,
I don't think I've ever seen it.
The value versus the measure value.
Oh, oh, oh.
It's just called alpha.
Sometimes,
the unshielded one is called the bare alpha,
the shielded one is called the renormalized alpha.
Right.
Okay.
Well,
that brings us to the weak interactions.
The weak interactions are called weak,
primarily,
because the decay times associated with them,
are very long.
They're much longer,
than the decay times,
associated with,
with either hadrons,
and they even tend to be longer,
than the decay times associated with atoms.
So,
there are processes in nature,
decay processes in nature,
in which particles,
elementary or otherwise,
decay,
by weak interactions,
where the time scale,
in other words,
the half-life for these decays,
is far longer,
than any scale,
that can be accounted for by these,
by numbers like this.
So, as an example,
here's some examples.
Well,
the lifetime of the neutron.
The neutron,
is a hadron,
and it decays.
Neutron,
goes to electron,
proton,
plus anti-neutrino,
and the lifetime for that is about 12 minutes.
That's absurdly long.
On particle physics scales.
Part of the reason,
is easy,
but it hardly accounts for the,
for the extraordinary stability of the neutron.
Part of the reason,
is the neutron is only a little bit bigger,
than the combined masses of the electron,
the proton,
and the neutron,
neutrino.
Let's just see.
Somebody have a question?
Somebody have out their pocket calculator,
pocket,
the mass of the neutron,
is,
940 MeV.
I don't know,
about 940.
The mass of the proton,
is about 939.
I think the actual difference between them,
is about one and a half MeV.
But then there's the electron,
which has a mass of about half an MeV.
All together,
out of this 940,
almost a thousand MeV,
the difference of mass,
of the proton,
the amount of available mass left over,
is tiny.
It's 0.1% or less.
If the neutron,
was slightly lighter,
than the sum of these masses,
it could not decay at all.
Just energy conservation would not allow it.
Remember, mass is energy.
It would not have enough energy to decay,
and still leave over some energy,
for kinetic energy of these particles.
So if the neutron was exactly,
the same as the sum
of the energy of the electron,
the proton,
and the neutrino,
the sum of the mass of them,
it wouldn't be able to decay at all.
If you gave it a mass,
tiny, tiny, tiny, tiny bit above that,
it would be able to decay,
but it would take a very long time.
The decay would be very slow.
So part of the slowness,
or the long lifetime of the neutron,
is attributable to the fact
that there's very little energy available,
for the decay to take place.
But given that,
that's hardly the bulk of the story.
12 minutes is so absurdly long,
that there's something much,
much more than that going on.
Another example,
let's see, where do I have it?
I guess I didn't write it down.
Another example of a,
this is called a weak decay,
for obvious reasons,
it's called a weak decay.
Another example,
is a charged pion.
Let's say a pymelon.
Minus.
A charged pion,
decays,
to an electron,
electron has negative charge,
and an anti-neutrino.
Yes, and an anti-neutrino.
That's another possible decay.
Charged pion,
goes to an electron,
and an anti-neutrino.
A positively charged pion,
could become,
a positron,
and a neutrino.
The lifetime for that,
I believe is about,
10 nanoseconds.
Longer,
than these,
atomic decay times.
And atomic decay times,
are very, very long,
by comparison with,
particle physics decay times.
Now,
this,
uh,
there is a decay of the charged pions,
to these particles.
There's another decay,
involving muons,
we're gonna come to muons soon enough,
similar to electrons.
But the point is,
not the particles that they decay into,
but two things.
First of all,
they also decay very slowly,
nanoseconds.
But there's plenty of energy available,
for these,
these decays.
These decays are not suppressed,
by the fact that the energies of the initial,
or the masses of the initial and final states,
are very close to each other.
So there's something else,
going on,
uh,
in weak interactions,
whatever weak,
whatever weak interactions are,
there's something,
that makes them proceed,
very, very slowly,
and weakly.
Alright,
so that's what we come to next,
is weak interactions.
Uh,
the,
primary,
or oldest example of which,
is the decay of the neutron.
The beta decay of the neutron,
called beta,
because electrons are originally called beta waves.
Alright,
that's,
and this is called,
the beta decay,
of the,
pion.
And in fact,
it's quite similar,
quite similar physics,
goes into both of them.
So,
to understand,
what's going on,
we need to understand,
about some more particles.
Particles that we haven't come to yet,
the leptons.
So,
we have,
a,
b,
h,
Then along here, let me list the up quark, the down quark,
the charmed quark, the strange quark, the top quark, and the bottom quark.
All right.
Each one of these boxes is filled.
There are red, blue, and green up quarks.
Let's put an x there.
There's an x here.
x here, x here, and so forth.
These x's represent all the possible quarks that exist.
Now, quantum chromodynamics has to do with
symmetries which connect red to green to blue.
It has to do with these unitary
transformations which mix up the colors of quarks.
They do not.
Those symmetries do not mix horizontally.
An SU symmetry, a color symmetry, may rotate an up red
quark into an up blue quark or an up green quark,
and the nature of the symmetry is to
act vertically to mix up things this way.
And also, at the same time, will mix the
different down quarks, the different colors of down quarks.
Okay.
The same symmetry will mix the different colors
of charmed quarks and strange quarks and so forth.
So the color symmetry acts vertically.
It mixes up the different rows here.
Yes, the unitary matrices mix up red, green, and blue.
I might have done better to put the rows where
the columns are and the columns where the rows are, but...
No, it's okay. It's good. It's good.
No, no. It's good. It's good. Right.
The weak interactions are associated with
symmetries which act horizontally in this picture.
They mix up with down.
They mix, and the same time that they
mix up with down, they mix charm with strange.
And they mix top with bottom.
Let me just remind you that an up quark
has the same properties apart for its mass,
same properties as a charm quark or a top quark.
The down quarks are similar
to strange quarks and bottom quarks.
Ups have charge two-thirds.
Downs have charge minus two-thirds.
Same here and here.
All right. So these are symmetries which
mix, if you like, upness with downness.
At the same time, charmness with strangeness.
And topness with bottomness.
Mixed up.
So it mixes these up, the symmetries.
Those symmetries, would you care to
speculate on what group might be involved?
SU because it acts on things, on doublets.
We simply have three doublets here.
They don't take up to charm or up to top.
They simply act on up and
down horizontally among pairs of things.
A group SU .
It is a gauge symmetry.
In other words, it is also,
comes together with forces, with gauge bosons,
with interactions and with
gauge interactions, with gauge fields.
We're going to get to those short enough.
But we've left out something from this table here.
It's kind of as if there was a fourth color.
Now the reason, the fourth
row here is not usually identified
as a color.
And the reason is because the
particles do not interact with the gluons.
But nevertheless, it is another row here.
Another row in which there are
particles which are filled in here.
And in a certain sense, they're,
well not in a certain sense,
they are also doublets.
These particles are also doublets.
And also get mixed up under this SU symmetry,
which moves things horizontally.
What are they?
What are those particles?
They're the leptons.
So in a sense, the fourth color
could be thought of as lepton number.
But what are the leptons?
The leptons are, first of
all, in the first column here,
there are analogous to the
up, or analogous to the down,
there is the electron.
The electron is a lepton.
But its partner, its partner is the neutrino.
But there are different neutrinos.
There's not only one neutrino.
This is called the electron neutrino.
What comes in the next column?
The muon.
The muon, in every respect except for mass,
is the same as an electron.
Just as in every respect except for mass,
the charm quark is like an up quark.
Or the strange quark is like a down quark.
And together with it, there's its own neutrino,
the muon neutrino.
And finally, the last one is called the tau.
And nu sub tau.
All of the charged leptons,
incidentally, neutrinos, of course,
as you might guess from their name,
are electrically neutral.
The electrons, muons, and taus have charge minus one.
They are put under the down column here,
not because their charge is
the same as the down charge,
but because the difference between the charges of the two
is the same as the difference up here.
What's the difference between the two?
The difference between the two is the charge up here.
What's the difference between the charge
of an up and a down?
Two-thirds minus minus one-third.
So the difference between this column and this column
is plus one unit of charge.
The difference between this column and this column
is also one unit of charge.
One, sorry, zero minus negative one.
So as you go from here to here,
you decrease charge by one unit,
as you go horizontally.
Now, should we take a break for five minutes?
Let's take a break for five minutes,
and then I will tell you about the W bosons.
W bosons are the gauge bosons of the weak interactions.
All right, so let's try now
to see if we can make
a microscopic gauge theory of the weak interactions.
As I said, the weak interactions
are based on a gauge theory
which mixes up to down,
neutrino to electron, and so forth.
And so rather than to
get into mathematics for the moment,
the mathematics of the group SU ,
which we'll come back to,
let's think a little more simply.
We've seen that in various situations,
the gauge bosons typically,
have the quantum numbers,
or the quantum properties,
of a particle and an antiparticle.
In the case of the...
In the case of the quantum chromo-dynamical interactions,
it is a quark and an antiquark,
so that's why we had
nine gauge bosons and so forth,
or eight, removing the trace.
So we could start by saying,
let's look at the population
and the possibilities of gauge bosons,
which have the properties of...
of a particle and an antiparticle.
But, let's not distinguish between
whether we're talking about quarks,
red quarks, blue quarks, green quarks, or leptons.
Let's just say a particle from this column,
with an antiparticle of this column.
And for simplicity,
let's just focus on the leptons.
You'll see in a moment
that you'll get the same thing
if you focused on the quarks.
But, let's focus on the leptons,
and talk about objects that we could make
with a lepton and an anti-lepton.
All right, first of all,
we could have some simple things,
electron with a positron.
Now, I don't really literally mean electrons and positrons.
We could have electrons and positrons.
Electrons and positrons have no charge at all.
So, let's drop that for a minute.
We'll come back to it.
There are things which have
properties of electrons and anti-electrons,
neutrinos and anti-neutrinos.
But more interesting for the moment
is the combination of electron-anti-neutrino.
So,
what is the charge of an object
which has the same conserved quantities,
the same properties as an electron
stuck on top of an anti-neutrino?
Well, let's just focus on its charge,
its electric charge.
Its electric charge is minus one.
Neutrino is neutral.
Electron has negative charge.
So, whatever this object is,
it has negative electric charge.
Let's give it a name,
and let's call it a gauge boson.
Let's assume that it is also a gauge boson.
Gauge boson means that it behaves like the Maxwell field,
the whole same thing.
But it has negative charge.
Let's call it W.
W, that's the traditional name for it.
W minus.
Why minus?
Because it has negative electric charge.
We could...
That was this one with this one.
We could have taken down quark with,
I guess, anti-up quark.
Yeah, down quark.
What happens if you take down quark with anti-up quark?
How much charge do you get?
Again, minus.
Same as this.
Down quark with anti-up quark would also have minus charge.
So, if you like, you could also imagine
that the W minus has the same properties
as a down quark and an anti-up quark.
In other words, it's one from the second column
and an anti-one from the first column.
That's the property that it has.
Let's call it W for weak, in fact.
I think W was originally the notation for weak.
The negatively charged W boson.
Okay.
And, of course,
there's also a positively charged boson,
W boson,
which is like anti-down with an up
or like positron, E plus, with a neutrino.
E plus with a neutrino would be a W plus.
Let's suppose the pattern is pretty similar
to quantum chromodynamics,
that the W bosons are like
either photons on the one hand
or like gluons,
which means that they would be objects
which could be emitted
from the leptons.
They would be objects which would allow
a lepton of one kind
let me not label it,
to become a lepton of another kind
by emitting a W boson.
Let's see if we can find some examples.
An electron can emit a W minus
to become a neutrino.
Electron becomes neutrino
by emission of a W minus.
You see the action of the gauge bosons
is to do the same kind of transition
that the symmetry is ultimately going to be.
to do to mix electron into neutrino
in very much the same way
that the colors got mixed
by emitting gluons.
You could follow the lines if you like
and say the electron
and the anti-neutrino over here
can be imagined to be a W minus boson.
Same pattern.
Let's just draw it by saying
a W minus is emitted.
But that's not all you
can do with a W minus.
You can also have a down quark
go to an up quark
with a W minus.
That also works.
And in fact,
the W minus is an object
which can be emitted
in a transition from,
let's see,
from the left to the right.
So,
the W minus is an object
which can be emitted
from, let's see,
from the right column
to the left column.
A red down quark
can become a red up quark
by emitting a W.
A blue down quark
can become a blue up quark
by emitting a W.
Likewise for green.
But you can go further.
The strange quark,
not the strange quark,
the, yeah,
the strange quark
can become a charmed quark.
That's another one.
Strange quark,
charmed quark,
again,
W minus.
So this new symmetry,
this idea of a new symmetry
which acts horizontally
and only horizontally
between neighboring pairs here,
introduces the possibility
of gauge bosons
which cause transitions
between electron neutrinos,
electron neutrino,
down quark and up quark,
strange quark and charmed quark.
Now a W plus and a W minus
are antiparticles of each other.
The meaning of that
is that you can flip these diagrams,
put the W minus down W here,
but when you flip it,
it becomes a W plus.
So a W plus can be absorbed
by an electron
plus a unit of charge,
minus a unit of charge
to become a neutrino.
So a whole family
of different processes
are codified by this one vertex here.
We can turn them upside down,
a neutrino goes to,
you know what we're allowed to do.
We've done these things before.
And that's the basic new element
of the weak interactions.
Actually, that's all, yeah.
Well, it's not clear to me
why you have a W minus here.
You have W minuses
in all three of these cases.
It's like a charge conservation.
It couldn't be W plus.
Would you accept
I don't know what a W means?
W is the name of a particle.
It's the name of another gauge.
Yeah, but the charge conservation
tells me it's going to be a minus.
Right.
But I haven't seen any reason
why it should be the same particle
for the two.
Well, okay, that's right.
But what it comes down to in the end
is an empirical fact.
It's the empirical fact that the symmetry
of the weak interactions
acts simultaneously
on all of these doublets here.
When an up goes to a down,
a charm has to go to a strange,
a top has to go to a bottom,
and the leptons have to mix
with each other simultaneously.
The implication of that,
the implication of that
from a practical point of view
is simply it's the same symmetry
which acts, it's the same gauge bosons
which are there.
You could have imagined a theory
in which it's quite mathematically consistent
to imagine a theory
where different W-type bosons
would have been emitted by up quarks,
charm quarks, or tau quarks,
or even leptons.
It's a fact of nature.
A fact of nature that's nature-based.
A fact of nature that's nature is simpler
than it might have been.
That the same gauge bosons
cause transitions between any
any point row,
you know what I mean.
I'm going to get tongue-tied
if I try to say it.
Okay, well, first of all,
how do we, what processes can we explain?
Yeah.
Quick question.
Can a W-
can a negative neutrino
as well?
Negative, uh, say it again.
Can you flip the arrows?
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
You can flip arrows and you can flip lines.
Yes, yes, certainly you can flip arrows.
Yeah, absolutely.
Absolutely.
And you can also flip lines up and down
in various ways.
For example, another way you could flip the lines,
you could take this up quark here,
have it, instead of going out,
instead of an up quark going out,
an anti-up quark comes in.
Whenever you flip a line from past to future
or from future to past,
you also change from particle to anti-particle.
Yeah.
I don't understand this,
but on the rightmost diagram,
W minus there is a strange anti-tron.
Yes.
So that's the same as a down anti-tron?
Down anti-up?
Yes.
The same?
Wait a second.
Sorry.
Yes.
That's a strange anti-tron, right?
That's the same as a down...
It's not literally a strange and an anti-tron.
It's just a rule that tells you
that whatever these W bosons are,
they're associated with transitions
from one column to the other.
But you did an anti-tron.
Did I?
Sorry.
Strange...
Electron to neutrino.
Strange to charm.
Is that wrong?
No.
It's not an anti-charm.
That's the point.
Who said it was an anti-charm?
Well, it shouldn't have done.
It was a W.
No.
No, no.
All right.
If you follow the lines like that,
at the point where the line turns around,
it has to be thought of as an anti-particle.
Yes.
Right.
Okay.
So,
you're saying that
the line turns around
and the particle is a neutral particle.
Yes.
Right.
Okay.
So,
you can think of it
as a W.
Or,
if you like,
you can always think of it
as strange
anti-charm
coming in
and making a W boson.
Okay.
Just keep in mind
whenever you flip
from the past
to the future,
if you want to know
what a W boson
will decay to,
let's read it
downward,
it will decay
to a strange
and an anti-charm.
All right.
And
that really can have
a negative effect.
Right.
So,
you can create
a W boson
from an electron
and an
anti-neutrino
and then
cause the W boson
to change
into a
strange
and a charm.
Exactly.
That's where
some of these processes
are going to come from now.
So,
let's think about
the various processes.
Let's start,
just for fun,
let's start
with the decay
of the pi minus.
What is a pi minus?
A pi minus
is a
decay
of the
pi minus
and a decay
of the pi minus
is a quark
and an anti-quark
with altogether
negative charge.
So,
let's see,
a quark
and an anti-quark
with negative charge
had better be,
here's the pi minus,
that's equal to
a
down quark
and an
anti-up quark.
Down
and anti-up.
Now,
what can a down
and an anti-up
do?
Let's see if we can find
down and anti-up here.
Here it is right here.
Down
and anti-up
can become
a W minus.
That's a possible transition
that is allowed
by
the physics of W bosons.
So here's a W minus.
But now,
a W minus
can do something else.
A W minus
here is,
let's say,
here is
W plus
W plus.
Let's put W plus
upstairs here.
Sorry,
this is W minus now.
And let's put the neutrino
downstairs,
anti-neutrino.
And read this as saying
that W minus
goes to what?
Electron
anti-neutrino.
So W minus
can go to electron
anti-neutrino.
So W minus
can go to electron
anti-neutrino.
So W minus
can go to electron
anti-neutrino.
And
here it is.
E minus,
ordinary electron.
So that's the basic
underlying process
that governs
the beta decay
of the negatively charged
pion
into a
electron
and an anti-neutrino.
Now, which anti-neutrino is it?
There are three distinct
anti-neutrinos.
It's the electron
anti-neutrino over here.
anti-neutrino.
But it can also,
I didn't draw all
the various possibilities,
but any place you saw
an electron,
you can put a muon.
Any place,
and as long as
you carry along
the muon neutrino.
So another process
is muon.
And muon is
the electron
anti-neutrino.
And muon is
the electron
anti-neutrino.
And muon is
the electron
anti-neutrino.
And just for clarity,
this is not strictly
a Feynman diagram, right?
This is just showing
an interaction.
It's pretty close
to a Feynman diagram.
Well, except for
the time direction.
Oh, yeah.
Right.
I don't know why
all of a sudden
I change directions.
Yeah.
For some reason,
yeah, right,
time is now
going horizontally.
I've become
a computer scientist
and they measure,
yeah, yeah, they do.
Right.
So,
right.
Yeah, it's pretty much,
yeah, it's good.
We can turn it up.
I can't do that easily,
but, yeah.
Yeah, that is
essentially a Feynman diagram
describing the decay
of the pi minus
to the muon.
As it happens,
the, for technical reasons
having to do
with some complications
in Feynman diagrams
that are not interesting
to us,
as it happens,
the primary decay,
well, primary,
I mean the most probable,
is the muon.
And the muon
is the
muon
that is
the muon
antineutrino.
The most probable decay
of the pi minus
is to the muon
antineutrino,
not to the electron
antineutrino.
It's a technical point
of no,
no special interest
to us.
It just happens
to be that way.
Wouldn't it be consistent
instead of
considering
these Feynman diagrams
with a time
deal
as more like
a chemical equilibrium
deal?
Which way
you're going?
empty space except somebody made a pi minus. A
pi minus was created how? A pi minus might
be created by some nucleons coming together
and creating by strong interactions. By strong
interactions a pi minus might be created. Now
that pi minus is just going along and
saying wait a minute, I can decay if I
like into a neutrino and a muon. Then of course
the neutrino and the muon have enough energy,
kinetic energy to fly off and they won't come
back together again because they've departed, they've
gone away. Okay, on the other hand
it is true that if you were to take
a muon and an antineutrino and fire them toward each
other there would be a certain probability that
they would make a pi minus. So yes, you
can read it both ways. Let's go, yeah.
Quick question, you have, like in one
dimension you have a S-shape and you have
a pi minus. What's the difference
between a pi minus and a muon?
Well, you have two different dimensions in a
pi minus. One of the dimensions is the
pi minus and one of the neutrinos. So the pi
minus is a pi minus. So you have a pi minus
right.
Beautiful.
I was wondering when you go
from, let's say, what is the costhφο.
A poinzsupport function or is that?
Computerensible something.
So, it can, we could take a pi
plus that is very similar, but between sura materials
and a minimum of so called number or
even numbers but we could different things, but
we can take a right,
a three times over melts one.
Yeah, you did that.
Yeah!
And then, again, just recent maybe
good last words are very rare.
Yes.
I guess it actually is a much better question.
I don't have an answer to those.
There are a total of 21- perceiving angelic places
and I am glad that I answered them or
you guys got a lot of questions.
keep in mind we're doing something
a little bit funny because we have
SU2 has how many generators?
Three.
So how many gauge bosons should it have?
So far we only have W plus and
W minus. There must be another one lurking around
and that other one must
be associated somehow with something like
electron anti-electron
and neutrino anti-neutrino, but we'll come to it.
Just like the, yeah, we'll come to it.
There is a third gauge boson lurking around
and it does play a
big role in the weak interactions,
but it didn't play a big role
historically in the weak interactions just because,
for reasons we'll come to.
Historically it was the W boson
which was the first to be conjectured.
Yeah.
Speaking of historically,
was the weak or the
strong force sort of suspected first?
Of course, all right, so let's talk about the history.
The history of these forces goes
back to Becquerel, goes back to radioactivity.
Alpha, beta, and gamma decay.
Alpha decay was what?
Emission of a two-pronged atom.
Two protons and two neutrons from a nucleus.
That's a strong interaction.
It's part of the theory of hadrons and nuclei.
Beta decay, that was this one right here.
Weak interactions.
And gamma decay?
Photon.
Historically they happened at the same time.
In the same experiment.
Question?
Yeah.
The energy conservation, how it works,
are you assuming some kinetic energy in all of these?
Okay, yeah, the energy, all right, let's work on that.
You never worry about the energy
conservation in intermediate states like this.
If the energy of the intermediate state doesn't
match the energies of the initial and final state,
it just means that the intermediate state
can only last for a very short time.
There's an energy time uncertainty principle.
You can violate the energies in a
Feynman diagram for short periods of time.
So don't worry about conservation
of energy between here and here.
The only energy we have to worry about
is the initial energy and the final energy.
Okay, so let's worry about it.
A pion has an energy of about a mass.
Let's suppose the pion is at rest.
The mass of the pion is roughly about 140 MeV.
All right, what is the energy
of the muon and the neutrino?
Well, first of all, it's the rest
energy of the muon and the neutrino.
Okay, and the rest energy,
the rest mass of the neutrino,
sorry, the mass of the muon,
I think is about 100 MeV.
I forget exactly.
And the mass of a
neutrino is, for practical purposes, zero.
Too small to be important here.
All right, so there's more energy to start with
than the energy in the
masses of the two final particles.
Does that mean it can't happen?
No, it just means the two particles
will go off and carry some kinetic energy.
So the difference between the energy on this side
and the sums of the masses on this side
is just the kinetic energy of the outgoing particles.
That's the energy balance.
The momentum also has to be conserved,
and that means if the pion
was at rest to begin with,
the momentum of the muon
and the momentum of the neutrino
have to be equal and opposite,
and they'll go out back to back, so to speak.
If you analyze the neutron decay in
the same way as you look at it...
We're going to do that now.
Yeah, let's do the neutron decay right now,
see how a neutron works.
Oh, let's do something simpler first.
Let's do the muon decay.
The muon is also something that can decay.
So let's take the muon.
Here's the muon moving along.
Now what can the muon do?
The muon can become a neutrino submuon
and emit a W.
What kind of W? W minus, right?
It can become a W minus and a neutrino.
But now one of the
things a W minus can do
is it can become an electron and an antineutrino.
So this W minus can now become an electron
and an antineutrino of the electron variety.
Can this happen?
The only thing that would... Yes, it can happen.
Not only can it happen, this
is the way the muon decays.
The muon decays,
because it is sufficiently much heavier
than the electron,
much heavier than the electron,
about 200 times heavier than the electron.
The neutrinos are practically massless,
so the energy balance is
you have about 100 MeV here,
a half an MeV here,
and the rest goes off in kinetic energy.
So that's an example of a...
what's called a purely leptonic process.
No quarks in it at all.
Is that an antineutrino?
Is it what?
An antielectron.
Yeah, it is.
Right.
So it's one neutrino, one antineutrino, and an electron.
Okay? So that happens.
And that's the primary decay.
It's the only decay of the muon.
So the muon is an unstable particle because of this,
but the reason the muon
is unstable and not the electron
is just that the muon happens to be heavy enough
to be able to decay to the electron.
The electron is not heavy
enough to decay to the muon.
So in a sense, it's an accident of the masses.
The same is true of the tau, incidentally.
The tau can also decay to other leptons.
But, all right, that's the mu decay.
And notice the components are the same.
The basic components are the same.
A transition from one column to another,
followed by a W,
and then the W makes another transition
from one column to the other.
Or, if you like, a decay
All right, what about the decay of the neutron?
Decay of the neutron...
Would it be consistent to say
the purpose of a linear accelerator, per se,
is to effectively increase the mass of the electron
so that it can now go the other direction?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
I mean, you don't change the mass,
you just put enough energy in it.
You put enough energy...
Absolutely.
Yeah, that's exactly right.
Okay, we were going to do neutron decay.
So the neutron is...
Maybe I'd better switch to vertical.
I don't want to...
Vertical.
Vertical notation, back to vertical.
Neutron is three quarks,
two down quarks,
and an up quark.
Right?
Minus...
Minus four thirds plus two thirds...
Sorry, minus two thirds...
Yes, that's a neutron.
Electrically neutral.
Neutron coming in.
Okay, now what is possible?
First of all, we can have the up quark
become a down quark
and emit some sort of W.
But that'll give us three down quarks.
Three down quarks is a fine thing.
There's nothing wrong with three down quarks,
except that the mass of the neutron
is less than three down quarks.
The mass of three down quarks,
of a particle with three down quarks,
is always too heavy for the neutron to decay.
So that's not what happens.
What about one of the down quarks?
The down quark can emit a W,
become an up quark.
This is again a W minus.
The down quark emits a W minus,
and that's a down quark.
And now we have two up quarks
and a down quark.
Up, up, down.
What is that called?
Proton.
That's a proton.
And the W does what the W always does.
It decays to an electron
and an anti-neutrino.
Electron, anti-neutrino.
So that's the beta decay of the neutron.
Could it decay into a muon in a neutrino?
Not enough energy.
The muon is too heavy
so that there wouldn't be enough energy left over
for the muon.
But other than that,
if it were not for that,
it could happen.
Another way to say it is if you could
jam some more energy into the neutron.
How can you do it?
You give it a shove.
You give the neutron a whack,
you excite it,
and if you excite it enough,
it can decay to a proton,
a neutrino, anti-neutrino, and a muon.
But without somehow providing that extra energy,
the neutron will only decay to the proton,
electron, and anti-neutrino.
Okay, now let's come...
Let's see, where are we?
I think we're finished for tonight.
But remember, we have a puzzle.
And the puzzle is,
why is it that the weak interactions
give such slow decay rates?
And I can think of one reason,
namely, the coupling constant,
or the analog of the fine structure constant,
could be ridiculously small,
so that the probability of emitting these W bosons
would be very, very small.
That is not the reason.
The fine structure constant for the weak interactions
is about the same as for electromagnetism.
That is not the reason.
The reason is something else,
and we'll come to the something else next time.
Yeah?
When you say that theory has its own truth,
you mean that the Lagrangian...
The Lagrangian is invariant under those operations.
That's exactly what it means.
I didn't want to start writing bunches of Lagrangians,
so I've used the shorthand
of saying there's a symmetry, right?
But that's what it means, yeah.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.