Stanford University.
Yeah, all right. So let's just for a
moment stop and say what we'll do next time.
I'm not sure whether tonight I will get to one
of the key puzzles, which is called the gauge hierarchy.
We may. I had planned it in my notes, and we
may get to it, especially since I'm getting rid of the review.
But next quarter, I want to study some of
these paradoxes, not paradoxes, but difficulties of the theory,
and how things like supersymmetry relate to them, how supersymmetry may
or may not solve some of these puzzling features of the theory.
How unification, what unification? Right now we have SU
, we have SU and we have U .
I'm talking now about the
forces weak, electromagnetic, and strong.
Do these somehow sit in some bigger structure?
Is there a group, for example, which contains
the subgroups SU , SU and U ?
I haven't told you what a
subgroup is, but you can imagine.
Is there a bigger structure, a bigger mathematical
structure that contains SU , SU and U ?
Yes. There's a subgroup, there's a group called SU .
And there's a lot of interesting evidence that this whole structure that
I've described so far fits very, very neatly into an SU structure,
in which quarks and leptons are
all part of the same multiplets.
We'll talk about that. Supersymmetry, unification,
and the various puzzles that arise.
And I will tell you a little
bit about what I mean by that.
I'll tell you a little bit about
what LHC is cooked up to discover.
All right? Now, if one thing that LHC was cooked
up originally to discover was, of course, the Higgs boson.
The Higgs boson, discovering the Higgs boson
is not just discovering the Higgs boson.
For example, it's more than just
discovering the existence of a particle.
It also involves a whole
bunch of properties of this particle,
which are all related to the
fact that it is a Higgs boson.
For example, I told you, I think it was last time, how the
Higgs boson and the Higgs phenomena is related to the masses of fermions.
We looked at the Dirac equation. Instead of looking at the Dirac
equation, we might have looked at the Lagrangian for the Dirac equation.
I don't know if we ever wrote
down the Lagrangian for the Dirac equation.
I don't think we did. Let
me write it down for you.
Yeah, we did the Klein-Gordon. Let me
write it down for you. It's very easy.
We first write down the Dirac equation.
Derivative with respect to x mu of,
no, derivative with respect to time of psi,
what was it, minus or plus, I don't remember,
plus,
derivative with respect to x sub i, where
x sub i means x, y, or z,
times alpha i, psi, we can
put the alpha i out here,
and we set that equal to what?
Beta times the mass, right, times psi.
That was the Dirac equation. Let me
move everything over to the left-hand side.
Did I ever tell you my greatest mathematical discovery?
You don't need the equal sign.
Right.
You made that discovery too. How old were you?
No, you told me.
Oh, I told you. Okay.
Okay, this is the Dirac equation. Now supposing I want
to derive this Dirac equation by variation with respect to something.
In particular, it happens to be psi star.
It's a very easy way of constructing a Lagrangian
such that when you vary with respect to psi star,
it's the Dirac equation which falls out.
All you have to do is
multiply the Dirac equation by psi star.
Psi dagger of psi star.
Now it's not zero. It's still zero.
But now it is not the Dirac equation.
It's the Lagrangian for the Dirac field.
All right.
What does it have in it?
It has terms.
Psi dagger, derivatives of psi.
Those are the kinds of things which
move a particle from one point to another.
Remember in the Klein-Gordon equation, the kinetic term was associated
with the hopping of the particle from one point to another.
And that's what these terms are.
It absorbs a particle
and moves it to another.
It moves it to a new point of spacetime.
That's what the derivatives do.
They move it to a new point of spacetime.
At the same time, they jiggle
its spin in a certain way.
That's what these kinetic things are.
And the mass term is just
a term which takes a particle,
absorbs it, and emits it from a
point of space with no derivatives at all.
It just absorbs it and
emits it from the same spot.
That's the Lagrangian for the Dirac equation.
Do you need a gamma-naught
in there after the psi dagger?
Psi-R?
No.
Okay.
All right.
So you asked me.
I hadn't used that language, but
I will now use that language now.
Good.
Just for those who are
curious about the more covariant language,
I'll give you a couple of examples.
This is a very simple one.
This is a very simple covariant language.
If you take psi dagger
and you multiply it by beta,
that gives you something that's called psi bar.
If you want to get back from
psi bar to psi, you multiply by beta.
Why?
Because beta squared is equal to 1.
All right.
So you can write this.
You can rewrite this in the following way.
You write it as psi bar over beta squared.
You write it as psi bar beta.
That's just psi dagger.
d by dt.
And then over here, what will we have?
Then we will have plus psi bar beta alpha
sub i derivative with respect to x sub i psi.
And then what about this one over here?
Sorry.
Let's put the...
Yeah.
This one is going to be
plus beta beta m psi.
What will that be?
Beta squared.
No, no.
Well, it's just psi bar m psi.
m psi bar m plus m psi bar psi.
Now, if I change the name of
these symbols, we can call beta gamma naught.
Why naught?
Because it's connected with...
naught usually refers to time.
The four coordinates of space-time are the zero
component for time and 1, 2, 3 for space.
So this one is usually called gamma naught.
Beta is sometimes called...
In fact, most frequently in modern
physics, the alpha-beta notation is mostly abandoned.
And you use gamma.
So this becomes psi bar gamma naught dt psi.
And this one, now we're going to change the name.
Beta times alpha, just the product beta times
alpha i, we're going to call gamma i.
Psi bar gamma i di
psi plus m psi bar psi.
That's the Lagrangian.
And now it has a very, very neat form.
You can think of gamma naught d by
dt as being gamma naught d by dx naught.
This is gamma i d by dx i.
It looks like a nice covariant sort
of four-vector product of gamma matrices times derivatives.
In other words, you can write
the whole thing in the form...
psi bar...
gamma mu d by dx mu.
Let's just call it d by d mu.
So now mu goes from
one to four plus m psi.
Okay, that's much more elegant than
the original form that Dirac wrote down.
These are also...
The alphas and betas are called Dirac matrices.
The gammas are also called Dirac matrices.
Yeah?
You said the psi on the far
left here was psi bar and you didn't...
Right.
Psi bar.
All right.
But all you have to remember, though,
is that psi bar is not psi dagger.
It's psi dagger with an extra gamma naught.
All right.
But this is the elegant form for the equation.
In fact, psi bar psi happens to be a scalar.
And psi bar gamma psi is a four-vector.
It has an index mu.
So this is a more elegant way
to present the Dirac equation, the Dirac-Lagrangian.
The Dirac equation is just setting this equal to zero.
Okay?
The Dirac-Lagrangian looks like this.
Now, from this point of view, let's just examine...
Well, let's examine the various terms.
You know there's a fifth Dirac matrix.
Anybody know what it's called?
Gamma 5.
What's missing?
Gamma 4.
There's no gamma 4.
In fact, it's just a glitch.
There's another...
There's one more gamma matrix which is called
gamma 5, which happens to be the product of
gamma naught, gamma 1, gamma 2, gamma 3.
It's called gamma 5.
It happens to be one more matrix.
Okay.
And in fact, the eigenvectors of gamma 5...
Gamma 5 squared is also equal to 1.
It has two eigenvalues, plus 1 and minus 1.
And the two eigenvectors or the two
eigenvalues correspond to the left-handedness and the
right-handedness of the particles.
Gamma 5 is called helicity.
Chirality, excuse me, chirality.
Handedness.
Chiral for hand, you know, like...
What was the Greek word for hand?
Chiron, chiros, something with a chir, c-h-i-r.
Chirality.
Yeah, gamma 5 is called chirality, and
it can be plus or minus 1.
And it corresponds to the handedness of the two particles.
Now, if you work it out, if you work
out the various things, you'll find that the handedness
of the particles is equal
to the handedness of the particles.
You'll find that this term here does
not couple the left-handed and the right-handed components
of psi.
The left-handed and right-handed components of
psi mean the things with eigenvalue plus
1 and minus 1 for gamma 5.
But just think of them as electrons or
particles with a right-handed helicity or a left-handed
helicity.
Sorry, these four here do
not multiply left-handed times right-handed.
It just happens they don't.
You can work that out by yourselves.
This one does.
Psi bar times psi happens to be...
It happens to be...
Let's write it this way.
Psi dagger left, psi right
plus psi dagger right, psi left.
That's what it is.
So the mass term here mixes
up the left-handed and the right-handed particles.
That's what a mass is, a Dirac mass is.
It's a term in the Lagrangian.
It seems weird that it should
have anything to do with inertia.
It's a term which causes a left-handed fermion
to flip to a right-handed fermion, to flip
to a left-handed fermion, and so forth.
And that's what's over here.
The other terms don't do that.
So that means a massless fermion has a definite chirality.
The mass term flips the chirality
back and forth and back and forth.
Yeah.
All right.
Then we talked about...
Then we talked about a
class of interactions, the weak interactions.
Let's put in particular focus on the
Z, the emission and absorption of Z bosons.
That is purely left-handed.
For some odd reason, for some odd reason,
the Z boson only is emitted by left-handed particles,
not by right-handed particles.
This is not true of the photon.
This is only true of the Z boson.
Sorry, the W boson.
The Z boson is a little more kinky.
It has asymmetric couplings to left-handed and right-handed.
But let's focus on the Ws.
They couple through only the left-handed degrees of freedom.
So that means that in effect, with respect
to the charges, with respect to the transformation properties,
under the SU . . .
The SU that's connected with the W,
the emission of W bosons, the left-handed fermion
is charged and the right-handed fermion is uncharged.
You're not allowed to put in a Lagrangian
something like this, which would take a charged
particle to an uncharged particle.
It would mean a process in which a
charged particle would come in and get absorbed and
uncharged particle go out, violates charge conservation.
So this would not be a legal term in
a Lagrangian that had a gauge symmetry which only coupled
to left-handed particles.
All right, then the question is how
do you get a mass for fermions?
We know that electrons and quarks, they all have masses.
There's something wrong.
Ah, here's where the Higgs boson comes into play.
The Higgs boson also plays the role of a charge-to-farm.
It's a very charged object with
respect to the SU of weak interactions.
In fact, it's a doublet.
Just like the electron and neutrino are
doublets, the Higgs boson is also a doublet.
I didn't emphasize that, and
I'm not going to emphasize it.
I've sort of skirted around it.
The Higgs boson also transforms under SU . . .
And, roughly speaking, the way to make
this into a legitimate form of a charge-to-farm
is to multiply by the appropriate Higgs boson field here.
The Higgs boson, if you like, carries a
weak charge, which is either the same or opposite,
depending on which component we're talking about, as
the weak charge of, let's say, the electron,
if we're talking about electrons here.
The right-handed particle has no
charge with respect to the SU.
So what we have to do is put
a Higgs boson here and a Higgs dagger here.
This means the emission of a Higgs boson and
the emission of an anti-Higgs boson, if you like,
with the Higgs boson carrying off the charge of
the left-handed particle when it became the right-handed particle.
So we introduce into the Lagrangian
something which takes a left-handed fermion,
emits a right-handed fermion, but also
allows a Higgs boson to be emitted
in such a way that the weak charge of
the electron or the quark or whatever it is
escapes in the form of
the Higgs boson, the Higgs doublet.
And that would be the end of the story,
except for the spontaneous.
simultaneous symmetry breaking,
which has to do with the
Higgs field getting an expectation value.
The Higgs field,
well, I think we called
it phi last time, didn't we?
I think we called it phi.
Let's just continue to call it phi.
And we made a phi particle here.
That would be the end of the story,
except that for whatever reasons,
nature has chosen
the energetics of the Higgs field,
this phi here,
to have one of these Mexican hat potential energies.
Why did it do that?
Why did nature do that?
We don't know.
Okay, but we're very lucky that it did.
Otherwise, chemistry would go to hell.
And things would be very, very unpleasant.
But with one of these upside-down Mexican hat potentials,
that means that phi
is equal to a number,
just the magnitude of the Higgs field here,
which we called F,
plus a fluctuation,
a fluctuation away from that value.
And that fluctuation is what
we actually call the Higgs field.
All right.
So let's go back now.
What happens to this term,
what happens to these terms in the Lagrangian?
They break up into two pieces.
Not these two pieces,
but these two pieces.
One of them is...
Oh, I left out one thing.
What did I leave out of this expression?
A numerical number.
G.
The Yukawa coupling.
Let's call it G sub Y.
And there's a different G sub Y for each fermion.
These two should be the same.
All right.
G sub Y is just a number,
a pure number,
carries no dimensions.
They're called Yukawa couplings.
And where they came from,
I don't know,
somebody wiser than me put them into the Lagrangian.
Okay.
So here they are.
All right.
Now let's use the fact that
phi is equal to a non-fluctuating part,
which we call F for the non-fluctuating part.
We call it F.
Don't...
And for the fluctuating part,
we call it H,
the Higgs boson.
That's not my notation.
That's a standard notation.
So this becomes GYF
times psi dagger left psi right
plus psi dagger right psi left
plus GY Higgs field,
times the same thing.
Same thing.
Okay.
Now we have a prediction for what the number F...
Where did that come from?
The number F we obtained,
that same number F went into the
mass of the Z and W bosons.
The shift of the Higgs field also determined
the mass of the Z and W bosons.
Okay.
Once you've measured the mass
of the Z and W bosons,
and this was done a long, long time ago,
they were measured,
the masses are measured,
about of order 100 GeV,
90 GeV, something like that.
So that told us what F was.
That told us what the number F was.
F is a number of
about really 200 GeV for F.
Okay.
So that's a number...
It has units of mass, incidentally.
It has units of mass.
200 GeV.
Ah.
Once we know that from Z and W physics,
then from the masses of the fermions,
we can read off what these Yukawa couplings are.
Once we know, for example,
the electron Yukawa coupling is
some very, very small number.
Why?
Because the electron is much
lighter than the Z and W.
The Yukawa coupling for the top quark,
that's large.
Why?
Because the top quark is so heavy.
So the masses of the quarks
wind up being these Yukawa couplings times F.
And so far we've really gotten
out no more than we put in.
We've gotten out no more than we put in.
We got F from the masses of...
Well, a little bit more,
but basically the masses of the Z-W system.
We got F,
and then from the masses of the fermions,
we got the Yukawa couplings.
All right.
So if that's all there was,
we would have put in
as much as we got out.
But now we also have something else.
We have G-Y Higgs times things like...
Let's just call them psi dagger psi.
These are terms in Lagrangian
which take a fermion...
This could be an electron,
it could be a whatever it happens to be,
which take a fermion, absorb it,
and re-emit it, plus a Higgs boson.
So these are then processes where,
let's say, electron, or it could be muon,
or it could be tau,
or it could be some quark...
emits a Higgs boson.
Or it could be a Higgs boson,
coming along,
and decaying into an electron and a positron.
Same diagram.
Okay?
So once the Higgs boson materializes
as a particle in the laboratory,
we should know what the various decay rates are
for it to decay to the different kinds of electron,
positron, muon, anti-muon, or whatever.
We'll know all of the interactions between the Higgs bosons,
and the fermions,
and be able to predict all their decay rates,
all the Higgs boson decay rates.
Obviously, it'll prefer to decay to heavier particles,
as long as there's enough energy,
because these Yukawa couplings are larger.
Yukawa couplings are the coupling constant
for the Higgs to break up into its constituents,
into its decay products.
So at the moment, I mean,
Higgsology is a pure theory.
In the sense that it's predicted by the theory.
There seems to be no other
way to make it mathematically consistent,
but neither the Higgs,
nor the direct couplings to these particles,
and so forth, have been detected.
That will happen.
Well, I hope it will happen.
And so there's a lot of predictive power.
The theory also already has
an enormous amount of predictive power.
Predictive power in the interactions
between the Z's and the W's,
which are experimentally detected.
The interaction of the Z's and the W's,
not only with respect to the fermions,
but with respect to each other.
Z's, no.
How would you actually predict the decay time?
I don't mean going through all the nitty-gritty details,
but I mean, sort of,
how would you set it up
to actually make that prediction?
Well, you can't really define it that way,
but you can think of
it as an elementary quantum mechanics.
You calculate a Feynman diagram.
You can just think of it as elementary quantum mechanics.
This gives you a term in the Hamiltonian,
which takes the Higgs boson to a pair of particles,
and it just gives you the transition amplitude,
which you square.
And once you've squared it,
you integrate it or sum
it over all the final states.
And that's the decay rate.
It's a standard calculation that
is basically a Feynman diagram.
If you like, this gives you the amplitude.
You square the amplitude to get the decay rate.
Squaring the amplitude, you can just do
by putting this right on top of itself like that.
Here the amplitude is squared.
And that becomes a Feynman diagram.
You calculate the Feynman diagram by Feynman's rules.
One of the things that comes
out of it is the decay rate.
But this is more than we're going to do here.
That's what we have to do.
So it's a very, very definite calculation
within standard quantum field theory.
And it's the kind of calculation
we've been doing since the 1930s.
So it's quite well known.
The only things that you have
to put in, which are new,
are the values of these coupling constants,
masses of particles, and so forth.
Okay, so that was the masses of fermions,
the masses of the Z and W bosons,
all of them being proportional to this constant F.
Why don't we talk about the Higgs itself?
Why don't we talk about
the dynamics of the Higgs boson?
The dynamics is really all contained
in this Mexican hat potential.
The minimum of the Mexican hat potential
tells you how much the field is shifted,
and it tells you what F is.
You can make up different potentials that have this shape.
There's a favorite one which
actually has some important theoretical significance.
And it goes as follows.
Let's go to the origin over here.
At the origin, the Higgs potential
is a sort of upside-down parabola.
Let's forget what it does far from the origin.
Let's just concentrate on near the origin.
An upside-down parabola means something like minus,
let's call it mu squared, phi squared.
And it's traditional to put a 2 in here.
It's just traditional.
Minus because it's an upside-down parabola.
Remember, if it was plus mu squared, phi squared,
what would you call this term?
You would call this term
the mass of the Higgs boson.
You would call mu the mass of the Higgs boson.
Or you would really call mu squared the
square of the mass of the Higgs boson.
Making it negative is a little bit weird.
It's as if there was an
imaginary mass for the Higgs boson.
But don't worry, there's nothing wrong with this.
It's perfectly okay to have
a potential which is upside-down.
The only thing which is unusual about it
is putting the field at the
origin is not a stable position.
It tends to roll off and roll down the hill.
Whereas if the mass term was positive,
it would oscillate about the central position here.
So the field does not oscillate about the top
because of this minus phi squared.
Now, if all you have is minus phi squared,
it would just go down and down and down,
and the field would just run away to infinity.
There would be no ground state to the system.
There would be no vacuum.
If the vacuum is the state of lowest energy,
there would be no state of lowest energy.
So we've got to put in something
to keep it from running away to infinity.
We better put in something to turn it up.
The simplest thing to turn it up is plus lambda,
where lambda is just a number,
a pure number,
times phi to the fourth.
Why do I want to put in phi?
Why not the phi cubed,
or phi to the fifth?
Why not odd powers?
Because we want to keep it symmetric on both sides.
This was an important aspect of this potential,
was to keep it nice and symmetric.
So phi to the fourth is symmetric.
Phi cubed is not.
This is the next thing you can put in.
You can put in all sorts
of things to higher powers here.
They're not so important.
The most important one is phi to the fourth
and expanding the potential and the mass.
So it's just a number.
It's not a power series.
You can put in more,
but this is the most important thing.
And in fact, it's also traditional
to put a four over here.
You'll see why in a moment.
A two over here and a four over here.
What is this number?
This number is called a quartic coupling constant.
Quartic because it has phi to the fourth.
It is dimensionless.
It's a pure number.
And what we know about that pure number,
not from direct experimental evidence,
but from a lot of indirect evidence,
and what we know about that number
from somewhat indirect properties of weak interactions,
is that it's small,
but not absurdly small.
Probably about 1%,
probably about
1.01 or something like that.
So it's a number.
It's not 10 to the minus 20.
It's not 10 to the
minus 15 or anything like that.
So just think of it as a
number for the moment of order one.
It's also dimensionless.
Mu is not dimensionless.
It has units of a mass.
Okay, now let's try to find out what f is.
f is dimensionless.
So if you look at the equation,
you can see that the
number of units of a mass
is not dimensionless.
It's not dimensionless.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to take the position at the minimum here.
All we have to do is
minimize this with respect to phi.
We cooked it up so
that it would have a minimum.
A rapidly falling quadratic term,
and then taken over by,
incidentally, near the origin,
this is smaller than this, right?
Phi to the fourth is smaller
than phi squared near the origin.
So this has not got much effect near the origin.
It picks up steam
and eventually becomes much bigger than phi squared.
So we're going to go to large phi.
So that turns it back up.
That's the logic.
Okay, let's just find the minimum of phi.
Sorry, the minimum of v
with respect to phi,
and that will tell us
how much the field gets shifted.
All right, that's easy.
We just differentiate with respect to phi.
The derivative of phi squared is 2 phi.
That eats up this 2 down here.
That's why I put the 2 down there.
Minus mu squared phi.
This is the derivative of
v with respect to phi,
plus lambda,
which is a number of order of magnitude 1,
phi cubed.
I also put the 4 down here
so it would kill the 4 when I differentiated
with respect to phi to the fourth.
And we set that equal to 0.
All right, now we can divide by phi.
We divide by phi.
Make this phi squared.
And what do we get?
We get phi squared
is equal to mu squared
over lambda.
Again, lambda is an ordinary number.
Don't think of it as very big or very small.
This is the value of phi at the minimum.
It's also called f.
It's also the shift of the field, f.
And so f squared
becomes mu squared over lambda.
Again, I emphasize,
lambda is not the interesting number here.
It's the common garden variety number
like 1 or a tenth or a hundredth
or something like that.
It's not very big, that's for sure.
Okay.
So, f is controlled by mu.
f is also approximately the mass
of the z and the w boson.
It's also the thing which comes into the mass
of the fermions.
Where are they?
All of the particles have masses proportional to f.
Let's take the square root of this.
So it's mu or f or mu.
Which is the controlling factor
which controls all of these masses.
All of them.
All the masses of all
the particles that we know about.
Okay, that raises an interesting question.
Why are all of the particles that we know about
controlled by the same phenomenon,
namely f?
Why aren't there particles which have masses
without spontaneous symmetry breaking?
We can certainly make up a theory of such particles.
For example, just make up a particle
whose left-handed and right-handed components
both have weak charge.
Then we have no reason
to put this phi in there.
We wouldn't put the phi in there.
And you could put any mass
that you like in front of it.
And it's perfectly symmetric.
So, if there was a particle
which was
whose left- and right-handed
components both interacted with the weak interactions
the same way,
they could have a mass
which was not proportional to f.
All kinds of other particles could all
particles that don't have any weak interactions at all,
if there were such particles,
could have masses which are not controlled by f.
The general thinking which we'll come to,
and I'll explain why this is the general thinking,
is that the natural mass scale for particle physics
is enormous.
Much, much higher
than the masses of any of the ordinary elementary particles.
It's thought that only this one number, f,
is the unusual number in physics,
the very, very small mass scale,
whose origins are at present unknown.
But what is thought, and I'll explain as we,
well, this quarter, next quarter,
various points,
the idea that really the only mass parameter,
the only small mass parameter in nature,
is this f here.
And those particles,
which by necessity have to have masses proportional to f,
why?
Because it's in the nature of their mathematics
that they would have to be massless
if there was no shift of f.
Only those particles
are light enough to have been detected at present.
That's the belief,
that's a very widespread belief,
that there's a good reason
why all the particles have masses proportional to f,
because any that don't
probably have masses which are much, much larger.
But still we have to explain the smallness of f.
Small compared to what?
Well, that's an interesting question.
Small compared with what?
What is the natural mass scale
for elementary particle physics?
So that's where I think we want to go next.
Plank mass?
Hm?
That's one possible mass, yes.
Yes.
All right, let's see.
I think it,
we'll take a break in two minutes,
but yes, one possible mass,
which we'll talk about in a few minutes
after the break,
is the Planck mass.
Another is the so-called unification mass,
which I'll show you what it is.
These masses are typically
16 or 17 orders of magnitude,
well, let me see,
15 orders of magnitude heavier
than the mass, than the, than f.
than the z or w boson, for example.
So what we're left with then
is a puzzle.
Why is this f quantity so small?
Once we can understand
why the f quantity is so small,
it drags down the masses
of all the other particles,
it drags them down simply because
they cannot have mass
other than proportional to f.
They would naturally be massless
in a world without spontaneous symmetry breaking.
So, yeah?
Would you say that again
about the 15 orders of magnitude?
Yeah, the natural, all right,
f is a number of about 100 GeV.
All right, that's, sounds like a lot of,
sounds like a big mass, all right?
The other mass scales which come
into particle physics, which we know about,
the other possibly much more fundamental
mass scales are much, much heavier than that.
15 orders of magnitude heavier than that.
And what particles correspond to that?
None that we've ever discovered, obviously.
You're right, many, but we predict.
Yeah, well, yes, of course,
we know what particles we predicted,
but why did we predict them 15 orders
of magnitude higher?
In other words, when I say that there are
other mass scales that we know about,
we know about them from something.
So the question is, where do we know about them
if we've never seen, if we've never seen them,
if we've never seen particles of those masses?
And we'll talk about that after the break.
I gather that in these very, very low temperature
condensed matter boson kinds of things,
there's all sorts of analogs to particle physics.
But aside from that, is there any common,
in solid state physics, or any common example
that Higgs-like mechanisms?
Yes, yes. All right.
So you asked about Bose condensates.
So a Bose condensation, or more precisely,
superfluidity, which is similar to a Bose condensation,
it's a condensation of helium atoms, okay?
Helium atoms, helium atoms, of course,
not elementary particles, okay?
But on some scale, they are elementary particles.
If you're interested in scales of water molecular size,
a helium nucleus is an elementary particle,
and it can be described by a field, okay?
That field naturally in ordinary vacuum
has a value zero, just corresponding
to no helium atoms present, okay?
Spontaneous symmetry breaking can happen,
which can shift the value of the helium field.
When that happens, in the same way that F
is a shift of the Higgs field,
when that happens, it's, roughly speaking,
called a Bose condensation.
When the Bose condensation happens,
it spontaneously breaks a certain symmetry,
and it's called, and it creates superfluidity.
But if the helium atom were charged,
if the helium, not the helium nucleus,
the helium atom, if the helium atom were charged,
it would behave like the Higgs boson
and make a mass for the photon.
Now, does that ever happen?
Anything like it ever happen?
Yes, it does.
In a superconductor, electrons can pair up
and bind together in the superconductor,
very weakly bound pairs,
and those pairs of electrons have charge two.
They're not helium atoms.
They're not neutral here in the atoms.
They're called Cooper pairs,
and they're bound configurations of electron,
not electron and positron, but electron and electron.
But they're separated?
The Cooper pairs, aren't they separated?
They're separated, they're not very far
separated in space.
They're separated at the opposite ends
of the Fermi surface.
Right.
No, think of them as particles.
First approximation, think of them as particles.
They're charged particles,
and then they condense.
They condense, which means the field
for this pair of particles gets shifted.
You can think of that field as really just being
the product of the electron field with itself,
describing two electrons,
or you can think of it as a new object
which carries charge two.
When that field gets shifted,
it creates a condensate of Cooper pairs.
It creates a kind of super fluidity
for the Cooper pairs,
but it's now a super fluid of charged particles.
It becomes the Higgs phenomena.
It's of course a superconductor,
and the superconductor in essentially
every possible way behaves like the Higgs phenomenon.
The photon gets mass.
Now it's a tiny, tiny mass
because the scales are so terribly different,
but the,
the Compton wavelength of the,
of the photon becomes finite,
and it behaves very, very much like this,
like this spontaneously shifted Higgs field.
In fact, the phenomena was first discovered
in the context of superconductors,
and it was rediscovered entirely independently
by,
by Higgs and other people.
Okay, let's take a little break.
When you begin at the primordial description
of elementary particles,
you begin with the Lagrangian,
and in the Lagrangian there are a collection of parameters
such as masses of particles,
charges of particles,
and they're sort of the input.
On the other hand,
they're very rarely,
if ever,
the actual measured quantities.
The measured quantities that you actually measure
are usually the product
of all kinds of interactions and things
that take place
between the high frequency modes of a system
and the low frequency modes of the system,
which renormalize or change the values of the parameters
that you associate with experimental observations.
An example is electric charge.
So let's talk about that a little bit
and how charge gets renormalized.
I'm not going to do any calculations.
Calculations, you'll have to go and get a book
and try to follow it.
But the phenomena,
the phenomena is a fairly simple one
that's well known.
It occurs in condensed matter physics.
In fact, it just occurs in classical
electrical physics.
Electricity and magnetism
associated with electric,
what's it called?
Dielectric, thank you.
With dielectric materials
and conductors.
The actual observable charge,
normally observed charge of an object,
is defined by the Coulomb law.
But the Coulomb law at large separation,
the asymptotic force between two charges
when they're far apart,
and that force, as you well know,
is the product of the charges.
Let's call it E1, E2.
Let's take them to be equal charges.
And in particular, let's suppose they have
charge of the electron, just to be simple.
Then it's just E squared
divided by R squared,
or in the potential energy,
just E squared divided by R.
So you take two charges far apart
and you measure the charge,
you measure the force between them.
At any given distance,
it will not be precisely given by this formula,
but if you asymptotically separate them,
then you'll find asymptotically,
with respect to R,
the force between them,
or the potential energy between them,
goes like E squared over R.
Attractive for opposite charges,
repulsive for like charges.
And that defines, if you like,
the charge of a particle.
Coulomb law at spatially very large separations.
Now, if in a material you do this,
you take charges in a material,
or even just the air,
and you separate them
and see what the force law is,
you'll find that it's not exactly given
by the formula in which you go
to the particle physics table,
the particle physics table of particle properties,
read off the electric charge of the system.
Typically, you won't read off the electric charge
of an ordinary chunk of material,
but you might happen to know how many electrons,
or how many excess protons or electrons are in it.
So you might know its charge
in units of the charge of the electron,
you take them apart,
and you discover, no,
the force is always a little bit less than that.
Always a little bit less than that.
Unless you're in absolute vacuum.
In absolute vacuum, completely empty space,
by definition,
the electric charge is what you measure
by measuring the force at a large distance.
Now what is it that happens in a material?
Let's begin with a conductor.
With an electric conductor,
what happens to a charge that's put into the conductor?
Well, the charge creates some electric field.
For example, suppose it's a plus charge,
it creates an outward electric field,
the electric field creates a current,
the current starts charges moving,
and until the charge is completely discharged,
until it's completely discharged,
in other words, until the charge has gone out
to the boundary of the conductor,
the flow of charge doesn't stop.
So the charge flows until the charged object,
let's draw the charged object over here,
there it is,
charge flows away from it,
collects on the boundary,
but let's put the boundary off on Alpha Centauri someplace,
and of course, an opposite charge,
so if this is plus,
an opposite charge cloud is found around it,
it completely discharges it,
so that outside there's no electric field at all,
and no more reason for the charges to flow.
Now these charges are of
course bound to the positive charge,
they're bound to it,
and the whole thing forms a neutral structure.
If you take another negative charge over here,
exactly the opposite thing will happen to it,
it will create some plus charge around it,
same deal,
the charges will flow until it's completely neutralized,
and then you take these two charges,
you thought you had two charges to begin with,
you evaluate or measure the
force between them at large distances,
and you find out that there is none.
So, the charge that you put in to begin with
is not the experimental charge
at the end of the day,
the experimental charge at the end of the
day in this case is just plain zero.
Now what happens is you start moving the two charges,
let's suppose they're really small,
and you start moving them closer and closer together.
Is this screening?
Screening.
This is device screening.
Supposing these charges are really small,
in particular they're smaller than
the clouds around them that form.
The clouds around them are controlled by
various properties of the metal and so forth,
and the electrons moving in the metal,
and we imagine making these charges even smaller.
We bring them really close together.
We bring them so close together that
the screening cloud can't get between them.
Typically there's a scale for the screening cloud.
It's controlled by the dynamics
of the electrons in the system,
and the particles making up the screening cloud
typically have a certain distance between them,
and that distance controls the size of the screening cloud.
When you bring these two
particles closer than the screening cloud,
they're no longer screened.
They actually feel each other's raw basic charge,
and you see that there's a Coulomb force between them,
which is the usual E squared over R.
Okay?
So you could say then
that the charge of the electron,
or the charge of the particle in this case,
is really a function of distance.
In the case of the conductor,
E of R is zero at very large R.
It's whatever the ordinary charge of
the particle is at very small r,
and the force law, instead of
being just plain E squared over R,
has E squared of R divided by R squared.
This is just a definition of
E squared of R, if you like.
I don't put anything new into it
by calling it E squared of R,
but it does have a nice sound to it.
It's called the running charge.
Running is a function of distance between them.
Okay, now what happens if you
have something less extreme than a conductor?
For example, a dielectric.
A dielectric, if you like, has electrons
which are bound together.
Electrons are bound to the atoms.
Electrons are bound to the atoms,
but they're free to shift a little bit.
If you like, you can almost think
of the electrons as being on springs,
where the one end of the
spring the electron is attached to,
the other end of the spring the ion,
the positively charged ion is attached.
And ordinarily, the electron moves symmetrically,
vibrates symmetrically.
Of course, this is not really a good picture
of an atom, but it's good enough for our purposes.
The electron oscillates and vibrates back and forth
symmetrically about the atom.
So on the average, the dipole
moment of the atom is zero.
But now you put the atom into an electric field,
and what happens is the
electron cloud shifts a little bit.
It shifts a little bit, leaving a dipole left over.
The current doesn't flow.
The charge just shifts a little bit
because they're bound to the atoms.
Okay, so now what happens if
you put a charge into a dielectric?
Well, a very similar phenomenon happens.
Let's suppose we put a minus charge in over here.
All the ions are heavy.
They don't move very much.
But the electrons which are
bound to them by the springs
move out away from the central atom.
What does that leave?
That leaves a little bit of plus charge here.
But it doesn't completely screen the charge.
It screens some fraction of the charge.
So that if you look very,
very far away from the charged particle,
you'll find that the field,
the electric field is diminished by a certain fraction,
but it doesn't go to zero very far away.
The fraction is controlled by the dielectric constant.
The dielectric constant will tell you what the screening is.
So again, you'll find that a large separation,
this plus charge and this minus charge,
don't satisfy the expected Coulomb
law that you might have expected
from the actual, let's call it
the bare charge of these particles,
but it's diminished by this,
by this effect.
It's diminished, the Coulomb law is correct,
but with a diminished value of the charge.
So in this case, you would also have an
E squared of R or an E of R.
Again, if you bring the charges very close together
so that they're within the screening cloud,
then you feel the full strength of the bare charge.
So again, E squared is a function of R.
In this case, it wouldn't go to zero and infinity.
It would just go to some constant,
a fraction of the original charge.
Again, the concept of a running charge.
All right, now, exactly this phenomenon,
it really is exactly this phenomenon,
happens in quantum field theory.
The origin of it is the pairs,
let's take quantum electrodynamics.
In quantum electrodynamics,
the vacuum is full of electron-positron pairs.
There are Feynman diagrams
where electrons, positrons are created by photons,
even just electron-positron loops with no photons,
and they inhabit the vacuum, if you like.
The other way you can think about it
is you can think about it
in terms of Dirac's negative energy C.
The vacuum is filled with this negative energy C.
Or you can imagine that there
are electron-positron pairs in the vacuum.
What happens when an electric field comes along?
The electric field will shift the positrons one way
and shift the electrons the other way,
so that every little virtual pair,
electron-positron pair, will become polarized.
Polarized in exactly the same way that
atoms become polarized by an electric field.
The plus charge is shifting one way,
the minus charge is shifting the other way.
That's what happens in the vacuum
when you put an electric field on.
Okay, that's step number one.
Step number two.
Of course, you put in what you thought
was an original bare charge of magnitude E.
The charges in the vacuum rearrange a little bit.
The vacuum is basically a dielectric.
It's basically a dielectric.
The charges shift a little bit,
and in such a way that negative charges
are screened by a little bit of positive charge
from these virtual pairs,
and positive charges are screened by
a little bit of negative charge.
The upshot is the charge
that's felt at a large distance
is not the same as the numerical value
of the charge that you put into the Lagrangian,
which is usually called the bare electric charge.
But again, you start moving the
electrons closer and closer to each other,
and at some point they get closer
than the size of the screening cloud.
But there's one difference in this case.
In this case, there is no set distance
that the electron positrons tend to be separated by.
The right statement is that the separation between
the electron positron pairs depends on their energy.
The higher the energy of the
virtual pair, the closer they will be.
So there will be electron
positron pairs which form relatively big,
let's call them atoms, they're not atoms,
but let's call them atomic neutral systems.
There will be ones of
higher virtual energy which are smaller,
ones of yet higher virtual energy which are even smaller,
ones which are higher energy which are even smaller.
Okay, so what happens when you put the charge in?
And bring another charge closer and closer to it?
And bring another charge closer and closer and closer.
At first, you will bring them close enough that they'll
be within the distance of the low energy virtual pairs.
The low energy virtual pairs will no
longer be able to screen the charge,
and so the charge will look a little bit smaller, sorry,
a little bit bigger than it would when they were far apart.
Why? When they were far
apart, they were completely screened,
not completely screened, but they were
screened by all possible virtual pairs.
You bring them a little bit
closer, the low energy virtual pairs,
which had a large separation between them,
you bring the charges closer than that,
and the low energy virtual pairs
are no longer important in screening.
But the higher energy virtual
pairs are still doing some screening.
You bring them a little closer,
the higher energy pairs are still doing some screening.
The higher energy virtual pairs fall out
of the equation because they're too far apart,
and yet higher energy ones are still there.
The effect is that that E squared of R is
a function which keeps changing and changing and changing with R.
It doesn't stop changing at some particular small distance.
The closer and closer you bring the electron
together, the larger the charge will appear to be.
So if you were to plot,
the virtue of the fact that there are
pairs of every possible energy in the vacuum.
So if you were to plot the electric charge
as a function of radial separation,
let's plot it as a function of inverse radial separation.
Inverse radial separation is like energy.
The closer things are together, the higher their energy.
So let's plot it as a function of inverse separation,
one over R, which is also
related to energy or momentum or whatever.
Then the electric charge that you'll see will increase.
It'll increase very slowly, in fact.
It's a very slow logarithmic increase.
It doesn't increase rapidly.
That's why it's very hard to see in an experiment.
It's a logarithmic gradual increase of
the size of an electric charge
as you study smaller and smaller distance phenomenon.
It's also true, for example,
electric charge comes into
calculations of scattering of electrons.
If you scatter electrons at a low energy,
they only get within a certain distance of each other.
The higher the energy you scatter them,
the closer those electrons can get to each other
by virtue of the uncertainty principle.
And when you do the calculation,
you have to put in the running charge.
If you scatter electrons at enormously high energy,
they behave as if they had
a larger charge than at smaller distances.
So that brings us to the idea of running charge.
What is the fundamental charge?
What is the most fundamental value of the charge?
Is it one of the long distances?
No, that's the one that's controlled by
all of this complicated screening taking place.
As you get the smaller and smaller distances,
you sort of peel away the screening cloud.
you peel away more and more of the screening cloud.
So it's really at the smallest distances
where the basic parameter that you put into the Lagrangian,
the bear charge,
manifests itself.
How small is small where
you start seeing a significant effect?
Well, you start seeing a measurable effect,
but a high precision measurable effect,
at a few times at about
the Compton wavelength of the electron.
So what's that, 10 to the minus 11th?
Compton wavelength of the electron.
The electron is half an MeV,
so that's about 10 to the minus 11th centimeters.
About 10 to the minus 11th centimeters.
You start to see the running of the charge.
But this thing continues to . . .
Well, it would keep going on
if the physics didn't change somehow,
at very small distances.
We don't know what the physics
is at very, very small distances.
Well, sort of implying that the small one is there,
there we don't know what happens, actually.
At very small distances.
Right, that's right.
We don't know what happens
at very small . . .
So we can only extrapolate a certain . . .
Yeah.
So for gluons, it's kind of the opposite thing?
There's some . . .
It does. It does.
How come?
Well, that's a more complicated phenomenon.
A more complicated phenomenon that's
closely connected with the fact
that gluons interact with gluons.
And because gluons interact with gluons
in a very nonlinear kind of way,
the effect is actually the opposite.
How do you determine the bare electric charge?
You go to infinitely small distances,
and you measure at
infinitely small distances the interaction,
and that's the bare electric charge.
But you'll never get to infinitely
small distances because . . .
But it asymptotically approaches something.
No, it doesn't asymptotically.
It just keeps growing and growing and growing.
Yeah, logarithmic function is unbounded.
Right.
So it keeps growing until something happens
that was not taken into account by these calculations.
What could it be?
Our smallest distance in the world, the Planck distance,
something else happens,
and from experimental physics, we
don't know what terminates this.
We certainly believe it's terminated at the Planck length.
This physics certainly doesn't make sense at Planck length.
But there has to be a particular
length to be saying that's bare electric charge.
So let's call it Planck length.
That's the second one.
Okay.
That's a great idea.
But you see, you can compensate.
You can change that length,
and if you also at the same
time change what you called the bare charge,
it would compensate.
Right.
So at any given level, you could terminate it,
call that charge the bare charge at that length,
or change the length scale
if you appropriately and judiciously change
the value of the bare charge
where it comes out at the
low energy end, won't know about it.
Right.
So that's the phenomena of renormalization,
changing things in such a
way as to keep the physics,
the experimentally known physics, fixed.
Is that what you're zooming in and attenuating?
We're zooming in and looking at closer and closer distances.
Now, of course, we don't do that experimentally.
So we do that in our mind,
and we ask how do we have to
change the physics at smaller and smaller distances
to keep it fixed at experimentally accessible distances?
How do we have to change the electric
charge as we go to smaller and smaller distances
in order to keep the
physics fixed at any given wavelength?
So what this is telling us is
that as we go to smaller and smaller,
more and more refined description,
more and more fine-grained description,
the value of the electric charge that we have
to put into the bare description has to grow.
Now, as I said, that will change at some point
where the physics of quantum
electrodynamics gives way to something else.
Okay.
So that's the electric charge.
Let's go.
Does the same phenomena happen with gravity?
The equations are somewhat similar.
We'll talk about it.
It's quite a different phenomenon, but
we'll come to it perhaps today.
I don't know if we'll come to it today, maybe.
Okay, now let's talk about the strong interactions.
The strong interactions, things are more complicated.
Let me remind you of what we
learned about the force law between quarks.
The force law between quarks does
not behave like E squared over R.
What happens is some new phenomena where
the flux lines that come out of quarks,
these are not the electromagnetic flux lines,
these are the flux lines of
QCD, they're called chromoelectric flux lines,
attract each other.
They attract each other in a
way that does not happen in electrodynamics.
It's the self-interaction between gluons.
And that has the effect of turning
the Coulomb field into long tube-like structures,
which are sort of squeezed by
the vacuum into these long tube-like structures.
The effect of this is as you separate quarks,
the energy grows linearly
with the separation between quarks.
You create this Turkish taffy gooey stuff in between them,
and the energy of it grows simply as
the length of the gooey thing between them.
That means that the force law, the energy grows linearly.
What does the force...
All right, so let's write that down.
Instead of the energy growing like E squared over R,
it just grows linearly with R.
So this is the wrong formula.
We should have put here perhaps E
squared or something like E squared times R.
Let's not call it something times R.
Well, we can either say
we had completely the wrong theory,
or we can say that E
squared is growing like R squared.
We can say the picture from electrodynamics,
where charges are screened.
Simply the opposite happens,
that E squared grows with separation.
Something happens in this nonlinear effect here,
which is quite the opposite,
and so E squared grows with separation.
Incidentally, at very small distances,
again, distances which are so small,
smaller than the size of these flux tubes,
it reverts back to E squared over R.
Okay.
So it reverts back to the good old Coulomb law.
But another way of saying it
is that instead of E squared
as a function of distance getting larger with distance,
it actually gets smaller with distance.
E squared is getting smaller...
No, sorry.
With inverse distance.
It's getting smaller with inverse distance.
Larger with distance, smaller with inverse distance.
So therefore, if I plot
the quantum chromodynamics coupling constant,
it will fall as a function of inverse R,
like that.
What about the one for the weak interactions?
Well, the weak interactions are sort of in between.
They're sort of in between.
They have similarities with both.
They're in between.
They go like that.
Well, maybe not as fast.
It's an interesting and quite remarkable fact
that if you actually take the standard model
and you work out how the charges...
First of all, you need to
know what the various coupling constants are
in the laboratory.
Those are the ones that control physics
at whatever scales you've done your experiment.
You've got 100 GeV or whatever,
and you put in their values,
and then you run them using just the standard model,
the polarization of the vacuum
and all the properties from the standard model.
These three numbers more or less come together
at a common point.
They more or less come together at a common point.
Now, in a more...
Well, in the supersymmetric version
of the theory, which we will
talk about next time a little bit,
next quarter,
they come together with rather high precision,
about 1%.
About 1%.
They come together at about 1%.
That looks like there's something happening
at some energy which is unifying these forces.
Their coupling constants seem to be the same
at some high energy here
if you just extrapolate these curves.
The curves are calculable.
Of course, you have to assume
that no new physics comes in.
That no new physics comes in,
or if new physics comes in,
you have to take it into account.
New physics might shift these curves a little bit.
In the supersymmetric version of the theory,
these three numbers come together very nicely
to about 1%
at an energy of about 10 to the 16th GeV.
Why is that energy so high?
It's because these curves vary logarithmically.
They vary slowly.
When things vary slowly, they vary slowly.
And so it takes a long range of scales
before they come together.
And they come together at
about 10 to the 16th GeV.
10 to the 14th times larger
than the mass of the W.
So it's some huge energy.
It looks from these curves
that some kind of unification is taking place there.
Now, is this good enough to...
Is this...
It's a relatively high precision agreement
in the supersymmetric theory.
In the non-supersymmetric theory,
it's not such high precision agreement.
But it's tantalizing, and it's interesting
that this is the tendency for things.
All right.
If this is correct,
you might guess that the fundamental length scale
of particle physics of the standard model
is up at this 10 to the 15th GeV.
It's where the input seems to be simplest.
Simplest in that the three coupling constants
seem to be the same.
We'll talk about what that means mathematically.
It has a very deep...
It could have a very deep mathematical meaning.
But for the moment,
it's just an observation
about numbers,
that they come together
at a particular energy.
Now, that energy also happens to be the place,
if you were to plot the strength
of gravitational forces.
Gravitational forces are very weak
at large distances,
but I'm going to show you why in a moment.
They get stronger and stronger and stronger
at small distances,
not only because of the usual
1 over r squared in the force,
but above and beyond that,
the forces of gravitation
become stronger and stronger.
And if you were to lay on top of that,
let's see,
the forces of gravitation
would become strong at small distances.
So that would mean gravitational forces,
which are credibly weak at long distances,
would do something like that.
And they don't quite all cross at the same place,
but they cross within a factor,
remember these are logarithmic curves,
they cross within a couple of orders
of magnitude of each other.
The gravitational, the weak,
the electromagnetic,
and the strong interaction
cross all within a couple of decades
of energy of each other,
or a couple of decades of length scale,
at about somewhere between
10 to the 16th, 17th, 18th,
GEV.
So what all this means,
especially the gravitational side of it,
we don't know,
but if there is a unification scale,
and if this really does correspond to some unity
between the three forces,
it looks like it happens at a scale
which is not too different
than the Planck scale.
The Planck scale is the scale
where gravity would become comparable
to the other forces.
So let's talk a little bit about
gravitational forces,
and why I say that gravity gets stronger
at small distances.
Ordinarily,
now we're going to talk about what happens
to gravitational forces
as you vary the distance scale.
And the only point here is that
when you understand how gravity
depends on length scale,
you find out that gravity sort of falls
on the same scale
as the other forces.
So we have a little bit of a
ballpark with the other forces
at scales which are very small.
Gravity is really no weaker
than these other forces.
Okay, so to understand this,
we first have to erase the blackboard
a little bit.
We're used to thinking that
the force law of gravity is
one over r squared,
or Coulomb.
You'd be surprised if I told you
it's really one over r cubed
at very small distances.
You wouldn't be surprised.
بدي
ودن
I thought I heard something like that.
Yeah, you said something.
Okay, so let's go through why it's
1 over r cubed at very small distances.
The reason is we write
down, what do we write down?
We write force, let's work with force this time.
We worked with energy before. It
doesn't matter which we work with.
Force is equal to m, m, two
particles, masses, r squared, and Newton's constant, right?
That's the force between two particles.
All right, now this is a non-relativistic formula.
This is the formula for particles at rest.
When particles have a high energy,
or when objects have a high energy,
it's energy that gravitates and not mass, not rest mass.
A moving object will gravitate
more than an object at rest.
If you take a box full of high energy particles,
those high energy particles will gravitate
more than an object at rest.
They will gravitate more than they would if
they were brought to rest within the box.
So the right formula, or a more correct formula,
a more correct formula is to put here,
use E equals mc squared,
or m, m, not m squared,
E equals mc squared, or better
yet, m equals E over c squared,
and put in here energy of particles,
E over c fourth, I believe, right? Over c fourth.
All right, so this is
a formula which is more accurate
when the particles are relativistic.
Okay, now let's go to quantum mechanics,
and imagine bringing two particles very close together,
much closer together than their Compton wavelengths.
Because of the uncertainty principle,
if we've brought them close together,
that means that their momentum is extremely uncertain.
To say that their momentum is extremely uncertain,
you can say that their momentum is very large.
Roughly speaking, if you brought them to
within a distance r of each other,
the momentum of them must be at least of order,
what is it, h bar over r, right?
Okay?
Now, what about the energy of these particles?
The energy of these particles, you might think,
well, the energy of a
particle at rest is mc squared.
If it has a little bit of velocity,
you add plus one half mv squared.
Sorry, one mv squared over two.
But what happens when the momentum gets really large
when r gets very small,
these particles become highly relativistic.
Why?
Their momentum gets much larger than any pre-assigned number
when they get very, very close together.
What's the energy of a particle,
a relativistic particle with momentum p?
Relativistic means it's moving with
almost the speed of light.
Anybody remember?
What is it?
No, that's non-relativistic completely.
No, no.
No, the energy is p times the speed of light.
Right.
p times the speed of light.
Okay?
So, we can now say
p is h bar over r.
And now we can plug
this into the force between particles.
Okay, so what is it?
So, p is equal to h bar squared.
Let's just, the particles come close together.
Let's assume they both have about the same energy,
which is a good assumption.
So, that's h bar squared c squared over r squared.
That's just e squared here, e one times e two.
That's this factor here.
Then there's a c to the fourth in the denominator.
From here, there's a g and another r squared.
So, r to the fourth.
Did I get it right?
Yeah.
Right.
How about c squared?
The c squared is canceled.
Yeah.
Well, they don't cancel.
C squared.
When I said the force
law was one over r cubed,
I meant the energy, not the force.
The force is one over r to the fourth.
So, when you bring particles really close together,
squeeze them by whatever means,
either an accelerator accelerates them to very high energy
so they can get very, very close together,
or you put them in a box and squeeze them.
Well, no box is going to
hold particles that are that high.
There are other particles that are that relativistic.
But somehow or another, when
the particles get that close together,
the force law is quite different than Coulomb.
It's one over r to the fourth.
Okay, now let's ask the following question.
Yeah.
Well, we're talking gravitational force here,
so it's an attractive force.
It's an attractive force.
Right.
And it is much more potent
at small distances than it is at large distances.
One over r to the fourth is much, much bigger
than one over r squared.
This is because the relativistic speedup
causes the mass to increase
but not the charge to increase.
Right, right, right, exactly, exactly so.
Exactly so.
Okay, now let's ask at what length scale r
is the gravitational force
approximately the same order of magnitude
as the electromagnetic force.
Let's do a little, let's,
there's the electric charge,
the electron's electric charge is a pure number.
It happens to be fairly small.
Let's forget, but not ridiculously small.
It's a fairly small number of something like a tenth
or something like that in natural units.
So for the first round,
we could just set the electric charge of an electron
equal to one for simplicity.
And then we could ask at what length scale
is the force, the gravitational force
between a pair of particles
the same as the electromagnetic force,
let's say a pair of electrons.
Does that ever happen?
At ordinary scales,
electric forces are vastly larger than gravitational forces,
electric forces.
As you bring them closer together,
because the gravitational forces increase
like one over r to the fourth,
eventually the gravitational force will cross
the electrostatic force,
and at smaller distances will become even more important,
even larger.
So let's see where that happens.
To find out where that happens,
we should set this equal
to e squared
over r squared.
For simplicity for the moment,
let's just set the electric charge equal to one.
It's not equal to one,
it's about a tenth or something,
about, it's smaller than one.
G or e?
You just erased a g.
Oh, sorry, I didn't mean to erase g.
I didn't do that.
E.
Let's simplify and put a one here,
which is not too long.
E squared is really something like
about a tenth.
But it's not too bad,
it's approximately right.
Now we can read off from this
at what scale these two kinds of forces
become equal to each other.
Just multiply by r to the fourth.
This becomes r squared here.
Now take the square root of it.
Wait, did I...
Something wrong.
You had r fourth,
it would be r squared now.
It's r squared, yeah.
Okay.
I think I made a mistake.
I still think I made a mistake.
Hmm?
No, but it's not right.
Wait, um...
You don't know the answer.
H bar c over c squared r to the fourth
is one over r squared.
Right.
So I have h bar g over c...
h bar g over c...
is equal to r.
It's r squared, not r to the fourth.
It was an r...
It was an r to the fourth here, right?
Yes.
And then there was a one
over r squared r to the fourth.
So I got an r squared here.
So I got an r squared here, right?
Right.
Right?
I think it was doing r, right?
Hmm?
What you read out sounded like you were
just doing the square root on both sides.
What am I going to get?
I'm going to get h bar over c...
squared root of g.
h bar over c squared root of g, right?
Yeah.
It's equal to r.
r.
Which is the square root of
h bar squared g over c squared.
c squared.
No, c squared.
Is that dimensionally correct?
Must be.
Well, you took out electric charge and...
No, no, electric charge is dimensionless.
Oh, wait a second, wait a second, wait a second.
Yeah.
Hold on.
I think I lost something.
I think I lost some dimensions.
This is energy.
This is...
All right, let's work, let's
do it in terms of energy.
It's r cubed in terms of energy.
And I want to set that
equal to e squared over r.
But this is not dimensionally
consistent if r is dimensionless.
So I need some h bars and c's in there.
Um...
They're charged.
Hmm?
You need to get rid of the charge, don't you?
Well, I want the charge to be dimensionless because
I happen to know its value in dimensionless units.
It's about a tenth.
It's close to one.
So, uh, so we have to put some correct...
This has units of energy, right?
If I...
So, so we have one over r.
One over r.
And if I put an...
This is not correct yet.
It's not correct.
It's dimensionally consistent.
If I put an h bar
here, then this would be momentum.
If I put a c
there, it is now dimensionally consistent.
All right?
c h bar over r has units of
energy, and now this electric charge here is dimensionless.
And that's the one which is,
um, uh, which is about a tenth.
Close to one.
Okay, so I made a mistake.
I thought I made a mistake.
I should have...
Uh-oh, I erased it.
It's lost.
It's gone.
It's okay.
You're...
You have h.
You have your c square.
Right.
h, h square g.
You have c after...
And then...
All right.
I...
Back to the course.
All right.
Exchange everything.
I...
I think it's right now?
Yes.
Okay, now multiply it by r...
r cubed...
And we get r squared up here.
Now we...
Now we get a c down...
c cubed down here.
And remove an h bar.
And I get r now is equal to the
square root of g h bar over c cubed.
I think I like that better.
Nice.
Thank you.
Alright.
Now I can see the...
Here.
Thank you.
Yep.
So, uh, so, this thing, right here...
Yeah.
Oh, I'm not sure what I mean by that.
Now I'm not sure what I mean by that.
A constant...
What?
All right, what is that length?
That's the Planck length.
So the Planck length is the place where, because of
this growth of energy with squeezing, with diminishing the wavelength,
because of that, the gravitational force
increases and becomes comparable or even bigger.
A few factors of 10 bigger than
the electromagnetic force at the Planck length.
So the electromagnetic force, the weak force, the strong force, and the gravitational force
all grow or all become more or less comparable somewhere near the Planck scale.
This is thought to be deep.
This is thought to be something.
This is thought to be something important.
If it is as important as it sounds, then the
puzzle becomes not why is the Planck length so small,
or why is the Planck mass so large, or why
is that 10 to the 19th such a big number?
It is why that F
is so small in natural units.
How does it happen that that F, which controls
the masses and the energy scales of all weak electromagnetic,
all the orbitals,
all the ordinary interactions,
in particular, controls the mass of the
Z, the W, the quarks, the electron.
Why is it so small?
That's one number, which is some 15 orders of magnitude smaller
than any fundamental length scale, as far as we can tell.
And it's just that one number which is very small.
Once that one number is explained, why it is so small, all
the masses of all the elementary particles that we know about follow.
And that's the Planck length.
All the others, for all we know, could be
up at the Planck mass, at the natural scale.
They have no reason to be light.
Their masses did not have to
be proportional to this symmetry breaking scale.
So that's kind of where we are,
puzzled about why this F is so small.
Now, we'll go more deeply into this next quarter.
It's not only that it's small.
It's also very, very finely tuned.
And, oh, we'll come back to it.
So if you could somehow calculate F,
then you could calculate the other masses.
If you could calculate F, you could, but any
ordinary calculation of F will give a huge number.
Why?
Because it'll come out to be proportional to the
fundamental scale, unless there's some incredible conspiracy that, so.
Yeah, you can calculate it in all sorts of theories.
And it'll come out huge.
I'm trying to visualize the Planck length in terms
of the screening distance when we get so close.
In gravitational physics, it's not
helpful to think about a screen.
Oh, OK.
Yeah, that's right.
That's just .
Yeah, it's just not useful to think about a screen.
If you had higher orders of the feet.
Higher orders of what?
Of the Higgs field, of feet.
And you can say feet of the sixth, et cetera.
P.
What's P?
Phi.
Phi, yeah, Phi.
Phi, for fun.
Each of those appear on a
logarithm, is that what you're saying?
Well, there are real reasons why not.
You wouldn't want to put in Phi fifth there, because
that would break the symmetry between plus Phi and minus Phi.
You could put Phi sixth there.
But there are...
Those are annihilation and creation operators, those Phis?
Yeah.
That represents four Higgs particles coming together?
Absolutely.
OK, so that's another...
Right.
Once you know these numbers, you can
predict something about the scattering of Higgs bosons.
Two Higgs bosons go to two Higgs bosons.
Right.
Is the Lagrangian a polynomial
in all the field variables then?
OK, so that's pretty restrictive, isn't it?
Well, it's not...
It's more restrictive than you think.
Beyond Phi to the fourth becomes what is called non-renormalizable,
which is a bad thing to have in a theory.
So...
Yeah.
We can talk about why Phi
fourth is the natural exponent of this.
The Lagrangian is polynomial in all the field
values and there's never any exponent above four.
Right.
Except when there is.
Have you left out any terms like self-interaction or...
Well, self-interactions are what goes into
the running of these coupling constants.
For example, the self-interactions between gluons are what gave
you the opposite effect from what happens in electrodynamics.
Self-interaction between flux lines pulls them together into a sort of cable
and the upshot is that the running electric charge changes quite differently.
And the other thing I thought of
was cross-terms between interact... between kinds of interactions.
Well, there are such things.
They come in in higher orders
and you have to calculate them.
But fortunately for us, all of
the coupling constants are quite small.
So the higher order cross-terms are
smaller than the things that they're determining.
What exactly did you mean when
you said F is finely tuned?
I didn't come to it.
We'll discuss it.
I'll tell you.
Not now.
But I guess that's...
It's important.
Since we've talked about renormalization in groups, can you
say something about what the renormalization in groups is?
Not tonight, but at some point.
Okay.
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.