Stanford University.
All right,
let's begin if there are no other questions.
All right.
What we're going to talk about
tonight is the principle of least action.
Now,
the principle of least action is a misnomer.
Which of the words is wrong?
The word that's wrong is least.
It is not generally the case that the equations
of motion of Newton or anybody else for that matter,
classical equations,
tell you that the action,
whatever that is,
we're going to come to it,
that the action is minimum.
It tells you that the action is stationary.
So let's talk about the notion of minimum,
stationary,
and so forth in,
first of all,
a simpler context.
Let's think about the laws of physics.
But a special case of the laws of physics.
The special case of the laws of
physics is what are the laws determining equilibrium?
What are the laws determining the configurations
of a system when it doesn't move,
when it's not moving,
when it's stationary?
So that's a question.
What are the laws of equilibrium?
Equilibrium means that there are no reasons to think.
We don't think the object moves,
if it's an object or whatever it is.
And the answer,
of course,
is that the forces are equal to zero.
If we have an object
and it's not going to move,
doesn't move,
it doesn't accelerate,
let's say it doesn't accelerate,
it doesn't move,
but in particular it doesn't accelerate,
then we can ask what
are the laws that govern that?
And the answer is that the forces are zero.
If the forces are derived from a potential,
as all real forces are,
if the forces are derived as the derivatives of potentials,
potential energy function,
which is a function of a collection of coordinates,
I'll call them x,
later on tonight I may start calling them q,
but for the moment let's just call them x,
they could be the coordinates of a particle,
they could be the coordinates of many particles,
then the condition that nothing
moves is that the forces vanish,
which is the same thing as
saying that the derivative of the potential,
let's take the case first of all
of a particle moving on a line,
that the ordinary derivative in that case,
the ordinary derivative of the potential,
d by dx is equal to zero.
That's the condition that the force is equal to zero.
And another way of saying
that is that the force is,
that the potential energy is stationary.
What does stationary mean?
It could mean,
it means that the derivative is equal to zero,
that's all it means.
Okay,
but if you want to
draw a graph of the potential,
where in this graph are the forces equal to zero,
they're equal to zero,
where the derivative is equal to zero,
at the minima and the maxima of the functions.
Now,
notice,
first of all,
equilibrium does not require that
the potential energy be minimum.
It requires that the derivative be zero,
which is the right words of it,
the potential energy is stationary.
Stationary means it doesn't change if you move,
if you move slightly to the
left or slightly to the right,
and it's just another way of saying the derivative vanishes.
But let's think about,
let's think about a small displacement of x.
At the moment,
we're not necessarily at the minimum.
We might be at the minimum,
we might be anywheres.
And let's think about how much the potential
energy changes when we move a little bit.
And the answer is,
of course,
dv by dx.
Times,
let's say,
let's call the motion delta x.
Times delta x.
The change per unit x
times the small change in x,
and that we can just call delta v.
The change in v when we change
x a little bit by amount delta x.
And what is the rule?
The rule is you're in equilibrium
when delta v is equal to zero.
Now,
I made it a little more complicated.
It's a little more complicated over
here than it was over here.
But we're going to find out,
it's a useful notation,
a useful way to think about it,
that you're in equilibrium whenever you're at
a point where the potential doesn't change
when you move a little bit,
when you make a little delta of x.
Now,
of course,
this is true to first order in delta x.
It's not completely true,
but it's true as an approximation
for first order in delta x.
Now,
let's go on to a little more complicated situation.
Suppose there are several coordinates.
I'll draw it as two coordinates because I'm
not very good at drawing 12 or 15 coordinates.
You say,
why not three?
Well,
the reason they're three is because
I need an axis for v.
I only have two axes left over,
and I'm not even very good at that.
But here's two axes left over.
x,
2,
3.
x and y.
I don't know.
Let's call this x.
Let's call this one y.
And suppose that the potential energy has some shape.
It's a function of position.
And it's a function which varies both with...
Now,
don't get...
This is not a roller coaster.
This is a hilly terrain which varies in both directions.
Then where is an object in equilibrium?
Again,
it's in equilibrium
when all the components of
the force are equal to zero.
And that means when all
of the partial derivatives of v
with respect to,
let's call it,
x,
i now.
And x,
i can mean x or y,
or it could mean 59 other coordinates
or 10 to the 23rd more of them.
v of x is a function of all the coordinates.
Partial of v with respect
to any given one of them
is the component of force along that particular direction.
And when all of them are equal to zero,
not one of them,
but when all of them are
equal to zero for all i...
How do mathematicians write for all i?
Upside down a or something.
And where do they put the i?
Over here?
All right.
I won't write it right,
so I won't even try.
dv by dx is equal to zero for all v.
Now,
on this side over here,
let's imagine...
Oh,
and where is that?
Let's first talk about what kind of places satisfy that.
First of all,
the bottoms of hills
are places where dv dx is equal to zero.
The tops of hills are also.
At the top of a hill,
every place you go goes downward.
Well,
every place you go starts out flat,
that's this condition,
but then it proceeds to go downward.
At the bottom of a hill,
you're at the bottom,
so any place you go is up.
It's a second order.
There are other kinds of stationary points.
The other kinds of stationary
points are called saddle points.
A saddle point is...
You've all been on saddle points out in the mountains.
A saddle point looks like that.
Is that clear?
I think it's clear.
All right,
somebody standing over here is in equilibrium.
The derivative of v,
this is v,
with respect to,
let's say,
y,
is equal to zero.
There's no variation as you go over
the top of the hill this way,
and it's also zero if
you go this way over here.
So you are in equilibrium at this point,
but two different directions,
and one of them,
the force...
In fact,
in one of them,
the force pulls you back,
and the other,
if you deviate a little bit,
the other one,
the force...
sends you down the hill.
But as long as you're right at the top,
you're in equilibrium,
right at the saddle point.
Not at the top,
but right at the saddle point.
So the generic situation for a stationary point
is not that it's a maximum or a minimum,
but that it's stationary in the maybe different directions
where you go down,
some directions where you go up,
but right at the saddle point.
If you move a little bit,
the change in the potential energy is zero
in the first order.
Now what is the change in
potential if you move a little bit?
Let's say we change x and y,
or however many there are.
If there are only two coordinates,
the change in v would be the
derivative of v with respect to x.
That's the amount that v changes
if you move x a little bit
times delta x plus dv by dy times delta y.
What this says,
wherever you are,
you don't have to be at the bottom.
Wherever you are,
the change in v,
if you move a little bit,
is the derivative of v with respect to x
times the little change in x
plus the derivative of v with respect to y
times the little change in y.
And that we can call delta v.
Let's call it delta v.
Delta v,
a symbol like this means,
it's a little bit of an implicit symbol,
it means the change in v for any,
any little motion.
It doesn't specify which direction
or how much you're moving,
but for any infinitesimal deviation
from the point in question,
this is the change in v.
And the condition of equilibrium is
exactly the same as it was before,
that delta v is equal to zero
for every possible choice of delta x and delta y.
For every possible choice of the v.
That's the condition of equilibrium.
And so we can write then,
that the general law of nature
for equilibrium
is that the variation of v is equal to zero
for any little motion at all,
to first order in small quantities.
That's a sort of summary of all of classical physics
when equilibrium is,
when there's no time dependence.
All right,
and it's also,
you know,
just a little bit of mathematics,
stationary points.
Now of course,
we're not interested in equilibrium only,
we're interested in more complicated motions.
We're interested in whole motions.
We're interested not in finding points
that satisfy the equations of motion,
but whole trajectories.
Trajectories are curves through space and time.
They're functions.
X of t,
y of t,
z of t.
And the principle of stationary action
is a principle that says not that you,
that some point is preferred,
but a whole trajectory,
a whole function.
The problem of finding functions
which minimize some quantity
is this famous mathematical problem.
It's called the calculus of variations,
and we're going to go through some examples.
We're going to go through a
little bit of the mathematics of it.
It's not very hard,
it's pretty easy.
There's an analog of this equation,
analog of these equations,
just a little more complicated.
But let me give you some physical
or some physical and mathematical examples
of questions which are answered by
the principles of the variational calculus.
For example,
the simplest one,
which you probably all know,
but let's spell it out anyway,
is what is the shortest line between two points?
Shortest means minimum.
Minimum means stationary.
So what does that mean?
You pick two points,
let's say two points,
and on the plane,
it could be in three-dimensional space,
it could be whatever you like,
but pick two points on the plane
and ask what curve
minimizes the distance between them.
The distance now is this.
It's the incremental distance
as you move along the curve.
It's not this one,
that's for sure.
You all know what it is,
it's a straight line.
Let's see if we can set that question,
if not the answer,
let's see if we can set
the question up mathematically.
Let's not put the origin over here.
We have two points,
let's call them x,
this is x and y,
one,
this is x,
two,
and y,
two.
And I want to find the curve,
here's the curve,
which minimizes the distance between them.
That curve is defined by a function.
And we could take it to be just a,
let's take this to be the x-axis,
let's take this to be the y-axis,
and it's defined by some y of x.
Suppose I give you a y of x
that passes through these two points,
then along that y of x,
there's some distance,
measured along y of x.
In other words,
you take a tape measure
and you hug it to the line,
you measure some distance,
what is it?
Let's see if we can calculate it.
If I take some little incremental distance there,
let's say it corresponds to dx,
there's a little incremental distance dx,
then what's the length of that segment?
The length of that segment,
of course,
the length of that segment,
the distance here is dy,
the length of the segment
is the square root of dx squared plus dy squared.
It's the length of this little line here,
which is the hypotenuse of a triangle,
I don't want to draw too
many pieces to this curve here.
There's a horizontal distance,
a vertical distance,
and the length of the little segment,
let's call it ds.
I don't know,
again,
I don't know what the history is
of using s for distance along a curve.
I don't know what it is.
ds,
s is distance along a curve,
ds is obviously the square root
of dx squared plus dy squared.
Let me divide inside the square root
by dx squared.
Alright,
then I can take out a dx on the outside,
dx on the outside,
and write this as one plus dy by dx squared.
Is that much clearer?
All I did was divide in the denominator
by dx,
by dx squared,
but that means I have to multiply
by square root of dx squared,
which is just the dx on the outside.
That's the distance in this little increment here.
And then what's the total distance from here to here?
The total distance is the integral,
the sum of all these little incremental distances.
And so here we have it.
The distance from one to two
is just equal to the integral of this,
dx.
What do I mean by dy by dx?
y is some function of x.
dy by dx is simply the derivative of it.
So here's what you're instructed.
You're instructed to find the curve
that has the property
that the integral along it,
dx,
of the square root of one
plus the derivative of the function squared,
plus the square root of the derivative of the function
underneath the square root,
is equal to the shortest possible length,
is minimal.
To say that it's minimal
means that if you move it any little bit,
it'll increase.
If you move it this way,
it'll increase that,
and if you move it that way,
it'll increase.
But it also means you're at the bottom of something.
You're at the bottom of this quantity
with respect to any little change
in what the function is.
By analogy,
with the case of just an ordinary function,
we can write that
the condition is that the variation of this
is equal to zero.
The analog of being at the bottom of something
is always that the variation,
no matter,
for any little change of what,
what are we going to change,
incidentally?
We're going to change the function.
Any little change in the function
will increase the length.
will increase the length in the same way
that any motion away from here will increase it.
Implication is that the derivative is equal to zero,
or
the variation is equal to zero.
So the question then is,
how do we solve a problem like this?
Solving it for us is going to mean one thing.
We are not going to frequently
be able to solve most problems.
This one we can solve.
But the answer is a straight line,
of course.
But solving an equation like this for us
is going to mean to
reduce it to a differential equation,
to an equation similar to this one,
similar to Newton's equations.
Reducing it to an equation of motion
which would allow us to
study it in little incremental steps.
So,
solving a variational problem like this
means reducing it to a simple differential equation.
That's the,
that's,
we will take that to
be a solution of the problem.
Alright,
that's one example.
Let me give you some more examples
of similar situations.
Here's another one,
a very similar one.
It's the principle not of,
oh,
incidentally,
you could ask this question,
not on the flat blackboard,
but you could ask this question on an arbitrary surface.
Supposing I give you a surface,
it could be the surface of the Earth,
it could be the spherical surface of the Earth,
or it could be a terrain out in,
in a hilly country somewheres.
And I would like to
put a stake in over here
and a stake in over here,
and find the shortest distance between them,
in other words,
the shortest route between them.
Physically or experimentally,
how would I do it?
I might attach a string over here,
pull the string as tight as possible,
and when it's pulled as tight as possible,
it will define some shortest distance between them.
It will not be a straight line.
Why?
Because the surface is curved.
So you could generalize this question.
I won't write the equations for it,
but you could generalize the equation here,
and it would be the same kind of thing.
The distance from here to here would be some integral,
sum of little incremental pieces,
and the condition that it's minimum or stationary
would be that its variation is equal to zero.
When you change,
when you do what?
When you change the trajectory a little bit.
Not trajectory,
but trajectory.
You can shift the line a little bit.
So that's another example.
Principle of,
not the principle,
but the problem of finding
the shortest path between two points.
The shortest path between two points on a curved surface
is called a geodesic.
And a geodesic on a
flat plane is a straight line.
Okay,
so we all know this.
Let's do another one.
There is a physical principle,
a law,
about light.
It's Fermat's principle of least time.
How much,
what's the path of a light ray between two points?
Path of a light ray between two points.
Now of course the answer is a straight line.
Why is it a straight line?
Because the principle is that it
should take the least amount of time.
That's the principle.
The principle of least time,
light rays move in a way
which minimize the amount of time
to go from one point to another,
and if the light ray moves with constant velocity,
constant speed,
then it's just going to be the shortest distance
between the two points.
But you can imagine situations
where light moves with a variable velocity
from place to place.
Like,
for example,
neutrinos move faster in Italy
than they do in...
But no,
we don't need to go that route.
Light moving through materials moves with a velocity
that depends on the index of refraction.
Index of refraction can vary from place to place.
So supposing we had a light ray
moving from here to here
with a speed of light
which depended on where we were.
So here we are,
we have a light ray moving from here to here,
and the speed of light,
c,
is some general function of x and y.
It's a function.
Now how do we do the problem?
Well,
let's again construct the time that it takes
to go from here to here as an integral.
It's clearly the sum of the time that it takes
to go every little incremental distance.
The little incremental distance,
let's go back a step,
the little incremental distance from one point to another
was the square root of dx squared plus dy squared.
Now,
that's the distance between these two points.
How long does it take
for light to go between them?
Time is equal to distance divided by velocity.
Right?
Time is distance divided by velocity.
Here's the distance the light
ray goes between here and here.
Divide it by the velocity,
but now remember that the
velocity is a function of position.
We can do the same trick that we did before.
Take out the factor dx
and write this as one plus dy by dx squared.
And now our problem
is to find the function y of x
which minimizes this integral.
The thing in the integral
depends on both x and y,
but also on the derivative
of y with respect to x.
That's characteristic,
that the things in the integrals
that we're going to be examining
depend not only on x and y,
or position or whatever it happens to be,
but also derivatives.
Derivatives or slopes of functions.
So here's another example,
very similar to the...
And in fact,
this is the way light moves
through a medium of variable index of refraction.
It finds not the shortest path,
but the shortest time that it can go.
We don't need to dwell on that very much.
I think probably a good many of you know that.
But now let's think about this.
Let's talk about mechanics problem.
The general mechanics problem,
let's take the special mechanics problem first.
The special mechanics problem that we always deal with first
is a motion on a line,
one dimensional motion on a line.
And we can think of the horizontal axis as x,
the vertical axis as t.
Now,
t is the independent variable.
Usually you plot the independent variable horizontally,
but because time is a variable,
as everybody knows,
flows upward.
I got a very interesting...
from your granddad,
gave me a very interesting paper
on the cognitive issue
of how time is represented in various cultures.
And how is it represented graphically
in terms of space things.
And it turns out
that the psychological experiments
say that for all people who use an alphabet
which proceeds from left to right,
they all...
Here's the experiment they did,
a fascinating experiment.
They took a bunch of pictures of people,
for example,
starting with a child,
an older child,
same person,
older,
old man.
And they told them to arrange those pictures
in a sequence.
All people who used
systems of writing
which proceed from left to right
put them,
you know,
from left to right,
that way.
Chinese,
who write from top down,
put them this way.
Child,
old man.
Israelis,
which way they go?
The other way.
So it's apparent that they envision time differently,
this way,
for Israelis.
And the only people who go from bottom to top
are physicists.
She didn't say that,
the psychologist.
I just said it now.
It's apparently the only people who realize
that time flows upward are physicists.
Don't ask me why,
I have no idea.
But in any case,
that's a bit awkward,
because we also usually think of
the independent variable in a graph
as the horizontal axis,
right?
And we like to think
of time as the independent variable
and position as the dependent variable.
What's x of t?
So I'm going to turn this graph around.
We're going to make this time
this x,
and the trajectory of a particle
is going to be a curve.
The problem,
so there's a standard problem of mechanics,
we've talked about it before.
If you know the initial conditions,
and what do the initial conditions consist of?
They consist of knowing the position
and the velocity.
So on this diagram here,
knowing the position is of course knowing what x is
at a particular time.
Knowing the velocity is knowing the derivative.
So if you know the position and the derivative
at one instant of time,
Newton's equations allow you to construct
the whole trajectory if you know the forces.
You need two pieces of information
for each coordinate,
a position and a velocity.
The other version of classical mechanics
is to say,
again,
you need two pieces of information for each coordinate.
Instead of knowing the initial position and velocity,
you know the position at time t0,
let's call it x0,
and you know the position,
let's call it,
this is at t1,
and you know x at time t1,
let's call it just x of 1.
So what you're given then
is the location of an object,
a particle,
or whatever it is,
at two different times,
and you're asked to fill in the trajectory in between
that corresponds to the actual orbit
between those two points.
This time,
the initial velocity
will be part of the solution.
You'll need to aim it in the right way
with the right velocity
to get it to go to that point,
in space and time.
So the initial velocity will not be now an input,
it will be part of the solution.
This is the other form of the problems of mechanics,
the problems of all of physics.
Given an initial and final configuration,
find what interpolates between them.
And guess what?
The answer in all problems of classical physics
is to minimize something,
is to minimize something associated with the path
between these two points.
And in fact,
that something is an integral
from one point to another,
and it's called the action.
When I say minimize,
I mean make stationary.
Minimize,
maximize,
or otherwise make stationary.
Something called the action.
It's analogous to the distance between two points in space
or the time along a trajectory for a light ray.
One other example,
one other example of a problem
of calculus of variations,
just to make one more example,
is the problem of finding the configuration
of a chain,
of a chain with a weight
in a gravitational field.
All right,
again,
it's pinned down at two places.
The two places don't have
to be at the same elevation.
It's pinned down at two places.
The chain itself is a function,
and you're trying to find a function
which minimizes what?
The energy,
the potential energy,
the potential energy.
Find the configuration of lowest potential energy
or stationary potential energy.
There's another one,
but all these problems have the character
two points that are fixed,
and some integral in between.
The potential energy is also an integral.
It's the potential energy of each little piece,
and some integral
needs to be made stationary.
Now,
what's the connection between
this form of mechanics?
Well,
let's write it out first.
Let's write it out first.
There is a quantity.
Let's call it A for action.
It is an integral over the trajectory.
So we can write it as an integral dt
from t naught to t1
of something that depends on the trajectory.
What is that thing?
We're going to call it L,
the Lagrangian.
It's the Lagrangian,
and what does it depend on?
It depends on every point along the trajectory.
It depends on the position along the trajectory,
and it depends on the velocity along the trajectory,
x dot.
That's analogous
to the situation over here
where the thing in the interval
is an integral
dependent on both the derivative
of the function
and the quantity,
and the x itself,
x,
maybe even y.
The analogy here would have,
well,
it would have x being like t.
The thing you're integrating over is x.
Here,
the thing you're integrating over is t.
And you're trying to find a trajectory
which minimizes a certain quantity.
The question is,
how do you do that
or better yet,
maybe not better yet,
but maybe a little more modest,
how do you,
how do you
reconstruct this problem
as a problem that looks like Newton's equations?
That's what we want to know.
What's the connection between this form
and Newton's equations?
All right,
so the first thing I'm going to show you
is that such problems can always be reduced
to differential equations.
So let's see how this works.
It can always be reduced to a differential equation,
and the differential equation has a name.
It's called the Euler-Lagrange equation.
Now,
it's,
the equation depends on what
L of x and x dot are.
L of x and x
dot could be many different things.
You could put all kinds of functions in there.
Each function that you put in gives you
a different Euler-Lagrange equation.
But nevertheless,
this problem,
let's write the problem,
the problem is to minimize
or otherwise make stationary
the action.
Make it stationary,
in other words,
to do the same thing to it
as you do when you find the minimum
of a potential energy.
Make it stationary.
Okay,
so the way to do it is to reduce it
to the problem of minimizing an ordinary function.
And the way you do that
is by replacing
this precise problem
by an approximate problem.
The approximate problem
goes like this.
Divide up the time axis
into little increments.
Replace the trajectory,
let's,
replace the trajectory
by a sequence of
intervals
and so forth.
Take the size of each increment
and call it epsilon.
Epsilon,
small number.
Epsilon is always a small number.
Call it epsilon.
What we're going to do in the end
is shrink it to zero.
In the process of shrinking it to zero,
we will replace this sort of piecewise
straight line by an arbitrary curve.
We're going to shrink epsilon to zero.
But before we do,
let's work out the approximate theory.
The approximate theory here
replaces the integral
by a sum.
Alright,
so how do you replace an integral by a sum?
Integral dx
or integral dt.
Integral is just a fancy symbol for sum.
This becomes
summation.
The reason the integral is drawn like an s
is because it stands for sum.
But,
we're going to replace
that continuous sum,
integral by an ordinary sum.
What are we going to sum over?
We're going to sum over each one
of these little segments here.
Let's call this the i-th segment over here.
Well,
let's call it,
let's not use the segments.
Let's call this the i-th site.
This is i minus one.
This is i plus one.
Can everybody read that?
i minus one,
i,
i plus one,
and so forth and so on.
We'll label these lines i.
And let's take into account,
first of all,
what do we do with dt?
What does dt really mean?
It means this little distance here.
This is what it means.
It really means that little distance.
That becomes epsilon.
dt is replaced by epsilon.
Now,
how about
the action from here to here?
Well,
up on the top,
we wrote
that it is an integral
of that thing called l over there.
So,
we should write l here.
l of
Let's see how I did it.
I want to get it
just the way I did it.
Yeah.
l of what?
l of x sub i.
That's the value of
x at this point over here.
That's replacing
x over here.
Incidentally,
what is x a function of over here?
x is a function.
It's a function of time.
It gets replaced by a function
or a discrete function of i.
Alright,
so l is a function of i.
And what about the velocity?
What are we going to do with the velocity?
x dot.
x dot is the velocity.
What are we going to do with it?
Well,
we're going to replace x dot
by the ratio,
the slope,
basically,
the ratio of delta x
to delta t.
In other words,
we're going to replace it by,
let's see what it is,
let's write it
x sub i plus 1
minus x sub i
over epsilon.
This is the approximation
to the velocity between
i and i plus 1.
I'm now focusing on the interval
between i and i plus 1.
Right over here.
This quantity,
this Lagrangian quantity,
depends on position
and it depends on velocity,
and velocity is being approximated
by the change in position
divided by the time interval.
What do we do with this?
We sum it over all of these little
intervals here.
That's an approximation to the action.
Now we have a function
which is only a function
of some discrete variables,
x sub i,
all the x's.
We've replaced the continuous function
by a function of these heights.
This is an ordinary function now
of these heights.
And we can ask to make it stationary.
How do we make it stationary?
By differentiating with respect to the x i's.
Let me just,
just in case anybody has gotten
confused,
i does not stand
for the direction of space,
it doesn't stand for the particle number,
it just stands for time.
Okay?
Alright,
so let's go to
a particular point over here,
the point i.
And let's ask,
let's differentiate this expression
with respect to x i.
We're changing x i,
keeping everything else
fixed.
Keep everything else fixed,
and we're going to calculate the derivative,
the partial derivative with respect to x i,
moving this up and down,
varying it a little bit,
of this expression.
Now,
it varies for two reasons
when you change x i a little bit.
It varies because x i varies,
but it also varies
because if you keep x i plus one fixed,
and vary x i,
the velocity changes a little bit.
So there's two reasons
why this expression
changes when you change x i a little bit.
We have to take them both into account
to get
the
right thing.
So let's blow up
the region
of interest.
The region of interest,
here's x i
over here,
here's x i plus one
no,
this is t i,
sorry,
no,
this is just i,
sorry.
Here's x i,
here's x i plus one,
and here's x i minus one.
x i minus one.
And this is i minus one.
i plus one.
Why don't I bother drawing
any more than that?
Here's the curve
in here,
I don't want to draw it flat.
Here's the curve in here.
The reason I don't need to
draw the rest of the curve
is because I'm only interested in what happens
when I change x i a little bit,
keeping all the other ones fixed.
So,
the only terms
in this sum
which change
when I change x i a little bit
are these two.
The two neighboring intervals.
If I change x i plus one,
I have to worry about the next one over.
But at the moment,
I'm just writing down
in the action,
if I vary x i a little bit.
I'm differentiating this expression with respect to x i.
So,
let's just focus
on these two terms.
These two terms are
L of
x i
I'm rewriting
what's there.
x i plus one
minus x i over epsilon
plus
L of
x i minus one
x i minus x i minus one
over epsilon.
It should all be multiplied by epsilon,
but that's not going to make any difference.
All multiplied by epsilon.
Epsilon is from here.
Okay,
so I've just selected out
these two terms.
This one depends on x i over here.
This one depends on x i
an interval over.
This one depends on the velocity
between here and here.
This one depends on the velocity between here and here.
Now I want to differentiate
this function with respect
to x i.
This could be
x seven.
i could be seven,
i plus one eight,
and so forth.
Let's differentiate it with respect
to x i.
Okay.
This term depends on x i directly.
This one does not.
It only depends on x i minus one.
So this one we have to
differentiate with respect to x i over here.
That will give us
epsilon times the derivative
of L with respect
to x i.
And this is
x i
and x i
plus one minus x i
over epsilon.
Let's just call this velocity.
velocity
i.
This symbol I'm just
going to call velocity.
It's an approximation to the velocity.
And I'm going to label it as
belonging to the point v i.
Now what about this one over here?
This one does not depend on x i.
This depends on x i minus one.
So when I differentiate it with respect to x i
I don't get anything.
Alright.
What about when I differentiate with respect to x i
from the dependence from here?
What do I get?
Now this one's a little bit easier.
Let's do this one first.
We get
plus epsilon
L of
x i minus one
sorry
We're
differentiating with respect to x i here.
Anybody know what we could do?
Yeah.
V.
Right.
Good.
Partial of L.
With respect to v i
times the change in v i
when I change x i a little bit.
And what is that?
That's one over epsilon.
The change in v i when
I change x i a little bit.
Now what about this one over here?
Same kind of thing.
One over epsilon
derivative of Lagrangian
with respect to the velocity
and the derivative of the velocity
with a minus sign.
Why?
Because when I move v i a little bit
in this term over here
if I,
let's say I increase v i
then the velocity increases here
but it decreases here.
So that means there's a minus sign here
and this is the derivative
of L with respect to v
but at point
i plus one.
This point
is moved forward by one unit
relative to this one over here.
So there are two terms
well three terms,
excuse me.
One of them is just
the derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to position
and the other two
have to do with the derivative
of the Lagrangian with respect to velocity.
But notice that
they're shifted with respect to each other a little bit.
In fact
this is the difference of
two functions at neighboring
points divided by
epsilon
all times
there's an overall epsilon everywhere
that doesn't matter.
What is
the difference of two functions
divided by epsilon and the limit that
epsilon is small?
It's just the derivative.
The derivative with respect to what?
Time.
And
so we can replace
all of this by simply
writing its minus
if you keep track of the signs
derivative with respect to time
of the
derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to the velocity.
So it has two terms
the variation
we can write this now
the variation of the action
when I vary
x i a little bit
has two terms
it's proportional to
d by dt
of the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to the velocity
which is x dot
and there's a minus sign
let's see
maybe this one's the minus sign
plus
derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to x
Okay,
again just to go through it
briefly again
we just
differentiate the Lagrangian with respect to x
that's clearly an obvious thing to do
we want to see how much
this thing changes when we
vary x i a little bit
that's this term
and then there are two terms
coming from the velocity dependence
one
associated
with the interval
in front of that point
and one associated with the interval behind that point
and they come in with opposite sign
because when you move this point
up and down
the velocities in the two terms here differ
by sign
and by velocity
if you move this point up
this velocity increases
and this velocity decreases
that's why there's a minus sign
and that's why there's a derivative with respect to time
alright,
so the general rule
the action principle
is equivalent
you go to each point
you say
the action is really a function
of a whole bunch of discrete points
you apply
the principle of the Lagrangian
principle of differentiating
and setting equal to zero
and you get
you now have an equation
at each time
this equation has to be true
what is the equation?
it has to be equal to zero
differentiating the action with respect to x i
and setting equal to zero
that makes the action stationary
this is the general form
of Lagrange's equations
the Euler-Lagrange equations
let's write them down here
somebody gives you a Lagrangian
you simply spit out the answer
it's a machine
given a Lagrangian,
you spit out
the machine spits out an answer
and the answer is simply a differential equation
d by dt
of partial of L
with respect to
let's call it x dot
is equal
this one came with a minus sign
this one came with a plus sign
so it's just equal to partial of L
with respect to x
that's a general way of
and this is a differential equation
we'll see
we'll work out some examples
this is a differential equation
we'll work out versus
a question
yeah
so the results
that we have
correct me if I'm wrong
it seems like it depends on
that this result is similar
is valid for any function of
x and x dot
is that true?
yeah
we call it Lagrangian
you can call it the distance between two points
you can now take
there's an example up there
in that example
x replaces t
and y replaces x
I'm sorry I did that,
but I did
that basically tells you what the
trajectory of a straight line is,
an equation that has linear solutions,
straight line solutions.
All right,
now,
the question.
I said that this is
an alternative formulation of Newton's equations.
What I meant by that is that we can find
an L such that when you write down the Euler-Lagrange equations,
it is Newton's equation.
I will tell you,
now we're just going to do it.
Now we're just going to do it.
We're going to write down what L is
for a particle moving in a potential energy.
Our potential energy is V of X.
Another thing we need is the kinetic energy.
This is the potential energy,
P.
Kinetic energy.
One-half m,
X dot squared.
Potential energy and kinetic energy.
And now I'll tell you what the Lagrangian is.
The Lagrangian,
which depends on X dot and X,
is just equal to the kinetic energy.
And now we can take a vote,
but I won't.
Should we put in V of X?
No,
I won't.
I want the sub-divide.
I object you to a vote.
The answer is no.
You put in minus V of X.
Now that's odd.
That's weird,
right?
How come it's not the sum of
the kinetic energy plus the potential energy?
Well,
it's just not the energy.
We're looking for something which will have the
property that when we apply the Euler-Lagrange equations,
we get Newton's equations.
The only thing we can do now is to apply
the Euler-Lagrange equation and see that it really is Newton's equation.
Okay.
So what's partial of L with
respect to X dot in this formula?
Partial of L with respect to
X dot is just M X dot,
right?
In fact,
it's the momentum.
And that's a good thing to remember.
That partial of L with respect to
X dot is what we usually call momentum.
That's going to recur and recur and recur.
And it's going to be our general definition of momentum.
We still have to differentiate with respect to time.
So far,
I just wrote partial of
L with respect to X dot.
Now it says differentiate it with respect to time.
So this is going to be X double dot.
Okay.
What about DL by DX?
Here's the X dependence.
DL by DX is minus...
Because of this minus sign,
is equal to minus DV by DX.
Or just ordinary derivative of V with respect to X.
DV by DX.
Well,
if you remember,
this is nothing but Newton's equations.
Equation.
One equation.
Mass times acceleration is equal to minus DV DX,
which we call force.
OK.
So at least in this one example,
we have reduced the problem of making
the action stationary to solving Newton's equations.
They're equivalent.
Okay.
They're completely equivalent.
How about many particles and many coordinates?
If there are many particles and many coordinates,
that means that the X space here is many dimensions.
things coming out of the blackboard,
but the trajectory is still just a curve.
The trajectory is now a
curve through a many dimensional space,
and we have to apply
the same rule to every coordinate,
x,
y,
z,
x of particle 1,
y of particle 7,
and so forth.
We have to apply exactly the same rule.
First of all,
what is the Lagrangian?
I should start with what the Lagrangian is.
The Lagrangian is exactly the same except that
it's a function of all of the coordinates.
I hesitate to write x,
y because I've used that,
I made a mistake.
I should not have used i over here.
That was a bad thing
to do because by doing it,
I used the notation which I'm going to...
i now stands for the
particles and the directions of space.
Okay.
Different i.
We're finished with this i.
We're finished with that one.
We did what we needed with that.
We're finished with it.
Let's erase that blackboard.
i does not stand for discrete time anymore.
It stands for x,
y,
or z.
It stands for particle number 1,
3,
7,
15.
It's all of the coordinates that we're interested in.
The Lagrangian becomes a function of all of the coordinates.
It's a function of all of
the coordinates and all of the velocities.
All of the coordinates and all of the velocities.
And if you go through exactly the same exercise,
you can try it out yourself,
go through exactly
the same exercise,
you find out that at each point of time,
at each interval,
there's a
separate equation for each coordinate.
You want to minimize the
action with respect to each coordinate.
And so all that happens is you
have a separate equation for each i.
You have a Lagrangian,
which depends on all of the
coordinates and all of the velocities,
and the equations,
the Euler-Lagrange equations,
are simply one equation for each coordinate.
All right,
so let's go through what the
construction is then for many particles.
If you have many particles,
you do exactly the same thing.
Potential energy is v of xi.
Kinetic energy is the sum over all the i's.
m xi.
mv squared.
You do exactly the same thing,
and what do you get?
You get m x sub i double dot,
and what happens to dv by dx?
It becomes the partial derivative
of V with respect to xi.
When you vary things with respect to xi,
you get things called invi.
coming from the velocities and things coming
from the explicit dependence of v on xi.
And what is that?
That's just ma is equal
to the ith component of force.
Now you can see why
this had to be minus here.
If I would have made it plus,
I would have
gotten instead of Newton's equation,
I would have gotten mass times acceleration is minus
the force,
and then I'd have to go back and say,
look,
I have to redefine what I mean
by force,
I have to redefine what I mean by potential energy,
but with the definitions
we've used up till now,
the Lagrangian is kinetic energy minus potential energy,
and
that gives you Newton's equations as
the Euler-Lagrange equations for the action principle.
Now that's a lot of stuff,
that's a lot of stuff and it's abstract.
Is it?
Yeah.
So it seems like the Lagrangian and the
action principle comes from a kind of working back
from the answer.
Like we want to use Kagan's
variations and we still need a functional
that's equivalent to Newton's law.
Is that the way to look at it?
No.
No,
it's not the way we
would want to look at it.
We would want to think about it differently.
What we want to think is that the specification
of a Lagrangian is a function of the momentum
of the energy.
So the Lagrangian is an extremely neat packaging
of the laws of physics for a particular system.
That the Lagrangian,
one function of all of the coordinates,
one function of all the coordinates,
which is built out of the kinetic and potential energy,
but one function packages all of the
laws of physics for that system.
So really I...
No.
And you have to think about it the other way.
The given is the Lagrangian.
It's the
way physical problems are packaged and
the calculation calculates for you the equations
of motion from the Lagrangian.
So physicists usually think about the Lagrangian as given
and whenever a new law of physics
of some kind is being speculated about,
it's never
speculated about by the academic.
writing down the equations of motion.
You speculate because it's more convenient,
it's simpler,
there are fewer unknowns,
you speculate about what the form of the
action is.
So it's one function that packages
the entire laws of physics for
that particular system.
Okay,
that's good.
That's one reason why it's a useful
thing,
because it packages things simply.
The other reason is because it's an
extremely good tool for changing variables,
for changing coordinates.
We
have written down the laws of scones.
In Cartesian coordinates we can
write them down on polar coordinates,
we could
write them down in your favorite coordinates.
We've written them down in
coordinates that we've imagined to be standing still.
We could try writing them
down in coordinates which are moving,
or
expanding.
We can write them down in
coordinates that we've imagined to be
accelerating or rotating,
we'll do that in a minute.
It's complicated to rewrite all of Newton's equations
directly in,
for example,
rotating or other kinds of coordinates.
It is a lot easier
to rewrite the Lagrangian or the action
in an arbitrary coordinate system
and then
once you have the Lagrangian
you can construct the equations of motion.
The point is that the action principle
is really a statement that doesn't
depend on the coordinates you use.
If I tell you that
the shortest distance between here and here
is a straight line,
that doesn't depend on what coordinates
I use on the table here.
I could use Cartesian coordinates,
I could use polar coordinates,
curvilinear coordinates of all kinds.
The physical fact that it's a straight line
is independent of the coordinates.
And the physical fact that the straight line
is the shortest distance between the two points
does not depend on the coordinates.
So when I say
a straight line
is the shortest distance between two points,
that's true in any coordinate system.
The action principle in the same way
is true in any coordinate system.
If you change coordinates,
the form of the equations of motion change,
but the actual value of the Lagrangian doesn't.
So we're going to do some examples of that type.
I don't know,
maybe we're up to that now.
So it's an extremely convenient tool
for changing coordinates.
Let me give you the first example.
The first example is taking
a simple particle and...
This is a terribly complicated problem,
in fact.
If you tried to do it directly,
taking Newton's equations,
or even just,
forget Newton's equations,
just the equation without any force,
just forget forces,
just the equation for a particle moving
in a straight line.
And what I'm interested in now
is two frames of reference,
one is a stationary frame of reference,
an inertial frame of reference,
and in this frame of reference,
Newton's equations apply.
And in fact,
we're going to set force equal to zero,
so that just says mass times acceleration equals zero,
mass times y double dot is equal to zero.
It's a two-dimensional problem.
The other coordinate system,
which I'll draw in red,
looks like this.
Now that's pretty easy,
except we're going to make it harder.
We're going to make it harder
by making the red coordinates rotate with time.
All right?
And ask,
in other words,
if physics is seen by somebody standing on a carousel,
what do the laws of physics look like?
In particular,
the simplest of all laws of physics,
what does it look like,
and how do we describe it
from the viewpoint of a turntable or a carousel?
You might have a little bit of fun
trying to work it out directly
without ever having heard of the Lagrangian,
and then try it with the Lagrangian,
and I think you'll find that the Lagrangian
is the fast way to do it.
Okay.
The blue coordinate system
is described by x,
little x and little y.
The red coordinate system
is described by big X and big Y.
And the red coordinate system
is described by a little x and little y.
Can I prove that?
No.
You're supposed to laugh at that.
Okay.
The angle between the x-axis is theta,
but theta depends on time.
In particular,
theta is going to depend on time
like omega t.
In other words,
it's a uniformly rotating coordinate system.
If you can set omega t equal to theta,
if you want,
temporarily.
And now the question is,
what is the coordinate transformation
between the big coordinates
and the little coordinates?
I'll let you work that out.
I'm going to give you the answer.
The answer is little x,
I'm going to write little x and little y
in terms of big X and big Y.
Little x is equal to big X
times cosine of the angle,
cosine omega t,
plus big Y times sine omega t.
How about little y?
Anybody want to take a shot at it?
Minus X sine omega t.
Plus Y cosine.
Plus Y cosine of omega t.
That's correct.
You can check this.
You have to sit down
and do a little bit of coordinate change.
This doesn't depend on the fact
that the coordinate system is rotating.
If you just call omega t theta,
you'll see that this,
and experiment around with it,
you'll find out that this is the way
two-dimensional coordinates change
if you rotate by angle theta.
All right,
now here's what we know.
We know in the little coordinate system,
let's give them names.
Oh,
let's not.
In the stationary coordinate system,
the non-rotating coordinate system,
Newton's equations and Newton's laws
are the right laws,
and we can summarize that
by writing a Lagrangian.
The Lagrangian in action.
Integral L d t with L equaling.
Little one half m,
m over two,
x dot squared,
little x dot squared,
plus y dot squared.
No potential energy.
The simplest thing,
with no potential energy at all,
if we apply the Euler-Lagrange equations to this,
we'll just get m x
double dot is equal to zero
from the left-hand side.
m x double dot is equal to zero.
No potential energy,
so there's no right-hand side at all.
Same thing for y,
and that just tells us
that things move without exception.
So we have to do
How do we work it out
in the big coordinates?
Well,
we say,
all we have to do,
the principle is the same,
the principle is the principle of least action,
but all we have to do is rewrite the action
or the Lagrangian
in terms of big x's and big y's.
That's not hard.
It looks much harder than it is,
but it's easy to do.
All we have to do is figure out
what x dot and y dot are,
and plug them into here.
So I'll write down the answers for you.
You can check them.
Little x dot is equal,
we're just going to differentiate this
with respect to time.
It's big x dot times cosine omega t.
Oh,
it's going to take more room.
All right,
let's do it.
Cosine omega t,
and now we have to differentiate the sine.
Sine also depends on time.
So what's the derivative of this term?
Am I making a mistake?
Oh,
sorry,
sorry.
We're doing this one.
Yeah.
We need a factor of omega.
Yep,
we need a factor of omega,
omega x,
times the derivative of the cosine,
which is sine omega t.
I think I have the sine of,
here's the sine,
right?
Good.
Now we have to differentiate this,
or it's plus y dot sine omega t,
and then plus omega y cosine omega t.
Straightforward differentiation of x
with respect to t.
You do the same with y.
You do the same with y,
and then you calculate x
dot squared plus y dot squared.
It looks a bit messy,
but it's really very simple.
It takes just a little,
essentially by inspection,
and I will tell you what it is.
We're rewriting the Lagrangian
in terms of the big coordinates.
You have to use over and over again
cosine squared plus sine squared is one.
For example,
well,
let's just see what's in y here.
There's going to be another term in y,
in y dot,
I'm not going to write it all down.
I'm just going to write one term.
y dot is going to have
minus x dot sine omega t,
right?
Plus all sorts of other stuff.
What happens when I square this one,
sorry,
when I square this x
dot squared plus y dot squared,
little x dot squared plus y dot squared,
I'm going to get big x dot squared cosine squared
and big x dot squared sine squared.
That adds to one.
So I can be pretty sure there's going to be
an m over two times big x dot squared.
Likewise,
when I square y,
where's y dot?
When I square y dot squared,
I'll also get a big y dot squared.
And both of these will multiply
sine squared plus cosine squared,
which is one.
Now,
the next type of term which appears,
will be what happens when
I square this term over here.
This is going to have an omega squared,
an x squared,
and a sine squared omega t.
I will also find in here,
an omega squared x squared cosine squared omega t.
Just spend a few minutes with it.
So what I'm going to find is,
I think it's plus omega squared.
What you get is two dot,
well,
let's see,
this x dot by this y over here,
cross terms with x dots and y's,
and y dots and x's.
The last term that you get,
and that only has one power of omega in it.
So that's,
I think,
plus or minus,
let me just see what the sine is.
Plus,
omega times x dot y minus y dot x.
All the variables on the side are the rotating coordinates.
That's what you get.
As I said,
it looks much harder than it is.
I don't want to go through the algebra,
because I make algebra mistakes all over the place,
but this is what you get.
No sines and cosines left over.
They all come in the pattern,
sums of squares,
or they just cancel.
Okay.
So this is what you get.
Now,
what do you do with it?
You say,
principle of least action.
We think of this as the Lagrangian.
The rule is,
principle of least action,
and so we apply the Euler-Lagrange equations to it.
Let's work out the Euler-Lagrange equation for x.
I think I can,
well,
let's put this up.
Put this up,
pull this down.
And how does this work out?
If there's a combination of .
There's something wrong.
Yeah,
everything's capitalized,
sorry.
Sorry,
I see.
Before we do the equation,
let's just look at this for a minute.
First of all,
if omega is zero,
if the coordinates are not rotating at all,
omega equals zero,
this just looks like the good
old Lagrangian for x and y.
And what are we going to get?
We're going to get that things move
in straight lines in the capital XY coordinates.
Of course they are,
if the coordinate system is not rotating.
Now let's forget for a moment this
term over here and look at this term.
This has the look of a particular coordinate system.
It's a potential energy.
It's a function of x and y.
Remember what we normally would write.
We would normally write that the
Lagrangian is equal to t minus v.
So this has the look of a
potential energy where the potential energy here,
it's a fictitious,
but you can call it fictitious if you want,
call it a fictitious potential energy,
a fictitious potential energy,
v fictitious,
which is equal,
to minus omega squared m over two,
x squared plus y squared,
capital x squared and y squared,
minus,
because the Lagrangian always has t minus v.
What would a potential energy like this
do to a particle in xy space?
It's a circle.
There's a radius there,
looks like a radius.
It's a potential energy which depends
on the square of the triangle.
It's a distance from the origin.
Which way is the force point?
Outward.
Radially outward.
You have a potential energy
which falls off in any direction,
x squared plus y squared is r squared.
The potential energy is negative.
That means you're on the top
of a hill at the origin.
If you're at the origin,
you're at the top of a hill,
and the top of the hill is falling off quadratically.
What is this?
It's a centrifugal force.
If you're on a rotating carousel,
and you put a particle down on the floor,
it'll get pushed out toward the edge by centrifugal force.
So this is just centrifugal force.
This one is Coriolis force.
It's Coriolis force,
and notice it's a new
kind of term in the Lagrangian.
It's a new kind of term
which depends both on coordinates and velocities.
Linear in velocities and coordinates.
It's something new.
It leads to a kind of force.
Whenever you have a situation like this,
it leads to a kind of
force which is called a velocity-dependent force.
So to see how it works,
what we want to do
is write out the Euler-Lagrange equations.
Let's write out the Euler-Lagrange equation for x.
We start with partial of
L with respect to x dot.
What is that?
mx dot,
what we usually call momentum,
but now there's another term.
It's m omega over 2 times y.
Derivative of L with respect to x dot.
So let's add that in.
Plus m omega over 2 times y,
right?
Did I get that right?
Now what are we supposed to do with this?
We're supposed to take d by dt of it.
What does that give us?
mx double dot plus y dot...
And what does that equal?
It equals the derivative of
the Lagrangean with respect to x.
Does it depend on x?
Yeah,
you bet.
It depends on x over here.
So there's an omega squared m times x...
and it depends on x over here.
That's minus m omega over two times y dot,
plus or minus.
Oh,
sorry.
We're supposed to set this equal to this,
right?
Yeah.
Partial of L with respect to x dot
equals partial of L with respect to x,
equals.
And what's the other term?
The other term should be plus
m omega over two y dot.
Comes from here.
Differentiating with respect to x gives us
m omega over two times y dot.
Now the sine,
the sine.
Do I have a sine mistake?
Yes,
I have a sine mistake.
Over here.
Coming from this sine over here.
Now this doesn't look too familiar,
but I can make it look more familiar by saying,
look,
this is what I call acceleration,
and this is m a.
Let's put everything on the other side.
Let's put everything on the other
side and call it the fictitious force.
What does the fictitious force have?
It has omega.
Omega squared m times x.
What is that?
This is the x component of acceleration.
That's a centrifugal force.
It's a centrifugal force.
Centrifugal force,
the component of it is proportional to x.
The x component of it is proportional to x.
What about the other term?
The other term,
they add,
minus,
minus m omega y dot.
And now we have something truly new.
We have a force on
the right-hand side which is proportional,
it's the x component of force,
which is proportional to the y component of velocity.
Or minus the y component of velocity.
It's a velocity-dependent force.
It's called Coriolis force.
I'm not going to go
into why hurricanes are so important.
I'm going to go into why planes work
and to show you how the details are just,
what I'm mainly interested in is showing you how
the action principle makes calculations like this easy and fast.
What about the y component of equation?
It's m a sub y or m a y
double dot is equal to omega squared m times y.
This is capital Y.
Capital Y.
And then plus m omega y.
And then we have a x-dot.
So there's an effective force seen on
the rotating turntable or on the carousel,
which is centrifugal force.
It looks sort of like a garden-variety potential energy.
Garden-variety potential energy,
except it's pushing outward.
And then a velocity-dependent force.
A new thing,
a new kind of thing.
We might not have guessed the term,
but this is interesting.
it very easily.
Well,
we might have or we might not have,
but it's packaged extremely
neatly in the action principle.
Would this work for arbitrarily curved coordinates?
Yes.
For any coordinates.
And not only can the coordinates be curved,
but they can
be time dependent.
Here these coordinates were not only curved,
but they were also time
dependent.
Let's do another simple example.
This is a simpler example.
Polar coordinates,
just ordinary polar coordinates,
not time dependent,
not moving,
ordinary polar coordinates.
And work out the equations of motion for
an ordinary particle with a potential which depends
on radius,
let's say.
Okay.
So what's our coordinates?
Now our coordinates are just,
this is x and this is y,
this is
r,
and this is theta.
Okay.
I want to write down the one
half m x dot squared plus y dot
squared.
But I want to write it
in terms of r and theta.
Okay.
That's easy.
You just write
that x,
now theta is not changing with time.
Theta is now the theta coordinate of the particle.
It is changing with time.
If the particle moves,
theta changes with time.
Okay.
And
so does r.
But x is equal to r cosine theta,
y is equal to r sine theta.
We can take the
time derivative of x,
the time derivative of y.
Square them and add them together.
Yeah,
what do we get?
This is equal.
I'll tell you what
it is.
It's one half m times r dot squared.
That's the term coming from r.
And then there's
a term coming from theta and it happens
to be plus r squared theta dot squared.
Now as
I said,
you get this simply by
differentiating x with respect to time.
X dot squared,
r squared.
for example,
will be r dot cosine theta plus
r minus r sine theta theta dot.
y dot will be r dot sine
theta plus r cosine theta theta dot.
Let's look at it,
x dot squared plus y dot squared.
x dot squared will have r dot squared times
cosine theta plus cosine squared plus sine squared,
so that'll be your r dot
squared.
It'll also have r squared sine squared,
cosine squared,
and theta dot
squared.
That's this term here.
What about the cross terms?
We have this times
this and this times this in a cancel.
So this is
then going to be the какимokias.
Now that this is the other way around,
the last
the Lagrangian and polar coordinates.
If I want to add a potential energy,
let's
add a potential energy,
that will be minus V of R.
I'm taking the case now
where the potential energy depends
on distance from the origin.
It could
depend on theta too,
but for our purposes now
it's called a central force problem.
The central force problem,
the potential energy only depends on distance from the
origin,
and there it is.
Now we can write down the Euler-Lagrange equations very
simply.
Okay,
let's fool,
the Euler-Lagrange equations are now for R and theta.
R and
theta are our new variables.
So what is the Euler-Lagrange equation for R?
You
start with partial of L with respect to R dot.
R is replacing one of the X's,
and
that's a
equation for R dot.
R is replacing one of the X's,
and that's a
equation for R dot.
Sorry,
there's an M here,
isn't there?
That's M R dot,
and
that's it,
right?
That's partial of L with respect to R dot.
We have to
differentiate this with respect to time.
That gives us M R double dot.
What is that?
That's the,
the radial acceleration,
and it is equal to the sum of two terms.
The
first term is the derivative of Lagrangian with respect to,
to
to r contains,
looks like it's equal to m r theta dot squared,
and then from here,
minus
dv by dr,
derivative of v with respect to r.
What do we have here?
First of all,
you
might have guessed this in the first place.
This is the r component of force.
r component
of acceleration,
r component of force.
What is this thing over here?
It's again a centrifugal
force.
It's a centrifugal force,
not because the coordinates are rotating,
but because
the particle itself may be changing theta.
As the particle changes,
as the particle is
moving around,
whipping around,
it also experiences a force
outward proportional to theta dot
squared.
So that's the r equation.
What about the theta equation?
The theta,
this is of
course,
tells you how r changes with time,
but you have to know what theta dot,
you have
to know what theta is doing.
So the question is,
what is this?
This is the r component
of force.
The question then is,
what is theta doing?
To find what theta is doing,
you work
out the Lagrange equations for theta.
So that's d by dt of
partial of l with respect to theta
dot.
That's the left-hand side.
And what does that give?
That gives m r squared theta dot,
right?
d by dt of m r squared theta dot.
And what's it equal to?
d l by d theta.
That's the other part of the Euler-Lagrange equation.
The other half of the Euler-Lagrange
equation is the l by d coordinate.
Well,
what is the
l by d theta?
l doesn't depend on theta.
It depends on theta dot,
but it doesn't depend
on theta.
So it's just what?
Zero.
Now that's very interesting.
Look what it says.
It says,
let's erase this over here.
d by dt of m r
squared theta dot is equal to zero.
This
says something is conserved.
Here's the conserved quantity right here.
Angular momentum.
Angular
momentum.
m r squared theta dot.
Its derivative is zero.
That's the conservation of angular
momentum.
What did it follow from?
It followed from a moment ago.
It followed from a moment
ago.
When it was a moment ago,
it followed from a moment ago.
So it followed from a moment
That's what it's doing now.
It's doing other things,
assuming that v did not depend on
theta.
If v had depended on theta,
we would have gotten another term on the right hand
side here.
So if v only depends on radial distance,
then there's a conservation law.
And this is very general.
If you have a Lagrangian that
doesn't depend on a coordinate for one
reason or another,
then there will always be a conservation law.
We'll come back to
that.
That's going to be a very important theme,
probably next time.
Do we do that?
Yeah,
if you have a Lagrangian that
doesn't depend explicitly on a coordinate,
then there will be a conservation law,
and it'll be a conservation of this quantity right here.
Okay?
We're going to come back to that.
Incidentally,
there's a name for coordinates
which don't appear in the Lagrangian.
It's a historical name.
They're called cyclic coordinates,
and there's nothing cyclic about them.
Absolutely nothing cyclic about them.
They're called cyclic coordinates if they
don't appear directly in the Lagrangian.
And theta is a cyclic coordinate.
Now,
of course,
theta happens to be cyclic.
It's an angle.
But you can have all kinds of
coordinates that aren't angles that can be cyclic.
Okay.
It's a bad name,
but it is the name that goes with them.
Whenever there's a cyclic coordinate,
there is a conservation law,
and the conservation law happens
just because there's no right-hand side.
There's a d by dt
of something with no right-hand side,
and so it's conserved.
The thing which is conserved?
Partial of L with respect to velocity.
Okay,
but now that,
just to go a little bit further,
we can now say,
look,
I can't tell you what the angular momentum is.
The angular momentum is determined by initial conditions.
Whatever the initial condition was,
it determined some angular momentum.
Angular momentum is usually called L.
But whatever the initial condition was,
it determines some angular momentum.
Whatever it is,
it doesn't change with time.
So this tells us then,
sorry,
the angular momentum is equal to a constant L.
It doesn't change with time.
So once you know it,
you know it.
The initial condition tells you what it is.
Whatever it was to start with,
it stays that way.
And so what it tells you is that
theta dot is equal to L over L.
Over m r squared.
That's what it tells you.
We can plug it into here.
I'll let you do that.
Just plug into this equation here.
Theta dot equals this.
And you get an equation just for r.
You've figured out what theta is doing.
The conservation law has told you what theta is doing.
And now you can plug it back into here.
And you can plug it
back into the equation for r.
Okay,
the central points here.
What are they?
The central points are,
number one,
Lagrangians package problems in a
simple and minimal kind of way.
One function of all the coordinates and velocities
completely determines all of the equations of motion.
Number two,
the Euler-Lagrange equations are a very,
very efficient tool for changing coordinates.
One way of saying it is the
Euler-Lagrange equations are invariant on the coordinate.
They take the same form in every coordinate system.
If it's minimum,
it's minimum.
And it doesn't matter what coordinates you use.
So they're an efficient tool for changing coordinates.
And number three,
the idea of a conservation law coming when
a certain coordinate doesn't appear in the Lagrangian.
Okay,
do we have any questions?
There must be many.
Or exhausting.
Is there another motivation or meaning for the
Lagrangian that captures some aspect of the system?
Is there another?
Try a little bit harder.
Well,
is there an independent reason why
you would arrive at the Lagrangian?
Other than that,
it's the right thing to put in?
Oh,
yes.
It's called quantum mechanics.
But for us now,
it's simply a fact of experience.
Not a fact of experience of
pushing things around and so forth.
I'm talking about the experience of basically a hundred
years of classical physics in the 19th century between the,
well,
between the end of the 17th century
and the later part of the mid-19th century.
That many laws of physics,
it was realized,
could be cast in this form.
Not just particles moving around,
incidentally.
Waves,
electromagnetic fields,
everything you can think of is cast in this form.
So,
as I said,
a matter of experience,
meaning the experience of a physicist for a
hundred years or more than a hundred years,
eventually led to this framework.
And there are no examples,
there are no known examples of laws
of physics that don't fall into this framework.
If this was all there was to it,
we would be puzzled.
Why is this true?
The answer is that it's a deep
aspect of quantum mechanics that leads to it,
but that's for a later time.
Okay.
Yeah.
In the Lagrangian you have in
the right-hand side of the board,
can you resolve the energy there
into kinetic energy plus some other energy?
Potential energy?
Because it looks like you
have that last term as neither.
Yeah,
ignore it.
That's right.
Okay.
We need a deeper concept of energy.
The deeper concept of energy is called the Hamiltonian.
And we will come to it.
This is the Lagrangian form of the equations.
But I will tell you anyway what the energy is.
The energy is just the sum of these two.
This does not contribute to the energy.
Exercise.
Prove that the sum of these two is conserved.
Take the equations of motion and prove that
the sum of these two is conserved with time.
I don't want to do it now because we're going to do it
in a uniform way when we study the Hamiltonian formulation of classical mechanics.
But it's a good question.
What happened to energy?
Answer,
this one doesn't contribute to energy at all.
All right.
Question.
If you know you're describing
an object curving through a trajectory,
what if that curvature is caused by a gravitational field?
Yeah.
Well,
first of all,
we're not thinking about general relativity.
True.
Right.
If we want to do,
all right,
gravity is all set up for us here.
All we have to do is remember
what V is for a gravitational field.
What is a gravitational field of a massive object?
M.
Little m,
the mass of the object,
times big M,
the mass of the gravitating center,
times G over R.
So that's for general relativity.
No,
but we're not doing general relativity at the moment.
General relativity is a long way down the line.
So,
excuse me,
those energy terms,
you stated earlier they're from fictitious forces.
So are,
no,
that's the connection.
So are those fictitious energies?
Look,
fictitious is a funny word.
Well,
no,
because.
Because we're talking about you're on
the merry-go-round and you're seeing something.
Yeah.
And by definition,
in the first coordinate system,
you said no forces.
Right.
Okay.
But from a merry-go-round,
it looks like there are forces.
Right.
So then you would back calculate and
it would look like there were energies.
Right.
So there are forces.
The person on the rotating frame of
reference will say in every possible respect,
this is a potential energy and that's a.
So the answer.
Okay.
The answer is that energy is not something
which is invariant under coordinate transformations in general.
In particular,
it's not invariant
under time-dependent coordinate transformations.
Given a coordinate set,
given this problem,
there is a conserved energy,
but it is not the same energy that
the other fellow in the rest frame said.
Actually,
it is.
I take that back.
It is the same energy,
isn't it?
Right.
Remember what this came from?
Let's see.
Where did it come from?
No.
It's not the same energy.
Yes.
No.
No,
not quite.
it's not.
Yeah.
That's right.
It could be.
You could have a particle at rest.
Let's see.
What do we want to do?
A particle at rest.
Yes.
in the rotating frame.
Now it won't stay at rest in the rotating frame,
but somebody could
be holding it.
If they were holding it,
it would have no kinetic energy.
Well,
no,
no.
The particles at rest at the stationary frame,
how does it look from the rotating
frame?
Oh,
it moves around in a circle.
Right.
It moves around in a circle.
So it looks like it has kinetic energy.
It looks like it has kinetic energy,
right.
Right.
But it also has some centripetal
energy.
And it has some centripetal energy also.
All of it.
Yes.
But that term gives it no energy.
There's no energy there.
Yeah,
so energy is another
subject.
Energy is not a terribly
natural object in the Lagrangian formulation.
It's
a very natural object in the Hamiltonian formulation.
We will come to it.
Anything else?
A question?
And where you have that,
the rightmost term,
x dot,
the perpendicular term,
if I
can call it that.
Yeah.
Up in here on the left.
No,
here,
right.
Sure.
On the red cord that's up there,
I was wondering if,
I was trying to figure out
how to draw using the red x-axis
that component from this point of view.
I don't know how
to draw that.
Right.
So let's draw the red axis of the
stationary as if we were in the red coordinate
frame.
And you want to know what
that final force or perpendicular component.
It's going
to be proportional to y dot.
Right.
Whatever it is,
this is,
all right.
Where is the y dot?
Where is it?
Where is the force?
The force is,
what was the x component of force?
Well,
it was proportional to y dot.
It was some coefficient.
And the x component,
and the
y component of force was proportional to minus x dot.
Yeah,
there's an omega there,
probably an m,
but the important thing was the y dot and
the x dot.
All right.
So the first thing is,
you want to know what the y dot is.
And you
got to draw it like this.
Now,
what it's actually performing,
is a vector of some Trajectory 3,
an over B
vector after some intervalks.
And the labor is going to be a constant.
It will move as
This is where we got the F of x,
too.
I'm going to get the F of x.
A step wind down,
and then it launches a little Hudun's force,
and then it into a
tricolor.
force is perpendicular to it.
It's proportional to the magnitude of the velocity.
That tells
you a lot,
there's not that much more to know.
It's proportional to the magnitude of the
velocity.
Let's go back,
take this away.
So it's perpendicular to the velocity,
proportional
to the magnitude of the velocity,
and proportional to the angular velocity of the coordinate
system.
Thank you.
So all this discussion about energy,
what thing,
when you compute
the Lagrangian,
you're doing in an inertial frame,
right?
Well,
you probably wouldn't
start out in a rotating frame,
right,
you probably wouldn't.
But I think the lesson
here is that not so much that you
start with a form of the equations of motion,
but you
got from somewheres.
You got from somewheres and here is
how to transform it from one coordinate
system to another.
Right?
But yeah,
sure.
Typically for a problem involving particles
like this,
you might say,
look,
we know the answer in the inertial frame.
But I think you wouldn't,
you wouldn't write down a Lagrangian as,
I mean this seems obvious,
but as m over two big
X dot squared plus Y dot squared,
just a priori,
because you have,
kinetic energy is in an inertial frame of reference,
right?
Right.
Yeah.
No,
the rule is,
Newton's rule is that in an inertial frame,
the laws of motion are Newton's equations,
which translates into the statement
that in an inertial frame,
this is the form of the Lagrangian.
Right.
Incidentally,
this kind of term here is
not particularly unique to Coriolis force.
You know any place else where
a similar term like that occurs?
Charged particle in a magnetic field.
Right.
For a charged particle in a magnetic field,
you would have the charge of the
particle and the magnitude of the magnetic field.
In particular,
if you had a magnetic field pointing into the blackboard,
or out of the blackboard,
either way,
charged particle of charge E,
magnetic field B,
uniform magnetic field,
this would be the form of the Lagrangian.
Are there any constraints on what kind of
function can be a Lagrangian other than smoothness?
There are.
And we'll come to that.
But at the moment,
I haven't...
I haven't told you anything that would make you
to suggest there are certain kinds of constraints.
But the answer is yes.
Incidentally,
one thing.
An exercise is to take those equations of motion.
I lost them.
Where are they?
They are of the form X
double dot is equal to omega...
What is it?
Omega squared X plus Y dot...
I'm leaving out masses.
Y double dot is equal to omega here.
Omega squared Y minus omega X dot...
something like that.
Can you prove that one of the trajectories
of the system is just moving in a circle
about the origin?
It better be,
because that's just the
original particle standing still somewhere.
Moving in a circle would be
what the person on the carousel sees.
You should be able to see that that...
that that...
that gives rise to a
particle that moves in a circle.
Once you know that,
then you should know that particles
in a magnetic field move in circles,
because the equations are exactly the same.
Would it remain in the same circle
or would it tend to go out?
No,
it leaves in the same circle.
It leaves in the circle.
では
There are solutions of the equations
where it just stays in circles.
Of course,
you can also have it going out and going out.
Without this term,
it wouldn't move out.
This term is so important.
A divergence though.
A charged particle
moving in a circle.
In a magnetic field.
Let's just say some force is
making it move in a circle.
I remember a long,
long time ago,
something about physics says that it's
that's unstable.
It's going to radiate energy and collapse.
These are the equations
without taking into account radiation.
Radiation is another story.
No other questions?
Where do we get hurricanes?
They're fictitious.
Coriolis,
of course,
I'm told is very important today.
Are there any meteorologists here?
The geological science.
Can you explain that?
No,
I can't.
So this framework is thought to cover everything,
correct?
Everything.
Classical.
But an analogous framework would be
thought to cover everything else as well.
Everything that we know about,
yes.
So if somebody came across some principle of
physics that we were not able to cast into
this lagoon,
what would that be?
Well,
that would be like a revelation.
Absolutely.
Right.
Because it comes from quantum physics and that can't be.
Now,
there are phenomena which look like they
come from equations which are different than this.
For example,
just the phenomena of a
particle moving through a viscous fluid.
But the reason why these equations don't look like the
right equations is because you're ignoring the fact that they're not.
The degrees of freedom of
all the molecules and everything else,
as far as we know,
and
we certainly know about molecules and
atoms and all that sort of stuff,
everything in
nature,
when everything is taken into account,
falls into this pattern.
General relativity,
Maxwell's electrodynamics,
the standard model of particle physics.
And,
you know,
these days when a particle physicist is,
or a particle,
any kind of physicist,
is interested in trying out new laws.
Right.
The laws of physics,
trying out new equations and so forth,
the usual pattern is to write down a Lagrangian.
Is to write down a Lagrangian
and then from that derive the equations.
Now,
that's not to say someday
somebody may not discover something else.
It looks unlikely,
but at the moment the action principle is extremely general.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.