Stanford University.
We're actually moving along rather nicely,
I think.
We are getting to the point
where we have covered the absolute,
absolute,
absolute minimum of what you
need to know to go on.
But still,
we're going to learn some more about classical mechanics and
probably a good deal more.
All right,
if there's no other questions,
well,
we still have a minute or two.
So I won't start for
another minute with a formal lecture.
Yes,
sir.
I think there's a pretty good textbook by Griffiths.
Isn't there on classical mechanics?
Griffiths,
David Griffiths.
Yeah,
there's the classic book that I learned out of
50 years ago or more,
yeah,
more than 50 years ago.
Herbert Goldstein,
classical mechanics.
He's not even a physicist,
he was an engineer,
I think a chemical engineer or
something,
and decided to write a book about classical mechanics.
And it's been the gold standard ever since.
Goldstein.
variational mechanics or whatever it is.
Yeah,
there's a book by Langsos on variational principles.
Yeah.
I think,
how do you say it,
Langsos,
I don't know.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Well,
look,
this is a good,
all right,
look,
we have this group that sort of acts as a,
not as a blog,
what would you call it,
just a group.
Somebody,
whoever wants,
put out some suggestions for some books.
My problem is I don't read,
I don't know how to read.
So I don't read very much.
I can write beautifully,
but I can't read.
No,
that's not true.
I read a lot.
But I'm always the wrong
person to ask for literature surveys.
I almost never know.
That's why,
it's easier for me to write a textbook than
it is for me to go to the library
and find one.
That's why I do it.
Okay.
Shall we begin or does
somebody else have a physics question?
Politics question.
I don't know anything.
No politics.
What's that?
Is the neutrino issue resolved?
No,
it's not resolved.
I think people are starting to
get some idea that it has,
you know,
they don't see a neutrino
go past them over here and then
over here see a neutrino go past them.
There's an accelerator beam,
the accelerator beam is a pulse beam,
protons come and the
pulse has a certain shape.
The pulse shape is a pulse.
The pulse shape is,
or the width of the pulse of
protons coming is much broader in time
than the discrepancy.
Yeah,
so they really have to study the
shape of these things and so forth.
And there's some questions about whether they,
I certainly wouldn't say whether they know
what they're doing.
I don't think that's the issue,
but you know,
whether they know what they're doing when
it comes to.
The exact shape of the pulse and when the,
it's not the shape of the pulse,
the pulse
they know.
But I think one of the questions
that I understand is the pulse comes,
it heats the target,
the
target gets hot,
the next piece of the pulse
comes and it hits a hot target.
The hot target I guess
is full of things with velocity.
I'm not sure if the point is that the
velocity of the target gets imprinted on the pulse
and distorts the pulse.
Anyway,
I don't know.
What's that?
No,
no,
wait,
yeah,
okay.
So I heard from my student about this.
He didn't know what it was about.
So we sat down and did a little calculation.
It's not,
it's not a question of specialization.
It's not a question of specialization.
It's a question of the partial relativity.
Are you interested in what the,
what this Dutchman said?
I mean it's probably,
it's almost certainly not the solution of the problem.
I don't think these people made a really dumb GPS.
They have real experts.
Okay.
So here's what the Dutchman said.
He,
Dutchman is not being used in a derogatory sense.
It wasn't.
The Hollander.
And he's.
He's a smart guy,
I mean it was a smart point,
but he said there's a satellite,
the satellite
beams the signals back and forth.
Over here we have the source,
which is called CERN.
Over here we have the target,
which is called the Grand Sasso Mine.
And in fact,
this is only about 500 miles.
On the other hand,
the satellite is way up there someplace,
but nevertheless I'm going
to draw it over here.
And he said,
well,
if you're in the rest frame of the satellite,
the satellite's moving.
Satellite's moving with a pretty significant velocity.
It's about 22,000 kilometers high.
It's moving with whatever velocity is
appropriate for it up at that height.
It's not in geosynchronous orbit,
so it is moving relative to the Earth.
And what he said was,
well,
this is the picture you draw if
you think the satellite was standing still,
and there's
the target.
A light pulse goes from here to here.
He said,
during the time that the light pulse moves,
the target moves to about over here.
Incidentally,
I don't know exactly what he said.
I did read the paper,
but his formulas were the same as mine,
so I think he must have
been saying the same thing.
And he said,
during that period,
So really the target was over here not over here
And so the time delay for the signal to get
from here to here is really a little bit shorter
by an easily computable amount
and the amount is about 15 nanoseconds
He I think correctly points out that there's another effect
from this end over here signal goes out from here
It's not really a signal
going this way in this way
But I think you can think of it
as a signal going from here to here
They said well for the signal to have gotten
to here had to have started a little bit earlier
So you get you get two effects in the time
of flight of the of the signal from source to
to target
each one
Each discrepancy or each
difference was about 15 nanoseconds.
I worked that out.
That's right and
and and
Therefore altogether you get 30
nanoseconds and then he said well
Just maybe they did this twice.
They did made the error twice
I do not understand why he
thinks they made the error twice
I don't know and so it
could all add up to 60 nanoseconds,
which is the right discrepancy
I would be stunned if they made this mistake,
but I
They didn't make that mistake
What's that
I'm sure that's accounted for
I mean exactly
position error will be already 5 nanoseconds
Or 5 meters.
Just from would you well relativistic this effect?
Look,
I don't believe this.
I just wanted to see whether the order
of magnitude or the effect was about that
But it is
there's not chance that they make this error
Would you call that relativistic data?
No
Because he's
He has the Fitzgerald
whatever
contraction
That is a tiny Lorenz contraction,
which is much smaller between these,
which you have to,
you don't have to add in
it's completely negligible
I think it's about 10% of the,
so no,
I don't think so.
But,
you know,
it does involve light,
it does involve motion,
it does involve relative motion,
so you can call it what you want.
But they didn't make this error.
Anyway.
This is,
I don't think there's much point in talking about it.
But I think it's going to
wind up being some highly technical,
difficult issue
involving the beam pulse and things which are
way beyond my knowledge of that kind of thing.
So I think you just sit and wait.
Okay.
I want to go back a little bit to what
is really at least half of the heart of the subject,
namely the subject of symmetries and conservation laws,
and just really...
quickly go through it.
I was a little bit dissatisfied with
my own discussion of it last time.
I think I probably didn't make
sufficiently clear what a symmetry is
and the difference in particular
between active and passive transformations.
You can think either way,
active or passive,
either way.
There's an appropriate argument that gives the...
I don't know if you can see it,
but there's an appropriate argument
that gives the same result.
But let me just spell it out for you.
Let's think about it the following way.
We have a particle on a line as an example,
just as an example.
And now somebody comes along and says,
perform.
That's something you're required to do.
Perform the transformation,
x goes to x plus 1.
What exactly does that mean?
Oh,
incidentally,
we imagine that the line is going
to be the same as the line.
It is a coordinate.
So that every point on it is labeled.
Every point has a name.
This one is named x equals...
Well,
this one's called named x equals minus 1.
This one's named x equals 0 and so forth.
Think of the coordinate labels as
just the names of the points,
if you like.
Alright,
but of course it's done in a special way,
not arbitrary.
What does it mean to say perform
the transformation x goes to x plus 1?
It could mean two things.
It could mean relabel the points so that every point
that was originally labeled x is now labeled x plus 1.
This one was originally labeled x equals 0.
And after the relabeling it becomes,
let's call it x prime equals 1.
Particle stays in exactly the same position.
If it happened that there was a potential energy,
for example,
that looked like this,
the potential energy would not
change because the particle hasn't moved.
Right?
Okay.
The other definition of what you could mean by perform
this transformation is take the particle from where it is.
Keep the coordinates fixed but move it.
Wherever it is,
whatever x it's at,
move it to x plus 1.
Under that transformation,
the potential energy does change.
The first notion is called a passive transformation.
You don't move anything.
You just relabel points.
The second version is called an active transformation.
You literally take everything in the system,
not just one particle but every particle
and whatever else you have besides particles,
and lift them and move
them one unit to the right.
That's an active transformation.
It's quite clear that the active transformation,
since it moves the particle,
will change the potential energy.
Yeah?
So,
then whatever is causing this potential energy to
exist is not considered part of the system?
Right.
Exactly.
We're going to come back to that.
That's exactly right,
so let me state it now.
In saying that the system was a particle,
we of course are first of all making an approximation,
but more than that,
we're dividing it.
We're dividing the entire system into two parts.
One part is the particle,
the other part is the Earth with
all its hills and valleys and so forth.
Okay.
If I,
of course,
were to move everything,
including the Earth,
the potential energy would not change.
But what we're focusing on is the particle thinking
of the Earth as just too heavy to respond.
It's a situation where with essentially no loss of accuracy,
we can say the Earth just doesn't move.
Of course,
there's a slight loss of accuracy there.
If the particle accelerates or decelerates,
it recoils against the Earth,
the Earth moves a little bit.
But because the Earth is so heavy,
it's irrelevant.
Or it's for practical purposes,
we can ignore the motion of the Earth
and we just say the Earth is fixed.
It gives rise to a potential
which is a definite function of x.
And we're going to leave it that way.
We're not going to change the location of the Earth.
We're not going to change the
location of the top of the potential,
for example.
And we're just going to say the transformation we're going to
do is to move everything relative to the Earth in effect.
Okay.
So,
but we simplify it by just saying there's
a potential energy which is a function of x.
And therefore,
if we move the particle,
we move the potential.
The potential energy changes.
Okay.
So that's the notion of an active transformation.
And I think it's easiest to think about,
yeah,
the active version.
So one thing that still confuses me,
even with this description,
when we did the rotation last time,
so we not only changed the positions,
we changed the velocities.
When you,
yes,
if you change,
no,
we didn't change the velocities.
Well,
yes,
okay,
we did.
We did.
We rotated.
We rotated the velocities.
Okay.
Right.
So the velocity was a vector.
And when we rotated all the positions,
we also rotated the velocity.
Okay.
So we not only rotated,
we not only rotated the
position at an instant of time,
I should say,
okay,
one more thing.
When we say do the transformation
x goes to x plus 1,
we mean that every time,
all times,
send x to x plus 1.
When we say to rotate the coordinate
system so that x varies a little bit,
we mean at all times.
We'll come to it in a minute.
I'm going to go back through
it just to refresh you very quickly.
All right.
So here's the game.
We have some configuration space,
which is the space of the q's.
The q's,
incidentally,
I will use x.
When thinking about Cartesian coordinates for particles.
Otherwise,
more generally,
we'll discuss q's.
But x's are just a special case.
All right.
So we have our q space.
Here's our q space.
The system,
and it's multidimensional,
or it's not multidimensional.
It's got some number of dimensions.
And a configuration is just a point in that space.
Now,
there are many configurations.
All right.
For every point in this space.
There's a configuration.
And now what we mean by a coordinate transformation,
an active coordinate transformation now,
is that we take the system,
wherever it happens to be,
and move it to a new position.
We move it to a new position.
If this point is called q sub i,
then we shift q sub i by an amount.
Let's call it delta q sub i.
It's a shift of q sub i by an amount.
This is delta q.
All right.
Which may,
in fact,
depend on where we are.
In other words,
the delta q over here might be
different than the delta q over here.
Might be different than the delta q over here.
But it's fixed.
It's fixed once and for all,
meaning to say that there's a definite transformation.
But the transformation,
the amount that you shift,
may depend on where you are.
That's allowed.
Okay.
So then delta q sub i
is not just a constant then.
It depends on where you are.
And in order to indicate that,
we introduce a function for each i,
which is a function of all the coordinates,
and a small constant delta.
Now the small constant delta is just really for bookkeeping.
It's kind of a redundant notation.
If we just thought that f,
we could imagine that f was just small.
But it's a sort of redundant notation.
We'll think of f as not necessarily being small,
but make the shift small by
having a sort of universal constant,
which is assumed to be small,
so that delta squared can be ignored and so forth.
All right.
This is the nature
of an infinitesimal coordinate transformation.
Every point moves.
And the points,
the coordinates of the points,
may move.
But they don't move by an
amount which depends on where you are.
That's this over here.
All right.
That's an infinitesimal coordinate transformation.
And that's what we mean when
we speak of an infinitesimal coordinate transformation.
Now,
when you do so,
the potential energy may change.
Of course the potential energy may change.
This is an active transformation.
It may even be that the kinetic energy transforms.
Okay.
Let's say what happens to velocities.
Oh,
the one thing that we do assume is
that these f sub i's are independent of time.
When we shift things,
we shift them by amounts which don't depend on time.
Okay.
For example,
if we're just talking about a shift of x,
x goes to x plus a small amount,
that small amount is assumed not to depend on time.
And therefore,
in that case,
the velocity itself does not shift.
The velocity doesn't shift if we made the
transformation x goes to x plus a constant.
Then,
if we time differentiate this,
it says that x dot goes to
x dot with no change in the velocity.
Okay.
Why?
Because we moved everything to the right by one unit.
Moved it both at time t and also at
time t plus a little t plus a bit.
And so the velocity hasn't changed in between.
Okay.
In general,
there may be a change in the velocity,
but for this particular case,
there would be no change in the velocity.
Yeah?
Is that final delta there in
your equation a constant across all points?
This delta is a constant.
Yeah.
This delta is a fixed constant which in the
end of the day we'll say is very small.
Okay.
And it's just a bookkeeping device so
that we don't have to call this small.
That's all.
We'll see why in a moment
we don't want to call that small.
It's a bookkeeping device to say all the transformations
are small and of the same order of magnitude.
Good.
Some of these f's may be zero.
For example,
if we're talking about two-dimensional space,
x and y,
we make a transformation only of the x coordinate.
x goes to x plus a
little bit with no change in y.
Then the y component of f would be zero.
The x component would not be.
Okay.
So as I said,
we keep track of the smallness by the constant delta.
All right.
As I said,
when you do such a transformation,
the potential energy will in general change.
It may not,
but it may.
It may change.
In addition,
even the case of a small energy,
it may change.
Even kinetic energy may change.
For example,
the kinetic energy in some coordinates,
in some non-Cartesian coordinates,
might have the form of t of q.
That's just a function.
Any function of q times q dot squared.
Some function.
An example would be polar coordinates
in which the theta term,
the term associated with the theta velocity,
involves r.
Remember that?
r theta dot squared?
Right.
So you can have kinetic energies,
which also have dependence on q.
And then when you move things,
even the kinetic energy might
vary if you make a transformation.
So in general,
the entire Lagrangian may vary,
and usually will.
The situation where the Lagrangian doesn't change,
and moreover,
doesn't change no matter where you are,
not only at the point
where the system happens to be.
You might say,
all right,
I'm interested in the system being right over here,
and then I do a
transformation which takes it over here,
and find out that it doesn't
change the Lagrangian at this point.
No,
no.
That's not enough to say there's a symmetry.
To say there's a symmetry means
that at every point in time,
there's a symmetry.
At every point,
no matter where you are,
the Lagrangian doesn't change.
For example,
for a potential energy,
let's just think about what it
would say about a potential energy.
The potential energy is a function of x and y.
And the coordinate transformation I may be
interested in is just an x shift.
Let's take the case of just an x shift,
so that x shifts a little bit.
What does it mean to say that the potential
energy doesn't change if you make an x shift?
It means it doesn't depend on x.
No matter where you are,
up or down,
left or right,
if the potential energy doesn't change when you vary x,
what does it mean about v?
It means it's independent of x,
but it can depend on y.
It can depend on y because
y doesn't change when you shift x.
On the other hand,
if I were to say a different type of transformation,
shifting vertically,
and saying the potential energy doesn't change,
would say v was a function of x.
And if you were to say even stronger that the
potential doesn't change no matter which direction you translate in,
it would say the potential were a constant.
The potential was a constant,
completely independent of x and y.
Okay,
so that's the notion of the potential energy changing
or not changing when you make a small transformation.
But in particular,
we mean when we say that the
potential doesn't change under a small transformation.
It doesn't change wherever you are,
under that transformation.
If both the potential and the kinetic,
or let's say more generally,
if the Lagrangian itself does not
change when you make a transformation,
then that is a symmetry.
Wherever you are,
you make such a little motion,
at all times,
then the Lagrangian,
if the Lagrangian doesn't change,
then it's a symmetry.
Yeah?
So the Lagrangian has to stay the same,
but does that...
Same value,
same numerical value no matter where you start.
But does that condition have to be true
separately for the potential energy and for the kinetic?
No.
In many cases,
in many cases the Lagrangian doesn't even divide
up into a kinetic and a potential energy neatly.
So that's a good question.
And the answer is no.
It does not have to be separate.
It's kind of hard.
It would be kind of hard if one
term didn't depend on velocity and the other didn't,
did and didn't.
But in general,
the most general Lagrangians won't divide up
in a neat way into kinetic and potential.
They'll just be functions of q and q dot.
And then it wouldn't even be possible
to even ask the question in that case.
So the answer is no.
Only the whole Lagrangian has to not change.
Yeah?
I'm probably reading it too much,
but are you saying that it won't change or that
it will change so little we can ignore the change?
Okay.
This is an infinitesimal transformation.
The most we could expect if we made
such a transformation would be an infinitesimal change.
If we make an infinitesimal shift,
the most we can expect is
an infinitesimal change in the Lagrangian.
To say that there is no change means no function.
There is no first order change.
No change proportional to the delta itself.
Now,
that's enough to prove that
a finite version of the transformation,
which just means doing it repeatedly enough times,
usually means a number of times
proportional to one over the small number,
doing the transformation over and over
until you build up a finite transformation,
that also doesn't change the Lagrangian.
If it's the case that it doesn't
change the Lagrangian no matter where you are.
A simple example would be a potential
which you might think depends on x.
Okay?
You might think it depends on x.
And then you say,
all right,
what happens if I move x a little bit?
Then there's a variation of x,
a little bit,
the change,
sorry,
the variation of the potential,
the small change in the potential,
is just the derivative of v
with respect to x times delta x.
Now,
supposing it's true that this is equal
to zero no matter where you start.
And delta x is just a number.
Delta x is just delta,
the number,
the small number.
Suppose it's true that no matter where you are,
the small shift doesn't change v.
Then that says dv dx is equal to zero.
And not only does it say dv dx is
equal to zero at the point where the particle is,
it's zero no matter where the particle could be.
If this is equal to zero for all x,
then dv dx is equal to zero.
And that,
of course,
does say that v is constant.
And it also means that if you were to
build up a finite shift by little infinitesimal ones,
it still wouldn't change v.
So typically,
if you have a situation where the small change
in coordinates does not lead to a comparable change,
in other words,
a first order change in the Lagrangian,
then that's a symmetry.
And you only mean,
you only have to check,
you only have to check that the Lagrangian hasn't changed.
It hasn't changed to lowest order,
meaning to order delta.
Delta squared,
you don't worry about.
You don't have to worry about it,
because long as it's flat for all x,
or more generally,
as long as it's,
so to speak,
flat for all q,
then repeating the transformation endless numbers of
times won't change the value of the function.
Okay,
so that's the notion of a symmetry.
And when you have a symmetry,
you have a conserved quantity.
So I won't go through the derivation again.
We'll just write down what it is.
If this is your little shift,
then the conserved quantity,
which I called q last time,
q for quantity,
q is,
notice that each coordinate is being shifted.
Some of them may not be shifted,
but that just means some of these are zero.
The general situation is every
one of the coordinates gets shifted,
then q is the sum of all the coordinates
of a contribution from each one of the coordinates,
and the sum is multiply the momentum conjugate to
q sub i by the little shift f sub i.
Now you can see why one doesn't want to
think of f sub i as an infinitely small quantity.
I want to think of this as a,
you know,
as a finite quantity.
So I don't want to
necessarily restrict f to be small.
Then it follows that the time
derivative of this is equal to zero.
That's the theorem we proved last time.
And you can go back over the derivation of it,
but this is kind of the bottom line.
We also looked at some examples.
Let's go,
hmm,
let's just remind ourselves of the example.
There was translation symmetry.
In translation symmetry,
let's go back to x.
Yeah,
x,
y,
z.
An example would be delta x
is equal to one times delta.
In other words,
f is just one.
If f is just one for x,
then it follows that q is
just the momentum of that particle.
On the other hand,
we can generalize this in two different ways.
At least two different ways.
The first way we can generalize it
is to notice that we could imagine symmetries
if we had full translation invariance,
real translation invariance,
that it doesn't matter where you place the system.
Then we'll also have the other coordinates.
And so forth.
All of the coordinates will have shift symmetries.
And under that circumstance,
all the components of the momentum,
px,
py,
and pz,
are all conserved.
All right,
so momentum conservation follows from shift symmetry,
from the idea that if you move a system,
and there's nothing to move it relative to,
nothing that influences it,
then momentum is conserved.
Oh,
another way,
another direction that we can generalize it
is that we can imagine there are many particles.
Many particles,
x sub i,
y sub i,
and z sub i.
Now,
i doesn't label the coordinates,
it labels the particles.
There are three coordinates for each particle.
All right,
then what we would want to do,
and you can assume the
particles are interacting with each other,
but as long as the forces
only depend on the relative positions,
in other words,
as long as the potential energy between pairs of particles
doesn't change when we move them both,
then there's a symmetry,
not with respect to moving one particle at a time,
but with respect to moving all of them,
simultaneously.
In that case,
all of the coordinates,
let's say the x components,
let's look at x momentum conservation.
Then,
we don't just move one particle,
we move them all,
and in that case,
it's the sum
of the p sub i's which are conserved.
In other words,
we have to sum over all
the degrees of freedom which we shifted.
Okay.
Translation invariance means momentum conservation.
Again,
I'll just emphasize,
it doesn't mean,
we're not talking about motion
of one system relative to another
if they exert forces on each other,
we're talking about the entire system being displaced.
If the Lagrangian doesn't change,
we have a symmetry.
The circumstances under which that wouldn't be true
is if we had some object which was very,
very heavy,
so heavy that it doesn't move,
we don't think of it as part of the system,
there it is,
but we study the motion of
the system relative to that object,
then we won't have a symmetry.
Then the potential energy will change.
Okay,
let's just remind ourselves about rotation.
Rotation was a little less trivial example.
Let's talk about rotation of the xy plane.
If this is x and y,
and let's for the moment
suppose we have a single particle,
then if we make an infinitesimally small rotation,
that means we rotate the position of the particle
by an infinitesimally small angle delta.
Well,
it's not very well drawn,
but I think you get the idea.
We shift everything,
no matter where the particle is,
we shift by amount delta.
Then the coordinate transformation is delta x,
the small change in x when we rotate,
now think of this as
a rigid rotation of the plane,
the small change in x is y times delta,
no,
minus y times delta.
If we're over here in this sector,
yeah,
minus y times delta,
and what is delta y?
That's x times delta.
You can work that out.
Okay,
let me show you another way
you could think about this fact here.
If it's true that this represents a rigid rotation,
then it must be true that it
doesn't change the length of the vector xy,
the length or the distance from the origin.
Here's our point.
Wherever it is,
we rotate a little bit,
by angle delta,
and the particle moves to that point.
Let's ask,
does this transformation,
this infinitesimal transformation,
does it change the distance from the origin?
Better yet,
does it change the square
of the distance to the origin?
So let's write down the square
of the distance to the origin,
r squared is equal to x squared plus y squared,
and now let's say,
supposing we make a little shift,
what happens to r?
Okay,
so in particular,
we can calculate the change in r squared.
The change in r squared
is equal to twice x delta x
plus twice y delta y.
If you have a product of two things,
and you vary,
make a variation,
then it becomes delta a times b
plus b plus a times delta b.
Alright,
so apply it to x squared plus y squared,
the change in r squared is
two x delta x plus two y delta y.
Now let's plug in.
Delta x is minus y times delta.
Delta y is plus x times delta.
These are going to cancel.
This one is going to have
a two x y times delta,
and this one's going to,
one of them is minus,
this one's minus,
and this one's plus.
And there is no change.
They're equal and opposite.
Alright,
so that's one way to check
that this is in fact a infinitesimal rotation
that preserves the length of all distances from the origin.
You can do better.
You can prove that this
is the form of a rotation.
Okay,
now that we know that,
we can feed it into this formula.
It's a mechanical process now
of feeding into this formula
and constructing the conserved quantities.
Assuming,
assuming that the Lagrangian doesn't change.
The circumstances under which the Lagrangian doesn't change
would be,
for example,
that the potential energy
is only a function of radial distance.
That would do it.
Oh,
incidentally,
when you do this,
you'll also discover,
just by differentiating the formula with respect to time,
that the change in the velocity,
the x component of the velocity,
is minus the y component of the velocity times delta,
and the change in the y component of velocity
is equal to the original x
component of the velocity times delta.
And you can feed that into
x dot squared plus y dot squared
and see that the,
that the kinetic energy doesn't change.
Kinetic energy doesn't change.
Distance from the origin doesn't change.
So if the potential energy only
depends on the distance to the origin,
the Lagrangian doesn't change.
We have a symmetry.
The Q that goes with it is,
alright,
there are two terms,
this P sub x times the little shift of x,
that's minus y,
minus,
minus y P x,
and then plus x P y.
Now,
this,
I think you'll mostly know,
most of you will notice,
first of all,
it's called the angular momentum.
It is the angular momentum.
It is also a component of the cross product.
If we call this,
if we think in three dimensions now,
we imagine that we're in three dimensions,
put back the z axis,
doesn't change anything that we did,
we're still rotating in x y.
This is the vector r,
or let's call it little r,
the vector r that represents the
position relative to the origin,
then this is nothing but the z component,
this is the z component of r cross P,
cross product,
not x,
but r cross P,
cross product,
r cross P,
it's the z component of that,
z component of it.
So,
it says that the z component of r cross P,
which is the z component of angular momentum,
is conserved.
That's what angular momentum is,
r cross P.
Now,
if this is true,
let's think ahead a little bit.
If we're really thinking about a three dimensional problem,
we got this conservation law
by considering rotation of the x y axes.
Focus,
looking down the z axis and rotating.
We could do exactly the same thing
looking down the x axis
and rotating the y z plane.
If we did so,
we would find all of
the components of r cross P
were conserved.
And in fact,
well,
okay,
this is the first one,
this is the z component,
the next one would be y minus z P y
plus y P z,
and what's the last one?
y z x
P z
plus z P x.
These are the three components of the angular momentum.
The angular momentum is a vector,
and these are the three components of the angular momentum
for a particle,
and they're conserved.
If the potential only depends on radial distance
in the three dimensional sense.
If the potential depends on radial distance.
Now we can generalize this in yet another way.
If there are many particles,
and even if they're interacting with each other,
as long as the potential energy,
the sum total of all potential energies,
but in particular the individual potential energies,
as long as they don't change when you rotate,
again,
we rotate everything simultaneously,
then we,
then the conservation law just becomes
the sum of all the particles of r cross P.
And that's angular momentum conservation.
But the importance for us
is that it follows from symmetries,
assuming that the system is symmetric.
Okay?
So for example,
a planet in orbit around a star,
if the potential energy only depends on distance,
therefore it's invariant under every possible rotation,
you can do that holds the star fixed.
Okay?
All components of angular momentum are conserved.
Questions?
Yes?
Yeah,
if you imagine like a two dimensional,
like a cone that comes to the exact point,
and x is exactly at that point,
if you add a delta,
I mean,
or just one dimension,
there's a v,
and it's right at the point if
you do a delta on the one side,
one side or the other,
you have much different Lagrangians with,
you know what I'm saying?
It's like an unstable point,
and the delta has a significance
as to which direction it is.
Yeah.
What does that,
how does that relate to all of this?
Well,
for all purposes,
we're going to assume that
all functions have unique derivatives.
You do have to worry about things like that.
It's a legitimate worry,
but for our purposes,
I think,
and we're going to say,
if we have a thing like this,
it really means this.
And we'll assume that all functions
have a unique derivative at every point.
Of course,
we're going to assume that all functions
have a unique derivative at every point.
If you really had literal,
well,
okay,
that's something we'll assume.
Everything is differentiable,
continuous,
no funny businesses of different
limits coming from different directions.
Such things would lead to modifications of what I'm saying.
It's true.
Like if I have a penny
on the top of a pencil,
pointing to...
Well,
being at the top is not a problem.
The derivative is flat.
It's a position of unstable equilibrium.
It's true.
It depends,
but it's not a...
Okay.
Yes.
So you,
early,
very early on said delta does not depend on t,
therefore x dot goes to x dot.
There's no transformation,
change in x dot.
But yet in the rotational case,
there is...
Okay.
All you do,
right,
the rule is that the change in the time derivative of
a coordinate is the time derivative of the change in the coordinate.
Okay.
So that's the general rule.
If the change in the coordinate
happens to involve the coordinates themselves,
then the change,
this is what would follow.
Right.
So this is the rule that you count on.
Yes.
So you mentioned in passing before that,
you know,
the Lagrangian might not separate
into the potential and the...
Right.
Is that because it's a complicated functional form,
or is there some other concept...
It could be for more than one reason.
I mean,
or it could be because you're using funny coordinates.
It could be because you're using funny coordinates.
The motion of the...
We've talked about this before.
The motion of a particle in
a magnetic field has three terms,
really.
x dot square,
x dot square plus y dot squared,
typical standard kinetic term,
a term which might be a general potential energy.
And then there's this velocity-dependent term,
which contains both the x's and the velocities.
So there's an example where there are terms
which contain both the x's and the velocities.
And when you shift things,
you have to shift things consistently.
So a variety of different reasons
that it might not separate
into conventional kinetic plus potential.
But the Lagrangian is still defined as...
E minus V,
is that...
No,
in that case,
you do not try to represent
it in terms of T and V.
It is only if the Lagrangian...
When do you say that it's T and V?
The general rule is,
if the Lagrangian has the form of some function,
I called it T before,
of Q,
something quadratic,
we can even make this more general,
i and j,
sum over i and j,
q sub i dot q sub j dot,
you know what I mean by that.
A quadratic form in the velocities.
And then minus something which depends only on the q's.
A thing which is quadratic in the velocities
is called kinetic energy.
A thing which does not contain the velocities altogether
is called potential energy.
When it divides up like this,
then it's simple.
The Lagrangian is just T minus V.
But there are situations
where you can have mixed dependencies.
For example,
things involving q dot times functions of x,
some functions of q.
These have neither the form of something quadratic in q,
nor are they simply functions of q.
Then you have to simply think of the Lagrangian
as a function of q and q dot.
It's just a function of q and q dot.
Not profitable.
It's just not profitable to
try to break it up into...
Which raises the question,
what do we mean by energy then?
Right.
We're going to come to that.
In fact,
we're going to come to it,
I think,
right now.
Yeah.
Question.
I think in the first
class you talked about a chain
just hanging like a...
And you said the concept of least action
was applicable to the shape of how that...
No,
I didn't say the principle of least action.
In that case,
it's the principle of least energy.
Yeah.
In that case,
you're not talking about the motion of a system.
You're talking about the equilibrium configuration.
So this is in Lagrangian?
Well...
In a different form?
It's not pertinent now.
Let's just get to the dump truck.
Here's our equations.
dp sub i by dt
is equal to minus...
In the situation where you can divide
things into a potential energy and so forth,
dv sub i by dq sub i.
Remember that?
That's the Euler-Lagrange equations.
If you have a situation
which for one reason or another
you expect to be static,
in other words,
no motion,
then this is zero.
In that case,
you just say dv dq is equal to zero.
What does that mean?
That means you're at the stationary point of a potential.
Who asked me?
Yeah.
Okay?
Right.
So a special case
of the Euler-Lagrange equations
is just the equations for equilibrium
when you know for some reason
or when you ask that nothing be changing
with time.
Good.
Okay.
Let's move on to
energy.
Let's assume for the moment that the
Lagrangian does have the form t minus v.
T minus v,
as I said,
seems a little peculiar
while subtracting the two energies
does seem a little peculiar.
The one thing we haven't
talked about yet is energy conservation.
Is energy conservation associated with a symmetry?
That's the question we want to discuss tonight.
And that will bring us
to the notion of a Hamiltonian.
The answer is yes.
But it's not a symmetry
of the type that we've discussed.
It's not a shift of the cues.
Okay.
So let me draw a picture.
Let's think about space-time.
The horizontal plane here could be space.
We're not thinking about relativity,
incidentally.
We're just drawing a picture of space and time.
These two coordinates could be x and y.
Or we could just call them q1 and q2.
These might not be Cartesian coordinates.
But there's some general coordinates.
And the vertical axis here is time.
And now we think about some expression of time.
So we have some experiment taking place,
some process taking place,
which begins at some time...
Oh,
let's go back a minute.
So far,
we've discussed translation invariance,
which means sliding the system by translating it.
We've discussed rotational invariance,
which means rotating the plane here.
Now we're going to discuss another invariance,
which is time translation invariance.
What it means is you imagine an experiment taking place.
Over here is the start of the experiment.
And you start the experiment
by prescribing some initial conditions.
Initial conditions mean the position and velocities
of every molecule or every particle.
You start with some known initial conditions,
and you wait a while,
and after a period,
there's an outcome.
There's the income and there's
the outcome of the experiment.
After a certain amount of time,
you started at,
let's call it,
t0.
And you ended the experiment at t1,
and there's a result to the experiment.
Okay.
Now,
supposing we time translate the whole thing.
Now I mean an active transformation.
Instead of starting the experiment at t0,
we started at a later time.
But we also ended at a later time.
Exactly the same experiment,
except displaced in time.
How much displaced in time?
By an amount that we'll call delta t.
We displace the initial part of the experiment
and the final part of the,
the final,
the final detection,
or whatever it is,
by the same amount.
Everything has just been shifted.
We did the same experiment.
Instead of starting at noon and ending at 1 o'clock,
we started at 12.01 and ended at 1.01.
All right?
Is the physics,
are the results of the experiments the same?
Okay,
now that's going to depend on whether
the system we're talking
about is time translation invariant.
How could it not be time translation?
That's the definition of time translation.
Every experiment is insensitive to
such a shift of delta t.
Can you think of a situation
where it might be sensitive to it?
It's a condition of time translation.
Yeah.
So for example,
here would be an example.
You have a capacitor.
You don't have to know
anything about electricity and magnetism now.
The capacitor is just two metallic plates,
some plus charges on one side,
some minus charges on the other side,
and you put a charged particle in here.
The charged particle will accelerate.
There will be a Lagrangian.
There will be a potential
energy of the particle in here,
and the potential energy,
in fact,
will be proportional to the distance along here.
And if the charges on
the plates were constant in time,
then we could shift the experiment forward,
backward in time.
It wouldn't make any difference.
On the other hand,
we can imagine that these
plates are connected to a battery
or generator and being charged up.
Start with no charge on them
and slowly ramp up the charge
in a way that we have complete control over.
Assume we have complete control over it,
so we don't have to think of
the capacitor as part of the system.
Of course,
we have such good control.
We just say we know what the capacitor does.
What about the particle motion?
Thinking of the particle as a system.
Now,
the result of an experiment
will depend on when you begin.
By the experiment,
I mean now not the
process of charging up the capacitors.
That's given.
That's frozen.
It's being done by somebody else out of the room.
You're doing the experiment inside the capacitor plates.
It does depend on when you start.
You'll get a different answer if you
start when it's charged or when it's uncharged.
So that's an example where a
system would not be time translation invariant.
Of course,
you might argue,
and you'd be right,
that if we did the whole experiment,
including whoever it is that is charging up the capacitor,
did the entire experiment and
shifted everything forward by some time,
then we would get the same answer,
and that's correct.
But let's not do that.
Or for the moment.
For the moment,
let's not do that.
In order to understand what it would
mean to have a time non-translation invariant system,
some parameter of the system,
it could be the electric field,
another parameter.
We have a harmonic oscillator,
a spring.
X dot squared is the one-half
mx dot squared is the kinetic energy,
and the potential energy,
v,
is...
k over 2,
x squared,
where k is the spring constant.
You can imagine situations where the
spring constant might change with time.
I'll give you an example.
You put the spring,
the whole spring and everything else,
into an electric or a magnetic field,
and you turn up the electric and magnetic field.
The electric and magnetic field has a small
effect on the atoms and the inter-atomic spacing
and all sorts of things.
The net effect could easily be a
small time dependence in the spring constant.
That would be another example that if
you didn't worry about the external conditions
and you only worried about the
particle on the end of the spring,
you would say that you
did not have time translation invariance.
We're going to find,
after a little break,
that time translation invariance,
implies energy conservation.
On the other hand,
you could say,
well,
what does that mean for when
you don't have time translation invariance?
What it means is there's an exchange back
and forth between the thing you call the system
and the rest of it of energy.
Energy being transferred back and forth,
in this case,
between the capacitor and the particle,
or whatever it was,
whatever the agent was that was
causing the change in the spring constant,
transfer of energy.
So from one point of view,
you can think there was no symmetry,
and the energy wasn't conserved.
From a bigger point of view,
where you take more into account,
you would say there was a symmetry,
if you translate the entire
experiment back and forth in time,
and in that case,
the full energy,
including the energy of the capacitor,
plus the energy of the particle,
plus whatever energy there is that causes them to interact,
that will be conserved.
So,
after about five minutes,
we'll come back and we'll talk about energy conservation,
which will bring us to the Hamiltonian,
which is really where we want to go.
Did I say delta x equals epsilon?
Well,
I mean,
I just...
That's great.
I love that.
It's much better.
Delta x equals epsilon.
Because I hate delta x equals delta.
Yeah.
Like,
the formula at the top
right of the board there is...
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
As you know what it is,
it's really confusing.
Yeah.
We could replace all these on this side by epsilon.
Why didn't I think of that?
Yeah.
It's a good book.
Which?
It's Heming Oether's Magnificent Theorem,
or something like that.
Oh,
I don't know about it.
It's a technical...
It's everything that a...
...physics student should know about the Melters thing.
Okay.
Who wrote it?
You don't...
Can you look it up?
Well,
put it online.
Put it online.
Put it on the website.
I'm not filming it.
Do you know how to...
Put it on the class website.
Emmy Neurther,
the...
...the author of the Beecher's Wonderful Theorem,
Magnificent Theorem.
Yeah.
I have a question.
Since we never here defined the Lagrangian other than actually the
difference between a kinetic energy term and a potential energy term...
Is it the case...
Yeah.
If they don't divide up into quadratic in velocity
and quadratic in or at a function of position
then there's then there's no sense in which you
can think of it as a potential it's just a
Lagrangian it's just it's a function of Q's and Q
dots you say well the question is not how you
define it the question is where do you get it
from one answer is you might get it from experiment
another answer is you might get it because
you already know the equations of motion from
somewhere and so you look for a
Lagrangian which gives that another possibility is
you have some preconceived theoretical prejudices
about the way the thing should
look but somewheres from some place either
experiment or just trial and error until you
match the equations of motion or a
theoretical prejudice you are handed a Lagrangian the
Lagrangian may be simple and have the
form of a quadratic thing in velocities minus
and
a function of the positions or it may not in any
case what do you do with it what you do with it
incidentally well okay what do you do with it
you apply Euler Lagrange equations to it and that
gives you the equations of motion and you solve
them and that tells you how the system moves
all right so we're
gonna take an abstract look at it now
and assume there is a Lagrangian again where it
came from it's not our business for the moment
let's talk about what it means for the Lagrangian
or to have a time translation and variance let's start
by 16 ai and a slight formula to solve that
Let's take again,
let's start with this very simple system.
Let's say the harmonic oscillator,
the Lagrangian for that system is
just one half m x dot squared,
I'll use x now,
minus k over 2 x squared.
K is the spring constant,
the Hooke's law spring constant,
and this is it.
If k is constant,
then we say the system has time translation invariance.
If k varies with time,
it doesn't.
Alright,
so how do we generalize that idea?
How do we generalize that idea?
By looking at the Lagrangian,
how do we know if it has time translation invariance?
And it's very,
very simple.
If the Lagrangian is only a function of
the q's and the q dots,
but does not have an additional explicit dependence on time,
then it's time translation invariant.
If the parameters of the problem,
for example k or any other parameter,
has a time dependence,
then you add that into the dependence of
the Lagrangian as an explicit dependence on time.
I'll tell you what that depends on.
That means,
more clearly,
the question is if you know q and q dot,
do you know the Lagrangian?
Or do you also need to know the time?
In the case of a particle moving
in a varying electric or magnetic field,
in order to know
what the Lagrangian is at an instant of time,
you need to know what time it is.
On the other hand,
if it's not varying with time,
then there's no explicit time dependence
here.
So an explicit time dependence means a
time dependence above and beyond the time dependence
that's there because q and
q dot are changing with time.
An explicit time dependence,
which has to do,
usually,
with the fact that the system
that you've treated only a part of the system,
and there are parameters in your description,
which are time dependent.
So there's no explicit time dependence,
and of course,
even in a battery,
the segment
at x and y,
the total duration of this is one
or two times the Tokian 50 megawatts.
So there is an explicit time dependence potential.
on the particle.
Could be gravitational,
for example.
The gravitational potential energy of
each of these heavy weights here
would create a potential energy and therefore a force
on the particle.
Now imagine the
dumbbell was turning.
It was spinning or
revolving around a pivot at the center
here.
We're not going to try
to solve the equations of the
dumbbell.
We're just going to say,
look,
we know this dumbbell is so heavy,
we know how it's moving,
and we simply put that in
as input,
then the forces on the
particle here will be time dependent.
The Lagrangian will be time dependent because the
potential energy will be time dependent.
That would be
an explicit time dependence here.
What does it
mean to say you have time translation invariance?
Very,
very simple.
It simply means
that there is no explicit time dependence.
That's it.
You know everything about the system
if you know the q's and
q dots at an instant of time.
You don't also have to say what time it is
in order to know what
the value of the Lagrangian is.
That's all it means.
No explicit
time dependence in the Lagrangian.
I'm going to work out the conservation of energy
for you,
assuming
that there is no explicit time dependence.
And then I'm going to tell you,
it's in the notes,
it's what
worked out in the notes a
little more generally with an explicit
time dependence.
I want to do it the simplest
possible way so that you don't get lost in details.
And then I'll come back and tell
you what happens if you
do have an explicit time dependence
there.
So,
let's suppose
that you thought that the Lagrangian was
the energy.
You didn't know
that the Lagrangian is t minus v
and that the energy is t plus v.
And you just thought,
ooh,
maybe this thing called the Lagrangian
is the energy.
I can check that by seeing
whether it's conserved.
You know,
if it's an ordinary system
and we expect it to be a conservation of energy,
let's just try it.
Let's just try it and see if it's conserved.
How do you find out?
Well,
first of all,
you start by saying the Lagrangian
is some function of all of
the q's and the q dots.
Let's calculate its time derivative.
What better way is there to calculate
whether it's conserved than
to calculate the time derivative?
Okay,
so let's try to calculate this.
d by dt of the Lagrangian.
Let me explain what this means.
The system
moves through the coordinate space
and as it moves through the coordinate space,
the potential and kinetic energy of the Lagrangian
changes with time.
The question is,
as you move along a trajectory,
is the value of the Lagrangian changing or not?
Alright,
so how do you calculate this?
You just say,
well,
first of all,
this is equal to
the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to the coordinates
times
the time derivative
of the coordinate
plus
this is the change in the
Lagrangian when you change the coordinate
times the change per unit time
in the coordinate
plus
partial of L
with respect to q dot
q double dot,
right?
q double dot.
You differentiate with respect to the argument
and then you multiply it by the
time derivative of the argument of the function.
Is that clear?
Alright,
I feel
this is basic calculus.
I can't motivate this except to say
it's the change in the
Lagrangian when you change a coordinate
times how fast the coordinate is changing
plus the change in the Lagrangian
with respect to q dot.
Because the velocity
may be changing with time
times the time derivative of the velocity
which is the second derivative.
Okay,
now let's assume
that the motion along here
satisfies the equations of motion.
First of all,
what is dL by this?
Am I missing something in this formula?
A summation,
right?
The time derivative
each one of the coordinates
can enter into it
summation over i.
Each one of the coordinates
is changing
the Lagrangian depends on each one of the coordinates
and so there's a sum
over i in this formula here.
Okay,
let's manipulate it.
Now we do a little bit of magic.
And the magic is always the same.
There's not much of a
variety in this business.
Once you learn the trick
it's pretty much a one trick game.
Okay.
Let's start with this one.
The L by dq sub i dot.
What is that?
It's a p sub i.
That's the definition of p sub i.
Remember?
The L
Oh,
this
I have this habit of sometimes switching between
script and you know,
okay.
The L by dq sub i dot
is definition p sub i.
That's the definition of the canonical momentum
conjugate to q sub i.
So let's use it.
This is just definition.
I'm not doing anything very substantial here.
p sub i times
q sub i
double dot
which is incidentally
q sub i dot dot
q sub i double dot is also
q sub i dot
dot
It is.
I suspect we're going to use that.
That q sub i double dot
is q sub i dot dot.
Okay.
Now.
This is plus
q sub i dot.
But what's the L by dq sub i?
p dot.
That's Lagrange's equations.
The L by dq sub i
that's p sub i dot.
Okay.
So we get p sub i dot here.
Sum over i.
Now look at what we have.
We have the time derivative of this
and the time derivative of this
well.
I'm going to write the formula
and I'll show you where it comes from.
This is the same thing as
d by dt
of
p sub i
q sub i dot
under the sum
summation.
على
إستفادة
I take away the summations?
Let's take away the summations
just to unclutter the formula.
In fact,
I mean,
this is true even without the summations.
This is what we have.
P sub i,
why is this true?
Well,
the time derivative of this product
is the time derivative of the first factor times
the second factor.
That's this one.
Time derivative of the first factor times the second factor.
Plus the first factor times the time derivative
of the second factor.
Here is where we make use of the fact
that q double dot is q dot dot.
If you know what I mean.
If you don't,
don't worry about it.
I just mean.
Should there just be one dot
on top of the q i?
The last one.
Which one?
The last right dot.
All the way to the right.
Yeah.
One dot.
Right,
look at it.
Just look at it.
D by dt of this whole thing.
This is all here.
All inside of a bracket.
The derivative of a product
is the sum of two terms.
One term would be p dot q dot.
That's this.
And the other term would
be p times q double dot.
Okay?
That's a little magic,
and-
I think what
they are getting at is that is an odd sign?
Over the Q.
Is that two dots or one dot?
No,
that's one dot.
One dot.
I see.
Okay.
Sorry about that.
One dot.
Now does that make you happier?
Good.
Right.
P dot Q dot plus P Q dot dot.
So this is inequality.
Inequality.
Let's go back and put back the sum.
I won't actually put back the sum
because I don't want to clutter it up.
But think about the sum.
What have we found?
We've found that DL by DT happens
to equal the time derivative of something else.
Happens to equal the time derivative of
P sub I Q sub I dot sum.
Sum over I.
Well,
that's interesting.
You have one time
derivative equaling another time derivative.
First of all,
the Lagrangian is not itself conserved.
The time derivative is not conserved.
It has a right-hand side.
And in general,
this right-hand side will not be zero.
But supposing we now subtract these
two and set that equal to zero.
Now,
in fact,
we have that.
The time.
The time derivative of some quantity is equal to zero.
All right,
so let's write down what that quantity is.
Let's.
look at it
it's the Lagrangian
minus
the sum over all the
canonical coordinates,
all the coordinates
sum over i
p sub i
q sub i dot
that is conserved
it's got a name
I'm going to write down its name over here
it's called
minus
the Hamiltonian h
you'll see in a moment
why that minus is there
you could call it h if you wanted to
that would be fine
you could call it h
it would still be conserved
it's a historical fact
it's just a historical
fact
that it was called minus h
so we write then that h
which is a conserved quantity
is the sum over all
the directions and the coordinates
that are in its base
p sub i q sub i dot
minus the Lagrangian
okay let's work this out
and see what it is for some simple examples
let's take some simple examples
simplest example
l equals
one half
the mass
times
x dot squared
minus v of x
what is this?
this is a particle moving
in a potential energy v of x
let's work out what it is
of course here I've substituted x for q
whenever I'm thinking about a particle on a line
I'll call it x but it's really just q
okay
first of all
what is p
p sub i
or just p
there's only one coordinate
p is m x dot right
so let's calculate what h is
h is the mass of the energy
which is first of all there's no sum now
there's only one coordinate
it is p which is m x dot
and what's q dot
just x dot
for some odd reason in my notes
this is written as
this times x dot
I think I just wanted to emphasize
that it was a product of two things
just uh
I'm gonna go and erase that and just call this
x dot squared
and
so p q dot
is nothing but m x dot squared
you might have noticed
that it's not a half m x dot squared
now let's subtract
the Lagrangian
subtracting Lagrangian is
minus in brackets
m over two
x dot squared minus v of x
okay what do we get all together
we get one half
m x dot squared
from this and this
m x dot squared minus
a half m x dot squared
that's just m x dot
that's just m over two
x dot squared
kinetic energy
and what happens to the v of x term
magic
v of x minus v of x in the Lagrangian
gets converted to plus v of x
in the Hamiltonian
you see what happened
minus times minus is plus
this is the conserved quantity
not the Lagrangian itself
Lagrangian is not conserved
you have to add that term in
or subtract it off
or whatever
and that changes the sign
see the Lagrangian has minus v of x
and so minus the Lagrangian has plus v of x
that's as simple as that
this of course is what we usually call the energy
this is very general
we could have done it for any number of particles
it would have come out exactly the same way
each particle would have made its contribution
any number of dimensions of space
any number of particles
exactly the same thing would have happened
so we find out yes there is a conservation law
and that conservation law
at least in the cases where we recognize
what energy is
potential plus kinetic
it's just the energy
more generally
when the Lagrangian doesn't divide up
in a recognizable and specific way
it's just simple potential and kinetic energy
nevertheless
this quantity is conserved
we proved that without assuming
that the Lagrangian
had any particular special form
starting at the top
no special form for the Lagrangian
we did use a definition
that the L by dq dot
is equal to p
but then the rest of it
right up to here
can in any way depend
on the specific form of the Lagrangian
so whatever the Lagrangian is
pq dot minus the Lagrangian
is the conserved quantity
as long as there is no time dependence
yeah yeah
we'll come back in a minute
as long as there is no time dependence
ok
in the notes I worked it out
with time dependence
but you can kind of see what would happen
if there is an explicit
let's see
supposing the Lagrangian
explicitly depended on time
yeah let's just go back
oh boy
I wish I were two feet taller
I really don't want to push this up
and pull that one down
ok we'll do it
do you anything
am I missing something here
if there was an explicit time dependence
partial of L with respect to t
in other words
you keep the q's and the q dots fixed
and just differentiate what that corresponds to
in our case over here
where
where the spring constant
might have an explicit time dependence
is just differentiate the time dependence
you would have a k dot times x squared
one half k dot times x squared
you'd be differentiating this thing over here
so yeah
there's another term there
let's see if we can track the other term
where did it go
one more term
that's the L
ok so the L by dt
then
would have on the right hand side here
partial of L
with respect to t
now first of all
what is the difference between
dL dt this and this
this
the left hand side here
this dL dt
is actually the true
derivative with respect to time
along the trajectory
as the particle moves
or as the system moves
in other words it contains not only
the partial derivative with respect to t
but also the fact that the q's are changing
that's the side over here
or this one over here
this is what you get just by doing nothing
but differentiating the parameters
in the Lagrangian
ok
so this is what we
get and this is equal to
minus dH dt
let's see this thing over here
L minus pq dot
that's minus H so this is equal to
minus dH dt
so we have the theorem then
that
the time derivative
of the Hamiltonian
if there's an explicit time dependence
is equal to minus
the time the partial derivative
of the Lagrangian
with respect to time
in other words
energy would not be conserved
if the Lagrangian had a
explicit time dependence
here
from this case over here
what is the dL by dt
the partial derivative
partial derivative of L
with respect to t
no t
no explicit time dependence here
only here
is minus k dot
of t
divided by 2
x squared
what this says is
wherever the particle happens to be
whatever x it happens to be at
happens to be over here
then
if you want to know
sorry this is um
yeah this is dL by dt
and that is equal to
minus
dH by dt
that's
I just use this over here
ok
so
the energy in this case
is not conserved
it's time derivative
is not zero
it's x squared
whatever x squared is
times the time derivative of the spring constant
the time derivative of the spring constant
translates into a time derivative
of the energy of the oscillator
so if x happens to be zero
when you're sitting at the origin
then this is zero
but where if any other situation
wherever x happens to be
there will be a time derivative of the energy
ok
as I said that is because
you've separated the system
into
the thing that you're looking at
and
ignored the thing which is
causing the change of the parameters
alright
that's
the notion of a Hamiltonian
let's see
question?
you said that
energy is not conserved
does that mean the definition of energy
is derivative of the Hamiltonian
is that the definition of energy
the definition of energy is the Hamiltonian period
I'm sorry yeah
yeah
um
as I said
in all the cases where the Hamiltonian
can be written in a familiar form
of a potential kinetic minus a potential
then the answer is the kinetic plus the potential
when it's written in an unfamiliar form
the Hamiltonian tells you
what the rule is
for the definition of energy
and if you treat the whole system
including
including the dumbbell
the rotating dumbbell up there
you treat it all together
energy will be conserved
ok
yeah
can you explain this again
in the context of the example that you had
in the earlier classes
which example?
of a stationary particle and an observer on a merry-go-round
where
all of a sudden we've got the
centripetal force and the
Coriolis force
whereas
because of the rotational invariance
because what?
the Lagrangian didn't change
remember
no no remember that in that case
we were not just talking about a rotation
we were talking about a time dependent rotation
we weren't just talking about a coordinate change
or a time translation
we were talking about a
rotating coordinates
that sit there and rotate
that's a different story
uh
in the first examples
we talked about time
we just do some
change of variables
and it's that change of variables
it doesn't change with time
it's just a fixed change of variables
in the second example it's a time shift
uh
so
the rotating coordinates is a separate
separate beast of its own
we could take the Lagrangian
that we computed
including
the effect of the rotation
just take that as an absolutely
Lagrangian and ask what the
Hamiltonian is associated with it.
I was going to
wait to do that until we
talked about particles in electric and magnetic
fields because it's a because
they're very very closely related.
I think I will
wait on that.
Now I don't know whether it's
a good idea to continue now with
more material or whether you're all saturated.
We've been going for an hour
and a half.
What does that mean?
Lagrangian wasn't the derivative of anything.
We calculated the time derivative of the Lagrangian.
And then we took the Lagrangian of it
and then we could come up with Hamiltonian.
So let's summarize everything we
know up to now about Lagrangians.
First of all,
Lagrangians are functions of q,
q dot,
and I'm simplifying,
I'll leave out the little sub i's.
And possibly also explicitly dependent on t.
May or may not this explicitly dependent on t.
Okay.
Lagrangian's equations of motion or
the Euler Lagrangian equations of motion.
Well,
first,
before we do that,
p sub i is just,
I keep doing this,
dl,
forget the i,
by dq dot.
Of course,
there's a separate one of these for each i,
but let's simplify.
P is dl by dq dot.
The Lagrangian equations of motion are that p dot for each i
is equal to partial of l with respect to the corresponding q.
Sometimes it's written as d by dt of partial of
l with respect to q dot on the left-hand side.
But if I use the fact that
dl by dq dot is called p,
it's just p dot equals dl by dq.
Okay.
So those are the basic Lagrangian equations of motion.
Then,
next,
let's get everything here.
If there is a symmetry,
an ordinary symmetry,
not a time translation symmetry,
if there is a symmetry of the form delta q,
let's put an i in here now,
f sub i of q,
shall we call it epsilon now instead of delta?
Yeah,
there were too many deltas in the formula,
but epsilon is just what we called before delta.
If we have a symmetry of this type,
if we have a symmetry of this type,
then it follows that there's a conserved quantity,
q,
I want q which is equal to the sum of all
i of p sub i times f sub i of q.
And,
of course,
q dot is equal to zero.
That's what it means to say that it's conserved.
We proved that last week.
Okay.
I quoted it this week.
But we proved it last week.
We proved it last week.
If we have time translation invariance,
no,
let's not write that.
Let's do it without time translation invariance.
All right.
Generally,
the time derivative of the Lagrangian along,
Okay.
the trajectory of the system,
the time derivative along the trajectory of the system,
what do we find?
That it was equal to minus or plus?
Minus or plus?
D by dt.
Plus,
right?
Yeah.
I think I have it right.
Plus the explicit time dependence.
Or if we transpose,
So,
what is the time dependence?
To the other side of the equation,
we get this.
And then this just reads that minus dh
dt is equal to plus dl by dt,
where h is equal to the sum
of the pq dots minus the Lagrangian.
Now,
usually what you do in thinking about this,
the way we thought about it up till now,
the p's were definite functions of q and q dot.
You get them by differentiating the
Lagrangian with respect to q dot.
So,
this side here is something that's known
in terms of q and q dot.
And this whole thing here is written
What does it give?
It gives kinetic plus potential when
there is a kinetic plus potential.
So,
this is conserved.
d by dt of h is equal to zero
when the Lagrangian doesn't have
an explicit dependence on time.
All right.
This is basically all the equations
that we've done up till now.
Definition.
Euler-Lagrange equation.
If there's a symmetry,
there's a conserved quantum.
If there's a relativity,
there's a theorem.
An ordinary symmetry.
And if there's time translation,
even without time translation,
dh by dt is equal to minus dl by dt.
Why did I write this this way?
Let's write it the other way.
Minus dl by dt.
Again,
the sign gets flipped here.
That's funny.
The sign gets flipped,
but it's correct.
So,
those are the co-equations.
Go through them.
Try to derive them.
There's a small number of tricks in deriving them.
Get familiar with them,
and you'll find this is very easy.
So,
the Hamiltonian...
If you take the simple case where
t and v are discrete and separable,
then the Lagrangian is minus v
and Hamiltonian is t plus v,
correct?
Mm-hmm.
And it seems that you can describe
mechanics either using Lagrangian or the Hamiltonian.
Well,
we have not discussed yet
the Hamiltonian formulation of mechanics.
We will.
Right.
That's unknown.
At the moment,
we have not.
But I think the question is,
are...
You know,
it's the motion is some function
of the Hamiltonian or the Lagrangian.
Is there some reason to pick one or the other?
Is that a question?
They have different character to them,
the equations.
Is there some reason to pick one over the other?
No,
they're equivalent to each other.
But they emphasize different features.
The Lagrangian emphasizes the least
action or the stationary action idea.
It really is the stationary action idea.
That's where it came from.
And it came from the idea of saying mechanics
can be formulated in terms of an action principle.
The Hamiltonian principle is different.
It's more abstract.
It's easier in many ways.
The equations are very easy.
But it's more abstract.
And you might ask yourself historically,
why the hell did Hamiltonian
invent it in the first place?
Well,
he was playing around and just trying to sort
out all the possible different formulations you could have.
But of course,
the Hamiltonian formulation played the
central role in quantum mechanics.
Very central role in quantum mechanics.
So I can't do that now.
But we can work out the Hamiltonian theory.
The point is the Hamiltonian is not just the energy.
It is the energy.
But that's not its only significance.
The formulation.
The Hamiltonian formulation of mechanics is a very
different emphasis in a way than the Lagrangian.
Well,
we have a few minutes.
We can do a very simple example.
I have another question.
Did Newton know about what we
would call the Hamiltonian conservation of energy?
No.
I don't think so.
If he did,
he didn't say.
Does he know about the .
He must have if he did all the .
No.
F equals ma.
OK.
Yeah.
So I don't know.
No.
How do we know that there's always,
that every system has a branch in the corresponding
Is that just an experimental fact?
It is an experimental fact.
It's also a thing that follows
from the rules of quantum mechanics.
So.
If we didn't have quantum mechanics,
would it be theoretically possible that we'd have
a system that didn't have a Lagrangian?
I could write down equations of
motion that didn't have a Lagrangian.
But you know,
that's a counterfactual.
If we didn't have quantum mechanics,
what would be true?
Well,
I don't know what would be
true if we didn't have quantum mechanics.
We have quantum mechanics.
Classical mechanics does not
precede quantum mechanics logically.
Quantum mechanics precedes classical mechanics logically.
So if you want to know
why something is true in classical mechanics,
or why,
well,
yes,
if you want to know why
classical mechanics takes on a certain form,
there are two possible
reasons.
One of them could be that the things
that you're happening to talk about are required
by logical consistency of the equations.
You know,
this equation,
dq by dt is equal to minus dq by dt.
I think we know we
don't want to write that equation,
right?
We just don't want to write that equation.
That equation,
well,
it does say dq by dt is equal to zero,
equals one.
That's a bad equation.
So we don't write it
down because it's mathematically inconsistent.
Right?
But we could write down an equation which is consistent.
dq by dt,
and now I mean dx by dt,
I might as well write dx by dt,
is equal to some known
function of x,
is equal to x,
or minus x.
That's a perfectly good equation.
You can solve it.
It has,
you know what the solution is.
The solution is x is equal
to e to the minus t.
It's perfectly good.
Nothing wrong with it.
But the problem is,
if you want to solve it,
you have to solve it.
Why can't it be a fundamental equation?
It can't be because quantum mechanics
doesn't have systems that behave that way.
And that we do understand why.
But I can't tell you now.
This question keeps coming up
over and over and over again.
Please accept my,
you know,
be patient.
Be patient.
I cannot tell you why classical
mechanics has the form that it has,
except to say that if it didn't,
quantum mechanics didn't.
Quantum mechanics would not make sense.
Yeah?
For every real system,
there's a Lagrangian.
But for every Lagrangian,
there's not a...
That's almost certainly true.
Right.
Not everything you write down is
realized in nature as a real system.
But Goldstein said that the Lagrangian was
basically just a tool for inventing potentials.
Well,
it's not a tool for inventing potentials.
You could invent potentials without the Lagrangian.
But it's a tool for inventing potentials.
It's a tool for inventing mechanical systems,
if you like.
You know,
it also is a powerful tool for solving certain problems,
which I haven't emphasized.
Maybe I should at some point emphasize or give you an
example of a system which is easily studied with the Lagrangian method,
which is awfully hard to
think about by F equals M-A.
Coriolis?
Hmm?
Coriolis.
That makes it easy,
but I was thinking about the double pendulum.
Yeah,
the double pendulum,
a pendulum hung from a ceiling with
another pendulum hung from it like that,
swinging,
the whole thing swinging.
Awfully hard to think about the
forces and to think about the...
The way you do it is you write down...
You first invent some coordinates.
The coordinates could be this angle.
And let's say...
Oh,
I don't know,
maybe the angle relative to the angle of the angle.
So the vertical over here,
phi.
We fix the length of the pendulum.
And then we write the velocity of
this particle and write one-half mv squared.
We write the part of the velocity of this particle.
Also write one-half mv squared for it,
for the v's being determined
in terms of theta and phi.
And then add the potential energy.
And then you have a Lagrangian.
It's rather easy to do in this form.
And once you have the Lagrangian,
you grind out the equations
of motion by the standard method.
Much,
much easier than trying to
think about the forces acting and...
So the Lagrangian is often a
compact way to solve a problem.
You figure out what the potential energy is.
You figure out what the kinetic energy is.
You subtract them from each other.
And you got the Lagrangian.
Once you have the Lagrangian,
you apply these rules.
And that's exactly what we have with the three particles,
except that you've said that one particle is
so big and dominant that it's an anchor.
Yeah.
So...
What's the point?
It would be like Sun,
planet,
and moon.
You know,
Sun,
Earth,
and moon.
Same kind of...
Right.
But I think this is a nice
problem to set up and solve using Lagrangian,
which will show you the power of it.
And how easy it is to solve problems writing the
Lagrangian first and then working out the equations of motion.
It's also extremely useful if you're changing variables.
Instead of trying to change variables
in each of the equations of motion,
you change the variables in the Lagrangian.
This is what I showed you last...
Not last time,
time before.
How you go to the rotating coordinates.
It's easier to just compute the Lagrangian than it
is to take the equations of motion and transform them.
That's almost always harder.
Yeah.
But to solve that problem,
you say the Lagrangian is equal to t minus v.
Yeah.
And I think earlier today you
said you can't always say that.
Alright.
But in this case,
it is because it's really just a collection of particles.
I don't understand.
How do you know when it's not t minus v?
Things which are made up out of ordinary particles,
it's always t minus v.
Because it's t minus v.
But t minus v is in an inertial frame.
Yeah.
So,
it's t minus v in an inertial frame.
We're in an inertial frame.
We're watching this from an inertial frame.
That's as long as they're not relativistic.
That's right.
It's not relativistic.
There are no magnetic fields present.
Then it's just t minus v.
Collisions which change momentum are extreme moment.
Yes.
That's just what I was going to say.
Collisions are due to forces.
Forces are due to potential energies.
Collision.
Why does a collision happen?
A collision happens because there's
a repulsive force between particles.
You seem puzzled by that.
You seem surprised.
Well,
inelastic collisions...
inelastic collisions involve many,
many particles.
I mean,
it's still true that inelastic collisions are
just collisions between lots and lots of particles.
But...
The particles can get excited into internal motions that don't correspond
just to the net center of mass motions of these particles.
In addition,
they can heat up.
But,
in the end of the day,
the equations for each
particle is just Lagrange's equations.
I'd ask to finish this question,
because if the particles of
baseball are hit by a bat,
then I can analyze that in
terms of efficacy as I may.
Not if you want to keep track of the
heat that's generated in the baseball when it gets whacked.
Actually,
it would be very hard to...
Right.
You might smash the baseball,
the bat might get broken...
Not so easy.
How about a rigid body?
A finite extent?
Yeah.
That we can often study with F equals mA.
You mean the Lagrangian and so on is a...
It's T minus V.
Huh?
Yeah.
Yeah,
we could talk about rigid
bodies and Lagrangians for rigid bodies.
And maybe that's a good exercise.
Yeah.
So,
you're talking about conserved quantities
and classical versus quantum mechanics.
Does the energy time of certain relation
imply that energy is not strictly conserved?
No.
It says...
What it says is that to measure it accurately,
you have to take a long time.
That's what it says.
Right.
Strictly conserved.
But if you want to know it accurately,
it takes a long time to measure it.
Yeah.
I think what I hear
you saying is that Lagrangian approach,
the Newtonian approach,
and the
traditional Newtonian approach,
those are all sort of logically equivalent.
So,
does that mean that you could derive technical...
Well,
it's the logically equivalent under
the circumstances that you're talking about.
Yeah.
So,
you can derive technical circumstances that they apply.
Now,
you can invent Lagrangians which don't
naturally lend themselves to equations mx
double dot equals f of x.
Here's a Lagrangian...
Okay.
Let's work out a non-standard Lagrangian,
but it's a perfectly good Lagrangian.
Okay.
So,
let's...
From the Lagrangian point of view,
there's nothing wrong with it.
Instead of writing q dot squared,
or minus some v of q,
let's make it definite,
minus
q squared over 2.
I've left out the mass and the spring constant.
That doesn't matter.
Let's change it.
Let's put another q squared here.
Multiplying the q dot squared.
It's perfectly good.
It is of the form of
an L of q and q dot.
But,
it doesn't have...
We could add something else here.
We could add q q dot,
for example.
It just doesn't lend itself to a description
in terms of a conventional kinetic and potential
energy,
particularly with this term here.
But still,
we could write out the equations of motion.
Let's do it.
Okay.
So,
partial of L with respect to q dot.
What is p?
p is not equal to q dot.
It's equal to q squared q dot.
Where'd that come from?
Derivative of Lagrangian with respect to
q dot now contains a q squared.
Okay.
So,
our equations of motion are p dot
equals partial of L with respect to q.
Let's see what we get.
p dot is q squared q double dot.
That's from differentiating this.
Plus 2q q dot squared.
Where did that come from?
Differentiating this with respect to time
gives us 2q times q dot.
But now we have another q dot there.
And what's that equal to?
That's equal to the derivative
of Lagrangian with respect to q.
Now q occurs in both of these.
q occurs in both of these.
So,
what's the derivative of Lagrangian with respect to q?
It's q times q dot squared minus 1,
I believe.
Is that right?
Yeah.
Both of them have q squared over 2.
So,
when I differentiate with respect to q,
it just leaves a q.
And then it multiplies q dot squared minus q.
So,
what does this give?
It looks like it gives q squared q double
dot plus q q dot squared equals minus q.
Okay.
There's nothing special about this.
It's just an example.
I can't hear you.
I could.
Unless q is 0.
Yeah,
we could divide by q everywhere.
Okay.
We could calculate the Hamiltonian if we wanted to.
We could calculate what the energy is.
Let's calculate what the energy is.
We just calculated what p is.
p is equal to q squared q dot.
We're supposed to multiply p by q dot.
So,
let's do that first.
p q dot.
That's q squared q dot squared minus the Lagrangian.
Minus q squared q dot squared
over 2 plus q squared over 2.
So,
in fact,
it does have,
it looks like q squared q dot
squared over 2 plus q squared over 2.
It does look like t plus v.
We could think of this
as t and this as v.
We can make up examples which are
more complicated where it won't naturally be.
We can break up in that way.
Is q squared q dot squared t?
Say it again.
Is q squared q dot squared reading t?
Yeah.
Well,
yeah.
If you call this t,
yes.
If you call that t.
Yeah.
Notice all that happened when you
went from the Lagrangian to the Hamiltonian,
again,
was the same thing.
The q squared changed sign and
the other term stayed the same.
Right.
Yeah.
How do you account for friction in a Lagrangian?
You don't.
Friction is due to the collective,
to the motion of tiny particles
which are too small to see.
You can think of them as being all the
large number of particles that you can't keep track of.
But they're described by the same kind of description,
but you can't keep track of them.
That's all.
The Lagrangian equations don't describe friction.
Would you define a potential that
is a big sort of lacking?
I mean,
it's a major thing in the world.
What's that?
Friction is a major thing in the world.
It seems like there's no such thing
as friction at the level of elementary particles.
There's no such thing as friction at
the level of electrons and protons and neutrons.
Friction is a statistical effect of lots and
lots of particles that you just can't see.
Do you know how Hamilton arrived at his formulation?
Was he playing with energy and said,
oh,
it has this form?
I really don't know.
I wasn't there.
No,
I'm just kidding.
I don't know.
No,
We're working on it.
Right.
You said that Lagrangian is not always T minus V.
Is there some more general expression
for Lagrangian?
How do you get to those
regimes that aren't T minus V?
Experiment,
guess,
or some symmetry principle.
But conceptually,
though,
is it the case that the
energy is not always T minus V?
No,
it's the same thing,
but I'm just kidding.
So,
what if you're correct to say
that to build a Lagrangian function,
you're going
to have energy terms that correspond to kinetic
energy and then you're going to subtract the
sum of everything else that contributes to energy?
What?
If you're going to construct a Lagrangian function,
right,
it seems like you're adding
up a bunch of energy terms.
So,
you have to have some concept
of what might be the energy.
I know,
I know.
But,
you know,
if we were studying calculus and I said,
here are the rules for doing a
derivative,
you do the following things,
F of X plus epsilon
minus F of X divided by
epsilon.
Would you raise your hand and say,
where do you get the function from?
This is a calculus.
This is a calculus of,
it's a systematic calculus of the function of the energy.
It's a calculus that underlies classical mechanics.
The fact that real systems conform to this,
experiment,
guess,
or symmetry,
but basically
it's an abstract mathematical system.
It's an abstract mathematical system and if you
ask where do you get the pieces from,
these places.
How is it that,
one more,
I'll say it once more.
How is it that real nature,
classical nature,
conforms to this abstract system?
Quantum mechanics.
So there's nothing more to say.
There's nothing more to say except to
study this mathematical system and understand how
it works.
There is a little bit more.
We haven't gotten yet to the issues
of reversibility and how to do it.
But we have to study how and whether this
is related to the things that we talked about
in the very first lecture.
Remember what we talked about in the very first lecture?
Laws of physics which
were both reversible and deterministic.
And we meant something by that.
We meant that you don't lose information,
that trajectories don't run into each other.
In fact,
that this whole story is closely related to that.
We will get to it.
But in steps.
So I was just going to say that
going back to the Lagrangian for classical mechanics,
really the way we got it
was we went to variational calculus.
You went to what?
Yeah.
Variational calculus.
Well,
we started with the principle
of least action or stationary action.
Right.
But I mean even there,
the way you came up with the
function that you put in that integral
is just this working back from the answer.
You wanted one that would
give you the equations of motion,
right?
Well,
yes.
In that particular case,
So even for quantum mechanics,
is that the same way you get the Lagrangian?
You have the,
I don't know,
the Schrodinger .
Quantum mechanics logically begins with the Hamiltonian.
And then you work your way through to the Lagrangian.
And in quantum mechanics,
the Hamiltonian is a much,
much,
much more intuitive concept,
believe it or not.
Yeah.
The Hamiltonian and classical mechanics is an abstraction.
It's a deeply abstract thing.
And the Hamiltonian formulation of mechanics,
whereas in quantum mechanics,
it really is
very intuitive.
But we can't start with
quantum mechanics because it's too alien.
We need some concepts from
classical mechanics to start with.
One of these days,
maybe I'll try teaching it the other way.
We'll start with quantum mechanics.
Yeah.
We can do it.
And then derive classical mechanics as a limit.
Does the quantum mechanics,
can you describe friction in terms of quantum mechanics?
You cannot describe a particle moving,
for example,
through a viscous fluid by quantum
mechanics.
Without describing all the particles of the viscous fluid?
If you want to study a quantum mechanical
version of an object moving through a viscous
fluid,
it is necessary to keep track of all the particles.
String theory.
String theory,
same thing.
Friction is simply just a very,
very complicated effect of lots of particles.
Statistical.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.