Stanford University.
What I wanted to do first was
to show you the power of Lagrangians for
solving simple systems,
for solving simple problems.
I think I'll show you two of them,
two examples.
They're similar to each other.
I recommended last time that
people study the double pendulum.
And somebody,
I think it was Sanjay,
said,
why not a,
was it you who said,
somebody said take a wedge moving on
a frictionless plane with another block of
material sliding up and down,
who said that?
Yeah,
okay,
Leonard said that.
And yeah,
they're both interesting,
very similar problems,
in fact.
They're not hard problems.
You could solve them both using F equals ma.
It's a little tricky,
and you'd probably spend more
than a little bit of time
figuring out the double pendulum for sure.
That one would probably drive you crazy before
you figured out how to use F equals
ma to solve it.
The blocks sliding around,
a little bit easier.
But if you know the rules of Lagrangian mechanics,
it's a mechanical exercise.
A completely mechanical exercise,
you can be dumb as
hell and still solve the problem.
Sort of.
By incidentally,
by solving the problem,
the first problem is to find a good pin.
Solving the problem does not mean
necessarily solving the equations of motion.
It means finding the equations of motion.
Once you find the equations of motion,
you can put them onto a computer.
And numerically solve them.
They're just differential equations.
So I regard a mechanical problem as solved
when the equations of motion have been written
down.
For the purposes now.
Now often you want to do better than that.
Of course you want to do better than that.
But that can often be hard enough.
So let's begin with the
simple problem of an inclined wedge.
Or whatever.
Whatever we call it.
Sliding on a frictionless plane.
And it has another object over
here sliding up and down it.
Which for our purposes I'll
just take to be a very,
a point,
essentially a point particle.
Sliding up and down the plane.
The point particle has mass little m.
The wedge has mass big M.
And you can set it in motion.
And of course.
The rule of course.
Is that the little particle here is constrained.
Either mechanically constrained by some device.
Some sliders and other things.
But it's constrained to move
along the hypotenuse of the wedge.
Find the motion.
Find the motion of the system.
And of course the motion means
the motion of both things simultaneously.
But as I said.
What I mean is the equations of motion.
All right.
So the first step.
Is always to assign a set of coordinates.
You can think of them as generalized coordinates.
But sometimes it pays to just use Cartesian coordinates.
Sometimes it pays to use Cartesian coordinates.
We could either call them X's or Q's.
It doesn't matter.
But find a set of coordinates.
Which are sufficient to describe the motion of the system.
A set of coordinates.
Coordinates don't mean the motion.
Coordinates mean an instantaneous configuration.
So we want an instantaneous configuration of this system.
To be labeled by how many
coordinates does it take to describe it.
First question.
All right.
The assumption.
Let me state the assumption.
The assumption is that the wedge is
constrained to move along the frictionless surface here.
It may do it by itself.
Meaning to say it may be heavy enough.
To stay on the surface.
But if not.
We will constrain it by means of mechanical devices.
To slide only along the surface without friction.
And we also constrain the small
mass to move along the hypotenuse here.
Then how many degrees of freedom.
How many coordinates does it take to describe this.
Yes.
You're right.
Two is correct.
And for example.
I could give you.
The x.
Let the horizontal axis be x.
I could give you the x value.
Of the corner over here.
The x horizontal coordinate of the corner.
That would locate.
The.
The triangle for you.
And then I could also give you the.
Either the x component of this mass.
Or.
The distance along the hypotenuse.
Or the distance along the horizontal axis.
Let's use the x coordinate.
One thing is true.
In general.
The choice of such coordinates is by no means unique.
You just have to pick two of them.
And stick with them.
All right.
So I will choose for this example.
Not the distance along the hypotenuse.
Just to give.
Just to make some variation.
I will choose.
The horizontal coordinates.
So this one.
Let's call this one big x.
Which I'll.
Just to make sure we
don't confuse it with little x.
I'll.
Indicate it like that.
That's the position of the corner of the triangle.
Along the horizontal axis.
And then.
The.
The position of the mass here.
Relative.
To.
The.
Corner.
Relative to the corner.
Not relative to the x axis.
But relative to the corner.
I will choose another coordinate.
Little x.
Now.
I could also.
Have just used.
The x position of this.
Nothing wrong with that.
In other words.
Not the x position.
Relative.
To the corner here.
But just the x position.
Relative to.
To the.
To the zero.
To the origin of coordinates.
Both will work.
You get your choice.
But I decide.
I am going to.
Choose the two generalized coordinates.
Be the x position of this point.
And the little x position.
Of the mass.
Relative.
To the corner here.
In other words.
It is.
This distance over here.
All right.
So that is the first step.
Choose some coordinates.
Make sure that they are good coordinates.
Make sure.
That they are not redundant.
In other words.
Make sure that they are really sufficient.
To.
Encode.
The instantaneous state of the system.
First step.
Next step.
Write down the Lagrangian.
The Lagrangian is.
T minus V.
So.
The next step is.
T minus V.
And so.
Our next problem.
Is to find.
The kinetic energy.
Of the whole system.
Consists of.
The kinetic energy.
Of the moving block.
The moving wedge.
And also.
The kinetic energy.
Of.
Let's call this guy over here.
The particle.
Let's call it the particle.
All right.
This is easy to do.
The kinetic energy.
Of the wedge.
What is that?
That is just.
One hand.
Half.
Its mass.
Times.
Its horizontal velocity.
Squared.
And its horizontal velocity.
Is going to be.
Capital.
X.
Dot.
Squared.
That's the kinetic energy.
Of.
The block.
Next.
We want to compute.
The kinetic energy.
Of.
The small mass.
Here.
And here's where we have to be careful.
It's not one half.
M.
Little.
X.
Square.
Dot.
Squared.
It's actually one half.
Mass.
Times.
The actual.
Full.
Velocity.
Of this.
And the full velocity.
Of the particle.
Has two components.
One.
Is.
The rate.
At which.
Little.
X.
Is changing.
But that has to be.
Added.
To the velocity.
Of the block.
The velocity.
Of little.
M.
Let's.
Let's write it.
On the block.
To the right.
That's capital.
X.
Dot.
Plus.
The velocity.
The x.
Component.
Of.
This is the x.
Component.
Incidentally.
This is the velocity.
Of the mass.
Little.
M.
But the x.
Component.
Of it.
As opposed.
To the y.
Component.
Of it.
Okay.
So first of all.
It has capital.
X.
Dot.
But then.
The velocity.
Of.
That's the x.
Component.
What about the.
The y.
Component.
Of velocity.
Of.
Of a block.
That is.
To some extent.
Let's.
Let's write down.
The y.
Component.
V.
Little.
M.
Y.
Well.
We don't need.
An extra.
Y.
Coordinate.
To describe.
The.
Particle.
Here.
The.
Y.
Motion.
Is completely.
Dictated.
By the little.
X.
Motion.
Here.
Okay.
In fact.
We can write an equation.
That y.
Over.
X.
Is equal.
There's an angle.
Here.
I didn't write the angle.
What should we call the angle.
Alpha.
Nothing.
I don't want you to say.
Alpha.
Okay.
So that angle.
Is called.
Alpha.
And it's a number.
It's not something.
That's free.
To change.
And so.
Y.
Over.
X.
Is equal.
To tangent.
Of.
Alpha.
For example.
If.
For.
Forty.
Five.
Degrees.
Then.
Y.
And.
X.
Would.
Be.
Equal.
To.
Each.
Other.
All.
You know.
Just.
To.
Keep.
This.
A.
Really.
Clean.
Example.
Let's.
Actually.
Take.
The.
Example.
Where.
Alpha.
Is.
Forty.
Five.
Degrees.
You.
Can.
Work.
Out.
The.
Case.
With.
A.
General.
Angle.
The.
Particle.
Vertical.
Of.
X.
It.
Is.
Vertical.
Of.
A.
Particle.
Is.
Strictly.
Y.
Dot.
Which.
Is.
Equal.
To.
X.
Dot.
Or.
Tangent.
Alpha.
X.
Dot.
If.
and we can write the kinetic energy of the particle.
One half m,
little m,
standing for the particle mass over here,
over 2,
and then the x component of velocity squared,
that's capital X dot plus little x dot squared,
that's the x component of mv squared,
and then plus m over 2 y dot squared,
which is just another x dot squared,
little x dot squared.
That's the kinetic energy.
Now we can open it up
and work it out if we like.
Why not?
This is m over 2.
Let's leave it this way.
Let's just leave it.
There's no particular advantage to expanding it out.
What else goes into the Lagrangian?
Potential energy.
What potential energy is there?
Well,
I'm assuming that there's no forces acting,
explicit forces on the system,
acting in a horizontal direction.
No gravitational force pulling it horizontally,
but let's assume there's a gravitational...
There's a gravitational force pulling it vertically.
Then there would be the
gravitational force acting on big M,
but that's not important because
big M can't move vertically.
The potential energy of big M is fixed
by the fact that it's always at sea level,
whatever,
or at the level of the motion here.
So we don't need to write
down any potential energy for big M,
but we do need to write
down a potential energy for big M,
because its altitude can change.
In fact,
its altitude is just x.
So what's a good potential energy?
A good potential energy would be
V equals little mg times y,
or equivalently x.
So this is T,
potential kinetic energy,
sum of two terms,
and this is the energy.
And then we want to subtract the potential energy,
which is just minus...
Just subtracting it is just mg little x.
And that's all Lagrangian.
That's all there was to it.
How do we work out the equations of motion?
Euler-Lagrange equations.
Okay.
Um...
I don't particularly want to do that,
but...
But what I do want to do is
work out what the conservation of momentum says.
You can work out the equations of motion for this.
Well,
let's write down one or two things.
How about P capital X?
The momentum conjugate to capital X.
Now,
you might think it's just mx dot.
That would be the usual mechanical momentum of the thing,
but it's not the definition of momentum we've done.
It's the definition of momentum we've been using.
The definition of momentum as we've defined it
is the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to capital X dot.
That's its definition.
You got to stick with the definitions.
The derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to capital X dot...
Derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to capital X dot...
Is Px.
And what is it?
It is capital Mx dot.
The thing,
of course,
that we expect.
But then there's more to it from here.
From here,
there's plus m over 2.
Well,
the 2 is going to cancel.
And there's little m times
the derivative of this thing here
with respect to capital X dot.
And that's another factor of capital
X dot plus little x dot.
Everybody see what I did?
I differentiated what was in here
with respect to capital X dot.
And that just gives me capital
X dot plus little x dot.
That's the definition of the momentum conjugate to x.
What about the momentum conjugate to little x?
P sub little x is equal
to the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to little x dot.
What did I do here?
Did I?
Yeah.
OK.
Right.
What is that?
Everybody remember where this term came from?
It was the y motion.
I had forgotten for a second.
I was looking at where did that one come from?
Yeah,
that was the y motion.
OK.
So notice the y motion actually makes a
contribution to the x component of canonical momentum.
We'll call it,
that's the word for it,
canonical momentum conjugate to little x.
What is it?
It's m over 2 big
x dot plus little x dot.
Sorry,
not m over 2,
but just m,
big m.
No,
little m.
Little m from here,
and then another one from here,
plus another little m times little x dot.
Now,
this may surprise you.
You might have thought that
momentum is just good old momentum,
mv.
That is not the definition of momentum that we
use in the abstract mathematical system that's called classical mechanics.
So this is it.
These are the definitions of momentum.
Is there any conserved momentum?
Well,
is there any symmetry?
Is there any symmetry that this system has?
The answer is yes,
it does have a symmetry.
It has a translation symmetry.
But when you translate,
what do you have to do with little x?
Well,
first of all,
what happens when you translate the whole system?
What happens to big X?
You add a little constant to it,
right?
You add an epsilon or a delta to it.
What happens?
That's big X.
What happens to little x?
Nothing.
If you translate the whole thing and,
you know,
really translate it,
little m moves with big M.
So little x doesn't change when you translate.
Okay,
so let's write down the symmetry.
The symmetry is delta big X.
We can just,
we used to use delta.
But we wound up saying that
epsilon was a better symbol for it.
Just call it epsilon,
a little number.
What about little x?
Zero.
Okay.
Now let's work out the conserved quantity.
There is a conserved quantity.
We can be sure there's a conserved
quantity just because it has a symmetry.
And that conserved quantity,
Q,
is equal,
to the sum
of all the coordinates
of the corresponding momentum
times
the little change in the corresponding coordinate.
What is the,
the f function for this here?
The f function,
remember,
delta of the coordinates is equal to f times epsilon?
f is one.
What is the f function here?
Zero.
Okay,
so,
p times the corresponding f function
for capital X,
f is one,
for little x,
it's zero.
So there's only one term,
and it's just p capital X.
In other words,
as you might have expected,
the x component of momentum is conserved.
That's the conserved quantity.
But it's not the mass,
times the velocity of the block here.
That's not conserved.
Why isn't it conserved?
The reason it's not conserved is that because
there are forces between big M and little m.
Well,
you know,
if you try to give big M a push,
then there's a force exerted on little m,
little m exerts a back force on big M,
and there are forces on big M.
So the momentum,
the ordinary momentum,
the conventional momentum,
namely,
Mv,
of this block is not conserved.
What is conserved
is the canonical momentum conj...
Oh,
how do I know it's conserved?
Yeah,
I know it's conserved because there's a symmetry.
But we can look at the equation of motion.
We can look at the equation of motion
and say the equation of motion
is that px dot,
let's write it down,
let's get rid of this,
px dot is equal to what?
Derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to capital X.
There is no capital X in the Lagrangian.
There's only capital X dot.
Capital X itself does not appear in the Lagrangian.
It's a cyclic variable.
It's a cyclic variable
which simply doesn't appear in the Lagrangian.
And so this is equal to zero.
That's the conservation of momentum for this system.
And if you want to know what it really is,
it's capital M capital X dot
plus little m little x dot,
as you might have expected.
It's really the total momentum.
You can work that out.
Uh...
Um...
Okay.
Yeah,
it's true.
It's just the ordinary total momentum.
But it appears in this problem
as the momentum conjugate to capital X.
All right,
we can work out all of the equations of motion.
How about,
how about the vertical?
How about the,
um...
Is there a symmetry with respect to vertical motion?
No.
If you...
If you move...
The,
the,
uh,
the triangle is not allowed to move up and down.
And,
uh,
the,
um...
This thing only moves up
and down when the triangle moves,
but when it does move,
the potential energy changes.
So there's no corresponding component
of Y momentum that's conserved.
Uh,
so this is,
this was an easy one.
Let's see,
did we write down,
uh,
the equations of motion?
Well,
here's one equation of motion.
Let's write down the other one.
That one,
that was...
D by D,
uh,
T of P sub capital X,
and that was equal to zero,
because in the Lagrangian here,
there just is no dependence on capital X,
no explicit dependent on capital X.
What about,
um,
P sub little x dot?
That's equal to the derivative of
the Lagrangian with respect to little x.
Does little x appear?
Yeah,
little x appears right over here.
Okay?
So that's equal to minus the derivative
of the Lagrangian with respect to little x,
which I believe is,
um...
Uh...
Plus,
is it plus?
Yeah,
um,
the derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to,
minus the derivative,
yeah,
it's equal to Mgx.
No x,
right?
No x.
It's Mg.
Just Mg.
Thank you.
So it's a little bit
surprising that P sub x dot,
even though x is a horizontal coordinate,
nevertheless,
there is a gravitational field associated with it.
And of course the reason is
because x is equal to y.
Because x equals y,
there's a potential energy when you move little x,
and that manifests itself as
a right-hand side to the equation.
Should that be negative or positive?
Positive,
I think.
Px dot is equal to plus.
And the reason,
uh,
let's see,
am I right?
It's plus Pldx,
but Pldx itself has a negative side.
It depends on the direction of x.
Pldx has a minus sign,
but we're supposed to put minus
Pldx on the right-hand side here.
No.
We're supposed to put plus Pldx.
Excuse me.
Minus.
My mistake.
We have the minus over in
the Lagrangian because it's T minus V,
correct?
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Okay.
Right.
That's right.
So the equations are Pldx is equal to dv,
not minus.
Minus dv by dx.
Wait,
wait,
wait.
Yeah.
Yes.
Okay.
That's an example where it wouldn't be
terribly hard to write down the Newton equations,
F equals ma for the
block and for the particles separately,
but you'd also have to remember
that there are forces between them,
and you'd have to worry about the forces between them.
They're equal and opposite and so forth.
You'd have to solve for the forces between them.
In this context,
we never had to talk about the forces between them.
It just didn't enter into the discussion.
The forces between them are simply assumed
to be such that the constraint is satisfied,
namely that the particle stick stays on the inclined plane.
So it's much easier.
All right.
I'll show you the other example.
You can work this one out yourself.
It's a bit more tedious.
The example is the double pendulum.
Very similar in many ways.
The double pendulum is,
this is just a vertical axis.
Pendulum is suspended from a point up here.
Let's take the case where the pendulum length is one.
So that we don't have to keep
track of a bunch of irrelevant stuff.
And let's take the pendulum bob
over here to have unit mass.
So again,
we don't have to keep track.
This is a simple system,
but now we add to it a
second pendulum connected to the first pendulum.
Like that.
So they're both free to swing.
The length of each rod here,
of each pendulum rod,
is one.
And for simplicity,
let's take the mass of each bob,
the pendulum bob,
this one and this one,
to both also be one.
All right.
So how do we describe this system?
What are the first,
again,
rules?
First thing,
find a set of good coordinates for it.
Well,
it's pretty clear the good coordinates are angles.
When I say the good coordinates,
you're perfectly free to choose other coordinates.
But I have some instinct here
that this is an angular problem.
And so I guess it's not completely mechanical.
The choice of coordinates,
to some extent,
you want to choose coordinates
that make the problem easiest.
That can be an art.
But,
you know,
if you choose wrong coordinates or impractical coordinates,
it just means your equations will get long and ugly.
It doesn't mean that you'll be doing anything wrong.
All right.
So we really have two choices here.
The angle here,
I can't think of any possible reason why I would not use
the angle of the first pendulum relative to the horizontal as a coordinate.
The ambiguity,
and it's not an ambiguity.
It's not an ambiguity in the problem.
Again,
it's an ambiguity in how
you decide to solve the problem.
It concerns the second pendulum.
Do you want to choose the angle
relative to the vertical and call it something?
Or do you want to choose it relative to the line that
would be the extension of the first one and call it alpha?
Let's use the black chalk.
Okay.
All right.
So either phi,
which would be relative to the vertical,
or alpha,
which is relative to theta,
so to speak.
All right.
So we could take a vote.
But I'm not going to take a vote because I
happen to know the one which gives the easier answer.
The easier answer is to choose alpha like this.
Relative to this one.
Now let me tell you
why before we do anything else.
Let's forget for the moment the gravitational field.
Let's forget it.
This is just a thing swinging around.
If it were just a single pendulum,
there would be no gravitational field and it would
just swing around and around and around and around.
Let's take the single one first of all.
There's an obvious symmetry.
The obvious symmetry is just angular symmetry.
If there's no gravitational field,
then there's an obvious symmetry,
just rotation.
Well,
this is the same thing.
This system also has a rotation symmetry.
If you rotate the entire,
just keeping this angle fixed,
keeping this angle over here fixed,
rotate the entire thing,
that's also a symmetry if there is no gravitational field.
And that would be true no
matter how you choose to coordinate it.
But an advantage would be that
the symmetry option would be the same.
So,
the symmetry operation will only involve theta and not
alpha if we choose alpha to be relative to theta.
If we chose alpha to be relative to the vertical,
then when we rotate the whole system,
both theta and alpha both transform.
And it makes it a little more complicated,
but nothing that we couldn't handle.
Nevertheless,
we'll use alpha.
Okay.
So,
how do you figure out the kinetic energy?
Well,
you could try working directly with the angular variables,
but it's often a little more intuitive to say,
look,
let's work out the kinetic energy by starting with the kinetic energy
in Cartesian coordinates and then rewrite it in terms of the angles.
So,
it's often a good thing to realize that your objects are moving around
in Cartesian space and that the kinetic energy is just one-half mv squared.
All right.
So,
what you do is you say,
all right,
let's just for the moment,
as an auxiliary step here,
let's introduce the x component and the
y component of this pendulum bob here.
Notice I'm measuring y vertically downward.
It doesn't matter,
but just for variety,
we'll measure y downward.
So,
this is a positive y over here.
Okay.
So,
what is the relationship between xy and yy?
Well,
first of all,
x is equal to sine theta.
Y is equal to cosine theta.
So,
x and y are not new variables.
They're just sine theta and cosine theta.
That's all.
However,
we can also write the velocity of this pendulum bob.
X dot is equal to theta dot times cosine theta.
And y dot is equal to theta
dot minus theta dot times sine theta.
We just differentiated with respect to time,
found x dot and found y dot.
Here are our components of velocity.
We really don't need x and y anymore.
But now we also need
to know the components of velocity.
We need to know the components of
the velocity of this guy over here.
Also,
a unit rod here.
And to do that,
we have to figure out what the x
and y components of this guy are over here.
What should we call them?
Herman.
Hmm?
Last time it was Herman.
Herman?
Okay,
Herman.
But I need a symbol for Herman.
It's not a question of what his name is.
It's a question of what
symbol do we use for Herman.
Let's call it x prime and y prime.
X prime and y prime.
Okay,
so what are x prime and y prime?
Alright.
Here,
it is convenient to think of
the angle relative to the vertical.
The angle relative to the vertical is alpha plus theta.
Okay?
Good.
What is x prime?
x prime,
let's write it here,
x prime is going to equal
x plus sine of theta plus alpha.
Is that clear?
Sine of theta plus sine theta plus alpha.
That's just this bit of it over here.
So I added this bit to this bit.
But x I already know.
It's sine of theta.
So x prime is sine of
theta plus sine of theta plus alpha.
What about y prime?
Y prime is going to equal y,
which is cosine theta,
plus this bit over here,
which is cosine theta.
Which is just going to
be cosine of theta plus alpha.
What about the velocity of this one here?
We just differentiate with respect to time.
And we find that x prime
dot is equal to x dot,
which is theta dot cosine theta.
Plus the time derivative of this.
Sorry,
did I write?
Theta.
Theta,
thank you.
Plus the time derivative of this,
which is plus theta dot plus alpha
dot times cosine of theta plus alpha.
Is that right?
Mm-hmm.
Minus cosine,
right?
Or minus cosine.
Derivative of sine is cosine.
Yeah,
right.
We also have y dot squared,
y prime dot squared.
I'm not going to write it.
It does involve some minus signs and so forth.
What do we do with this?
We write down the kinetic energy of the two objects.
One of the kinetic energies is just
x dot squared plus y dot squared.
That's just theta dot squared.
Why?
Because cosine squared plus sine squared is 1.
So there's one term,
which is theta dot squared.
But there's also x prime dot
squared and y prime dot squared.
And it's a bit of a mess.
It's not too bad.
You spend a few minutes,
probably of order 60 seconds.
I can probably do it in 45 seconds.
You can probably do it in 60 seconds.
I'll write it down for you just to show
you the type of thing that I'm talking about.
This is the kinetic energy,
t.
Kinetic energy is equal to theta dot squared plus theta dot plus alpha dot squared
over 2 plus theta dot times theta dot minus alpha dot times cosine of alpha.
OK.
Thank you.
What about the potential energy?
Excuse me.
Yeah.
Sorry,
I missed that.
Is that the kinetic energy
obtained by adding together the two?
Yeah.
x dot squared plus y dot squared plus x prime
dot squared plus y prime dot squared over a half.
Yeah.
There's no,
I didn't make a mistake.
There is no missing half here.
There were two terms.
And I combined them together.
This is the kinetic energy.
Let's for the moment forget potential energy.
Let's not think of this as a
pendulum for a minute and look at this.
Is there a conserved quantity?
Well,
it better be a conserved quantity
because if there is no gravitational field,
then there's a rotation symmetry.
And the way to see it
is that there's a cyclic coordinate here.
Which is the cyclic coordinate?
It's the one that doesn't appear in the Lagrangian.
It's theta.
Theta doesn't appear in the Lagrangian.
And that means alpha does.
Alpha does.
It's cosine alpha.
But theta itself doesn't.
By theta appearing,
I mean without a time derivative.
Theta without a time derivative.
It doesn't appear.
And so you can be sure
that whatever p sub theta is,
its time derivative is going to be zero.
Let's not work it out.
You can work it out yourself.
You just differentiate the Lagrangian
with respect to theta dot.
And you'll find a conserved quantity.
The conserved quantity really is.
Just the sum of the
angular momenta of the two bobs,
or the two pendulum bobs.
But you don't even need to
know how to calculate the angular momentum.
You just say,
look at this thing.
There was a symmetry.
In this particular case,
it was just the fact
that there was a cyclic coordinate.
And a corresponding conserved quantity.
Had you used the other coordinate,
namely the one relative to the vertical,
neither coordinate would be.
Cyclic.
But you still would have found a
conserved quantity if you went through the rules.
Okay?
So.
And it would be the same conserved quantity.
All right.
So those are just two examples.
And believe me,
if you wanted to do the double
pendulum here by F equals M A,
that would be a little bit nasty.
But here we got it.
Once you get the Lagrangian,
you got the equations of motion.
You have the conservation law.
There is one.
Oh,
we left out one thing.
Yeah.
We did leave out the gravitational force.
Now that would violate the rotational symmetry.
And you wouldn't have a conservation law.
But let's just write down what it would be.
What's the potential energy?
The potential energy is M G times the Y coordinate.
It's actually times minus the Y coordinate.
And the minus the Y coordinate involves cosine theta.
So the potential energy,
this would be the potential energy.
And we would subtract it.
So T minus V would be,
did I do this right?
No.
No,
no,
no.
I did not do it right.
No,
no,
no.
That's only the first mass.
And incidentally,
since the mass is one,
it's just G cosine theta.
That's only the first.
So the potential energy of this one and the potential
energy of the other one would be minus M G cosine.
I guess it's cosine of alpha plus theta.
Just the height of this one.
No,
it's cosine theta plus cosine alpha plus theta,
right?
You're right.
Yeah.
Whatever it is.
It's the height.
The height,
which is the sum of these two.
You're right.
It's the sum of two cosines.
And you write it out.
And there's some potential energy
here that you can write down.
Once you've written the potential
energy and the kinetic energy,
to find the equations of motion,
you just mechanically work out Lagrange equations of motion.
So in that sense,
the Lagrangian is a very compact,
easy way to take a complicated system,
which in this case has rods.
It has all kinds of things going on.
The rods,
when the rods try to stretch,
they exert forces.
All sorts of complicated things go on that you'd
have to take into account in F equals M A.
And it's automatically taken into account.
So that's the power of the Lagrangian formulation.
The simulation of mechanics.
Yeah.
Question for T minus beta.
Should that dot minus alpha dot
be theta dot plus alpha dot?
Very likely.
Maybe.
I don't know.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
I think so.
You're right.
Yeah.
I think that's right.
Well,
one of the two of these is wrong,
I'm sure.
Let's see.
Which one?
When you take the x dot prime and square that,
you have to write that.
Right behind you.
You get a theta dot term.
This,
I think,
should be minus.
And this,
I think,
should be minus.
That's what I have in my notes anyway.
But my notes could conceivably be wrong.
Depends on which direction is positive for alpha.
Right.
It does.
And we're not going to worry about it.
You get the point.
You can fiddle with it yourselves.
It's a...
You know,
this thing can be solved.
The two combined equations,
there's another concern.
What's the other...
Even with the gravitational field,
but especially without the gravitational field,
it's not hard
to solve.
Even with the gravitational field,
it's not hard.
To solve it,
you need to use two conservation laws.
What's the other conservation law?
Energy.
T plus V.
If you write down that T plus
V is fixed and call it energy,
and the angular
momentum you call just a fixed energy.
All that'sHoist power.
Absolutely,
you're right,
고C dov
transform?
statues .
An growth...
Is there a way that
you can see that it's chaotic
from looking at the equations?
No,
not really.
And in fact,
sometimes there are systems
which have transitions as you change parameters.
They can go from not chaotic to chaotic.
So no,
there's usually no easy way.
Yeah?
And if you don't know what chaotic is,
don't worry.
We'll come back to it.
For conserved systems,
p dot has got all of that .
Say it again.
For conserved systems,
p dot always has equal 0.
p dot always equals 0?
Yeah.
No,
p dot is equal to dv by d,
is equal to the derivative
of the Lagrangian with respect to theta,
which in many cases
is just the derivative of the potential energy
with respect to theta.
It's only equal to 0 here because the Lagrangian doesn't
involve theta.
It's a cyclic coordinate.
OK.
Yeah?
The momentum conjugate to a cyclic coordinate.
Yeah.
The momentum conjugate to a cyclic coordinate
is always conserved.
And that's a special case of the symmetry idea.
It's a special case where
the symmetry acts on only one
coordinate.
All the others are left fixed by the symmetry.
OK.
So for example.
Here,
the symmetry operation acts on theta,
but keeps alpha unchanged.
So when the symmetry is defined,
or when
you define your coordinates in a clever way
so that only one of
them shifts under the symmetry operation,
that's when you have a cyclic coordinate.
But as I said,
you don't have to be clever in your choice
of coordinates.
If your goal is to
write down the equations in motion
and stick them on a table.
You can write down the equations on a computer.
And you don't care how complicated they are.
Any set of coordinates will work.
Yeah?
Pardon my ignorance here.
But suppose that we just have
a single pendulum and no gravitational force.
OK.
Then we give it any kind of motion.
It's just going to go around and around.
That's conservation of angular momentum.
Right.
And if we have a double pendulum,
then if both of them
start out with no motion,
it's just going to sit there.
Right.
But if we give them each an initial velocity,
then.
Yeah.
It does.
That's correct.
And it can do extremely complicated things.
And still,
the angular momentum is conserved.
OK.
So yeah.
Without gravity,
though,
the theta dot and alpha dot
are constant,
right?
No.
So the angular velocity of each.
I don't think so.
Let's see.
OK.
No.
I don't think so.
Let's work out.
OK.
Let's work out the equations of motion.
Let's work out the equations of motion and see.
OK.
To say that theta dot is constant is
to say that theta double dot is 0.
Right?
That's really just a question because it's so .
Well,
that's the definition of what they.
Right.
So let's check.
Let's work out the equations of motion.
Partial of L with respect to theta dot.
We're first going to work out p sub theta.
So that's theta dot from here.
It's twice theta dot from here.
Right.
dL by d theta dot.
What about from here?
There it'll give us plus theta
dot minus alpha dot from here.
And then from here another twice theta dot.
And then minus alpha dot.
Does that look right?
Yeah.
That's cosine alpha.
Cosine alpha.
Let's see.
This times cosine alpha.
Right?
Yeah.
And what does that equal?
That equals dL by d theta,
which is 0.
Or another one.
No.
What is this?
This is p sub theta.
dL by d theta dot.
OK.
Now we want to time differentiate it.
We want to take d by dt of this
and set it equal to dL by d theta.
All right.
So let's take the time derivative of this.
The time derivative of this has theta double dot,
theta double dot,
alpha double dot.
Now it has two terms from here.
One of them is to
differentiate the thing inside the bracket.
The other is to differentiate the cosine alpha.
So there will be one term
which will be theta double dot,
cosine alpha,
alpha double dot.
And then there will be twice theta dot minus
alpha dot times another alpha dot with a minus
sine times sine of alpha.
Coming from differentiating the cosine alpha.
And that is a thing which is equal to 0.
OK.
So what is the derivative of theta?
To the derivative of respect to theta.
The derivative of Lagrangian respect to theta.
This is the first term in Euler-Lagrange.
The second term is the derivative
of the Lagrangian respect to theta.
Say it again.
Which is 0.
The L d theta is 0.
There's no theta in here.
Oh,
OK.
Right.
This is in the absence of a gravitational field.
Good.
Yeah.
So this is just 0.
Now,
this is the thing which is 0.
Not theta double dot.
Not necessarily alpha double dot.
And in fact,
what's going on is they're exerting torques on each other.
Their motion,
their relative motion and the swinging
is exerting torques on each other.
And the effect is that theta
double dot is not equal to 0.
Alpha double dot is not equal to 0.
We can write out the other equation also,
the equation for alpha.
You know how to do it.
But no,
the answer is no.
The angular velocities of the
individual bobs will not be conserved.
It's the angular momentum that's conserved.
And they transfer angular momentum
back and forth between them.
You know what it's like?
Supposing you just have two particles on a spring.
The two particles move off.
Momentum is conserved.
Do the individual accelerations,
are the individual accelerations 0?
No.
They go like this.
They exchange momentum back and forth.
And neither velocity is constant.
It's true the center of mass velocity is constant.
Well,
there's an analog of the center
of mass motion for the rotations.
But it's not this angle.
It's not this angle.
It's some combination of the two of them.
So there is some kind of
notion of the center of angular,
center of,
it's actually center of moment of inertia.
That is,
that,
but it's neither alpha dot nor theta dot.
They just transfer energy and
momentum back and forth between them.
In this case,
the forces are going through the rods,
right?
The forces are going through the rods.
Yeah.
Right.
But if you look at this one over here,
there's a force on this particle going this way.
And there's a force on this one
going this way or something like that.
There is a net torque on this.
All right.
So that means there would be a
net force in this direction over here,
something like that.
And that force is a torque on this.
So it's going to go in
this angular direction here and accelerate,
causes an acceleration of theta.
If you don't know what a torque is,
it doesn't matter.
It's just a force which tends to rotate things.
Okay.
Now we want to come to the Hamiltonian.
The Hamiltonian is energy.
And that,
of course,
is one of the very great significances of the Hamiltonian.
It is energy,
and it's conserved.
But the Hamiltonian is the basis of
another distinct and new formulation of mechanics.
We have three formulations.
The first,
so far.
The first is Newton's equations.
The next is the principle of least action.
Which is the same as
the Euler-Lagrange or Lagrangian formulation.
And the third,
did I say there were three already?
I only count two.
Am I right?
Hmm?
Hmm.
The third formulation is the Hamiltonian formulation.
And it looks different than either of them.
It's equivalent.
But it looks different than either of them.
And it also,
in its own way,
has enormous power.
I'm sort of tempted at this point to go something,
back to something in the very first lecture.
And tell you to keep your eyes open
for something like this happening in Hamiltonian mechanics.
Remember we discussed various laws
of dynamics for simple systems.
We had one like that.
We had a six-sided die,
which we had various kinds
of laws that we made up.
And we said these are good laws.
But we also talked about bad laws.
Bad laws,
for example,
would be this.
This law is deterministic.
It tells you where to go next,
no matter where you are.
But it fails to be able
to tell you where to go next.
It tells you where you were in the past.
If you find yourself at this point,
you could have come from here,
or you could have come from here.
These are bad laws.
I told you in the beginning that the
analog of these bad laws are forbidden in physics.
The easiest way to see that they're forbidden,
or the analog idea,
is from Hamiltonian physics.
From the Hamiltonian.
We're going to find that the Hamiltonian,
that an analog of the same
thing will be forbidden in Hamiltonian physics.
Now what characterizes this?
Here's another example.
Let me draw another example.
A node at the center,
several states around it,
and here's a law,
a possible law,
or an impossible law.
If you're here,
you go here.
And in fact,
no matter where you are,
you wind up here.
Where do you stay after that?
You just stay there.
Deterministic as hell,
but not reversible.
Notice that in these laws,
there is often a sense of convergence.
A sense of convergence that there are more arrows pointing
in to a point than there are arrows going out.
That's the kind of forbidden thing.
And of course,
the opposite is also forbidden.
Namely,
a divergence where arrows come out of a point.
And I suppose we can have
this one go around to itself again.
This time,
we can't even say what the future is.
we can say what the past is,
but we can't say what the future is.
If we're over here,
we don't know where to go next.
Do we go here?
And so forth.
Neither a divergence nor a convergence is allowed.
If our laws of physics are intended to be reversible.
Yeah?
Just a question.
The top right hand diagram,
the forbidden one?
This one?
Yeah.
Now,
if you put that in a gravitational field...
Put what in a gravitational field?
You've got to look at the
bottom and point at the top.
You're reading too much into this.
These are just three abstract states.
You spin a rope trigger,
and they just change places.
Okay.
But you're reading too much into it.
So it's cyclical.
This law of physics is not cyclical.
If you start here,
you go there,
and then you go here,
here,
here.
It's cyclical after a certain point,
but it never cycles back to here.
So how do you differentiate the bottom forbidden state from,
let's say,
something like a black hole?
Right.
With difficulty.
With difficulty and subtlety.
Let's not...
It's a fair question,
but I won't answer it.
Okay.
Keep in your head the idea that the flow associated with
the law of physics should not have a divergence or a convergence.
Keep that in your head.
That's the meaning,
the ultimate meaning of reversibility,
even at this point that I haven't
told you what convergence and divergence mean,
except in the last two sentences.
Okay.
Let's define or prove or work out,
derive,
Hamilton's equations of motion.
Now,
in Hamilton's equations of motion,
the focus is not on
the q's and the q dots.
It's on the q's and the p's.
What are the p's?
The p's are the momentum conjugate to the q's.
Okay.
The number of things that you need to know to get
a mechanical system started are twice the number of degrees of freedom,
twice the number of q's.
It could be the q's and the q dots,
or it could be the q's and the p's.
In fact,
in general,
for good mechanical systems,
the q dots...
Okay.
...can be solved for in terms
of the q's and the p's.
I'm going to give you some
examples to show you how this works.
So that the q dots can always be
thought of as functions of q's and p's,
and you forget them,
and you think about the q's and the p's.
I'm going to show you how this works.
This may be a little bit obscure right now,
but I'll show you how it works.
Okay.
So,
the focus is on the q's and the p's.
And we're going to find that there's
a symmetry between the q's and the p's.
Not the kind of symmetry
we've talked about up till now,
but a kind of equality between them.
That does not mean that p is equal to q.
It means they're sort of on
the same footing in the Hamiltonian formulation.
In the Lagrangian formulation,
the p's were just these wacky things where you
differentiate the Lagrangian with respect to the q dots.
In the Hamiltonian formulation,
it's the p's and the q's and the Hamiltonian.
And the Hamiltonian is thought of as
a function of the p's and q's.
No q dots ever appear...
Well,
q dots appear,
but not in the formulation of the Hamiltonian.
Okay.
So,
let's start...
Okay.
With an example.
Let's do an example.
I think it's best to start with an example.
Let me remind you what the Hamiltonian is.
The Hamiltonian is equal to the sum over
all the coordinates of q dot times p.
I won't bother putting little i's in.
Sum over all the coordinates minus the Lagrangian.
We worked that out last time.
And we found out that as
a consequence of the Euler-Lagrange equations,
this quantity is conserved.
I'm not going to do it again.
This quantity is conserved.
It's the conserved energy.
And it's the Hamiltonian.
Okay.
Now I want you to think in the back of your mind that
q dot can always be re-expressed in terms of the q's and p's.
So think of this Hamiltonian not as
a function of q dot p and q.
But think of it as just
a function of p and q.
Let's work out an example to see how this works.
The example is the good old harmonic oscillator.
I'm going to take the harmonic oscillator with a Lagrangian,
t minus v.
Here's the Lagrangian.
Now,
why am I writing it this way?
I'm writing it this way because it's
the simplest way to write the Lagrangian.
The Lagrangian for harmonic oscillator.
What is the parameter?
What is the important parameter about the harmonic oscillator
which comes in as a numerical parameter into the oscillator?
Omega.
You might say m and k,
meaning the mass and the spring constant.
But in fact,
by a suitable change of variables
and a rescaling of the coordinate,
you can get rid of m and k.
And replace it by just omega.
I'm going to assume that's done.
And it doesn't matter how it's done.
You can just take this as a Lagrangian.
As a sample Lagrangian.
One over twice omega times q dot
squared minus omega over two q squared.
This is kinetic energy.
And either because I just like
putting a one over two omega there.
Or because you can always do it.
You can always rearrange the
harmonic oscillator to look like this.
Notice the omega goes in the
denominator here and the numerator here.
This is kinetic energy.
This is potential energy.
This is a restoring force.
And omega is just a parameter.
Okay.
Let's work out the various things
that appear on the left hand side.
In this Hamiltonian side.
First of all is p.
What is p?
p is the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to the velocity.
And that's just equal to q dot over omega.
Right?
q dot over omega is p.
But instead of reading this p
is equal to q dot over omega.
I'm going to read it the other way.
q dot is omega times p.
In other words,
I'm going to read this as telling me
what q dot is in terms of p.
Instead of p in terms of q dot.
I haven't done anything very brilliant.
I've just expressed q dot in terms of p.
And now we're going to rewrite the Hamiltonian.
Alright.
So the Hamiltonian then.
Here it is.
h of q and p is equal.
There's only one coordinate in this case.
There's no sum.
q dot times p.
But q dot is omega times p.
So what do I get?
I get omega.
I get omega p squared.
Omega p squared.
Now we have to subtract the Lagrangian.
So we have to subtract.
I'm going to do it in two pieces.
One over two omega.
And what is q dot squared?
q dot squared is omega squared p squared.
Okay.
So let's write it.
Minus one over two omega.
p squared omega squared.
Oh,
that's nice.
The omega in the denominator is canceling.
It's canceled by one of the omegas in the numerator.
Keep in mind.
But I want to write down the last term.
The last term in minus l
is plus omega over two q squared.
Okay.
So notice what happened here.
The q dot p term combines
with the kinetic term in the Lagrangian.
Here's the kinetic term in the Lagrangian.
It's being subtracted off.
It's not omega squared p squared.
It's a half omega squared p squared.
Let's cancel out the omega here.
This and this are the same
except for the factor of two.
So what do I get?
I get omega p squared over
two plus omega q squared over two.
q squared plus p squared.
That's the Hamiltonian.
And the important things that I want you to come away
with is that when you're doing the Hamiltonian version of classical mechanics,
you get rid of the q dots.
You get rid of the
q dots by solving for them.
Now,
sometimes you can't solve equations.
Not because you're not good at it.
Not because you're not powerful
enough to solve the equations.
But because the equations don't have solutions.
You can write down Lagrangians for
which there will not be solutions.
They're bad systems.
They're systems which cannot come from quantum mechanics.
So unless it's possible to solve for
the velocities in terms of the momenta,
this is not considered a legitimate Lagrangian.
Even though there may be sensible Euler-Lagrange equations.
All right.
So that's the idea of a Hamiltonian.
You write down q dot p minus L.
It depends on q dots.
But you get rid of the q dots
by solving for them in terms of the p's.
And now you have the Hamiltonian.
Okay.
Let's think about this for a moment.
This is kind of interesting.
Omega over two times q squared plus p squared.
Oh.
If you think it was magic and a wonderful thing that
the omega came out in the numerator in both terms here.
I set it up that way.
I did it on purpose.
That's why I put the omega
in the way that I did.
So that in the Hamiltonian it
would just come out as a factor.
Okay.
There was no magic there.
It just was a trick that I did.
I did it in the Lagrangian so that
it would come out this way in the Hamiltonian.
Okay.
So the energy,
the Hamiltonian is the energy.
It's proportional,
first of all,
to omega.
But to q squared plus p squared.
One of the things we're going to learn
to do is to draw diagrams of the motion.
This is phase space.
And phase space is the space
of the q's and the p's.
Q horizontally,
p vertically.
Now,
of course,
once we go beyond one degree of freedom,
we won't be able to draw it on the blackboard.
If we have two degrees of freedom,
then we have four variables altogether.
Three degrees of freedom,
six variables.
But at least we can draw q
p space for one degree of freedom.
Q p.
Think of these,
think of this function here.
This function is constant with respect to time.
Now,
what are the surfaces or what are the
trajectories of constant q squared plus p squared?
They're circles.
They're circles of different radius.
Different radius means different values
of q squared plus p squared,
and therefore different values of energy.
So here's what we've learned.
We've learned that the system,
the harmonic oscillator system,
moves through phase space
with time on circular trajectories.
Oh,
actually,
I think they're going to,
if I remember correctly,
I think they go the other way,
clockwise rather than counterclockwise.
They move on,
the system moves on circular trajectories.
Whatever the value of q squared
plus p squared when you begin,
it must stay that.
That means it has to stay in a circle.
Why must it stay that?
Because we already know that this thing is the energy,
and energy better be conserved.
On the other hand,
we should try to see what
the equations of motion actually say,
but in particular,
what the equations of motion say
in Hamiltonian form.
So this is just an observation that
with the notations that I've used here,
the q's and the p's move on circles.
Wherever you start the system,
wherever you start the system,
any place you start the system,
it'll be on one of these circles,
and then it will just move in a circle.
I keep drawing counterclockwise.
I think it's clockwise orbit indefinitely,
forever and ever.
You know what this is like?
We talked about conservation laws the first day.
We talked about,
for example,
laws of physics like this.
This is a good law.
This is a good law of physics.
This is a law of physics for the die.
If you're on a cycle,
if the laws of physics,
if the laws of motion
happen to divide the space up
into separate cycles,
then there's a conservation law.
The conservation law simply corresponds
to which cycle you're on.
If you're on here,
you never get off there.
Well,
it's a very similar situation.
If you're on this trajectory,
you stay there.
You never get off it.
If you're on this one,
you never get off it.
It's just energy conservation.
There are other conservation laws,
and therefore other surfaces in which you get trapped on.
But this will do for the harmonic oscillator now.
Okay.
What I want to do in the remaining time tonight
is to derive Hamilton's equations.
To derive Hamilton's equations
and to show you how
they work for the harmonic oscillator.
And that will be enough for tonight.
We use a standard trick of calculus.
If we have a function of some variables,
let's say Q's and P's,
and I make a little
disturbance of the Q's and P's,
I move them a little bit in the phase space,
the function changes.
If the function is a non-trivial function,
it changes.
How much does it change?
I'm not changing with time,
just changing because we've moved the point
a little bit in phase space.
Just the functional dependence.
What's the change in F?
The change in F is given by
the partial derivative of F with respect to Q
times delta Q
plus the partial derivative of F
with respect to P
delta P.
This is just standard calculus of two variables.
The change is the change in F
because you changed Q a little bit
times the little change in Q
plus the F by dP little change in P.
That's standard.
You can read it the other way.
You can say if somebody gave you
that the change in F
was proportional to something,
let's just call it a thing over here,
let's not call it the F by dQ,
let's call it A,
and let's call this one over here B.
Somebody told you that the change in F is
A times delta Q
plus B times delta P,
you could read off that
that A must be the partial derivative of F
with respect to Q
and B must be the partial derivative of F
with respect to P.
So you can read it in two ways.
One way is just to say,
look,
this is what we know from calculus.
The other way is to say,
look,
if I give you delta F
and it's got an A and a B,
then A and B must be these derivatives.
Okay,
that's the trick.
That's a central trick
to so much of classical mathematics.
Or the derivations in classical mechanics.
And we've used it before,
but let's apply it to the Hamiltonian,
the Hamiltonian itself.
Let's write the change in the Hamiltonian
when I change,
when I make a little change,
whatever that change happens to be.
Except now,
I'm not going to tell you
what the Hamiltonian is,
in terms of Q and P.
I'm just going to tell you
that it's Q dot P minus L.
I'm going to go back to this equation over here.
And I'm going to say,
what's the change in the Hamiltonian
if I change things a little bit?
Whatever it is that I'm going to change.
I'm going to change Q,
Q dot P,
everything,
whatever it is that I change.
All things.
What's the change in H?
Let's write it over here.
Let's do it over here.
Change in H,
change in Q dot P.
Well,
first of all,
there's a sum.
There will be a Q dot times delta P.
There will be a change in Q dot times P.
The change in a product
is the change in one factor times the other.
Here's the change in P times Q dot.
And the change in the
other factor times the first one.
That's it.
And then there's minus the change in the Lagrangian.
Minus the change in the Lagrangian.
And the change in the Lagrangian
is the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to Q dot
times the change in Q dot
minus the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to Q
times the change in Q.
I'm writing it as if there were only one coordinate.
You can put back all the summation signs
and you'll,
and you will,
and the little sub I's.
Oh,
I actually put a summation sign here,
didn't I?
Yeah.
This is,
I've changed everything that could be changed.
Q dot P,
get this term,
and in L,
we can also change Q dot and Q.
There's nothing else to change,
and this must be the change in the Hamiltonian.
Okay,
some things cancel.
Fortunately,
it looks kind of ugly,
but some things change.
Let's,
some things cancel.
What's the L by the Q dot?
Oh,
the L by the Q dot,
thank you.
Okay,
what is the L by the Q dot?
P.
This is P delta Q dot.
But here's P delta Q dot.
Magic.
We get rid of it.
I'll let you stare at it
again before I get rid of it.
The L by the Q dot is P,
and so these two things cancel.
That's nice.
All right,
so we have Q dot delta P,
and here we have the L by the Q.
What is the L by the Q?
It's the time derivative of the momentum.
P dot.
Right.
So let's put that in.
Minus,
minus P dot times delta Q.
That's it.
That's the whole change in the Hamiltonian
when I change Q dot P
is when I change everything in sight.
The Hamiltonian changes by that much.
Now keep in mind at the end of the day,
we're going to want to replace the Q dots
by some functions of P.
Q dots will be functions of P,
but for the moment,
here we are.
Well,
now let's compare that with this equation over here.
The change in a function when
you change Q a little bit
is the F by the Q.
When you change P a little bit,
it's the F by the P.
So now look what I can do.
I can read off from here that the change,
that the derivative of H with respect to P,
that's the change in H when
I change P a little bit,
is the Q velocity.
And the other equation is
that the derivative of the Hamiltonian
with respect to Q is minus P dot.
And there's an equation like this for each I.
That's it.
That's the whole upshot of Hamilton's equations.
These are Hamilton's equations.
If you know the Hamiltonian as
a function of Q and P,
then Hamilton's equations of motion are
just differentiate H with respect to P,
and that gives you Q dot,
differentiate H with respect to Q,
and that gives you minus P dot.
One of the things you see is how
parallel Q and P come into the equations.
Okay,
there is a little sign change here,
but apart from that sign change,
Q and P come in in
an entirely parallel manner into Hamilton's equations.
These are Hamilton's equations.
Let's apply them to the harmonic oscillator.
Let's apply them and see what it tells
us about the motion of the harmonic oscillator.
Oh,
one other thing.
Well,
okay,
let's do it for the harmonic oscillator.
How many equations do I now have altogether?
How many Lagrangian equations were there?
If there are n coordinates,
how many Lagrangian equations?
n.
How many Hamiltonian equations?
2n.
Right.
The Hamiltonian equations are first order in time,
and there are twice as many of them.
The Lagrangian equations are second order,
and there are half as many of them.
So let's work out,
let's take the Hamiltonian for the
harmonic oscillator as a prime example.
What did I say it was?
Omega over 2.
times p squared plus q squared.
That was it.
That's the Hamiltonian.
Here it is in terms of p and q,
it's a function of p and q.
And I can now read off
what the equations of motion are.
It's really simple.
So we start with dh by dp.
dh by dp.
And what is that?
that's Omega P right Omega P and that's
equal to Q dot this is just a statement
that the momentum is proportional to
the velocity no not too surprising momentum
proportional to velocity okay but now let's
write the other equation the H by
D Q what is that that's Omega times Q
and that's equal to minus P dot these two
are the equations of motion for the
harmonic oscillator let's just go see how
we see that these are equations of
motion for the harmonica they don't look
they may not look familiar to you
but one step makes them familiar take this
equation and take its time derivative
why what am I getting at
the familiar equations are the
second-order equations F equals ma right
so let's work out the second-order equations
let's get rid of P and see if
we can find a second-order equation for
the coordinate Q to do that we just
differentiate the Q equation once with
respect to time that gives us the
acceleration Q double dot is
equal to Omega times P dot
you
just differentiating this one good because now
we have P dot down here is
minus Omega Q so we get Q double
dot equals minus Omega squared Q this of
course is the standard harmonic
oscillator equation of motion for an
oscillator with frequency Omega
we're not going to solve it right now
you mostly know how to solve it with
sines and cosines and it it is just
the oscillator but in this form here if you
look at this form here and you go
back to the circles in phase space all this
is
these two equations the equations for P and
Q that tell you what p-dot is or
that tells you what q-dot is as a
function of P and what p dot is a
function of Q it's simply the equation
that tells you that things move around
on the circle with constant
angular velocity constant and angular velocity
but constant Omega and that Omega is
independent of the distance they all move
all the points on the phase space
wherever you start the whole thing just
rotates around with frequency Omega wherever
you are for example if you're
over here you just rotate around with
frequency Omega if you're over here you
rotate around with the same frequency so
the whole thing just rotates like a
rigid pinwheel like a rigid pinwheel
and that's the way a Hamiltonian
physicist would think about the motion
of the harmonic oscillator of course you
can project it onto the Q axis and
it things just go back and forth you can
also project it onto the P axis and
they go up and down but but thinking
simultaneously in terms of P and Q
is a very powerful way to think
about motion there's another way you
can think about it instead of thinking
about it as a rigid pinwheel think about
it as the motion of a fluid think about
it as the motion of the fluid
whole bunch of points filled up with points
here the points represent
starting points represents possible starting
points and think of it as a
fluid the fluid just rotates around the center
here with a constant frequency of
the frequency of the frequency of the
constant velocity kind of incompressible
fluid rotating with constant velocity
that's the character of Hamilton's equations
they tell you how points move
around in phase space it's exactly what
they do they tell you wherever you are
in Q the next place that you'll
be is determined by how a Hamiltonian depends
on P whatever the momentum is the
next value of the momentum will be determined
by the
P and Q so that's Hamiltonian mechanics and
I think the next time I think we'll
we'll stop the questions now I
think that's probably enough the next time
we'll get back to this issue
of convergence and divergence what it comes
down to I will tell you right now what
it comes down to what it comes down to
is that whether this fictitious fluid
this fictitious fluid has a divergence
or a convergence whether the points in the fluid
tend to come together and what's the
right word well it is called convergence
but whether no it's actually whether the fluid has
sources sources sources making it converge
or diverge and what we'll prove
is that Hamilton's equations ensure that
the motion of this fictitious fluid does
not have any convergence or divergence in
it so we'll see what we typically see
but we'll define that carefully next time
and that brings us full circle
back to the basic simple ideas that we started with
of points moving from one point to another
in a deterministic way
the statement you made earlier
about systems which
or Lebronians for which the
two dots could not be resolved
as keys being not with good systems
is that a provable factor or an empirical factor?
no,
it's empirical
you could argue that you
could prove it from quantum mechanics
quantum mechanics would go to hell in a handbag
if you tried to take some of these other cases
yeah
I think I lost that in minutes
you're right
if you had p squared and q squared
that doesn't work for me
and that omega p doesn't equal q dot
in terms of units
how do you know?
well,
p is a velocity
and omega is one over time
yeah,
but what's the u and q?
q is a position
no,
q isn't a position
q is just an abstract coordinate
it's just a coordinate
okay,
good,
let's go back
good
let's go back to the basic harmonic oscillator
with the usual coordinates and velocities
and then I'll show you
how you get to this form
well,
the form that we had before
and we'll try to figure out
what the details of the units are
okay
do you recognize this?
m x dot squared over two
minus or plus,
depending on whether you're doing energy or Lagrangian
minus k over two x squared
okay
yeah
um
right
okay
that's it,
that's the Lagrangian
we're going to make a change of coordinates
oh,
let's look at the units first of all
x has units of length
mass has units of mass
time has units of time
what are the units of the Lagrangian?
energy
and of course this does have units of energy
one half m v squared
had better have units of energy
otherwise we don't know what the hell we're doing
so uh
right,
so this is units of energy
and everything is dimensionally consistent
um
what is omega?
omega
anybody know what omega is
in terms of k and m?
square root of k over m
if you solve the equations of motion
you will find that the frequency of the
oscillator is square root of k over m
okay
alright,
so that's what we begin with
now what I'm going to do is I'm going
to do a little bit of a test here
so what I'm going to do is change coordinates
I'm going to make a change of definition of coordinates
I am going to define a q
so that omega over 2 q squared
that's this term over here,
the potential energy term
is equal to k over 2 x squared
this is the relationship between q and x
I'm simply forcing it
I'm forcing omega over 2 q squared
to be k over 2 x squared
I can do that,
I can change variables
and so let's see,
so what do I get?
first of all,
the easy part,
we get rid of a factor of 2
and we get rid of omega
by putting it in the denominator
but omega is square root of k over m
so what's k over omega?
it must be square root of m over k
so this is equal to square
root of m over k x squared
ah,
you're right,
it's square root of km
that sounds better,
square root of km
this is the definition of q
q is equal to the fourth root
I don't know how to write fourth root
yeah
that's the definition of q and it ensures
that this term over here
is equal to this term
but it's at a cost,
the cost of it
this is not really a cost but nevertheless
q no longer has units of length
q now has some cockamamie units
that I can't even figure out
what are the units of q?
I don't know
whatever k was,
mass,
one quarter,
times a length
the units of q are not the units of length
let's keep going and now go to the kinetic term
let's go to the kinetic term
if q squared is square root of km x squared
then what is q dot squared?
well,
when you take time derivatives
let's go to,
when you take a time derivative of q
the k and the m,
those are just fixed constants
they don't change
so it's pretty clear that q dot squared is
going to be the same factor squared over m
square root of km times x dot squared
if I take the square root of that,
it's just a derivative
if q is equal to
q is equal to k over
omega which is square root of km
if I take the square root
of this and time differentiate it
it will just become this
so that's q dot squared
now let's look at q dot squared
oh,
yeah,
ok
let's look at the kinetic energy term over here
what is the kinetic energy term?
the kinetic energy term m x dot squared over 2
that's going to be m over 2 x dot squared
but x dot squared is q dot squared over
the square root of km
but the square root of k
but m over the square root of km
is just equal to
square root of m over k
q dot squared with a one half
and what is that?
this is just 1 over omega
so all of this becomes
1 over 2 omega
q dot squared
do you remember what I started with for the Lagrangian?
it was
1 over 2 omega q dot squared
plus q over 2
sorry,
plus q squared
times omega over 2
I think that's what we have here
alright
I changed variables
in such a way as
to bring it into a certain form
I did it because I knew
it was a smart thing to do
by the time I got to the Hamiltonian
but the answer to your question is
once you make this change of variables
q no longer has units of length
that's the only thing that's changed
q doesn't have units of length
omega still has units of 1 over time
it's the same omega that it was
energy still has units of energy
but that's where the discrepancy of units comes from
so
yeah
q still has the normal units of momentum
which does?
q still works out to
be the normal units of momentum
p should still
p,
um
yeah I think so
I think p still comes out
to have the same units of momentum
that should be right I think
no
um
depends on which p you mean
q is equal to q over 2
and the conjugate to q has different momentum
different units
different units than um
yeah
so if you use x and p
mhm
yeah
then I would have had to draw ellipses
that of course is the reason that I
yeah that's exactly right
yeah
then I would have gotten
what would I have gotten?
let's just let's uh let's
alright what I would have gotten for h
would have been?
not this p and this q
but uh the ordinary p and the ordinary x
I would have gotten
a different p
p squared over 2 m
plus uh plus k uh
k over 2 x squared
so what we would have
said is that the energy is
a certain coefficient times p squared
plus another coefficient uh times x squared
and as you say we would have ellipses
instead of uh circles
so
so that that really was the primary
reason why I made this change of variables
was to illustrate how
how symmetric the system really is
when uh when we
right variables are used
so I got lost when you
said Lagrangian's equations are second order equations
mhm
and are n of them
and the Hamer-Ponin equations are first order equations
and are two n of them
no
I got lost
oh oh ok you didn't understand what I said
oh ok
I see
alright let's uh let's
well yeah
ok
here are
two first order equations
first order means only first time derivatives appear
alright
here are two first order equations
combine them together
and you get one second order equation
this is the usual f equals m a
ok
this is the form that
the Euler-Lagrange equations come out in
so two equations
one of which can practically be
regarded as the definition of p
p proportional to velocity
and the other one just p dot
that is proportional to the force
but you can take these equations
think of them as a pair of first order equations
which are equivalent to a single second order equation
ok now when you did
the derivation using Lagrangian formulation
you
one second order equation
this is it
that's the Euler-Lagrange equation
f equals m a or the Euler-Lagrange equation
ok I was thinking of what p and p dot
in terms of derivatives of l and q and q dot
yeah but just don't even think of p
forget p altogether and just write
p dot
since
Hello
is equal to,
what did I say it was?
1 over omega?
1 over 2 omega?
q dot squared plus omega over 2 q squared.
Forget p.
Just let's write the Euler-Lagrange equation.
dL by dq dot,
that's q dot over omega.
And now we have to
differentiate it with respect to time.
That's equal to dL by dq,
which is equal to minus omega q.
This is a second order equation.
It's q double dot over omega
is equal to minus omega q.
It's the same equation as this one.
Just multiply by omega.
So the Lagrangean equations,
if you don't introduce p,
and you don't try to get smart,
and introduce p,
the Lagrange equations are second order equations,
and there's one of them for each q.
The Hamiltonian equations,
two for each q,
or one for each p,
and one for each q.
But as you see,
by the simple trick of differentiating one
and putting it into the other,
it becomes a second order equation,
plus a definition,
if you like.
Yeah?
One more question.
When you say that the Hamiltonian formula is very powerful,
is what you're saying,
does that somehow amount to saying
that the phase space is a better geometrical representation
than configuration space?
Different purposes.
For example,
you see extremely clearly in phase space,
that the most important thing is the
motion has no convergence,
and that this fluid,
this fictitious fluid,
doesn't tend to squeeze together or fly apart,
in analogy with the situation for
the simple systems that I showed you.
That you see very,
very clearly.
You see cycles,
you see conserved quantities being associated with cycles,
or surfaces in the space.
So,
some things are much easier
to see in the Hamiltonian form.
Look,
each one is what it is,
and is good for different reasons,
different purposes.
The real bottom line,
and the reason we're doing this,
is because the Hamiltonian is a very,
very central object in quantum mechanics.
Where are we aiming?
We're aiming,
really,
to get to modern physics.
That means we're aiming to get to quantum mechanics.
And we're aiming to get to quantum mechanics in relativity.
These are the prerequisites for it.
And as we'll eventually find out,
the Hamiltonian has a much
more intuitive meaning in quantum mechanics
than it does in classical mechanics.
This was a bunch of magic.
A bunch of,
you know,
a bunch of fiddling.
It's beautiful.
You get very,
very simple equations.
The equations have a simple geometric description.
And you can see all sorts of beautiful things.
But ultimately,
the bottom line is that
the real essence of the Hamiltonian
comes from quantum mechanics.
So,
when you write a Lagrangian,
it's the kinetic energy minus the potential energy,
right?
And the potential energy is the integral of the forces?
Yeah.
Can you,
like,
motivate?
I mean,
let's say you motivated that by deriving a backward slope.
Yeah.
Is there any...
Is it always the integral
of forces that's functionally positioned?
I would say it slightly differently.
I wouldn't say that the potential...
Yeah,
the potential is the integral of
forces if the forces are conservative.
But an equally true statement and an equivalent statement
is that the forces are the derivatives of the potential.
So,
I think that's a better way to think about it.
Forces are derivatives of potential energy.
And think of potential energy
as being more central than forces.
Okay.
So,
I've got one...
You were just saying that
where we're headed is modern physics.
Oh.
So,
you were saying at the beginning of
the class that the goal of this sequence
is to get us to where we can
understand sort of the problems at the frontier.
Hopefully.
So,
would you say a few words
about what some of those are?
Like,
is it quantum gravity or dark energy?
No,
absolutely.
Quantum gravity,
the structure of cosmology,
elementary particle physics,
the Higgs boson.
Why it is that neutrinos can't
go faster than the speed of light.
String theory.
The big theoretical problems tend to revolve
around the combination of quantum mechanics and gravity.
And the implications for cosmology.
I say the big theoretical problems.
Some of my friends would say,
no,
the big theoretical problems
revolve around elementary particle physics.
And both are true.
And how all this fits together into some neat structure where
all of it is simultaneously accounted for is the big problem.
The big problem is what it
always was since the day of Einstein.
Unifying all the various different pieces of physics.
But especially cosmology and elementary particle physics.
Quantum field theory.
I actually don't have to tell you that.
You know that.
And,
you know,
I don't have any great wisdom about
what the solution of these problems is.
I do have great wisdom,
but I'm not going to tell you.
But...
Okay.
I think we'll go home and solve it or something.
Time to go home.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.