Stanford University.
We're going to finish talking about particles and magnetic fields.
Maybe even a little bit about electric fields too.
Electric fields are much easier.
I want to finish that today.
And then for my money, we're sort of finished.
But we will meet next time and I'll think of something to talk about.
But what's that?
Today's the 10th lecture, right?
Oh, today's the 10th lecture?
Oh, okay.
Well, then we won't meet next week.
Unless I don't finish today.
Which I think I will because it doesn't seem too hard to do.
Let me just quickly review.
There are electric and magnetic fields.
They're vector fields.
They depend on position and they also have components.
They have direction, they have magnitude, and they depend on where you are.
Electric field is one example.
Magnetic field is the one that we're really dealing with now.
And so we call it B.
We put a little arrow on top to indicate that it's a vector.
And we say it's a function of position.
We can also write it in terms of its components.
Bi of x.
Or we can write that bi of x means bx, by, and bz.
All the same things.
All right, that's the magnetic field.
They all depend on position.
There's a rule about magnetic fields.
Where this rule comes from is not apparent at the moment.
It's a rule about magnetic fields that's partly an experimental rule,
partly also very consistent with our general theory.
So, it's a rule about magnetic fields.
Or generally theory of electromagnetism.
It is a rule which may break down in the future.
It's the rule that there are no sources of the magnetic field.
No analogs of charged particles for magnetic fields.
No magnetic monopoles.
As I said, in the future, this may prove to be wrong.
But at least experimentally, and within the current framework of theory,
it's true.
That the sources of magnetic fields are not magnetic fields.
The sources of the magnetic field are zero.
And that's the condition that del dot b is equal to zero.
If b was a flow of a fluid, it would be saying there are no sources of the fluid,
no pipe ends sticking out in space where water is flowing away in every direction.
All right, so del dot b equals zero.
We can call that a constraint on a magnetic field.
Not any magnetic field is allowed.
Only some magnetic fields are allowed.
Those which satisfy del dot b equals zero.
Incidentally, one other thing for tonight in any case.
This does not have to be the case in general.
But for our purposes tonight, let's assume that the magnetic field and electric field,
if it exists, are not dependent on time.
They don't vary.
Nothing big or different happens.
But just to be definite, time independent, static, electric, and magnetic fields.
All right, now.
We want to make sure that when we start thinking about magnetic fields,
that we satisfy this condition here.
It would be nice if we could write it in an automatic way,
where we didn't have to keep checking whether we are correctly implementing this condition.
And one way of doing it, it's the accepted way of doing it,
it's the effective way of doing it that works extremely well,
is to say that the magnetic field,
is the curl of something.
That something is called the vect- oops, the vector potential.
And the reason that we do that is because
for any field A,
the divergence of a curl is always zero.
So, all we can say is, look,
we don't ever have to check or think about
whether the divergence of the magnetic field is zero,
if instead, we replace everywhere's B by del cross A.
And that introduces the notion of a vector potential.
It's automatic.
We don't have to think about it.
However, it does introduce another element into things.
And the other element that it introduces is that the vector potential is not unique.
If we start writing our equations in terms of the vector potential,
then different vector potentials will sometimes correspond to exactly the same physics.
And in fact, what's the condition?
The condition is that two different vector potentials are the same
if they lead to the same magnetic field.
What is the freedom in choosing,
the vector potential?
Well,
now we use another fact about
calculus or about vectors and scalar fields, about fields.
And it's the fact
that the curl
of any gradient,
the curl of any gradient
del S
is always equal to zero.
So, that means
that if we add a gradient to A,
it will not change its curl.
That happens to be the only ambiguity.
It's possible to prove
that there's no other ambiguity
in the vector potential
other than adding to it
the gradient of a scalar.
That's the only ambiguity.
Any two vector potentials
which give rise to the same magnetic field,
the difference between them
will automatically be a gradient.
That's a mathematical theorem.
And so we can say that
the vector potential is ambiguous up to a certain point.
So, the vector potential is ambiguous up to a certain kind of transformation.
It's called a gauge transformation.
This is called a gauge transformation.
As I said, it represents an ambiguity in what the vector potential is.
But what about the magnetic field?
What happens to the magnetic field when you make a gauge transformation?
And of course, the answer is nothing.
That's the whole point.
And so one says that the magnetic field is gauge invariant.
In fact, anything that has real physical measurable significance
is gauge invariant.
We have an idea that the magnetic field,
as well as lots of other things
that we might measure directly in the laboratory,
are gauge invariant.
So, we do something a little bit odd.
We're going to talk about this more.
We do something a little bit odd.
We add into the system a new object, the vector potential,
at the cost of it.
It is effective in taking care of this constraint,
but it leads to ambiguities of its own.
And then we remove those ambiguities,
by saying the only thing that we're allowed to really think of as physical
are those things which are gauge invariant.
In other words, those things which really, really only depend on the magnetic field
and not on the vector potential itself.
That becomes a principle.
The principle of gauge invariance.
I don't think we have to write down the components of the magnetic field
in terms of the derivatives of A.
We've done that before.
If we need it, we'll come back to it.
Okay, let's write down an example.
Let's write down a particular example,
which we'll use later in the evening.
It's the example of a uniform magnetic field.
Uniform magnetic field pointing in the blackboard.
I think I wrote it down last time,
but let's write it down again,
and check out some of the things we've been doing.
Alright, so it's a magnetic field for which Bx is equal to 0,
oh, okay, now I've forgotten.
Bx, no, Bx is equal to B,
By,
sorry, wrong,
Bz is equal to B,
Bx is equal to 0,
By is equal to 0.
It's a magnetic field along the x-axis.
Now of course it doesn't matter what axis it's along,
we can always orient the axis.
It's a magnetic field along the z-axis,
we can always orient the z-axis so that it's along the magnetic field,
and little b is just a constant.
Alright, let's first of all see if we can represent it by a vector potential.
The answer is yes, and I'll write down the answer.
Here is a vector potential immediately.
First of all,
we can, the,
I'll write down the answer.
The answer is that A
x,
check it out, let me get the sign right, it's,
alright, Ax is equal to 0,
Az is equal to 0,
and Ay is equal to Bx.
Let's check that.
The only possible derivative is the derivative of Ay with respect to x.
That's the only derivative that doesn't, that isn't 0.
Derivative of Ay with respect to x,
that's not 0.
I can subtract off that for free,
derivative of Ax with respect to y, since that is 0.
Ax is 0.
And this happens to be the z component of the magnetic field.
Alright.
What is the Ay by x?
It's just B.
So, that is the z component of the magnetic field.
This works.
But, it's not the only thing that can work.
Why is it that I've chosen y and not x, for example?
The field is along the z axis, so it's not surprising that the z component is special.
But x and y, they seem sort of symmetric in this problem.
Magnetic field into the blackboard.
I'm looking at it in the xy plane.
Why did I pick out y instead of x?
Alright.
Here's another solution.
Another solution.
Ax equals minus By.
Ay equals 0.
And Az is equal to 0 again.
How about that?
In this case, the only derivative is,
the derivative of Ax with respect to y.
This time there's no Day with respect to x.
But the derivative of Ax with respect to y is minus B.
Well, that's good.
Because there's a minus sign over here.
So this is again, exactly the same magnetic field.
Bz equals B.
Alright.
So these must be related then, by a gauge transformation.
Let's see if we can find the gauge transformation.
That's necessary to relate them.
The S.
I'm not going to search for it and then find it.
I'm going to just write down what the answer is.
And we'll check it.
Alright.
I have forgotten the answer.
But I know what the answer is proportional to.
The answer is proportional to some constant times xy.
So here's what we're going to do.
We're going to start with this representation.
This is the representation over here.
We're going to gauge transform it.
What are we going to do?
We're going to add to A the gradient of this quantity over here.
And we're going to see what we get.
Alright.
So what's the gradient of this quantity?
The gradient, the component in the x direction,
that's just the derivative of S with respect to the gradient of the S.
The component of the gradient of S in the x direction.
That's just C times y.
And what about the gradient of S in the y direction?
That's C times x.
So what happens now if we add to these,
this pre-existing vector potential.
Let's erase this for a minute.
If we add to this pre-existing vector potential,
exactly what's written here.
So what happens to AX?
AX becomes the original AX, which was 0,
plus the gradient of S.
That's C times y.
Z, nothing happens to AZ because the gradient of S has no Z component at all.
And finally, this stays 0 here.
And what happens to this one?
We add to it BX plus y.
BX plus what?
BX plus CX, right?
BX plus CX.
Okay, now what I'm going to do is choose C.
I haven't told you what C is yet.
C could be anything.
I can do many different gauge transformations with different values of C.
Let's now choose C.
And in particular, I want to choose C to be minus B.
Clever, clever, clever.
Then this becomes 0.
And what happens to this one?
It becomes minus B times y.
So what I've done is succeeded in going from the representation
where the y component is B times x,
all other components are 0,
to another representation where the x component,
is minus B times y,
and the y component is 0.
So they're the same.
They're related by gauge transformation.
There's a zillion other gauge transformations you can do.
Let's see, what else could we do?
We could choose C to be minus 1 half B.
Let's see what happens then.
C is minus 1 half B.
So what happens to this?
This becomes B over 2,
times x.
And what happens to this one?
This one becomes minus
B over 2 times y.
Still, we'll get the same magnetic field.
This is a little exercise to prove that the magnetic field comes out exactly the same.
Alright, so these are called gauge transformations.
And a particular choice,
a particular choice is called a gauge.
We could call this the gauge in which AX and AZ are equal to 0.
Here's a gauge in which both AX and AY both have the same magnitude,
but opposite sign.
There's a third gauge,
which was that AY is 0,
and AX was minus B over 2 times y.
So these go under the name of different gauges.
And the principle that the phenomena,
the actual physical phenomena that take place
should be independent of the particular gauge,
that's called gauge invariance.
This is an absolutely central principle in modern physics.
So important that, um,
it governs everything.
It's...
It's big.
Really big.
Yeah?
Can you make A have the same symmetry as B?
Uh, which is, what symmetry is that?
Rotation about the, no.
No, no, you can't.
It wouldn't represent the same situation.
Right, no, you can't.
No, there are limits.
Obviously you can't do anything you want.
There are limits.
And, uh,
you could do a lot more than this.
This was only one particular c equals c,
s equals cxy,
that was only one particular thing you could do.
There's a lot of other things you could do.
I just did, I just used that as an example
to show you how you can go from one gauge to another.
Sometimes, uh,
you say things like,
alright, I'm going to look for a gauge,
I think I can prove it, I know I can prove it,
that there always does exist a gauge
in which the x component is equal to zero
of the vector potential.
You can prove that.
It's not just for a uniform magnetic field.
And then you would speak about the gauge
in which the x component is equal to zero.
Or the gauge in which the y component is equal to zero.
Alright, so that's the lingo.
That's the, that's the language of gauge, uh,
of gauge theories.
A question.
A gauge transformation always refers to
the addition of a,
of, I guess, a field in which the gradient is,
you arrive at the field by taking the gradient of the scalar.
Yeah.
Well, does it always refer to that?
In electrodynamics and in the theory of charged particles,
it always refers to that.
Uh,
then it's a similar,
more complicated structure,
which we're not going to get into tonight, obviously.
And the choice of coordinates in a, uh,
in a, in a gravitating system,
the choice of coordinate system that you describe
a curved geometry by is also called a gauge.
The, again, it's a choice that you can make,
how you coordinate a curved space,
but the physics had better not depend,
the physical phenomena don't depend on how you,
in your, um,
uh, wisdom has this decided to put coordinates on,
uh, on space.
So, again, that's the notion of gauge invariance,
but we're going to be speaking tonight at least only about
this electromagnetic variety of gauge transformation.
And as I think I mentioned last time,
I honestly don't, uh,
no, I, I was going to say,
I don't know the origin of the term gauge.
I do know the origin of the term gauge.
Uh, it was a historical sort of glitch.
That at one time for a brief period,
people thought it had to do with transforming your units
of measurement at different places.
They thought somehow this had to do with changing your unit
of measurement and there, it didn't.
It was just a wrong start.
Uh, yeah.
Question.
Um, does it turn out that there are either computational
or other kinds of advantages to using one gauge or another?
Very often.
We, we, we,
let's try to get to one.
Uh, yeah.
Oh, yes.
That, that is a very good point.
Sometimes this can be a nuisance,
but sometimes it can be a positive distinct advantage
because it can happen that certain things,
certain things are manifest,
in other words,
obvious in one gauge and very non-obvious in some other gauge.
It might be that this or that property is manifest in one gauge,
but that or this property is manifest in another gauge.
And so you may use one gauge to study energy conservation
and another gauge to study Lorentz invariance.
I'm not making that up.
I mean, that is the way it works.
Uh, yeah.
Sometimes it seems somewhat similar to eigenspaces
and finding eigenvalues.
Is there any relationship there or is that just sort of out in the...
Well, of course, everything is related to everything else,
but not in any obvious way at this point, no.
Um, okay.
Now let's come to the Lagrangian.
We talked about the Lagrangian last time.
There's a Lagrangian now for a point particle.
It is not the Lagrangian for the electromagnetic field
or anything like it.
It's just a Lagrangian for a particle moving
in a static magnetic field.
Uh, electric fields are easy.
We won't even bother with them tonight.
We're just going to do magnetic fields.
The Lagrangian, I, we, we talked about it last time.
We'll just go over quickly again, uh, the idea.
There's, first of all, the Lagrangian for the free particle,
just a kinetic energy,
one half mv squared,
one half, let's just write m, uh, mv squared.
V squared, of course, means the sums of the squares
of the time derivatives of x, y, and z.
Maybe I'll write them out.
Maybe, uh, maybe I'll just write them all out.
Just be really concrete about it.
x dot squared plus y dot squared plus z dot squared.
Okay.
That's the Lagrangian for the free particle.
If that's all there was, the free particle would just be a free particle,
no forces on it.
It would just move in straight lines and be dull.
All right, what do we add to it?
Last time we talked about it,
and I'm going to tell you what we add to it.
We're not going to derive it from anything.
We're going to just write it down.
It has a numerical coefficient which is proportional
to the charge of the particle.
It is the charge of the particle.
Electric charge measured in some units.
The last time I put a speed of light down here,
it's quite obvious that it's only e over c
which comes into things,
and in different choices of units,
e over c is sometimes just called q or whatever.
I've kept the speed of light in some units or other
that I'm familiar with and that I use all the time.
There's a speed of light downstairs.
But you could, of course, just change the definition,
get rid of the speed of light,
and change the definition of what you mean by the electric charge.
It's just multiplying it by a number.
I'll leave the e over c in there.
It just somehow appeals to me aesthetically.
E over c, I like it.
I'm used to it.
Times the vector potential dotted into the velocity.
This is obviously one thing that I could write down.
I could also try writing down things involving the magnetic field.
I advise you to try to do that and play with it
and see if you can find anything interesting.
Find some other way of dealing with things
and see what you get.
But we're not going to do that tonight.
So a dot v means, literally,
ax times x dot plus ay times y dot plus az times z dot.
And what do we want to do with this?
All right, I think I showed you last time
how you prove that the equations of motion are gauge invariant.
Let me just really briefly remind you.
You begin with the action principle.
You take two points in space and time.
And you say, let me find the path
which minimizes or otherwise makes stationary
the action which is the integral of the Lagrangian.
We have something new.
We have something which seems to depend
on the vector potentials here in the Lagrangian.
And so we have to ask, when we make a gauge transformation,
like up on the top there,
does it influence the action?
If so, we might be in trouble.
So we worked out last time
there's a contribution to the action
when you make a gauge transformation.
When we make a gauge transformation,
there will be a contribution to the action
e over c times the change in the vector potential,
and that's, well, let's write it as
the gradient of s times x sub i dot.
This is not the full contribution from a times velocity.
It's the change that we get
when we make a gauge transformation.
This is the change in the action
coming from a gauge transformation.
And the point was that
this is integral of dt, of course.
And if you use a little bit of calculus,
you'll find that this integral
is nothing but e over c
times the value of s at,
let's call this the final point in space and time,
let's call this the initial point in space and time,
s of x final,
minus x initial.
We worked that out last time.
How do we see that?
This is dx dt.
dt over t cancels.
And each little piece here is the change in s
from going from one point to a neighboring point,
and you add them all up,
and finally you get...
the difference in s at the two endpoints.
Now, so, first conclusion.
The action is not gauge invariant.
When you do a gauge transformation,
the action changes.
But does it change in an important way?
Does it change in a way which affects
the finding of the trajectory,
the trajectory which minimizes the action?
Now, remember what we're supposed to do.
We're supposed to keep the endpoints fixed.
We nail them down,
and we explore all trajectories
and look for the ones which minimize...
or look for the one which minimizes the action.
If we keep the endpoints fixed,
then when we vary the trajectory around,
this doesn't change.
And because it doesn't change,
finding the minimum doesn't depend on it.
So the answer is, although the action itself
is not quite gauge invariant,
exploring the trajectories
keeping fixed the endpoints
does give rise to a gauge invariant answer.
The trajectory which minimizes the action
will not depend on a gauge transformation
for this reason.
All right, so we can be quite certain then.
We don't have to check it.
We're going to check it anyway.
But we don't have to check that the equations of motion
that follow from this Lagrangian
will be gauge invariant.
What does it mean to say they're gauge invariant?
Yeah.
It means when we work out the equations,
the vector potential is going to disappear,
and what's going to be in its place?
The magnetic field.
In other words, the gauge,
the vector potential is going to come in
in combinations which we'll recognize
as components of the magnetic field.
Okay?
All right, so let's do that.
Here's our Lagrangian.
And I'm going to be really concrete
and pedantic about it.
What's the first thing we do
when we encounter a Lagrangian
and we want to work out the equations of motion?
Remember, the equations of motion,
let's write them down.
They're p dot i,
where p is what?
p is the momentum,
is equal to partial of L
with respect to xi.
Those are the Lagrange equations of motion
where, let me remind you what pi is,
pi is the partial derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to xi dot.
In other words, pi is the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to the velocity.
Now, now I have to
tell you more about the notion of momentum.
There are two numbers.
There are two notions of momentum.
There are two distinct notions of momentum.
One of them is just the old-fashioned momentum,
mass times velocity.
Okay?
Mass times velocity.
It's called the mechanical momentum.
Where should we write it?
Okay, let's put it over here.
mv equals mechanical momentum.
That's also the definition
that we encounter in elementary physics.
Mass times velocity is momentum.
Here's a different definition,
namely, the derivative of the Lagrangian,
sorry, the derivative of the Lagrangian
with respect to the velocity,
different definition,
and it's called the canonical momentum.
It's the momentum that you use
in Hamilton's equations.
throughout our formal,
construction,
thing that goes into Poisson brackets,
partial of L with respect to the velocity,
derivative with respect to the velocity.
Are they the same?
Well, supposing there's only this term here,
and we differentiate L with respect to x dot,
what do we get?
We get mx dot.
So yes, they're the same.
Supposing this weren't here,
but there was an ordinary potential energy,
v of x, or u of x,
I forgot what we called it.
Maybe we called it u of x.
I'll call it u of x.
A potential energy u of x.
U of x doesn't depend on the velocities,
the velocity components,
so when you differentiate L with respect to x dot,
this doesn't contribute.
And it's still true that the canonical momentum
and the mechanical momentum are the same thing.
But with a magnetic field, or in general,
in general, they're not the same thing.
Let's see what we get.
Here.
What is p sub i?
p sub i is partial of L with respect to,
let's take the x component,
let's not do i, just x, x dot.
That's equal to mx dot,
but there's an extra term from here.
Plus e over c, a sub x.
That's it.
That's the canonical momentum.
It is not equal to the mechanical momentum.
They are two quite different things.
When you're asking whether momentum is conserved
by virtue of a symmetry,
you're talking about this beast,
not this one over here necessarily.
They might be the same, but they might not.
Okay, so there we are.
There's our p sub i.
And we want to work out the Lagrangian equation.
Here it is.
p sub i dot is equal to partial of L with respect to x sub i.
So let's work it out in detail.
Okay, first of all, what is p sub i dot?
It's just the time derivative of this.
And what's that?
That's m times the acceleration.
That's good.
We got the acceleration, and that's where we want to go.
We want to get some F equals m a formula.
m times the acceleration,
but then there's another term.
e over c times the time derivative of a of x.
Now, a of x is, of course, a function of position.
It depends on where the particle is.
The particle is moving around.
The vector potential varies from place to place.
And so at the position of the particle,
the vector potential will vary with time,
even though there may be no explicit dependence.
The field may be completely constant
at any given point,
because the particle moves, a changes.
So what's the change in a per unit time,
the derivative of a x with respect to time?
It's changing because the position is changing.
So what do we get?
We get derivative of a x with respect to x times x dot
plus the derivative of a x with respect to y,
times y dot,
plus the derivative of a x with respect to z,
times z dot.
What did I do?
I just took this a x over here,
and I said it changes because the position of the particle changes.
It's x changes, it's y changes, and it's z change.
This is the change in x and change in a,
change in a x,
because the particle moves.
All right, that is the left-hand side of the equation.
How about the right-hand side of the equation?
We still have the right-hand side of the equation,
so let's go to the right-hand side of the equation.
That is the derivative of L, in this case,
let's say p sub x,
the derivative of the Lagrangian with respect to x.
This term here doesn't depend on x at all.
It only depends on velocities.
How about this term? Does this term depend on x?
Well, sure it does. a depends on x.
So, we get on the right-hand side,
e over c,
times the derivative of a x with respect to x,
times x dot.
Then there's a term from here,
plus partial of a y with respect to x,
times y dot,
plus partial of a z with respect to x,
times z dot.
All I've done was differentiate each one of these with respect to x.
Sorry, I'm in the wrong place, aren't I?
The equals should go here.
It's the right-hand side of this equation.
All right, so let's go to the right-hand side of this equation.
Let's bring it down where it belongs.
The thing in this bracket over here
looks a little bit like the thing in this bracket over here,
but they're actually quite different if you look at them.
The first term is the same.
Derivative of a x with respect to x times x dot.
Same thing over here.
Any questions about this? I don't want to go too fast.
Yeah?
In the Lagrangian, is the second term a kinetic energy or a potential energy?
That's a word.
It's neither.
So how do you know whether to add it or subtract it?
Oh, I'm saying let's try it out.
Let's just try it out.
We could try it out subtracting it, too.
We can try it out both ways.
We could try all kinds of things.
I'm short-cutting a bit of the work for you
and telling you what the answer is,
and now we're going to check the answer.
But subtracting it would only correspond to changing the sign of a.
So we just go a to minus a.
Replace a by minus a.
The formulas would be the same,
except wherever you would see an a, you would stick a minus a.
So it wouldn't make much difference.
All right, so here we are.
And at this level, we might,
at least,
as well never have heard of a magnetic field.
We've written down some equations of motion.
We never heard of a magnetic field.
Let's just follow our noses with this equation
and see what we get,
pretending we had never heard of the concept of a magnetic field.
That last term should be ax.
Yes, you're right. Thank you.
No, it's az.
Ax, ay, az.
The middle one is y.
Yeah, middle one is y. Good.
Yeah, okay.
So you're at the top.
You're differentiating this with respect to x,
this with respect to x,
and this with respect to x.
Okay?
On the other hand, the term in the left only has ax's.
It only has ax's on the left,
and that's because it comes from calculating the time derivative of ax here.
See, they come from different places.
On the right-hand side,
you're getting something that comes from differentiating with respect to x.
So you get three different terms.
Derivative of ax with respect to x,
derivative of ay with respect to x,
derivative of az with respect to x.
On the other hand, on the other side of the equation,
you're differentiating p sub x with respect to time.
So it's always ax,
but different velocity components there.
Okay, that's the setup,
and now let's see what cancels and what doesn't cancel,
and manipulate it,
and see what kind of things we get.
First of all, the left-hand side contains m,
and just the a component of the acceleration.
Let's call it by a familiar name,
the x component of acceleration.
Next, certain terms cancel.
Let's cancel the ones that cancel.
ax with respect to x times x dot,
same thing over here.
So let's...
I don't want to erase them.
I just want to block them out.
Whoops, I missed something.
I didn't catch x dot here.
There.
Okay.
Now, that's equal to...
We're going to bring everything over here
onto the right-hand side of the equation.
We're going to transpose it,
which means we have to change the sign.
So everything in this bracket is going to go over to the left-hand side.
Obviously, there will be an e over c.
And let's combine the things that first multiply y dot.
Here are two things that multiply y dot.
So let's combine them.
One of them is partial of ax with respect to y.
And what's the other one?
Partial of y with respect to x.
With a minus sign.
Because we...
Let's see.
Did I get it right?
Partial?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I think this one comes in with a minus sign.
That one went over to the right-hand side.
And the other one has a plus sign.
d a y with respect to x.
Times, I think it's y dot.
Y dot.
Oh boy.
It's looking good.
We're getting components of x.
We're getting components of the magnetic field, in case that slipped past you.
Okay?
But then there's another term.
Let's put a big bracket around it.
And now let's combine the things which multiply z dot.
That will be plus partial of az, oops, az with respect to x minus partial of ax with respect to z.
Times z dot, huh?
Oops, closed bracket.
And that's it.
But we can make it look a little prettier.
First of all, what is this?
Partial of az with respect to x minus partial of ax with respect to z.
It's clearly a component of the magnetic field.
Which one?
Plus or minus?
I'm asking you because I don't know.
z, x, I think it's by, isn't it?
Is it?
I have to look up in my notes.
It's either plus or minus.
And of course my notes can easily be wrong because I haven't checked them.
Let's see.
Let's see if I, m a x equals e over c partial of a y with respect to z.
y with respect to x minus partial of x with respect to y.
Yep, yep, yep.
And I have, if I'm correct, I have m a x equals e over c times b z y dot minus b y z dot.
Okay.
It's either that or minus that, but I think it's that.
So first of all, first lesson to learn is it does something.
It creates a force.
The right hand side is not zero.
First thing.
Second thing, that force is gauge invariant.
It does not involve the end of the force.
It's not a force.
It's a force.
It's a force that involves the ambiguity in a.
Good.
This is also good.
And finally, it's whatever it is, it's something whose x component involves the z component
of magnetic field and the y component of velocity minus the y component of magnetic field times
the z component of velocity.
And it sounds awfully much like either plus or minus b cross v.
All right.
If I've done my homework correctly and I didn't make any mistake, then I think it should be
e over c v cross b.
And I'm not going to give you enough time to check that because I don't want to know
if I'm wrong.
All right.
Or at least it's the x component of that.
Don't tell me if I'm wrong.
If I'm wrong, just keep it to yourself.
I don't want to know.
Okay.
Meaning it's a worse thing than it is.
It's a worse design and signs are not for the blackboard.
Okay.
What you can do exactly the same thing with the other components, the y component, the
z component.
And of course what this is, is it's the Lorentz force law.
I call these the Newton-Lorentz equations.
Mass times acceleration is e over c times v cross b.
This side is Newton.
This side is Lorentz.
I call them by the name Newton-Lorentz equations.
And they tell you if you didn't already know it, but you knew more about the vector potential
side of things, you would have discovered by this argument that the force, magnetic
force on a charged particle is e over c times v cross b.
Quite an elegant structure in some ways.
Even though we had to introduce this thing called the vector potential, which was somewhat
ambiguous.
Now, it's actually a theorem, and I won't try to prove it, that you cannot express the
motion of a charged particle in an action form, in the form of a Lagrangian equation
of motion without introducing the vector potential.
You've got to.
You can try just fiddling around with only the magnetic field and you won't get anywhere.
What would happen if instead of the vector potential you substituted in the magnetic
field itself?
Then every place that you saw the, every place you see the a field, you would see a b field,
and you'd wind up with a thing which was the curl of the b field.
That's not the Lorentz force law.
Anyway.
Uh.
Alright, are we, uh, are we ready for more?
Alright, let's go on to the Hamiltonian.
Next is the Hamiltonian.
We're going to plow through this thing and do basically all of charged particle physics
tonight in a magnetic field.
So the next thing is, is there a Hamiltonian?
There is a Hamiltonian.
The next thing is, is there a Hamiltonian form for this?
In other words, is there an expression for energy?
And can we use that expression for energy to, um, to use, uh, as a Hamiltonian?
Let's first write down, we're going to need the, we're going to need the canonical momenta.
So what is it?
So the Hamiltonian is equal to mx dot plus e over c times ax.
Py is equal to my dot plus e over c ay.
Pz is equal to mz dot plus e over c az.
Alright, we'll need those.
Okay, the Hamiltonian.
What's the rules for the Hamiltonian in terms of the Lagrangian?
I'll remind you.
The Hamiltonian is equal to the sum over all the coordinates of the ith component of momentum
times the ith component of velocity minus the Lagrangian.
And the Lagrangian is a function of x and x dot.
Now, the Hamiltonian is supposed to be a constant.
The Hamiltonian is supposed to be a function of x's and p's.
This was really easy in the previous cases because p was essentially just x dot times the mass.
So you could just, wherever you saw an x dot, you could just substitute p over m.
Well, it's not much harder here.
You do the same thing.
You just say, I will solve these equations for x dot, and that's easy.
Let's, yeah, let's rewrite them.
Px minus e over c ax over m divided by m is equal to x dot.
I've just transposed the e over c a to the left and divided by m.
That tells me what x dot is.
It tells me what x dot is in terms of p and functions of x.
Well defined.
It's defined functions of x.
So I know what x dot is now.
Same thing with y dot and z dot.
And I can simply plug it into this Hamiltonian.
It's a little bit of a nuisance.
I'm not going to carry it out.
It's not very hard.
It's extremely easy, as a matter of fact.
It's just keeping track of a few terms, canceling them out.
You've got to keep track of a few terms, canceling them out.
Let's see.
Let's just remember what's here.
In the Lagrangian, all right, let's write it.
Let's write it.
L of x and x dot.
Let's write it in detail.
It's equal to, first of all, p sub x, x dot plus p sub y, y dot plus p sub z, z dot minus m over 2, x dot squared minus m over 2, y dot squared minus m over 2, z dot squared.
And then what have I left out?
I've left out the e over c, a dot v term.
And so that's minus e over c, a over c, a sub x, x dot minus e over c, a sub y, y dot and so forth for z dot.
I don't have room to write it.
So I'm going to write it.
All right.
That's it.
So what do you do with this?
You take it and you substitute in for all the x dots these expressions over here.
It's not very illuminating until you do it.
It's not very illuminating, but it is the right thing to do.
Could you have guessed the answer?
Actually, I don't see how you could easily guess the answer, but the answer is very simple.
I'll tell you what it is.
It is...
p sub x minus e over c, a sub x squared over twice the mass plus p sub y minus e over c, a y squared over twice the mass.
And same thing for z.
Okay.
All right.
So you do this.
You take the sum of the squares of these expressions here.
Plus p z minus e over c, a z squared over 2m.
All you do is you take the sums of the squares of these expressions here, well, the ones in the brackets here, and divide by 2m.
So anything else?
Okay.
So you do this.
You take the sum of the squares of these expressions here, and divide by 2m.
Does anybody recognize what this is?
I'm sure you do.
This object up here, if you substitute in x dot for it, what is it?
Can you tell what it is?
Oh, the .
It's just 1 half mv squared.
It is just 1 half mv squared.
p minus e over c divided by m is x dot.
All right.
Because it comes in squared, you wind up with a mass in the numerator.
So you do this.
You take the sum of the squares of these expressions here, and divide by 2m.
All right.
So anything else?
Okay.
All right.
So anything else?
Okay.
All right.
So anything else?
Okay.
You wind up with a mass in the numerator, and you get x dot squared plus y dot squared
plus z dot squared.
It's exactly the same thing you would have written down if there was no magnetic field.
But does that mean that the magnetic field has no effect?
No, it doesn't.
It doesn't.
The energy is exactly the same function of the velocities as it was without the magnetic
field.
But that doesn't tell you very much.
That doesn't tell you very much.
The Lagrangian itself is different, and the Hamiltonian, when expressed in terms of the
momentum and not the velocities, is different.
That means when you go to work out the equations of motion, it will be different.
We know it is.
We're going to get to Lorentz force law on the right-hand side.
Nevertheless, the numerical value of the energy is 1 half mv squared.
It's conserved.
And so that tells you that a particle moving in a magnetic field has a constant speed.
The magnetic field does not change the speed.
Does it change the velocity?
Yes, because the velocity can change its direction.
Does it change the speed?
No, it doesn't change the speed.
The kinetic energy, 1 half mv squared, is conserved.
It doesn't change.
Therefore, the velocity, the magnitude of the velocity doesn't change.
But still.
The magnetic field does something.
Do you know why the ordinary, old-fashioned kinetic energy is conserved?
Because the force is perpendicular to the velocity.
When the force is perpendicular to the velocity, it's v cross b.
When the force is perpendicular to the velocity, it doesn't change the magnitude of the velocity.
It's a constant.
Any force or any acceleration perpendicular to the direction of velocity doesn't change
the magnitude of the velocity.
And so it's natural and it comes out, comes out of the equations, that the energy, 1 half
mv squared, is conserved.
But it's a different function of the canonical variables, the x's and the p's.
And so when you go to use Hamilton's equations, you get different answers.
Okay.
Let's take a little break.
For a few minutes.
For five minutes.
And think of questions.
What I wanted to go through to show you how it works is the motion of a charged particle
in a uniform magnetic field.
It's simple.
It's elegant.
And it can be solved.
In fact, we'll even do, we'll do a uniform electric and magnetic field.
But first, let's do a uniform magnetic field.
Okay.
First, let's just look at the equation of motion.
Well, okay, let's, of course we're going to look at the equation of motion.
But it's not what I meant to say.
Uniform magnetic field pointing in the z direction.
There were two gauges that we studied, or that we looked at.
One was the magnetic field pointing in the z direction.
And the other one was the magnetic field pointing in the z direction.
Now, I'm going to go through those gauges again.
And I'll show you some examples of that.
One was that a sub x, now, did anybody write it down?
In both cases, a sub z was equal to zero.
Okay.
Yeah.
A z is equal to zero.
A x is equal to zero.
And A y is equal to zero.
Okay.
We could do that one.
That's an interesting one.
But it's not very interesting.
Of limited interest, shall we say.
Yeah, okay.
So let's just plug it in.
Let's plug it in and put it in.
Should we put it in the Lagrangian or the Hamiltonian?
Let's see.
Let's put it in the Lagrangian.
Let's put it into the Lagrangian.
So here's the Lagrangian.
Let's erase everything that we don't need.
Oh.
Okay.
So.
Now we're being very, very concrete and studying a very particular problem, no electric field,
and only one component of the vector potential is not zero, and it has a very definite value.
So let's erase everything which is zero.
Ax is zero, that gets rid of this term.
Az is zero, that gets rid of this term.
And what about ay? That is equal to b times x, is that right?
b times x.
So we have a term in Lagrangian which is dependent on x and y dot.
Are there any cyclic coordinates?
Anybody remember what a cyclic coordinate is?
It doesn't appear in the Lagrangian.
Because it doesn't appear in the Lagrangian, it means that the Lagrangian doesn't change if you shift that coordinate.
That's called a symmetry.
So one way of spotting symmetry is fast is just to look for cyclic coordinates.
And do you see any cyclic coordinates? I see two of them.
y and z.
x appears in the Lagrangian, but not y and z.
So it's quite clear then that if you shift y or you shift z, the Lagrangian doesn't change.
It involves y dot, but y dot is not y.
y dot is just y.
y dot is just y dot.
Alright, so there are two cyclic coordinates.
Let's look at the first cyclic coordinate.
Oh, alright, here. And also let's come over to here.
Let's come over to here.
a sub x is 0.
a sub z is 0.
And a sub y is b times x.
Alright, so there are two cyclic coordinates.
Alright, so which ones did we say were cyclic? I've forgotten.
y and z?
y and z. So what does that mean about y and z?
It means that the corresponding
momenta are conserved.
Right? If you have a cyclic
coordinate, the corresponding
momentum is conserved.
That's an example of Noether's
theorem. That's an example of conservation
as a
consequence of symmetry.
What is the symmetry? The symmetry
is just shifts of the cyclic
coordinates. Since the cyclic coordinate doesn't
enter, it doesn't matter if you shift it.
If you translate it.
Okay, so which ones? That means that
that in particular, let's start with p z.
p z is conserved.
What does that say about
the z motion?
It says that the acceleration
of z is 0.
p z is conserved.
That means that z dot,
the velocity in the z direction
is conserved. That means
the acceleration in the z axis
is 0.
So, first conclusion,
p z
dot is equal
to 0, or
acceleration
in the z direction
is equal to 0.
So as far as the z axis goes,
the particle just moves along with
uniform velocity down that
axis.
Excuse me. I missed what?
p z dot is 0.
Because z doesn't, because
Okay.
Is that a symmetry argument?
Yeah. It's a symmetry argument.
And it says that the Lagrangian is symmetric
and the z goes to z
plus a small shift.
Why is it so?
Because z doesn't appear in it all together.
Good.
Okay, so that's the first thing we see.
That the acceleration
in the z direction is equal to 0.
Now what's the other one which is conserved?
y.
p sub y. p sub y is conserved.
What does that say?
Let's take a look at that.
p sub y,
that says that d by dt
of
m y dot
plus e over c
b x
is equal to 0.
Saying something is conserved
is just another way of saying
its time derivative is equal to 0.
I've plugged in for p sub y
what it is, and here's what I get.
And now let's work that out.
That's the mass times the
y component of acceleration
plus e over c
times
the magnetic field
times the x component of
velocity. Let's write it. v sub x
equals 0.
That's kind of interesting.
It doesn't say
that
the acceleration in the y direction
is 0.
What it says is that the acceleration
in the y direction
is equal to minus
e over c
b over m
times
v x.
This
is nothing but the Lorentz
force law, incidentally.
Mass times acceleration
minus some force
which involves the b field,
the velocity.
This is absolutely nothing but the Lorentz
force law for the special case of
constant magnetic field.
And so it gives rise
to this equation over here.
a sub y
or we can put the m back.
Let's put the m on this side.
Mass times acceleration
in the y direction
is proportional to the magnetic field
times the x component of velocity.
What about the
x component of
acceleration?
There are two ways
we could do it.
There are two ways we could do it.
The first would not
use a conservation law.
We'd just work out
the x equation of motion.
We didn't have to work out the y
equation of motion.
All we had to do was spot a cyclic coordinate.
And what did we get?
We got this equation over here.
This equation, incidentally, is
gauge invariant.
There's no memory of
it has the acceleration,
it has the velocity,
it doesn't have the vector potential in it.
It's a real equation about real things.
Acceleration you can measure,
velocity you can measure.
It's a real objective phenomena
and that's what it says.
Okay, next.
What about the x component of acceleration?
As I said, you can do it in two ways.
The first is just to work out the equation of motion for x.
But the other is to be slick
and change gauges.
We chose a particular
gauge which was very
good for
figuring out what
the y motion was doing.
Why? Because y didn't
appear in the Lagrangian.
y didn't appear in the Lagrangian
and so it was a cyclic coordinate
and from that we were able to use
momentum conservation and it gave
us a simple answer.
What's the trick?
The trick is to say, let's use
the other gauge.
And the other gauge, where is it?
The other
gauge is az is equal to zero,
ax is minus
by,
and ay is equal to zero.
What happens if I do that?
Then this
changes, it becomes minus
and instead
of xy dot
we get x dot y.
It just
interchanges x and y
and puts
in an extra minus sign.
So now which
coordinate is cyclic?
In this form,
this is a different form, a different gauge,
a different coordinate is cyclic.
Now it's the x coordinate
which is cyclic.
And therefore the x component of momentum
is conserved. But the x component of momentum
is no longer just mx dot.
It's mx
dot plus
e over c
minus sign
b times y.
Let's get rid of everything else here.
The x
component of momentum has changed
its definition.
Say it again.
We have to say canonical momentum, not mechanical.
Yeah, we have to take canonical momentum
when looking at conservation laws.
Right.
And now this one is conserved.
Guess what that one's going to say.
That's going to say mx double dot
minus e over c
b times y dot is equal to zero.
In other words, it's going to say m
I think it's going to be m if we do it right.
The x component
I think is going to be equal to plus
e over c b v sub y.
I may have lost
a sign here someplace.
Whenever you go from x to y,
there's always a sign change.
And that's about all.
Alright, what is this?
This is the other Lorentz force law.
Finally,
m a sub z is equal to zero.
That's, those are the
conservation laws, and they
really are nothing but, they
really just express
the Lorentz force law. Nothing more to
them than that. But we didn't have to work
out the equations of motion. We
judiciously chose one gauge
and used one conservation law,
then flipped gauges and said,
oh, in this new gauge, something else
is a cyclic coordinate, and wrote
down the corresponding
conservation law.
Alright, let's do a little bit more.
Yeah?
So the components of momentum,
of canonical momentum,
are not gauges of variance? They are not.
They are not.
The components of mechanical momentum are.
So the canonical momentum
is not a real physical?
It's not something you measure.
Right. It's not something you measure.
On the other hand, it is the thing that goes into
the formal mathematical machinery.
Poisson brackets,
Hamilton's equations,
um,
and, uh,
and so forth.
So, yeah, you pay a price that you've
introduced things, which, I won't say they're
not physical, but they're
not directly measurable. You've introduced
them into the formalism,
uh, and that is
a price, but
uh,
the price is, um,
definitely worth it, since there would be
no way to do all this without
the vector potential.
That might not be a tragedy in classical
physics. In classical physics, you say, oh,
who the hell cares about, um, Hamilton
and Lagrange and all that stuff? Let's just write
down Newton-Lawrence force laws.
And that's true. You could.
Um,
quantum mechanics,
it would be a true disaster.
No way, no way around it.
Okay, let's, uh, let's
study, just for fun now, let's study what
the motion of a system is
in a magnetic field.
We really don't need this anymore.
Now we can just go back to the
Lorentz force law.
The purpose,
we're finished with classical mechanics,
with the formal structure of classical mechanics.
But since we started in on the
motion of particles in a magnetic field,
we might as well finish it.
Uniform magnetic field, what is the motion?
Alright, so let's write it down. Again,
it's mass times acceleration is
equal to, uh, minus, uh,
minus or plus, is equal to, um,
uh,
E over C V cross B.
Alright, now B is into the blackboard, right?
B is into the blackboard,
and let's think about motion,
which, uh, we've already seen
that not much happens along
the z-axis. There's no acceleration
along the z-axis. So in
particular, if the particle is at rest
with respect to z-motion, it'll stay that way.
Let's just leave it that way.
Particles at rest in the z-axis,
if it's only moving in the xy plane,
then these become
equations for x
and equations
for y.
Now B is along the z-axis.
First of all, that means
the acceleration
is perpendicular to both
V and B.
The true acceleration,
in fact, we could write this just,
let's just write it as a vector equation,
equals E over C
V cross B.
Okay,
here's the particle moving in the plane
in the xy plane.
And this tells us that
the acceleration is perpendicular
to both B,
that means it's in the xy plane,
and the velocity.
So it tells us that
the acceleration is perpendicular
to the velocity.
If the velocity is like that,
then the acceleration is perpendicular
to it. Acceleration perpendicular.
What about the magnitude
of the velocity? Does the magnitude
of the velocity change with time?
That's one of the conservation laws,
conservation of energy. And since the energy
came out to be just a good old-fashioned
kinetic energy, the velocity is constant.
So the particle moves along
here with a uniform
velocity.
It has a force perpendicular to it.
And what's the magnitude
of the force perpendicular to it?
Well, the B
field is constant with respect to
everything, it's just pointing in the z-axis.
Okay.
The magnitude of the velocity
is constant.
Therefore,
the magnitude of v cross
B is constant.
It's moving in the xy plane with a constant
speed.
B is in the perpendicular direction.
It means that the magnitude
of the acceleration is constant.
So the magnitude of the acceleration
is constant perpendicular to the velocity.
What's the solution
of a particle
moving so that its acceleration
is always perpendicular to its velocity
and constant?
Circle.
It moves in a circle.
And let's see what we can find out
about that circle.
Um,
if a particle moves
in a circle with velocity
v and radius r,
then its acceleration is
v squared over r.
The magnitude of the acceleration is v squared over r.
The mass
times v squared over r
is the mass times the
magnitude of the acceleration.
And that's equal
to e,
the magnitude of the velocity
times the magnitude of the
magnetic field.
Just the magnitude of v cross B
is just the magnitude of the velocity
times the magnitude of the field.
So now we can
cancel out one power of velocity
and
what we have
is a relationship between
the radius of the orbit and its velocity.
Whatever the velocity
of the orbit is,
the radius is given by
mv
over eb
is equal to the radius of the orbit.
So now we know everything.
What about the center?
When I say it's moving in a circular orbit,
where's the center of that orbit?
Nothing I said
determined the center of that orbit.
There's an orbit of this type
moving about any center.
Wherever you are,
there's an orbit which circulates
around that point.
So there's an infinite number
of circular orbits
characterized either
well, first of all
by their position,
the position of the center,
and next by
the velocity of the center.
So the center of the orbit
is the
magnitude of the velocity
or the magnitude of the radius.
One or the other.
So every place you can go in a plane
there could be an electron moving in a circle.
Some big circles,
some small circles.
The bigger the circle,
the larger the velocity.
Or the bigger the velocity,
the larger the circle.
And there's a lot of orbits.
A lot of orbits, but they're all circular.
So it's interesting, just for fun.
Let's add an electric field.
Let's add an electric field
and see what we can find out.
Let's write down...
We dropped the c in there.
We put the c back...
Yeah, where does the c go?
You're right.
It's e over c.
So it's c times velocity.
c times velocity.
That's weird, isn't it?
Did I do that right?
Well, it is e over c.
I'm sorry.
The bigger the electric charge...
Let's see.
The bigger the electric charge,
the smaller the orbit.
Large electric charge means tight orbit.
So e does go in the bottom.
And if e goes in the bottom,
then c goes on the top.
Yeah, that's right.
Okay.
So now we know all about charged particles.
Incidentally,
I'm going to write down
the number of particles.
Okay, that's enough.
The b doesn't do any work on it
because the force is always at right angles.
Perpendicular, always at right angles.
Right.
Quick question.
When you first wrote down that Lagrangian,
it went by kind of fast.
That right-hand part
had to do with the magnetic field.
Did you just say,
I happen to know the answer,
I'm going to write it down?
For which part of it?
The vector potential.
The original a dot v.
Yeah.
Well, it depends on where you want to start.
You could start here.
You could start here and say,
here is a thing we could add to a Lagrangian.
Let's investigate what it does.
Let's imagine we did that.
We say, look,
we have these x dot squared terms in a Lagrangian.
Let's see what happens.
Let's explore the possibility
that we add to the Lagrangian
something involving a vector.
Something involving a field,
a of x dot velocity.
Let's explore it.
The first thing we would discover
if we made that argument about
we would quickly discover
I don't know how quickly we would discover it,
but we would discover
that the equations of motion are gauge invariant.
We would discover
that from the argument
that the action
doesn't respond to an addition
of a gradient to a
or it responds,
to a gradient to a gradient
at the end points,
we would discover the interesting fact
that the equations of motion
would be invariant under a gauge transformation.
Interesting fact.
Put it in your hat and we'll come back to it.
But then we would just go through
the analysis of the equations of motion
and come and derive the Lorentz force law.
If we never heard of the Lorentz force law,
we would say, ah, here's a new thing.
Here's a new way that particles could move.
So that would be one starting point.
Just write it down.
Another starting point
might be some conviction that for some
reason
there should be a notion of
gauge invariance and
that the Lagrangian
we should write down should be gauge invariant.
That would be a very modern
point of view, but the reason that point of view came about
is because of so many experiences
having discovered things the long way
and discovering
oh, there's this principle of
gauge invariance, so now when you're
going to write down a Lagrangian, the first thing you do
is you make sure it's gauge invariant.
Um, may not be terribly satisfying to you.
Or you can simply start
with the Lorentz force law and say
let's look for an action principle.
Now, um,
that's, we could have done it that way.
It would,
why didn't I,
uh,
it's a little harder, that's all.
It's just a little harder to make, prove the
theorem that you have to introduce
the vector potential, but, uh,
I just wanted to make sure I remember where the vector potential is.
Yeah, well we started, we started
by saying, let's just
try this out. Let's see what it does.
And let's, you know,
the whole thing could have been reversed because
let's try this out.
We would have discovered the equation of motion
involved this funny thing called
dA by dx minus dA
by dx
times x dots.
We would have discovered that.
We might have said,
let's give this thing a name, let's call it b.
Since it's the only
thing that really does come into the force law.
And we would have discovered the magnetic
field. That's one
line of logic. Historically, of course,
it didn't happen that way.
But it could have happened that somebody
just sat down and said, let's explore this
kind of term in the action.
Uh,
Do we need to do something to
show that what we're considering as a
possible Lagrangian is legitimate?
That it obeys whatever constraints?
Well, that
raises the question of what are the constraints
on a Lagrangian that it is.
Um, and
the usual answer is everything is okay
as long as you
can derive a Hamiltonian,
a unique Hamiltonian.
Now that always involves solving
for the velocities in terms of the
momenta.
Remember, we have to solve for the x dots
in terms of the momenta.
Sometimes you get equations that don't have
unique solutions.
Then you're in hot water.
Uh, but, um,
Yeah, it's a legitimate
question. What are the legitimate
Lagrangians? And they're basically
those that lead to a sensible Hamiltonian.
And they don't lead to ambiguities
in the equations.
Yeah?
Should this be v squared in this equation?
Uh,
I don't remember.
We canceled out of v.
Oh, we canceled out of v.
We had a v squared on this side, and we had a v on this side.
Yeah?
Does the symmetry under, uh,
gauge transformation give us a conserved quantity?
Not at this point.
Eventually, yes.
In classical
In classical electrodynamics.
Yeah.
But it's a conserved
It's a sort of
It's a conserved quantity that we knew anyway, but
let's not try to go for that now.
It gives us
It gives a conserved quantity,
but only
when you include into the dynamics
the equations of motion
of the vector potential itself.
And that's already, um,
beyond us for now.
Maxwell's equation?
Yeah, I was just going to ask, how does all of this relate to Maxwell?
Well, it doesn't.
In order to make it relate to Maxwell's equations,
we have to add to the action
the things which generate Maxwell's equations.
This has just got to do
with a fixed
given electric and magnetic field
how do particles move?
Now we can ask,
alright, but now let's ask how
the electromagnetic field itself changes
with time. And that involves
adding additional things to the Lagrangian
that have to do with the dynamics
of the electromagnetic field.
That I was going to teach next quarter,
but it looks like we're putting it off for a quarter.
At least a quarter.
Um,
there is an action
for the electromagnetic field
and, uh, it satisfies
the principle of least action.
This is one of the
terms in it,
A times dx, but it has
more.
The more doesn't involve the
coordinates or the velocities of the particles.
So when you're studying
the motion of the particles
and their equations of motion, the rest of it doesn't matter.
Uh, if delta B is not zero,
how would it change these equations?
Well, you couldn't write
them down.
If delta B were not equal
to zero, then you
couldn't express B in terms
of a vector potential, and if you
couldn't express B in terms of a vector potential,
you couldn't have written any of this down.
But, you could have
said, I don't care,
I'm just going to write down the Lorentz
forces. And that's okay, you
can do that. You can say, I don't care
whether the whole thing
comes from a Lagrangian or not.
I'm just going to write down
that M A is
equal to E over C V cross
B.
And hell or high water, that's
my rule, and it's a perfectly good rule.
It's a perfectly
good equation of motion.
It does not follow from a
Lagrangian unless
B is
um,
comes from a vector potential,
but who cares?
Um, the answer
is you would have a lot of trouble with quantum mechanics,
but that's for another time. Yeah?
This might be for another time
as well, but since you said magnetic
monopoles are likely to
actually exist, or maybe expected.
What's that? Say it again?
You said that the non-existence of
magnetic monopoles is
thought to probably be wrong.
Can we rescue this?
You know, in the presence of
monopoles? Yeah. Yeah.
Yes, you can.
Um,
Yeah.
Magnetic
monopole is the north end of a magnet,
or the south end of a magnet.
There's always another end there.
There was
a magnet called the
D'Aquino-D'Ansel.
But if you had a very, very long magnet,
and you took the south pole end of it and stuck it off
on Alpha Centauri somewhere, and just waved
around the north pole of it,
and if the magnet, the bar magnet,
or the whatever it was, was sufficiently
skinny and thin
so that you couldn't see it,
maybe it was so thin that it would pass
right between the molecules in your body,
uh,
without harming them,
without a magnetic monopole.
So, that's a kind of
existence proof, in a sense.
There's nothing wrong with that
from the point of view of fundamental principles
that you have an extremely
skinny, uh,
bar magnet, so skinny
that nobody can see it, and so skinny that
it can pass between
the atoms of your body.
It doesn't violate anything in classical physics
anyway. So, you take
a very long bar magnet.
Now, that bar magnet
really does have, or it could be a solenoid,
it could be a solenoid. A solenoid
is a, uh,
you know, wires going around with current
flowing in them, and
the magnetic field comes out
just as if this were a magnetic monopole.
But, if you look really carefully,
you would discover there was also a magnetic
field in here.
So it goes in here
and out here.
Well, if this
solenoid is really,
really thin,
uh, perhaps it doesn't affect
the motion of particles and so forth,
unless a particle by accident just happens
to pass through the solenoid,
which may be an extremely improbable thing
if the solenoid is thin enough,
then you've manufactured yourself
a monopole.
Question?
The magnetic flux density in the solenoid
or the bar magnet is, of course, infinite.
Yeah. No, no, no. That's kind of a...
No, actually.
Yeah. No.
Um...
That, of course, is the objection, but so what?
So there's an infinite magnetic field in there.
What's the next statement?
The next statement is that there's an infinite
energy flux density in there. Good. Right.
Right. Right. So supposing I were to
tell you that the wires of the
solenoid have negative
energy, just enough to cancel that out.
Oh, but besides,
what do you care if it has infinite energy?
It's just an invisible thing with
infinite energy, so it's got an infinite energy.
So what?
You say it's hard to move then, right?
Well, you just need somebody very strong.
No, it...
It, uh...
You're asking
a serious question. The answer
really turns out to be much more interesting.
The answer is, in quantum mechanics, that the energy
is actually a periodic function of a magnetic
field, and
if you put in the right
quantum of magnetic
field through here, then it's truly invisible
and it doesn't cost any energy.
Point particles do have a magnetic moment.
Hm? Point particles
do have a magnetic moment.
Magnetic moments, but not magnetic
monopoles.
Point particles have magnetic moments, but
bar...magnetic dipoles, but...
so do bar magnets.
A dipole
is not a monopole.
A monopole means one pole.
A dipole means an equal and opposite pair
of poles.
Right, it's very difficult to distinguish
having
a north pole
and a south pole
with nothing in between.
And having a north pole
and a south pole with a very skinny
bar magnet between them.
Um...
...
So...
But it's kind of interesting. Supposing
you tried to separate the north pole from the
south pole.
So you, uh, take a
scissor and cut the
solenoid connecting them.
North pole, south pole, and then move
the north pole far away and the south pole
far away.
Unfortunately, the place
where you cut it develops a north pole
and the place where you cut it over here...
North pole.
North pole. South pole.
So you just make a pair of magnets. You don't make
a magnetic monopole.
So can you have a tape to stretch
the dipoles
farther apart?
Without breaking it, you mean? Yes.
Yeah.
But, you know, I mean, I say I don't need
to stretch it to infinity to fool you into
thinking there's a magnetic monopole over here.
I just take this thing, I put
the rest of it in my back pocket, and I say
look, here's a magnetic monopole, guys. Look, I got
one.
At the risk of violating what you said earlier on, the analogy would be the same as quarks and anti-quarks, right?
Quarks and anti-quarks confined by, uh...
Yeah.
Yeah. Uh...
Right.
You can't isolate a quark.
Exactly. Same phenomenon.
Right.
Same phenomenon. Or a very similar phenomenon.
So I didn't want to get into magnetic
monopoles. I thought, make the story
simple. In classical
electrodynamics, without
worrying about the subtleties of monopoles
and so forth, one
of Maxwell's equations, this is one of
Maxwell's equations, del dot p equals zero.
If you start mucking around with this,
it's possible to
rescue the situation,
but new physics has to
go into it, such as
such as
solenoids
with negative energy to cancel out
your infinite energy.
So some new physics has to come in,
and that new physics
is not built into ordinary
electrodynamics.
See, in ordinary electrodynamics, there
you're perfectly right that there's a
magnetic field in there, a certain
magnetic flux. You've squeezed
it down to a very, very
thin solenoid
that increases the magnetic field,
and in fact, it increases
the field energy in there.
E equals mc squared, so among
other things, you've increased the mass
of that solenoid,
and you really
can't
get away with that,
but new physics comes into
play when this thing shrinks down
to sufficiently small size.
That new physics could involve
all sorts of new things about
elementary particle physics, and it does,
and those new things
change the picture, and in
fact, make the
energy to be a periodic function
of the magnetic field, so that if you
make the magnetic field, or
magnetic flux, so if you make
the magnetic flux through there big enough,
all of a sudden, the energy
returns to zero. But that's, as I said,
lots of new physics goes in there.
Things like superconductivity?
Um,
no.
Why, no, no, no, no, no,
I mean, this is,
this is, um,
way beyond,
this is
particle physics of a very high energy
kind that would take to do that.
Magnetic monopoles,
if they exist, are expected
to be associated with physics
at enormously high energy scales,
and not, uh,
something we're likely to see in the
foreseeable future. On the other hand,
every
good theory that I know of,
of elementary particles, has
magnetic monopoles in it.
So, they're probably part
of the story, but they're
not part of classical
electrodynamics.
One more
question, yeah.
Yeah, I've read that Hamilton
spent a lot of his years
working with
some strange numbers called
quaternions, and there's the
quaternions,
that sort of thing. How did they
fit into this whole theory?
Um,
no, they were a separate issue, really.
I'll tell you what this
idea was. I think I've
showed you many times how powerful complex
numbers are in keeping track of
rotations and things like that
of a plane, and they're
almost completely useless for keeping
track of rotations and things in
three dimensions.
Hamilton wanted to invent a
formalism where
there was similar,
a similar
structure for three-dimensional space.
So,
he said, instead of having one
imaginary number, and in fact,
what he wound up with,
maybe not so happily, I don't know,
was a theory of four-dimensional space.
But,
he said, let's
add, instead of
having only one imaginary number,
where i squared is equal to minus one,
he introduced three of them,
i, j, and k, one for each axis
of space.
This is sort of like
thinking of
the imaginary numbers associated with
the vertical axis. And then there was
a fourth axis, the fourth axis was
for the real numbers, one.
And then
you just start writing numbers,
constant times i plus another constant
times j plus another constant times k.
You have some rules about
multiplication. i times
j equals k.
And cyclic
permutations of it.
And it
works very well.
It's got another name now.
It's called
Pauli matrices.
The Pauli matrices
of quantum mechanics are the
quaternions.
But,
it really didn't have much to do with,
there's other
work on mechanics.
It was a separate issue.
The big long bar magnet
you discussed to North Pole
and the South Pole would behave the same way.
Say it again?
You have a big long
skinny magnet that stretches out to
the south of the century to simulate a monopole.
And you
discussed the North Pole having monopole properties.
Did the South Pole
behave the same way?
Except it has the opposite magnetic charge.
It's like a plus charge and a minus charge
except magnetic instead of electric.
Yeah.
Right.
And if you bring them together,
touch them together,
they just disappear.
It's like taking the North Pole of a magnet and the South Pole
and bringing them together.
There's no poles left anymore.
Not there, anywhere.
Okay.
You know at some point you
might go into chaos, at least
with respect to phase-base.
Yeah, well, I guess we ran out of time, didn't we?
Yeah.
So I guess
uh
yeah, it's the one thing
I would have done had we had another week
or so.
That's alright.
You've got the material now. You can go and
um
It's all orbits
in phase-space. Orbits in phase-space.
Okay.
Let's uh
Let's quit.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.