This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
All right,
I am not going to tell
you the entire history of cosmology.
We're gonna get straight to the point.
The point is the expanding universe
and the geometry of the expanding universe.
Well,
let's back off for a
minute and discuss what it is,
where it is we want to go.
I want to teach you the basics of modern cosmology,
and the basics of modern cosmology consist
of a handful of things,
not a lot,
but of course the things which went into the discoveries,
especially the observational discoveries.
There are a lot more
that I'm going to tell you,
but basically we're going to take,
you
know,
go to the end of the story to a large
extent and say what is it that we know now.
We're going to start with the basic Big Bang theory.
We're not gonna go back in time
before there was a Big Bang theory.
We're gonna start with the basic Big Bang theory,
the three possible versions of it.
We're gonna do it from two points of view.
So it's gonna start with the general theory of relativity,
somewhere around the entire
universe.
But it's going to start
with the aims and it Democracy,
and it's going to start with
The simple principles that we're going to describe,
and then edges and articulations
And then in the third cosìote rule
we're doing a test on relative everybody.
are of Big Bang cosmology,
and we'll work out some examples of expanding universes,
the geometry of them,
not the physics of them.
This is the geometry of them.
The physics
is driven by energy and momentum and other dynamical things.
To get a handle on that,
I don't know if we'll do it this week,
but next week,
either this week or next week,
we'll move on to the Newtonian,
F equals MA cosmology.
F equals MA cosmology takes us a long
way,
and we're going to see some connections,
some connections between the geometry and the F equals
MA version of cosmology,
what Newton would have understood as cosmology.
Then we're going to put
them together into a single
package called Friedman-Robertson-Walker FRW Cosmology.
That will take us a couple of weeks.
From there,
we'll address some other questions.
What is inflation?
What is the inflationary theory of cosmology?
What is dark energy?
What is dark matter?
How are they different?
The cosmological constant,
which is dark energy,
the current accelerated expansion of the universe,
and then,
perhaps,
the cosmological constant,
which is dark matter.
Perhaps we'll move on to some more modern esoteric subjects,
such as why do
physicists think perhaps there's much more
to the universe than we can see,
but more than we ever
can see,
and the idea of a multiverse.
I'm not sure what else.
We'll fill in some details as we go
along.
If there are particular things you want me to discuss,
I'll do it as usual,
but let's get
started.
Okay,
let's begin just with the idea of space,
and the simplest possible space,
one-dimensional
space for simplicity.
Then it will immediately add two more dimensions.
Space,
not spacetime.
And it's just good old x-axis.
axis imagine it goes on indefinitely both
in the left direction in the right
direction and imagine embedded in it
are some objects which are equally spaced
they're embedded in the space and I'm
going to give them a name now they're
called galaxies okay one-dimensional galaxies
but they're just particles or
objects which are embedded in this line
okay now the first question is let's
let's label a line with a coordinate
and let's label a line with a coordinate
which in this particular case just measures
off this is X equals zero and
let's use the presence of these galaxies
to define a coordinate so that by
definition the next galaxy over is X equals one
obviously it's not the same thing as the first
one but it's the same thing as the second one
obviously this is an enormous
idealization where I have the galaxies
perfectly uniformly spaced this is of course
not the case in the real world
incidentally for those who may
wonder the world is three-dimensional not
one-dimensional so that's a further
idealization or a further fiction X
equals two this is worse than Flatland this is
Lineland here's X equals minus one whoops minus one
is X equals minus two and
roughly speaking these coordinates simply label
which galaxy we're talking about we could
think of them as the name of the
galaxy this galaxy is called X equals
two this one is called X equals one
they're just labels which move with the
galaxies if the galaxies are moving if
they're spreading apart if they're coming together this
coordinate just as attached to the galaxy all right now
how far is the galaxy from the galaxy to the galaxy?
Is it from let's say x equals zero
to x equals one well it's some distance it's
not one unit this is these are just
the names of these points these don't say
anything about distance I'm going to
assume they're equally spaced but what
is the spacing I haven't told you what
the spacing between them is in meters or
kilometers or light years pick your
favorite unit for the time being the
units that aren't important
but what's that well they are one
galaxy apart if by galaxies we mean the
distance between galaxies hmm well we could
use the size of each galaxy but we
could use and whether well I don't want
to use the size of the galaxy because
it's going to raise a question I
don't but let's say meters meter sticks we
measure them off and I'm going to call
the distance between X equals 0 and X
equals 1 in meters or whatever definite units
we use the reason I don't want to
use the size of galaxies is because
the size of galaxies changes with time they
tend to contract so I don't want to
get into that but just good old meter sticks
good solid meter sticks that don't
change with time and let's say the
distance between X equals 0 and X
equals 1 let's just call it a a
that's that's it what's the difference
what's the distance between X equals 0
and X equals 2 twice a
because I've assumed that they're really equally
spaced in particular the distance between
any two points is just let's
call it Delta X that's the difference in X
times a a times the difference in X if
it's X equals 2 minus X equals 0
and it's 2a this is the distance
between any two galaxies Delta X means
the difference of X this could be X equals
let's see 1 2 3 4 5 the distance
between the galaxy called X equals 5
and the galaxy called X equals 1 that's
Delta X equals 4 times a is the distance a
times 4 is the same as 4 times a and
so that's the difference between X equals
3 and X equals minus 1 that's also
4 times a and so that's the
notation that's the notational thing we're going
to do distance is the coordinate difference
times a and a has a name it's
called the scale factor it's called the
scale factor its name is name is the
scale factor
okay now the galaxies may be moving
think of this line imagine this line for
the moment as an elastic thread
an infinite elastic thread but about
infinite is too big right for right
now a very large elastic thread and there
are two Giants at the end and the
two Giants are having fun with the people in
this in this universe and they're
pulling maybe they all also even
allow it to go the other way they
change the total length of the of the
world so to speak just by
pulling on this thread and stretching it
contracting it doing whatever it is they
decide to do mostly stretch it but for
the time being what does that mean about
a that simply means that a depends on
time the distance between two nations
neighboring galaxies will depend on time
exactly as it would think of rubber
band cut the rubber band open though I
don't want to be double and think about
stretching and instead of galaxies think
about the rubber molecules you stretch
that increases the distance between
neighboring molecules you contract it
that decreases the distance and so in that
way in general a is a function of
time
in this world with these Giants who are
pulling on the end of the string this is
not string theory incidentally nothing to
do with string theory not yet anyway
I've heard that in Berkeley there's
a restaurant called noodle theory can
anybody confirm that this is true
noodle theory ok ok so
this is this is the universe
and the universe is such that first
of all it is homogeneous homogeneous means
equal spacing that's all equal spacing it's
everywhere is the same so to speak
every one of these galaxies looks at
its neighbor and says you are a certain
number of meters away galaxy over here
sees the same thing as a galaxy over
here and so forth that's the
term homogeneous everywhere is the same equal
spacing but the spacing itself imagine
that it's time dependent ok let's now
calculate the rate at which the distance
between two galaxies grows or shrinks the
rate at which the distance changes
with time let's calculate it there's another
word for the rate at which distance changes
what?
I don't know
what velocity right actually speed but velocity
right velocity so when I say I'm
calculating the rate at which the the
galaxy at x equals 4 moves or increases
relative to x equals 1 I could
say it another way I'm calculating the velocity
of x equals 4 relative to x equals 1
but I don't just want to call it the
velocity I want to call
it the velocity of one point
relative to another all right we know
what the distance is here's the distance
it's a times Delta x now we're
taking two fixed galaxies two fixed galaxies
this one over here and this one
over here we're not going to change those
galaxies and that means that Delta x is
not going to change with time we just
fixed the two galaxies we want to talk
about but what does change with time a
alright?
so what is the distance
at which the galaxy will move?
is the rate at which d increases with time.
It's just d dot,
and for those who haven't been,
who are new to this class,
dot always means time derivative,
derivative with respect to time,
d by dt.
That's what a dot means,
derivative with respect to time.
I'll use that notation,
and it means the rate
at which the thing is changing with time.
The rate at which d is changing with time,
delta x is not increasing or decreasing,
so d dot is delta x,
that's unchanged,
but a is changing with time,
a dot.
The time rate of change of a product like this,
if one of the factors is not changing,
is just that factor times the
time derivative of the other one.
So this is the rate at
which d is changing with time,
let's call it d of delta x,
the distance between two points separated by delta x,
that's just this.
Now I'm going to do,
oh,
and what do we call this?
We call this the velocity,
the relative velocity
between the two points.
It's the velocity of the two points,
the velocity that the astronomer at x equals one
would see x equals five moving away from him,
or moving toward him.
It's also the velocity that x equals five would see
of x one either moving away or coming closer.
It depends on whether the
derivative is positive or negative,
whether they're growing larger or less,
whether they're approaching or receding.
All right,
so let's write this,
and now I'm going to write,
a totally unnecessary step.
I'm going to divide this and multiply it by a.
Physicists and mathematicians are always dividing
and multiplying by the same thing,
and you think,
why bother?
Well,
let's look at it.
Here's a times delta x.
What is that?
That's d.
Okay,
so I can rewrite this as a dot over a.
That's the ratio of the rate
of change of a to a itself
times the distance.
Now I've discovered something interesting.
The velocity of recession,
well,
I haven't discovered anything interesting yet,
but I will have discovered
something interesting in a moment.
Okay.
Does a dot and a depend
on which galaxies I'm talking about?
No.
a and a dot are the same for every galaxy,
a in particular.
a is just the distance between neighboring galaxies,
but it doesn't depend on which galaxy we're talking about.
So a is the same for everybody,
the scale factor.
It's a universal idea,
which everybody agrees about,
what the distance to his neighbor is.
It changes with time,
but a dot over a does not depend on x.
It doesn't depend on which galaxy we're talking about.
And what this equation then says
is the velocity between two points
is proportional to something which does not
depend on which galaxy we're talking about,
a dot over a,
we're going to give it another name in a moment,
times the distance between them.
Anybody know what the name
of a dot over a is?
The Hubble constant.
Velocity is proportional to distance,
is what this says,
with a number in there,
a dot over a.
Now,
is this necessarily constant
if the universe is expanding and contracting,
or doing whatever the devil
these giants have decided to do?
Is a dot over a a constant?
No,
it changes with time.
But it doesn't change with position.
It's a constant in the
sense that it's the same everywhere,
but it is not a constant in the
sense that it does not depend on time.
So the Hubble constant,
the thing which people,
I prefer to call it the Hubble parameter,
calling it constant makes you think,
it's like the electric charge of an electron,
or something else like that,
that it really doesn't depend on anything.
No,
the Hubble constant is a function of time,
but it's not a function
of which galaxy we're talking about.
So,
what does this say?
It simply says,
the further apart two galaxies are,
by that I mean,
the further apart,
in real distance,
the faster they will be moving apart.
I say apart,
but again,
I could be more talking about coming together.
And the factor of proportionality is the Hubble constant.
Where among other things,
it says that if you look out,
if an observer over here,
looks out to more distant galaxies,
the further away he looks,
the faster you will be seeing them move.
If he looks at his closest neighbor,
you'll see him moving away from him,
perhaps,
at a certain rate.
If he moves at the second,
if he looks at the second nearest neighbor,
he will see him moving a little bit faster.
If he will see the third nearest neighbor,
he will see him moving yet faster.
The further away he looks,
the faster that will be moving to the right.
The same is true.
There's nothing in this which has focused attention
on x equals zero,
or x equals one.
It's the relative separation of two things
which are entirely symmetric,
and it's the same everywhere.
So there's no notion of a center to this line.
All points are the same as every other point,
but every pair of points are increasing their distance
with a velocity that's proportional to h times d.
That's the Hubble law.
Now,
there's nothing especially one-dimensional about this.
Let's do it in more dimensions.
Any questions about the meaning of this formula?
Yeah,
if the galaxies are far enough apart,
then they are going faster than the speed of light.
Right.
That will play a very important role in cosmology.
What you're saying is correct.
Um...
And we will come back to that for sure.
It's one of the most important things.
Okay.
One other thing.
If these...
Again,
Alice and Bob.
This is Alice's galaxy.
This is Bob's galaxy.
Alice and Bob are sending each other messages
with light waves or whatever.
The faster Bob moves off to the right,
the more Doppler shift...
Again,
they're sending their messages
with standard message senders
made in the same factory
of exactly the same kind.
So they're sending light,
if you like,
of a very,
very definite frequency
in their own reference frame.
But by the time it gets from Alice's signal,
by the time it gets to Bob,
the Doppler shift will have reddened that light.
Or,
yes,
reddened it.
I'm always going to assume from now on
that everything is being stretched
and not contracted,
at least for the moment.
So Bob will detect Alice's message being slowed down,
but Alice will also detect Bob's message being slowed down.
Everything is entirely symmetric between them.
And it's simply the problem of two people
moving apart from each other,
or the sending light rays.
The faster they move apart,
the more redshifted the signal will be.
So that's a fact about an expanding universe.
The further you are away,
the faster you move,
and the faster you move,
the more Doppler shifted
will be messages.
Now,
the kind of messages that we really have in mind,
of course,
is messages which are sent at frequencies
which are determined
by basic underlying physics.
The underlying physics might be transitions of atoms
from one energy level to another energy level,
spectral lines.
Spectral lines are good,
standard frequency or wavelength...
What should we call them?
They have very definite wavelengths
in their own frame of reference.
And so,
for example,
if Alice is sending Bob
a particular spectral line from the sodium...
from some sodium transition,
that will be sent,
in his frame of reference,
at the usual frequency of a sodium line.
But by the time it gets to Bob over here,
it will be reddened or lowered in frequency.
One way that Alice can measure the distance to Bob
is by monitoring the frequency of the light.
Or the spectral lines that come from Bob's galaxy.
The faster he's moving away,
the more reddened the frequency will be.
So that gives you a tool.
Now,
we're not going to spend very much time
talking about observation.
But that gives you a tool,
or gives Alice a tool,
for measuring the velocity of recession,
of any galaxy.
That's velocity.
How about the distance to any galaxy?
Are there various ways?
Are there ways of measuring
the actual distance to a galaxy?
Well,
let me give you a very simple...
more or less what Hubble actually did.
Hubble estimated,
in his first round of detections,
his method for estimating the distance to a galaxy
was very simple.
If the galaxy was bright and big in the sky,
it was close.
If it was small and dim,
it was far.
Uh...
The dimness of a given size object...
Well,
from the size in the sky and from the brightness,
he could estimate the distance.
For reasons unknown to anybody,
Hubble decided to plot on a plot...
the distance...
of a given galaxy that
he could see in the sky.
Again,
pretty much just from the size of it.
There are much more sophisticated ways
of measuring distance than just by size and brightness.
But that's clearly one way to measure the distance.
And on the vertical axis,
he measured the velocity of the galaxies.
Well,
first of all,
the first thing he discovered
is that all of the distant galaxies...
Now,
distant to Hubble
doesn't mean what we would call distant galaxies today.
Hubble...
When was Hubble?
When did Hubble do these wonderful things?
In the 20s sometime.
Uh...
Not 1820,
1920.
Did he really use galaxies,
or did he use something else?
He used galaxies.
Yeah.
Oh,
it's an interesting historical fact
that up until...
Let's see,
when was it?
I'm not exactly sure.
Again,
it was Hubble.
Probably 1920 or something.
I'm not sure when exactly.
The idea of a galaxy didn't exist.
All we knew about was one bunch of stars,
the Milky Way,
across the sky,
and people spoke of an island universe,
that we lived in an island of stars
with nothing out further than that.
They did discover that there
were these blotchy things out there.
But it was not recognized that those blotchy things
were other island universes,
so to speak.
It wasn't really until sometime in the...
in the middle of the early 20th century
that Hubble realized that what he was seeing
when he saw these smudges in the sky
were collections of stars.
That they were collections of huge numbers of stars
which rivaled in size and in size
and number of stars the Milky Way itself.
So that was the first discovery.
The universe is filled with galaxies.
And then he,
as I said,
measured the distance of galaxies
and the velocity of galaxies.
And he discovered,
first thing that surprised him,
the galaxies are moving away from us.
Apart from one or two galaxies
which are very close to us,
our closest neighbor,
in fact,
just happens to be moving toward us.
It's a more or less accidental fact
that it's so close to
us that it's sort of trapped
by our galaxy's gravity.
And it happens to be moving toward us.
What's the name of the closest galaxy?
The Andromeda.
Right.
So the Andromeda is moving toward us.
That is more or less an exception.
If you look out beyond the Andromeda galaxy
to galaxies three,
four,
five,
six times further away
or a hundred times further away,
they're moving away.
So that was the first discovery.
Almost all the galaxies,
and in particular,
all of the distant galaxies were moving away from us.
Furthermore,
they were moving away from us
by a velocity which depended on their distance.
And when he plotted it,
he got a perfect,
exact,
straight line.
Nonsense.
Of course he didn't get it.
He got a mishmash
which was all over the place.
Error bars.
But somehow he looked at this,
and whether he was intuiting the right answer
or he was a master of statistics,
which I don't think he was,
or whatever it was,
he drew a straight line to it
and he said,
look,
velocity is proportional to distance.
He actually didn't
know why.
He had no idea.
The simple argument did not exist.
It's been explained in an even simpler way
than this,
but this picture here
is correct and really at the heart of the matter.
But it was explained by other people just saying,
look,
why are you surprised
that the fastest horse goes the furthest in a race?
That if you look at a horse race,
expect that the fastest horse
is the fastest one that's gone the furthest.
The fastest galaxy is most likely to be
the one that's gotten furthest away from you.
But that,
of course,
is just a...
It's true,
but this is the right way to say it.
This is the right way to say it.
Velocity is proportional to Hubble constant times d.
Now,
Hubble was not very good at the time
at measuring the distances to the galaxies.
This wasn't his own fault.
He just had crude tools at the time.
And he measured the galaxies as being maybe
ten times closer,
I think,
than they actually were.
So his Hubble constant was off by a bit,
like a factor of ten.
That had implications.
Let me explain why.
The bigger the Hubble...
That,
of course,
meant that the Hubble constant
was too big...too big or too small.
Wait,
he measured...which way did he measure it?
He measured the Hubble constant being too big,
as I remember.
Yeah.
He measured the Hubble constant being too big
by a factor of ten.
Now,
that meant that his estimate,
for example,
of this galaxy moving away was ten times too big.
Not that the velocity...the velocity was correct,
but the estimate of the Hubble constant itself
was ten times too big.
It took a while to correct it.
We're going to interpret...we're going to discover
another interpretation of the Hubble constant.
It's basically one over the age of the universe.
I will tell you why later,
not right now.
So he had misestimated the age of the universe
by a factor of ten.
What's that?
It's really hard to tell how far away...
And the more sophisticated tools came into play,
but he misestimated things by a factor of ten.
But he corrected them later.
He corrected them.
In any case,
that's the Hubble law.
It's very,
very central.
I said we can also do
the same thing with more dimensions.
Let's take two dimensions instead of one dimension,
just for simplicity,
x and y,
and again,
make a grid.
Of course,
it's nonsense to say that the galaxies
are at the corners of the grid,
but...
but that's an extreme idealization.
But let's imagine galaxies at the corners of the grid.
Then every galaxy is labeled with two names,
a first name and a last name,
x and y.
And x and y stick with the galaxy.
x and y of a galaxy doesn't change with time.
It just is...
It's just a label that labels the galaxy.
But the distance between neighbors is again called a
in both directions.
Ah,
that brings up an interesting question.
Why is it...
Do we know?
Do we know that the separation between galaxies
in this grid model...
We could ask,
how do we know that the separation
between galaxies along the x-axis is the same
as the separation between galaxies along the y-axis?
Do we know?
What do we know about it?
Well,
supposing the galaxies were not equally spaced,
or not that they were...
They were equally spaced,
but they were more crowded in the x-direction
than they were in the y-direction.
At the corners,
like that.
When we look down into...
When we look out into the sky,
we would discover that things are different along the y-axis
than they are along the x-axis.
We'd look out along the
x-axis and see very crowded galaxies.
We'd look along the y-axis,
and discover they were very,
very separated.
We don't.
We see the same distribution of galaxies
pretty much in every direction in the sky.
There's a principle involved.
It's not a principle.
It's actually just a name for that fact.
It is called the isotropy of the universe.
Two basic names.
The homogeneity of the universe.
That means everywhere is the same.
Now,
this is everywhere is the same,
at least on a scale larger
than the distance between these galaxies.
Looked at on a bigger scale,
we would say every place is
the same as every other place.
Everybody has a couple of neighbors around them,
and that's all.
And every place is the same as every other place.
This here is also homogeneous.
This place is the same as this place,
or has the same properties as this place over here.
This one is the same as this one.
There's no sense in which
this one over here is special.
No different than that one.
But there is something different about this than this.
It has to do with angles
in the sky rather than positions.
It's not isotropic.
It isn't the same in every direction.
It's the same in every place,
but it isn't the same in every direction.
There's a directionality to this,
a directional bias.
When we look in the sky,
we don't see different things in different directions.
Of course,
that's not entirely true.
I mean,
when I look up,
I see something different than when I look down.
When I look on a scale of our galaxy,
if I look into the plane of the galaxy,
I see the Milky Way.
If I look out of the plane of the galaxy,
I see a much darker sky.
But on a scale bigger than this,
on a scale bigger than a few hundred galaxies,
the sky looks the same in every direction.
So,
the principle is called homogeneity and isotropy.
Now,
how well do we really know
that the universe is,
or how well did Hubble,
or the people at that time,
really know that the universe was homogeneous?
And the answer is not very well at all.
They were able to look through telescopes
only to a minute fraction
of what we can see today.
So,
really,
there was no good reason to believe
that the universe was homogeneous on
scales much bigger than they could see.
Nevertheless,
all cosmologists assumed it,
and it turned out to be essentially correct,
that the universe is homogeneous and isotropic,
same in every direction,
same in every place.
That makes life simple,
much simpler than if it was
just randomly different in different places.
Okay,
where were we?
Yeah,
let's come back now to two dimensions.
And the spacing of galaxies
along the x-axis and the y-axis,
the grid size is the same.
What's the distance between two galaxies
separated by distance delta x along the x-axis
and delta y along the y-axis?
Okay.
If...
Anybody want to shoot at it?
What's the distance?
Square root of...
This is Pythagorean theorem.
Well,
first of all,
what's the distance along the x-axis?
It's a times delta x.
The distance along the y-axis,
in other words,
if we took two galaxies,
one over here and one over here,
this is the distance...
What's that?
Yeah.
A times the delta x.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Yeah,
that's right.
But let's write it down anyway.
Let's go through the steps.
The distance along the x-axis is a times delta x.
The distance along the y-axis is a times delta y.
And then using the Pythagorean theorem,
the distance between them is just
d is equal to the square root of
delta x squared
times a squared
plus delta y squared
and now we can factor the a squared
out of the square root
and again,
as Michael says,
it's just proportional to a.
It's proportional to a,
the distance,
and now instead of just simply delta x,
it's the square root of delta x squared
plus delta y squared.
Well,
what would happen if there was a third dimension?
Plus delta z squared.
That's the three-dimensional Pythagorean theorem.
Which I don't know if Pythagoras
knew or if he didn't know.
Okay,
that's the distance.
What's the velocity between these two points?
One over here and one out here somewheres?
It's just the time derivative of this.
Alright?
So the velocity
is given by the same square root,
which I won't bother to write,
times the time derivative of a.
a dot.
That's the velocity of a dot.
That's the velocity of recession.
And now we just multiply
it and divide it by a.
a over a.
Same trick as before.
And recognize that a times the square root
is just the distance.
So we get exactly the same formula as before.
Distance times Hubble constant.
The Hubble constant doesn't depend on direction,
it doesn't depend on where you are,
but it does depend on time.
In general.
It may depend on time.
Velocity equals distance times Hubble constant.
And it doesn't depend on the dimensionality of space.
Okay,
that's the Hubble law.
And as I said,
it's an extremely simple idea.
Now let's talk about the geometry of space.
Just one question for a minute.
And you may get to this later,
but this has always bothered
me about this sort of thing.
So the velocity is proportional
to Hubble constant times the distance.
This means the distance actually is increasing,
so velocity is increasing.
So Bob and Alice are
both being accelerated within our model,
but neither one of them perceives that.
No.
The velocity is not,
well,
you don't know whether the velocity is increasing with time.
What you can say is,
the velocity increases with distance.
Alright?
But,
here's a possibility.
The velocity of all of these,
um,
yeah.
Whether the velocity of a given galaxy
is increasing or decreasing relative to us
depends on how A is changing with time.
For example,
let's take a simple possibility.
Supposing A was simply proportional to time.
The distance between two neighboring galaxies
is just increasing with time,
with some velocity,
some particular velocity.
Let's just call it T.
Velocity 1U.
A was proportional to T.
That's just,
each link here in this lattice of galaxies
is increasing linearly with time.
What,
how does the velocity,
what is the velocity between these two points?
T.
DT.
Delta T,
Delta A.
The distance between them is A,
and the velocity is just
dA,
dT,
which is 1.
Well,
I don't want it to be 1,
because 1 stands for the speed of light,
and let's,
let's,
a half,
or a quarter,
a quarter T.
Supposing A was increasing like a quarter T.
That's a perfectly good law.
Then,
the velocity between the two neighbors here
is just one quarter,
and it stays one quarter for all time.
It doesn't change.
But what's the velocity between
this point and this point?
Twice the velocity between the neighboring points.
So it's one half.
The velocity increases
with respect to looking at more and more distant neighbors,
but it may or may not increase with time,
the velocity.
With time,
the velocity between any two galaxies.
Here's another example.
Supposing A increased
like T squared.
The distance between this galaxy and this galaxy
is increasing like T squared.
What is the velocity between them?
2T.
The velocity is just 2T.
In this case,
the velocity between these two galaxies
is increasing with time.
In any case,
it increases with distance.
Depending on the details
of how A depends on time,
the galaxies may be accelerating away from each other
or even decelerating.
For example,
supposing A,
let's take another law.
Well,
let's take the law A goes
like E to the minus T.
Is that a good law?
No,
that's not a good law.
Uh,
Log T.
Okay,
let's take log T.
Uh,
yeah,
let's take log T.
Good,
thank you.
That was good.
Log T.
What is the velocity between these two neighboring points?
The velocity between them
is the derivative of log T,
which is 1 over T.
In this case,
the velocity is decreasing with time.
As time gets bigger,
the velocity is decreasing.
That would be saying that they're decelerating
relative to each other.
So you can have acceleration,
you can have deceleration,
but always the Hubble law is correct
as a function of distance.
Okay.
That's the basic Hubble law
and it is the basic fact
that all else is built on.
The...
You know,
it used to be thought
that the universe was decelerating.
The reason was very simple.
Uh,
well,
it was thought that gravity
was pulling the universe together.
If gravity was pulling the universe together,
think about it starting expanding,
gravity would slow it down.
Just like gravity slows down this pen
as it's going up
and will eventually turn it around,
it was thought that the universe was expanding,
but that the pull of gravity
was pulling things back together
and therefore decelerating it.
That's what was thought to be the case.
We now know that that's not the case
and the universe is expanding
at an accelerated rate.
Okay.
Everything is accelerating away from us
rather than moving with a uniform velocity.
Okay.
Other questions?
I've got one.
Yeah.
How do you set the initial value of A?
I mean,
since it's changing?
Well,
you pick...
Yeah,
that's a good question,
but you pick some particular time
at any time.
The initial value of A
is somewhat arbitrary.
Um,
it's not really the initial value of A.
It's at which particular time
do we set A equal to some particular...
Or do we measure A?
It doesn't matter.
You'll always get the same answer.
You might worry about
when the particular details,
how they affect the Hubble constant.
I think you're asking,
what you're asking about is
supposing you called this distance 2A or 3A,
would you get a different answer for the Hubble?
Just by name.
You just gave it a different name.
Instead of the scale factor being
the distance between these two galaxies,
let's take it to be the distance out to
one-third of the way to the next galaxy.
We could do that.
All right?
So we would have another Hubble constant,
sorry,
another scale factor,
which was bigger or smaller,
it doesn't matter,
than our original Hubble,
our original scale factor,
but the ratio of A dot
to A would be the same.
For example,
supposing I defined another scale factor,
let's call it B.
B is three times A.
Just another definition for the scale factor
so that it's three times bigger
than the original definition of it.
All right?
What about B dot over B?
You might get worried.
You might think you get a different answer
for the Hubble constant,
but you don't.
You get three A dot,
over three A.
The threes cancel.
So what matters,
really,
is not the scale factor itself,
but how it's changing.
That's the important thing.
How it changes,
not its overall magnitude.
But we'll come back to that.
It's really a question of units.
The scale factor would be different,
numerically,
if we measured in meters,
or if we measured in kilometers,
and so forth.
And it would be different
if we chose a different time
at which we...
No,
it wouldn't be different.
what I said is right.
Okay,
let's talk about geometry a little bit,
the geometry of spacetime.
But first,
the geometry of space.
The geometry of space and spacetime
is determined by a metric.
The metric in exactly the same sense
as we talked about last quarter.
I'll try to be self-contained
for those who weren't here last quarter.
Let's start with a very simple geometry.
Again,
a one-dimensional geometry.
But for fun,
let's change it a little bit.
Not the infinite straight line,
but let's take...
Oh,
let's first consider
the infinite straight line.
Yeah.
We have our coordinate x,
and we have that the distance
between any two points
is delta x times a.
Let's think of that in terms of a metric.
Remember what a metric is.
A metric is an expression
for the distance between
two very close points.
When the points are close,
we can replace this delta x
by the symbol dx.
Same thing,
except when
small magnitudes are small,
we replace them by calculus notation.
A times dx.
That's the distance between
two neighboring points.
And what's the square of the distance
between two neighboring points?
Let's call it ds squared.
That's equal to a squared
times dx squared.
Well,
that tells us something
about the metric.
The metric is just the definition
of the metric.
The definition of the metric
of a one-dimensional space,
this is a very simple case,
the metric is just a squared.
It's the thing that multiplies
dx squared to find
the distance squared.
S here stands for
distance,
of course,
because...
Wait a minute.
S isn't distance.
S is...yes,
s is distance.
Space,
spatial distance.
ds squared is a squared dx squared.
If a is changing with time,
then the metric is changing with time.
But still,
this is just
a one-dimensional space
with a metric,
and that metric
might depend on time.
So you see where we're going.
We're starting to talk about
geometry of spaces.
One-dimensional spaces are too simple
to have an interesting curvature
or anything like that.
The metric of space is just
a coefficient out here.
We could write that as
gxx dx squared.
And what would gxx be?
It would just be a squared.
So eventually,
we're going to want
to connect up the idea
of the expanding universe
with a metric of space-time,
but we'll come to that.
Let's...
Good.
Now,
what about proper time?
Remember what proper time is.
Proper time is a function
of d tau squared.
That is equal to d t squared.
This is the proper time
along a trajectory.
Let's now imagine
that what we're talking about
is space-time.
Let's draw space-time.
Here is space-time,
x and t.
All right.
Our galaxies are not changing with x.
But wait a minute.
They are moving further and further apart,
so how can I possibly decide to draw them
as if they were all parallel like this?
This looks like they're all
at the same distance forever and ever.
That is where the scale,
the time-dependent scale factor comes in.
Remember that the distance
between these neighboring points
is not just delta x.
It's a times delta x.
And that changes with time.
Now,
what is the proper time
along the trajectory,
let's say,
of a particle
between two neighboring points?
The proper time,
what do we call it,
d tau squared?
That's equal to d t squared
minus the square of the square of the square.
That's the spatial distance between them.
What's the spatial distance?
a squared d x squared.
The square of the spatial distance
between these two points
is a squared d x squared.
Not just the x squared,
because x isn't really
spatial distance.
It's just a label
which is labeling these points.
You could have given them
different names,
Fred,
Harry,
Joe,
Nancy,
whatever you like,
but we gave them names
which were x equals 1,
x equals 2,
x equals 3,
x equals 4.
The fact that x doesn't change
for a particular galaxy
is the same fact as your name
doesn't change with time.
That doesn't mean that
the distance between you,
between Fred and Harry,
doesn't change with time.
Fred and Harry are their names.
The distance between them
is governed by both
the difference of x
and the scale factor a.
All right,
so here is
our formula now
for the proper time
along a trajectory.
It's not just d t squared.
Now,
t here is time measured
by clocks moving along here,
ordinary clocks moving
with this galaxy.
If x didn't change,
if we were talking about
observations along a galaxy,
in other words,
moving with a galaxy,
we wouldn't have any dx squared,
and we would just say
the proper time
was the ordinary time.
But if a point is moving
through the galaxies
from one point to another,
then we would say
that the proper time
is d tau squared minus a squared,
dx squared.
All right,
this becomes
the spatial distance,
and a may depend on time.
So another way of thinking
about the scale factor
is that it's the space component
of the metric.
Let's just compare that
with d tau squared.
Well,
I didn't even compare it.
Here's a geometry.
It's a spacetime geometry,
and what is its metric?
Its metric,
again,
is a set of components.
The set of components
represents the coefficients
in this form here.
The dt squared has a one,
and the space minus a squared.
Zero,
zero.
The zeros represent the fact
that in this formula,
there could be terms,
but there aren't,
with dt times dx
and dx times dt.
So there are no off-diagonal terms.
And this is the geometry now.
This is the general relativity
description of this expanding space.
The general relativity description
of the expanding space,
going back to last quarter,
is that a certain component
of the metric,
the space component of the metric,
is changing with time.
That's the way you describe
a geometry which is either
being stretched or contracted.
If the geometry is being stretched,
then this component of the metric
we call as gxx.
gxx is minus a squared.
It is the thing which changes
with time as the universe
changes its size,
or as the universe changes
its scale factor.
Scale factor is the thing
which changes with time.
And the space component
of the metric is the same thing.
The same is true in three dimensions,
or two dimensions,
or however many dimensions,
the only difference being
that the metric would contain
more terms.
Minus a squared dy squared
minus a squared dz squared.
The x squared plus the y squared
plus dz squared,
this is just the Pythagorean theorem again,
but now multiplied by a squared.
So we would have a metric
which would have a one
in the time-time component
and a minus a squared
minus a squared minus a squared,
and zeros everywhere else.
That would be the metric
of a uniform,
not uniformly,
of an expanding space
with a scale factor
that was a function of time.
So another way to say expanding universe
or contracting universe
is that the metric of space
is time dependent.
In other words,
it's a special case
of general relativity metric
of space-time where the components
of the metric change with time.
A growing with time,
expanding,
A shrinking with time,
contracting.
All right,
so that connects then
this idea of the time dependence
of the separation between galaxies
with the basics of Einsteinian
geometry of the universe.
And all three A's in that matrix
are the same function
because of homogeneity and isotropy.
Good.
Let me make a slightly finer distinction.
They're not dependent on position
because of homogeneity.
They're not dependent on direction.
All right,
the fact that they don't depend
on position,
moving around in X
as opposed to T,
they could depend on T,
but they don't depend on X,
that's homogeneity.
The fact that all three are the same,
that's isotropy.
Okay?
That the different,
the three directions
all look the same,
that's what says
that these three are the same.
The fact that everything is the same
from place to place says that A depends,
possibly depends on time,
does depend on time,
but does not depend on position in space.
So it's an extremely simple
metrical geometry
where all of the coefficients
are independent of position in space
and isotropic,
meaning the three are the same,
but time dependent.
Time dependent,
but not space dependent,
and not angle dependent,
or not axis dependent.
All right,
now,
that,
uh,
incidentally,
Yeah?
I think I'm a little confused.
Are we not supposed to think of
dx as a distance?
Yes,
dx is not the distance.
A times dx is the distance.
It's just a label.
It labels the galaxies.
If you like,
here's the way to think about it.
There's a bunch of galaxies out there.
Let's,
let's...
And at some particular time,
it doesn't really matter when,
but at some particular time,
somebody drew a...
coordinate grid through them.
And now the rule is,
the coordinate grid follows the galaxies.
As the galaxies expand,
uh,
there's a galaxy over here,
there's a galaxy over here.
The coordinate mesh follows the galaxies.
All right?
That means the distance between here
is not delta x.
Delta x is always the same
between these two galaxies by definition,
because this coordinate grid,
uh,
follows the galaxies.
Okay?
The distance is a times delta x.
That,
that would be the answer
in meters or kilometers or something.
Which one?
A?
Between two galaxies.
Yeah.
The,
the distance in light years
would be a times delta x.
That's right.
As opposed to delta x.
Delta x is...
Dividing by c squared,
obviously.
Yeah.
I,
I'm going to configure it
for c1.
Well,
you could,
you could put the units
of distance into dx.
So...
You could,
you could put the units
of distance into x,
but I choose not to.
I put each of the,
the units of distance into a.
Yeah.
That's,
that's arbitrary.
That's an arbitrary decision
on my part,
whether I want to put the units
of distance into x or into a,
the product of a times x
of units of units.
So should we think of it
as a dx squared?
Yeah.
Is that the answer?
A dx squared.
That's the same as a squared
and a x squared.
Yeah.
Right.
The metric coefficient for time
is equal to 1.
Is that just by convention also?
Uh,
that is a convention.
Not a,
there's no,
there's no physics in that.
Um,
supposing I changed it.
Let's change it.
Now,
what is not a convention
is that the coefficient
doesn't depend on position,
but it could depend on time.
So let's suppose that it was
t squared dt squared,
just for fun,
okay?
Just for fun,
let's suppose
that we had t squared dt squared.
This can be written another way.
t dt squared,
right?
I'm going to put a 4 here
just because you'll see why
in a moment.
That's twice t dt squared.
What's twice t dt?
It's also the same as
dt squared squared.
The differential change in t squared
is dt squared.
In other words,
whatever is here,
it can be written,
I've got to say this right,
you can always change variables.
Given a thing like this,
you can always change variables
to a new definition of time
where this becomes just dt squared.
If it's not dt squared,
you can find a new change of variables,
of time variable,
where it becomes dt squared.
Yeah?
I think there's another possible question
about whether there should be
c squared dt squared.
Oh,
yeah.
You're using c.
Well,
I would put the c squared over here
or put it over there.
Yeah.
But you can also absorb it
into the scale factor.
You can absorb it into the scale factor
if you like.
But my rules are going to be c equals 1.
One light year per year.
Okay?
That's the speed of light.
One unit in light years per year.
Light years per year is not such a bad unit
for astronomy.
If you put this into Einstein's general theory,
field equations,
what do you get for the energy
momentum vector?
Well,
so far...
Be careful.
All right.
A couple of corrections.
Energy momentum tensor.
Yeah,
no,
that's a good question.
Uh...
And this is something we're going to spend
a lot of time with,
so let's not do it now.
That's right.
Right.
This is a metric.
You could say you can put it
into Einstein's equations.
Remember that Einstein's equations
have on the left-hand side
something that involves
just the metric
and on the right-hand side
has the energy momentum density
or the mass density
or whatever energy momentum mass,
all the same stuff,
on the right-hand side,
energy and momentum.
So if we put in this geometry,
we could calculate what kind of
energy momentum distribution
we would have to have
in order that it solves
Einstein's equations.
So we're going to come to that.
That's a very important part
of the whole thing.
But for the moment,
for now,
we're just doing geometry
and not dynamics.
Dynamics is what determines
how the metric changes with time.
Geometry is just the abstract
description of a space
or space-time.
Okay,
so an expanding universe
is one where the space components
of the metric change with time
and given the homogeneity
and isotropy of the universe,
A is not a function of position
and it doesn't depend on which direction
we're talking about.
That's basic rules of cosmology.
And they're not absolute rules
in the sense that one could discover,
it's inconceivable that one will discover
that the universe is not isotropic.
In fact,
it's not exactly isotropic.
It's certainly not exactly isotropic
in different directions.
You actually do see slight differences.
It's certainly not homogeneous.
It's not the same here as it is
a light year away from here.
So it's certainly not exactly homogeneous.
It's not exactly isotropic.
And we could discover in principle
that the universe is fairly far
from isotropic and homogeneous.
Thus far,
we've made no such discovery
and I think it's unlikely that we will
because I think we've seen about as much
of the universe as we're ever going to see.
The universe is bigger than the portion
we can see.
And it's bigger than the portion
we can ever see.
So we don't know that on distant scales
bigger than we can see,
we obviously don't know very much.
We don't know if the universe is homogeneous,
isotropic on those very large scales.
But it has turned out that over the size
and scales of the universe
that we can measure astronomically
or by whatever means,
the universe is isotropic and homogeneous
apart from local variations on small scales.
You know,
it's kind of like a farmer's field.
If the farmer has planted his,
you know,
his corn well and accurately,
then on a scale of 100 feet,
it looks pretty homogeneous,
equally spaced rows and so forth.
On the scale of two inches,
it's very non-homogeneous.
And on a big enough scale,
namely a scale bigger than the whole farm
or the whole field,
it's again not homogeneous.
What we know about the
universe is that on a scale,
on scales between distances between galaxies,
100 galaxies apart or so forth,
that out to scales as far as we can see,
the universe is homogeneous.
We don't know whether it's homogeneous
on bigger scales,
and we probably will never directly
be able to find out.
Okay,
let's come now to closed geometries.
You said you never really
directly find out.
Does that imply you think there might be
an indirect way to find out?
Well,
perhaps.
I think most thinking these days
is that it's not homogeneous
on big enough scales.
But that's certainly something we'll talk about
before we're finished.
My bet very strongly is the universe
is not homogeneous on large scales.
But I will never win my bet.
I will also never lose my bet.
But then you could write a book.
I can only write a
book if I win my bet.
Or lose my bet.
I mean,
you know,
I'd be willing to write a book
if I'm losing a bet.
That book won't be written because
for basic fundamental reasons,
we won't be able to see much further
than we can see now.
That's called the existence of a horizon.
It's a problem.
Couldn't you derive the idea from gravity
to look at masses beyond what you can see?
No way to tell what's beyond what you can see.
So even the gravitational force
would be limited by T.
No.
If we're sitting here in this room,
we are in the field of the sun,
and we're circulating around the sun.
But there's no easy way,
there's no way for us in this room,
on this earth,
without being able to see out beyond the room,
to tell that the sun is there.
Now,
we can measure tiny,
tiny tidal forces.
But the tidal forces in this room,
I don't feel stretched.
Do you feel stretched?
I'm not talking about the tidal forces
due to the earth.
There's certainly tidal forces due to the earth.
I feel,
well,
I actually can't feel those either.
If I jump off a springboard,
a diving board or something,
while I'm in free fall,
I don't feel squeezed and pulled,
and I can't tell that the earth is there.
If I close my eyes,
I could be in free fall
a zillion miles from the earth.
So the answer is that you can't tell
that there's a large mass out there,
except by its tidal forces.
It only has tidal forces
if it's close enough to you,
and you are big enough to feel the variations
of the gravitational field from place to place.
So if there's a large lump of mass,
very,
very far out there,
we're just freely falling in the presence of it,
and we don't feel it,
except,
I say,
through tidal forces.
And there are possible tidal forces
which are too small to feel
if things are far enough away.
Right,
so the horizon,
which we haven't even begun to discuss yet,
is an ultimate barrier to...
And the frightening thing,
frightening,
I don't know if it's frightening,
frustrating,
frightening,
fascinating thing
is we know with virtual certainty
that the universe is at least
a thousand times bigger in volume
than the horizon,
than we can ever,
ever,
in principle,
ever see.
So we know the stuff out there
that we will never be able to detect,
and we can't tell what it is,
we can't tell if it's similar to us,
we can't tell...
Why do you know that?
That's why you took this course,
to find out.
Microwave anisotropy,
measurement of the curvature,
but if I don't answer that,
remind me to answer it,
but not now.
Okay,
let's talk about the idea
of a closed universe.
Now,
a closed universe,
well,
it's best described by example.
The infinite line is an open universe,
closed and bounded.
I'm not sure...
Closed and bounded.
The infinite line is an open universe,
the infinite line is certainly not bounded.
A line segment
like that
is bounded.
Only has a certain size.
Bounded means it has boundaries.
It has...
it comes to an end...
Well,
that's not what bounded means,
excuse me.
It doesn't mean that it has boundaries.
It just means,
in some sense,
it's a finite extent.
Now,
the universe is not,
as far as we know,
anything like this line.
It doesn't have to be a line.
We could be talking about a square
or a cube.
A cube with walls.
The universe could all be inside
a cube with walls.
What does this violate?
It violates homogeneity.
Every place is not the same as...
And isotropy,
for the case of a cube.
Yeah,
and isotropy.
Somebody standing right at the center
sees something quite different
than somebody standing up here
near the corner.
Number one.
Number two,
even at the center here,
even if you are at the center,
you look in different directions,
you see different things.
In one direction,
you see a corner.
In another direction,
you see
a smooth face.
By see,
I mean detect
by whatever means you can detect
the shape of the universe.
So,
a bounded universe
seems like it's out of bounds
in the sense that if the universe
is truly isotropic and homogeneous,
then,
let's concentrate on homogeneous,
then it can't be a cube with walls.
Good.
Okay,
so a sphere is a very interesting case.
Here's a sphere.
The circle is good enough.
I mean,
the interior of the circle.
Here,
this region here.
Somebody at the center
looks out in different directions
and sees the same thing in every direction.
So,
from his perspective
or her perspective over here,
the universe appears isotropic.
All right?
But it's certainly not homogeneous.
Somebody over here
does not see the same thing as somebody over here.
This person over here
sees a wall close to him on the right
or upper right here
and far from him in the other direction.
In fact,
this observer over here
on this galaxy
does not see an isotropic universe.
Doesn't see an isotropic universe
because this direction is different
than that direction.
It's neither...
It happens to be isotropic
for one special person,
the person at the center.
But for everybody else,
it looks non-isotropic
and it's certainly not homogeneous
because the properties over here
are different than the properties over here.
All right,
so that boundary
is a...
We don't know,
as I said,
that the universe is truly on very,
very large scales
isotropic and homogeneous.
But let's take it as a principle.
In fact,
it is called
the cosmological principle
that the universe is isotropic and homogeneous.
Now,
I remember as a young...
as a young physicist
being absolutely convinced
that it must be true
because it's a principle.
And then when you ask,
where does this principle come from?
Well,
we assume it's true.
So it is the cosmological principle,
but it could...
Any day of the week,
we could make some radical discovery
that it is not true.
I don't think it's going to happen
for reasons that you'll understand later.
Yeah?
Does isotropy everywhere
imply homogeneity?
Yes.
That's a good point.
Isotropy everywhere implies homogeneity.
In other words,
isotropy is homogeneous.
Yeah.
If the universe is not homogeneous,
then somebody will see it being homogeneous.
An isotropic.
But if it's homogeneous,
it doesn't mean it's an isotropic.
No,
no.
That's right.
For example,
here is a universe.
This is a universe of arrows.
It's a universe made of arrows,
and they're all pointing
in the same direction.
They densely fill space,
let's say.
That's very homogeneous.
This goes on and on and on.
It's homogeneous in that
it's every place the same,
but it's not isotropic.
It has a direction associated with it.
Right.
And isotropy doesn't imply homogeneity.
This fellow at the center here
sees isotropy
when he looks out,
but this is not homogeneous.
But if everybody
sees isotropy,
if everybody sees things
being the same in every direction,
that happens,
yes,
to imply homogeneity.
So they're not quite independent.
They're two different concepts.
They're related,
though,
in a particular way.
Yeah.
So if you're on the surface
of the sphere...
Ah.
The surface of the sphere.
That's another thing.
On a very bald sphere,
bald meaning featureless,
every place is a sphere.
Every direction is the same
as every other place.
Every direction that you look in
is the same as every other direction
that you look in
on the surface of a sphere.
And it's bounded.
Remember,
bounded does not mean
that it has a boundary.
Now,
we're talking about
little creatures.
Let's imagine
little two-dimensional creatures,
flatland creatures,
except instead of living on a plane,
they live on the surface
of a perfect sphere.
And they can't look away
into the sphere.
And the reason is
because light only travels
on the sphere itself,
on the surface of the sphere,
in this theory,
or in this world.
If light only travels
on the surface of the sphere,
all they can do is look around
within the surface of the sphere,
look that way,
that way,
and on the surface of the sphere,
all directions are the same
and all places are the same.
So that's basically the key
to combining isotropy,
homogeneity,
and boundedness.
Again,
boundedness
does not mean a boundary.
These creatures do not fall off
the edge of the earth
when they get to a certain point.
They go around.
So boundedness does not mean boundary.
It means boundedness.
Finiteness in some sense,
right.
Okay.
All right,
the simplest example
would be life on a plane.
Life on a closed curve.
For example,
life on a circle.
Okay.
A circle has a metric.
Let's talk about a life on a circle.
A nice parameter,
a nice parameter
which could be a coordinate.
Again,
there might be galaxies
sprinkled around on this circle.
Every point on the circle
is the same as every other point.
Not quite true,
of course.
The points between the galaxies
are different than the points
on the galaxies.
But on scales bigger than
the size of a galaxy,
every point is the same as every...
Incidentally,
what does isotropy
mean in one dimension?
Isotropy is clear in two dimensions.
You look in different directions.
What...
Left and right.
Left and right being the same.
That's right.
So here,
for example,
is a one-dimensional world
which is homogeneous,
but not isotropic.
It consists of little arrows
pointing in one direction
all along it.
Left is different than right.
Left is different than right,
but every place is the same
as every other place.
So in a one-dimensional world,
you can also have an isotropy,
non-isotropy.
What it means is simply
left and right.
Left and right along the line
are different.
Okay.
So if I just have a population
of galaxies like this,
on the average,
left and right are the same.
Every point is the same
as every other point.
And I would say this was homogeneous,
isotropic,
and bounded.
Okay.
Let's talk about the metric.
Let's talk about its geometry.
How do we...
What might we characterize
the position by?
Well,
we could use x,
but x is an inconvenient variable
on a circle.
A convenient variable on a circle
is angle.
So we could pick one galaxy
and call it theta equals zero.
Theta is my notation for angle,
or at least one possible notation
for angle.
And we could characterize
every other galaxy,
this is theta equals zero,
by some theta.
And what's this galaxy over here?
Well,
we could call it minus,
a negative angle,
or we could call it 364 degrees.
It's almost all the ways around.
So...
What did I say?
Did I say 364?
Oh,
that's the number of days
in a year.
Gee,
365...
I'm sorry.
Sorry,
I got the number of days
in a year confused
with the number of degrees
on a circle.
Wow.
Okay,
right.
359 degrees.
Not quite all the ways around.
Not quite 360 degrees.
Okay.
But we could use an angle
to characterize the position.
Again,
let's suppose for the moment
that the radius of this circle,
or the circumference of it,
the little bugs who live in this world,
have no sense of radius,
because they have no sense
of where the center of it is.
It's not in their world.
But they do have a sense
of circumference.
They can measure the circumference
by marching along it
till they come back
to the same place.
They can measure the circumference.
The circumference means something.
And of course,
they could call the circumference
2 pi times something
if they wanted.
And that's something
they might call the radius,
but they would have
no particular reason to,
but they could.
So they have a sense
of circumference.
And let's now talk about
the distance between,
the distance around the circle,
the size of the circle.
We can call,
let's call,
let's see,
I don't know,
let's call the total distance
around the circle,
do I want to call it a
or do I want to call it
2 pi times a?
I think I'll just call it a.
Scale factor.
Scale factor is the total distance
around.
Now supposing we have,
let's,
yeah.
Why am I calling that scale factor?
We'll see in a moment.
But let's take the distance
between two points,
theta equals 0
and theta equals theta,
just theta.
What's the distance
between those two points?
a times theta.
Let's define it to be
a times delta theta.
Our a is not,
let's see,
we've got to do this right.
Let's get the numbers
in there correctly.
We're going to measure angles
in radians.
All right,
so the total distance
around in radians is 2 pi.
Total distance around is 2 pi.
So this point is 0,
and if I go all the ways around
and I come to the point
just below it,
that's 2 pi radians around.
Okay,
the total distance around
is 2 pi,
let's call it 2 pi times a.
I'm going to call it 2 pi times a.
Where a would be the radius
if I decided to plot it as a circle.
If I decided to plot it,
now remember,
these people who live on here
can't tell whether it's a circle
or whether it's a curve like that.
They have no way of telling
because they can't see into the interior.
All they know is the distance around.
But let's pretend
that we drew it as a circle.
Then the total distance around it,
I would call 2 pi times a.
But what's the distance
between two neighboring points?
Let's suppose the points were separated
by a distance delta theta.
Then the distance between them
would be a times delta theta.
The radius of the sphere,
the radius of the circle
times the change in angle.
The distance between two points
on a circle,
a circle of radius a,
is a times the angular distance.
Well,
this is very much like
a times delta x.
It's just I've used theta,
and theta happens to have the property
that when you go around the circle,
it comes back to itself,
that you come back to yourself.
But otherwise,
this is very much like
a times delta x.
In fact,
we have a metric.
We can say the distance
between two points squared,
between two neighboring points squared,
is a squared d theta squared.
So in fact,
we have a metric on a circle,
very,
very similar to the case
of the infinite straight line,
except now the space is bounded.
It's bounded because when theta comes
all the ways around by two pi,
you come back to the same place.
This is a closed and bounded universe,
and here is its metric.
Now,
this is not a space-time metric.
This is just a space metric.
So you could imagine the creatures
who live on this thing measure
this distance around here,
and then they know what a is.
They know what a is.
But you can also imagine a changing with time.
Again,
a changing with time
would correspond to the radius
of this circle changing with time.
In that case,
we would write ds squared,
distance between two points,
is a of t squared times d theta squared.
And we might even write a space-time metric.
We might write d tau squared,
the space-time metric,
is d theta squared.
d t squared minus a squared,
a of t squared,
d theta squared.
That should be a squared and t squared
in the line up from the second line up.
No,
not here.
One up,
one up.
One up off that,
a squared.
a of t squared.
Yeah.
No,
it's a squared.
d theta squared.
Good.
Yeah.
Right.
All right.
What does this geometry look like?
Let's try to think about it as a space-time.
As a space-time.
We'll start.
The vertical axis is going to be time.
Let's start at one instant
when a has some particular value.
Here's a.
Let's say a equals one or seven or something else.
So it looks like a circle.
That's a circle.
Let's start at one particular time.
Now,
the vertical axis is the time axis.
As time goes on,
a changes.
That means,
let's say it gets bigger.
That means that the space-time geometry
grows with time.
Let's suppose at some time it stopped growing
and turned around and shrunk.
Started to shrink.
Turn it around.
And start to shrink.
Maybe it does something crazy.
Oscillates.
Starts to grow again.
The surface,
the space-time looks like a surface.
And it looks like a surface of a,
it looks like a vase or a vase,
whatever you call it.
In fact,
we might even imagine
a space-time which starts,
what would the scale factor be at this point?
If the universe started infinitely shrunken.
Here it is.
It starts infinitely shrunken
like a circle of infinitely small size.
And it starts to expand.
Expands out to some maximum size.
I'm not taking this as seriously
that it expands out to maximum size.
Expands out,
starts to shrink again,
starts to grow again,
does whatever it does.
What would be the scale factor at this point?
It would be A equals zero at that point.
So in this closed and bounded universe,
A equals zero corresponds to the thing
shrunk to zero size.
Right?
And then it starts to grow.
It grows from zero and very quickly begins to grow.
It becomes something not zero.
And then changes its size,
maybe in and out and in and out,
whatever it does.
Whatever it does.
Okay,
so that's a geometry.
It's quite clear that this geometry is curved.
It's quite curved.
It's curved in the sense of Einstein.
That's a closed and bounded,
this is the simplest example
of a closed and bounded universe,
which also happens to be time dependent.
In this universe,
Hubble's law is still correct.
For exactly the same reasons as before,
the distance between two points
again involves A times delta theta.
Distance is A delta theta.
The velocity is A dot.
Times delta theta.
And that's the same as A dot over A
times A delta theta,
which is Hubble constant A dot over A
times distance.
So Hubble's law is still true.
The velocity between these points
is proportional to the distance between them.
You get into a little bit of confusion
when the distance is so large
that it comes around the other side.
Let's forget that for a moment.
But an astronomer over here,
looking not too far away,
would see Hubble's law.
And that's the idea of a closed and bounded universe.
Notice that the closed and bounded universe
is not an explosion from a point
in three-dimensional space
where stuff gets ejected out.
It's not like the explosion of a hydrogen bomb
where something is concentrated
in space and then goes flying out into space.
It's the same everywheres.
Everywheres it's the same.
And yet if we imagine galaxies,
let's imagine galaxies or particles or whatever.
Here they are.
They're spread out on here.
They separate because the distance
between them gets larger.
They start to come together again.
They start to...
What happens to them
when we look way back at very early times?
They're very close to each other now.
Let's say there are 360 galaxies.
Those 360 galaxies are well spread out here,
but they're very,
very close together here.
Here they're even closer together.
If they get too close together,
they're not separate galaxies anymore.
Get them even closer,
they're not even separate atoms anymore.
But notice there's no special point in space.
Space now does not mean this three-dimensional room.
It means this one-dimensional closed and bounded universe
that little bugs live on.
No special place.
No sense of being ejected out of some particular place
like the bomb explosion,
but instead just a uniform rapid expansion
taking place everywheres at the same time,
satisfying the Hubble law.
But things get pretty crowded down here.
Infinitely crowded if the universe began as a point.
So when somebody comes and asks you,
well,
where did the Big Bang take place?
Where did this Big Bang take place?
Where were all these things ejected out of?
The answer is everywhere.
Okay?
So,
question.
Yeah?
You said the space-time is curved.
Is it curved if that was a cylinder?
Say it again?
You said the space-time is curved.
Would it be curved if that were a cylinder?
No.
If it were a cylinder,
it would not be curved.
If it was a cylinder,
in other words,
if A were constant with time,
that would be like this.
That would be this world.
What are the high-potentials?
Cone.
Oh,
good.
Cone isn't even in...
Yes,
good.
Good.
Cone.
All right.
First of all,
cylinder.
A cylinder is the case where
A doesn't depend on time at all.
Right?
Good.
That's just a constant A up and down.
That is not curved.
That's not curved.
That's obviously not curved.
Well,
if space is curved,
then space-time is curved.
No,
no.
The cylinder,
the space-time is not curved.
It looks like it's curved because I
tried to draw it in three dimensions,
but it's not curved.
Remember why.
You could take a scissors and cut it open.
Take a scissors,
cut it open.
Without stretching it,
without stretching it,
you could lay it out on the plane.
And it would be...
You don't have to stretch it
to lay it out on the plane.
Okay,
so that's curved.
That's not curved.
If you laid it out on the plane...
So there it is.
I've cut it open,
laid it out on the plane.
Just mathematically cut it open in my imagination.
Then the cylinder is in here,
but this point and that point are the same point
in the sense that when I cut it here,
this point,
which half of which went this way
and half of which went that way,
become these two points,
which are really the same point.
So no,
the cylinder is flat.
Or equivalently,
in this particular case,
for a one-dimensional universe,
not the same,
the three-dimensional is different,
but for a one-dimensional universe,
the time-independent universe is flat.
Okay,
flat in the space-time sense.
Now what about the cone?
First of all,
what does the cone correspond to?
It corresponds to...
There's the cone,
the space-time cone.
How does the scale factor grow with time
in the space-time cone?
Linear.
The size of the cone is linear in the time.
You double the time,
that means double the distance along here.
You double the size of the cone.
So that means A is proportional to time.
Again,
a quarter,
a fifth,
a tenth,
whatever.
The scale factor is proportional to time.
Is this or is this not flat as a space-time?
It's not flat at the bottom.
It's not flat at the bottom,
that's for sure.
It's got a conical singularity there.
But cones,
if you slice them and open them up,
are flat.
So a cone is flat.
You make a cone out of
a flat sheet of paper by...
I mean,
it's the same deal as we studied last time.
Just by sewing the edges together,
you make a cone,
but the only place that the cone is curved
is right at the tip of the cone here.
That's the only place where there's any real curvature.
So,
yeah,
this is also flat except for the tip.
The tip is the origin of time here,
the Big Bang or whatever.
We haven't gotten to Big Bangs yet.
All right,
so...
I think it's time to quit now.
Next time,
we will discuss
not the circular universe,
but the spherical universe,
or the universe which is a three-dimensional sphere,
and the geometry of it,
and then we'll go on to discuss
what is the thing which determines
how the universe grows,
what is the dynamics
which causes it to grow or shrink
or whatever it does.
And that will bring us to
the end of next week.
The preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.