This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Okay,
let's go back to where we were the last time.
We were talking about the metric of space.
Today what we're going to do
is a little bit of geometry,
and then we're going to get
really into the dynamics of cosmology.
The dynamics actually means how does the scale factor,
we discussed the scale factor last time,
how does it change with time?
How does the universe grow
or shrink or whatever it does?
How does that take place with time?
In other words,
what's the evolution equations which
govern how the universe expands
and if it eventually contracts,
how it contracts?
Those equations are known as the F-eq.
F-r-w,
Friedman-Robertson-Walker equations.
Other people,
they're really the Friedman equation.
And we're going to study them tonight.
But we're not going to
derive them tonight from general relativity.
We're going to derive them from Newton's equations.
Newton's equations are enough to get us started.
And then later we'll see how
it fits together with the equation.
So let's begin with the idea of flat space.
Geometry,
well first of all,
we're always going to assume,
unless I state otherwise,
that the universe is homogeneous and isotropic.
If it's homogeneous and isotropic,
and it changes with time,
then Hubble's law will always be true.
Hubble's law,
that velocity is proportional to distance,
will always be true
whenever the universe is homogeneous and isotropic.
Does that mean linearly proportional?
Yes.
Distance,
now that's a statement at a fixed time.
The constant of proportionality,
the so-called Hubble constant,
depends on time in general.
Only for very,
very special situations is
the constant proportionality constant.
Generally it's not.
It's constant with respect to space.
It doesn't vary from point to point.
That's homogeneity.
If you found different
regions of space expanding differently,
you would say that space is not homogeneous.
So when one says the Hubble constant,
I may sometimes lapse into calling it the Hubble constant.
Keep in mind,
it is constant with respect to position in space,
but not constant with respect to position in time.
All right,
let's talk about the metric of space-time,
given that space is flat.
Can space,
three-dimensional space,
be flat and space-time itself be curved?
The answer is yes.
If you have a metric which is time-dependent,
which describes flat spatial
slices embedded in four-dimensional space-time,
where the space itself may be expanding or contracting,
in other words,
the space may be thought of
as an infinite flat rubber sheet,
but the giants far away
who are holding this rubber sheet
are pulling on it in such
a way as to expand it,
contract it,
make it time-dependent,
then the space-time itself is curved,
but we'll come back to the curvature of space-time.
Today I want to think about space itself.
Is there any issue about the fact
that the measuring rods are expanding too?
No,
the measuring rods are not expanding,
but the coordinates,
the coordinates are expanding.
So objects are not,
the space in between the molecules or whatever
is not expanding enough to make the thing expand?
Right.
The,
uh...
Forces which hold meter sticks together
are far stronger than the forces which are,
the forces due to expansion,
and so the meter stick is
being held together in a way that,
that is not expanding with the background space.
But what is happening is disconnected things,
like galaxies which are far enough apart
that they don't feel strong gravitational fields
between one another,
they will be separating.
All right?
So...
Objects which are large enough and diffuse enough
that they don't feel any forces binding them together,
those will expand with the expansion.
But things like meter sticks which are
held together by strong electric and magnetic
and,
uh,
electrical forces and other kinds of forces,
those won't expand with the
ambient expansion of the universe.
All right.
I have a question.
You can't model it,
though,
as a force between points,
is that correct?
Because otherwise it'd be an acceleration.
You can,
you can think of the expansion of the universe
as a small force between points,
uh,
let's say between atoms,
okay?
Yes.
But a small force,
imagine a small additional force,
imagine a meter stick.
And now let's imagine a very small,
very,
very small force of repulsion,
very small,
of repulsion between the atoms.
What will it do?
Uh,
will it tear the meter stick apart?
No.
It might cause the meter
stick to expand a little bit.
Well,
imagine for the moment a uniform,
time independent,
small extra repulsive force between atoms.
All it will do is make the
equilibrium position between the atoms slightly different.
It'll cause,
like having a spring.
Supposing I have a spring connected to the wall,
and it's a real good,
hard,
tight spring,
so that in equilibrium that spring is really small.
And then let's add another small,
small force pulling the spring away from the wall.
Just another small uniform force,
for example.
What will it do?
Will it cause the,
uh,
the,
the particle at the end of the spring
to fly off and go flying off?
No.
What it'll do is it'll just change
the equilibrium position by a little bit.
It'll be so small that you can't just overlap,
experiment,
and...
Well,
it depends,
of course,
on the magnitude of the force
versus the size of the spring constant.
Right.
That's right.
The forces due to expansion are
minute on the scale of ordinary,
uh,
ordinary matter.
Far,
far,
far smaller by many orders of magnitude,
smaller than the interatomic forces.
And so,
that's right,
they could not possibly be measured
in terms of a slight,
um,
modification of the size of a,
uh,
meter stick.
But would that,
wouldn't that force,
if there were,
if there,
if there were no attraction between the things,
wouldn't that produce an accelerated movement apart?
Accelerated would not.
Decelerated,
if there was no forces between the objects,
yes,
they would expand with the expansion of the universe.
Accelerated.
In our universe,
which is an accelerated universe,
yes.
Well,
I,
if there's a force,
it would seem,
unless the force is changing,
it would seem so,
forces produce acceleration,
as I recall.
That's right.
Wait,
wait,
what did you say?
If there is no force,
then there's an acceleration?
I'm just,
I'm just asking if the force,
in fact,
if that's the correct model,
because a force would produce acceleration,
well,
by itself.
It's not just,
it's not like a linear growth.
Well,
comfortably.
Okay.
Right.
Um,
you are right.
Expansion by itself doesn't create a force,
but some kinds of expansion can
be modeled in terms of a force,
namely accelerated expansion.
But we'll come to that.
Let's,
uh,
let's,
so our model of the world,
then,
is there are meter sticks which don't expand.
Measured in meters and measured in meter sticks,
the distance between galaxies does grow.
And we can imagine coordinates
which are embedded and expanding with the galaxies.
We can also imagine coordinates which are not expanding.
They turn out not to be as useful.
So in that framework,
every galaxy,
to the extent that the galaxies don't have extra random,
what's called peculiar motion,
to the extent that the universe uniformly expands,
uh,
each galaxy is located at
a particular value of the coordinates,
and that never changes.
So what changes with time?
What does change with time is the meaning,
the relationship between the coordinates
and actual distances measured in meters.
That relationship is codified by the scale factor.
Okay.
So let's begin,
then.
Let's,
uh,
let's,
we want to get somewheres tonight,
so let's very quickly say,
um,
if I have a flat space,
which I can just draw
as a coordinate grid like that,
then it has a metric,
let's call it the s squared for spatial separation,
for distance,
uh,
for space.
The s squared is some constant,
any constant will do,
let's call it a squared,
times the x squared plus the
y squared plus the z squared,
where a is just a fixed number,
and what does it stand for?
It stands for the distance measured in meters
between neighboring points
separated by a distance delta x equals one.
So if this distance,
not this distance,
but this coordinate separation,
is one unit on each side,
then a represents the distance
between neighboring points on this grid,
and it goes out here in front in the metric.
Now,
if the universe is expanding,
then the distance between neighboring points on the grid
will grow with time,
and that means that
a is now a function of time.
a is a function of time,
and that's the metric of space
that tells you the distance between points
at a fixed instant of time.
What about proper time?
Let's go back over here
to the special theory of relativity.
Uh,
in ordinary special relativity,
the proper time
between two neighboring points of space-time
is given by
dt squared
minus the spatial distance squared,
minus,
we might as well just call it the s squared,
minus the space distance squared.
That's the form that we're going to use.
That the metric of space-time takes
dt squared minus ds squared.
In ordinary special relativity,
we usually write this,
uh,
depending if we,
if we introduce the speed of light into the story,
then this just becomes,
uh,
minus,
dx squared plus dy squared
plus dz squared
divided by c squared.
That's the usual metric
of the special theory of relativity.
And by looking at this,
we would just read off
that ordinary special relativity
corresponds to a metric like thi-
well,
the space components of the metric,
the space components,
ds squared,
look like this.
We would just say that a
was one over the speed of light.
But now,
we're imagining
that a can change with time.
When a changes with time,
we have a time dependence there,
and the metric of space-time
now becomes d tau squared
is equal to dt squared
minus a of t squared
times dx squared
plus dy squared
plus dz squared.
So,
the metric of space-time,
is first of all time independent.
It doesn't depend on x.
The coefficients of the metric
don't depend on position in space.
They only depend on time.
That's the homogeneity
of the universe.
Of course,
in detail,
the universe isn't quite homogeneous,
and so,
really,
this is an idealization.
And we could represent this
by saying the metric tensor,
g mu nu,
has the form
one in the time-time place,
g naught naught,
or g time-time,
is one.
That's the coefficient of one.
No off-diagonal elements.
There are no terms like
dx dy or dx dt.
All the other terms,
all the other off-diagonal terms
are zero.
And the other terms on the diagonal
are all minus a squared,
minus a squared,
minus a squared.
And that would be the metric
tensor,
or the components
of the metric tensor
of this metric.
It's a very,
very simple metric.
It's almost as simple
as flat spacetime.
The only thing is that the relationship
between the spatial measure
and the time
is time-dependent.
That's peculiar.
We can draw,
we can picture
this geometry,
the spacetime geometry,
if we like,
by imagining it.
So we're imagining a time axis.
This is just a cartoon of it.
And now,
at some early time,
the coordinate grid
might correspond
to a fairly small spacing
between neighboring galaxies.
But as time goes on,
the same grid
corresponds to larger
separations between galaxies.
And if the universe continues
to expand,
then the grid
would look like this.
This is just a picture
to focus your eye
on what's happening.
As time goes on,
the sheet of rubber is expanding.
And so the actual distance
measured in meters,
or centimeters,
or whatever it's measured in,
is expanding as time goes on.
But this galaxy,
this is Alice's galaxy over here.
This is Bob's galaxy over here.
Alice and Bob remain separated
by one unit of space.
And so the unit of coordinate
is increasing units of
meters,
but a fixed distance apart
in terms of the coordinates
that we're assigning.
This is the way
we're assigning coordinates,
in such a way that each galaxy
has the same coordinate value
throughout the history
of the evolution.
Okay,
so this picture
goes with this metric.
A is the actual distance
between neighboring points.
And as you can see,
something rather dramatic happens
if A becomes zero.
In particular,
if A in the past
was zero at some time,
that effectively means that
everything is squashed
on top of everything else.
Squashed in the sense that
the number of meters separating
Alice's and Bob's galaxies
go to zero,
which means Alice and Bob
are squashed on top of each other.
That's why one says
that when A goes to zero,
the density becomes infinite.
So infinitely small A
is something to watch out for.
It means everything is crammed
on top of everything else
with infinite density.
On the other hand,
as A gets big,
that means the coordinate mesh
in units of meters gets huge,
and it means everything
is separating and becoming
more and more diffuse.
In that equation,
the small t,
A of t,
whose t is that?
Does that make any difference?
No,
it doesn't make any difference.
You mean by whose t do you...
No,
okay,
so what do we mean
by whose t?
You mean which reference frame,
or do you mean which units
are we using for t?
What if it were a t
riding on a light beam,
and it would never change?
Right,
okay,
good,
good.
This metric,
this form of a metric,
is only true in one frame,
well,
not quite only one frame
of reference.
This form of the metric,
you can ask the question now,
is this form of the metric invariant
under some transformations?
What coordinate frames,
in particular,
there are other coordinates
in which the metric
has exactly the same form.
For example,
if I just rotate
the coordinates,
in other words,
that just corresponds to rotating
the direction of x and y and so forth,
the form of this metric would not change,
and that's because dx squared
plus dy squared plus dz squared
is invariant under rotation.
On the other hand,
if I tried to make
a Lorentz transformation,
the form of this metric would change.
There's only,
at every point in space,
we're talking about a particular velocity,
a reference frame,
with a particular velocity,
and what is that velocity?
Physically,
what does it correspond to?
It corresponds to the velocity
of the local galaxy.
All right,
so galaxies are moving apart,
and we are following those local galaxies
with coordinates embedded in the space,
and the assumption is,
in that coordinate system,
the metric looks like this.
In some other coordinate system
where you might be whizzing by the galaxies,
or you might be rotating,
your frame of reference might be rotating,
it might be accelerating,
it might be doing nothing more complicated
than just moving relative to the galaxies,
the behavior of this metric is different.
So in the coordinate system,
which is moving with the galaxies,
this is the form of the metric.
Yeah,
any other?
Yeah.
If you're moving,
you wouldn't see,
it wouldn't be isotropic.
That's right.
So this is the form
of the metric in the frame,
which,
in which the world is isotropic.
It seems to me you ought to say
it's aging with the galaxies,
too.
What's that?
You ought to say it's aging with the galaxies,
too.
Well,
I don't know the coordinate frames.
I mean,
the time factor has to...
What about this?
Yeah,
that's the one that you have to,
that has to be key to the galaxy's age,
it seems.
Well,
each galaxy carries clocks with it.
Right.
And the clocks measure this dt.
That's right.
This t is the time measured by a clock moving,
the clock made in the standard cosmic clock factory,
where every clock was made out of the same materials,
the same atomic clocks,
for example.
And this time is measuring the time
in the frame of reference moving with the galaxies,
which means it's the time each clock
moving with the galaxies measures.
Yes?
In this reference frame,
the galaxy's motion is dt equals d tau.
Here.
That's right.
That's correct.
In this reference frame,
time along the galaxy lines,
time along the world lines of a galaxy
is the same as proper time
along the world lines of the galaxy.
That's correct.
Correct.
That's why it's what clocks measure.
That's why it is what clocks measure.
Are there transformations that leave
this form of the metric invariant?
You know,
like the Lorentz transformation
leaves the Minkowski metric...
Yeah,
there aren't very many transformations.
The presence of material in the universe,
namely galaxies,
how to say it,
breaks the symmetry
and picks out a particular frame of reference.
Now,
physics in this room
is different because of our own presence,
because of the material in the room.
The equations of particles moving around,
for example,
would be different in frames of reference that were moving
than in frames of reference that were standing still.
For example,
in a frame of reference which is moving rapidly,
an object standing still in that frame of reference,
okay,
so we have a frame of reference
which is moving rapidly relative to you guys,
that's me,
I'm moving rapidly,
and I start juggling.
Do I have to take into account my own motion?
Well,
the answer is,
in practice,
yes.
Why?
Because the atmosphere is not moving with me.
So if I move fast enough,
my juggling devices,
juggling pins,
or whatever they are,
are going to be swept along by the atmosphere.
Empty out the room completely
and make a real true vacuum,
and then,
or cause the air to
move with me for some reason,
but best to just remove the air and everything
and make a true vacuum,
then my rules for juggling
and the way I would juggle would be,
the same in the moving reference frame.
So it's the presence of actual matter
that affects the laws of physics,
not the laws of physics,
but the rules for juggling,
for example.
We have to remove photons too,
right?
Yes,
you have to remove everything,
absolutely.
All right?
So in this case,
it is the galaxies themselves
which are creating the metric.
Remember,
mass creates the metric,
but if the galaxies are in a particular way,
in a particular frame of reference,
if they are homogeneously distributed
and isotropically distributed,
then in that frame of reference,
this must be the form of the metric.
As was mentioned,
in another frame of reference,
for example,
a frame of reference moving along,
the world would not be isotropic.
All right,
now,
what we're going to do is first begin
by studying Newtonian cosmology.
Newtonian cosmology gets us a long way.
It gets us to the basic laws of cosmology,
to the basic laws by which
the scale factor changes with time.
Now,
remember,
you can either think of the scale factor
as something in general relativity,
or you can just think about it
as the distance between the natures.
So,
let's take a Newtonian perspective on it,
completely Newtonian,
and see if we can work out
how a Newtonian homogeneous
and isotropic universe would behave.
All right,
see if we can find out
how the scale factor would behave.
So,
what are we starting with?
We're starting with a world.
I'm just drawing,
that's a little patch of the world.
I can't draw the whole thing on the blackboard.
And the world is,
well,
it's filled up with a gas,
a uniform gas,
and of course that gas is not really
a gas of air molecules.
The gas points are galaxies.
Galaxies,
stars,
and so forth.
And it's pretty uniform.
It's uniform enough on a large scale
that we can pretend that it's just plain uniform.
Now,
let's take,
let's place ourselves,
who are we?
Are we anybody special?
We're going to find out
that the equations,
although we're going to write them
from our own perspective,
from the perspective of somebody
who,
in his own egotistical imagination,
is at the center of the universe,
we're going to find out
that the way the universe looks to us
is exactly the same way
as it would look to us
if we were to look at it
from the perspective of somebody else,
that anybody can call themselves
being at the center.
But let's take the perspective
that we are at the center,
first of all,
and let's write some equations.
Oh,
before I do that,
what do we do here?
I seem to have lost a page of my notes,
and in fact I jumped ahead of myself.
My,
my printer is a very,
it's got a nasty little demon in it
which mixes up pages
and loses them.
Yes,
right.
What,
how do the motion of the galaxies,
what determines it in a Newtonian theory?
Well,
it's gravitation.
The gravitation will tend to pull them together.
That's basically what gravitation does.
It's a pull.
It tends to pull things together.
And before we actually enter into cosmology,
it's worthwhile talking first
about the motion of ordinary particles
in the gravitational field of a heavy mass.
That's the starting point.
That starting point is going to be useful
in studying the rest of the universe.
So let's just step back
and think about a heavy mass point
or a heavy mass here.
Some mass,
let's call it capital M for the moment.
Capital M.
And imagine a second mass,
small m,
which has been ejected by force.
By some initial impulse,
initial impulse,
it has been ejected away
from the gravitating Earth,
for example,
or star,
or whatever it happens to be.
It's been ejected away
by an initial thrust,
but then just simply allowed
to ride the gravitational field
and do whatever Newton says it should do.
Well,
all we need to know,
all we really need in order to,
uh,
go through and work out the cosmology of,
in a few minutes,
is we need to know energy conservation.
That's all that really comes into the equations
for cosmology is energy conservation.
All right?
So what is the energy of this point mass
which has been ejected away
from this heavy static object?
What is the energy of it?
There are two kinds of energies that it has,
kinetic and potential.
Kinetic energy,
what's the kinetic energy of this?
mv squared mass times its velocity squared.
I'm going to assume
that the velocity is radially outward.
This is not correct.
This is two.
This is small m.
This is the kinetic energy of the outgoing mass.
What about its potential energy
in the gravitational field
of the,
uh,
heavy object here?
Anybody remember?
Well,
it's got the product of the masses,
the product of the masses.
It's got Newton's constant
divided by the distance.
I'm going to call the distance between them
just d for distance.
And am I missing anything?
The force contains the distance squared.
So,
the potential energy only contains the distance.
Okay?
Not mg,
not mmg divided by d squared.
That's force.
Energy,
the potential energy,
is just product of m,
g,
and distance.
That's all.
One thing is missing out of this.
Negative sign.
Gravitational energy,
gravitational potential energy,
is negative.
Now,
remember,
forces always push in the direction
to decrease potential energy.
The gravitational field of the Earth
pulls in a direction which decreases
the potential energy of this pen.
All right?
So,
force pushes you in the direction
of decreasing potential energy.
Uh,
did I get this right?
Sorry,
it's plus,
isn't it?
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Uh,
no,
it's minus.
It's minus.
It's minus because it corresponds
to the force being attractive.
Force being attractive makes it minus here.
Uh,
putting this mass very close to the planet
creates a large amount of negative potential energy.
Putting it far away creates a smaller amount
of negative potential energy.
The energy becomes more negative
by pushing towards here.
So,
that's why the,
uh,
potential energy is negative
for gravitation.
Corresponds to an attractive force.
And that's it.
What does energy conservation say?
It says that this energy
doesn't depend on time.
That's all.
There might be many,
many different objects
ejected out
from different positions,
for example.
Each one may have a different energy.
When I say the energy is constant,
I simply mean that the energy
of this particular particle
doesn't change with time.
So,
it's constant.
Let's just call it constant.
All right,
now,
I want to play
with this equation a little bit.
Actually,
not so much.
For the time being,
let's leave it the way it is.
Now we come back,
yeah.
The potential energy increase
with distance rather than decrease?
Yes,
yes,
yes.
Let's see why that's true.
Okay.
First of all,
let's plot 1 over d.
Let's forget the constants here.
Let's forget all the constants here.
All right.
Let's plot the function 1 over d.
What does the function 1 over d look like?
It looks like this,
correct?
It decreases at large D.
You asked the question,
so nod your head and answer
if you understand.
Okay.
Here's d.
1 over d decreases with large D.
But what about minus 1 over d?
Minus 1 over d is exactly the same
except upside down.
That's minus 1 over d.
All right.
Which way does the force push?
It pushes toward decreasing potential energy.
So it pushes,
if you like,
toward smaller distance
or pulls,
equivalently it pulls.
So an attractive force corresponds
to a negative potential energy like this.
All right.
So this is constant,
and this tells you some information.
Let's talk about the different possibilities.
The energy,
let's just call it energy
for the moment.
We'll just call it energy.
The energy has three possibilities.
It could be positive,
it could be negative,
or it could be just plain zero.
Those are the only three possibilities.
Can the energy be positive?
Let's imagine again the projectile being ejected
away from the surface of the earth
or something like that.
Well,
if the projectile,
the potential energy only depends
on the distance from the center of the earth.
d is the distance from the center of the earth.
That's fixed.
That's fixed,
let's say,
at the surface of the earth.
By making the velocity sufficiently large,
this term can easily be made
to overwhelm that term.
All right.
Just by making the velocity sufficiently large.
In that case,
the energy is positive.
It starts out positive,
and it must remain positive.
Okay.
So,
yes,
positive energy is possible.
What about negative energy?
Well,
yes,
you can have negative energy also.
Supposing the starting velocity is very,
very small.
Even better,
let the starting velocity be absolutely zero.
Then this term isn't there,
or it's negligible,
and the potential energy dominates.
In that case,
for sufficiently small velocity,
the energy is negative.
Can the energy be zero?
Sure.
Just make sure that the velocity is just right
to cancel this term at the starting point here.
Just choose the velocity in such a way
that these two are equal,
and then the velocity is zero.
All right.
What is that particular velocity called
that matches these two exactly?
That's the escape velocity.
If the velocity is smaller than the escape velocity,
let's plot.
Let's make a plot.
This is distance.
This is time.
What happens to this projectile?
Well,
if the velocity is less than the escape velocity,
we know very well what happens.
You just fall back down to Earth.
So let's start at time t equals zero
and throw our projectile up in the air
with a small velocity.
What happens?
The distance begins to increase,
and then it gets to the top of its trajectory,
and falls back down.
If we throw it with even less velocity,
it falls down even more quickly
and doesn't rise as high.
All right.
What happens if we throw it with a humongous velocity,
a huge velocity,
huge enough velocity,
and the energy is positive?
In that case,
we know what happens.
We simply get ejected completely
from the gravitational field of the Earth,
and starting with a large enough velocity,
there's some pull inward toward the surface of the Earth,
and so there is some deceleration,
but it's not enough to slow the spaceship
or whatever it is down.
Then the spaceship or projectile escapes.
It escapes and eventually moves off
with a uniform velocity,
which means a constant slope.
Somewhere in between these two behaviors,
is exactly the right starting velocity
to make the energy zero.
If it were any less the velocity,
you'd fall back down.
If it were any more,
you'd surely escape.
That velocity is just the marginal separation point
between escaping and not escaping.
That is the escape velocity.
And your distance just keeps increasing
and increasing and increasing,
but at an ever deeper speed.
It's a decreasing rate.
So that's the escape velocity.
This is E equals zero.
This is E greater than zero.
And these are E less than zero.
That's the basic decomposition
of radial orbits
into bound orbits,
which fall back down,
just at the escape velocity
where distance just gradually increases,
but with a slowing velocity.
The velocity slowing down,
but never enough to make it turn around.
And then positive energy
where the projectile moves off
with a velocity which doesn't get smaller.
The universe behaves the same way,
or the equations of motion of the universe
have the same property.
If the initial starting point
has all of the galaxies moving outward
relative to each other,
according to the Hubble law,
but with a big enough Hubble constant,
in other words,
with a big enough relative velocity,
then it will just shoot out
and the galaxies will all escape
from each other cleanly
and with no,
uh,
no tendency to fall back.
If the initial outward velocity
of recession is too small,
then gravity will beat the outward motion
and they'll all fall back
in a giant crunch.
The Big Bang will be followed
by a big crunch.
There is a point
with the starting values of the velocity,
which is like the escape velocity,
which is just barely enough
for the universe to keep expanding out.
Now,
what I'm talking about now
is Newtonian cosmology.
Newtonian cosmology,
there is a particular starting point
for the velocities
where you will do
exactly the same thing
as this escaping particle.
In fact,
we can use
exactly this expression here,
mv squared over 2
minus mmg over d
equals a constant energy
to figure out exactly what happens
to these galaxies here.
And the trick is Newton's theorem.
Let me remind you
what Newton's theorem says.
Newton's theorem
is a remarkable theorem.
Newton discovered it geometrically.
We discussed it,
I think,
last quarter at length.
I'll just remind you what it says.
It says that if you have
a spherically symmetric distribution of matter,
in other words,
think of yourself at the center,
well,
you don't have to think of it,
if there is a center,
and if about that center
the distribution of mass is isotropic,
forget homogeneous,
if it's isotropic,
the same in every direction,
then the gravitational field,
the gravitational force,
here's our lump of matter,
completely spherically symmetric,
then
the force on a particle out here
is exactly the same
as if all of the mass
were concentrated at a point at the center.
That's the first statement.
All right?
But the statement is a little stronger than that.
Supposing the point in question
was somewheres in the interior
of this ball of material,
the only restriction that we have
is that the ball of material
be spherically symmetric,
then Newton's theorem says the following.
It says that you can draw...
Where are we?
Yeah,
let's draw this carefully.
We have a distribution of matter
which is spherically symmetric.
It doesn't have to be uniform.
It just has to be isotropic
relative to the center,
and we place a particle over here.
What is the gravitational force
on that particle?
And the answer is,
you draw a sphere
at the same radius as the particle,
and you take all of the mass
inside that sphere,
and you pretend that it was localized
right at the center of the sphere.
What about the material
outside that sphere?
Newton's theorem says that it does not contribute
to the force on a particle.
In other words,
all the masses at a distance
larger than the particle
cancel out when they contribute
to the force of that particle.
Only the masses on the interior,
closer than the particle,
contribute to the force.
It's a remarkable theorem,
and it's a very good theorem.
In particular,
it says something
that at first sight
does not seem terribly intuitive.
Suppose you had a perfect shell,
a perfect spherical shell of matter.
Not a ball.
A ball means that it's filled up solidly,
but a shell of material,
a thin shell of material.
And you put a particle at the center.
What is the gravitational force?
The gravitational force on it.
It's clearly zero,
because it doesn't know which way to get pulled,
so to speak.
Why don't you put it over here?
It's also zero.
The force,
the force do,
you might think that it gets pulled
to the right,
because this mass over here is closer.
Okay?
But,
there's a lot more of the mass far away.
The mass on this side over here,
there's a lot of it.
The mass to the right,
there's only a little bit of it,
and they cancel.
What happens if we look at the,
if we take the particle outside the shell?
What is the force on the particle outside the shell?
Exactly the same
as if the entire shell were concentrated at a point.
That's Newton's theorem.
Uh,
the reference for it is the Principia,
and you don't even need calculus for it.
On the other hand,
not using calculus makes it incredibly difficult.
Okay.
The story is,
I don't know,
I don't know what the actual truth of it is,
but,
that,
that Newton,
of course,
invented the calculus for purposes like this.
Worked these things out using calculus,
but of course he knew that all his,
uh,
compatriots,
all his enemies,
didn't know calculus.
And so in order to convince them
of the truth of his theory,
he worked out everything using only Euclidean geometry.
And that's why the Principia is so hard to read.
But yes,
okay,
this is a theorem.
All
right,
so let's pick a galaxy or
a mass moving with the galaxies.
Let's pick it along the
x-axis,
although that's not important.
Since everything is isotropic,
it doesn't matter
which axis we pick.
But let's pick our mass along the x-axis,
and it's at coordinate x.
Let's work out Newton's equations.
Yes?
What's the meaning of spherical symmetry in a,
in a,
in
a homogeneous distribution?
Well,
it means anybody who looks around
and sees everything is the same in every direction.
No,
not isotropic,
homogeneous,
I meant.
What's the meaning of homogeneous?
Well,
I'm just saying.
For the moment,
I'm not using homogeneous,
but I will.
Well,
I'm just having trouble visualizing what,
what the shells would be in a homogeneous
universe,
cause it's sort of,
I don't know what to neglect.
Well,
so far I haven't introduced any shells.
into this.
Okay.
Well,
but not yet.
Yeah.
In the example you gave there,
should we be a little surprised that it
seems like as the particle moves across the boundary,
the force is discontinuous?
I don't know if you should be surprised.
It's a true statement.
Of course,
boundaries are not really infinitely thin.
They do really have a distribution.
A shell,
of course,
has some thickness.
And so everything would vary continuously.
But,
you know,
if you had a very,
very thin shell,
yes,
the force would vary discontinuously.
Should you be surprised?
Yeah,
I would say yes,
you should be surprised.
It is a little bit surprising.
Of course,
when you think about it enough,
and you work out the equations,
and you get familiar with it,
it's a little bit surprising.
less surprising and it's incidentally very
special to the 1 over R squared
Newtonian force law.
It would not be true with other force laws.
Other force laws
do not have this property.
This is the 1 over
R squared force law has this
property.
All right,
I'll tell you what the mathematics of it is.
The mathematics
is fairly simple and or a picture of what's happening.
If you imagine,
if you
imagine a mass point is instead of a
mass point imagine that it is a flow of
water which is materializing at this point
it could be coming in from behind
the blackboard a little pipe ending here
and the flow of water flows outward.
Outward in the plane of this plane.
The how does the how does the
velocity of the flow decrease with distance?
Well
it decreases with in two dimensions it's 1
over R and three dimensions it's 1 over
R squared.
So in two and three dimensions in
other words if at some point of the
world a flow of water flowed out
away from some point the velocity field would
be 1 over R squared.
Okay now imagine that
we put one of these little spouts
at each point around the circle continuously so
that around on the circle here the
there was a continuous distribution of flow of
water out of that circle.
All right.
What the water completely fills everything but what is the
velocity of the water in different places?
Well on the outside of the ring
the velocity is flowing outward and
it flows outward with a velocity that's
exactly the same as if the same
flow of water materialized at the center.
But
what about inside this circle?
Can there be any flow of water?
Which direction
would it flow in?
If it flew flew out radially
where would it be coming from?
Supposing the water flowed out here.
How could that be if there
was no source at the center?
How could it possibly be that there would be
water flowing away from the
center if there was no source
of water at the center?
That's essentially so so the answer is.
that in the interior of this shell of
sources of water there would be no flow.
It would stand perfectly still but the
center you move the second you move to
to the other side,
you would see a flow which is exactly
the same as if all the source were
concentrated at the center.
If you think about that for a little while,
you'll get the reason
why the one over r squared
force has this surprising Newtonian property.
But our purpose
tonight is not to derive it.
We discussed it earlier in the class.
I think we even derived
it.
We're going to use it.
We're going to use it to study cosmology.
And to use it to study
cosmology,
we just pick a point away from the center,
the center being arbitrary,
but nevertheless,
pick a center in the frame of reference where
the center is at rest right at the center,
where this blue galaxy here is at rest.
Pick that point,
and we'll apply Newton's equations
to.
And we'll apply Newton's equations to another second point,
which is at coordinate x relative
to,
this is x equals zero over here,
and this is x equals whatever it is over here.
So how
do we find the force on this particle over here?
Well,
what we do is we draw a sphere.
Knowing that everything is isotropic,
we can draw a sphere.
And that sphere is centered at x equals zero.
And using Newton's theorem,
Newton's theorem
tells us that the force in this frame of reference,
at rest with respect to this galaxy,
the force on the other galaxy over here is
exactly the same as if all the mass on the
interior of this red shell were
concentrated right at x equals zero.
And that left this
equals zero and all the other galaxies on
the outside don't exert any force on it.
In other words,
for a galaxy at point x,
it behaves exactly as if the entire mass within it,
within this sphere,
were concentrated at the center and as
if there were no other mass on
the outside.
So let's for the moment call
the mass concentrated within this sphere.
And notice the sphere grows as if x increases.
Of course,
the sphere will grow with x.
The sphere
always surrounds the same number of galaxies.
If the galaxies are separating apart,
the sphere
grows.
That sphere always contains the same number
of galaxies and therefore the same total mass.
So let's call the
mass within that sphere capital M for the moment.
It's the mass within that sphere.
Then the motion
of this point follows exactly the same law.
Where is it?
We erased it off the blackboard.
Let me write it out again.
One half m v squared,
where v is the outward velocity of this sphere,
z squared minus e squared,
one half v squared,
one half v squared minus
e squared m squared,
plus m squared minus m squared,
minus capital M mg,
over the distance,
is equal to something which is fixed with time.
Fixed with time does not change with time.
For
that particular galaxy,
let's just call it the energy.
Or let's just call it a constant.
some confusion later,
not confusion,
but just to save some steps.
Let's multiply this equation
by 2.
And it just becomes mv squared minus 2m
little m gd is equal to twice a constant,
but twice a constant is just another constant.
So the way I've written it here with the 2
here is exactly the same equation that I wrote before.
All we have to do to
implement this equation is find out,
to try to figure out what the
velocity of this particle at point x is.
And here is where the Hubble law comes in.
What
does the Hubble law tell us?
Well,
even before the Hubble law,
yes,
alright.
Let's begin
not with the Hubble law,
but with the actual physical distance.
I suppose we should give these galaxies names,
Bob and Alice.
Bob thinks of himself at rest,
and he sees Alice moving away.
The distance to Alice is equal to x,
but not x.
X has to
be multiplied by something.
A,
the scale factor,
as a function of time.
So,
what is the distance
to Alice?
Well,
the distance to Alice is equal
to the time derivative of d.
Now,
what about
Alice's velocity relative to Bob?
That's velocity.
That's equal to the time derivative of d.
Now,
does x change with time?
No,
x is just the coordinate fixed,
embedded inside Alice,
moves
with Alice.
So x does not change with time,
but a can change with time.
That's equal to
capital & v.
Let's use that in this equation
over here for this particular galaxy.
This
is all we need.
M,
oh,
incidentally,
yes,
let's go one step further before we move to
this board.
Let's go back to this board.
And let's divide by the mass of the projectile
particle.
The mass of the projectile particle is an apple.
If we divide the mass of the part,
then we get either x is equal to x,,
vs.
z is equal to 1,
enough boxed by that and that 갯
particle is also a constant.
That means the constant divided by m here,
m appeared in both
these terms here,
and the right-hand side was just a constant.
A constant meant constant with time.
What is a constant divided by m?
It's also a constant.
So I can just call it constant.
I don't
need to write constant over m.
All I need to remember is
that the left-hand side does not
change with time.
It's equal to something which is constant with time.
When I say constant with
time,
I don't necessarily,
yeah,
constant with time.
Okay,
let's plug in here and see what we get.
The square of the velocity,
that's the first term here,
velocity squared.
Velocity squared,
that's x squared.
That's fixed,
that's constant.
Times the square of the
time derivative of the scale factor.
Remember what we're trying to do.
We're trying to figure out how
the scale factor changes with time.
Well,
a dot is how the scale factor changes with time.
So far,
we don't have an equation for it.
I've just written down a dot.
There's also x squared here,
which depends on which galaxy
we're talking about.
Different galaxies,
different x's.
Okay,
now let's write the
down this term.
Minus twice g.
The distance is x times a.
But what about the mass within here?
The mass in here is not some,
just a number like the mass of the sun.
It depends on how big this
sphere is.
How big?
It depends on how many galaxies are inside it.
It depends on how many galaxies are inside it,
basically.
The number of galaxies inside that sphere
stays fixed with time because the sphere grows
with the galaxies.
It's fixed to pass through Alice here.
As Alice moves away,
the sphere grows.
But the galaxies don't move out of that sphere.
They stay inside that sphere for all time.
And so the mass within
that sphere stays fixed with time.
Okay.
Mm-hmm.
But depending on which sphere we were to take,
this sphere or this sphere,
that mass would
change.
So here's how we figure out the mass.
We say,
supposing,
using the idea that the
universe is homogeneous,
we say there is a well-defined,
that every instant of time,
there is a well-defined mass per unit volume,
a density.
Okay?
A mass per unit volume density.
So in order to find
out the mass in the sphere,
we need to take the density.
Let's call it rho.
Rho is the density,
the number of kilograms per unit cubic meter,
for example.
Rho is density.
Let's write it here.
Rho equals mass density.
And what do we multiply it by in
order to get the mass within the sphere?
Four-thirds pi s squared.
We multiply,
right,
the volume of the sphere.
You jumped ahead of me,
right.
The volume of the sphere.
And the volume of a sphere is four-thirds pi,
hmm?
X cubed.
R,
um,
no,
not,
yeah,
x cubed,
a cubed.
X cubed times a cubed.
D cubed.
D cubed,
if you like.
D cubed.
Right?
D cubed,
which is x cubed,
a cubed.
All right,
so four-thirds,
uh,
yeah.
So let's put it together.
Let's combine it.
It's a mess,
but let's put it together.
Oh,
sorry,
we have the right-hand side.
The right-hand side equals a constant.
Okay.
Any questions?
Say it again?
Rho changes with time.
Rho indeed changes with time,
and we're going to worry about rho changes with time.
Why does rho change with time?
Yeah,
because the galaxies separate,
and so it becomes less dense with time.
But at any given time,
this is,
it's the density that goes here.
Okay,
this term has an x squared in front of it.
Oh,
oh,
one other thing.
Rho may depend on time.
Oh,
sorry.
Rho may depend on time,
but it doesn't depend on position in space.
So it doesn't uh,
what
what's,
what principle is involved there?
Homogeneity.
So it doesn't depend on which x we're talking about,
but it does depend
on time.
All right.
Now.
Let's uh simplify.
x cubed,
a cubed over xa,
that's just x squared,
a squared,
right?
Notice that both of these terms contain x squared.
The other thing,
the other things that it contains
do not depend on where you are,
which galaxy you're talking about.
A is the scale factor.
That's the same everywheres.
G is Newton's constant.
Rho is assumed to be the same everywheres.
Certainly,
4,
3,
and pi are the same everywheres.
The only thing that varies from place to place here,
here,
here is x.
So the left-hand side is proportional to x squared.
That must mean that the right-hand
side must be proportional to x squared.
Now,
wait a minute.
I said it's constant.
How can it depend on x squared?
What did I mean by constant?
I meant that it doesn't change with time.
For each x,
it doesn't depend on time.
But in order for this equation to make sense,
this constant must also be proportional to x squared.
So that means in order
for the equation to make sense,
the energy of,
and remember the right-hand side is related to the energy,
the energy of more distant particles,
must be larger than the energy of the closer ones.
But that makes sense.
Of course it does.
They're moving faster.
So this constant,
what I called constant over here,
is really a constant with respect to time,
times x squared.
Otherwise,
the equations couldn't make sense.
Once we assume that,
once we assume that the equations make sense,
then you can divide away x squared.
And notice what you have,
and this constant now is a constant
both with respect to space and time,
what goes over here.
Okay.
Now we have something interesting.
We have an equation which doesn't depend on which
galaxy we started with and which galaxy we're talking about.
I could have put us at
the center and studied Alice's galaxy.
Or Fred's galaxy.
Or Michelle's galaxy.
Or George's galaxy.
George's galaxy is out there.
Anybody's galaxy.
Anybody's galaxy we like,
we would get exactly the same equation.
It depends on a.
It depends on time.
So it's an equation for
a as a function of time.
But it doesn't depend on which galaxy we started with.
It depends on which galaxy we started with as the center or
which galaxy we studied as the one moving relative to the center.
So we've managed to invoke a set
of assumptions which gives us a simple,
clean equation for the way a varies with time.
Now it depends on this constant on the right-hand side.
It depends on the constant at the right-hand side.
Just in order to put
it in a more standard form.
I'm going to put it
in a more standard form now.
Standard simply means historically standard form.
Standard form involves transposing this piece to the
right and dividing the whole equation by a squared.
So let's do that.
If we divide by a squared,
we have a dot squared over a squared.
Equals.
I'm transposing this to the right.
Equals 8 pi g over 3.
8,
2 times 4,
pi over 3.
8 pi g over 3.
Rho,
the density of mass.
That's all from that term.
That's it,
right?
Plus.
And on the right-hand side.
Plus constant.
I'm now going to call that constant.
Minus k.
Now,
does that mean that the constant is negative?
No.
It could be positive or negative.
That is to say,
minus k could be either positive or negative.
Or zero.
I have not biased it by writing minus k here.
There's nothing special about k being positive or negative.
It's a historical terminology.
k here can be positive,
negative,
or zero.
And divided by a squared.
Where did the a squared come from?
It came from the fact that
I divided the equation by a squared.
These are very famous equations in cosmology.
They're called the FRW equation.
These equations.
This equation is called the FRW.
Friedman,
Roberts,
and Walker.
Friedman is spelled with one e and one i.
F-R-E-I-D-M-A-N.
Alexander Friedman.
Uh.
And who Robertson and Walker are,
I don't know.
They were Johnny-come-latelys in the business.
I don't know how they got into it.
But there was Alexander Friedman shortly,
very shortly after Einstein's.
He derived it from the general theory of relativity.
I don't know why these equations weren't derived by Newton.
Newton wanted the universe to be static
and eternal and stay there forever and ever.
And he made some mistakes
along the way in order to,
he actually didn't make mistakes.
He just thought it should be and knew
there was something wrong with his own equations.
No.
Knew there was something wrong either
with his equations or his assumption.
In any case,
what does this equation tell you?
It tells you that if there's any mass density here,
in general,
unless these two exactly cancel.
But they can't.
They won't cancel in general,
these two.
That A will depend on time.
The left-hand side,
in general,
won't be zero and it'll depend on time.
And that means the universe will either expand
or contract or whatever it's supposed to do.
These are the FRW equations.
Now the problem is,
supposing I sent you home to solve this equation.
The first thing you would tell me,
you would ask me,
I think,
is what is rho?
Can we just put it in the equation?
Can we put a number in for rho?
What's the,
what's the,
anybody have any idea at
all what the density of material,
average material in the universe is today?
I don't.
I just wonder if anybody does.
You told us it was
about one proton per cubic meter.
I think it's more like about 50,
but,
you know,
it's a small number of protons per cubic meter.
It's a very,
very small number,
but that's okay.
A small number is all right.
It's not,
it's not time independent.
It won't stay that way.
As things expand,
the density will decrease.
As the density decreases,
what goes in here will depend on the scale factor.
So there's a hidden dependence,
there's an equation here involving
the time derivative and so forth,
but there's a hidden dependence on the scale factor here that
we have to unravel if we want to solve this equation.
Another thing we have to decide is
what value of k to put in there.
Now remember,
when you went to,
remember now,
k was like the energy of this
particle that was ejected away from you.
It could be positive,
negative,
or zero.
Yeah?
Actually,
m was a function of x only.
m was not,
m?
m was a function of
x only and not of time.
So we could have gotten rid of it by just
saying we can calculate m at any instant of time.
Yeah.
I went through,
you're telling me I went through what
is essentially an extra step of introducing rho.
I did it,
yes,
you're right.
I could have used m divided by volume.
Okay.
I didn't do that because,
because I wanted to put it in a standard,
I wanted you to get familiar
with this particular form of the equation,
which depends on the density.
All right.
The other thing one has
to decide is what about k?
It's a constant,
but it could be positive,
negative,
or zero.
Let me remind you what that means.
Well,
if minus k is positive,
it means it's like the situation where the
particle is receding with greater than the escape velocity.
In that case,
the universe just continues to expand forever and ever.
It doesn't slow down.
There may be some initial deceleration for the same
reason that if you shoot something away from the Earth,
at first it will decelerate because it's being pulled,
but as it gets further and further from the Earth,
the pullback becomes more and more diminished,
and it'll just shoot off with
a more or less uniform velocity.
Okay.
So if k,
if minus k is negative,
and k is positive,
that corresponds to the positive energy situation.
The universe just continues to grow,
and gravity eventually becomes irrelevant,
and everything shoots apart with uniform velocity,
or uniform.
That's number one.
Number two,
we have to do something about
figuring out how to express rho.
But the only other thing I wanted to
point out is that this a dot over a,
well,
it's actually squared over here,
but the last time I told you
another name for a dot over a,
a dot over a was the Hubble constant,
which isn't constant with time.
It was the Hubble constant.
So another way to write this
is that the Hubble constant squared
is equal to eight pi g times the
density of material minus k over a squared.
Is rho proportional to one over r,
one over x cubed here?
One over a cubed.
Yeah.
We'll come to the dot.
How did you get rid
of the x in the equation?
By finding by x.
x squared.
And also the other term,
which I've erased off here,
the constant term,
I said has to be proportional to x squared
if the equations are to make sense.
If the left-hand side is proportional to x squared,
the right-hand side must also.
But you can kind of check it.
You can,
um,
you can check the fact that as you move away,
if the Hubble law is satisfied,
then obviously the further away you are,
the faster you're moving,
and so the energy will depend on where you are,
and it will depend on it in the
right way to make this x squared over here.
So we just got rid
of the x squared by pi.
Does the,
uh,
does the constant have units?
I mean,
we started out with energy,
but we,
we canceled out,
uh,
this with squared and the next.
The constant in this form does not have units.
Okay.
Uh,
again,
let's,
I'm going to assume the speed
of light is equal to one.
What are the units of A?
Meters.
Meters,
or length,
length.
What are the,
what is the,
what is,
um,
oh,
I'm sorry.
Yeah,
no,
that's right,
that's right.
What about the,
the dot?
What are the units of dot?
Length over time.
A dot is length over time.
All right.
Now,
in units in which the speed
of light is equal to one,
length over time is dimensionless.
If we measure space the same way we measure time,
then A dot is dimensionless,
and the left-hand side has
units of one over A squared,
one over length squared.
Here's a one over length squared here,
so that means that K is dimensionless.
K is dimensionless,
has no dimensions.
You can check that this thing
has the same units over here.
But let's talk now about rho.
What do we know about rho?
Well,
let's take,
let's take a cubic cell of space,
and now let's let it be
one unit of coordinate on a side.
A cube of space,
a unit cube,
where
X is equal to one,
Y is equal to one,
and Z is equal to one.
So it's a cube,
it's not,
it's not a cubic meter in size,
it's just a cube in coordinate space.
One unit on a side.
And let's suppose that there's a mass M inside it.
Okay?
So in a cubic coordinate volume,
one coordinate unit on a side,
let's suppose there's a total mass M.
How much mass will be
there later in that same cube?
The same amount,
because the cube corresponds to an expanding cube.
The galaxies expand,
the galaxies don't expand,
but the difference between them expands.
The number of galaxies in there stays the same,
and so that mass is fixed
and stays the same for all time.
What is the density?
The density is the mass divided by the volume.
Okay?
Is the mass in there divided by the volume.
What is the volume?
A cubed.
So that's rho.
Now,
in terms of M,
we of course have to know,
at some point in time,
we have to know what the
mass inside a cubic volume is.
That's a parameter.
There are a number of parameters that go into here,
which are numerical parameters,
which determine the behavior thereafter.
We don't get a completely free lunch here.
Yeah?
According to that equation,
the Hubble constant is a functional rho.
Yeah.
Therefore,
it's not a constant.
With respect.
That's why I keep telling you
the Hubble constant is not a constant.
It's a functional rho,
and rho changes.
Right.
The Hubble constant is not a constant.
It's a functional rho.
ありがとうございました
The final examination is going to consist of one question.
Is the Hubble constant a constant?
That's right.
The left-hand side is not constant,
and the right-hand side is not constant.
All right.
Choices that have to be made.
The amount of mass in a cubic unit volume,
whether k is zero,
positive or negative,
and what its value is.
And that's about it.
That's about the only arbitrary things in this here.
All right.
k equals zero corresponds to the
universe being exactly at the escape velocity.
If things were shot out a little bit slower,
things would crunch a little bit faster,
they would just recede off,
and at k equals zero,
they just move away,
but at an ever-diminishing velocity.
Now,
keep in mind,
this,
at this stage,
is a model,
a Newtonian model of a cosmology.
It doesn't contain yet certain
features that the real thing has.
Is k equals zero?
Then the velocity between two galaxies is approaching zero?
Approaching zero.
Is it approaching zero in such a way so
that the distance between them is bounded or unbounded?
Unbounded.
Same as the particle being ejected from the Earth.
It slowly,
no,
it couldn't possibly come to a rest.
If it actually at some finite time came to rest,
it would fall back in.
So it slows down.
Yeah,
right.
It slows down,
but with the distance ever increasing,
but more and more slowly.
So the velocity goes to zero,
but the distance does not go to a constant.
We can work out how it behaves.
I think the distance grows logarithmically.
The distance grows logarithmically with time.
Oh,
so it's unbounded.
Yeah,
the distance is unbounded.
but the velocity goes to zero.
The velocity is actually bounded to zero,
whereas if the energy is positive,
the velocity is asymptotic to something greater than zero.
Right.
Exactly.
That's correct.
Okay.
Before settling on k,
let's plug into this equation
rho equals m over a cubed,
and m is just a parameter.
It's a parameter that has to be determined by,
by observation,
if you like.
Then this equation becomes m,
and it's not the mass of the sun,
and it's not the mass of the galaxy,
it's just the mass in the cubic region of space,
one unit on a side,
divided by a cubed.
And that's it.
That is the Friedman-Robertson-Walker equation,
the so-called matter-dominated case.
We'll explain what that means later.
Okay.
What about k?
We can make various choices.
The simplest choice is k equals zero.
That's the case where everything
is exactly at the escape velocity,
and it's simpler only in that the mathematics is simpler.
If I said k equals zero,
it's obviously simpler.
There are fewer terms in the equation.
That's all.
The equations are easier to solve.
So I'm going to take you
through the solution of the equation,
which is the equation.
And I'm going to write the equations in the
specially easy case where k is equal to zero.
That's just at the critical velocity.
And we'll see what happens.
Okay.
So let's rewrite it.
a dot over a squared
is equal to 8 pi mg
divided by 3 a squared
excuse me,
a cubed period.
That's it.
When k is equal to zero.
The equations with k are a little harder.
They're harder to solve,
but not that much harder to solve.
Okay.
How am I going to solve them?
I'm not going to spend
a lot of time solving different.
This is a differential equation for a.
a of t.
The a dt is equal to,
no,
it is what it is.
I'm going to solve it by guessing the answer
and then showing you that it solves the equation.
This is one way of solving the equation.
All right.
If you...
This is the way people usually solve equations.
And then they...
All right.
We could try various things.
We could try a is a power law.
We could try an exponential.
We could try all sorts of interesting functions.
A power law is usually the first thing you try.
A power law means that a increases or decreases...
Incidentally,
okay,
now we can see something interesting.
The right-hand side here is never zero,
and it's always positive.
The left-hand side is always obviously positive.
It's the square of something.
But it could become zero.
How could it become zero?
If the universe expanded and then recontracted
at exactly the point where it turns around,
a dot would be zero.
All right.
But the right-hand side is not zero,
never zero.
So that means this universe cannot turn around and contract.
Either it's growing or it's shrinking,
and it stays that way forever.
It's either eternally growing or eternally decreasing.
Eternally shrinking.
Well,
it can't eternally shrink,
because it'll shrink to a point,
but it can eternally grow,
and that means that a dot over a is positive.
It means the universe grows forever.
All right.
Let's try some things.
How about a grows like t?
a is proportional to t.
There's a possible answer.
Well,
it won't work,
but let's jazz it up a little bit.
We could try t squared.
We could try t cubed.
We could try t to the four-ninths.
We could try t to the pi power.
We could try all sorts of things.
Let's just call it t to the power p
and try to figure out what p has to be
to solve the equation.
One plus one.
Hmm?
No.
Mm-mm.
Let's also be a little more general.
How about putting some constant,
unknown constant there,
and see if we can plug this in
and put this formula into the equation
and determine what the two unknown constants are
and check that the equation is solved
by those appropriate constants.
That is the way I am quite certain
this equation was solved the first time.
Just try some simple solution.
This is a very simple thing to start with,
and it is the solution of the equation
with appropriate values of p and c.
So let's try it.
First of all,
what is a dot?
The time derivative of a.
All we have to do is differentiate this.
The c by assumption now is a constant.
It may work out that you
can't solve the equation this way.
Then you'd have to start modifying.
But let's check.
a dot is equal to c
p t to the p minus one,
right?
Everybody agree with that?
Okay.
What about a dot over a?
a dot over a,
let's divide by a.
a is c t to the p.
Well,
first of all,
the c's,
the constant c,
cancels out.
That's nice.
It'll come back.
That cancels out.
What is t to the p
minus one over t to the p?
One over t.
The p is the t to the p is canceled,
and then we end up
with t to the minus one,
which is one over t.
That's a dot over a.
It's always proportional to one
over t with the power law.
The power enters just in the numerator here very simply.
Okay,
let's write down the equation now.
a dot over a squared,
that's p squared over t squared,
right?
p squared over t squared on
the left side of the equation
equals eight pi m g divided by three,
and now c cubed t to the three p.
All right,
I've just cubed a.
a is c cubed times t to the p.
That goes here.
a cubed is c cubed t to the three p.
First question.
Can the left-hand side and the right-hand side
possibly be the same?
How can it be that something
which goes as one over t squared
can also go on the right-hand side
as one over t to the three p?
p is two-thirds.
Two-thirds?
Yeah.
That's the only way.
So,
what's the answer?
the first thing we find out is that this equation
can only be solved if p is equal to two-thirds.
Yeah,
two-thirds.
If p is two-thirds,
then what appears here is just t squared
in the denominator,
same as the t squared here.
So,
that's the first piece of information we learn,
that the universe expands
as the two-thirds power
of time.
It doesn't expand linearly with time,
a growing like t.
That would be sort of unaccelerated motion.
It expands less rapidly than that.
In fact,
it slows down somewhat.
So,
it's t,
so we can now replace t by two-thirds.
Everywhere's.
Well,
if we choose t to be two-thirds,
then the time dependence on both sides of the equation
is the same.
That's been guaranteed.
And so,
I can cancel the time dependence.
t to the three p just becomes t squared,
and I can now cancel it.
And lo and behold,
I have a formula.
Now,
t p squared is what?
Four-ninths?
P squared is four-ninths.
And now I can solve this equation
for the unknown constant c.
What is it?
c cubed is equal to nine times eight is 72.
Well,
nine times eight.
Nine times eight pi m g
multiplied by nine divided by four.
That's the equation I just wrote down.
Have I left any,
is that it?
Three on the bottom.
Nine times eight divided by four times three is six.
So,
I then determine c.
It's guaranteed that the equation is solved
by this assumption,
a equals six pi m g,
the cube root of that.
That's the cube root of that.
That's a.
Does it solve the equation?
You can check that it solves the equation,
but you'll just be going back
through the same steps that we did.
Okay?
It does solve the equation.
In fact,
it's the only solution.
It's the only solution of the equation.
And it tells you,
the most interesting thing that it tells you
is that the universe continues to expand,
expands as the two-thirds power of time.
Shouldn't there be an unknown constant?
Yeah,
the unknown constant can be absorbed into a shift
of what you call t equals zero.
Notice that at t equals zero,
the scale factor goes to zero.
The unknown constant,
whenever you have an,
yeah,
there is an unknown constant,
but you can put it into
the form t minus some t zero
to the two-thirds.
That becomes the unknown constant,
but then it's just a shift
of what you call t equals zero.
That's the only,
that's the only unknown constant.
So,
once you say that t equals zero corresponds
to the time at which a is equal to zero,
there's no more constants left.
All right,
well,
first of all,
among other things,
it tells us that if we go
back in time to a certain time,
a,
some t,
namely t equals zero,
a will be equal to zero.
a equals zero is this crazy condition
where everything is squashed on top of everything else
and the density becomes infinite.
So,
if you like,
the time,
and that,
of course,
is what we refer to as the Big Bang.
The Big Bang is when a,
to say zero is probably extreme,
we don't know what happens to matter
when it gets too dense,
but at some time,
a was so small that everything was so crowded
that atoms were crowded on top of atoms,
nuclei were,
quarks were crowded on top of quarks,
and it was a solid,
dense,
configuration.
That's time t equals zero,
when the scale factor is zero.
This t here is the time from that particular era
when things were very,
very crowded.
Okay.
Now,
this,
as I said,
first of all,
this is a model that does
not capture some of the physics.
It captures some physics,
not all of it,
but it captures enough to note some interesting fact.
Let's come back over to here.
a dot over a is the Hubble constant.
That's the Hubble constant.
On the right-hand side,
we have two-thirds t.
Now,
as has been pointed out,
the Hubble constant depends on time.
Yes,
it does.
Here it is.
How does it depend on time?
Like one over the time.
But here's a tool that you can now use.
The Hubble constant today,
is two divided by three
times the age of the universe.
That's what t is.
t is the time from the Big Bang.
And the Hubble constant
is simply
almost just one over the age of the universe.
Approximately,
apart from this factor of two-thirds,
the Hubble constant is
one over the age of the universe.
The age of the universe.
So if we know the Hubble constant today,
we can tell what the age of the universe is.
Or at least we can trace it back
to the point where our equations might not make sense
because they're too Newtonian.
They don't take into account quantum mechanics.
When matter gets very close together,
new things happen.
But we can trace it back
as far as the equations make sense
and say how long ago was the universe ejected
from this very,
very dense state.
All right,
we measure the Hubble constant.
We know what the Hubble constant is
just by astronomically measuring the distance
and the velocity of distant galaxies.
I never remember what the Hubble constant is
in any kind of...
What are the units?
It's meters per second per second.
No,
meters per second per kilometer.
meters per second...
It's given in ridiculous units,
astronomers'
crazy units.
What I do remember is the age of the universe.
All right?
What I do remember is easier for me
to remember the age of the universe
than the Hubble constant
as given in astronomers'
peculiar units.
Kiloparsecs per something per something.
And what is the age of the universe?
Again,
it's measured by measuring the Hubble constant,
distance and velocity.
And the answer is,
give or take a few years,
13 billion years.
Well,
it's somewhere between 13 and 14 billion years.
You said k equals 0.
That's pretty realistic.
It's pretty good.
Yep,
very realistic,
in fact.
We measure that constant k
in microwave and isotropy experiments,
and to the best of any measurement
at the present time,
k is 0.
It's 0 to within about 1%.
Okay.
But that's...
Hmm?
No,
no,
no.
The 1% is a bound.
In other words,
we know that it's not bigger than 1%.
It's not bigger than 1%.
That's small.
And we're going to talk about what k really means,
but let's put it this way.
High precision cosmology,
and it is now a reasonably high precision subject,
is still consistent with k being 0.
No known deviation from k equals 0.
Yeah.
The reasons for that...
I'm just sort of confused about what an am is.
It was the mass inside an arbitrary mass.
Arbitrary volume.
Yeah.
So we ought to come back to what's...
Arbitrary to a.
Right.
A also has a degree of arbitrariness.
Why?
Because there's arbitrariness on both sides.
The real thing which is not arbitrary is a...
All right.
A divided by m to the 1 3rd.
Okay.
All right.
Now why is this
particular combination the physically relevant
or physically meaningful...
What is A?
A depends on your choice of initial grid.
I could have taken this box to
be the distance from us to Andromeda.
I could have taken it to
be the distance from us to...
To the coma cluster or whatever.
The equations are always the same,
but the amount of matter
within a box depends on which
box I choose.
All right.
Supposing I double the size of the box of my...
Let's call it the fiducial box.
Supposing I double the size of this basic box,
what happens to m inside it?
It gets multiplied by 8,
right?
Right.
What happens to A divided
by m to the 1 3rd?
It doesn't change.
Okay.
So this is really the quantity which is
independent of your choice of conventions for how you
choose the grid.
Double the size of the grid,
A becomes only half as big as it was.
Is that right?
No.
Double the size of the grid,
A doubles.
I'm sorry.
Double the size of the grid,
A doubles.
The mass goes up by a factor of 8,
but the mass to the 1 3rd
goes up by a factor of 2.
So,
this is the form,
this is the quantity which is
independent of the choice of grid.
Does that answer your question?
It confused me about what I thought A was.
A is arbitrary.
A is arbitrary to some extent.
Try the density.
A over m to the 1 3rd is a...
A over m to the 1 3rd
is related to m over a cubed,
is it not?
Yeah.
Right.
This is the density and
that's the thing which is physical.
That's the thing which has real physical meaning.
The amount of mass within...
Well,
not A,
x,
right?
No,
m was...
M was defined to be
the mass within a unit box.
With an a cubed box.
Yeah,
with an a cubed box.
Right.
So,
it is the real physical density of matter.
This here is...
And it's...
It does change with time.
Of course it changes with time.
It grows like t to the 2 3rds.
But at any given time,
this quantity is independent of
the way you choose the grid.
Right.
Yeah.
Thank you.
ありがとうございました
But if you're going to use A
to compute the age of the universe,
you need to have a number from M.
No,
actually you don't.
Here's what we discovered.
Quite apart from what M is,
quite apart from what M is,
we always found that P was two-thirds,
right?
That was independent of M.
So that says that A
is equal to some unknown constant.
The unknown constant C depends on M.
All right?
C times T to the two-thirds.
Okay?
The unknown constant C cancels out
of the age of the universe.
A dot is equal to two-thirds
C times T to the minus one-third.
Is that right?
I've just differentiated it.
The Hubble constant,
which is A dot over A,
is just two over three.
Three T.
The constant here cancels out.
The constant cancels out,
and with it,
cancels out the dependence on M.
So it's quite remarkable that the
calculation of the age of the universe
doesn't depend on the density of mass.
At least the calculation in terms
of the connection with the Hubble constant.
The connection between the age of the
universe and the Hubble constant and so forth
is independent of M.
Is that sort of because the Big
Bang happened such that the K equals zero,
and then therefore we can now ignore C?
I mean,
it all cancels out.
If K was different from zero,
then...
Then it would be a little bit of dependence.
Yeah.
Yeah,
that's right.
If K was not zero,
it would be a little bit of dependence.
I'm sorry.
I'm studying the .
This is the .
Right,
right.
Hold on.
Some K equals zero.
When was the...
When was the equation?
When was it?
When was the math,
when did they publish it?
Well,
Friedman was killed during World War I.
Einstein invented the general
theory of relativity around 1915.
That doesn't leave much of a window.
Somewhere's in there.
Everybody know when World War I was?
End of 1918.
Yeah.
So,
right.
Now,
Friedman didn't have all of this quite
as in the form that I have it.
Exactly,
the history beyond that,
I don't know.
I don't know who Friedman and Robertson Walker were.
I'm sorry.
I don't know who Robertson and Walker were.
I'm not sure.
I'm sure they played some key
role in putting some of these together.
Yeah.
This all seems to depend on
an assumption of an open universe.
Is...
What...
Yes,
it depends on the universe being flat.
I've used flat geometry,
flat spatial geometry.
We're gonna come to that.
The three possibilities,
K equals positive,
negative,
or zero,
correspond to flat space,
and K equals negative is negative curved space,
and K equals positive is positive curved
space.
So,
that does depend on the universe being flat.
Yeah.
I want...
Really,
really,
in this form,
I suspect that the history
really doesn't go back past the
acceptance of the Big Bang Theory,
which was sometime in the 60s,
in this precise form.
Yeah.
This form has been sort
of set up to be useful.
It's been set up to be useful.
You...
The things that are in
it are the density of matter,
the scale factor.
How much of it Friedman actually wrote down,
I don't know.
Yeah.
The flatness of...
I mean,
you start off by talking about flat space.
Right.
And you use that assumption in estimating the density.
Well,
of course,
I didn't say flat space.
I said Newtonian.
Newtonian.
But,
of course,
space is flat in Newtonian.
Newtonian physics.
Right.
So,
if it weren't flat,
you'd have to make some adjustments to the equation.
Nope.
Interesting.
All you have to do
is put K in back in,
either positive,
negative,
or zero.
That's all it takes.
The equation itself...
Now,
I can...
I'll explain why in a second.
Let me get one more question.
Why...
Why there should be an equation based on
Newtonian physics that should have a density of...
Well,
I think that the question of whether
the equation should have the full complexity
is an interesting question.
But...
Yeah.
Go ahead.
Right now,
you said that the length of
meter sticks doesn't depend on A.
And sometime long
ago,
did the length of meter sticks depend on A?
Well,
sufficiently long ago,
I suppose,
the meter sticks were so crowded together that
they melted and blended into each other.
And...
The idea of a meter stick...
Sure.
At some point,
the meter sticks were just about a meter apart.
A little before that,
they were pushing against each other and got squeezed.
We're assuming they're perfectly rigid.
There's no such thing as a rigid body in relativity.
Remember that?
You remember why there can't be a rigid body?
Yes.
If there was a truly rigid body,
and you hit it on this side,
since its length can't change,
the other side would instantaneously have to move off.
Right.
But if that were true,
then you could send messages
faster than the speed of light.
So,
the other side can't move until
light has a chance to get there.
And so,
you know there's no such
thing as a truly rigid body.
Why do you think there is this coincidence of equations,
Newtonian and relativistic?
Ah.
Well,
all right.
Here,
I think,
is what you can say.
When do you expect general relativity to
become important in this particular kind of analysis?
I'm not going to pick that up.
It's when the curvature of space becomes important.
It's kind of like the Earth.
When does the curvature of the Earth become important?
When you're studying regions of the Earth which are
of order of magnitude the radius of the Earth.
If you study a small little patch of Earth,
then you needn't worry about the curvature of the Earth.
Now,
supposing we're interested in the question,
how does grass grow?
Do we have to worry about the curvature of the
Earth to figure out the principles of the growing of grass?
No.
Why?
Because grass is the distance between
little bits of grass is a lot,
lot smaller than the radius of curvature of the Earth.
As long as we're studying cosmology on distance scales
smaller than the radius of curvature of the whole universe,
that's supposed to be the whole universe,
thought of as a giant
three-dimensional sphere or something else,
we can still study little portions of it,
which may have many,
many,
many galaxies,
and the study of a little
portion of it on a small scale,
on a scale smaller than the total radius of curvature,
it will be a good approximation.
And the smaller the region,
the better the approximation,
we can do it by Newtonian mechanics.
Newtonian mechanics assumes two things.
Okay,
it assumes two things.
The first thing is that the curvature of space is,
on the whole,
is not important in the problem.
That gets rid of general relativity.
The second thing is nothing is moving
very fast near the speed of light.
Now,
as long as I study a small enough region
and use the Hubble law
that velocity is Hubble times distance,
as long as the distance is not so large
that the velocity gets up near the speed of light,
then the equations that we've written down are correct.
Well,
the equations we wrote down gave us an answer,
and you can think of that answer
as how the scale factor evolves with time
as seen by only looking...
If the Earth were to suddenly start expanding uniformly,
and we go out in a field,
we could measure the precise behavior of
the expansion of the radius of the Earth
without ever measuring the radius of the Earth itself
and without even realizing that the Earth was curved.
We would just watch how the
grass blades increased the distance between them.
So,
as long as the distance is small enough
that the relative distance between blades of
grass doesn't grow with the speed of light,
and as long as the curvature
of the Earth is not important,
we can study things in the small.
And that's what this is.
This is the study of cosmology on distance scales
small enough that we don't
get near the speed of light,
and small enough so that the curvature,
radius of curvature is important.
Does our Hubble body meet both of those?
It's the first,
right,
as far as we know.
The only thing that's important
is that there be a scale
which is big enough so that things are homogeneous
and small enough so that
curvature and velocity are not appreciable.
Alright?
So there is such a scale,
a few million light years on a side,
where the speed of receding velocities is
still much smaller than the speed of light,
and in which it's still much,
much smaller than the radius of curvature.
So we just take that region,
and we study it,
and we say it's good enough
to do it the right way.
So we said that h,
just to be considered constant,
doesn't b potentially become c light?
Eventually,
but as long as we study
things on smaller scales than that,
we're okay.
Yep.
We go out far enough,
and things will be receding with the speed of light.
But that doesn't explain why there's
a term in this Newtonian equation
that it corresponds to curvature.
Ah.
But there is a term.
There is a term.
Right.
We'll get there.
Next time,
next time we'll talk about curvature.
We'll talk about the curvature of space,
and we'll talk about Einstein's equations
and the relation between
Einstein's equations and Newton's equations.
Basically,
as you might expect,
plus or minus,
I can't remember,
k divided by a squared,
this is one of the Einstein equations.
Here,
let's just look at it.
K is a number.
K is a number,
a pure number.
Okay,
so a dot over a squared,
minus k over a squared.
This has to do with geometry.
It has to do with how the universe is expanding.
It has to do with the metric.
A is connected with the metric of space.
So what's on the left-hand side,
I've transposed this to the left-hand side over here,
plus or minus,
probably plus.
What's on this side here has to do with geometry,
the geometry of expansion.
What's on the right-hand side has to do,
with energy density,
m over a cubed.
Well,
why am I writing an m over a cubed?
It's eight pi g times the energy density.
Why energy density?
Mass and energy are the same thing.
This is clearly one of the Einstein equations
that connects on the left-hand side,
geometry,
with the right-hand side,
which is energy density.
All right.
So,
another way to derive exactly
the same equation is to write down
the Einstein equations and simply plug in
our assumptions.
Our assumptions,
homogeneous,
uniformly expanding.
Yeah,
plug in this metric with an arbitrary time dependence,
calculate the curvature,
calculate the Einstein tensor,
put it on the left side.
On the right-hand side,
put the energy density.
And that becomes Einstein's equations.
So,
and that's,
I think that's the way
the equations were first discovered.
Not by,
I think it was,
as far as I know,
it was,
it came later that people interpreted
these equations in terms of Newton's equations,
I think.
I'm not sure of my history there,
but I believe
that's the case,
that they first were derived
from general theory.
Any other questions?
Okay.
We'll see you next week.