This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
All right,
let's review a little bit the basic equations of cosmology.
And then I want to take you
through a little tour of these equations
and what they say about the structure of the universe.
And then perhaps we will get
to the subject of dark matter.
I want to talk about
dark matter a little bit also,
because most of the matter in the universe is dark.
So I will discuss that with you,
and I will explain to you in what way
it is either mysterious or not mysterious,
depending on your taste.
All right,
we derived the Friedman-Robertson-Walker-Lemaître,
I don't know who else,
equation from energy conservation,
assuming that the universe was homogeneous.
Incidentally,
in this course,
I never show these beautiful pictures of galaxies
and everything else,
just because I like to show them.
I don't know how to run the projector up there,
among other things.
But I will draw for you the universe,
the way it would look in one of these gorgeous,
gorgeous pictures.
You just have to substitute black
for white and white for black,
and then it looks like this.
It somehow looks better when you invert the color.
And on a scale larger than,
the size of clusters of galaxies,
there are clusters of galaxies,
on scales larger than the sizes of clusters of galaxies,
millions of light,
many millions of light years,
the,
many,
many millions of light years,
but not billions of light years,
smaller than billions of light years,
bigger than millions of light years,
the universe looks pretty homogeneous,
pretty smooth.
Okay,
so assuming that,
it's good and smooth,
and concentrating on one galaxy,
doesn't really have to be a galaxy,
it could just be an imaginary particle
moving along with the flow,
and thinking of ourselves as the center,
there's nothing important about where we are,
but just to get an orientation,
thinking of ourselves as the center of coordinates,
we studied the equations,
of energy conservation,
for this particle,
thought of as a Newtonian particle,
moving under the influence of gravity,
the gravity due to everything within a sphere,
centered on us,
and with radius equal to the distance of the sphere.
I'm just going to go through that again,
because it's really,
it's really simple.
If we choose,
let's put the galaxy over here on the x-axis,
and in fact,
let's put it at x equals one.
If it's at x equals one,
that means its distance,
okay,
what is its distance then from us?
And we are of course x equals zero.
Its distance is then by definition the scale factor a.
That's the definition of the scale factor,
the distance at x equals one.
The distance at x equals two is two a,
and so forth and so on.
So,
we could concentrate just on this galaxy by itself,
that's at,
that coordinate x equals one,
and we can study how it moves under the influence
of everything else in there.
It has an energy.
Its energy is first of all
a kinetic energy of outward motion.
Its kinetic energy of outward motion is one half,
now,
its velocity squared,
its mass,
let's also let its mass be one half,
let's let its mass be one unit.
Then I don't have to keep writing masses,
which just cancel anyway.
One half,
its mass,
times its velocity squared,
and what is its velocity squared?
If its distance is a,
then its velocity squared is just a dot squared,
where dot means time derivative.
That's its kinetic energy.
What about its potential energy?
Its potential energy is minus,
the mass contained within here,
now what's the mass contained within here?
It's four pi over three times,
that's the volume of the sphere,
no,
that's not the volume of the sphere yet,
we have to multiply it by a cubed,
that's the volume of the sphere,
we multiply that by the mass density,
and that's the mass of everything inside this shell,
four thirds of a,
four thirds pi,
that's volume,
times a cubed,
times the density,
okay,
that's the mass in there,
but remember the gravitational potential energy
is the mass times g
divided by the distance,
let's call it just distance,
so we have to put g in there,
the potential energy,
and then divide by the distance,
the distance is just a.
What does Newton tell us?
Newton tells us that this
is constant and independent of time,
so this is just some constant,
and I call that constant,
I think I call that constant minus k,
and making it minus k does
not necessarily mean that it's negative,
k can either be positive or negative,
but I just called it k.
And,
and that is the basic equation of cosmology,
to make it a little bit more familiar,
I don't know if familiar or not familiar,
depending on your background,
first of all we can divide by a,
and make this a squared here,
now we can divide the entire equation by a squared,
let's first multiply by two,
ah,
wait,
let's first multiply by two to
get rid of the half here,
that makes this eight pi over three,
and I should have called this
thing k only after multiplying by two,
for standard,
the standard notation would have this being minus k,
after I multiply by two,
but in any case it's constant,
so it doesn't matter whether I
call it k or two k.
Now I divide it by a squared,
and I get a dot,
so I get a dot over a squared,
that's the square of the Hubble constant,
or the Hubble non-constant,
let's shift this over to the right hand side,
and that becomes eight pi over three g,
and I've divided by a squared,
so this a squared is no longer here,
times the mass density,
and then minus k divided by a squared,
the a squared,
I just divided both sides
of the equation by a squared,
and this is the Friedman-Robertson-Walker equation,
Friedman,
FRW,
L,
and everybody else.
I'll tell you now,
although it'll take us to next week,
next week we will discuss
it in a little more detail,
the connection with Einstein's equations,
I'll just remind you that the Einstein equations,
in particular the time-time component of the equation,
the Einstein equations,
have the form of some tensor,
which is composed out of the curvature tensor,
what is it?
It's r00 minus one half g00 times the curvature scalar,
is equal to what?
Is equal to t00 with a constant in there,
which is related to,
there's also some eight pi's and three's,
there's also some,
I can't remember the exact numbers,
but I think it has eight
pi over three and g in it,
but things of that nature.
The connection is simple with this equation.
If I transpose all the things
without any energy density in them,
a dot over a squared plus k over a squared,
that's the left-hand side of Einstein's equations.
If we plug in an expanding metric,
which we'll write down in greater detail next time,
if we plug it in and calculate the left-hand side,
guess what we get?
We get a dot over a
squared plus k over a squared,
and the right-hand side,
we just get the energy density,
rho is of course the mass density,
but mass and energy are the same thing,
e equals mc squared,
and so this equation really is nothing but
the time-time component of the Einstein equation.
I tell you that now just for orientation's sake,
that we have not abandoned Albert,
for Isaac,
but at this stage,
Isaac and Albert say the same thing,
so we might as well think about Newtonian mechanics
to get a first orientation.
All right,
now,
next thing we did is we plugged in,
or we assumed a form for rho,
for the mass density,
and I'll tell you from now on,
I'm going to call it the energy density.
Okay?
The energy of a system at rest.
Now why are we talking about a system at rest?
Because our coordinates are moving with the material.
So the material in the coordinate frame that we're using
is everywhere is at rest relative to the coordinates,
and under those circumstances,
rho is nothing but the mass density at rest,
or the energy density at rest.
All right,
so let's,
uh,
let's take a little cube.
We take a cube,
which is one coordinate unit on a side.
That means its length,
width,
and height are A,
the scale factor itself,
and prescribe how much mass is in there.
Let's assume there is a mass M in there.
There's some value of mass in there,
and furthermore,
under the assumption of homogeneity,
on a large enough scale,
every cube of the same size has the same mass.
So let's just call it
the mass M inside that cube.
Then what is the density?
The density is M,
which is constant.
Uh,
the energy in that cube,
it stays constant.
Every,
the masses move,
but they don't go into or out of the box.
And so the amount of mass in there stays constant,
but the mass density is M divided by the volume,
which is A cubed,
and that's rho.
So now we can write our FRW equation
as A dot over A squared,
Hubble constant squared,
is equal to 8 pi G over 3,
and now M,
this constant M,
divided by A cubed.
This is not the mass of any specific object.
It's just the mass within this cube.
I call it M.
Maybe I should have used another letter for it,
but it doesn't matter.
The mass in the unit
cube minus K over A squared.
All right,
we decided last time,
and I'm going to continue for the time being,
imagining,
not imagining,
but using the empirical fact.
It is an empirical fact,
an observational fact,
that this constant K is very close to zero.
It's too close to zero to
tell whether it's positive or negative.
I will tell you now,
it does correspond to the curvature of space,
but,
it's too small to be able
to tell whether it's positive or negative,
and it's a very good approximation in cosmology,
just to ignore it.
And that's the simple equation
which describes the expansion of the universe.
This is called the matter-dominated universe.
It's matter-dominated.
What that means is that this formula here,
corresponds to a situation where you have
the energy in this box,
just in the form of particles at rest.
You count up all the masses in that box.
If the masses were moving with a tremendous velocity,
there would also be kinetic energy,
huge amounts of kinetic energy in the box.
And then we might say that we were talking about,
and if the kinetic energy was bigger than mc squared,
or bigger than just m if we
set the speed of light equal to one,
that means that the particles are moving
with very close to the speed of light,
then we would no longer say it was matter-dominated.
When one speaks about matter-dominated,
one is speaking about the mass
distribution being made up of things
which are essentially at rest,
moving with the flow.
So in that case,
yeah?
Um,
about the temperature.
For the time being,
since these particles,
since we can think of these as particles,
and the particles are not moving,
we can for the moment
just say the temperature is zero.
And we can also say the pressure is zero.
If all the particles came to rest in this room,
if the room got so cold
that all the particles came to rest,
in the room,
relative to the coordinates of the room,
there would be no pressure.
Pressure happens when there are particles
crossing the boundaries of this box.
And we'll see,
it is important,
we're going to come back to it.
But matter-dominated means the particles
are at rest in the box,
moving together with the box as the
box flows along with the flow of galaxies.
Then under those circumstances,
those are the circumstances where
we should label this now matter-dominated,
there may be other forms of energy,
there may be other forms of energy around,
so there may be other contributions,
but in our universe today,
well,
I was going to say something false.
I was going to say our universe is matter-dominated.
It is actually not.
It is dominated by dark energy,
but we'll come to that in a little while.
But all of the ordinary matter,
galaxies,
protons,
neutrons,
they all add up,
and this is the so-called matter-dominated universe.
The last time we solved the equations,
we solved the equations not by solving the equations,
but by guessing an answer,
standard honorable method to solve equations.
So let's try a power law.
You might have tried something else,
you might have tried sine or cosine or hyperbolic,
a new function or whatever,
but the first thing you always try is,
A is a power law.
So we tried,
constant times time to a power,
and we plugged it in.
What did we find?
We found,
first of all,
to match the two sides,
we had to choose P equal to two-thirds.
Maybe I should go through that again very quickly.
If this is A,
A dot is C P
T to the P minus one,
and A dot over A is equal to,
the C's cancel out,
and we just get P over T.
Square it,
and we get P squared over T squared.
So the point is,
the left-hand side,
is proportional to one over time squared.
The right-hand side,
is proportional to one over time,
to the three P.
A cubed,
goes like T to the three P.
So we have to have T to the three P,
being T squared.
That means that P has
no choice but to be two-thirds.
So that tells us that the universe
expands as the two-thirds power of the time,
it doesn't expand linearly,
A doesn't grow like time,
it grows like the two-thirds power of the time.
And we can also plug in,
and once we know that,
then we can plug back into the
equation and compute C if we like,
C doesn't tell us very much,
it's just if you're doing the bookkeeping
and you want to keep track of everything,
well,
you want to keep track of everything,
and if you do,
you find that C cubed,
is equal to six pi Mg.
And work it out.
This is the more interesting thing here,
that the universe expands as the two-thirds power of time.
What does that look like
if we were to plot it?
If we plot vertically,
the scale factor,
horizontally,
time,
then eight,
the two-thirds power,
looks,
I don't know,
something like this.
Linear would just be a straight line,
this is not as strong as linear,
so it turns over like that.
Okay,
that's the matter-dominated universe,
and it was the way the
universe behaved for a rather long time,
it behaved this way from about
a hundred thousand years in age,
that's pretty young,
the universe is ten billion years old,
from about a hundred thousand years in age,
to about a couple of billion years,
billion or two billion years,
or something like that,
it behaved according to this matter-dominated law.
Now,
before that,
the universe's energy was dominated by something else,
it was dominated by radiation,
not by matter.
So let me explain why.
The universe today is filled with photons,
we detect those photons,
most of the photons are in the microwave range,
for the moment we're not going
to discuss where they came from,
they are the remnants of the Big Bang,
but let's just take it as an observed fact,
that there are a large number of photons floating around
in the microwave range,
and in fact,
roughly,
there are about ten to the ninth photons,
for every atom,
or for every proton in the universe.
So the universe,
in terms of numbers,
just in terms of population,
is largely made of photons.
On the other hand,
the photons have very much less energy than the protons,
or even the electrons.
The protons have energy mc squared,
the photons have no mass,
but they do have energy,
they do have energy,
and they have energy,
every photon has energy,
but let's talk about that energy a little bit.
Incidentally,
when one speaks about the
photon having an energy mc squared,
we're talking about the rest energy,
how do we get away with
saying the photon has no mass,
but it has an energy?
Well,
we're not talking about the rest energy of the photon,
the photon has energy,
but it's moving,
if you tried to slow it down to rest,
it would just disappear,
it would have nothing,
no mass,
no nothing.
So,
photons have energy,
and let's discuss the photons,
why in the very early universe,
the universe was radiation dominated,
that means dominated by the energy,
that means the energy density
was mostly in the form of photons,
why that's true,
so,
let's begin with the formula
for the energy of a photon.
Again,
we can think of a box,
a unit on a side,
it's filled up with photons,
now photons move,
that means photons can pass out through the box,
but on the average there are as many photons
coming into the box as out of the box,
and so the number of photons
pretty much stays constant in the box,
but unlike the protons,
the energy of a photon depends
on the size of the box,
so let's discuss that a little bit.
Let's begin with the energy of a photon.
The energy of a photon.
Standard symbol for a photon is a gamma.
That doesn't mean it's a gamma ray.
Gamma rays are just high energy photons,
but gamma is the standard symbol for a photon.
The energy of a photon
is equal
to Planck's constant,
this terribly tiny constant,
10 to the minus 30 or whatever it is,
times what?
Times the frequency of the light
that that photon is composing.
Let's call that nu.
What are the units of nu?
One over time.
Yes,
yes,
but there's a,
certainly.
Hertz.
Cycles per second.
This is also h bar omega,
but I'll just call it h nu.
Now,
we have a wave going by us.
We have to,
we unnecessarily,
because we're already,
we've already studied quantum mechanics,
and we're completely familiar with quantum mechanics,
completely comfortable with it,
we have no trouble jumping back and forth
from wave to particle picture,
right?
Good.
Okay.
So,
associated with these photons is a wave.
And the wave moves with the speed of light c.
And,
if it was just an ordinary wave in this room,
moving past us with the speed of light,
it would have a wavelength lambda,
a wavelength lambda.
And the short of the wavelength,
clearly the,
clearly the biggest c,
stand there with your nose watching,
watching the wave.
You're watching the wave go past you,
and the electric field goes up and down,
and up and down,
and it oscillates.
It oscillates with a frequency.
That frequency is nu.
It's quite clear,
the faster the speed of light is,
the larger the frequency,
the more cycles per second,
and the shorter the wavelength,
the larger the frequency.
So the frequency is equal to the speed of light
divided by the wavelength.
So we can rewrite the photon energy as
h times c over lambda.
The important thing here is the lambda in the denominator.
Now,
what happens to a photon of a given wavelength
as the universe expands?
And here is where we will make an assumption,
the assumption is very well justified
by studying the dynamics of electromagnetic waves.
But here is the assumption,
that as the universe expands,
the photon wavelengths expand with it.
Imagine,
for example,
a wave in a wave guide,
or in a box.
And that wave is the longest wavelength
that you can have in that box.
It looks like that.
It has no nodes,
in other words,
it doesn't oscillate,
it just has one half of an oscillation.
What happens as the box grows?
As the box grows,
the wavelength expands to match the box.
It will not jump to a
wave with a node in it,
or with nodes in it.
Nodes mean places where it goes to zero.
It won't do that.
It will just expand with a box.
As the universe expands,
it's like an expanding box,
and the wavelength of every photon
gets stretched in proportion
to the increased factor of the wave.
In other words,
the wavelength,
whatever the wavelength was,
if the scale factor doubles,
then the wavelength doubles.
The wavelength is proportional to the scale factor.
Another way to say it,
well,
no,
that's good enough.
Every photon has a wavelength
that is not frozen in time,
but grows linearly together with the scale factor.
That means,
since the wavelength is in the denominator,
and the wavelength is growing with the scale factor,
it means that the energy of the photons is decreasing
as the scale factor grows.
And in particular,
the energy of any photon,
whatever its initial energy was,
it will still be the same
as the energy of the photon.
as the scale factor increases.
And the energy of the photon
as the wavelength gets longer.
So,
we have this box of photons now.
There's a given number of photons
in the box,
on the average.
It's true,
they pass in and pass out of a box,
but on the average,
there's a given number of photons in the box.
Every single photon,
as the box expands,
its energy scales like 1 over 8.
Now,
that means
that the total amount of energy
in this box
won't be a constant like M,
as it was when we just had
non-relativistic stationary particles there,
but it will scale
like a constant divided by m.
Now,
m here does not mean mass.
It's just a label.
It's just a parameter.
Whatever the energy in the box,
as A expands,
the energy will decrease
like a constant divided by A.
That's the energy per photon.
Now,
how many photons are in the box?
Let's suppose that there are n photons
in the box.
And the number of photons in the box
is 1 over A.
this is...
I made a mistake.
Let's just call this
something over A.
Constant of A.
That's per photon.
But,
if every photon in the box
has an energy that goes like 1 over A,
and the number of photons stays fixed,
that means
the total energy in that box
also scales
like 1 over A.
That's the point.
So the energy in this box,
energy in the box,
is some constant
divided by A.
Now,
what's the energy density in the box?
The energy density in the box,
you take the energy
and divide it by the volume of the box.
So we divide by the volume,
and the volume
is
A cubed.
So that's another A cubed
in the denominator.
And what we discover,
here's the discovery,
that the energy of a box of photons,
as you expand the box,
goes like 1 over A to the fourth power,
instead of 1 over A cubed.
When all we had was particles at rest,
we said the total mass in the box was m,
we divided by the volume,
and we said the mass density
was m over A cubed.
But for photons,
because each photon's energy decreases
as you expand the box,
it's 1 divided by 8 to the fourth.
Okay,
so let's go back now.
Now we have,
now imagine
that the universe,
instead of being filled with protons,
neutrons,
electrons,
ordinary particles moving slowly,
let's imagine that the universe
is filled with photons.
As I said,
photons pass through the box,
they come in and they go out,
but we'll assume that
the number of photons in the box
on the average,
as many come in as go out.
In that case,
we have to modify
the equation.
Which equation?
This one over here.
We have to modify it,
and instead of the right-hand side
being m over A cubed,
it now becomes m divided by 8 to the fourth.
So,
this is now the radiation-dominated universe.
It looks pretty similar.
A dot over A squared equals,
same thing,
8 pi g over 3,
and now the energy density,
which instead of being m over A cubed,
is a constant,
which I called m again,
different constant,
divided by A to the fourth.
It even has different units now.
Well,
can we solve that equation?
Yeah,
we can solve that equation.
We do it the same way.
Let's plug in,
let's make a trial solution,
a equals c t to the p.
Again,
a dot over A
is just p divided by t.
That's a dot over A.
p divided by t.
We square it.
p squared over t squared.
That's the left side.
Now let's go to the right side.
8 pi g over 3,
m,
and now A to the fourth.
So now I'm going to have in the denominator,
c to the fourth,
that's not going to be very interesting,
but t to the 4p.
A to the fourth is c to
the fourth times t to the 4p.
And now,
if I'm going to match both sides,
this one goes like 1 over
t squared as time goes on.
This one goes like 1 over t to the 4p.
4p had better equal 2.
Otherwise,
they can't match.
Okay?
So 4p had better equal 2,
or p equals 1 half.
So we've discovered that the radiation-dominated universe
expands
not like t to the 2 thirds,
but like t to the 1 half.
Square root of t,
in other words.
This expands,
and we can also calculate the constant c.
I'll leave it to you to calculate the constant c.
It's not very interesting.
Oh,
well,
I'll tell you what it is.
c to the fourth is
32 pi over 3 times gm.
That was not very illuminating to me either.
But,
the fact that the universe expands
like t to the 1 half power
instead of t to the 2 thirds
is somewhat interesting.
Okay.
Yeah?
Why is there a g in there?
There's always a g in...
g is normally gravitational,
right?
This is,
yeah,
this is the
gravitating effect of energy.
Remember,
in Newton's theory...
Yeah.
Okay,
good.
That's a good question.
We discussed it last time,
but let me come back to it,
not last time,
last quarter.
Newton's theory
is the theory of things moving very slowly
compared to the speed of light.
The dominant form of energy
when things move with slow
compared to the speed of light
is just the mass,
the mc squared energy.
That's,
you may think of m
as being simply the energy
plus a little bit of kinetic energy
may be there.
Alright.
When things move near the speed of light,
then the energy
is not proportional
to the mass.
It's more complicated.
For example,
photons
which have no
mass do have energy.
But the right hand side,
or the thing which
gravitates,
the thing which
pulls,
the thing which causes gravity,
is not rest mass.
It is energy.
When the object is slow,
then its energy and its mass are the same.
A rapidly
moving photon
will gravitate,
will cause things
to be pulled toward it.
Another example,
here's an example.
Take a box
and fill it with lots and lots of radiation.
Radiation,
so much radiation that it would melt
the walls of the box,
but let's make
walls that won't get melted
in our imagination.
And we fill this box with a huge amount
of radiation.
That box will gravitate more
than the box without the radiation in it.
It will have more energy.
E,
if the
box is at rest,
its energy is
the mass times,
it will gravitate.
It will gravitate and pull things toward it.
So it's energy which is the thing
which gravitates.
When we're writing this equation here,
this doesn't really stand for mass,
rest mass,
it stands for
energy density.
Okay?
So,
it's energy density which gravitates
and it gravitates proportional to Newton's
constant G.
Okay.
Yeah?
Is either of these
equations solvable with an A that
decreases with time?
Oh yeah.
In fact,
I mean
if you put back the one over A squared,
the K over
A squared term,
you'll find
examples where it increases and then
decreases.
Maybe we'll do that.
For the time being,
it's not too important
because there's no,
I mean it's
it may be important conceptually
for some reasons,
but
the universe does not appear to be
doing anything like that.
Yeah?
But the equation will,
there's a solution to the equation.
Yeah.
What happens to the energy?
You said the energy per photon,
so the total
energy goes down.
What happened
to conservation of energy?
No,
no,
no.
These equations are conservation of
energy.
This is kinetic energy.
Let's put back,
let's put back
the K over,
the K and multiply
by A squared.
These equations
state conservation of
energy,
but there's two kinds of
energy.
One of them
are the ordinary things such as photons
and protons and neutrons
and everything,
they go on the right hand side.
The left hand side
is the energy of expansion.
It's the energy of the gravitational
field.
It's the thing which is
left out until you know about general relativity.
Okay?
So these are,
well actually what is it?
It's really the
kinetic energy of the
outward moving things.
Here's kinetic energy,
here's the energy
of the object
in a frame of reference in which it's at rest.
So in other words,
this is
the rest energy of a box
moving with the flow
and this is its kinetic energy.
It's the sum of them which
is conserved.
And if you set it
equal to zero,
in other words
if you set this minus this equal to zero,
that's surely conserved.
So it's a balance between
two kinds of energy,
kinetic and potential.
Just the
assertion
about it's the energy
that's doing the gravitating.
It's the other kinds of energy,
yeah.
That is
not clear until you go to general relativity.
I mean that's...
That's right.
That's correct.
Right.
You might have
guessed it from special relativity.
E equals mc squared,
you might have guessed it.
In fact,
Einstein
did guess it.
That's exactly how he guessed it.
What he did was he
first examined...
He studied a box of photons like this.
And he said,
what's the mass of that box of photons?
Alright,
so here was his
thought experiment.
He said,
let's push
on that box of photons.
When you push
on the box of photons,
just take the box
by itself.
It takes
a certain force to accelerate the box.
Because the box has a mass.
But,
now when you start to accelerate
the box,
more photons
hit this side of the box than hit
that side of the box,
because you're pushing
the box.
This wall is moving away from the photons.
This wall is moving toward the photons.
And so you actually have to push
a little bit harder to push
against the pressure,
the radiation pressure
in the box.
That means
effectively,
the mass of the box is
a little bit bigger.
And Einstein worked
it out,
and he found
that the extra mass,
the extra inertia
of the box,
was in
fact proportional to the energy of the photons
in there.
That was
the origin of E equals mc squared.
Now,
he also had rather
early the idea of the
equivalence principle.
That
gravity works the same on
all objects.
And from that,
he came to the conclusion
that the earth
would pull on this box
as if it had a mass
not equal to just the mass of
the original box,
but the mass plus
the photons in there.
But if the earth pulls on
the box,
the box pulls on the earth,
etc.,
etc.
So rather early,
he had
the idea that energy
gravitates.
It took him a while to get it all together.
And ultimately,
yes,
it's the general theory of relativity
which tells us
that it's
energy which goes on this side.
Remember last quarter,
we talked about having to make tensor equations.
And
the left hand side of Einstein's
equation is a tensor.
The right hand side
is the energy-momentum tensor
composed out of energy and
momentum.
Okay.
So
we have
two kinds of cosmologies
real cosmologies
and real cosmology is a combination of both of them.
But let's try
to understand
under what circumstances
and when
and at what times
the universe might be matter
dominated and when it might be radiation
dominated.
In fact,
it is a question of when,
whether
the universe is matter dominated or
radiation dominated.
The reason
is the following.
I just explained to you
that as the universe expands,
the energy density of radiation
decreases.
But
it follows that when the universe
if you imagine contracting
it,
going backward,
the energy density of radiation
must have been much larger.
If you squeeze it,
it's
larger.
If you let it...
So at some point,
when the universe was really squeezed,
where the wavelengths of all the photons
were really small,
the photons had more
energy than the ordinary
matter.
Yeah.
So as the universe
ages,
does the P
go continuously
from one half to two thirds?
Not
abruptly,
for sure,
but
more or less in a
fairly narrow range of time.
It doesn't jump.
I was going to say it jumps.
It goes continuously
from one half
to two thirds.
But there's a space where it
gets very steep and then...
Well,
I was about to draw
or give you a rough idea,
but let's
just plot,
just to
get the idea up on the blackboard.
Alright.
Let's first plot energy density.
E density.
And let's draw both cases.
The matter dominated,
here's the matter dominated.
The matter energy density.
And that goes,
it goes to zero.
It does go to zero.
How does it go to zero?
It goes to zero like one over a cubed.
It also becomes infinite
when a goes to zero.
This is,
let's see,
this could be,
yeah,
this is a.
a on the horizontal axis,
scale factor.
When the scale factor goes to zero,
that's the situation where
the universe is shrunk to a point.
The density becomes infinite.
Alright.
Now,
that's the,
this is the
matter energy density.
Let's write matter out here.
And then there's
radiation.
The radiation
is one over a to the fourth.
One over a to the fourth is
smaller when a is big,
but bigger when a
is small.
So one over a
to the fourth looks like this.
And
at some point,
they cross.
At some point,
the
matter density becomes
less than the radiation
density.
So sufficiently early,
if we go back far enough,
the universe was radiation
dominated.
What does that mean in terms
of,
um,
exactly
what was asked before?
What does that mean about the growth of
the universe?
It means it started out early.
We'll try to estimate
in a moment where this happens.
When that happened.
In a little while.
Alright.
If I plot,
now I plot something different.
I plot the scale factor versus
time.
Okay.
The scale factor versus time.
Here was energy versus
the scale factor.
Scale factor versus time.
The scale factor for radiation
dominated
goes like the square root
of time.
T to the
one half.
And that looks
like this.
And let's extrapolate
it.
Okay.
But at some point where this crossover
happens,
it's a bad
approximation beyond that
to say that the universe is
mainly radiation,
the energy,
it becomes mainly matter.
At that point,
and not,
it's
not a sharp point.
There's
a region in
here.
It makes a transition
from t to the one half,
from square root of t,
to t to the two thirds.
T to the two thirds is bigger than
t to the one half.
And so that's what the universe looked like
for a fairly long amount of time.
The interesting question
is where did that point happen?
So,
we can talk about that
a little bit now.
Oh,
no,
before we talk about that,
let's talk about temperature.
Let's talk about temperature.
I want to talk about the various
interesting things which happened.
One of the things which happened
was this transition
from matter to
matter,
from radiation dominated
to matter dominated.
That happened after about 10,000 years,
roughly speaking.
Something like about 10,000,
maybe a little more than 10,000 years.
10,000 years after the Big Bang.
Something else happened
which is actually observationally
more dramatic.
What happened to the photons
that run the universe backward
to early times?
If you run it forward,
their wavelength grows.
If you run it backward,
their wavelength shrinks.
What happens to the energy of the photon
as you run it backward?
Increases.
What does that mean about the temperature
of the universe?
It goes up.
In fact,
to a good approximation,
the temperature
of a black body,
or the temperature
of a box of radiation,
is basically just the energy
of a single photon.
It differs by some numerical factor.
So,
apart from some
trivial numerical factor,
the temperature
of the radiation
is the temperature
of the photons
which are moving around
through the universe.
They have a temperature.
And their temperature
changes with time.
It goes like
1 over A.
Now when I say it goes as 1 over A,
I just mean it's proportional to 1 over A.
If A doubles,
the temperature becomes half as big.
If A quadruples,
the temperature is
one quarter as big,
and so forth.
So the bigger A,
the smaller the temperature.
The smaller A,
the bigger the temperature.
And just proportional to 1 over A.
Okay,
now,
that means as we trace backward,
there was a time when the temperature
was much hotter.
In fact,
there was a time when the temperature
was as hot as the surface of the sun.
The surface of the sun
is rather different
visually than
the space around it.
In particular,
the sun is opaque.
You cannot see...
It's not because the sun is too bright
to see the stars behind it.
That's not why you can't see
the stars behind it.
You can't see the stars behind it
because the starlight hits the material
of the sun and gets absorbed
into the sun and gets rattled around
and just gets absorbed
by the sun rather than transmitted
through the sun.
The sun is opaque.
Why is it opaque?
It's opaque because it's ionized.
Ionized means that the atoms
have been separated into
positive and negative charges.
An ordinary atom
is electrically neutral.
Because an ordinary atom is electrically neutral,
it means that
an electric field doesn't accelerate it.
A vibrating electric field
doesn't do much to the atom.
It may cause the atom to change
size and shape a little bit,
but it doesn't accelerate the atom
because the atom is neutral.
But if the atom were replaced
by a proton and an electron,
let's say a hydrogen atom,
if the atom was replaced
by an electron and a proton,
freely moving,
not bound to each other,
the electric field would
slosh the electrons back and forth.
It wouldn't slosh the protons as much
because the protons are heavier.
So when an electric field
passes through
an ionized material,
it sloshes the electric charge
back and forth.
And when it sloshes the electric charge
back and forth,
the electric charge
behaves as an electric conductor,
and electric conductors are opaque.
It's the reason that a mirror
is opaque.
Why can't light go through
a mirror?
Why does it bounce off?
Because the light hitting the mirror
drives electric currents,
and the electric
currents radiate the signal back.
So an ionized
material
is very
opaque.
If you
heat up hydrogen,
and in fact we haven't discussed it very
much yet,
what was the universe made out of?
What is the universe made out of?
Mostly hydrogen.
The universe is largely
hydrogen.
It was even more hydrogen in the past.
Hydrogen and some helium.
But if you go back early enough,
the temperature was high enough
that the helium
and hydrogen were ionized.
The electrons were pulled off the atoms,
and it was opaque.
It was hot
and opaque.
In fact,
it looked
it was about like the surface of the sun.
Let's ask when that happened.
See if we can figure out when that happened.
Well,
there's a particular
temperature.
What's the temperature of the photons today?
Three degrees.
Today's temperature,
temperature today,
is very cold.
Three degrees.
Absolute zero.
Above absolute zero.
Okay.
What is the temperature near the surface of the sun?
Anybody know?
Three thousand degrees.
Something like that.
About a thousand times
larger.
About a thousand times larger.
So,
the temperature
at which
the gas
ionizes.
Let's call
that the ionizing temperature.
And it's also
more or less the surface of the sun.
That's about three thousand degrees.
Well,
if the temperature
varies
like one over A,
as A gets smaller
and smaller,
the temperature goes up,
that means
that at a time of ionization,
the universe must have been the scale
factor must have been a thousand
times smaller than it is today.
The temperature
scales together with the scale factor
as one over A.
If the temperature
today is a thousand times
colder than it was
at ionization,
that means the universe
must be a thousand times bigger.
Let's see if we
can figure out when that was.
At what time that was.
Let's define
a time.
Let's remember the following now.
The scale factor
grows
like
t to the two-thirds.
Today.
T to the two-thirds during the matter
dominated
era.
The late times were matter dominated
after
the universe cooled down a bit.
Alright?
So,
A
grows as two-thirds.
What this tells us is
that the time to the
two-thirds today
divided by
the time at which
ionization happened to the
two-thirds
must be about a
factor of a thousand.
The scale factor today is a thousand
times bigger than it was at
ionization.
The scale factor
is proportional to the t to the
two-thirds.
And so
this tells us
that the scale factor today to the
two-thirds power divided by
the scale factor at ionization
to the two-thirds power
must be about a thousand.
Alright,
we know what the time today
is.
What's the time today?
This is today.
13 something.
About 13.5 billion
years.
It's about
13.5 billion years.
Now 13.5 billion years,
that we measure by measuring the Hubble
constant.
That tells us how fast the galaxies
are moving apart.
If we run it
backwards,
it tells us how long it was since
the galaxies were sitting on top of each other.
13.5 billion years.
Let's call it 10 billion years.
This is 10 billion.
So this is
10 to the tenth
to the two-thirds.
Let's see,
what should we do?
If we take
the three-halves power of both sides,
it becomes
T today
divided by
T at ionization
is equal to
1000 to the three-halves.
I've taken the three-halves side
of both equations.
The three-halves side of something
to the two-thirds,
they just cancel out.
What's 1000 to the three-halves?
What's the square root of 1000?
It's about 30.
So that's about 30,000,
right?
Yes.
It's a thousand
to the one plus one-half.
1000 to the one
is a thousand.
1000 to the one-half
is 30.
30,000.
Okay,
so that's 30,000
three times ten to the fourth
in years.
No,
sorry,
it's not in years.
Three times ten to the fourth.
Okay,
so that tells us
that T ionization
let's just solve that for T ionization
T ion
the time when ionization happened
if we run it backwards
is equal to T today
that is 10 billion years
10 to the tenth
divided by three times
ten to the fourth,
right?
Did I do it right?
Should you have 13 and a half
at the top?
13 and a half.
A billion.
Would you like me to put 13 and a half
at the top,
please?
No,
no,
no.
Are you rounding it down to 10 billion?
I was doing more to a magnitude.
Okay.
13 is 10.
We can adjust it later.
Alright,
so
10 to the tenth divided by
10 to the fourth is 10 to the sixth.
This is 10 to the sixth.
That's 10 to the fifth times
10 divided by three.
10 divided by three is three.
So that's 300,000 years.
After 300,000 years
before 300,000 years
the universe was completely
ionized.
It was completely opaque.
Light could not travel
very far.
There was a dense plasma
of
torn apart
atoms
the nuclei
were mostly
hydrogen with a bit of helium
and
the main thing is
it was hot and opaque.
As hot as the sun,
as the surface of the sun
and opaque like the sun.
Now let's
think about what that means to an astronomer.
Let's say an astronomer with a very good telescope
Here's the astronomer at the center of the universe.
The astronomer looks out
and as he looks out he looks into the past.
Alright,
so if he looks to
the next galaxy
the Andromeda
he's looking about 2 million years into the past.
That's not much.
If he looks out to some
distant galaxy out here
he's looking further into the past
and the shells
are both
distance
as well as
time.
Backward in time as you go further and further out.
Well,
as you go further and further out
the temperature
of the photons is increasing.
The temperature
locally out here
to a traveler
who is traveling with them
is higher than over here
because he's looking back into the past.
And as you look back into the past
the temperature was higher.
Eventually
at some distance
namely
about 13 or 10,
13,
13.5 billion light years
he sees back to the point
where the universe is ionized.
So
and out beyond that
the universe is completely ionized
and light cannot penetrate it.
It just scatters around.
Light just scatters around in here.
And then
at some point
as you move in
it becomes cool enough
for atoms to recombine.
For atoms to recombine
and become unionized.
For the electrons
to get trapped by the protons
and form atomic hydrogen
and atomic helium.
At that point the universe becomes pretty transparent.
Why is it transparent?
Because it's not a plasma anymore.
So way out far
it's a plasma.
It's a place.
Now of course it's a fuzzy place.
It's not a sharp place.
It's a fuzzy place where the universe
goes from being a plasma
to being a
or a time at which the
universe went from being a plasma
to being a
clear
system with just
some neutral atoms.
At that point
light can travel through the universe
without scattering very much.
This surface
where you go from
plasma to
ordinary gas
is called the surface of last scattering.
That's the surface of last scattering.
A photon
rattling around there
will come to that surface of last scattering
and then pretty much be able to
freely move through the universe.
So when we look out
all the things that we normally see
are on the inside
of the surface of last scattering.
And we can't really look out
beyond the surface of last scattering
not with electromagnetic waves anyway.
Yeah?
So basically what you're saying
is our limitations
with our telescopes
radio,
etc.
they cannot look
beyond 300,000
years ago.
That's it,
yeah.
Not 300,000 years ago,
but they can't look
earlier than 300,000.
Are there other things that can look back?
Yes.
Neutrinos are electrically uncharged.
They don't get scattered by the
ions in there.
Neutrinos just pass through
an ionized gas.
Eventually it gets hot enough
that even neutrinos
interact with each other strongly.
So there's some other shell
out here.
That's the surface of last scattering
for neutrinos.
But with a neutrino telescope
which doesn't exist of course,
such a thing doesn't exist,
but with a neutrino telescope
if you could see the very low
energy neutrinos,
then you would be able to see deeper
into the past.
A graviton telescope could see even deeper
But why
when we look out in the sky
and we look up here,
don't we
see the surface of the sun in every direction?
This is a modern form of
Olber's paradox.
If it's true that out here
everything is as hot as the surface
of the sun,
why don't
we look out at the night sky
and see the bright glare?
Redshift.
This is not standing still relative
to us.
It is moving
away from us with very
close to the speed of light.
And that means that every photon
on its way in here has been
redshifted by a factor of a thousand.
That's what made
the temperature go from
3000 degrees to 3 degrees.
So what we look out and we see
is microwaves
of temperature
3 degrees.
That's not much of a signal,
a 3 degree
black body.
You don't see it.
3000 degrees,
if you looked
out in every direction,
you'd burn your eyeballs.
So...
For neutrinos,
is that
when neutrons separated
to protons?
A moment of
scattering from neutrinos
when the neutrons
and electrons...
No.
No,
I think it was earlier than that.
It was at the time when the
weak interaction was as strong as the
electromagnetic interaction,
which was
a good deal more energetic.
Yeah,
I don't think that's...
And the
gravitons even further back,
but they're even harder to see.
And what makes them
hard to see is the same thing which
allows them to get through this junk.
The reason they get through the junk
is because they're so weakly
interacting.
You can see
that sphere.
That's what
you see in the cosmic background radiation.
You see this sphere.
I'm talking about the neutrino sphere.
We do in fact see that sphere.
Oh yes,
yes,
yes.
Yes,
that is what you see when you see the
cosmic microwave background,
absolutely.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Yeah.
What does that
think about gravitons?
Why would there be a shell for gravitons?
What would be your take to gravitons?
Oh,
gravitons become strongly interacting
with each other when the energy gets high enough
and when the temperature gets high enough.
And what would be the distance
from the Big Bang
to that point?
The Planck distance.
10 to the minus 33 centimeters.
10 to the minus 42 seconds.
Well,
the point that I was raising though
was it's the same thing
which makes them
be able to get through this junk
which makes them hard to detect.
They're hard to detect
because everything is transparent
to them,
including the detectors.
Right.
Yeah.
If I understood correctly,
the surface of the sun
is where it seems to be
because that's the temperature
at which light becomes
opaque to light.
So that's why the sun
is the size it appears to be.
That's the temperature at which
the ionization
or which,
it's called recombination
where the atoms recombine.
Now,
why is it as sharp as it is?
The sun has a fairly sharp
edge when you look
at it.
And the
answer happens to be the exponential
behavior of the Boltzmann distribution.
I didn't want to get into that today.
But on that same subject,
when you talk about the temperature of a photon,
you're talking about the temperature
of a black body whose central,
whose peak radiation is that temperature.
Yeah.
But that is not linear in wavelength.
The temperature
is essentially the
energy of the
average photon.
The average energy,
the photon
has an energy which is one over its wavelength.
So yes,
the temperature is one over the wavelength
of the radiation.
No,
no,
no.
That's energy density.
That's not the energy of a single photon.
T to the fourth is either
the energy density or the
or the energy flux,
the luminosity.
Yeah.
T to the fourth is
a combination of the energy per photon
and the number of photons
per unit volume.
Okay.
So in order to find the energy density
of a black body,
you have to know the energy per photon
and the number of photons per unit volume.
The number of photons
per unit volume goes like
T cubed,
and the energy of a photon goes as T,
and that's what gives you T to the fourth
altogether.
Yeah.
How about the neutrinos
don't have any
intrinsic motion.
They move with very close
to the speed of light.
The photons,
you can't stop them,
so they're always going,
but aren't the neutrinos that are,
aren't they sort of attacked,
just go to,
if you had a box full of neutrinos,
doesn't that same,
why are they moving?
Our matter is not moving
relative to the boxes
that are growing
with the ray of the universe.
Photons move,
yes.
I'm talking about neutrinos.
Why do neutrinos move?
Well,
the first approximation,
they're massless,
so they're very much
like photons.
They have a teeny,
teeny,
teeny tiny mass.
So they're very high,
so you can't treat them...
Their energy is much larger than their mass.
You can't treat them like
like nanoparticles,
they have to be treated separately.
For practical purposes,
you can treat them as being like photons,
yeah.
A neutrino would have to
have a very,
very,
very low energy
in order for it to be moving
much slower than the speed of light.
So,
you know,
it's only recently,
it's only in the last several years
that people have really been able
to measure the mass of the neutrino
because it's so small.
And for all practical purposes,
not all practical purposes,
but for many practical purposes,
neutrinos just move like a ball.
They move at the speed of light.
So these original neutrinos
also are very cold in some sense or another.
No,
they were hot.
They were hot.
Now...
Now they're probably about a little bit colder
than the photons,
maybe two degrees.
But similar to the photons.
Do you know what time
after the Big Bang the scattering
for neutrinos...
I would have to say,
but it's microscopically small.
It's much smaller.
Yeah.
We'd have to do some work.
Is that why it's two degrees cooler?
Because that surface is farther out?
Well,
the surface is...
No,
it's cooler...
Yeah,
it decoupled earlier and...
Yeah.
And stuff happened
that was out of equilibrium
and heated the photons
and didn't heat the neutrinos.
So...
Nobody,
of course,
has ever measured the neutrinos.
People...
I believe estimate something like two degrees,
but it would be a little bit colder.
Yeah.
And how about dark matter?
Would that also...
Okay,
now we want to talk about dark matter.
Yeah,
let's talk about dark matter.
Alright.
Alright,
dark matter
was not discovered
by studying cosmology
because cosmology means,
you know,
the universe
as a whole.
Cosmology means
the study of things bigger than
a few billion light years.
Anything smaller than that
is astronomy.
And then they've invented this word...
If it's ugly astronomy,
ugly,
difficult astronomy,
meaning to say that
it's not neat and elegant
they call it gastronomy.
That's not my word.
Yeah.
Alright,
so...
The dark matter,
which certainly has
an important cosmological
consequence,
very important,
but it was not discovered
by cosmologists looking
at cosmology.
It was discovered
by...
by astronomers looking
at galaxies.
A galaxy is a small object
on the scale of the whole universe.
And measuring what are called
the rotation curves of the
galaxy.
The rotation curves
are simply the rate at which
things move around
the orbital velocity
of stars at different distances
from the center.
So let's
start with orbital velocity
and let's go all the ways
back to the solar system
just to get a handle on
orbital velocities.
The solar system or
any system which is
composed of a central mass
and an orbiting
one or more
orbiting
planets,
let's call them.
Alright.
Now,
what I'm interested in
the mass of the central
object is m.
The things orbiting around it are
going to be lighter.
And I want to know the velocity
of an orbiting object
as a function of its radius.
As a function of its distance
from the center.
The orbiting object
let's say the orbiting object
has a mass little m.
Okay.
Let's see if we can
work it out.
What we use is Newton's equations.
F equals m a.
And we're applying it
to the planet.
Alright.
What is the force
on the planet?
The force is due
to the sun at the center.
It doesn't have to be the sun,
just some central
object in some orbiting planetary
system.
The force
is m m
g divided
by r squared.
Right?
Where r is
the radius of the orbit.
That's the force and it's directed
radially inward.
That's equal
to the mass
times the acceleration.
So what we have
to know is the acceleration of
an object moving in a circular orbit.
I'm going to write
down the answer.
The acceleration of a
circular orbit is toward
the center.
It involves the velocity
and the radius.
Anybody know the formula?
V squared over r.
I am not going to prove that.
We're just going to check its dimensions.
What's
the dimensions of acceleration?
Dimensions of acceleration
are length per unit time
per unit time.
Length per unit time squared.
Velocity per
unit time is acceleration.
Velocity is length over time
per unit time.
Let's just
check that velocity squared
over r has the
same units.
Velocity
squared has length squared over
time squared.
And r has length.
So hopefully
these have the same units.
They do.
It's a true fact
that the acceleration of a circular
orbit is toward the center,
same
direction as the force,
and it's proportional to the
velocity squared,
equal to the velocity
squared divided by the radius
of the orbit.
So let's do some cancellation.
The little m's
cancel out,
which means
that the acceleration doesn't depend
on the mass of this object.
We can multiply
both sides by r.
And then we find that
the velocity
is equal to the square root
of mg
over r.
In particular,
the velocity of a distant
planet is smaller than the velocity
of a centrally
located planet.
The velocity of Neptune
or Pluto
is much smaller than the velocity.
Not just the angular
frequency,
but the actual velocity
falls off
as 1 over the square
root of r.
Now,
if you look at galaxies through a
telescope,
what you see,
of course,
is light.
And it was always believed
that the amount of light
coming from a region
was proportional
to the number of stars
in that region and so forth.
So it would be proportional
to the amount of mass
in that region.
And galaxies are mostly
cores,
the center.
And then,
there are these,
some galaxies are spiral
arm galaxies.
If you look at them from the
edge,
they look like that.
But most of the light
and most of the material,
the observable material,
the light matter,
light matter means the matter that you can see
because it glows,
because it gives off light,
most of it
is in the core of the galaxy.
So,
if you were to just
take literally that
mass follows light,
that the mass distribution is
comparable to the light distribution,
and look at stars
at different
distances out here,
they would mostly be moving in the field
of a central object
similar to the
center of a solar system.
If that were the case,
now we can also look down on this from above,
it's a core,
a very
diffuse bunch of stuff out here that doesn't
have much light coming out of it,
and we can,
everything moves around.
We can measure,
we can measure
the velocity of
stars in such
galaxies,
or we can measure the relative
velocity,
we can measure the overall velocity
of the receding galaxy,
these are relatively nearby galaxies,
we measure the overall
recessional velocity,
and then we measure the difference between
the velocity of this point and that point,
we discover that this point is moving
toward us,
this point is moving away from us,
and in that way,
compare it
with the overall velocity,
we can pretty well calculate
the velocity
of orbiting,
the orbital
velocity,
not calculate,
measure,
the orbital velocity of
stars as a function of the distance
from the center.
And what do we
find?
Not me,
but what
do the people who do this kind of work find?
They find that
the velocity does not
fall off like one over
the square root of r,
instead,
it's pretty constant.
The velocity
of,
not the angle of r,
it takes
longer to go around far away,
but that's because it's along a distance,
but the velocity of a
star over here
is about the same as the velocity of a
star over here,
is about the same
as the velocity of a star near the outer
edge of the galaxy.
So there's something wrong
with this picture of a galaxy,
that
it's mostly composed of matter near
the center.
So you can do something else,
and say,
wait a minute now,
let's see if we can figure out
where the matter
really is.
Maybe
mass doesn't follow
light.
Maybe the
light distribution is not a
good sampling of the mass.
So let's use what we do know about these
velocities,
to see what we can say
about how the mass is distributed.
Okay.
Now,
think of,
let's suppose now that the mass
is not concentrated at the center,
but it's distributed in some
way.
It's distributed
in some way,
and from simplicity,
let's say it's
distributed nice and symmetrically,
then
what mass should we be using
in here?
For a planet,
or not a planet,
for a star at distance r
from the center.
What mass should we be
using?
Well,
we should be using
all of the mass out
to a distance r.
Remember,
a planet
or a star moving at a certain radius
feels all the mass
inside that shell.
So we can correct this formula,
and we can say,
let's correct this formula,
and say the right
formula
is m of
r
times g.
m of r times g.
The meaning of
this m of r is
it's the amount of mass
in a sphere of radius
r.
So far we've not assumed anything
in particular about that distribution
of mass.
We've just assumed
that there's a notion,
a functional notion,
of the mass
within a sphere of radius r.
This formula
is very general.
Of course,
it also doesn't say anything.
You don't know what m of r is,
but you measure v.
But v,
you
discover,
is constant.
You discover
that all of these velocities are the same.
So what does that say about
m of r?
It grows linearly with r.
The amount of mass
out the distance r
is
proportional to r.
So the amount of mass
in a sphere of radius
r
apparently
grows like r.
What about the density
of mass?
Does that grow?
No,
we have
to divide by r cubed.
If we want the average
density of mass,
we would want to divide by r cubed.
No,
it doesn't mean
that it gets denser
and denser as you go out.
But it does mean
that there's a halo of mass
out there
which is more pronounced
that most of the mass
of the galaxy is far out
near the edges
and maybe even beyond
the visible galaxy.
Now you say,
okay,
we can use the velocity
to actually tell us
what m of r is.
We can figure out
using the velocities
we can tell what the mass
out to a given distance r is
and we can compare it.
Take the whole galaxy
out to its very extremities
we know what the mass
distribution is
just from the rotation
the rotational speed
of the stars
and we can say
how much mass is there altogether?
How much mass is there
in this hidden unobserved mass?
In the hidden unobserved mass
that does not follow light
that is not proportional
to the light
there's about 10 times
the mass that we would
normally associate
with stars
and luminous objects
that is the light of the galaxy.
In other words,
the estimate of just saying
that the galaxy is made up
of stars
or luminous matter
like stars
captures only about
a tenth of the mass
of the galaxy.
The galaxy is at least
10 times heavier.
That's only counting
the dark matter in the stars.
That's correct.
Yeah.
I think that
that's true
that's
that is true
I may be
I think what's true
is the total mass
that's expected to be
in a galaxy is about
10 times the mass
of the luminous matter.
It does of course fall off
when you go far enough away.
But you're right.
Out to the boundaries
it follows this dark matter curve
and I believe the total mass
of a galaxy is roughly
about 10 times what you see
with light.
Is that right?
I think it's approximately
What?
No,
dark energy is about
30%.
Dark energy
is about 4%.
Dark matter
is 30 or 40.
10 to 1.
10 to 1 is about to work.
Right.
Dark matter
luminous matter
is what about 4% of the whole?
And
the dark matter is probably
another 30%.
So it's something like a factor
10 or 7 or something like that.
4 times 7 is 28.
Yeah.
But for some galaxies there's evidence
that a lot of the dark matter is beyond
the galaxy.
Yeah,
but I think the total amount
of it is about 10 times the mass
of a galaxy.
Total amount.
But some of it extends out beyond the galaxies.
I'm not an expert at this incidentally.
It looks like the density
would sort of go 1 over r squared.
Do they have a reason for that?
Let's see.
This is not something
that's
subject to anything
except simulations
and simulations
account for some of it,
but I don't know how much.
Are these ratios true for all galaxies
and galaxy-like structures?
Say that again?
Variationally.
Some galaxies.
Yeah,
I think for all big galaxies.
Yeah.
It's pretty much the same.
We can calculate what the density is.
Let's see.
The density is such.
Here's the row,
which is the
density
Let's do it a little bit better.
Rho of r squared.
Now if you integrate
rho of r
Now what do we have to integrate it with
to find the mass
within a shell?
4 pi r squared.
In particular
r squared dr,
right?
And
you're right,
4 pi.
I don't care about the 4 pi.
This is the thing which
is equal
to 1
You integrate it from 0
to capital R
and this is the total
matter,
the total mass
within radius r
and this is the thing which grows as r.
Okay.
So
how would you solve this equation?
Yes.
Well,
we can differentiate
We can differentiate
both sides of it with respect to r.
What happens when we differentiate an integral
with respect to r?
You just get the integrand,
right?
So we get rho of r
r squared
is equal to 1.
Rho of r
looks like 1 over r squared.
Rho of r is 1 over r squared.
But
there's a lot of matter out there
and
about 10 times what's in the galaxies.
What do we know about it?
It doesn't shine.
So that's one thing.
It doesn't produce light.
Another thing
we know about it is
it didn't contract.
It's a much bigger halo
than the size of the galaxy.
The galaxy is a fairly small thing
embedded in a big halo
of this dark matter.
The dark matter is in a form
of a spherical halo
even if the galaxy
is in the form of a
disk galaxy of some sort.
At least that's expected
and I think even observed.
So
it's a big
globular blob
of mass
that has not contracted
together with the
with the
luminous matter
to form a smaller,
more concentrated
thing.
What is it that causes
the
contraction
of a bunch of gas
to a smaller
hmm?
Lower the temperature?
No,
no,
no.
It shrinks.
When it shrinks,
the temperature goes up.
That's why stars form.
When it shrinks,
the star goes up.
It's a kind of friction,
dissipation of some sort or another.
Some form of dissipation,
some sort of collisions,
some sort of friction
is the thing which
causes...
If you just started
with a ball of gas
and the gas is going back and forth
and back and forth,
oscillating,
some of it's going around in a circle,
nothing much happens to it.
It just stays about that size.
It shrinks because of collisions
and because of radiation.
It radiates away energy.
And
interesting kinds of collisions
and processes have to happen
in order to cause it to shrink.
Well,
ordinary matter has plenty of different kinds
of processes.
In particular,
it radiates light.
And the radiation of
light causes it to collapse.
And other kinds of
processes,
collisions between
atoms and so forth.
Whatever this stuff is out there,
it's very collisionless.
And it doesn't radiate light.
So it's very weakly interacting.
Somehow.
It doesn't do very much
other than gravitate.
Wouldn't that make it unstable?
An unstable structure?
No.
What keeps it out there?
Kinetic energy.
Okay?
What keeps
the Earth
going around the Sun?
Why doesn't the Earth fall into the Sun?
Because there's no friction.
No friction.
Right.
But there's a little bit of friction,
so the Earth is slowly
falling into the Sun.
And at one time there was more friction,
which caused the primordial gas cloud
to coalesce and condense into things.
Uh...
So whatever this stuff is
out there,
it has a lot less friction
than other matter.
Yeah?
Is this a torus at a distance,
or
is it a spherical shell?
No,
it's not a shell.
It's a sphere,
but whose density goes down like
one over r squared.
And so it's a
sphere,
it's not a torus.
It's a sphere.
Not a torus.
Taurus would be very hard to...
No,
it's not a torus,
it's a sphere.
Large spherical blob.
Yeah?
A question from the possibility of
intergalactic dark matter
or dark galaxies.
Dark galaxies.
You mean just a blob
of dark matter.
Yeah,
I mean it would gravitate,
so...
Yeah.
How do you think it's not neutrinos?
Uh,
neutrinos
just wouldn't behave that way.
They're moving too fast.
So these are pretty slow particles.
Mm-hmm.
These are slow.
Is it a sphere or is it a ball?
A ball.
Well,
it's not a uniform ball.
A ball,
yeah.
A ball which is more
dense in the center,
but the density doesn't
suddenly fall off like the light does.
It gradually falls off.
Oh,
a question.
One more time.
How do we know that
there's dark matter outside the luminous
stars you see going around?
You can measure
the velocity of the
different arms of the galaxy
and say how much matters
inside
that.
I don't know.
But you can,
yeah,
you can tell,
you can roughly estimate the mass of a galaxy
by looking at the motion of other galaxies
in the vicinity of the galaxy.
So,
uh...
What's that?
Colliding galaxies.
But just the motion
of the,
I don't know,
I suppose the motion of the Magellanic clouds
and things like that,
they tell you something
about the total mass or the...
So,
um,
it must
be the motion,
the relative motion of
nearby galaxies
which give you some hint at what
the total mass of the galaxy is.
The black hole would not be coming
if there's dark matter,
is that...
No,
no,
no.
Dark matter's
very definitely collapsed.
You mean,
could it
be a bunch of
black holes?
Uh...
People have
talked about that,
and I think the general conclusion is no.
Um...
But I'm
not really sure exactly why.
There would be lenses...
Wouldn't there be lenses
if a massive thing...
There'd be lens...
Yes,
there'd be lensing,
but also
if those black holes originated
from ordinary matter,
it would say that in the primordial universe
before those black holes formed,
there was a
lot,
lot more ordinary matter
out there,
and that would be
deadly for nucleosynthesis and,
uh,
and,
the,
uh,
the origin of the elements.
So,
uh,
the best bet,
I think,
I think the best bet
by far is just that there are elementary particles
which are very weakly interacting.
Um...
Galaxies seem to have net angular velocity.
Oh,
absolutely.
Um...
But they're not as flat...
They're not...
The,
uh,
the dark matter is not
as flattened as,
uh,
as the galactic plane would indicate.
But presumably they have the same
net angular...
Not necessarily.
No,
I don't think so.
I don't think that's...
And where does the angular velocity come from?
Of the,
uh...
Well,
I mean,
you know,
the angular...
the angular velocity of
the solar system is not the same
as the angular velocity of the sun.
In fact,
the angular velocity of the solar system
is not exactly well defined.
Is not what?
Um...
Not exactly...
Oh,
oh.
Um...
Yeah,
yeah.
Good.
Yeah,
I would say
that the angular...
I don't know...
I don't know what's known about the
rotational motion of the halo.
I don't know.
The dark matter halo.
That's a good question...
It would be hard to...
It would be hard to
tell anything about it at all,
really.
Yeah.
I don't know the answer whether anything
is known about the rotational motion
of the halo.
What is the...
Decreasing energy?
What's that?
Is the dark matter
decreasing energy?
Decreasing
energy in what sense?
In the dark matter.
The energy is decreasing.
Decreasing with respect
to what?
Time?
As a function of time.
Uh...
Why would it
be decreasing?
It's pretty much staying the same.
It's not changing
very much.
Because it doesn't interact with anything.
It doesn't interact with anything.
Yeah.
It doesn't lose
kinetic energy or anything.
What about dark energy?
How does that...
We haven't...
That's another
question.
We haven't come to that.
We can...
When you're estimating the ordinary matter
in a galaxy,
if you add up all the
planets and the Oort cloud and the Kuiper belt
and all that stuff in a solar system,
how big a fraction of that is
the total mass of
a solar system?
Negligent?
I think it's pretty small.
Yeah.
Very small.
Uh...
The solar system is mostly
the sun.
Yeah.
From the point of view
of conservation of angular momentum
from the Big Bang,
it seems like
if there wasn't any net angular
momentum of that initial mass and you have
different galaxies,
they would net
out to have...
to not have a greater
angular momentum.
So...
Does that come into play with
also the net angular momentum
of...
Are you asking whether the
angular momentum of galaxies
shows some alignment?
Is that what you're asking?
Well,
I mean,
they all couldn't be spinning
clockwise from look at one direction.
They sure are.
I would have...
Somebody would have noticed.
Right,
right.
But from that point of view,
would that...
Can you conclude anything about the
angular momentum of these dark matter
clouds that they would also have to balance
to...
I don't think...
Well,
I think you...
I think it's pretty,
uh...
pretty darn certain that they average out on the
average,
but whether the angular
velocity of...
whether...
I think the question was
is there some locking which locks
the,
uh...
the
visible galaxy to the halo.
Right.
I think that was
the question.
I don't know.
Presumably the angular...
I will try to find out.
I don't know.
Presumably the angular velocity
of the...
the,
uh...
galaxy came from something that
happened in the early universe.
You would think at least they...
You would think at least
they probably point in the same...
same direction,
the angular velocity.
The angular velocity.
It would spin up the,
uh...
But even that I don't know.
And I
don't know if it's measured.
It's a good question.
I really don't know
the answer.
We don't know if it's dependent
on dark matter...
What's that?
If dark matter is found dependent on...
light matter,
uh...
or...
Well,
it seems like the dark matter
is more the primordial
thing that,
uh...
that coalesced.
Um...
It was probably the first thing to start
uh...
coalescing
into well-defined structures.
And the ordinary matter
probably followed it,
got trapped
by it,
but then the
friction of the ordinary matter
and collisions
caused it to sort of continue
to shrink,
while
the dark matter being largely
transparent to itself
didn't shrink,
except...
The only thing that affects the dark matter
is gravity.
Gravity
is enough to cause it to condense
and start to shrink and start to...
So its only common denominator is gravity.
What's that?
Its only common denominator
between the light and the...
Yeah.
Yeah,
that's the only serious interaction
between them.
Well,
then where did all the kinetic
energy come from that keeps
it from collapsing and doesn't interact?
Except for gravity.
You said
kinetic energy is keeping it from
collapsing.
Where did that energy
come from?
From potential energy.
It originally started...
It originally started with
a pretty uniform distribution,
but
don't think of it as a uniform distribution.
Just think of it as
very large,
diffuse
blobs of gas.
Very,
very large and very diffuse.
And they did...
Gravity pulled them together.
Gravity caused them to contract.
And they contracted some.
And in the process of contracting,
potential energy got converted
to...
Is it the case...
I just had a question here about the mechanics.
Is it the case if you have
particles that don't interact except
gravitationally and they're in a disk,
it's unstable and it must evolve to a...
I think...
I suspect the disk is unstable.
So it has to evolve to a
a...
Well,
radially varying,
but other than that,
a...
Yeah.
Now how the
globular structure
manages to stabilize
the disk-like structure in it,
that I don't know.
Maybe related to polarity?
To what?
To the polarity?
The uniform polarity within
the galaxy or something?
What does
polarity mean?
Well,
it's...
The polarity of magnetic polarity.
Oh,
it doesn't have to do with magnetic fields.
It doesn't have to do with magnetic fields.
I don't think.
I don't think so.
Even that I don't know
for sure.
This is really the subject
of people who
do large-scale simulations.
Is there less friction in a disk
than there is in
more random orbits?
Because if they're rotating
a disk,
they run into each other
much less often than
they do if all the orbits
are going...
Oh,
wildly haywire.
Every which way.
Yeah,
I'm sure that's true.
So it would seem to be that
there's some chance that
a dissipated process would lead
to
a disk-like structure.
Well,
it certainly did in the solar system.
And around Saturn and...
So I don't know.
I'm beyond my
pay grade now.
I'm not enough...
I'm not enough of a gastrophysicist
to know the answer to these questions.
How do they...
How do they get an estimate
for the amount of dark matter
between the galaxies?
Well,
I think from the relative motion
of galaxies.
The relative motion of the galaxies themselves
is sensitive to the material between them.
Is there much dark matter?
I thought that most of the dark matter
was right around the galaxies.
There wasn't much of it.
Well,
it's spread out something like
like this.
And how far that goes out,
does it continue like that
until you get to the next galaxy,
sort of?
Or does it
tail off and then a
flat region in between?
I don't know the answer.
Uh...
Let's see.
A galaxy is...
How big is the galaxy?
100,000 light years,
right?
Something like 100,000 light years.
And the distance to the next galaxy is about...
a million light years.
Two million light years.
Something like that.
So,
uh...
Uh...
Basically,
the dark matter within the clusters
of galaxies has
no uniform distribution.
It's like clouds in the sky.
There's more dense and less dense regions.
Yeah.
And it's...
It's disturbed by the progression
of the galaxy,
the motion of the galaxies,
within the cluster.
The point being what?
Well,
they've mapped out
the density,
the relative density
of the dark matter
within the clusters.
And they show these clouds
of stuff that's kind of random in nature,
which says that
the galaxies collect it
and it goes by the one over r squared.
But that either
increases or decreases
when they pass through each other.
Oh,
that's for sure.
But,
you know,
how it's distributed
in the region,
you know,
halfway between the galaxies,
I don't know.
Getting back to the single galaxy model
that you have up there,
most galaxies have a supermassive
black hole or black hole...
But that's a very small fraction
of the mass of the core.
Is there any way we can
analyze
dark matter in that
perspective in terms of
the black hole?
I think the dark matter
is so diffuse and spread out
over such a large distance
that I don't think it...
Black hole is a tiny little
thing at the core,
so I don't think so.
On a micro scale,
is there any interesting measurements
within the solar system
using planetary motion
to set any kind of limit?
On dark matter?
Yeah.
There are limits.
There are various kinds of limits
on the nature of the particles,
which might be the dark matter particles.
But I mean,
just by looking at
motion of the...
I don't know how accurately
measuring the motion of the planets,
but we can see general relativity,
but I wonder if you can see...
You mean,
is the dark matter appreciably
affecting the gravity of the solar system?
I don't think so.
No.
What sort of experiments are they...
I mean,
how do they...if they don't interact
What sort of experiments are they putting up
to try to detect the particles?
Well,
when you say they don't interact,
I mean...
Or maybe they just interact for a week,
what do you mean?
Yeah,
I mean,
if an electron passes
through a lump of lead,
it will interact with a lump of lead
every single time.
If a dark matter particle passes
through a lump of lead,
it may interact with the lump of lead
one out of 10 to the 13th times
or something.
Well,
you just let 10 to the
13th dark matter particles pass through,
and that's all of them.
So you just use the statistics of large numbers.
And,
you know,
there are lots of detection
schemes that are out
in place there,
searching for dark matter.
Thus far,
they're always out of the range
of detectability.
Wouldn't there be a signature of dark matter
infalling towards a black hole
to that horizon?
Well,
it's too diffuse.
It's very diffuse.
Is there any reason to believe that
dark matter is essentially
in circular orbits?
I mean,
again,
you'd have to get to some
dissipation point.
No,
I don't think there's any reason to believe
it's in circular orbits.
It's probably not in circular orbits.
I don't think there's any reason to believe it.
So there could be some very
highly elliptical orbits.
Yeah,
there's probably things like that.
So they could,
some of the dark matter could,
in fact,
just by accident,
run into the
black hole,
etc.
Sure,
but it's very diffuse.
So extremely elliptic orbits
are eliminated by the black hole at the center.
But the black hole is a tiny,
tiny,
tiny
little geometric object
at the center of the galaxy.
So you're eliminating
very,
very little bit that way.
Yeah,
no,
I think there's no reason
to believe that the orbits are circular.
The orbits,
the orbits are probably all over the place.
Some circular,
some elliptical,
some,
you know,
some very elongated.
Some of them just going back and forth,
except not hitting the...
And they'd be deflected by a neutron star
and every other mass as well.
They'd be deflected by everything.
It's all stirred up.
They'll pass through the
they'll pass through the
the
planets and
the stars and
presumably.
Yeah,
they pass
through most things.
I don't know if they pass through a neutron star,
but they probably
pass through the Earth very easily.
Right.
If you had
some sort of statistical
probability distribution on the types
of orbits,
then you could probably get
the rho of r as one over r squared,
maybe?
Or the rho of r would be...
No,
I
don't think there's any
easy way to get the one over r squared.
I don't believe there is.
For that,
that's equivalent to
knowledge of the distribution of energies
and
it doesn't fit anything simple.
It's not a Boltzmann distribution.
So I don't think there's any simple way.
As far as I know,
it is not known
exactly why the
distribution is what it is.
Now there's lots and lots and lots of
simulations,
and I don't know what the state of
the art is.
With gravitational lensing
diffuse,
you could try and measure it that way.
If it's a significant portion of the mass,
you'd have like twice the lensing effect
when you're trying to
image galaxies
behind it or around it or something like that.
Oh yeah,
you can...
Yes,
the lensing
due to galaxies is sensitive
to the...
Is that what you're saying?
It's sensitive to the mass?
Absolutely.
You'd have like a relative effect
if you took a look at the
optical mass or
radiation and then
it would be significantly larger.
So dark matter causes lensing.
It does?
Oh yeah.
Dark matter is part of the mass which
causes lensing.
So it's...
Is there
something to suggest in observation
that by way of lensing
you can discern the
distribution of dark matter?
I'm sure there is,
but I'm not an expert at it.
But I'm sure there is.
I mean that's
a very obvious thing to try to do
is to map out
the dark matter
by lensing.
There was an article
where they looked at galaxies
that were colliding.
And based...
Because the
visible matter interacts with
those stars...
populations of stars interact,
um...
you get
basically two hypotheses
about how the lensing
and
the evidence seems to be
that there's
a...
I guess a different
lensing effect
because the
dark matter doesn't interact
in the same way.
Are you talking about the bullet galaxy?
Yeah.
The bullet cluster is a
pair of galactic clusters that are interacting.
The gas on the inside
which is regular matter
is not when it's seen in X-rays.
And then you can measure the distribution
of the total matter by looking at gravity.
So you get a distribution of
gravitational lensing.
So you get a distribution of total matter
and a distribution of normal matter.
And what's left over is assumed to be dark matter.
The point is that
when the two galaxies collided
the ordinary material
interacted in a significant way.
The dark matter clouds
just interacted gravitationally
and was not such a significant interaction.
And the result was a separation
of dark matter from
the light.
And so
there's an example
The controversy had to do
with whether there really was dark matter
or whether Newton's
or Einstein's
gravitational theory
had to be modified.
You could try to
fit the rotation curves
of galaxies by modifying
Newton's force law.
We got it from Newton's force law.
Where is it?
Over here.
By modifying Newton's force law
And in that picture
there really wouldn't be dark matter
or the gravitating effect
would be modified
but it would still be attached
to the same masses.
It would be quite clear
that that would not be
a good description
if it was possible
to separate dark matter
from the ordinary matter.
And apparently
in this bullet class
we have a very good
idea of how dark matter
this is a bullet cluster
two galaxies collided
and the effect was a separation
of the dark matter
from the luminous matter
and so that kind of settled
the controversy of whether
there is dark matter
or whether it's simply
a modification of Newton's law.
Is the luminous matter
Any way that you can see it
optically,
any way that
you can see it electromagnetically
but yeah I think in first approximation
yes it was the visible light
the visible light
for the most part
So they used really
three new telescopes
to look at the same object
Yeah
But the original hypothesis
was that light
that mass followed light
that the luminosity
was a good measure
of the
abundance of mass
But that matter may emit
in a different field
in a different region
Well I think we would have
noticed if it emitted
any appreciable amount
of radiation into other
Now it's possible
that dark matter for example
annihilates and creates
gamma rays
Right,
sure
But that you wouldn't see
through ordinary telescopes
You'd see it in particle detectors
Right,
good
There must be a continuity
between dark matter and visible matter
Continuity
Well there seem to be
two very different things
They don't seem to be
Very little is known
What I would say about dark matter
is very little is known
in detail about what it is
But it's entirely consistent
It doesn't require any
radical modifications
of the rules
That there are more particles
than have yet been discovered
I think we all believe
We've probably just touched
the surface of all of the
particles that exist
And that there are particles
which can be very weakly interacting
Neutrinos as was mentioned
And so without doing any radical damage
to any of the principles of physics
we can easily accommodate dark matter
by just saying it's particles
that we haven't discovered yet
Well that sounds funny
but it's probably what it is
It gives every indication
of not being anything radically different
And since we're talking about
everybody and his brother
has postulated a particle
for one reason or another
and often for very very good reasons
There are probably more particles
Many of them weakly interacting
And it's probably what they are
If not,
not
Wasn't there a thought
that there's a lot of hydrogen
you can't see
unionized hydrogen
that kind of made up this mass
There was a time when people
thought that it might be just hydrogen
There was a time
Nobody thinks that anymore
And I think at least one of the reasons
is because the amount of it
is so large
that it would have radically affected
the creation of helium
and the early universe
and radically affected the nuclear physics
of the first three minutes
in some really awkward way
So it's
There's just too much of it
to fit into any
When we talk about nucleosynthesis
there's too much of it
And is there or not
any evidence that dark matter
has either electrical
or magnetic properties
Well the evidence is it doesn't have very much
They're not
Yeah
They're probably neutral
They certainly don't have any significant
electric charge
The standard model
has no
We'll talk to the
Standard model does not have particles of this type
The supersymmetric
standard model has a thousand of them
all over the place
So
Sometimes
people regard this as
evidence
or weak evidence of
supersymmetry
That's a bit of a stretch
but it could be
But there's a lot of good reasons
really sensible reasons
for thinking that there are more particles
and so
the dark matter could be
any one of them
It could be a combination of them
I think we'll find out
I think that's not
not out of the question
to find out in the next ten years