This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Somebody asked me some questions
which I thought were good questions,
so I asked them to
write them down and list them.
One,
and I thought I would answer them
in class because other people might be interested.
One,
does the apparent wavelength of the cosmic
radiation depend on the motion of the observer,
i.e.,
is there a Doppler effect?
If so,
doesn't that mean there is a preferred frame,
the one in which the wavelength
is the same in all directions,
neglecting the small fluctuations?
All right,
so the question is,
it's a good question,
it's a right question,
and the answer is yes
to almost all parts of it,
except where the...
The author of the question realized
that the answer must be no.
All right,
so there's a lot of matter around,
and also photons all over the place.
And the photons are isotropic.
What does that mean?
The typical energy of a photon coming from
the left is more or less the same as...
Not more or less,
it's about the same as the typical
energy of a photon coming from the right.
The temperature of the photons is pretty well
described by the average energy of the photons.
And so if we're way,
way out in outer space,
into galactic space,
and I'm not talking about the photons
that come from the sun or from stars,
I'm talking about the cosmic microwave background,
that which is there when everything else is removed.
So to speak.
Those photons appear to be isotropic.
They come at you from every
direction with about the same energy.
But then that means something a little puzzling.
Not too puzzling,
but a little bit puzzling.
If you are moving through this mess of stuff,
including photons,
mainly photons,
and you are moving through it,
let's say,
to the right with a large velocity,
large means comparable to the speed of light,
or some fraction of the speed of light,
then because of the Doppler effect,
you would see the photons coming
from this direction as having shorter wavelength,
meaning somewhat bluer than the
photons coming from the other direction.
Yes,
somewhat bluer.
Meaning to say that you would have
a bias in directions in the sky,
where in some directions you would see hotter photons,
higher energy photons,
and in other directions you would see lower energy photons.
Yes,
this is true.
That is really the way it works.
We are moving through the microwave background,
our planet,
moving with the solar system rotation,
with the galactic rotation,
and with the motion of the
galaxy and the clusters of galaxies,
and in fact,
when we look at the
microwave temperature in different directions,
it is not the same in all directions.
One direction is preferred.
I couldn't tell you which it is offhand.
I mean,
you know,
I don't remember.
But it has got to do
with known motions of the Earth.
And so the answer is yes,
there is such a Doppler effect,
and yes,
there is a preferred frame of reference.
The preferred frame of reference is the one,
where the microwave background
looks isotropic from all directions.
It happens to be,
and this is the key point,
it is the same preferred frame of reference
as defined by the galaxies themselves on the average.
The galaxies are at rest at any particular place,
any particular place,
the local galaxies are on the average
at rest in some frame of reference.
That's a preferred frame of reference.
And it is the same preferred frame of
reference that the cosmic microwave background is isotropic.
So that's the answer to question number one.
Yes,
there is a special frame of reference.
If not,
that's even harder to understand.
Yeah,
fortunately we don't have to get
into that part of the question.
Next question.
Is there anything in relativity
to limit the relative velocity?
Or can two coordinate points,
let's just call them galaxies,
can two galaxies have a relative velocity greater than c,
greater than the speed of light?
The answer is yes.
If they're far enough apart,
this is just the Hubble law,
and the Hubble law holds on distances which are much,
which may be arbitrarily large,
we don't know for sure,
but there's nothing wrong with extending
the Hubble law out to distances
such that velocity is equal to Hubble times distance.
If space is as flat as it appears to be,
and it does appear to be flat,
then there's no obvious bound,
certainly nothing within observation,
no obvious bound on distances.
If distance is big enough,
then the velocity,
the relative velocity of us,
to some distant galaxy will exceed the speed of light.
Can't do anything about it,
it's true.
Einstein never said that that was impossible.
Let's put it this way,
what he would say was impossible
is for one thing to pass
another right in front of your nose
at faster than the speed of light.
It doesn't say anything about very
distant things moving relative to each other
where they're greater than the speed of light.
But of course,
if something is moving faster than
the speed of light away from you,
and assuming that it continues to do that,
then it can never send a message to you,
because if it's moving away from you
with faster than the speed of light,
then light rays which are sent to the left
and light waves which are sent to the right
will be both swept along with the
motion and effectively be moving away from you.
So...
There is no such cosmic limitation on whether
distant things can be moving away from you.
The place where they're moving with the speed
of light relative to you is a horizon.
Yeah?
Wouldn't the light ray sent
in the reverse direction be backward?
Right,
yeah.
Wouldn't that still be traveling at sea towards you,
but stretched in wavelength to
where it is no longer light?
It's actually moving away from you.
Well,
let's put it this way.
Let's put it this way.
Okay,
the light ray is moving that way,
but space is growing faster
than the light ray can overcome.
Okay?
So,
there's a model for this which I like.
It's a model which I
invented in order to explain inflation.
But let me explain what the model is.
Okay.
Imagine you have a line.
And now you start stretching the line.
The line is made up out of atoms.
Okay?
And now you start stretching it.
What happens?
Eventually it'll break because the distance between the atoms
will grow larger than the atomic forces can handle.
But we also have secretly a source of extra atoms.
And every time two atoms get
further apart than a certain distance,
we put another one in.
Everywhere that it happens,
everywhere that it happens,
we keep filling it up with more and more atoms,
so that the line,
yeah,
so that the line continues to grow,
constantly being resupplied with atoms.
Okay?
Now,
it's not atoms really that we want to think about,
but it's a good model for it.
Then,
this line will grow,
first of all,
according to Hubble's law.
It will also grow exponentially.
The distance between any two points will grow exponentially.
And there will be some distance beyond which
two things will be receding with
greater than the speed of light.
But if you go to those places,
you can ask,
supposing here's where the velocity of separation
gets to be about the speed of light,
if you go to the left
and you send a light beam,
you can still certainly send a light beam this way,
and you can send a light beam that way.
The only problem is the
atoms are filling in so fast
that the distance between you and
where the light ray has gotten to
is growing faster than the light ray can overcome.
Can I ask you a question?
Yeah.
Does the ordinary,
does the relativistic form like this,
in order for the addition of velocities hold?
Locally,
at a point,
yes.
In other words,
if we have two observers,
three observers,
and they all pass each other,
one after another after another...
But it only holds in that,
but it doesn't hold in the
case of velocities exceeding the speed.
Yeah,
that's right.
You have to go back to the first principles again.
There you have to use some more fancy geometric...
If you have two photons
that are radiated from a point,
their separation velocity is 2c.
Yes.
As seen by you.
Yeah,
but you could send something out with three
quarters of the speed of light that way,
and three quarters of the
speed of light the other way,
and their relative separation to you will seem to
be one and a half times the speed of light,
but to one of them looking at the other,
uh-uh,
it looks less than the speed of light.
So this is different.
And a photon itself doesn't have an inertial reference rate.
Well,
it's moving with the speed of light.
So,
the point is you can't answer questions
like this just using ordinary special relativity.
You have to use general relativity,
and general relativity allows the metric of space to expand.
When the metric of space is expanding,
that's very much like this picture where
molecules are filling in the gaps in between.
For example,
if this were an ordinary line of atoms,
there would be a maximum velocity on it.
What would that maximum,
an ordinary maximum velocity,
the speed of sound on the,
uh,
or the speed of,
waves which vibrate on the,
uh,
on the string here.
Uh,
we could take it to be the speed of sound.
Ordinary,
ordinary signals sent back and forth by elastic vibrations,
or sound waves and so forth,
also have a limiting velocity.
As long as you're not stretching the string
and filling it in and filling it in,
then no signal,
other than a supersonic signal,
no signal which is restricted to be moving
slower than the speed of sound for some reason,
uh,
I forgot to say,
no signal which is moving slower than the
speed of sound can exceed the speed of sound.
That's a true,
that's a true statement.
But now,
but now,
imagine this thing is being filled
in in the way that I described.
What is the rule?
The rule is that the sound
waves relative to the local molecules
can't exceed the speed of sound.
That's gonna be our rule,
right?
The sound waves themselves propagating
from one molecule to the next
move through this material,
with the speed of sound,
and let's also suppose that nothing else can move faster.
Nevertheless,
if the string is big enough and long enough,
distant parts of it will be moving away fast enough
that they'll be moving away faster from you.
Just because more and more is filling in,
it's filling in so fast and
so much of it is filling in,
that a point sufficiently far away
will be moving away
in a way that sound
cannot get back to this point.
It tries to get back to that point.
It moves in this direction,
but by the time it's
moved one meter in this direction,
more than a meter's worth
of new molecules have been inserted.
All right,
so general relativity,
which allows space to behave in this way,
does allow objects
to exceed the speed of sound,
or speed of light,
excuse me,
in this sense.
But not relative to the local observers.
So no observer over here
can see a sound wave going past him
with,
faster than the speed of sound.
Are you saying that recession is a kind of drag?
It is what it is.
Uh,
no.
The stretching of the wavelengths
due to the expansion,
does that do something?
Is it due solely to expansion,
or is there another element to it?
It's solely due to the expansion,
but it's not distinct from the Doppler effect.
It's the same effect.
You can solely think of it,
if you want a simple way to think about it,
just think about it as being due to the expansion.
So a wave on here,
when the system expands,
the wave expands with it.
That's the simplest way to think about it.
Is that statement you just made,
is that theoretical,
is that just an empirical statement,
or is that just some sort of statement?
That the wave stretches as the universe stretches?
No,
it's a theoretical statement
based on the general theory of relativity
combined with the theory of waves
propagating in an expanding space.
No.
It is part of the mathematics
of the general theory of relativity,
of expanding space-time.
If you write a wave equation
in a geometry which is expanding,
you will find the waves expand.
So it's not an...
Is it an empirical fact?
Well,
yes,
but not in the sense
that we can actually expand space
and see the wavelength expanding.
It's an empirical fact,
an astronomical fact,
but it's also a deeply theoretical fact
that would be very,
very surprising
if it were false.
This idea is predicated on the idea
that atoms fill in the blanks as a script.
Is that what's really happening out in the cosmos?
No,
it's not atoms.
Little bits of space.
Little bits of newly formed space.
That's one way to think about it.
The other way to think about it
is just through the equations
of general relativity
in which there is an expanding metric.
This is the expansion factor,
the scale factor.
And the expansion of the scale factor
just produces more and more space.
If you like a model for it,
people like models,
is it like expanding space
and building a rubber band?
No,
because rubber bands have this habit
of thinning out when you stretch them.
And let's forget whether they break.
Somebody living in that rubber band
would notice the fact that with time
the interaction between neighboring atoms changes.
He would notice with time
the properties of the space that he lives in changing.
That's not the way general relativity works.
It works more like the situation
where there's a hidden reservoir of points
that you can keep inserting
so that as time goes on
the properties that one ascribes
to a region of space don't change.
Space doesn't thin out in that sense.
That's the way the mathematics works.
This actually would be very,
very useful.
Exactly these equations would be rather useful
in describing a line of atoms
if you really did insert more and more atoms.
They would be described by those equations.
Anyway,
let's see.
Did we finish the questions?
Yeah,
okay.
Allison Bob,
from the first lecture,
is there a relationship between the relative velocity
exceeding C and the surface of life
and the last scattering
and the size of the observable universe?
In other words,
coming back to this question
of,
here I suppose is Bob,
Alice is moving outward.
Well,
according to the Hubble law,
there is some distance out there
Here's Bob.
There's some distance out there
where things are just moving away from him
faster than the speed of light
and he can't get signals from them.
Alice,
let me get the question again.
Is there a relationship between the relative velocity
exceeding C and the surface of life scattering?
Yeah.
So there's some distance.
When Alice is beyond that distance,
her light waves cannot get back to Bob.
That's called a horizon.
We're going to have more to do with a horizon,
but that's just called a cosmic horizon.
And if space is expanding in the right way,
then that cosmic horizon has a fixed size
and it just sits there
and Bob is surrounded by it
and anything out beyond that horizon
is just invisible to him
because the light can't get back.
Now,
that distance is the place
where the Hubble law says
that distance d
is the place where the Hubble law says
that the velocity of recession
becomes equal to the speed of light.
It is not quite the place
where the surface of life scattering is.
The surface of life scattering is slightly in.
Slightly in.
It is the place where if a light ray
was emitted from that place,
by the time it got to us,
its wavelength would have been infinitely stretched.
That's what the horizon is.
Any light ray emitted from the horizon
by the time it would get to us,
why would it be infinitely stretched?
Well,
the reason is fairly simple.
A light ray emitted from very close to that point
takes a very,
very long time to get to us.
If it takes a long time,
then the amount of stretching that it undergoes
is enormous.
But the other way to think about it
is Doppler shift.
Anything that's moving away from us
with close to the speed of light
will emit Doppler shifted radiation
that we'll see stretched.
So things coming from the horizon,
that's the place where things are infinitely stretched.
That is what the horizon is.
The horizon is not quite
the surface of life scattering.
How do we know that?
Well,
the light from the surface of life scattering
is very close to the horizon.
We see it.
It is not infinitely.
We don't see it with our eyeballs.
We see it with infrared detectors.
It's not infinitely redshifted.
In fact,
it's redshifted by about a factor of a thousand.
It's a thousand times longer wavelength
by the time that it gets to us,
we discussed this,
than it was when it was emitted.
A thousand is a big number.
To the extent that a thousand is a big number,
the surface of life scattering
is very close to the horizon.
Where the redshift factor would be infinite.
So,
for many practical purposes,
the surface of life scattering
is at the horizon,
or close enough to it.
Yes,
that does define the size of the observable universe.
That's exactly what the observable universe is.
It's a portion of the universe
that light can reach us from.
So it's the portion of the universe
within our cosmic horizon.
In a box,
let's say,
there's a long wavelength that can happen,
I think it's half the distance or whatever.
Could you extend that to the universe?
No,
you see,
not really.
Here,
imagine this again.
There's nothing to forbid you
from having an arbitrarily long wave
embedded in this thing here
that's even larger than the horizon.
It's not like being in a box.
Not quite like being in a box.
So,
a little bit different.
Okay,
let's see,
is there any last question?
Yes,
that's right.
Distant galaxies
will someday pass beyond the horizon.
And will...
Not only distant galaxies,
even relatively close galaxies
will pass behind the horizon.
That was my question.
The d in that,
since h is going to be
a function of time,
is d getting shorter?
Oh,
okay,
we'll come to that.
I said h in principle
can be a function of time,
and it is a function of time.
What we know about the universe today,
if it continues the way it's going,
is h is asymptotically going to a constant.
So at late times,
you can think of h as a constant.
That's the accelerated expansion,
which we're going to come to today.
h is tending toward a constant.
So then d will fix that.
That's right.
So,
once h becomes a constant,
then this becomes a relationship
between distance and speed of light.
Does that mean that we won't be able
to see the microwave radiation?
The microwave radiation will get stretched
and stretched and stretched and stretched,
exponentially,
and so it'll just fade out of existence.
That's going to fade out of existence
before nearby galaxies.
Uh,
yeah.
Well,
a nearby galaxy will disappear,
will fade out of...
Depends on how good your detectors are,
obviously.
I would guess it will become undetected,
detectable before the galaxies,
uh...
Right.
Because the microwave...
I'm not sure which goes first,
the galaxy.
Well,
it would seem like the microwave radiation
is coming from even more remote things
than nearby galaxies,
so if we're not going
to be able to see them,
we...
Oh,
by the time the galaxies...
Yeah,
yeah,
I think that's right.
Yeah,
right.
So everything will cool down,
everything will disappear
behind the horizon.
Only the things which are accidentally
more or less gravitationally bound to us,
the solar system won't fly apart,
the galaxy won't fly apart,
but the distant galaxies will all recede
and will eventually be left in a...
as a truly isolated island
with nothing to tell us that those other galaxies
are out there,
except history,
except history books.
All right,
look,
I want to get on to...
I want to get on
to some more things about cosmology.
Now,
the name...
We're going to get just a little bit technical today,
not too technical,
but there are pieces which are essential.
The name of this series of courses,
at least in my own mind,
are the theoretical minimum,
the minimum number of things you need to know
in order to really understand the next step.
And the next step would mean
following a serious cosmology argument.
So I don't skimp on the essentials.
When the essentials are hard,
I do them in the simplest,
cleanest,
least technical,
least mathematical way that I can,
but I try to do them preserving the essentials.
We're going to do that today.
The other thing I don't like very much
is lots of jargon.
But sometimes it's useful to tell you about the jargon
so that when you read about astrophysicists
determining that W is equal to minus one,
you may want to know what W is.
And in order to tell you what W is,
I will have to tell you
what the definition of W is.
But there are six things which
are all pretty much the same
with different letters that describe them.
So I've sort of...
Somebody will put this on the web
and it's got some definitions and so forth.
All right.
But enough excuses.
Let's get down to it.
What I want to talk about is the relationship
between pressure and energy.
No,
let's go back a step.
We're late.
I'm going to start the class now.
We're going to stay a little bit late today
because I want to...
deal with some issues here.
Let me just do a very brief review.
So far we have found two kinds of matter
which can cause the universe to expand.
One of them was radiation
and the other was just ordinary atoms sitting still
moving together with the galaxies.
In fact,
they are just the galaxies.
One,
I think I named matter,
a matter-dominated universe,
a universe which is dominated,
whose energy is dominated,
by things which are more or less standing still
in their own reference frame
even though the entire universe is expanding.
As we move along with the expansion,
things standing still,
massive objects,
their energy is simply their mass,
and a universe based on that kind of energy density
is called matter-dominated.
All right.
So,
there's an energy density.
Let me just write the fundamental equation over here.
The fundamental equation that we've been working with
is that the scale factor squared,
the ratio of the square,
this is the Hubble constant squared,
that's equal...
Incidentally,
can green be seen well?
Does that work?
It's not as good as black?
Let me try black.
The trouble is the black ones
have always run out of ink.
a dot over a squared,
that's the Hubble constant squared,
is equal to 8 pi g over 3
times the energy density.
As always,
the speed of light I'll set equal to 1.
8 pi g over 3 times the energy density.
And that's our basic equation for how the universe expands.
a is simply the scale factor.
Expands or contracts or whatever it does.
All right.
The energy on the right-hand side
can come from various components.
And in standard cosmology,
what's called the standard momentum,
the model of cosmology,
there are basically three components
to the energy density on the right-hand side.
The first is matter.
Now,
matter is by definition particles or objects.
It could be black holes.
It could be galaxies.
But objects that are at rest moving,
and at rest means moving with the overall expansion.
That's called matter,
such things.
And the universe that is matter-dominated,
let's write down what it means.
It first of all means that the energy density
goes like some constant
divided by the cube of the scale factor.
The cube of the scale factor is just the volume.
And if the number of
particles within the volume stays fixed
and the mass of each particle stays fixed,
then the energy density is
just the mass within that region.
I guess I'm wrong.
I guess I called it m at one point,
the mass within the region,
divided by the volume of our co-moving piece of space.
And that's just a cubed.
So this is matter-dominated.
And we solved the equation
with that particular setup.
And what did we find?
We find that the scale factor grew
like t to the two-thirds.
Next,
we introduced another kind of energy density,
radiation,
made up out of photons.
Because the energy of a photon decreases
when a volume grows,
imagine a box,
imagine expanding the box,
each photon's wavelength grows,
its energy decreases,
and so as A increases,
this is,
let's call this matter,
rho matter,
rho,
let's call it radiation,
energy density and radiation,
instead of being one over A cubed,
is some constant divided by A to the fourth power.
It's the fourth power because each photon
has an energy which decreases
as A gets bigger,
as one power of A.
This is the radiation domina-
if all there is,
is radiation,
and no other kind of energy in the universe,
then it's called radiation dominated.
Of course you can have both together.
Then the equations get more complicated,
but in that circumstance,
A grows like t to the one-half.
Now,
the smaller A is,
the bigger the radiation component is
relative to the matter component.
The smaller A,
when A is very small,
this is bigger than this.
So that means in the very early universe,
the universe was radiation dominated.
After a time,
the individual photons lost their potency
because they expanded,
and the universe became matter dominated,
and so it made a kind of transition,
not a sudden transition,
a smooth transition,
from an expansion like square root of t
to an expansion that was
t to the two-thirds.
This is a little bit faster expansion than this,
and that happened after about 10,000 years,
pretty early,
at least according to the parameters
as we now know them.
We actually can't see back to that point,
but we can infer it by a variety of arguments.
All right,
there is a third component of energy
that's important in the universe.
Of course,
there's zillions of components,
but
the important,
dynamically important components
that really govern
the way the universe behaves on a large scale
is
what I'll call rho naught,
and that's vacuum energy,
dark energy,
cosmological constant,
all the same thing,
and we're going to come to that tonight.
What I will tell you about it
is it doesn't depend on A at all.
It's energy that's zillion,
and it's there in the vacuum.
Think again about this growing chain of atoms.
Waves along here,
sound waves,
would get less and less energy
as they got longer and longer wavelength.
So they,
in fact,
would,
the energy density would decrease with time
from a sound wave.
So let's suppose that there were embedded in this string
a set of impurities.
These impurities,
we do not have a source of new impurities.
We don't have in our pocket
a source of these new impurities.
Let's give those impurities names.
Let's call them hydrogen.
Okay,
they're hydrogen,
or we could call them galaxies,
or just ordinary stuff.
All right,
what happens
as more and more points fill in here,
points of space fill in,
the atoms get further and further apart.
And so again,
the energy density decreases.
But there is also just the energy density,
I shouldn't have called them atoms.
I wanted to reserve atoms
for the little rubber molecules
that were in here,
that were adding into it.
These are galaxies.
Galaxies,
galaxies.
The galaxies get thinned out by expansion,
and so their energy decreases,
that's why it decreases here.
The sound waves,
the number of waves that can fit in,
the wavelengths get longer and longer,
the sound waves get less and less potent,
less and less energetic.
So radiation,
which is the analog of the sound waves,
also the energy density decreases
as A gets bigger and bigger.
But we can just imagine,
that there's some kind of energy
associated with the material
that the string is made up out of.
It doesn't change with time.
It doesn't dilute.
It doesn't dilute because every time it tries to dilute,
we put another atom in there.
The atoms themselves,
the rubber atoms,
let's call them rubber atoms,
make believe the string is made of rubber.
Every time the distance between
rubber molecules increases,
we throw another rubber molecule in there.
So what happens
to this component of the energy,
the component that is associated
with the rubber molecules that we put in?
That does not go away
as the universe gets bigger and bigger.
It stays constant.
What's going on locally
within that rubber string
never changes with time.
And so this so-called vacuum energy
or dark energy,
it's the component which does not
go to zero as A gets bigger.
It's just a constant.
In fact,
you can think of it as a constant of nature.
It's a number.
It's there.
It's there in the vacuum.
It's peculiar.
You may find it odd.
I'm just going to write rho naught equals rho naught.
It doesn't change.
Those are the three components of energy
which are important.
In the evolution of the universe.
We're going to talk about them individually now.
Now,
with each component of energy,
these are the energy densities,
of course.
These are the energies per unit volume.
With each component of energy,
there is also a pressure
that's associated with it.
Let me begin.
I want to describe how energy
is connected with pressure.
Pressure is important in cosmology.
Let's talk about the relationship
between pressure and energy density.
Particularly,
let's start with radiation.
Let's start with radiation.
I'm going to start with a one-dimensional box.
A one-dimensional box is just a line segment.
Let's imagine that it's actually
a finite line segment.
For the time being,
it's not growing.
But it contains photons going back and forth.
And the photons move with the speed of light.
Every photon has an energy.
And when the photons bounce off,
let's assume that they bounce
off the walls of the box.
The walls of the box are
just the ends of the interval.
What happens when a photon bounces off
the end of the,
when it bounces off the interval?
It creates a pressure.
It creates radiation pressure.
Light bouncing back and forth between mirrors
exerts a pressure on the mirrors.
It's that radiation pressure which I want to,
and the relationship between the radiation pressure
and the energy density in there
that's going to occupy us for a while.
So let's see if we can figure it out.
The formula,
let's,
what we're interested in now
is the force on the wall of the box,
the average,
the time averaged force
on the wall of the box due
to the photon bouncing back and forth.
For the moment,
just one photon.
Later on,
we'll fill it up with lots of photons.
All right.
What is the equation for force?
Force is equal to
the time rate of change of something.
What is it?
What's the time rate of change of?
Momentum.
P.
Why does the momentum of a photon change?
The momentum of a photon changes
because the photon is originally going to the right
and it changes to the left.
Supposing,
let's call it small p.
Small p stands for momentum.
Large p will stand for pressure later.
Pressure and force in one dimension are the same thing.
All right.
So,
let's think of the photon
rattling back and forth many times.
Each time it hits the wall,
what's the change in the momentum of the photon
if the photon happens to have a momentum p?
2 p.
Okay.
So,
if the magnitude of the momentum is p,
when it reflects,
there's a change in momentum twice p.
What's the time interval between
successive jolts at the end of the box here?
The photon moves with the speed of light
and the distance is l.
So,
how long does it take between collisions with the wall?
2 l over c.
Why 2?
Because it's got to go and come back.
All right.
So,
the rate at which momentum
is being,
if you like,
which momentum is being deposited on the wall,
the momentum per unit time
that's changing by virtue of the reflection
is twice p,
but it happens every,
what did we say,
l over c?
2 l over c.
All right.
The 2s cancel.
And we can write this in the form
pc divided by l.
That's the force on the wall of the box.
Now,
next question.
What is the relationship between
the momentum of a photon
and the energy of the photon?
Anybody know?
We've done this a number of times.
In fact,
I think I'm not going to work it out.
Let's just state what it is.
The energy of a photon is its momentum
times the speed of light.
Let's just check its units.
It's easy to check its units.
Ordinary momentum is mass times velocity,
right?
All right.
Supposing we multiply that
by another velocity.
Here's momentum,
and we're multiplying it
by another velocity.
Then it will have units of mv squared.
But mv squared obviously has units of energy.
It's the kinetic energy.
So momentum times speed of light
does have units of energy,
and it is the energy of a photon.
It's momentum times its velocity
is its energy.
So we can rewrite that
the force on the end here,
this is the force,
that's pc over l.
That is the energy
of the photon
divided by the length of the box.
Well,
the photon rattles around many,
many times,
and we average over long periods of time.
What is the energy divided
by the length of the box?
It's the average energy density.
The energy divided by the length,
the average energy per unit length.
So we found out that the force
in this simple example
with just one photon rattling around,
the force is just equal to the energy density,
and that's it.
Force,
and let's call it rho.
Rho for energy density,
but let's keep in mind
that in this example,
energy density means energy per unit length,
not per unit volume for the moment.
Energy density rho,
rho stands for energy density,
is now supposing there's a
lot of photons in the box.
Each photon exerts a force
when it bounces into the end,
and each photon has an energy.
For each photon,
the force that it exerts
is equal to the energy divided by the length.
So when I add them all up,
it will still be true
that the total force will equal
the total energy divided by the length.
So this formula is not necessarily
the formula for a single photon.
In fact,
for a single photon,
it's kind of a little bit funny
because everything happens in jolts
that take a long time between jolts,
but if you have a lot of photons in there
and they're all doing the same thing,
then it gets smoothed out,
and the force,
or the pressure at the end,
is simply equal to the energy density.
Okay?
That's the one-dimensional case.
Now let's think about...
Any questions about this?
All right,
this is a fundamental fact,
and it's true in any number of dimensions,
not specifically this exact fact,
but similar facts are true
in any number of dimensions,
that energy density and pressure
are closely related.
So now let's come to three dimensions.
Let's take,
instead of a line interval,
let's imagine a box.
A three-dimensional box,
and for the moment,
let me suppose that all the molecules...
Not the molecules.
The box is full of photons,
uniformly distributed,
but let's make a simple wrong assumption.
The simple wrong assumption is that
all the photons are moving only along the x-axis
for the moment.
Suppose they only move along the x-axis.
The box is full of photons,
but let's take all those photons
in a narrow...
おやすみ
do you call such a shape?
a rectangular parallel pipette,
I believe
let's take all the photons in there
and let's assume,
as I said wrongly,
that they are all moving only in the horizontal
direction
then we can say exactly the same things
except we really should say it in the
following way
let's take a little element of area here
here's a little element of area
and take all of the photons
in that little element of area
I'm not going to write that as rho times the
length because I'm now going to think of rho as
oh,
I'm sorry,
I'm not going,
yes,
I'm going to think of rho
as the density per three-dimensional volume
alright
what is the corresponding formula?
well,
we can write it that way
so we can write it the same way
the force
is equal,
it is in fact equal
to the energy
in that rectangular hyperbolo-blah-blah-blah-blah-blah
divided by the length,
that hasn't changed
but now I want to divide both sides of this,
oh sorry,
that's divided by the length
now I want to divide both sides
of this by the little element of area
so let's divide it by
the little element of area there
A stands for a small area now
and now what's the length times the area?
that's the volume in this region here
what's the force divided by the area?
that's the pressure
that's the definition of pressure,
force per unit area
so we come to pressure,
not momentum now
I think I used small p for momentum,
yeah
pressure is equal again to energy divided by volume
which is again rho
but now this doesn't mean energy per unit length
it means energy per unit volume
now what's wrong with this?
this is a funny setup here
I have pressure on the ends of the box here
but if there are no particles going vertically
bouncing off the roof and the floor
there will be no pressure
on the roof and the floor
we know from experience that a nice thermalized
distribution of molecules or photons or whatever they are
will exert equal pressures in all directions
so let's imagine now
here's an oversimplification
but it's closer to the truth
let's suppose that there are
photons which move along the x-axis
photons which move along the y-axis
and photons which move along the y-axis
and photons which move along the z-axis
this of course is still an oversimplification
the typical photon will be moving at some oblique direction
which is neither x,
y,
or z
but let's just take this simple case here
where there are equal density of photons
moving vertically,
horizontally,
and in and out
same density of photons
and what will the right equation be?
well only those photons which are moving horizontally
will contribute to the pressure on this wall
only those moving vertically
will contribute to the pressure on the ceiling
only those moving in and out
will contribute to the pressure on the front wall
so what's the right formula?
the right formula is the pressure
is equal to the energy density
divided by three
one third of the photons
are moving this way
they all have energy
all of them have energy
but only a third of them
contribute to each component of the pressure
so the formula would be
in this oversimplified setup
rho divided by three
now
is this
the setup was oversimplified
the answer is correct
no matter what directions the photons are moving in
as long as they're all scrambled up enough
the right answer of course
is a given photon
is moving in some random direction
but it has an x component of momentum
a y component of momentum
and a z component of momentum
the total energy
is whatever the total energy is
but it works exactly as if
a third of the photons are moving this way
and a third of the
photons are moving the other way
so this is a correct relationship
I don't want to do it in detail
it is a correct relationship
really it's just that on the average
a third of the energy is
going into motion in this direction
a third is going into this direction
and so forth
alright so p equals rho over three
so this is the right answer
let's write that down over here
pressure
for the radiation dominated world
is energy density
radiation
divided by three
what about
the matter dominated world
is a world in which atoms are there
or they are there
galaxies,
objects are there
but relative to the box
the box,
if you want to imagine what the box is
the box is a certain
region of space that's moving along
with the flow
the atoms are not moving
or whatever is making up the material
is not moving relative
to the walls of the box
they're frozen
they're stuck
do they have energy density
sure,
each one has a mass
multiply the mass by mc squared
no,
don't multiply the mass by mc squared
multiply the mass by c squared
and you will find the energy of each one
but what about the pressure
is it exerting any pressure
on the walls of the box
no
because they're not banging into the walls of the box
they're standing still
they don't exert any force
on the walls of the box
so
this limit
of very slowly moving particles
moving with the flow
corresponds to
pressure equals zero
are there other possibilities
sure,
we could heat up this material
so that the molecules
are moving more
or so that the galaxies were moving more
then we would have some pressure
and we could get sort of halfway in between
we could have a parameter
the temperature of what's going on in here
when the molecules are cold
hydrogen is cold
or the galaxies are
cold
what does cold mean
cold doesn't mean that the stars are cold
it means that they're not moving
relative to the
to the
ambient background
cold molecules don't exert pressure
fast molecules exert pressure
speed of light,
sort of the same thing
as a limiting case
the pressure is fairly large
yeah
in the case of expanding the universe
aren't the particles actually moving apart
yes they are,
but take a small enough box
take a small box
so we don't have to
worry about the growth of it
and examine this for an infinitesimal box
for an infinitesimal box
this
this will work
ok,
so here we have
p equals rho over 3
radiation over 3
here we have p equals 0
and I'm going to write
a more general equation
I'm going to write
the equation that the pressure
this doesn't
not associated with this third line yet
let's erase the third line,
we don't know about the third line yet
not erase it,
just put it down here
rho naught
let me write a general equation
it's an equation which covers
a lot of different assumptions
it is the pressure
is proportional
to the energy density
rho,
whatever the energy density is
times a numerical factor
what is w for the cold gas
w equals 0
what is w over here
a third
w is a parameter
which when you vary it
from one thing to another
you can cover a lot of ground
about what the material
which is driving the universe is
for example
something between 0 and 1 third
would describe something called
warm dark matter
dark matter is not thought to be warm
dark matter is thought to be just as cold
and correspond to p equals 0
but for a while
people thought that dark matter
might correspond to neutrinos
neutrinos move pretty fast
they whiz back and forth
and they don't quite move
with the speed of light
and if that was what the dark matter was
then we wouldn't have p equals 0
because the neutrinos would be moving
we wouldn't quite have
w equals a third
because that corresponds to motion
with the speed of light
you would have something like
a little bit less than a third
so there's a wide variety
of different kinds
this is called the equation of state
w is the parameter
in the equation of state
that's just terminology
and w is just terminology
but if you want to follow
what's going on in cosmology
and the article says
well there's something or other called w
and astronomers are measuring it
to equal something or other
and they want to know what it is
so that's what w is
okay so that covers
the different
kinds of equations of state
but now let's come
to
yeah I want to continue with this
line of reasoning about the equation of state
how is w
related
notice that there's a relationship
or could be a relationship
between what w is
when w is equal to zero
it looks like the energy density
goes like one over eight cubed
when w is equal to one third
it looks like it goes
one over eight to the fourth
is there a pattern there
is there some reason
that as you vary this w
the energy momentum
sorry the energy pressure
ratio
is there some reason
that that governs how the energy density
changes with a
and the answer is yes there is a relationship
I'm going to show it to you
uh
it's tricky
it's not hard
no fancy mathematics
no fancy calculus
just subtle
it's a little bit subtle
little bit of calculus
but nothing fancy
but uh
some subtle reasoning
it's called thermodynamics
and thermodynamics is always hard
not because it's mathematically hard
this is very easy thermodynamics
but uh
nevertheless
a little bit hard
let's take a box
this box does not have to be a cube
it could be any shape whatever
alright
and expand the box a little bit
we could expand the box
by moving one word
we could move one wall out a little bit
we could move all three walls out a little bit
but what we're doing is just increasing
the volume of the box
there's molecules on the inside
molecules
or photons
or whatever
there may or may not be
and typically there will be
pressure on the walls of the box
when we move the walls of the box
we do some work
on the walls
the pressure on the inside
pushes against the wall
and does some work
how much work does it do?
let's see if we can figure
out how much work it does
supposing this wall moves
by a little distance
called dx
only the x wall moves a little bit
we move the x wall a little bit
how much work
is done on the x wall
by moving it a little distance dx
force times dx
that's the work done
what's the force?
pressure times area
so the work done
on the walls of the box
is the pressure
times dx
times the area
of the wall
what is dx times a?
that's the change in the volume
of the box
so it's pressure times area
times the change in the volume
of the box
you would get the same thing
if you moved the vertical
dimension a little bit
or the in out direction
a little bit
in fact you would get the same thing
if you changed all the directions simultaneously
the work done
is the pressure times the change in the volume
now
where does
what does that work
where does that work come from?
energy conservation
tells you that that
where does that work?
that work is the increase in the energy
of the walls of the box
where did it come from?
it came from
it got robbed
or the internal energy in the gas
whether it be photons or whatever it is
got robbed of a little bit of energy
and that energy went into work
the energy in the box decreased
that is why the temperature of a box
goes down when you increase the size of the box
the internal energy decreases
so we can write
the decrease in the energy of the box
is pdv
why the minus sign?
because the energy of the box
goes down a little bit
this is a very general fact
about gases of all kinds
that the change in the internal energy
when you just shift the walls
a little bit
is just pdv
this could be a spherical box
let's take it
it could be a spherical box
it could be a cubical box
it doesn't matter
and we might also write
that later on
let's do it now
no,
let's leave it this way for a moment
later on we're going to write
that the volume of the box is a cubed
a being the scale factor
later on we'll think of this as a box
one scale factor on a side
but for the time being it's just that
now,
what is the energy in the box?
the energy in the box
is the energy density
times the volume
e is energy density times volume
so what is the change in energy
if energy is
rho times v
and we don't know offhand
rho may change a little bit
we know that the energy is going to change
it may change because rho changes
or it may change because the volume of the box
or maybe both
so we should write
that the change in the energy of the box
is equal
to
rho
dv
plus v d rho
that's just the change in a product
when you change each term
each factor a little bit
just elementary calculus
dE equals rho dv plus v d rho
so
and that's equal
to minus p dv
let's take
everything with a dv
with a d volume and put
it on the right hand side
then we get
volume times dp
is equal
to minus
p
plus rho
times dv
dv rho
sorry
I have written in my notes here
which you will get a copy of over the internet
or something
I have p equals one third rho
some place
and then I put in brackets
p e e equals one third rho
r h rho
so that I wouldn't make that mistake
laughter
right
rho and p are not the same thing
v d rho
there's an equation
now let's remember now
that for a lot of interesting situations
the
where is it
that p
is related to the energy density
by a numerical number w
which happens to be one third
for photons
happens to be zero for cold
motionless energy
and it could be other things
so let's plug that in
let's plug that in
and we get an equation
v d rho
is equal to minus
now let's see
p is w times rho
so I think I will write
that this is w plus one third rho
one
rho dv
does everybody see what I've done
I've simply said
that w times rho
is equal to p
if I happen to know what w is
then this equation
can be nicely solved
I'll show you the solution
the solution we write
I'm going to do a little bit of
differentiation
differential equations here
we can write d rho over rho
is equal to minus
w plus one
w now is a number
w is a number
dv divided by v
I've divided by v
and I've divided by rho
alright for those who know
enough calculus what is d rho over rho
it's the differential change in
log of rho
so
this is the change in log of rho
minus
w plus one
what's dv over v
d of log v
this is not very hard to solve
it says that log of rho
is equal
whoops
minus
equals minus w plus one
log of v
so
what
the right hand side
if I multiply something
by the logarithm of v
that's equal to the logarithm of something else
logarithm of
v to what power
minus w plus one
alright
in other words one over v
to the w plus one
is there a constant
nope I don't think so
oh
uh
yeah there's an additive constant
yeah there's a one can add a constant
won't change anything
okay what's the solution to this
rho is equal to one
divided by volume to the w plus one
that's just right
just throw away the log cancel out the logarithms
rho is equal
to one
divided by the volume
to the w plus one
let me just remind you
what we use we basically used
energy conservation
that the work done in expanding
the box is
the energy
that is wrong
and then we used
the relationship between
internal energy and pressure
pressure to tell us the work
and
that's
this is the equation
dE equals pdV
and then we used
for energy
rho times volume
and for pressure
w times energy density
and that told us
that the density of the work
density behaves like one over the volume
this tells us
how the energy density changes
as we change the size of the box
now what box are we talking about
we're talking about a box
or we could be talking about a box
which is one unit
on a side
in cosmology
one coordinate unit on a side
but a box which is
in a small amount of time
will expand
when that box expands
we apply exactly this rule here
and what does it tell us
it tells us that rho
what's the volume of the box
proportional to a cubed
if I take a box
which is one unit on the side
its volume is a cubed
so what does it tell me
well there's a constant here
there's a numerical constant
a numerical constant
divided by a to the w plus one
that tells me
how the energy density changes
as you expand the box
well
did I get it right?
no I didn't get it right
there's a three
it's a cubed
w is a cubed
so it's three w plus three
did I do that right?
no three w plus three
yeah
three w plus three
no no it's not three w plus three
what is it
I've lost something
there's a four in there
where's my four
um
hmm
w times one
or is it w plus one
three times one plus w
that seems right
yeah that's right
okay let's try it out
here's w equals zero
that's matter,
cold matter
w equals zero
c divided by w
divided by a cubed
w is equal to zero
one plus w is one
c divided by a cubed
that's exactly this formula here
so we've got a very very
fancy argument
just to tell us
that if we have a bunch of
unmoving particles which exert no pressure
that the energy density
decreases like one over a cubed
duh
okay let's try it for radiation
for radiation
w is equal to a third
this is one plus a third
is four thirds
divided by three is four
that's a little less duh
a over four
okay
so for radiation it's a over four
but now you have the tools
to decide exactly
how rho behaves
given any equation of state
an equation of state means a value of w
w
so you could have other kinds of material
other kinds of warm gas
cold gas,
other kinds of mixtures
of gases,
whatever
for which w might be
some other number
if so
you simply plug into this formula
and this will tell you how rho changes
with a,
what good does that do you
well you couple it up
again with the
frw equation of motion
where is it,
we've erased it
we don't need this anymore
this was the final conclusion
and it's the reason
this tells you why w is an interesting
quantity in cosmology
tells you how the energy density changes
as the universe expands
but remember
we have a dot over a
squared
is equal to
eight thirds
pi g
times rho
so once we know
how rho depends on a
we can put it into here
and now
with a little bit of work
we put some constant
divided by
a cubed
to the one plus w
now with a little bit of work
you should be able to tell me
how rho depends on a
how a depends on time
for a given w
how do we do that
we just try out different power laws
t to the two thirds
t to the one half
I'm going to leave that for you
all you have to do is plug in
a goes like t to a power
plug it into this equation
and require that the left hand side
and the right hand side balance
and you'll find that this power
I don't remember the detailed relation
this power depends on w
when w is equal to zero
this power is two thirds
when w is equal to a half
the power is
one half
no no when w is equal to a third
radiation
yeah
so you can work that out yourself
and you can find out how the universe expands
for any value of w
with one exception
what's the exception
well you may have a little bit of trouble
yeah
you might have a little bit of trouble
with minus one
right
with w equals minus one
what is w equals minus one
does it mean anything
and is there an answer to the problem
yeah
w equals minus one
we'll see why
is exactly this vacuum energy here
the vacuum energy which doesn't grow
is the vacuum energy
or shrink or do anything
w equals minus one
just means
if you look at it
w equals minus one
that's a to the zero power
right
if w equals minus one
that says that the energy density
doesn't depend on a at all
one plus w equals minus one
w in that case would be zero
and we would just have c
divided by a to the zero
and a to the zero
is just
doesn't depend on a
alright
so w equals minus one
is exactly this situation
where
rho is constant
where rho
simply doesn't change
when you expand the universe
it's the situation
where the energy doesn't
dilute
it's as if you keep putting in
new things
as the universe expands to make up
for the increased
distance between things
alright is it an interesting
situation yes it is a very interesting
situation it corresponds to
Einstein's cosmological
constant it corresponds to what's called dark
energy or
vacuum energy
so
it's worth our while to spend a little
bit of time
working out
what happens when
w is equal to zero
no when w is equal to minus one
incidentally
w equals minus one
you might say wait that's weird
that means that the
pressure is minus
the energy density
well the energy density is positive
this is not the energy density being negative
the pressure is negative
is pressure
being negative weird how weird is
pressure being negative
well if you have two walls
positive pressure means
pushing against the walls
if you have two walls connected
by a rubber band you have to
pull them apart
they're being pulled together that's negative
pressure all negative pressure is is
tension a resistance against
against expansion
so negative pressure is a perfectly
good thing you take a rubber
band and you stretch it and it's an
example of negative pressure
it's pulling the ends together
positive pressure
is that which pushes against the ends
so negative pressure
is in itself not weird
uh
as i said it corresponds to a
kind of tension
it's certainly not mathematically
strange
and it's common in physics
pressure tension
the same thing one is just
the opposite of the other in sign
and the other is the opposite of the other
okay so let's work out
how the f r w
equation behaves
if w is equal
to minus one
in that case
the energy density
is just constant
so let's just plug in
that the energy density is constant
and we've already named it we've called it
rho zero
rho zero is a constant it doesn't
by constant i mean it doesn't depend on
time it's a constant of nature
if you like
it's something which you measure
and it never changes why doesn't
it change because it doesn't dilute
whoops
okay
the combination just as
again i hate terminology
there's too much terminology we can't help it
because
things get named independently
by different people and eventually
we just have too many names for things
the combination
eight pi g
rho naught has another name
anybody know what it is
lambda
rho naught is called vacuum energy
lambda is called cosmological
constant
they are the same thing
apart from some numerical factors
whenever there is a
cosmological constant it means there is a vacuum energy
whenever there is a vacuum energy it means
there is a cosmological constant
now why lambda was not
named eight pi g over
three times rho naught
that's a historical
fact
we'll find out why
Einstein didn't include the three here
there is no interesting
physics in it
yeah
I'll tell you what the interesting physics is
Einstein's equations
actually look like this
laughter
so when Einstein wrote his equations
it was natural for him to define
this thing over here
but when he solved the equations
not he
but when de Sitter solved the equations
he put the three over here
so
lambda is by definition
not the right hand side of this equation
there is an extra factor of three
alright
remember the right hand side of this equation
the right hand side is just a number
don't think about how it changes
or anything
if it's seven or six
or five or whatever it is
in some units or other
and we can take its square root
and we can write that a dot over a
is equal to the square root of this number
eight pi g over three
rho naught
or a dot
is a times a number
or a dot is a times a number
what's the solution to an equation like
a dot is proportional to a
an exponential
the time rate of change of a
is proportional to an exponential
now of course
the combination
a pi g over three
the square root of it
a pi g rho
over three
has yet another name
laughter
let me tell you what the other name is
but we don't need
I can tell you what
the other name is very quickly
let's put it back in this form here
do you remember what a
dot over a is in general
it's the Hubble constant
but of course the Hubble constant
is not typically a constant
but in this case it is a constant
in this case
the Hubble
this is the unique special case
w equals minus one
where the Hubble constant really is a constant
alright it doesn't change with time
this is rho naught I'm sorry
rho naught
so it's sometimes just called h
but if I call it h
we'll lose track of the fact
that h already
is something which can change with time
and so forth
so I'm just going to call it this
and our equation
is the time rate of change of a
is proportional to a
with a numerical coefficient
what's the solution
a equals
a constant
times
what
oh no not rho naught
a
e exponential
when the rate of change of something
is proportional to the thing
that's when you have an exponential
an exponential growth
the rate of change is proportional to the thing itself
alright
and what's the thing in the exponential
e to the
it's going to be e to the time
but there's a time constant
and the time constant
is just the square root here
square root
a dot over a squared
came from the square there
not a cube root
what's that
rho naught
rho naught inside the square root
alright
let me write it over
so it's clear
e to the square root
of eight
pi g
rho naught
divided by three
all of which is a number
times t
so
if there is a vacuum energy
if there is a component
of a vacuum energy
well if
here we're just doing pure vacuum energy
in a few minutes we'll talk about what happens
if all three of them are present simultaneously
but if there was only a vacuum energy
the universe would exponentially expand
and it would expand
at a rate
which is governed by this rho naught
now
the universe
it doesn't expand
it doesn't double in size
this is not a problem
e to this number here
or this number here
is not the doubling time
it's called the e-folding time
it's the amount of time that it takes
the universe to expand by a factor of e
but it's sort of like the doubling time
the doubling time for the universe
is not a second
and it's not a thousandth of a second
and it's not ten to the minus forty-three seconds
the doubling time for the universe
is pretty darn slow
what's roughly speaking
the doubling time of the universe
something like that
some of it
five,
ten billion years
of order the age of the universe
which sounds like an accident
and it doesn't seem like an accident
more or less accidental
at the present time
that the age of the universe
and the doubling time are about the same
that means that rho naught
is very,
very small
rho naught thought of
as an ordinary energy density
is very,
very small
but of course what it's competing with
is other very small energy densities
the energy density in the universe
due to ordinary matter
and galaxies and so forth
is very,
very small
galaxies are far apart
and so
the question comes up
which one of these is present
the answer is all of them
and let's discuss
let's first of all add this in
rho naught
equals
I'm just going to write rho naught
this is called vacuum
dominant
the vacuum dominated universe
and it's
a is equal
to e
to the square root
of a pi g
rho naught three
I'm not going to write it
times t
exponentially increasing
and this corresponds to w equals minus one
p equals minus rho
that's the basic idea of vacuum
dominant
doesn't that mean that eventually
even if rho is very small
it doesn't mean that eventually
it's exponential
it will overwhelm the other two
so wouldn't everything ripple
doesn't mean one thing
would just mean everything would rip apart
and it goes exponential
well
no it doesn't mean necessarily everything would rip apart
um
if you're holding hands
with your mate
and there's a weak tendency
or a small
exponential growth
it's not going to tear your partners
away from you
your grip
maybe stronger
than the tendency for
the expansion to pull him or her
away from you
um so no
it won't necessarily pull everything apart
but
what won't get pulled apart
is the clumpiness
on some average scale
on some long distance scale
a scale which is large enough
that the gravity
holding things together is too weak
to hold them together yes it will pull everything apart
it won't pull apart our galaxy
our galaxy is concentrated
and dense enough
and sort of well above
average energy density
so well above average energy density
that it's being pulled together in fact
it won't pull a solar system apart
it won't pull an atom apart
but it will pull apart a super cluster
or a sufficiently big
um sample
and so it's a delicate question
of what gets pulled apart
and what doesn't
I'm trying to be quantitative about that
and maybe I'll come back to it
but on the average over very large scales
yes things will get
or get pulled apart by this effect
ok so
um
excuse me a question
that last line
a equals e to the
that implies no asymptotic limit does it
does that imply the vacuum
the vacuum line
this is it asymptotic
right but
there's no upper limit
it keeps going
if t is large then that's big
yeah
if t is large it's very big
so it doesn't mean that a even over little distances
doesn't mean that a even over little distances
is close to it
if t is very large
yeah
eventually
but again over small enough distances
it's counteracted by other forces
this can be done
this can be modeled
by a weak force pulling things apart
on the average
if things were far enough apart
and dilute enough
everything would expand with it
but there may be places
where the energy density
is sort of concentrated in lumps
those lumps
may have enough internal gravity
to hold them together
so instead of the lumps expanding
the lump might even contract
but distant lumps will fall
and they will fly apart
so there is a lumpiness to the universe
the universe is doing two things simultaneously
the lumpiness is contracting
ever into more lumpiness
but meanwhile
on larger scales
everything is separating
and becoming more dilute
what about dark matter
which has all the gravity
yeah
okay so
dark matter is a
is part of this
there are two components
to the matter energy density
one of which
is familiar matter
it's the stuff which shines in the sky
and the rest of it
is dark matter
what do we say
dark matter is about 10 times
as much as ordinary matter
but it has the same equation of state
and so from the overall behavior
just from the overall behavior
without knowing more
all you can say is
there is a certain amount of matter
is there anything interesting in the
negative sign in front of that square root
is there
no negative sign in front of the square root
could be
when you take the square root
oh
yeah there are two possible solutions
there are always two possible solutions
does the universe
and the universe run backward
universe run backward
contracts
there's always
the equations are always such
that they admit two solutions
the forward going
thing and the thing which you would watch
if you ran the movie backward
there are always both solutions
and it comes from the fact
there's a square here
so when you solve for a dot over a
you take the square root
it could be positive or negative
physically of course
they're the same
but they correspond to watching it going forward
or watching it going backward
does that answer your question
it's not a contracting universe then
it's not a question of
no
no,
okay
the universe
let's forget for the moment this vacuum energy
in any case you always have two solutions
now
what are the two solutions
you see an object
far from the earth
and it has a certain
kinetic energy
and a certain potential energy
how is it moving
well all you can tell from its kinetic energy
is what its overall velocity
overall speed is
you can't tell whether it's moving away from the earth
or toward the earth
if you know something
you know we see
it's not a satellite
it's not going around
but you see a distant object moving radially
moving radially
we know it's kinetic energy
is it moving toward us or
is it moving away from us
you can't tell
unless you know an additional piece of information
namely whether it's moving away from you or toward you
its kinetic energy doesn't tell you
this is basically an equation
telling you about the kinetic energy
of something receding
it could be positive or it could be negative
things
given where it is
it doesn't help to say that the earth
attracts,
that doesn't mean that the object
far away is moving toward you
it simply means
that it may
decelerate,
if it's going away it may decelerate
but there's no way that you can know whether
it's moving away from you or toward you
that's an additional piece of information
alright,
the additional piece
of information is at least with a normal
concept of things
the universe is expanding
with ordinary time
what if we were contracting with ordinary time
would we know the difference
hard to tell
no,
I mean
well if everything was
running backwards,
including us
obviously we couldn't tell
we would just be part of a movie
running backwards
we would speak backwards
we would think backwards
so
turning,
it would just be
a change of variables from t
to minus t
so there's always that ambiguity in the equations
and we always pick out more or less
by definition,
the expanding
solution
ok
the expanding solution
what is it that determines
the direction of time when we say the future
versus the past
thermodynamics
it's thermodynamics
so it's the second law of thermodynamics
but we won't get into that today
uh
there certainly is ordinarily a
difference between past and future
but let's not do that now
alright,
let's
let's summarize now
the three components of
matter in the universe
these are all called matter
even though this is just plain vacuum
they're all called
well
again,
ambiguities of
terminology
that's matter,
that's radiation
that's vacuum
alright,
but collectively they're all called matter
maybe we should just call it stuff
stuff
let's call it stuff
alright
matter
meaning this
has two components
dark matter
and luminous matter
of which there is more dark matter
the radiation today
is very very weak
because it's been redshifted
but at some time
in the past
when the universe was about a thousand times smaller
because of the difference in the way
radiation depends on scale factor
at some time in the past
the radiation
was the dominant component
and in the future
long time future
as the universe expands
both of these will get smaller and smaller
and this does not get smaller
and smaller
and smaller and smaller
so in the remote future
the expansion of the universe
will be governed by the vacuum energy
alright,
let's draw some graphs
just to illustrate
drawing these graphs
because these are the kind of graphs you'll see
if you read a scientific american article
unfortunately
astronomers and astrophysicists have this
terrible habit
of taking simple graphs
and superimposing them upon each other
until you have so many
things on the graph that you can't possibly
figure out what's going on
but you could take them apart and say
you know
I'm taking the graphs apart
one by one
no,
I'm not going to take them apart
I'm going to put them on top of each other
I'm going to be an astrophysicist today
alright,
we could plot
as a function of scale factor
this is a function of the
expansion of the universe
we could plot energy density
and there are three kinds of energy densities
and let's put all three of them
on the same graph
it does help to put them on the same graph
alright,
we can start with
the easiest one
the easiest one is
rho naught,
it's just constant
it does not depend on a at all
we're not talking about now
a is a function of time
we're talking about rho
as a function of a
it's just constant
it looks like that
it doesn't dilute
diluting would mean going to zero
now let's take
radiation
I'm working upward
is very big
when a is small
and very small when a is big
alright
so it falls off quickly
here's radiation
it falls off quickly
now finally
sort of in between
is matter
let's make matter in blue
matter falls off
like one over a cubed
that means that small a
is smaller than the radiation component
but at large a
it's larger
and so it crosses over
it crosses over
but also goes to zero eventually
so it's a constant
let's imagine now
alright so there's a crossover point here
at that point
that's the point at which the universe goes
from being radiation dominated
to being matter dominated
that happened after about
10,000 years
very very early in the history of the universe
the universe was very very hot
and it was a very very
hot much too hot to be transparent
and so we can't directly look back to that point
it was about 100,000 years
in other words another factor of 10 later
when the universe became transparent
it's in here some place
but this is the crossover
from matter let's write down
this is radiation
this is matter
this is vacuum
and then later on when the universe
got bigger
there was a crossover between
matter and vacuum
what's the total energy density
well very early it was dominated
by radiation
so let's get a red pen
here let's
very early it was mostly just radiation
so it was this
then when it crossed over
it was mostly matter the radiation
became less important
and it tracked along here
well eventually
it just moved on to this line
but then if we waited long enough
the
both of these became smaller
than the vacuum energy and so it
gradually shifted and just became vacuum energy
so there were three eras
if you like the radiation dominated
era
everything was much too hot to be
to be transparent
the matter dominated era
where
most interesting things
of cosmology happened
but not life
life formed
some place
around here
where the crossover happened
this crossover is about
I don't know if it's four million years
four billion years,
five,
six billion years
some number of billions of years
of order of magnitude
the age of the universe
so more or less
we're in the transition region
more on the vacuum side
but more on the
than on the matter side
we're in here somewheres
but we're in this transition region
now let's
let's talk how do we know this
what's the observations that tell us
that this sequence is what happened
and for that we look at another graph
the other graph
is not energy density
versus scale factor
but scale factor versus time
it's simply the time history
of the universe
and how it grew
here it is
early on
the dominant form
of energy was radiation
the others were negligible
and the implication is
that the universe grew
like t to the one half
t to the one half is a parabola
turned on its side
so if there was only radiation
it would go like that
but then at some point
the crossover
matter
became more important
than radiation
but still
sorry,
more important than anything
still more important than vacuum
and it became more important
than radiation
and at that point
when I say point of course I mean
a range of times
but over a range of times
let's put it in here somewheres
it
made a transition
and instead of
going like t to the one half
it went like t to the two thirds
it didn't have a bump like that
in it but that's
so it made a transition
from t to the one half
to t to the two thirds
as I said we can't
see back that far it happened too early
so let's put it early
t to the one half
then t to the two thirds
and then somewheres in here
something very dramatic happened
instead of following
something like this
the universe began
to expand in an accelerated
way
why is it called accelerated
it's called accelerated
because exponential expansion
an exponential
is accelerated
that's,
what does acceleration mean
means it's the second derivative
second time derivative of something
ah
the second time derivative
of an exponential is as big as the exponential itself
so it's accelerated expansion
but just exponential expansion
or it's the same thing
Where are we?
Where are somewheres around over here?
Maybe a little bit further out
We've seen enough of this
exponential to know that it's there
We've seen enough of the exponential to be
pretty sure that it's behaving like an exponential
at the present time
But how do we see these different behaviors?
All we have now,
we're at a certain time.
How do we see?
We can't see the future
But we can see the past
And the way we see the past
is by looking out with large telescopes
out to
distances
that correspond to earlier times
So when we look far out and we count
galaxies and we see how the galaxies are moving
And how their motion correlates with their distance
Effectively we're measuring
What we're measuring is the Hubble
constant as a function of time
But equivalently we're measuring this whole curve
We can't see back
directly to the radiation dominated era
Most people believe it was there
But we can certainly see the matter dominated era
and the transition to the
to the cosmological constant dominated era
So
This is sort of looking at a certain
distance and measuring the couple constant it for that
Distance at that time and then a later time and an
earlier time and you get this curve when you're done with it
So it's a reconstruction but
it's not a very difficult reconstruction
If you,
what's difficult is the observations
but once you have the observations and
you've cleared out all the garbage in the
systematic
errors and everything else,
it's a relatively simple matter to reconstruct
the time history of the scale factor,
and it is completely
consistent with this transition
from matter dominated to cosmological
constant dominated.
As far as we know,
this is really tending to a
pure exponential.
We don't know anything else that looks like that.
And what that means is the
universe is going to exponentially increase apart
from those things which are attached to
us by gravitational cords or other kinds
of strong forces,
things which are sufficiently far away that they're
participating in this overall expansion,
those things will eventually just
disappear through the horizon.
I haven't told you yet about the horizon,
but now it's easy to,
it's now easy to
figure out what the horizon is.
Yeah,
let's see if we can understand now
the idea of the horizon.
I have a quick question about that,
because there seems to be
an implication what you said earlier,
the surface of last gathering kind of fades
into the horizon instead of going through it.
Well,
the surface of last gathering is quite a bit different.
It's not moving.
It's the place where the radiation that we're,
well,
sorry.
Yeah,
it is moving,
as time goes on,
the surface of last gathering will move out and,
but it will never get past the horizon.
In other words,
we will see the rate,
the radiation that we will see,
will be in the horizon.
The radiation that we will see will
be coming as our own time goes on,
the radiation will be coming from
a place which gradually moves out,
which is equivalent to the radiation cooling.
We will see a cooler and cooler universe,
which is equivalent to the universe expanding.
How is it different from the
local galaxies moving beyond the horizon?
No,
it's not the same thing.
Um.
Okay.
At a later time,
the radiation that we see will not come from
the same atoms as the radiation that we see now.
It will come from atoms which
were further away at that time.
So it's like seeing deeper and deeper and deeper into
the universe rather than seeing something moving away from us.
What is the chronological time
frame on this thinking on this?
Yes.
Like 50 years ago,
it was about the time when they
determined the early portion of the universe,
right,
when the big man theory started.
Yes.
It was kind of clarified by the man theory.
And that pre-takes my high
school education and it takes me.
I was like,
um,
are you really close to this?
It was the late 50s,
early 60s.
I graduated in 56,
so.
Sure.
And then the vacuum of the universe.
And then the energy portion.
That's like 10 years ago,
right?
Yeah.
10 years.
Sure.
And it was like in the 90s.
So all prior stuff was like the matter
dominated and it's pretty much the same thing.
Matter dominated was believed to
be the way the universe is,
yeah.
There's another difference also.
The other difference is what
we have left out so far.
Where's the FRW equation?
We're going to put it back next time.
A dot over A squared is equal to rho.
I'm leaving out A pi over 3,
blah,
and G.
Rho times stuff.
And then there was that other
thing minus K over A squared.
Remember that?
We've left that out.
Now,
numerically,
it seems to be very insignificant.
And so leaving it out seems okay numerically.
But it really is conceptually important.
It determines whether the universe is closed and
bounded or whether it's open or whatever it's doing.
Now,
in the old days,
before there was a cosmological constant and it
was believed that the universe was closed and bounded,
so that this term was there,
then people would have drawn curves which look like this.
They would have drawn curves like this.
And then they would have drawn curves where
the universe expands for a while and then recontracts.
And followed by a crunch.
This is nothing but the phenomena of
something going up and then coming back down.
K here tells you whether the
total energy is positive or negative.
K equals zero is right at the escape velocity.
So in the early days of Big Bang cosmology,
it was assumed the universe was closed and bounded,
which meant that K had a certain sign.
And nobody knew about vacuum energy.
Einstein had rejected his child as a bad mistake.
And so it was thought that the universe was
matter dominated with a net total energy below zero,
which means that just like
this thing will come back down,
the universe would crash.
This was called the Big Crunch.
And this was called the Big Crunch.
This was the Big Bang.
Now we don't believe in this part anymore.
Not that we don't believe in it.
Mathematically,
there was nothing wrong with it.
But empirically,
this K seems to be zero to a higher approximation.
And there's a component in the
energy which is driving this accelerated expansion.
So to the best of our knowledge,
the universe is not going to crash.
I missed the time when
the transition to the exponential occurred.
It's somewhere in the vicinity of about five billion years.
Ago.
Both ago and from the beginning.
Remember,
the universe is about ten billion years old.
Beginning of 13.
Oh,
okay.
I don't remember.
It's a fuzzy beginning.
But it's order of magnitude the age of the universe.
Half the age of the universe.
Yeah.
Somebody might look it up.
But I don't have the number.
Two quick ones.
One is,
is that vacuum energy related to the quantum vacuum energy?
Yes.
Or at least we believe it is.
All right.
Let me just tell you one more thing.
Today,
these energy densities scale differently with time.
A1 of A cube,
1 of A fourth.
But today,
today you can ask,
what is the relative abundance or the relative magnitude
of the different energy densities?
Well,
the relative abundance is the
sum of all the energy densities.
So I'll tell you what the relative abundance are.
Now that you know what they mean.
Relative.
Not absolute.
I could also tell you absolute.
But relative abundance.
The biggest single one is the vacuum energy.
Rho naught.
Let's write rho naught over rho total.
Okay?
This just means the fractional.
Rho total means the sum of all the energy densities.
This is today.
Today is about 70%,
0.7.
So most of the energy,
that means that we are well
into the region dominated by the
vacuum.
But not that well.
I mean,
it's not,
you know,
it's not 0.999 vacuum energy.
It's 0.7 today.
Rho matter is today.
Today,
about 0.3.
Rho radiation is negligible.
Very,
very small.
About,
I think about 10,000 times smaller than the matter energy.
So this is very,
very small.
Essentially zero.
Not much there.
But the rho matter comes in two pieces.
Rho dark plus rho,
let's call it luminous.
The dark matter,
well,
let's see,
the luminous is about 5%,
0.05.
And this is,
I guess,
is about 0.25.
That's the composition today.
If you run it backward or forward,
the ratio of dark matter and luminous is 0.25.
And the ratio of luminous matter will stay the same.
That's because they both scale like 1 over a cubed.
That'll stay the same.
So the ratio between these two.
But the,
oh,
I should,
I'm sorry,
I should divide by rho total.
Over rho total.
But depending on the era,
on the time,
the relative abundance of these three will be different.
If you go into the remote past,
radiation dominated.
If you go into the mid-past,
the moderate past,
matter dominated.
Go into the remote future,
this will become essentially one,
and it'll all be vacuum energy.
At which point,
the universe will just exponentially increase.
Cooling as it increases,
and it's interesting to think
about the astronomers of that period.
They will,
they will live in a universe
and look around them and see nothing.
Except for the,
except for the immediate galaxies which
will be in falling toward them.
The,
I think the Andromeda and the Magellanic clouds are
about the only thing that they'll see out there.
And by that time,
they will have merged anyway.
So they'll see a single galaxy.
This will be about in 100 billion years.
It'll take 100,
150 billion years or something like that.
Our galaxy will be completely isolated.
Oh,
another question is,
where is the horizon?
How far away is the horizon?
So,
to figure out where the horizon is,
what we want to do is
figure out what the Hubble constant is.
Let's figure out the Hubble constant.
Here we have it.
A...
Well,
let's just write down the name.
Let's write down the equation.
A dot over A is equal to,
what is it,
square root 8 pi g over 3 rho naught.
That's it.
That's the Hubble constant.
Did I get everything?
I think so.
Yeah.
And in the future.
In the remote future,
there will only be...
There will only be rho naught.
So this is not quite true today.
The other energies are in there.
But in the future,
wait a little while,
mostly it'll just be rho naught.
And this will be the form of the equation.
This is also the Hubble constant.
And so if we write
the equation that Hubble originally wrote,
namely,
velocity is equal to distance times Hubble,
square root of 8 pi g over 3 rho naught,
then we can ask the question,
how far away do you have to be so
that the outward recessional velocity is the speed of light?
And all you have to do
is substitute speed of light in there.
One.
In our units,
one.
And that tells you that the distance to the horizon,
the distance to where things are
moving away from you with the light,
is equal to the speed of light.
And the distance to the speed of light is 1
over square root of 8 pi g over 3 rho naught.
It's this distance which is about 10,
12 billion light years away.
But notice that it doesn't change with time.
Once this exponential expansion sets in,
the Hubble constant stays constant,
and the distance to the horizon stays constant.
The horizon is just fixed.
What is the horizon?
The horizon is where things are moving
away from us with the speed of light.
So as the galaxies in the universe expands,
one by one,
the galaxies will pass through this horizon,
and we can just wave goodbye to them.
They will get,
actually what will happen to them is they'll get more and
more and more redshifted until we just can't see them anymore.
That will happen to just about everything with the
exception of the nearby Magellanic clouds and Andromeda Galaxy.
And so the astronomers of that period,
unless they have good history books to remind
them of what people knew in the past,
will be very puzzled.
They will think that the universe is an
island in an otherwise infinite sea of empty space.
They will not be able to see the blackbody moon.
They will not be able
to see the microwave background radiation.
It will be too thinned out,
too redshifted.
They will have no way of even knowing there's a
cosmological constant because they won't see anything receding away from them.
There will be nothing out there.
So we can imagine them being very puzzled and
thinking that the universe was one galaxy and nothing else.
Read the early books.
That's actually very hard to keep
information over long periods of time.
If you just look at our brief history.
Back to literacy.
But certainly you can even go
back in time and you can say,
someone back there,
that there may have been other terms and they said,
well,
now it's only year three.
And they say,
well,
in year five billion,
they're going to only see this,
this,
and this.
Right.
It would be extremely hard for the astronomers at year three to know
that there was a cosmological constant because it was so much so subdominant.
But it's also true that there were no
astronomers at year three because it was too hot.
It's a curious fact that the cosmological,
all the cosmological parameters point to about the same scale of
time as the evolutionary time scale for evolving a human being.
You know,
a couple of billion years to a billion years.
You've got to go from the,
well,
first of all,
you've got to get the sun to cool.
I mean,
you've got to get the
sun to form and so forth.
That takes a couple of billion years or so.
But then the time scale for evolution is what,
three billion years or something?
Four,
five billion,
four billion years?
Yeah,
you've got to get the metals.
So the time scale for evolution of
a complex organism was about four billion years.
The first three billion years.
I mean,
another billion years of which
was simple single cell things.
And it required stability of things for that long,
for evolution to take place.
But you did say that the surface of
the last scattering would not go over the horizon,
it would just get weaker and weaker and weaker.
So the galaxies,
other than our local cluster,
are going to move through
the surface of the last scattering.
Yeah,
except that we won't be able to
see them as galaxies at that point.
We'll just see them merge into the…
They'll get so red shifted that they'll
get red shifting into the other galaxies.
it down to the same three degrees and it'll
be hard to distinguish them from any of the
other black holes.
So the surface of last scattering depends
on where you are because the astronomers
in those galaxies are not going to see
themselves moving through the surface of last scattering.
Oh,
they're not going to see,
no,
they're going to see us moving through the
surface of last scattering.
Right,
right.
Everybody's on an equal footing.
I've seen,
maybe at Ronald's stand,
I recall,
that,
you know,
first of all,
I should
say there's reason to believe that the universe,
the size of the universe is some order,
the
size of the universe is some order of
magnitude larger than what we can see now.
Is that evident
from what you said?
Not yet.
It becomes evident when we
talk about measurements of the geometry
of space.
And we can measure the geometry of space,
basically measure the sums of
angular mass.
So we can measure the angles of triangles.
But how big a triangle?
Very,
very big triangles.
What we can do,
here we are at the center.
We look out and we see the surface of last
scattering way out here.
And we see some blob
in the surface of last scattering.
What is
it?
It's a blob of over density or
under density or whatever it happens to be.
The surface
of last scattering is a blob
of over density or under density.
It's not a lump.
It's a lump.
I think it's a lump.
The surface of last scattering is somewhat blobby.
It's got some lumpiness in it.
We
see a lump and we have very good reason
to believe that that lump has a certain size.
Okay.
We draw a triangle.
We also know with fairly
good precision by now the distance
to the surface of last scattering.
So we draw a triangle,
an isosceles triangle with two
two d's and let's call it,
the third leg,
call it L for length or L for lump
Now if we have a triangle like
this and we know d's and L,
we know this angle,
theta
We know the angle if space is flat
If space is positively curved,
then this angle would be bigger
than we would estimate from Euclidean geometry
If space is negatively curved,
this is gonna be the subject of next week,
negative and positive curvature
But depending on the curvature of space,
we would either see this angle bigger or less,
bigger or smaller or equal to
what we would expect for Euclidean geometry
What do we find?
We find that to a point
We find that to about 2% or
better or 1% or better or better
That Euclidean geometry is correct
That means that space is flat
It is very much like measuring
triangles from me standing at the center
Looking out some distance,
a thousand feet or a
hundred feet or whatever it is
Some object of known size out
there and looking at the angle
And discovering that the angle
is consistent with Euclidean geometry
I know the size,
I see some battleship out on the horizon
Not quite on the horizon,
in closer
I know that battleship is,
how big is a battleship?
How many feet?
How many?
800 feet
I know that that's the battleship Missouri
Was Missouri a battleship?
The Bismarck,
I see the Bismarck out there
I see the Bismarck
The Bismarck is bigger than 800 feet I bet
And I know just how big it is
I also have reason to think
I know exactly how far it is
And I measure the angle
And I see that it satisfies
Euclidean geometry with a flat Earth
Well not quite flat,
I don't know that it's exactly flat
But I know it's flat to a good approximation
That tells me that the Earth is bigger,
significantly bigger than the distance to the Bismarck
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah
This is good for battleships
But what's an example of an object
out there that we know the size of?
We'll come to that
Oh,
next please
Lumps,
the largest lumps in the microwave background
And we think we know their size because
we know how long it took them to evolve
And we know the speed of
sound and so a variety of things
But it's the largest lumps that
are seen on the microwave background
It also turned out that the
real knot is not necessarily the constant
Just like the bubble that's passing
Experimentally it's very close to a constant
When you,
incidentally,
when you read about it,
if you read about it,
and you read about the measurement of W,
if people tell you that they've measured
W to be minus one to good accuracy,
that's the same thing as saying
that the vacuum energy is constant
So if you read in the
Scientific American that astronomers have concluded
that this strange parameter that
they call W is minus one
and it's getting more and more
and more closer to minus one,
that's an indication that the vacuum energy is constant,
and how close is it?
It's something like one plus or minus,
well it can only go on one side,
but to within about ten or five percent it's one,
minus one
Would general relativity work with a vacuum energy
for which the equation is stable enough?
There are ways of making a cropping constant
So does,
so at least in principle,
so general relativity doesn't exclude the
possibility of more radical vacuum energy
Right
But the vacuum energy is something which
is good reason to believe is there,
the other things are much
less reason to believe is there,
or comfortably
There's no singularity or anything at W equals zero,
things are well-begun
No,
there's nothing,
W equals zero is just non-relativistic cold matter
W equals zero
W equals one,
not minus one,
it's believed there's good reasons
to believe that W has to
lie between minus one and one
W being minus two would really violate general relativity
W equaling plus two would also violate general relativity
So the,
so the density calculation for matter and for radiation,
you assume that the energy was constant
and then you adjusted the scale factor
to figure out the formula
No,
no,
I did not assume it was constant,
we used that the change in energy
Is PPP
Yeah
Minus PPP
So we assumed that if we had an imaginary box
that was following a unit volume and the universe expanded
that the imaginary box moving along with it,
that work would be done on the walls
by the expansion and that would
account exactly for the change in energy
Okay
Now this can be done using fancier,
there are fancier ways to do this
But that doesn't have to
assume the total energy was fixed,
right,
and so the larger volume means a lower energy density
Okay,
yeah,
that's right,
the total energy,
total energy is fixed
So that's true for the first two,
but for the vacuum energy,
the density is constant
So that implies the energy
Well,
what if this equation is satisfied?
That's energy,
that is energy conservation
All right,
well,
remind me,
remind me to talk about energy conservation
The trouble with energy conservation is that
the energy of the universe is zero
So it doesn't say very much
so it doesn't say very much