This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
I want to come tonight to the idea of inflation.
Inflation is an important idea in cosmology,
maybe one of the most important and sort
of at the root of much that we know,
much that we suspect about cosmology.
But before I do,
let me remind you about what the presence
of a cosmological constant does in Einstein's equations.
The cosmological constant,
I'll remind you,
is just a term in the energy
which doesn't have a constant.
It doesn't dilute as the universe expands,
an energy density which does not dilute.
So it's just a term in Einstein's equations.
Einstein's equations are the same as the Friedman,
Roberts,
and Walker,
LaMaitre equations.
A dot over A squared
is equal to the energy density.
And I'm going to take the case.
The case of flat space,
although we may want to modify that later,
the case in which space itself is flat,
not space-time,
but space.
And in that case,
what goes here is just 8 pi over
3 times Newton's constant times the energy density.
And in general,
the energy density may dilute.
The energy density or mass density,
we discussed various cases.
There was the case of matter dominated,
where rho was just the mass energy
of a collection of particles that are expanding.
Because it's expanding,
the energy density decreases.
And in that case,
rho goes like 1 over A cubed.
We studied the case where rho was radiation energy.
That's what dominates in the very early universe.
It was 1 over A to the fourth.
And we also talked about vacuum energy.
And in vacuum energy,
rho is just constant.
So we can just call that rho naught.
Or we can call the whole
thing on the right-hand side lambda,
or something proportional to lambda.
There's some definition of lambda,
the cosmological constant,
which includes,
I forget how many 8s and pis and so forth.
But this whole right-hand side would be a constant then.
Let's suppose this is a constant.
Let's call this constant,
let's just give it a name,
h squared.
And h is a constant.
It does not change with time.
That's the nature of vacuum energy.
The nature of vacuum energy
is the right-hand side doesn't change.
Of course,
the reason I'm calling it
h squared instead of just h
is because the left-hand side is a square.
And this will have nice properties
when I take the square root.
It will say that A dot over
A is just equal to the constant.
So I'm calling this constant h,
where h is the square root of the
vacuum energy times g times 8 pi over 3.
That's square root of 8 pi g
over 3 times the vacuum energy rho naught.
Rho naught just means vacuum energy.
So if you know the vacuum energy,
then you know h.
As I emphasized,
h is a constant.
And then A dot over A
is just equal to that constant.
This is a special cosmology that
has nothing in it but vacuum energy.
Now,
remember also that A dot over
A is also the Hubble constant.
So for this very special case
where there is nothing but vacuum energy,
nothing but vacuum energy,
that is a special case,
when there's nothing but vacuum energy,
the Hubble constant is truly constant.
It doesn't change with time.
If the Hubble constant doesn't change with time,
what does that say about A?
Well,
we can write it as A dot,
which is dA by dt,
is equal to this constant,
Hubble constant,
times A.
And the solution to that equation is an exponential.
The rate of change of the scale
factor is proportional to the scale factor
with a constant of proportionality just equal to h.
And the solution to this is A,
is equal to some constant,
it doesn't matter,
we can just ignore what the constant is,
and write e to the ht.
In other words,
the scale factor,
or the distance between distant galaxies,
unbound galaxies,
galaxies which don't have enough gravity to,
between them,
to keep them from receding,
the distance grows exponentially.
That's space-time.
That space-time which is
exponentially expanding in that manner
is called de Sitter space.
It's just a very simple solution of Einstein's equations
with a positive cosmological constant.
Incidentally,
I've assumed that the vacuum energy here is positive.
Could it be negative?
Yeah,
it could be negative,
but in fact,
let's take the case where it's positive,
the vacuum energy density is positive,
then this is the solution.
And when I say it's the solution,
I mean to say that the geometry,
d tau squared,
is equal to d t squared,
minus A squared,
which is minus e to the 2 ht,
that's A squared,
times dx squared,
and dx squared means dx squared
plus dy squared plus dz squared.
How could it be negative?
You have a positive quantity on the left-hand side.
Yeah,
yes,
you're right.
It can't be negative and space be flat.
It can be negative if space is not flat.
For example,
there is the curvature term here,
plus or minus 1 over A squared,
but you're right,
the whole thing here has to be positive
in order for the left-hand side to be positive.
But this can be negative and this can be positive,
and something else happens.
But let's not belabor that,
because we're going to take it
to be positive in any case,
the vacuum energy to be positive.
Einstein put his cosmological constant in it
to make sure that the universe wasn't expanding.
Is that how he did it?
Is he just...
Well,
what he did was to say,
we know that there's ordinary energy in the universe,
so let's put in plus
some constant M over A cubed.
And then thought about the possibility of cancellation
between this and this.
Oh,
so he put rho naught equal to
minus M over A cubed in there.
Yeah.
It was a misstep.
It didn't make sense.
But that's why he introduced it in the first place.
Okay.
In any case,
in any case,
this geometry,
this geometry which exponentially expands,
the distance between any two points exponentially expands,
it has a constant Hubble parameter.
It's called de Sitter space.
Discovered by the Dutch astronomer Willem van der Leyen,
Willem van der Sitter,
very shortly after Einstein invented his theory,
long before it was known that the universe was expanding.
And it's an important space-time in cosmology.
It's important for two distinct purposes.
One of them is the
explanation of the currently accelerated universe.
Acceleration,
what does acceleration mean?
It just means that the second
time derivative of A is positive.
Let's go back to this simple,
this case over here.
This,
of course,
would be called an unaccelerated universe
because the second time derivative
of A is just plain zero.
This is accelerated because the second
time derivative of A is positive.
And in fact growing with time.
All right,
so that's the accelerated universe.
It's an observed fact.
Today,
this is a correct description of our universe.
Not quite.
And not quite because there is some
additional energy besides just the vacuum energy.
So let me just remind you
quickly what we know from observation.
We know that the scale factor in the
past was this usual t to the two-thirds.
That's the matter-dominated universe.
And then at some time of
order a few billion years ago,
somewhere more or less at the halfway
point between now and the Big Bang,
it began to end.
It began to exponentially increase or
it began to increase more rapidly.
Now,
t to the two-thirds doesn't look like that,
does it?
Yeah,
curvature is wrong.
T to the two-thirds look like that.
Convexity is wrong.
Right.
And then at some point it
did start to look like that.
And we're somewhere over here.
So this is an observation.
This is not something which is speculation.
And there's enough of this curve here that's been measured
that it does fit neatly on to the exponential.
It itself,
of course,
is not quite an exponential
because it's a transitory behavior,
but it appears to all observers tend to agree.
It looks like it's entering into an exponential phase,
right,
which is another way of saying that the
vacuum energy is bigger than the other energies,
roughly by a factor of two today.
But this is getting smaller and smaller with time,
and this is not getting smaller and smaller with time.
So that's our current understanding of the universe today.
It's exponentially growing.
It's the center of space.
And the Hubble constant,
which is not exactly constant today
because it's not exactly exponential,
but is tending to an exponential.
That's today.
It is also worth discussing the idea of a horizon.
I think we've done this before,
but let's do it again.
It's an important idea.
At some relative coordinate spacing,
let's call it delta x,
or at some,
not coordinate spacing,
at some distance,
some actual proper distance,
using Hubble's law,
we can calculate the velocity
as a function of that distance,
and at some distance it becomes
equal to the speed of light.
All right?
Remember that distance times Hubble is equal to velocity,
and so if we want the
velocity to be the speed of light,
then the distance that we have to go out to
is equal to the speed of light
divided by that Hubble constant,
the Hubble constant being the square
root of a vacuum energy density.
The smaller the vacuum energy density,
the smaller h,
the bigger the distance to that place
where things are receding away from
us with the speed of light.
That place,
of course,
is called the speed of light.
It's called the horizon.
And,
if you like,
it's a sphere around us
at a distance given by c over h.
Numerically,
it's about 10 or 12 or 15 billion light years,
which accidentally happens to be
about the same as the age of the universe.
Now,
whether that's an accident or not
is a matter of very intense argument.
But they're two different quantities.
One is the age of the universe.
In other words,
the time...
Where is it?
I threw away my graph,
but...
There it is.
The universe started in this,
and we're over here.
Okay.
So,
as it happens,
this distance scale,
apart from the factor of the speed of light,
is about the same as the age of the universe.
So the distance is about 10
or 12 billion light years away.
And at that distance,
as I said...
Yeah?
I was going to say,
isn't the Hubble...
Isn't the tangent line at any point...
If it happens to intersect the origin,
then those two quantities will coincidentally be the same?
In other words,
distance...
Distance to the horizon and...
Yeah.
That,
of course,
would be exactly true for a of t equals t.
Right.
Yeah.
Okay.
So at the moment,
it is a bit of a mystery
why the vacuum energy happens to be such,
okay,
that the distance to the horizon
or converted to a time by
means of the speed of light,
why the distance to the horizon is about
the same as the age of the universe.
Well,
it's not remaining the same either,
is it?
Which is it?
The horizon is a change.
The horizon...
The Hubble constant is remaining the same.
Of course,
the age of the universe is not remaining the same.
Right.
So as far...
So it sounds like it's a coincidence of
just us being here at the time that we're
here.
Right.
Let's take it to be just a coincidence.
Now,
is it a coincidence?
Is it a coincidence that the Darwinian time
scale for evolution happens to be the same
as the time scale as obtained from the vacuum energy?
No,
that's clearly something which we have to explain some day.
Question.
In the Sitter space,
is that assuming that there's
more than one point in space?
no matter and no radiation?
Yeah.
OK.
Absence of this term completely.
Well,
we did the Einstein equations.
We had a situation where the,
so I guess,
there's a form of energy,
this vac,
can you say something about this vac energy?
Because I'm pretty confused about what its source is
or what it is.
I mean,
do you think that if you didn't
have any matter or radiation,
that we'd be getting up?
I mean,
naively.
Right.
So for that,
we have to understand
why quantum mechanics gives energy
to the ground state of systems.
The vacuum is the ground state of,
let's say,
quantum field theory.
Ground state means the state of lowest energy.
Now,
in the vacuum,
it's possible to have
oscillations of electric and magnetic field
and so forth.
The oscillations behave like ordinary oscillations.
And ordinary oscillations have a ground state energy.
The ground state energy is not zero.
And the reason that it's not zero
is because of the Heisenberg uncertainty principle.
We're going off track,
but let's answer the question anyway.
If we have a harmonic oscillator,
that's the potential of a harmonic oscillator,
the energy of it is proportional to the momentum squared,
that's
the kinetic energy.
OK.
I'm not going to put in numerical factors,
plus the distance squared that you stretch the spring,
so to speak.
There's usually a factor of spring constant here
and a factor of 1 over twice the mass here.
But just leave it like this.
This is good enough for us.
P squared plus x squared.
Now,
classically,
the ground state
of the harmonic oscillator simply
means the configuration in which the spring
is at its equilibrium point,
not vibrating,
not stretched,
just sitting at its equilibrium point.
x equals 0.
And because the velocity of
it is also equal to 0
at the equilibrium point,
p is equal to 0.
And the energy is equal to 0.
p squared plus x squared,
both of these terms are equal to 0.
The Heisenberg principle does not allow
there to be a state in which,
both x and p are simultaneously knowable,
in the language of quantum mechanics,
diagonalizable.
And so there's a necessary fluctuation.
If x were literally right at the center here,
then p would have to have an infinite fluctuation.
If p were at the center,
in other words,
if the momentum was exactly equal to 0,
then x would have to have an infinite uncertainty.
And so there is no state of
the system in which both p and x
are exactly known to be equal to 0.
They both fluctuate.
But the sum of p squared plus x squared
doesn't necessarily have to fluctuate,
but it's got to be positive.
Since both p and x cannot simultaneously be 0,
the vacuum or the ground state energy
of a harmonic oscillator is not 0.
Now,
what is it?
What is the ground state energy of a harmonic oscillator?
1 half.
h bar omega,
where omega is the frequency of the oscillator.
Now,
the universe is full of potential harmonic oscillators.
Full of harmonic oscillators.
They're the oscillations of the electromagnetic field.
There's,
in fact,
an infinite number of them,
of low frequency,
high frequency,
and a large number of such oscillations,
not just the electromagnetic field,
but every field.
And every field has a ground state energy.
It's the energy stored in that
field due to zero point oscillations.
Every field behaves like an oscillator.
Every field has zero point energy.
And it's those zero point energies which
are one explanation of the vacuum energy.
The real puzzle is,
why?
Why it's so small.
It is very small numerically,
very small.
But that is not for tonight.
Let's just recognize that it exists.
As the universe expands,
it doesn't dilute.
It's just a constant.
And experimentally,
it really is,
or observationally,
it really does seem to be
there with a particular numerical constant,
which happens to be extremely small,
measured,
measured in natural units.
I have an idea.
Why isn't that just the last scattering baseline energy?
I don't know what that means.
I just mean that there's always three degree...
No,
no,
no.
It's not the three degree radiation.
That's radiation.
That energy decreases with time because the photons dilute.
And furthermore,
each photon decreases its energy.
It's not the three degree.
It's the oscillations that are there
when you remove all the real photons.
It's the virtual photons or just the zero point oscillation
that is necessarily present.
Of course,
we're not now talking about a
particle on the end of a spring.
We're talking about the
fluctuations of the electromagnetic field.
In fact,
do you know what these two things are?
What these two things would
be for the electromagnetic field,
which are,
which can't,
for which there's an uncertainty principle?
Well,
isn't this like sources?
B and E.
What?
Electric and magnetic fields.
The energy of an electromagnetic field
is E squared plus B squared,
with E being like momentum and B squared.
And there's an uncertainty principle
between electric and magnetic fields,
which is very similar to the uncertainty
relation between velocity or momentum and position.
Okay?
So they can't both simultaneously be zero
because of an uncertainty relation between them.
And the result is that even when you remove as
much energy as is possible to remove from the field,
there's still this residual zero point energy.
That's what constitutes,
or at least that's what's believed
to be the origin of this.
I'm having a tough time understanding,
if you remove matter and you remove radiation,
what causes the electric fields?
Like,
what's the perturbation and what?
I can't answer what causes it.
I can tell you that the
uncertainty principle requires it to be there.
We're making the assumption there is no electric field,
there is no mass.
Oh.
I thought you were...
Did I say there's no electric field?
You said decider space has only the...
The dark energy.
Right.
Okay.
It has no real photons.
It has only the zero point energy.
Okay,
you can have an electric field without real photons.
It just doesn't have any charges.
It's there anyway.
The field fluctuates anyway.
It doesn't need charges.
Right.
Yeah?
Could you go over that point about the
age of the universe being equal to the...
Inverse Hubble constant?
Yeah.
Okay,
let's take a second.
I know that it's equal to inverse Hubble constant,
but it's also equal to the distance
to the surface of last scattering or something?
Oh,
that's an approximation.
That it's the distance to the surface of last scattering.
But...
What do you say to the ?
Isn't that just a mathematical truism?
Just because of the equations,
it's just...
Yeah.
It's not an experimental fact.
Almost.
Yeah.
But not that H is
approximately the age of the universe.
No.
Clearly,
it does not have to be.
And this deciter space is simply not true.
H just never changes.
The age of the universe does change.
But H presumably...
It's exactly true.
It's only exactly true for this scale factor over here.
Let's see why.
All right.
Let's take this case.
A of T grows like T.
Then what is H?
H is equal to A dot over A.
What is A dot?
A dot is 1,
and T and A is T.
So this is just equal to 1 over T.
And it's clear that the
Hubble constant...
It's not constant,
but the Hubble parameter is just 1 over the time.
The time from the Big Bang.
That's true for any T-shape.
Any power law.
Well,
it's not quite true.
Take any power law here.
Then it becomes an A dot is equal to P,
T to the P minus 1.
And then divide that by A.
That means dividing it by T to the P.
And the answer is P over T.
So,
for example,
if P is 2 thirds,
then this would be 2 thirds over T.
And it would not
quite be the case that the
Hubble constant is 1 over T.
The Hubble constant was 1 over time,
but it would be 1 over
time with a factor of 2 thirds
in front of it.
Yeah,
but I'm assuming there's other
constants we're not including anyway.
All right.
That's right.
Excuse me.
3 halves in front of it.
H would be 3 halves 1 over T.
Did I write the...
Yeah,
1 over P,
so it's...
No,
that's right.
2 thirds is right,
but H is...
2 thirds is right.
Okay.
Yeah,
2 thirds is right.
That's H.
Left-hand side is H.
For the de Sitter universe,
it's infinite.
Wait,
okay,
wait.
H is equal to 2 over 3 T,
where T is the age of
the universe at any given time.
Okay.
Now,
let's come to the de Sitter case.
The de Sitter case,
it is not T to the P.
It is E.
It's exponential.
E to the HT.
Let's not call it H,
okay?
Let's just call it E to the constant,
gamma T.
All right?
A is E to the gamma T.
What is A dot?
Incidentally,
I could put a constant in front of it.
It wouldn't make any difference.
Let's put the constant in front of it.
What is A dot?
A dot is C gamma E to the gamma T,
right?
Just differentiate it E to the gamma T.
Now divide it by...
That's A dot.
Divided by A,
which is just C.
That cancels C,
and it cancels E to the gamma T.
So we find out that the
Hubble constant now is truly constant,
and it's just as gamma,
which appears here.
Okay?
This is the unique case in
which the Hubble constant is constant.
It's the only case where it's constant.
And once we know...
That the hub...that A dot over A...let's go back.
A dot over A is equal to the square
root of 8 pi G over 3 times rho.
This is the square root of the FRW equation.
All right?
So the Hubble constant is just the square root
of 8 pi G over 3 times the vacuum energy.
That's H.
Okay?
All right.
So there's a definite connection between this vacuum energy
on the one hand and the Hubble rate of expansion.
We call this sometimes the
rate of...the Hubble rate of expansion.
It's the thing that goes in here.
It tells us,
in this case,
1 over H is not the age of the universe.
What is it?
It's the time constant.
It's the time that it takes the universe to...
Not double in size,
but multiply by E.
Yeah.
The time that it takes for the universe to double...
I said double again.
Let me use double,
but I really mean multiply by E.
It's the time constant for
the universe to double in size.
And what is that?
That is the inverse of this H,
and it's about 10 billion years.
Okay?
So every 10 billion years,
we can expect the universe will double in size,
roughly speaking.
That's an approximation.
Could I ask you a question?
Yeah.
This vacuum energy density is constant,
right?
Yeah,
it's constant.
Well,
yes.
This,
of course,
is an experimental question.
Okay.
So if the universe is expanding,
so that implies to me that the energy,
the total energy,
vacuum energy,
is...
Is increasing.
Where is it coming from?
It's coming from the other side of the equation.
This minus this is equal to zero.
This is one form of energy.
This is another form of energy.
This is a kind of kinetic energy of expansion.
It's a kind of kinetic energy of expansion.
Both terms appear in the expression
for the energy in general relativity.
And it's conserved because it's equal to zero.
So this energy is coming from here.
Does that come from then all these particles originally?
That comes from Einstein's field equations.
If you apply Einstein,
if you apply the ideas of
Hamiltonians and energy to Einstein's field equations...
But we talked about all that kinetic
energy at the beginning of the universe,
right?
So is that basically being transferred?
Yeah,
it's a transfer of kinetic and passive energy.
Potential energy?
When we talk about energy
being conserved or entropy increasing,
are we talking...
Entropy or energy?
Either one.
Okay.
Are we talking about that within
the cosmic horizon or do we mean...
No.
...
including outside the cosmic horizon also?
Okay.
The cosmic horizon is fixed in size.
It doesn't change with time.
That's the same statement that the
Hubble constant doesn't change with time.
Right?
The energy within the cosmic horizon stays fixed with time.
The vacuum energy.
The vacuum energy is just the volume
of this times the vacuum energy density.
The vacuum energy density,
which is rho naught...
Let's work it out.
Okay,
so that's this diameter here,
which is...
What is it?
C divided by...
Square root of 8 pi g over 3 times
the square root of rho naught in the denominator.
That's the distance.
Now I want to...
What I want to do with it,
I want to cube it
in order to find the volume...
Cubed.
Four-thirds pi.
Yeah,
four-thirds.
Four-thirds pi.
Okay.
And then multiply that by the vacuum energy density.
And the vacuum energy density is rho naught itself.
There's some amount of energy in there,
but it doesn't change with time.
It doesn't change with time
the amount within the cosmic horizon.
So the portion that we can see,
the portion that we can ever see,
that energy doesn't change with time.
If it's the Sitter space.
Right.
So,
you know,
standing here from our vantage point and
looking out and looking at all the
vacuum energy that's out there,
no,
it doesn't change with time
the portion that we can see.
Okay.
Good.
So that's the basic idea of a cosmic horizon.
Things can pass through the cosmic horizon in
the same sense that they can pass through
a black hole horizon.
And I won't go into that in any depth now,
but once they do,
they're out of contact with
us in every way.
So that's the basic idea of a cosmic horizon.
Can I just follow up on a question?
So if it's not at the Sitter space,
does that mean that energy
flows out to the energy within
the cosmic horizon?
It might.
Well,
energy is a loaded term.
Exactly what do you mean
by the energy in general relativity?
In general relativity,
the concept of energy is a
little bit curious because it contains
this gravitational component as well as ordinary energy.
This is the gravitational component of the
energy here for this particularly simple kind
of geometry.
In mechanics you had a Lebron gen.
You want to get on
to the rest of the stuff?
Yeah.
Let's move on.
All right.
Now,
the same mechanism appears to
have happened in the remote past,
but instead of the time
constant being about 10 billion years,
it's a little bit different.
It's about 10 to the minus
32 seconds or perhaps that fast.
Where does this come from?
Well,
the origin of the question,
this is inflation.
This is the idea of inflation.
The universe in the remote past exponentially expanded.
Now,
when I say this happened,
of course,
to some extent this is conjectural,
but the
conjecture has passed a number of observational tests.
So when I say something has happened,
it's not just a conjectural test.
It's a very simple one.
You can feel free to put
a little bit of a question mark.
Did it really happen or am I guessing?
Okay.
So I will tell you what's
known and what the empirical evidence is,
but let me just shorten
my sentences by saying something happened.
It happened that in the remote past,
before anything that we can observe,
in other words,
out beyond the surface of last scattering
or earlier than the time when the universe
became transparent,
the universe was exponentially expanding.
Now,
why did that idea gain any
traction and where did it come from?
Well,
the basic place that it came
from was the flatness of the universe.
To make a long story short,
spatially,
the space slices of the universe are rather flat.
Flat meaning we don't seem to live in
a curved universe which is either positively curved
or negatively curved.
We seem to live in a very flat universe.
In fact,
not only a flat universe,
but a rather homogeneous universe.
On large scales,
bigger than super clusters of galaxies,
in particular on the larger scales,
the universe is very flat and homogeneous and smooth.
How did it get to be that
way and why is it that way?
The early ideas of the Big Bang were
that the universe started just in some random state.
It could have started with some very complex geometry.
It didn't have to be flat
and it didn't have to be homogeneous.
We don't really have a theory
of how it began in the very,
very beginning.
But let's suppose it began like a shriveled up raisin
or prune with all sorts of wiggles and texture to it.
Why?
What is?
Where did all those wiggles and texture go?
Where did it disappear to?
Now,
in fact,
we know,
here's something we know.
We know at the time
of the surface of last scattering,
in other words,
what we ordinarily think of as the Big Bang,
the beginning,
the beginning as far as we can see back,
already at that time the
universe was very flat and smooth.
So it's not that it flattened itself out and
stretched itself out between the Big Bang and now.
Big Bang,
I mean.
Looking back to the surface of last scattering,
the surface of last scattering itself is very smooth,
which indicates that at the time when the universe
was as hot as the surface of the sun,
it was already very smooth.
So something had smoothed it out.
Now,
you might say,
why do you need something to smooth it out?
Just postulate that it started out smooth.
Okay,
you can do that.
But in fact,
it wasn't exactly smooth.
We'll come to the deviations from smoothness.
But the question was asked,
why is it that the universe started so very smooth?
Why is it that the density in one place
is about the same as the density in a very,
very different place?
In particular,
we can imagine places which
are so far apart that light,
we can see them both.
All right?
We can see them both.
We see something way out
there and something way out there.
But we know that light did not have
time to get from one to the other.
So there was no way that a smoothing
process could have happened on such large scales.
And what is it that made the
universe smooth and flat on those scales?
Well,
the hypothesis is that the Big—that
what we ordinarily call the Big Bang,
that there was a prehistory to it.
And during the prehistory of it,
the universe exponentially expanded by an enormous amount and
got itself stretched out to be almost completely flat,
like the inflation of a balloon.
I like to think of it that way.
You start with a completely deflated balloon,
and the completely deflated balloon looks like a—you
know what a completely deflated balloon looks like.
It has all sorts of wrinkles—a wrinkle,
a wrinkly balloon,
a really wrinkly balloon.
And now you start blowing it up.
And after it's expanded a certain number of times,
it gets pretty homogeneous.
It gets pretty smooth.
Okay?
So if there was—and this prehistory would have had to be before the surface
of the last scattering because it's known it was already very smooth at that time.
All right?
What was the hypothesis?
The hypothesis was—called inflation due to
Alan Guth in the early 80s,
around 1980—that the universe underwent at that
very early time a period of exponential inflation,
exponential growth.
In other words,
that for a period,
it behaved like the Sitter space.
Are we assuming equilibrium before inflation?
No.
Whatever inflation does,
it stretches things out so much that you lose memory
of what the structure might have been like before inflation started.
It just takes whatever was there and stretches it out
so much that it just leaves it in this very,
very homogeneous configuration.
There was no previous homogeneity.
We don't know.
The good thing about inflation is
it erases all the initial conditions,
and so you don't have to know what the initial conditions are because you don't
have to know what the balloon looked like in the beginning because it gets stretched out.
The bad thing about inflation is it
erases all the information about how it started.
I don't know.
I mean,
if you have a blotch on
a raisin and you blew it up,
and you would still have a blotch—
No,
you're blowing it up to something very much
bigger than the size of the known universe.
So imagine there was a blotch on the raisin,
and the raisin got to be 10 to the 10 to
the 10 to the 10 times bigger than the observed universe exponentially.
Remember,
the idea was it was exponentially growing,
so it got to be 10 to the 10 to the 10
to the 10 to the 10 times bigger than the observable universe.
So it's just as if the surface
becomes transparent from previously opaque or something.
It's not transparent.
It just gets stretched out.
So that blot or that blob,
that little bit of inhomogeneity got stretched out.
It's still there,
but it's there on a scale much,
much bigger than we can see.
But you have to assume that it
wasn't sort of a fractal to start,
right?
Because in that case,
you wouldn't even,
you know—
Yeah.
You have to assume that there
was smoothness on some terribly tiny scale.
But if the universe is so big,
it's not.
If the universe expanded enough,
if it inflated enough,
then if you start on any scale with some fluctuation,
it will eventually stretch that fluctuation out.
That's known as inflation.
And the hypothesis is that in the very early universe,
that basically exactly the same kind
of thing happened that is happening today,
except with a Hubble constant at that time,
which was millions and millions of times larger.
Larger,
yes,
larger.
In other words,
with a vacuum energy which was very much
larger than the vacuum energy that we see today.
Okay,
now that's a curious idea.
It's a crazy idea.
Why was the vacuum energy
different then than it is now?
Can we even call it the vacuum energy if it was—if it
had to do with something which is different than the vacuum today?
And what's the answer?
What's the basic idea?
So the basic idea goes something like this.
Now,
we do have to talk—I'm going
to tell you what the idea is,
and then we'll come back at some point,
I hope,
and discuss what the empirical evidence for this idea.
At first,
it was just almost a throwaway idea.
Maybe something like this happened.
And as time went on,
observation got better and better to the
point where this picture is very clear.
And it's been pretty well confirmed by now.
That doesn't mean it's absolutely got to be right.
It means that it's the best
candidate for our understanding of what happened.
All right,
to understand,
you have to have the idea of a scalar field.
A scalar field is a field just like Maxwell's field,
just like electric and magnetic field,
except instead of being a
vector at every point in space,
the electric and magnetic fields are vectors.
They have direction at every point in space.
It's just a scalar.
No sense of directionality.
And let's call that field—let's give it a name.
Let's call it phi.
Is it any of the fields
that we see in nature today?
Is it identified—are its quanta identified
with any of the known particles?
Definitely not.
It is not identified with any observed
fields that we know about in physics.
And its quanta are not identified with any known particles.
So it's a hypothetical field which exists and fills
space in the same way as any other field.
And it has an energy.
It has an energy associated with it.
The energy that's associated with it
is a kind of potential energy.
And a potential energy that scalar
fields can have—and it's a potential energy,
V,
which the V is the energy.
It has standard terminology for a potential energy.
When I say it's a potential energy,
I mean it doesn't have to
do with the time derivative of phi.
Of course there's energy in a field if it's oscillating,
if it's fluctuating.
But there also can be energy in a field
just because the field is displaced away from zero value.
Now,
for the moment,
let's completely forget about quantum mechanics.
Quantum mechanics is not important.
It's not a function right now.
And it's some potential energy called V of phi.
V of phi is some function of phi.
Let's just draw some picture of it.
Here's some picture of it.
Any function,
whatever function you like,
you can put in here.
And,
of course,
you get a different theory out no
matter what function you put in here.
But imagine some function of phi.
Then,
if phi is one value or another
value or another value or another value,
the field energy,
and it's a kind of vacuum energy,
it's a kind of energy that's
there not really in the vacuum,
but there simply by virtue of having some space in
which there is a field which takes on a particular value.
It's very similar to vacuum energy,
V of phi.
But it can vary.
Can I ask a question about that drawing?
What's the horizontal axis?
Phi.
Phi and the vertical axis is V.
Right.
Now,
you're buying a whole set of ideas here,
none of which are obvious.
First of all,
that there can exist scalar fields in nature.
This is not obvious.
That they have potential energy.
Well,
the mathematics of physics,
the field theory suggests that they
can and do have potential energy.
And the potential energy can vary from point to point.
So different values of the
field can have different energies.
But one also has to
take it as a matter of,
you have to take it as a matter of faith.
I take it as a matter
of known mathematics that V of phi,
if phi is not changing,
for example,
if it just has some value over here,
is a kind of vacuum energy.
It's a kind of vacuum energy which doesn't dilute.
That's the main property of it.
It doesn't dilute.
This part of the energy of a field doesn't dilute.
Yeah.
If you drew a picture of space,
then,
would phi be constant over the space?
It may or may not be constant.
So then it could have different values.
Yeah.
It could have different values in different places.
That's right.
Let's for the moment suppose
that it was the same everywhere.
Let's take that case for the moment.
We take that case for the moment.
And we say,
what would the world be like?
Also,
phi itself is a function of x,
y,
z,
and t.
In principle,
it could be a function of x,
y,
z,
and t.
Let's take the case for the moment
where it's just constant for the moment.
It's just constant for whatever
reason at some value of phi.
Then in effect,
the world has a vacuum energy which
is just v at that value of phi.
That's the way scalar field energies work.
They behave exactly like vacuum energy.
In particular,
they don't dilute.
So then,
if that were the case,
we would simply say that the vacuum energy
is replaced by
v of phi.
Where phi is the value
that the field happens to have.
It might be over here.
As long as it's not changing with space or time,
it would just be a constant.
Phi being constant in space.
And then we would go back to
all the equations for the decider space,
or all the equations for the expansion of the universe.
And every place we saw rho naught,
we would stick v of phi.
In particular,
the universe would expand with a Hubble constant,
which would be equal to the square
root of 8 pi over 3 g,
and instead of rho naught,
I would write v of phi.
Now what happens if v of phi,
if phi varies from place to place?
Supposing over here it's a different
value than it is over here.
Or different values than it is over here.
Well first,
let's go back to the case where it's not varying.
What's happening where it's not varying?
The region of space over which
it's not varying is expanding exponentially,
like e to the ht.
What happens if it varies from place to place?
Then in different places,
it's expanding,
expanding with different time constants,
but stretching from place to place.
So if it's expanding exponentially by an
amount that depends on v at every place,
so if v is varying,
or phi is varying from place to place,
you would have exponential expansion everywheres,
but a different time constant in each place.
But if the universe expands enough,
if it inflates enough,
if it stretches enough,
and you're inside there someplace,
and you can only see out to your horizon,
eventually the stretching is so
much that your entire environment,
your entire environment has been stretched out to
the point where the field within your region
has become homogeneous,
has become constant.
So it's very much like this balloon.
The balloon could be painted with some
color which varies from place to place.
Red over here,
blue over here,
purple in between.
And then you expand it out,
inflate it out by many,
many orders of magnitude,
and somebody at the center,
or somebody at some point,
who only can see so far,
sees a very homogeneous color.
Same thing with this inflating universe.
v might vary from place to place,
but if it does vary from place to place,
it will get stretched out in
such a way that it will look,
for practical purposes,
as if it were very constant.
Now...
It would worry me,
though,
if phi varied,
let's say,
you know,
very proportional to something.
In other words,
it's not...
What you seem to have drawn is
a situation where phi is constant in patches,
and it seems to me like it could be...
It doesn't have to be constant,
just slowly varying.
Slowly varying.
Slowly varying on what phi,
on what scale?
Well,
it doesn't matter much,
because whatever scale it's slowly varying on,
eventually that scale will get stretched out.
Now,
you could imagine maybe it was so bad
to begin with that it would never stretch out.
You could imagine that.
But apparently that's not the way it was.
And that we judge because
the universe is today rather homogeneous.
All right.
So,
let me draw for you then
the way
experiment
various combinations of observations
suggests this V of phi to be...
Oh,
yeah,
all right.
Incidentally,
if you have a potential
energy function which looks like that,
it could be the potential
energy instead of for a field,
it could be for a coordinate of some kind.
What happens if you start the coordinate over here?
What happens if you start a particle
in a potential energy and you start over here?
You roll down.
Now,
let's suppose you start up here.
You roll down,
you roll over the hill,
and you eventually go somewhere else.
If there's a lot of friction,
if there's a lot of friction,
you might roll down the hill here
and just get stuck at the minimum.
The minimum,
really are places,
the minima,
really are places where the field would just be constant.
If you started the field over here,
it really wouldn't be constant.
It would,
it might roll down.
If there was friction,
and there is friction in cosmology,
if there was friction,
then it might just come to
rest at the bottom over here.
If it comes to rest at the bottom,
if the field comes to rest,
then it's constant.
That's the situation in which you can pretend
that the field is very
constant and doesn't change with time
if it's sitting at the minimum of the potential.
It could come to rest in any of these.
All right,
so here is what it is thought,
that the potential energy of some field,
which we have never discovered,
we've never measured it,
it is a conjectural,
speculative,
construction with a field energy,
with a V that looks something like this.
Now,
perhaps it starts with a shape of some unknown kind,
but then it gets very flat.
Not completely flat.
Question?
So the field energy doesn't vary for very much
over some range of phi.
And then all of a sudden,
it comes to the end of a cliff,
comes to a cliff and falls down.
It doesn't quite go to zero.
And then turns back up.
Now,
this is so ridiculous that,
so contrived,
let's put it this way,
it is so contrived that it almost seems,
seems quite ridiculous.
Nevertheless,
this is what observational cosmology
seems to demand.
So here's the picture.
The universe started in some unknown way,
in a way that we don't know,
with a field energy,
V of phi,
that was located on a plateau like this.
Because this was almost a flat plateau,
phi didn't change very much with time.
It changed very slowly,
like being on a very,
very shallow,
like this eraser on the tabletop here.
There's enough friction,
and in fact in cosmology,
there was a lot of friction.
The eraser doesn't move very much.
You could tilt the table quite a bit
before you would start to move off.
The kind of friction is not quite the same
as the kind of friction on this table here.
More like a viscosity?
Yeah,
more like a viscosity.
more like a fluid viscosity.
This is called slipstick friction,
which means it sticks until it slips.
All right.
Motion of an object through a liquid or a gas
is a better analog for what happens for cosmology.
So,
but there is a kind of viscosity.
Viscosity is the right picture.
There is a kind of viscosity
that's particularly associated
with an expanding universe,
and the faster the expansion,
the bigger the viscosity.
And so if this were a particle
moving on a potential energy surface like this,
in other words,
just a potential like this,
it would slowly,
slowly,
slowly move down here
under the combined effect
of the slope of the potential.
That means a little bit of a push
in this direction
and at the same time,
the viscosity would keep it moving slowly.
It would stay at this level
for a long period of time.
During that time,
V didn't change much.
So V was almost constant during that time,
and if V were constant,
then it would just be a constant vacuum energy.
So to the extent
that the universe slid down this hill very slowly
and the vacuum energy was still there,
the energy didn't change much,
then during that period,
the universe inflated.
During that period,
the universe exponentially grew,
and it exponentially grew
with a time constant that looks like this,
where V of phi
was just the value of V along here.
A very big value,
right?
What's that?
A very big value.
Well,
it depends on what units
you're measuring it,
of course.
So if you're measuring it
in ordinary,
everyday units,
it's enormous.
Even if you're measuring it
in elementary particle units,
it's very,
very large.
But if you're measuring it in Planck units,
it must have been,
it was very small.
So it depends on what units
you're talking about,
but in units anything like
the density of energy in this room,
it's humongously big.
Right,
so very,
very large energy here.
What's causing phi to move?
Hm?
The slope of the potential.
Okay.
The slope of the potential
is causing it to slowly drift
down that hill,
roughly as if,
roughly as if you had
a weak gravitational field.
Forget talking about ordinary gravity.
Imagine this room were filled with liquid,
filled with honey.
Hm.
Okay?
And you put a rock in it.
The gravitational field would correspond
to a tilt in the potential energy,
potential energy higher at one end
than at the other end,
higher up there than it is here.
The viscosity of the honey
would lead to the rock falling,
and it would fall slowly
with a terminal velocity.
All right,
so this slowly slides down here,
assuming the slope is small enough,
until it gets to the edge,
and at the edge here,
it suddenly goes over the edge
and winds up eventually down here.
Okay,
what does eventually mean?
Eventually means today.
Isn't that more like slip-stick?
No.
No,
no,
it doesn't.
It never sticks.
Well,
I mean...
It doesn't stick.
It looks like it's slipping.
It's slipping.
No stick,
though.
Right,
right.
It's not a station.
Right.
I always thought a slip-stick was a thing,
but a slip-stick wasn't a thing.
Slip was slip or stick.
Slider.
Slider was a slip-stick.
Did they call it that?
Yeah.
Oh,
they do?
Okay.
Okay,
yeah,
I guess from my engineering background,
I thought a slip-stick was a thing,
but no,
it's an adjective.
Slip-stick friction.
All right.
It's not slip-stick.
It's just slip or viscosity.
And then when it gets to the end here,
all of a sudden,
the potential energy changes rapidly.
That means effectively that there's
a large force on the universe
pushing it over the hill here.
And what happens when it gets down here?
When it gets down here,
at the minimum,
it comes to rest.
It comes to rest,
the combination of friction
and minimum potential energy,
it comes to rest.
All right.
Where are we today?
We're down at the bottom.
How do I know what the
height of this potential energy is?
Because I know today what the Hubble constant is.
So the Hubble constant is 8
pi 3 over g via phi.
That's the exponential growth of the universe today.
And that appears to be down here.
The coefficient down here is very,
very small,
much,
much smaller than it was up here.
Why this is true,
we don't know.
We really don't know.
But we do know what the
potential energy is at the bottom here
because we know today what the Hubble constant is.
Today.
All right.
And it's very small.
We also suspect,
and there's some evidence,
that the potential energy up here was very much larger
and that the Hubble constant was very much larger,
in other words,
that the doubling time of the universe
was many orders of magnitude larger than this one doubling
every 10 to the 10th years.
In fact,
with standard cosmological numbers,
this inflation took place with a time
constant of 10 to the minus 32 seconds
or something like that.
So it's kind of crazy.
I mean,
this is a crazy picture.
This is a crazy picture.
The amazing thing is that
it seems to have some validity.
All right.
We gradually drifted down here and came to the edge
and went down to here.
The expansion that took place
up in here is called inflation.
It's called inflation.
Where did the Big Bang happen,
incidentally?
The thing that we normally call the Big Bang.
The Big Bang happened after we
got pretty much down to here.
After we slid over this edge,
the Big Bang,
meaning to say,
what I mean by the Big Bang
now is the surface of the last scattering.
The surface of the last scattering
was very late in this picture.
It happened well after the universe settled down here.
So the Big Bang and everything
we actually can observe about cosmology
was down in here.
But before the Big Bang happened,
this period of exponential inflation took place,
according to theory.
And during that period,
the universe stretched itself out so much
that all of the wrinkles disappeared,
if you like.
So that means that the universe
at the time of the Big Bang
or the time of the surface of the last scattering
was already stretched out by many,
many powers of E.
How many powers of E?
That we don't know for sure.
You were going to ask a question.
The wrinkles are mainly wrinkles in
this primordial scale of the field then.
And also the gravitational field.
Also the gravitational field.
Yeah.
In other words,
the shape of space and its curvature
might have been fluctuating,
but also phi.
What is the x-axis?
Is that T or is it phi?
Phi.
Here,
in this?
Phi.
The field phi.
This is the potential energy as
a function of the field phi.
The field phi can depend on time
as the universe rolls down this hill.
Well,
it sort of acts like a time parameter.
Like a what?
It's acting like a time parameter here
because you've got a monotonic function that's...
It is,
in fact,
acting like a time parameter.
This is true.
Time parameter meaning to say
that it's monotonic function of time.
Yeah.
What's the part of the graph after that minimum?
Say again?
Here?
Yeah.
Who knows?
All we know is that we're living at some place
where the potential energy is not quite zero.
Yeah.
Nothing in our experience tells us very much about here.
Looking back in the past,
we discover something that looks like a motion like this.
We're going to come to what
the observational evidence for this is,
but...
This may be a bad analogy,
but when you're looking
at gravitationally derived potential energy
as a function of position,
but there's only potential energy in
the presence of a gravitational field.
Okay,
a gravitational field simply in this context
means a gradient of a potential energy.
Well,
what is the analog of
a gravitational field in this picture?
There isn't one.
Okay,
let's not get ourselves confused between gravity
as the real thing in this universe
and the model that I was
describing of a rock falling through honey.
Right.
Some force on a system
which pushes it from one place to another,
basically.
That's the gradient of the potential energy here.
The fact that it's not actually exactly flat.
Just in case it was not clear,
this was not intended to be exactly flat.
It was intended to have a small slope.
It's analogous to the table having a small slope.
If the table has a small slope,
then the potential energy differs from point to point.
And if something is on this table,
if there's no friction,
what happens if there's no friction?
It starts accelerating.
Okay.
What happens if there's some viscosity?
It reaches a terminal velocity.
It starts to accelerate,
but then reaches a terminal velocity
and just moves slowly across the table.
If the table has a small tilt,
it will move slowly.
Okay.
It will move slowly until it
gets to the edge of the table.
Okay.
And then it falls off.
So it doesn't oscillate through there?
Well,
it may oscillate down at the bottom here.
How did we observe that?
That's dark energy,
dark matter.
But where is Big Bang today?
All right.
The Big Bang and everything
we historically know about the universe
all took place after this got down
to very close to the bottom here.
And where is it today?
Also down at the bottom.
It fell down there and just stuck there.
Not stuck because of stick slip,
but stuck because it's the minimum of the energy.
And what is the period of
inflation when this balloon is expanding?
Is that just the cliff or the whole thing?
No,
no,
the whole thing here.
And that's about T to the minus,
like minus 32 seconds.
That?
Right.
10 to the minus 32 seconds.
Doubling every 10 to the minus 32 seconds.
Now,
that may seem very fast,
but on the scale,
on the Planck scale,
in units of Planck time,
it's very slow,
in fact.
The Planck time is 10 to the minus 42 seconds.
We don't know how long that was either.
Yeah,
right.
We don't know how long this was,
and so we don't know
how long this inflation took place.
So we don't know in that sense whether it
expanded by a factor of 10 to the 10,
10 to the 10 to the 10,
10 to the 10 to the
10 to the 10 to the 10.
We don't know.
All that information got wiped out by this expansion.
Now,
what happened?
What did this expansion do?
It did exactly the same thing
that it would do to a balloon.
It flattens it,
and it leads to a situation where
by the time you get to here,
incidentally,
falling off the edge here is called reheating.
There's nothing re about it.
It should just be called heating,
but it's called reheating.
Why is it called reheating?
This happened rather suddenly.
When a thing like this happens rather suddenly,
the energy that was stored in the field is
rather quickly converted to some other form of energy.
When you fell off the cliff here,
just like that eraser when it hit the floor there,
its energy,
its potential energy was converted to heat.
Then as you roll over the edge here,
and by the time you get down to the bottom,
the universe is hot.
It wasn't hot up here.
In fact,
any heat that might have been there to begin with
was diluted by this enormous exponential,
exponential,
exponential factor.
So if there was some thermal energy to begin with,
the universe simply expanded so much
that it got diluted to the point of almost nothing.
That first curve up there represents an injection of heat.
Well,
or something.
Right,
right.
But we also know nothing about that.
Right.
It's a history.
You're perfectly right that perhaps
in the very early prehistory
something happened over here that
was heating and then reheating,
but we know nothing about this really.
We can't observe this directly.
It's hard to observe.
We don't know if we can observe it.
It's just that we don't think it's lower.
Right.
So how the universe got up here,
why it started up there,
we don't know.
But we know that if it did start
up here and it stayed up there long enough,
that the initial conditions are sort of wiped out
or they're diluted so much that
we have no fossil memory of them.
Everything started very,
very stretched out,
which means the universe was extremely homogeneous.
Now,
this is going to be qualified.
We're going to qualify the statement.
I'm oversimplifying a little bit,
sort of on purpose.
If the universe expanded by a factor
of 10 to the 10 to the 10th,
then it would look extremely flat
by the time you got to here.
That's the reason we believe that the
right solution of the cosmological equations today,
involves flat space.
Remember I told you earlier on that observationally,
the curvature term,
this factor k,
which can be plus or minus 1 or 0,
is observationally 0,
meaning to say that the universe looks spatially flat
to about 1% or better than 1%.
But it seems to be spatially flat.
It seems to be spatially very,
very flat.
Geometry of space seems to be Euclidean geometry.
Why is this so?
Well,
to the best of our knowledge,
there was a period of expansion
which flattened everything out,
so that we are today looking
at the universe on a scale
which is very much smaller than its curvature.
We might as well use flat space,
because the universe radius of curvature is so
much bigger than the region we can see.
Alright,
now...
Question?
Yeah.
When you say 10 to the 10th,
is that just an arbitrary number,
or do you mean at least that big?
We don't know anything about
how long we remained up here.
We don't know how wide this plateau is,
and we don't know how shallow it is.
The shallower it is and the higher...
We actually don't know how high it is.
We don't know how broad it is,
and we don't know how...
Alright,
we have some bounds.
We have some bounds.
We know something about the combination of these parameters.
And basically what we know is that the universe doubled
or got multiplied by a factor
of E at least about 50 times.
E to the 50th.
E to the 50th,
okay.
Do we have any idea
how much energy got put in
to the system?
We have some bounds on it.
That's another way of asking
what the height of this is.
Yeah.
Yeah,
we have some bounds on it.
I would say the best bet would be
something like about 10 to the minus 14
in Planck units,
but that's a huge amount of energy in ordinary units.
So you want me to
give it to you in joules?
Well,
I can't give it to you
in joules without sitting down and saying,
I'm doing a calculation,
but it's 10 to a large number,
10 to the 90th or something.
Why did the universe reheat after the expansion slowed down?
Well,
it reheated because it came
to the edge of this cliff
and that potential energy was
converted at first into kinetic energy
of the motion of the field.
Just as this eraser,
its potential energy got converted to kinetic energy.
And then when it hit the floor,
where did that energy go to?
Well,
it went into thermal energy.
It went into thermal energy,
and that thermal energy is the energy
that the universe had at the Big Bang.
Yeah.
You made some sort of comment about dark matter,
some connection with dark matter.
You could ask,
might this field have oscillated here?
That oscillation energy conceivably could
be the energy of dark matter.
It would get diluted.
The energy of,
let's not get into that.
I did say that,
but this is not the important lesson here.
Can you say anything about the
actual value of phi at the present,
which is to say at v minimum?
Of phi?
Phi,
yeah.
You mean this distance?
No,
the value.
Of v or phi?
V or phi.
V is vertical,
phi is horizontal.
Vertical?
What is the value of phi relative to rho zero?
No.
No,
no,
no.
V has the same units as rho zero.
That's v.
Is that the same as rho zero?
Exactly.
That's rho zero.
Could you plot phi as a function of time?
Yeah.
I could plot it,
but let me just draw it instead.
I mean,
let me just put my
finger on here to follow it.
Maybe it came,
we don't know very much about this,
but it slipped down here and then very,
very,
very slowly
inched along here.
While it was inching along here,
things were exponentially growing.
And eventually it got to here and went .
.
Perhaps it oscillated a few times at the bottom,
but there was a good
deal of friction at the bottom
due to the expansion of the universe,
and so eventually it just
came to rest at the bottom.
And then t goes on,
but phi stays still.
Right.
In other words,
as when you get down to the bottom here,
you've gotten onto this branch of things
which is today's current deciduous space behavior.
Now,
do we know for sure
that it comes to rest here?
No,
but we know that it's moving slowly.
So this is a model of what we know.
We know fragments of this.
We don't know the whole picture with any great certainty,
but we know some fragments.
We know,
for example,
that this is not zero.
So the universe is exponentially inflating today,
but with this very long time constant.
We know that it was rather high over here,
many orders of magnitude larger than it is today,
and so the universe did apparently .
.
I have not talked about the observational evidence yet,
but the observational evidence indicates that along here
the universe grew by at
least a factor of e .
.
I said e to the third,
but it's a factor of 50.
Usually it's quoted as e to the 60,
but you can play with the numbers a little bit.
So the universe is e to the
60 times bigger than it was over here,
at least,
at minimum.
Now,
how many times .
.
Incidentally,
the number of times that it got multiplied by e
is called the number of e-foldings.
E-foldings .
.
An e-fold simply means multiplication by e.
Each of which took 10 to the minus 32 seconds.
Each of which took 10 to the minus 32 seconds,
but also that number is dependent on the height here,
and the height is not well known.
The height is not well known.
What's known is that there was
at least about e to the 30th.
So,
it's a factor of 50 or more e-foldings.
Sorry,
50 or more e-foldings.
Is it possible that it was flat on the top
and that there was just
sort of perturbations in the field
which flipped it off the edge?
If it's too flat on the top,
yeah.
It's not consistent that it was completely flat.
It had to have some tilt,
but it could be pretty close to flat.
There's no possibility for some kind of quantum effect
to flip it off the cliff.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
No,
no,
definitely.
Definitely.
So that you would just have .
.
It's sort of in this vast matrix of nothing.
You'd have a universe here and a universe .
.
If it were too flat at the top,
if it were too flat at the top,
it would have created too inhomogeneous a universe,
which was what I was about to explain.
Oh,
okay.
Right.
Okay,
so we know that it couldn't
have been too flat on the top.
So let me explain how we know that.
First of all,
I said .
.
This is an interesting story with many parts,
and I will not try
to get to them all now.
But .
.
What I meant was the universe inflates,
and the process of inflating becomes homogeneous.
Homogeneous on any ordinary scale.
On a scale,
let's say,
as big as the horizon size.
That's not terribly big.
It may have had many more e-foldings than that.
It may have been stretched out by many,
many times.
Bigger than that.
In the same sense that the Earth is much bigger
than the horizon that we can
see from six feet above the Earth.
Incidentally,
what is the horizon from six feet above the Earth?
A couple of miles,
I think.
Yeah.
The Earth is much bigger than that.
In the same sense,
our horizon .
.
Not in the same sense,
but in an analogous sense.
Our horizon is rather small on the scale
of the radius of curvature of the universe,
which means it expanded and inflated many times larger
than the region that we can see.
Okay,
so it got to be by this process of inflating,
by this process of stretching,
it got to be very,
very homogeneous,
except for one thing.
One thing prevented it from becoming completely homogeneous.
And that was?
Quantum fluctuations.
Now,
we can delve into this a little more deeply,
but not tonight.
Quantum fluctuations created .
.
Take what would have become an infinitely stretched out,
completely homogeneous universe,
and leave over quantum fluctuations
of various wavelengths in here,
which are the remnants of the
quantum mechanical processes which took place.
I will not try to explain them tonight,
but let me just say
that after this inflation took place,
no matter how long it takes place,
it never really gets completely
settled down to complete uniformity.
Why?
Quantum mechanics.
Quantum mechanics and quantum field theory
ensure that there is always fluctuations.
It's kind of an uncertainty principle thing,
again,
but the fluctuations were there
even after it may have expanded
by 10 to the 10 to the 10 to
the 10 to the 10 to the 10 .
.
factor.
There were fluctuations.
In other words,
the field was not completely homogeneous.
It varied from place to place by
an amount which was controlled by quantum mechanics.
If there was no quantum mechanics,
it would be completely flat.
With quantum mechanics,
it varies from place to place.
Okay.
Now,
let's come to the central picture,
which is really what has
gotten the whole subject very exciting
over the last 10 years.
Let me draw .
.
Well,
okay.
Here's the edge of the cliff.
Let's draw that edge of the cliff over here.
What I'm plotting here vertically is ordinary space,
ordinary space X.
What I'm plotting horizontally .
.
What am I plotting horizontally?
Um .
.
I guess .
What am I plotting horizontally?
Uh .
.
The field,
phi.
What I want to draw is the contours,
the contours of the field.
The contours mean the surfaces of constant field,
like a contour map.
It's not a contour map of elevation.
It's a contour map of the field phi.
Now,
if phi was completely homogeneous,
it does vary with time.
Here's what you would see.
At one time,
you would see a completely homogeneous field.
That would mean that phi is
the same at every point of space.
Here's space vertically.
Here's the field phi is horizontal.
Phi is the same over here as it is over
here as it is over here as it is over here.
That means that phi has gotten very homogeneous.
What would happen with time?
As time transpired,
as time went on,
it's transpired,
you would roll down the hill,
which would mean that the field would gradually move,
moving to the right,
until it got to the edge over here.
When it got to the edge,
that's the value of phi where reheating occurs.
It would suddenly fall down,
and the sudden change in
phi would fall down to here.
So with time,
if you plotted phi as a function of position,
it would be constant,
constant a little later,
constant a little bit later,
slowly drifting to the right.
And then,
if it were all that homogeneous,
in other words,
all that smooth,
every place in space would go
over the edge at the same time,
if it were completely homogeneous.
But now let's put quantum mechanics in.
What does quantum mechanics do?
It puts some fluctuation into the field,
and so we could expect that the
that the contours will show some fluctuation.
They will not be exactly homogeneous.
And as we roll down the hill,
some points reach the edge before other points.
Here's the way I like to think about it.
Imagine a bunch of soldiers walking in lockstep,
arm in arm,
and they're walking towards the edge of the cliff,
all together.
If they are homogeneous,
if they are really very well lined up,
with no fluctuation in the rank,
in their location,
then they all fall over simultaneously.
But what happens if some
soldiers are slightly behind other soldiers,
some of them a little bit in front,
some of them a little bit,
and they're moving really,
really slowly?
Then there can be a long time delay
between the time one fellow falls over
and the time another fellow falls over.
So there can be large gaps in the time
between the time that the
different pieces fall over the edge.
Now,
when you fall over the edge,
when a piece of space falls over the edge,
let's just take a very simple situation.
Imagine the field is homogeneous except for a little bump.
So the contour looks like that.
It gradually drifts to the right,
and this point over here falls
off the edge before this point.
So a region of space
is created which has been reheated.
It's down at the bottom here,
whereas the rest of space is still
up at the top of the cliff.
All the soldiers except for
one are up on the top.
One guy has fallen over.
Now that one guy has fallen over,
that one region of space here,
is inflating less rapidly than the region up here.
The vacuum energy down here is small.
So it's inflating slowly down here and rapidly up here.
What happens?
What happens is the energy that's in here,
the new energy that's in there,
the kinetic energy,
the energy of falling off the cliff here,
is expanding.
It's expanding less rapidly in space than
the rest of this region out here.
So a little lump of energy forms.
A little lump of energy forms.
A little bit later,
let's say a little bit later,
another bump goes over the edge.
By the time this bump has gone over the edge,
this one has been over for a while,
and it has expanded somewhat.
It has expanded somewhat.
Then the next one falls over the edge.
All right.
So what does this lead to?
This leads to inhomogeneities in
the energy density over here.
It leads to inhomogeneities in the energy density
because different regions went over
the edge at different times,
and their kinetic energies
were expanded and diluted differently.
There's a particular pattern
to the kind of fluctuations in energy that take place,
but what do these fluctuations of energy be?
What do they become eventually?
These are the seeds of galaxies.
The energy density is not uniform
after you fall off the cliff,
and in fact,
the slower that you're moving,
the bigger will be the inhomogeneities.
If you're moving very,
very slowly,
then the time between this fellow falling over the edge
and this fellow falling over
the edge can be very large.
During that time,
uh,
this region may have grown,
and then when the next one goes over,
this one will have already spread out.
So the energy density will be most variable in space
if the field is moving very slowly.
It would seem it would be the other way
because the expansion slows down,
so you'd go over and you'd expand less.
Oh,
it has kinetic energy.
Yeah,
it expands less.
Yeah.
And so the first...
Yeah,
yeah,
that's right,
that's right.
So,
yeah,
but,
right,
but the point is that it will create,
it will create variations in the energy density
that will first of all come
from the original variations in the field,
but then magnified by this effect
that,
uh,
that one guy goes over before the next guy,
and therefore the effect is,
uh,
different rates of expansion in the two regions,
and that has the effect
of making a variable energy density.
That variable energy density is necessary.
It's necessary because without it,
there would be no galaxies.
So it's a funny combination of inflation,
inflating the universe and making it very smooth,
but leaving over these little fluctuations,
which eventually became the seeds of galaxies.
Now,
this is a highly quantitative story.
I'm describing it descriptively,
but it's something that can be quantitatively computed
from the quantum fluctuations in a
field and in an expanding space,
and you can compare it with the properties of,
uh,
of the fluctuations,
which you can trace back from known galaxies,
from known properties of the distribution of galaxies,
you can trace it back to the earliest times
right after this reheating took place,
and,
uh,
it fits.
It fits well.
Yeah.
Uh,
could you say that it was cooling,
and that after it falls,
it cool,
it doesn't cool as fast?
Um,
no,
not,
that's not really quite right.
It's a question of expansion that,
uh,
that by the time this guy falls over,
this guy is already spread out,
and,
uh,
done some expansion.
Expanding as fast as possible.
So it's not expanding as fast.
It's not spreading out as fast.
No,
it's not expanding as fast.
That's right.
So it's a combination.
There's a competition of things going on.
Expansion in the,
in this piece that fell over the edge
and the inflation of this other fluctuation here,
and it gives rise to a pattern
of fluctuations of energy density.
That was,
for all practical points of,
for all practical purposes,
the observational start of the universe.
Very homogeneous.
Let me ask it this way.
The later fluctuations,
are they hotter or cooler than the earlier ones?
They're cooler.
Well,
they're cooler.
They're cooler because they've been stretched somewhat.
When this one...
The late,
the earlier ones are hotter than the later ones.
No,
the earlier ones have cooled some.
The next one that goes over,
you see,
when you go over the edge,
if a little piece of space goes over the edge,
it gets this much energy.
All right,
that much.
Then that energy is diluted by expansion afterwards.
So if a little piece of space,
let's say that much space goes over the edge,
it picks up...
So it's hotter at the point that it's falling over.
Yeah,
it's always hotter,
right.
All right,
so then this one cools a bit,
and then the next one falls over,
and it's somewhat hotter.
Okay.
Yeah.
So the hottest places are the
last places to go over the edge.
Yeah,
so...
But that's right.
But the main point is that it
leads to inhomogeneities in the energy density.
And those inhomogeneities,
they're small,
in fact.
They were,
I mean,
observationally,
the variations in the energy
density are one part in 100,000.
This is dark energy density,
the variations,
right?
No,
this is primordial density fluctuations.
This is neither dark...
Dark energy is this.
Oh,
okay.
That's the energy today.
But phi,
you're saying,
includes matter and radiation?
Yeah,
that's right.
It turns into all kinds of very hot stuff.
Right,
matter,
radiation,
and that kind of stuff.
And it varies from place to place.
Observationally,
about one part in 10 to the 5.
Now,
that one part in 10 to the 5 is
not a number that we can derive from this picture.
That one part in 10 to the 5
tells us some constraints on the shallowness of this...
The...
ご視聴ありがとうございました
how flat it is,
the flatness of it,
the height of it,
it puts some constraints on the parameters
once those constraints are imposed then it
creates a spectrum of fluctuations at different wavelengths,
different size scales
these guys get spread out,
this guy comes next,
he's smaller in space and so forth
so the effect is that
you have a fluctuation density spectrum
fluctuations on different scales
what happens to a variation in
energy density that you start out with?
well,
if you have a bit of over density over here,
let's say over density
and a bit of under density over here
the over density gravitationally attracts
material from the under dense region
and so the over dense region gets more over dense
the under dense region gets more under dense
and the effect is to magnify the spectrum of fluctuations
so just a very very
small little fluctuation to begin with
will gradually build up depleting the under
dense regions and increasing the over dense regions
and that's the origin of galaxies
so
from the spectrum of galaxies,
from the spectrum of,
not the spectrum,
from the distribution of galaxies in space
one can try to reconstruct the density
fluctuations that were there at the very beginning
now the very beginning means after reheating
and compare them with the
theory that this picture leads to
which is namely quantum fluctuations in the
field being magnified by falling off the edge
and then being processed by gravity
the answer is it fits very well
it fits very well with this picture
and it's the only thing that
fits very well with this picture
you have to assume that it's
a fairly small volume at that point
where?
that the observable universe is a small volume
at which point?
in galaxy formation
at the time of galaxy formation the observable universe was
was...
some pretty good fraction of what it is today
I'm not sure what you're asking
I'm just wondering how fast this movement
from under dense to over dense takes place
oh,
well once it starts it happens fast
is that during reheating?
no,
that's after reheating
that's after,
at the end of reheat
at the time of reheating
that's when these fluctuations were first established
in other words
after going over this edge here
there was some density fluctuations which
were bigger than they were in here
but whatever they were
but still one part in ten to the five
roughly
one part in a hundred thousand
magnifies the quantum fluctuations
yeah,
magnifies
by going over the edge you magnify the quantum fluctuations
but then gravity still hasn't done its work
gravity doing its work
magnifies them more
and eventually magnifies them a great deal
and turns them into galaxies
and stars and planets and so forth
does that violate the second law?
it sounds like it
sounds like entropy is going the wrong way
it's not
gravity sometimes does things like that
it has that effect
it tends to concentrate things
yeah
but it's not,
no,
it's not violating the second law
nothing can violate the second law
but it does,
it looks somewhat counterintuitive
in that
gravity is rather peculiar from
the point of statistical analysis
to statistical mechanics
most things tend to make things flat and evenly distributed
gravity tends to make things clump
and the clumping actually increases the entropy
the ultimate is to clump them into black holes
and black holes really have a huge amount of entropy
yeah
so,
how is the microwave background reflected in all of this?
the lumps in the microwave background
the lumps in the mic-
these,
yeah,
these are the lumps in the microwave background
so mostly the mass doesn't really count that much
it's the microwave background that predominates here
well,
no,
it's that this stuff gets
imprinted on the microwave background
so,
um
all of this structure
evolved for a period of time
gravity did not become important
until after the surface of last scattering
gravity only became important
after
the universe cooled down to below the
temperature of the surface of the sun
so until that time
the fluctuations were pretty much primordial
just these primordial fluctuations
and they imprinted themselves on
the surface of last scattering
so that what we see in the sky
in the surface of last scattering
is pretty much these primordial
that means that those regions
have to be far enough apart
that the thermal doesn't wash them out
the thermal radiation of the
before the surface of last scattering
yes,
that's right
you said that phi was a scalar field
so that wouldn't be an electromagnetic field
no,
it's not
phi is not an electromagnetic field
so how did all the
so the photons just went with
no,
what happened is all of this energy
look
what happens to that energy when
that thing hits the floor there
some of it gets converted into electromagnetic energy
not very much,
incidentally
most of it just gets converted into heat
but the question is what happened
when this field fell down here
okay
it got,
what could it get turned into
what can that energy get turned into
by the time you settle down at the bottom
what could that energy be
the only thing it could
be is particles of different type
that's the only other thing that
we know that can carry energy
is particles of different type
um
so
so in falling off the edge here
this field energy here
presumably got converted into various kinds of particles
those particles may have been unstable particles
they may have decayed
what did they decay into
they decayed into electrons and positrons
protons and anti-protons
or quarks and anti-quarks
some photons
and when a large amount
of energy is deposited like that
what does it do
it heats,
turns into heat
after a while it just turns into heat
that heat
um
eventually became the
photons,
electrons,
positrons,
protons,
anti-protons
that uh
so the uh
the reheating
is actually where you get the manifestation of the uh
is where you get what
manifestation
of matter inflation
I mean you're getting inflation of the universe
yeah
and but it's at that reheating
point where it manifests as a
inflation in the mass and the particles
well it's where it becomes particles
it's where that energy gets converted into radiation
particles
uh
electrons,
protons
the details of this are not known
the details of how you got from here to electrons,
positrons and so forth
are not in detail known
the only thing you know
is that when you have energy
contained and a slowly expanding incidentally
once you got down here
the universe was much more slowly expanding
on the scale of the
rapid particle reactions that take place
the universe was very slowly expanding
when you got down to here
alright
so what happens if you take a bunch of energy
and put it into a pot
which is very very slowly expanding
well it comes to thermal equilibrium
it somehow eventually equilibrates
and turns into a thermal equilibrium
whatever the temperature happens to be
so the details of what go
on as you go across here
don't really matter much
all you know is a lot
of energy was dumped into a pot
which very very slowly expanded
and that's enough to tell you
that some percentage of it is going to be electrons
some of it's going to be positrons
some of it's going to be whatever it is
let me ask this
how much of physical theory survives
going back behind the clock?
how much gravity does it have?
pretty much gravitation
and quantum field theory
but none of the other physical ingredients exist
you mean up on the top here?
yeah
right
that's pretty much right
no photons,
no particles of mass
and no particles at all right?
because the phi has no
well the only thing that was there
were these fluctuations
these quantum fluctuations in the fields
in particular the quantum fluctuation in this field phi
and uh
it's not worth calling them particles
so the actual act of the reheating
is that the cause of the big bang or
yeah that's
yeah you may if you like think
of the reheating as the big bang
but it's still
it's still expanded many times over
before it became the visible big bang
remember it was so hot
and it went over the edge here
energies here much much higher than
electron positron energies and so forth
much much hotter than the surface of the sun
when it went over here
so the universe was still very opaque
it had to cool down
before it became transparent
so when we look out and
see the surface of the last scattering
that's very late on this scale
where is it on that graph?
it's down at the bottom
that's where the last scattering occurred?
yeah down at the bottom
everything in
everything that we can
measure,
see,
observe
happened at the bottom
so by that stretch then
when you have the quantum fluctuations
then there are really multiple
big big bangs right?
each one as it falls off is causing
well yeah yeah yeah but
well if you like
but on the other hand these fluctuations are on scales
anywhere from very very much bigger
than the horizon
to anywhere as much much smaller
so some of these fluctuations
were small enough in size
that we see them manifested as
galaxies and stars
even planets
that's probably a stretch
galaxies and stars
yeah
wasn't there some discussion of acoustic waves
and all this process doing some
kind of
stuff itself
yeah
right
I guess it has to do with the under density
over density
well this happened
the acoustic waves are a phenomena
that preceded the gravitational things
yeah
we're going to talk about acoustic
I don't know
we have one more class?
alright
the acoustic waves are particularly interesting
because they give us a measuring rod on the sky
alright
they give us the measuring rod
which when we look out
to the surface of the last scattering
I will tell you about
the acoustic waves the next time
ah
you see
lumps of stuff which were
associated with acoustic waves
whose size you know
where do you know them from?
that I'll tell you next time
but because you know their size and because they're not
because you know their distance
you can start looking at triangles
as those acoustic waves
which are
manifestations of
of the processing of these fluctuations
they start to slosh
they basically start to slosh
and they created lumps
and the lumps are of known size
because the laws of
acoustics and so forth are known
we know the size of them we know the distance
and we can measure this angle
that's enough to use some geometry
to tell us that space was either flat
positively curved or negatively curved
and ah
so those acoustic waves are important
and I'll
it's too late for them now
ok
alright do we have another class?
I've lost track
we have one more?
two more?
ok good good good
alright
so the next time I
will tell you a little bit
about how
the geometry of space got measured
from all of this