This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Maybe you could say what omega is,
too.
Do you see that?
Oh,
omega,
big omega.
Big omega.
Yes.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay,
so you asked me what omega is.
Omega is an important quantity,
so let's discuss it.
You go back to the Friedman-Robertson-Walker equations,
and those have the form a dot over
a squared.
We know about that.
On the right-hand side,
we have various things.
We could have a vacuum energy.
Let's talk about today,
or at least for an
era well after the radiation-dominated era
ended at the time,
which includes the present today,
when the equation of state—I'll
just wait a minute.
I'll wait a minute.
All right.
So somebody asked me what capital omega—now,
there are several capital omegas,
incidentally.
Yes.
One of them simply represents the sphere,
the two-sphere or the three-sphere.
That's another—that's a different omega.
In cosmology,
there is another omega,
which has to do with the percentage of matter or
the percentage of energy in different forms,
that come in different forms.
Okay,
so let's—the percentage of the energy that
goes on the right-hand side of the expansion
equation.
The Friedman-Robertson-Walker equation.
The left-hand side,
of course,
is the Hubble constant or the Hubble parameter squared.
The right-hand side can contain,
first of all,
a vacuum energy.
Let's see,
it's not called—we shouldn't call it lambda.
Rho naught,
8 pi g,
8 pi g over 3 times the vacuum energy.
Then,
if we're talking about—.
Rho naught,
8 pi g over 3 times the vacuum energy.
Then,
if we're talking about the era,
which includes today,
when radiation was not very
important and which mostly the
energy density of the universe,
apart from the vacuum energy,
is dominated by ordinary,
non-relativistic,
slowly moving objects,
such as galaxies.
Then there's another term in here,
which is,
let's say,
rho mass.
It's a matter.
It also multiplies the 8 pi g over 3.
So let's put a bracket around it.
The vacuum energy.
The part which doesn't change with expansion.
And that,
of course,
just to remind you,
this part here is some constant,
let's call it
m divided by a cubed.
So it dilutes with expansion.
Rho.
There might also be a radiation part,
but let's ignore it.
It's very,
very small.
After the period when the universe was very,
very hot,
when it cooled below the temperature
of the sun,
let's say,
radiation was not so important,
and the matter part of the energy
density was the important part.
And let's see.
Is there anything we're missing?
Yeah?
We're missing?
Yes.
So we did well.
We're missing things.
Rho S thou shickm.
So let's do Y.
What I did was touching the temperature of the earth.
So if we move along,
I've actually mastered this part,
which is,
if I think about it,
almost all world languages spin 180 degrees,
no matter how many times I shake my weight,
Then all Omega is is it's the fraction of energy
well
Let's put it this way.
Yeah
It's just a fraction of
energy carried by the different components
Okay
It must add up to one
for the simple reason that
Sorry,
I'm saying it not quite right.
I'm saying it not quite right
All right
Yeah
What I want to do is get rid of
this and put it over on the other side
Three over eight pi G let's get rid of
it over here and let's forget this for the moment
Now
These two
Have to add up to this.
This is the square of the Hubble constant
They've got to add up to
this but not if K is
Anything is either plus one or minus one
if K is plus one or minus one.
They don't quite have to add up
to the left hand side here
The thing to do yeah to understand this
the thing to do is to divide this
Equation by what's on the left hand side?
Let's just simplify it and call it Hubble squared.
This is the eight pi three over G
But let's ignore that for
the sake of argument for here
It's just Hubble squared times a number and
that's equal to the sum of three terms
Here's the way to think about it's the
sum of three terms Rho naught plus Rho matter
Minus K over a squared and this is either plus one over a
squared or minus one over a squared or whichever and then divide it
by Hubble squared and then divide it by Hubble squared
divided by Hubble squared one
divided by Hubble squared
These things have to add up to one that's just the trivial I
just divided by the left hand side of the equation to get one
here
All right,
but notice that's not the only thing we could
say we can say if K is equal to zero
These two things have to add up to one
the
energy density in the vacuum
Together with the energy density and
matter must add up to one
otherwise
Space can't be flat now first of all
Since Rho naught and Rho matter vary differently with time
There's no way that this can be constant
So the only way you can have it add
up to one is if Rho matter over H squared
if as if there's no
rho naught
lenses
H
Rho term
So where's which body of Rho
is the most Miller of a
That would be thek here
In Hy这么
you can argue you we work with label
is equal to time
how many Rho sigma
because they are let's call them
symmetry stress at times number of times是不是
add up to one if k is equal to zero.
That's what the equations tell you,
that if rho naught
plus rho matter over h squared add up to one,
then what do you do?
You measure the different
components of the energy,
you add them up,
you divide by the observed Hubble constant
squared,
and here's a prediction.
If space is flat,
if this is not important,
then these
have to add up to one.
The energy density,
the vacuum energy density plus the matter
energy density divided by the square of the
observed Hubble constant must add up to one.
Now these things,
this is called omega.
This is called omega,
and the first term here is
called omega zero,
or sometimes omega vacuum,
or sometimes omega lambda to stand for cosmological
constant.
And the second term here is just called omega zero.
The third term here is called omega matter.
Rho divided by h squared is called omega.
First conclusion is if space is flat,
omega naught plus omega m must add up to one.
So
in that sense,
if k is equal to zero,
omega naught and omega matter are simply the fraction
of energy carried by either vacuum energy or matter energy.
That's what they are.
They can change with time,
but they have to change with
time in such a way
as to add up to one.
But if,
on the other hand,
space is
curved,
if space is curved,
then we can put on the
right-hand side 1 plus k over
a squared h squared,
and then the sums of the omegas
do not have to exactly add up
to 1,
adding them up.
Let me remind you what this means.
You first measure,
to the best of your ability,
astronomically in various ways,
you measure the vacuum energy,
you measure the matter energy,
and you divide it by
Hubble-squared,
the sum.
The sum may or may not add up to 1.
If it adds up to 1
that's an indication that space is flat.
So when people say,
space is flat,
it implies that the sum of these
two have to add up to one,
and in
that case they really are just a
fraction of energy carried by matter and
by vacuum.
Okay?
If these two don't quite add up to one,
for example,
if they add up
to something bigger than one,
that says that k is positive.
It implies that the
universe must be positively curved.
So if you measure Hubble and you measure Rho,
and the ratio is bigger than one,
then space must be positively curved.
If it's
less than one,
then k must be negative
and space must be negatively curved.
So
this is what Omega is.
Omega is a measure...
Yeah?
Does matter include dark matter?
Yes,
it includes dark matter.
And anything else besides just
dark matter and regular old particles?
Yeah,
well,
we could add in here Rho radiation,
but it's such a
small...
It's such a small fraction that it doesn't matter.
So in practice,
it's just matter and vacuum.
Yeah?
Is there some measure of dark
energy other than the Hubble constant?
The Hubble constant itself is
not a measure of dark energy.
It's the way that the Hubble constant changes with time.
The fact that it doesn't
seem to be changing with time,
which is the indication of...
Dark matter.
Dark energy.
Yeah.
The fact that the change,
the time rate of change
of the Hubble constant is decreased,
which is the same thing as saying
that we're on this branch of exponential expansion.
In other words,
if A dot over A is becoming constant,
that's equivalent to saying A is exponentially increasing.
So the observed apparent
tendency toward exponential increase...
is the measurement of...
is the direct evidence for Rho naught.
Okay.
But isn't that the same thing as...
indicating...
I mean,
how is that separate from H?
Ah.
Well,
okay.
Okay.
It's not.
You're asking,
observationally,
how do you tell the difference.
Observationally,
what you actually measure is K.
What?
What you actually measure is K,
and K tells you what Rho naught is.
Observationally,
you measure the fact...
geometrically,
we haven't had a chance to get into this,
but geometrically,
you measure the fact that on large scales,
space is flat.
That tells you that K is equal to zero.
Once you know K is equal to zero,
and you have also measured the matter energy,
then you know what Rho naught has to be.
Given now that you know what Rho naught is,
you can then predict the
way the universe expands with time.
You find out that it's not zero,
and it says that it's accelerated.
So there is a predictive...
there is a prediction in there.
From the fact that space looks flat,
it tells you that Rho naught...
Or that...
You told me Rho naught from the other...
Yeah.
This you measure.
Omega is like one minus something to get here.
You measure this by measuring the ordinary
material in the universe that you can see,
plus the part that you can't see,
which is the dark matter,
which you measure gravitationally by the orbits of...
stars around galaxies.
Well,
now we have like three different ways to measure that.
Yeah,
that's right.
We have three different...
several different ways to measure this,
several ways to measure this.
They're both measured,
and they add up to something close to one.
Sorry.
Yes,
they add up to something...
No,
We also measure the Hubble constant,
and it all adds up,
but on top of that,
the measurement of the curvature itself
is equal to zero.
So you solve for both zero and...
Yeah.
So we have some cross-checks.
There are various cross-checks,
and...
the cross-checks involve the acceleration of the universe,
which tells us that,
the direct measurement of matter and dark matter,
the direct measure of the Hubble constant,
which just looks out to different distant galaxies
and tells you how fast they're moving.
Indeed,
they add up to about one.
And that tells us that space ought to be flat.
And then you measure the curvature of space
by triangulating it,
and you find that it's flat.
Okay,
too good approximation.
So...
So those are the pieces of evidence
that are telling us that,
however we got that way,
we don't know,
but space is very,
very flat
to a couple of percent.
Why is it so flat?
Well,
the theory is that it inflated.
Being flat just means it's very big.
It's very big and very smooth.
Very big and very smooth and very homogeneous.
On scales,
how big?
On scales of billions of light years.
On scales of billions of light years,
in fact,
really tens of billions of light years,
it's very flat,
very homogeneous.
How did it get that way?
The speculation or the conjecture,
and by now it's more than a conjecture,
there's good empirical evidence for it,
that the universe underwent,
in a very early period,
before what we normally call a Big Bang,
the universe underwent a period of exponential expansion,
and that exponential expansion just stretched it out,
stretched it out so much that it appeared
very,
very flat.
Now,
you can overdo a good thing.
The universe is very flat,
and at the time of the Big Bang,
it was very smooth,
but if it were perfectly smooth,
if it had been perfectly smooth,
then there would be no way for structure to form.
A perfectly smooth universe,
one which is perfectly symmetric,
will stay perfectly symmetric.
The equations of gravity and so forth,
will not create lumpiness
out of perfect smoothness.
And so we know that the universe wasn't perfectly smooth,
and if we trace backward
from the current knowledge of galaxies
and the current knowledge of the degree
to which the universe is not homogeneous,
if we trace that backward,
we find out that at the time
when the universe first became transparent,
at the time that radiation decoupled from matter
and so forth,
the time that we normally call the Big Bang,
there was something like about one part
in ten to the fifth
anisotropy and inhomogeneity.
That means if we were
to have plotted at that time
the energy density or mass density
as a function of position,
we would have found that it's very,
very constant,
almost perfectly flat,
but,
and of course I can't draw this on the blackboard,
with about one part in ten to the fifth,
there was a bit of wiggliness in it,
wiggliness in it at different scales.
That wiggliness,
now that's much,
much smaller
than the current.
Now,
by now,
stuff is concentrated into galaxies
and it's highly anisotropic,
not anisotropic,
inhomogeneity,
and it's homogeneous on small scales.
So what happened,
and this is something that we can follow,
starting with this primordial little bit of fluctuation.
Where it came from,
we have some ideas,
but where it came from,
we don't ask at the moment,
we say supposing it was there,
what happened next?
Well,
the little overdensities,
these are regions of overdensity,
they were surrounded by regions
of underdensity,
let's draw those dotted,
and then other regions of overdensity
and so forth,
other regions of overdensity.
The regions of overdensity
gravitated and pulled things toward them.
In fact,
they pulled the matter
immediately in between these two regions,
into the two regions,
increased the overdensity,
and increased the magnitude
of the underdensity.
So,
it's a sort of self-reinforcing feedback
that the more flux,
the more inhomogeneity you have,
the more gravity will lead it to become
yet more inhomogeneous.
This is different than the air in this room.
If we created a perturbation
in the air in the room,
a little wave-like disturbance,
that wave-like disturbance will eventually disappear.
It will disappear,
it will come to thermal equilibrium,
and the room will again become homogeneous
in its content of air,
for example.
So,
gravity is different than other forces.
It tends to lead to this instability
where a little overdensity
will increase itself.
In fact,
if you just took a completely homogeneous universe
and put in just a little bit of overdensity,
it would start sucking the material from nearby
and create an underdensity.
The underdensity would start to grow,
and the overdensity would start to grow,
and eventually the thing would collapse
and form perhaps a galaxy.
Yeah?
Why didn't gravity do that before that?
Ah,
that's a good question.
Okay.
That's a good question.
That is a good question.
Why did it happen at the time
that radiation became unimportant
compared to the other...
All right.
The reason has to do with pressure.
Remember,
we talked about,
we talked about the relation
between pressure and energy density.
I wrote it on the blackboard.
Pressure is equal to something called W.
W is just a parameter.
Times the energy density.
I think I called it epsilon.
Does anybody remember what I called it?
The density of energy?
Rho.
Maybe rho.
Yeah,
we called it rho.
Sure.
Sure we did.
Okay,
so let's see how much you can remember.
for radiation,
what is W?
Ordinary radiation,
electromagnetic radiation
filling a room.
This room is not filled with electromagnetic radiation.
It's mainly filled with atoms.
But blackbody radiation.
For blackbody radiation,
the pressure,
this is not momentum,
it's pressure.
Anybody remember the formula?
One third.
All right.
The energy density was pretty high,
and therefore,
at that early time,
and therefore there was a good deal of pressure.
What positive pressure does is it tends to do
exactly what happens in this room.
Positive pressure tends to homogenize things
if there's positive pressure.
Positive pressure is good for homogenizing things.
It pushes everything out and tends to create
a homogeneous background.
That's in fact why the air in the room
is homogeneous to positive pressure.
Now what about,
what about matter dominated?
Or let's,
before we do that,
what about vacuum dominated?
Anybody remember vacuum dominated?
Yeah,
minus one.
But I just ask you
that to see if you remember.
All right,
but what about,
what about matter dominated?
Zero.
No pressure at all.
That means that if there was no pressure
whatever in this room,
and there was no gravity,
let's start with no pressure and no gravity.
If there were no pressure,
in other words,
if the air molecules exerted no pressure,
how could that be?
What would it take for the,
for the molecules to,
to exert no pressure?
They would have to have zero velocity,
right?
Zero velocity.
They'd be standing perfectly still.
Obviously if they stand perfectly still,
and you create a bit of inhomogeneity,
it's just frozen in.
It doesn't do anything.
Why?
Because the molecules are standing perfectly still.
P equals zero means everything's standing still.
But now,
let's add a little bit
of gravity on top of that.
If we add a little bit
of gravity on top of that,
then the standing still is not enough
to overcome the tendency of gravity
to pull things toward the center.
So it's a kind of competition.
Gravity versus pressure.
Pressure keeps things from imploding.
Gravity can overcome pressure if it's strong enough
and cause something to implode.
Now,
very simply,
during the radiation-dominated era,
the pressure was so high
that it simply prevented gravity
from doing its work and causing,
causing implosion.
Radiation pressure was very high,
and it just prevented,
it just prevented lumps from forming
in the same way that
it does in this room here.
Eventually,
the radiation pressure became negligible.
The pressure due to the motion of galaxies,
the motion of other things,
was also negligible,
and gravity became the most important part.
Gravity became more important than the pressure,
and at that point,
stuff started to contract.
Yeah?
So that was before the,
the difficulty of the 16th.
Don't you need a dissipation mechanism to have...
Yes.
Well,
actually,
you need a dissipation mechanism
to cause the ordinary baryonic matter
to collide.
Not to,
not to have the dark matter
create halos.
So the first thing that happened
is the dark matter,
the fluctuations in the dark matter,
and the fact that the pressure was so small,
started to create lumps of dark matter.
Now,
the dark matter created lumps,
and the ordinary matter sort of followed those lumps.
But then the dissipative mechanisms
caused the ordinary matter
to start to collect near the center of those lumps,
and the dark matter didn't dissipate,
so it just stayed there,
out there as big halos.
So you don't need dissipation,
you don't need...
I know what you're thinking.
There's a form of dissipation in cosmology,
which I was going to
talk about in a few minutes.
There's a form of dissipation in cosmology
which doesn't have to do with the normal things.
It has to do with expansion.
Expansion creates its own kind of dissipation.
And...
the expansion of the dark matter,
expansion replaced dissipation.
Since the dark matter is effectively an ideal gas...
Yeah.
It's an ideal gas at zero temperature.
Would we still see it in its original configuration?
No.
Here was its original configuration,
and gravity started it moving a little bit.
Gravity started it condensing into lumps.
But its potential energy can't go anywhere.
Well,
expansion eats up the...
I was going to talk
a little bit about the relationship
between dissipation and expansion,
and we'll see it because
we'll need it for something else.
But just in an expanding time-dependent universe,
you don't need dissipation to slow things down.
So we'll come to it.
Was the dark matter...
Did the dark matter exist
when there was nothing but energy?
Is dark matter...
What do you mean nothing but energy?
All there ever is is energy of various forms.
You mean radiation energy.
Was dark matter there,
or did it come out of that radiation?
No,
it was there.
In fact,
the...
There are two time scales
which are close to each other,
but not exactly the same.
There's the time scale,
or the time,
at which the universe became transparent.
And there's a separate time scale,
which is the time scale when the matter energy density,
in other words,
the non-relativistic dark matter,
that energy density became larger than the radiation energy.
Those are two crossover points.
One of them is the place where it cooled enough
for atoms to recombine,
and the other is a place where the matter density
in the dark matter exceeded
the radiation pressure
and allowed contraction to start happening.
The contraction started happening a little bit before,
maybe a factor of ten in time,
that sounds like a little bit
on the scale of these things,
happened a little bit
before the universe became transparent.
So unfortunately we can't look back to it.
A little bit before,
the universe was maybe another factor
of ten smaller,
that the gravity started to do its work
on the dark matter.
If the dark matter hadn't been there,
and it was only ordinary matter,
then the start of the contracting phase,
not the contraction of the universe,
but the contraction of these lumps,
would have happened about the same time,
just more or less accidentally,
about the same time that the universe became transparent.
And we might have been able to look back
and actually see it happening,
but we can't.
So it's the dark matter which provides...
Yeah,
two more questions,
and then I want to...yeah.
What of the prologies you've given us
did the elements greater than helium develop?
The elements greater than helium
developed inside stars,
for the most part.
The reason I haven't talked about it very much
is because it's not really considered
to a certain extent part of ordinary cosmology.
It happened too late.
It happened...it's really part of astrophysics.
It's really part of the dynamics of stars.
Almost all of the heavy elements,
except for a tiny,
tiny bit,
which was produced during the Big Bang,
never say none,
I mean,
never say never,
but during the Big Bang,
virtually nothing but hydrogen and helium were produced.
Oh,
yeah,
a bit of...
Well,
that's a form of hydrogen.
Yeah,
right.
A bit of deuterium,
hydrogen,
and helium.
Everything else was almost completely negligible,
although a little bit,
little trace bits of it.
The actual current abundance of it
was mainly made during the stellar evolution
in thermonuclear processes.
So in some sense,
it's not considered part of cosmology.
It's part of...
It's a very basic part of astrophysics.
That's probably taking a narrow view of cosmology.
Yeah.
In addition to the inhomogeneity and position,
there also had to be a little in motion
so the galaxies would have
angular momentum as they came back?
Oh,
they also had some angular momentum,
yeah,
but that was just inherited
from these fluctuations that they started with.
But those were density fluctuations.
Those were density fluctuations,
but they also had some motion.
There was also velocity fluctuations,
density and velocity.
And what we actually see in the sky
is temperature fluctuations across the sky,
which are remnants of these little bits
of overdensity and underdensity,
and also a little bit of their motion.
The motion of the gas at that time
either toward us or away from us
also tended to produce some variation
in the apparent temperature on the sky.
So let's just remember,
I mean,
we look back,
we look way far out
to the surface of last scattering,
and some of that surface of last scattering
is a little bit overdense,
some of it is a little underdense.
The overdense regions tend to look
a little bit hotter to us.
No,
the overdense regions tend to look
a little bit colder to us,
excuse me.
The reason is because the overdense regions
have a little more mass,
they have a little more gravity,
and because they have more gravity,
the photons that come from them
are somewhat redshifted more than they would be
from the other regions.
So from the overdense region,
where gravity is a little bit stronger,
it's pulling the photons back.
So what we see looking from here,
the overdense regions,
the photons look a little bit less energetic.
From the underdense regions,
they look a little bit extra energetic.
But there's also another thing going on.
This gas is in motion.
Some of the motion may be toward us
or toward us,
so there's also a bit of Doppler shift.
And the Doppler shift also,
things which are moving toward us look hotter,
things which are moving away from us look colder.
All of this gets folded in,
and it's complicated,
the difficult numerical calculations
to start with a given initial condition
and to evaluate what flows out of that.
Experts do that.
And the conclusion,
basic conclusion,
was at the time that the Universe became transparent,
or even a little before that,
there was about one part
in 10 to the fifth variation
in the energy density of the Universe.
So on the one hand,
it was very,
very smooth.
It was also,
the Universe is also known to be very flat.
So it was very,
very smooth.
It appears as if it expanded a great deal.
But on the other hand,
if it had expanded infinitely,
you might have thought
that it would iron out these variations here.
So could it be that these variations
are due to the fact that it didn't grow
by an enormous amount?
Well,
I wish that were the case,
but it's not the case.
These fluctuations are there
because of quantum mechanics.
They're quantum,
they're remnants of quantum mechanics,
and they would be there
even if the Universe had expanded
by an infinite amount,
or infinite,
of course,
is silly.
Even if it expanded by 10 to the 10
to the 10 to the 10 to the 10th,
that would not have erased these fluctuations.
Those fluctuations would have been created anew
by quantum mechanics.
So I thought we would
talk about that a little bit
and get to the point
into a little bit
why it is that people believe this crazy theory
that the Universe exponentially expanded.
And remember what it took.
Who doesn't believe it?
What's that?
I don't know.
There are from time to time
people who will put forward other ideas,
and usually the excuse is,
well,
it's just another idea
to provide a straw man,
in other words,
a...
A foil.
A foil,
yeah.
Right.
I don't know anybody who doesn't believe it.
That may be a bad sign
that there's too many people believing,
too many believers.
You know,
I have my friend,
Don Page,
who is an evangelical Christian.
He's also a very famous physicist
and a great one.
And we argue all the time
about whether such things
as whether Jesus can be proved
to be the Son of God and so forth.
And one of his arguments is,
how could so many people believe it
if it weren't true?
I mean...
So maybe inflation is like that.
I don't know.
I don't think so.
I think there's some spectacular
empirical success of the idea.
But in order to tell you
what that empirical success is,
I have to tell you
a little bit more about it.
All right.
Let's remember.
The idea starts with the existence
of a scalar field.
And it's a scalar field
that has a potential energy,
which is just a function
of the field strength.
All right?
So we have a phi,
which is some scalar field.
What it's doing there
and how it comes into the physics
of particle physics and so forth
is unknown.
It's some scalar field called phi,
and it's there for no other purpose
other than to provide some vacuum energy.
The vacuum energy,
or the energy of this field,
it has one component,
which is just due to the usual energy
of an oscillating field,
like the electromagnetic field.
The electromagnetic field
has energies from two sources.
One comes from its time dependence,
that's the electric energy,
and the other comes from
its space dependence,
its gradients,
and that's its magnetic energy.
But this field has another form of energy,
which is just potential energy.
V,
can this be seen?
I'm writing with blue on blue.
No,
okay.
How about pink on blue?
V of phi.
So the energy in this field,
if I wanted to,
I could write it down,
and many of you who have done
some of these classes
would recognize it.
There's a term in the energy density
which contains time derivatives squared.
There's another term
which contains spatial derivatives squared.
This is the energy density.
It's conventional to put a factor of two in there.
So vibration of the field,
that's this one,
gives energy.
Variation of the field in space,
that's this one,
gives energy density.
And then one more term,
a potential energy,
V of phi.
And everybody will agree
that scalar fields typically
do have such potentials.
An example would be the Higgs field,
which some of you may or may not know about,
but that's one which we empirically
have good reason to believe in,
and that has a V of phi.
So V of phi is not an unusual thing
or a peculiar thing,
but its shape is a little bit unusual
and contrived.
Contrived meaning to say
that you'd have to maybe tune some parameters.
V of phi is a function of phi.
Well,
there are zillions of functions around.
Most of them are not very simple.
One is a simple function of phi.
Phi is a simple function.
Phi squared is not too complicated a function.
Phi cubed is pretty simple.
If you start adding things like
one plus phi plus phi squared,
you can make some pretty complicated functions.
And so it is with V of phi.
It's a complicated-looking function,
meaning to say it's not the thing
that you might have written down
on your first calculus examination.
But nevertheless,
it has to have a shape
which looks something like this.
It has to be fairly flat over some range.
Over some range,
it has to be fairly flat.
Not absolutely flat.
You don't want it to be absolutely flat.
You want it to have
a little bit of a slope,
a little bit of slope downward.
And then at some critical value of phi,
the bottom drops out
and it falls away like so.
Now it doesn't quite fall to zero.
It falls to something very small,
though.
And in Planck units,
in natural units,
units,
what are Planck units?
Planck units are units
in which c is equal to one.
That's not hard to think about.
Planck's constant is equal to one.
And Newton's constant are equal to one.
Those are called Planck units.
They're units in which the natural unit of length
is the Planck length,
which is 10 to the minus 33 centimeters.
The natural unit of time
is 10 to the minus 42 seconds.
And the natural unit of mass,
anybody know what the Planck mass is?
How much?
10 to the minus 5 grams.
All right,
so it's some units.
So some natural units
in which the most basic constants of nature
are equal to one.
This falls down to something very small,
about 10 to the minus 123.
That's the vacuum energy today.
Up here,
it was larger.
It was still small in Planck units.
We know that it could not have been large
on the Planck scale.
It was perhaps much,
much bigger than this,
but much,
much smaller than Planck.
The universe started,
what does it mean to say
the universe started over here?
What does it mean to say?
This is not a place,
incidentally.
This is a value of the field.
What does it mean to say
the universe started at this point?
When I say started,
I don't mean to say that
it literally started at that point.
I mean to say we can trace it back
to a certain starting point,
which was more or less like this.
And the details of this,
incidentally,
are not well known.
This is more of a cartoon of a situation
whose details are really somewhat unknown.
But more or less like this.
What does it mean to say the universe started
at a particular point on this plot?
Well,
it means to say that the universe started
with the field value being something,
having some value,
filling space.
Now,
it's not important
whether it varies
from place to place at this point,
because what's going to happen is
the universe is going to expand so much
that wrinkles in phi
will get enormously stretched out,
and the region where we sit
is deep in the interior
of one of these very stretched out regions.
And so for practical purposes,
we might as well assume
that after a little while up here,
the universe expanded by so much
that our part of it,
and perhaps much more than that,
was very,
very ironed out.
Why did the universe expand so fast?
Well,
that's the Robertson-Walker equation,
or the Friedman-Robertson-Walker equation,
and V of phi,
V of phi,
incidentally,
is something which does not,
um,
what's the word I'm looking for,
does not dilute.
So it's like vacuum energy.
In fact,
the V of phi was perfectly flat
it would be exactly the same
as vacuum energy.
If for some reason
the universe just sat at a point,
in other words,
the phi did not change
and it just sat there,
then the value of the potential energy
at that point would be vacuum energy.
So as long as this is pretty flat,
the universe will be exponentially expanding
with an exponential factor
with a Hubble constant
which will be proportional
to the square root of this vacuum energy,
the square root of V of phi.
I'm leaving out eight pi's and that sort of thing.
Let's just put proportional to,
the Hubble constant will expand
proportional to the square root of V of phi,
and the universe will exponentially expand
like e to the h t.
That will continue,
yeah.
What is phi to phi now?
What's the space?
Is the field on some version of space-time?
Yeah.
But what is...
The field.
But what is that space-time?
Do we know anything about that space-time?
We don't have Einstein's field equations,
right?
Oh yes,
we do.
We do.
Absolutely.
This is...
That is Einstein's field equation.
Okay,
but everything else got,
okay.
Yeah,
yeah,
yeah.
Oh yes.
Yes,
yes,
this is Einstein's field equation.
And if we wanted to simplify it,
or we would just write
for rho naught plus rho matter,
we would just write V,
V of phi,
for the energy density.
That's good enough as long as phi is slowly varying.
What happens to these pieces of the energy?
Well,
as long as phi is moving slowly with time,
this is not important.
And as long as it's been stretched out,
as long as things have
been stretched out a great deal,
then the gradient of phi is small.
So these are unimportant,
and V of phi is
the big thing in the energy
while you're up on the top here.
Then of course you eventually slide down this shallow hill.
We can talk about the
dynamics of that in a moment.
You slide down this shallow hill
until you get to the edge,
and then plop,
down you go.
In this picture,
cosmology,
all of cosmology is a roll
from up on the top of a potential,
up here somewheres,
down to the bottom.
Almost everything that we know about,
almost everything we know about,
and certainly everything we can observe,
happened after the universe plopped to the bottom down here.
With the exception of this exponential expansion,
almost all of which,
in fact all of which,
took place up on the top here.
Going over the edge is where the vacuum energy
was converted into the energy of particles,
radiation,
and other more familiar forms of energy,
but not all of it.
Some little bit of it
was left over as vacuum energy.
Why?
We don't know.
This is just a picture that emerges from
lots and lots of detailed observation.
So when the big U went
over the edge of the hill here,
off the edge of the cliff,
that's the place where vacuum energy,
this vacuum energy,
not this vacuum energy here,
but this big vacuum energy up here,
was converted into ordinary energy,
ordinary things,
including dark matter.
Dark matter and other things.
I can't think of any known process that converts
vacuum energy into matter energy.
Is there one?
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
This field,
like any other field,
has quanta associated with it.
When the field rolls down to here
and oscillates back and forth,
those quanta have energy.
This is a kind of harmonic oscillator.
It oscillates back and forth here.
The energy of those harmonic oscillators
is another way of speaking about the quanta,
the energy of the quanta of that field.
So when this field,
which is called the inflaton,
it has a name.
Once you name it,
you no longer ask why it exists.
You just say it's the inflaton.
The inflaton field goes over the edge,
and it starts ringing down here.
It starts oscillating.
Those oscillations are another way of talking about
the particles,
the field quanta,
which are the field quanta
associated with this particular field.
All right?
Now,
those field quanta may or may not be stable.
If they were perfectly stable,
that's all that would exist.
There would be no way of transferring that energy
to other kinds of energy.
But typically,
the situation with scalar particles,
like the Higgs particle or other scalar fields,
is they're unstable,
and they decay.
So one of these particles forming this sloshing stuff here,
let's call it the inflaton,
can decay.
What can it decay into?
Who knows?
Photons,
electrons,
E plus,
E minus.
And that's the way the energy gets converted
from the sloshing of this inflaton field
into ordinary energy.
Or ordinary particles.
Now,
do we know enough about this field
to say that this must happen?
No,
but we know enough about nature
to say that it must happen.
Most of the energy in the universe
is composed of either dark matter or...
One thing this could be,
the sloshing around in here,
which is a form of energy,
could be the dark matter.
But we still have to get
some of it out into photons
and protons and neutrons and so forth.
So some decays of this type must have happened.
That's the only way to get it to transfer.
But there's all kinds of processes
that can convert this sloshing stuff
into ordinary particles.
So that's happening even today,
the conversion of...
Dark matter could be decaying.
If in fact this is connected with dark matter,
we don't know what dark matter is with precision.
Yeah,
that could be happening today.
Today in this picture,
we're really stuck down at the bottom here.
The sloshing ended,
but...
If I get to it,
I'll show you why the sloshing ended.
So what we normally think of as
the vacuum energy
is really the residual effect of this vacuum energy.
Yeah.
Do you think there's some kind of...
There may be some connection between the UV-IR connection
and the...
I don't know.
Let's get to an important point here.
You might ask if...
Well,
first of all,
if you started up on the top here
and you fell over the edge,
wouldn't you start...
By energy conservation,
wouldn't you swing back and forth here
and perhaps come back up onto the top?
Or at minimum,
wouldn't you expect to endlessly swing back and forth here?
Is there any reason why this energy would get degraded
as if there was dissipation,
as if there were friction,
which would cause this field
to slide down to the bottom?
Now,
think of a mechanical analogy.
The mechanical analogy is a particle rolling
on a potential like this.
Why does it come to rest down here?
Does it come to rest down here?
The answer is it better come to rest down here
because if it didn't,
our universe would be filled
with this enormous quantity of energy,
and it's not.
It's pretty much empty space.
How did it get to be empty space?
Where did all that energy go?
And I'm going to tell you it dissipated.
You say,
what do you mean it dissipated?
Dissipated into what?
Well,
there's a form of dissipation
which takes place in cosmology
that doesn't have to do with...
genuine friction.
It resembles friction very much,
but it is actually due to the expansion of space.
So I thought I would take a couple of minutes
and show you where that comes from.
To do that,
you'll have to recall something
which not everybody in the room may know,
but it's Lagrange's equations of motion.
This is the expression for an energy.
Let's suppose
that the field did not vary with position in space.
Just to make the story simple,
let's ignore the gradients of the field
with respect to position in space.
Why?
Because it's gotten itself stretched out so much
that this is unimportant.
Let's assume that's unimportant.
All right,
this is the potential energy.
This looks like a kinetic energy of something.
It's not a kinetic energy of something.
It's not the motion of a particle,
but mathematically,
it's proportional to the square of a time derivative.
It looks like a kinetic energy
of a degree of freedom,
which in this case is a field,
and this looks like a potential energy.
What would be the Lagrangian?
This would be the energy.
What would be the Lagrangian of such a thing?
Energy is T plus V.
Lagrangian is T minus V.
T stands for kinetic energy.
So the Lagrangian...
So the Lagrangian is T minus V.
Now,
actually,
this is not the Lagrangian.
This is the Lagrange density.
You have to multiply it by the volume of space.
This was not the potential energy.
This was the potential energy density.
To get the potential energy,
you have to multiply it by the volume of space,
right?
Same here.
This was energy density.
So what's the volume of space?
Well,
A cubed.
A cubed of time.
So now,
if we know how A cubed behaves with time,
we have the Lagrangian of this field,
phi.
Okay,
let's work out its equation of motion.
Do you remember how to work out
the equation of motion for Lagrangian?
You take partial of L with respect to phi dot.
That's A of T cubed times phi dot.
And then take the time derivative of that.
That's the left-hand side.
What about the right-hand side?
Anybody remember?
Dv d phi.
Like a force.
Like dv dx.
Like dv dx,
except there's the A cubed here.
A cubed dv or dv d phi.
dv d phi is the slope.
And it's the force term
which creates what would be an ordinary acceleration
if A was constant with time.
But A is not constant with time,
so we have a little bit of work to do
to take this derivative.
To take the derivative,
what is the derivative?
Well,
the first term,
the d by dt acts on the phi dot.
And that gives us A cubed times phi double dot,
which is like the acceleration.
Not the acceleration of the expansion of the universe,
but it's just the acceleration of this field phi,
the second time derivative of phi.
That's one term.
What's the other term?
The other term comes from differentiating the A cubed.
And that's 3A squared of t times what?
Times A dot times phi dot.
And that's equal to A cubed dv d phi.
But I want to divide both
sides of the equation by A cubed,
just to get rid of as
many A cubed as I can.
All right?
So on the right-hand side,
I'll just have dv d phi.
And on the left-hand side,
I'll get rid of this A cubed.
I'll get rid of A squared,
but it will leave me with
a 1 over A in the denominator.
So let's put 1 over A,
A dot over A.
What's A dot over A?
There's another name for it.
Not the square root of H.
It's H.
Right.
Just H.
So this is the Hubble constant.
Now,
have you ever seen...
Oh,
this is minus.
There should be a minus here.
Minus dv d phi.
Yeah,
minus dv d phi.
Force is proportional to minus
the derivative of the potential energy.
Have you ever seen an equation of motion
with a single phi dot in it like that?
Viscosity.
A ball or a rock falling through water.
This is essentially the equation of motion
of a rock falling through water.
Here's the gravitational force on it,
dv d phi,
and it's proportional to the slope here.
Here's the acceleration,
and here's the viscous drag force.
Here's the viscous drag force.
So,
believe it or not,
this is called Hubble friction.
Hubble friction.
It's not real friction.
It's due to the time dependence
of the size of the universe.
That's where it came from.
It came from differentiating A.
But it resembles very,
very closely
the equation of motion for an
object moving through a viscous fluid.
And if V has a more or less uniform slope,
it's like an object falling through a viscous fluid
under the presence of a uniform force.
What happens under those
circumstances to the falling object?
It comes to some terminal velocity.
It comes to some terminal velocity very quickly.
A drop of rock in water,
and it very quickly comes to terminal velocity.
So,
the universe starts sliding down this hill.
If this is shallow enough,
it goes very slowly down the hill here.
And as it goes down the hill,
viscous friction,
or Hubble viscosity,
or whatever it should be called,
Hubble damping,
brings it very quickly to a terminal velocity,
and it just slides down this hill slowly
till it gets to the end.
During the time that it's sliding down the hill,
or sliding down a hill which is of very,
very shallow nature,
there's some vacuum energy.
And that vacuum energy
causes almost exact exponential expansion.
When I say almost exact,
it's not exactly
because there's some slope here,
so the vacuum energy changes from one time to another.
But if this is reasonably flat,
the universe will grow exponentially,
approximately,
with a constant H here,
and then it will come
to the end and fall down.
And how many times does
the size of the universe double?
Well,
that depends on how shallow this is,
how broad it is,
and how high it is.
The height of it goes into the coefficient here,
goes into the time constant here.
The width of it and the slope of it
determine just how long it's going to stay.
And the height of it stays up
on the top of the hill there.
So by making it broad enough and flat enough,
you can make the universe expand
as many times as you like
during this period of inflation.
Okay,
so then you would say,
if it exponentiates by many,
many,
many orders of magnitude,
why doesn't that iron out all
of the other orders of magnitude?
Well,
it's not because of the variation in the field.
Why does it have any variation at all
by the time it gets over the edge here?
What is that variation?
That variation is that small little bit
that's necessary for galaxies to form.
So on the one hand,
you've explained the flatness of the universe
and the homogeneity,
but it looks as though you might have overdone it.
You might have overdone it
and lost the possibility of explaining
the existence of galaxies.
Well,
marvelously,
that's not exactly right.
So to understand why it's not exactly right,
we have to take some things from quantum mechanics.
Let's suppose that the universe was not expanding,
and just the simplest possibility,
let's forget the expansion of the universe for a moment,
but let's add quantum mechanics
to this picture of a field,
a field filling space,
where the field,
because of the expansion,
but we're going to forget the expansion,
but because of the expansion,
the field has gotten extremely ironed out,
so it's almost perfectly homogeneous,
but quantum mechanics makes it fluctuate.
Quantum mechanics makes it fluctuate.
One way of seeing the fact that quantum mechanics
makes it fluctuate
is just by looking at the similarity
of the field of its energy
plus V of phi.
By looking at the similarity
of such a field with
the motion of an ordinary particle.
This is like kinetic energy,
and there's some potential energy over here,
plus another term over here.
Why is it?
It's kind of like a harmonic oscillator.
This V of phi could conceivably be
a harmonic oscillator potential,
but there's also a harmonic oscillator potential
in here,
hidden in here.
Why is it that harmonic oscillators
have zero-point energy?
They have zero-point energy
because of the uncertainty principle.
You cannot have phi being fixed and locked,
and at the same time have the velocity of phi
be fixed and locked.
It's the uncertainty principle.
The uncertainty principle,
in the same way that the uncertainty principle
tells you that there's zero-point energy
of a harmonic oscillator,
ground state energy,
whatever it's called,
the same mathematics tells you that phi
is necessarily,
even in its ground state,
even when all the energy is sucked out of it,
it's still oscillating with zero-point energy.
So that means if you were to look microscopically
at this field,
you would see it constantly
in a state of agitation,
even just in the state of absolutely lowest energy.
Okay,
why don't we notice those fluctuations?
And for the most part,
we don't notice them,
because they're too rapid.
They take place too rapidly for most observations.
And we average over them.
Okay,
we average over them.
Most such fluctuations are fairly short wavelength,
and the short wavelengths oscillate very fast.
And because they oscillate fast,
we don't notice them.
But in cosmology,
the situation is a little bit different.
And to understand how the situation is different,
you have to take into account
the expansion of the universe.
That's the main new thing,
Okay,
let's draw the universe.
Horizontal is space,
as always.
Vertical is time.
And x goes horizontally.
x is the coordinate x.
It doesn't measure distance.
It measures coordinate along here.
Here are the various galaxies,
for example.
I'm putting them equally spaced,
which of course they're not.
And of course the world is three-dimensional,
not one-dimensional.
But these are the galaxies.
I've approximated them by saying they're equally spaced,
and they're just vertical lines.
But the distance between galaxies
is not the difference in x,
but what is it?
Ax.
Ax,
a being scale factor.
So distance is a of two.
So it's e to the h times delta x,
where delta x might be the distance
in coordinate between two points.
So if a is,
let's imagine now
that a is exponentially expanding,
e to the h times delta x.
That means the distance between galaxies
on the average,
if they're far enough apart,
is expanding exponentially.
Delta x is of course not expanding exponentially,
delta x is just a fixed coordinate positions
of the galaxies.
You can think of it as their names.
But it's the scale factor
which is increasing exponentially.
Now what happens to a wave in here?
What happens to a typical wave
as the universe expands?
It gets stretched out,
but in these coordinates it's not stretched.
In these coordinates it stays more or less stretched.
It's more or less the same with time.
It has a fixed wavelength in x,
but that means an exponentially growing wavelength
in proper distance.
So the wave more or less has the same profile.
It may be oscillating,
but it's not expanding on this diagram,
because this diagram already has the expansion built in
as the expansion of the distance between these points.
But it oscillates.
The field oscillates.
In general it oscillates,
unless its wavelength is too long.
If its wavelength is too long,
it doesn't oscillate.
So let me explain why it doesn't oscillate.
Supposing we have...
Why does a wave oscillate,
first of all?
Why does an ordinary electromagnetic wave oscillate?
Think of a rope
stretched between two points.
And perhaps the rope has some curvature over here.
Maybe it does,
maybe it doesn't.
It may have some curvature,
it may not.
Why does the rope over here get pulled down?
It gets pulled down by its neighbors,
by the neighboring segments of rope,
which would typically be down here.
But what if the neighboring
segment of rope was up here?
Which way would it get pulled?
Up.
So the only way to know
which way it's going to get pulled
is to know what the neighbors are doing.
In particular...
Well,
yes,
to know what the neighbors are doing.
But supposing
the size of the wave here
was about as big as the horizon.
About as big as the horizon.
Remember what the horizon is.
The horizon is the distance beyond which
things are moving away from you
faster than the speed of light.
You can never get any information
from beyond the horizon.
That's a principle.
Nothing can communicate from behind the horizon.
So here's a piece of rope
that if the scale is big enough
for the variation of the position of the rope,
one could imagine
that this piece of rope
is out beyond the horizon.
Supposing this piece of rope
was out beyond the horizon,
can it have any influence on this piece?
No.
So it better be
that the tendency to pull on this piece of rope
or this piece of field,
this little piece of field in here,
that had better be
tremendously diminished
when the wavelength of the wave
becomes about equal
to the size of the horizon.
When the wavelength is longer
than the size of the horizon,
then the pieces which are pulling
on a piece over here
are out beyond the horizon.
And the answer is,
if you follow the mathematics,
that when waves get longer wavelength
than the size of the horizon,
they freeze.
They're not pulled back by the neighbors
and they just freeze.
Their motion becomes frozen.
Why should I worry about waves?
I'm worried about quantum fields,
my goodness.
What are we talking about?
Waves longer than the size of the horizon?
Well,
the point is
that the universe is expanding.
So take a wave of a certain wavelength
and push it ahead in time.
On this graph,
it has the same wavelength.
But the distance between these points
exponentially grows.
So no matter how small
the wavelength is to start with,
eventually,
as the universe grows and stretches,
each hidden wave,
each zero-point oscillation,
will eventually have a wavelength
longer than the size of the horizon.
When that happens,
the wave stops oscillating.
It just stops oscillating.
It is no longer pulled back and it freezes.
It just freezes.
So,
the wave is not pulled back.
if we wait long enough,
let's suppose this wavelength here is,
I don't know,
10 to the minus 8 centimeters.
Some small wavelength.
And it's oscillating like mad
because it's being pulled back into place by its neighbors.
But as time goes on,
this 10 to the minus 8 centimeters
grows to the point
where it may be as big as the horizon.
Will be as big as the horizon.
When that happens,
all of a sudden,
the wave freezes.
So,
the zero-point oscillations
in an expanding universe,
in an exponentially expanding universe,
the zero-point oscillations
become frozen.
First,
the longer wavelength ones
become frozen.
So,
eventually,
this wave over here will become frozen.
But then,
what about shorter wavelengths?
Shorter wavelengths
will take a longer time,
but they will also eventually
become frozen.
Even the very shortest wavelengths
that you can imagine
will eventually become frozen.
Yeah?
If you do the horizon distance
on the origin of that graph,
would it kind of
asymptotically go to the vertical axis?
Yeah,
that's a good point.
All right,
so let's draw
what the horizon would look like.
Yeah.
The horizon,
what is the horizon?
let's work out what the size of the horizon.
The horizon is the distance
that corresponds to the speed of light
using the Hubble formula.
All right,
so it's velocity,
sorry,
distance,
I always have to work this out.
Distance is,
sorry,
velocity is equal to
Hubble times distance.
The place,
the distance at which,
this is the speed of light,
that's called the horizon,
and that distance,
therefore,
is the speed of light
divided by the Hubble constant.
That's the distance that corresponds
to the distance to the horizon.
All right?
So that's the distance,
what did you ask me?
You asked me a question.
Doesn't it approach the
Oh,
yeah,
right,
right.
Yes,
yes,
it does.
The distance is a fixed number.
The distance to the horizon is fixed.
It's just C over H,
and in an exponentially expanding universe,
H is fixed.
All right,
but the distances on this graph
are exponentially increasing.
So a fixed distance on this graph
looks smaller and smaller.
A fixed distance of Hubble size,
this is called Hubble size,
this distance here,
would look smaller and smaller
because it's being compared with
exponentially growing distances.
So that means that the horizon size
would look like this,
exponentially getting smaller and smaller with time,
and that's why each wave
will eventually,
it's frozen,
becomes frozen
when its wavelength gets longer
than the horizon size.
Okay?
Or when the horizon
in coordinate distance
is shrunken to be smaller than the,
all right.
Okay,
so each wave gets frozen,
and they pile up on top of each other.
They pile up on top of each other,
each one frozen,
and what was originally quantum fluctuations,
very rapidly oscillating,
become large scale fluctuations of the field
which grow and which pile
up on top of each other
and which just freeze.
Okay?
At the end of this,
by the time you get to here,
all these waves are piled up
and made some sort of variation in the field,
some sort of frozen variation in the field.
And so the next question is,
when this field which now varies from,
and notice,
notice,
it does not matter
how long it's been inflating.
It could have been inflating,
you know,
so long that the universe is 10 to the
10 to the 10 to the 10 to the 10,
and would go on all night.
That's how big,
that's how much bigger it is.
That's how much it would be ironed out.
But nevertheless,
as time goes on,
new fluctuations get frozen.
New waves become frozen.
More and more of them become frozen.
And so the end result is there's always a variation
that's kind of a fossil remnant
of early vacuum fluctuations
that got frozen into the system,
and they get frozen in,
pile up on top of each other,
and become a large scale,
massive macroscopic variation of the field.
Yeah.
What happens to the amplitude as it gets bigger?
What happens what?
The amplitude of the fluctuation,
is it scaling down?
Yeah,
it's scaling down.
It's diluting at the same time.
Its energy density is diluting as it expands.
So in fact,
I mean,
it doesn't get out of control
from the point of view of energy density,
but it just keeps making,
you know,
more oscillations top,
piled up on more oscillations.
And the effect is a kind of stationary,
steady state variation that's,
yeah.
That's what I was going to ask.
You get to a steady state where the,
where as time goes on,
you erase the earlier.
Well,
you stretch them out.
You stretch them out.
Yeah.
And new ones keep coming in.
You stretch them out so
that they're bigger than the horizon.
So if you look at it at one time
and look at it two hours later
or two years or whatever the hell it is.
Right.
It looks the same.
That's called a scale invariant spectrum.
Scale invariant spectrum.
And one of the things that has been known
about the initial.
It seems like you were saying
that the older fluctuations were ossified
by being frozen.
Right.
But it sounds like what you're really saying is.
Well,
they were ossified first.
Not only were they ossified,
they were straight out.
They were ossified and then stretched.
But they're not seen as fluctuations
because the wavelength is so long.
They're older.
I mean,
they're beyond the horizon.
Okay.
Remember,
there was the horizon.
There were two different horizon scales.
There was the horizon up here
and there's the horizon down here.
The horizon up here just means
the distance scale associated
with the vacuum energy in here.
Okay.
The Hubble scale down here means
the distance scale associated
with this energy density.
They're very different.
There's a small horizon up.
Right.
A small horizon up here.
These waves become ossified
when they move.
During this era,
the waves get ossified
when they get bigger
and bigger.
Then the horizon associated
with this energy scale.
This could be some microscopically small thing
from our point of view.
Right?
Then they get frozen.
So they're not seen as fluctuations
even though they're frozen.
They're frozen.
At a point where it's actually
far enough away that when we get it small,
our horizon grows again to see it?
That's right.
Our horizon grows.
What happens at first
is that these waves get bigger
than the temporary...
It's really a false horizon,
but a temporary horizon over here.
But then the horizon grows.
When it rolls down here,
the horizon suddenly turns that way,
and these waves come back into the horizon
and they start to oscillate again.
They start to fluctuate again.
But by that time,
they're stretched out
on enormously large scales,
and they're piled up
so you have a huge pile of waves
macroscopic structures,
and those macroscopic structures
start to slosh around again.
In fact,
that's really what happens.
They start to slosh around again.
The words we use is
they go out of the horizon
and come back into the horizon.
So they expand out beyond this temporary horizon
and then get swallowed up by the larger horizon,
at which point they become a very large,
and they start to slosh around again.
Right.
But as I said,
by the time they start sloshing around again,
they're big,
macroscopic...
Take a long time to swing.
Right,
and take a long time to swing.
All that,
when the field was flat up there,
all those beef holdings occurred
in really a very small amount of time.
Well,
we don't know how long.
let's just say,
take the example last week,
like you say,
maybe 60 people.
Oh,
that would be a very,
very small amount of time.
I mean,
by macroscopic standards,
yes.
Very,
very small.
I don't know if you can answer this
in the timing game,
but how did you calculate the power spectrum
that you get?
Well,
just from this picture,
the waves keep...
different wavelengths
keep passing out of the horizon,
but at each stage,
the same thing is happening,
exactly the same thing is happening
as the previous stage,
and it's on a logarithmic scale.
One can calculate it and see
that at each stage,
it looks the same,
except everything's scaled up
and it reaches this sort of stationary phase.
That's a little too complicated to go into,
but it does achieve this scale invariant behavior
where the same,
more or less the same
amplitude of oscillation
for every wavelength.
That's not exactly true,
but close to it.
And the result is
a particular structure
of frozen-in oscillate,
frozen-in density variations.
Okay,
now let's go a little bit further
and talk about what happens
when you go over the edge here.
When you go over the edge,
those fluctuations get magnified.
Not magnified,
not magnified in spatial size,
but magnified in amplitude,
or in energy density.
The energy density,
the energy variation from place to place
gets magnified.
And it gets magnified proportional,
or inversely proportional,
to how slowly the field,
no,
inversely proportional
to how fast the field
was rolling down here.
The flatter it is,
the smaller the terminal velocity
as it's rolling down here.
The smaller the terminal velocity,
you might think this is a little bit
counterintuitive,
but the smaller
the terminal velocity,
the bigger the variation
in the energy density
will be after you
fall off the edge here.
So let me just show you why that is.
I talked about it a little bit last time.
I was a little bit tired last time.
So let me just say
a little bit more about it.
Okay,
so the field is varying
from place to place because of these
quantum fluctuations.
Let's say to the right
is red,
and to the left
is blue.
Then there will be
regions which are redder,
regions which are
let me use green,
here's green
back here,
and
red over here.
So there will be greener regions
and red regions,
and green regions
and red regions.
Now,
I don't really mean
back here and up here,
I just mean small deviations
from here to here.
Small fluctuations.
This is an effect
that has to be fairly small,
otherwise it would
create too much random mess in the universe.
So it's a small effect,
but there are greener regions
slightly to the left,
and redder regions
slightly to the right.
Naturally,
the redder regions
fall off the edge
before the greener regions.
Okay?
Supposing a little red region over here
falls off the edge
of the cliff.
It falls off the edge of the cliff,
and all of this
vacuum energy,
let's suppose all of it
for simplicity,
all of it
got converted to radiation energy.
That's a simplified
story,
but let's
suppose it just got all turned
into photons and so forth.
So let's see,
the redder
region after,
because
it was a little bit ahead,
it was a little bit ahead
moving toward the edge of the cliff,
it got there first
and fell off the edge.
So this redder region
would have
all of its energy
turned into
a kind of energy
which dilutes with expansion.
The greener
energy,
which is still up on the top
here,
is still vacuum energy.
It does not dilute.
Okay?
So what
happens to the energy density in here?
The energy
density in there decreases.
It decreases
just
by the standard rules.
By the time you're down off this cliff,
you're in a
world now which is pretty much
like ordinary cosmology.
Ordinary materialism
material,
radiation
or whatever.
If it were
radiation,
we know the energy density
in there would go as 1 over 8 to the
fourth.
The
scale factor in that region or the
expansion factor in that region would be
growing and the
effect would be that the energy density
in there decreased.
Okay?
What about
the energy density in the greener region
after it fell off the
edge of the cliff?
It would be higher than the red.
It would be higher because it fell off
later.
So by the time
a bit of green energy
goes over the edge,
the red
energy has already been redshifted.
It has already been
redshifted or diluted by
expansion,
whereas the greener
regions are
not yet diluted.
But if you wait a little more,
the redder regions will get even more diluted.
The green region will start
to get diluted.
And
the even greener region
will come and fall over the edge
and make a yet higher
energy density region.
This is the way that
oh,
and what is this effect proportional to?
Well,
the slower
the average motion,
the longer the time scale
between
different pieces falling over
the edge.
If everything is moving
extremely slowly,
even if one point is
slightly ahead of the other here,
if it's moving extremely slowly,
there will be a large
gap in time between
the time the first piece rolls
off and the time the second piece rolls off.
That means
that the red energy will get
highly diluted by the time
the green energy falls off.
So the flatter this is,
and the slower it moves,
the larger will be the
variations in the energy density from
place to place.
The final upshot
is a spectrum of
fluctuations of energy density
which is
the remnant of all of this
which depends,
it depends on the height of this,
it depends on the width,
it doesn't depend much on the width,
but it depends on the slope a little bit.
Why the slope?
Because the terminal velocity depends on the slope,
and the slower the terminal velocity,
the bigger
will be the fluctuations.
It doesn't depend much on the width.
So for that reason we can't say
how many e-foldings took place.
But it depends on the height
and the slope
in such a way that the shallower
the slope,
the bigger the fluctuations.
Also,
the higher it is,
the bigger the fluctuations.
The higher it is,
the more energy density,
the larger will be the fluctuations
and the flatter.
And there's a formula that you can work out.
That will tell you how big the fluctuations are.
But the point is
that
the detailed result
of such an analysis
fits extremely well
with
with empirical data.
So what's the height and the slope?
No.
Unfortunately you cannot tell what
the height and the slope is.
You can only tell a combination
of the height and the slope.
There's one combination
of the height and the slope
that you can predict.
And,
uh,
well,
okay,
that's not quite true.
Okay,
not quite true.
Um,
if the height is high enough,
then
there are,
in addition
to the production of these density fluctuations,
there are production
during the gravitational era here,
or during this inflationary era,
there are also gravitational waves produced.
And so
admixed into this
density fluctuation
and the temperature fluctuation
on the sky,
there may be also gravitational waves
that are visible.
If there are gravitational waves,
that will tell us how high it is.
But
if it's too low,
then there won't be visible gravitational waves
and that's possibly the case,
very likely the case.
So it's going to wait
until the gravitational waves
can be detected
from this period,
and that will give us some idea
of how high it is.
Most likely it will just tell us
it's lower than a certain amount.
If the energy density were any bigger,
I'll tell you the,
in Planck units,
if the energy density
were bigger than about
10 to the minus 14th,
which may sound small,
if the energy density
were bigger than about
10 to the minus 14th,
then we would have already been
swamped by gravitational waves from it.
So we know that the energy density
is less than 10 to the minus 14th
because we were not swamped
by gravitational waves.
On the other hand,
if it's less than about 10 to the minus 16th,
then we have no chance of seeing
the gravitational waves,
and so there's a narrow little window
which we have no reason to believe is...
Something like that,
I think.
Narrow little window
where you could see gravitational waves.
10 to the minus 14th
might actually be 10 to the minus...
I don't remember the precise numbers,
but it's in that ballpark.
There's only a narrow region
of parameter space
where you could see these...
Is the units of Planck
of mass over Planck volume?
Is that what you refer to?
10 to the minus 16th
is something like that?
What units are those?
Mass to the fourth.
Why is it mass to the fourth?
Let me explain why it's mass to the fourth.
First of all,
if you set c equal to 1
and h-bar equal to 1,
those are natural things to do,
then mass
is the same as inverse length.
Mass is the same as inverse length.
So let's just...
Mass and inverse length are the same thing.
What did you ask me?
I forgot.
Oh,
what are the units of the energy?
Alright.
It's energy density,
first of all.
Energy density.
So it's energy
divided by length cubed.
And if 1 over length
is the same as energy,
then it's energy to the fourth.
Okay.
So it's m Planck to the fourth
of the units.
Right.
And
and
empirically,
we know from the lack
of gravitational waves
in the spectrum of
in the cosmic
background spectrum
that
it's less than
maybe it's 10 to the minus 12,
I don't remember exactly,
but
and the problem is
that if it was another decade
or two smaller than that,
you would have no chance of seeing it.
So you're caught between
being swamped by it
well,
you're not swamped by it,
and a couple of decades
down and you couldn't see it.
Would swamp-like meaning
affect our cosmology in a major way?
Oh,
yeah.
Yeah.
We would have seen a lot more
structure in the microwave
background.
Yeah.
Due to the excessive freezing out of these long
waves in time,
shouldn't pi be
undergoing a random walk?
Yeah.
It does undergo a random
walk at any point.
At any point in a
time,
it undergoes a random walk.
It's exactly what it does.
But of course it undergoes different
random walks at different places,
and that's what makes the variation.
Yeah,
it's a statistical process.
That's exactly right.
So if you focused on one particular
point in space,
you would see
one mode freeze out,
then the next
mode freeze out,
the next mode freeze out,
with random phase between them,
and it would make a random walk.
That's exactly right.
So the question is,
has it preoccupied people for a long
time,
which is what happened at
t equals zero is
irrelevant.
There is no t equals zero.
Well,
irrelevant or not,
well,
no.
I mean,
there is no
t equals zero
in this model.
Okay,
so
the...
Well,
let's put
it this way.
The success
of this theory,
and it has been
highly successful in correlating
a lot of data on different
wavelength scales.
When I say
correlates,
lots of data.
It correlates data about
fluctuations on very different
scales.
Scales
comparable to the whole size of the
sky,
variations across the sky,
which are
large scale down to very
small scales of a thousand
times smaller than the size of the whole
sky,
and it correlates all
those fluctuations,
density fluctuations,
basically
into one
set of parameters,
covering this potential here.
So in that sense,
it's highly successful.
The upside of it
is it washes out whatever the initial
conditions were,
because this
stretching washes out
what came before,
and only
the quantum fluctuations which are produced
later are relevant.
So the
success of it is that it washes
out what came before,
but what's
one era's success
becomes another era's
success.
second thing we want to know is
what happens earlier.
And all of the
things which made this a very successful
theory work against
us in finding out what happened earlier.
So inflation,
when it occurs,
tends to wipe out the past.
And as I said,
that's both good and bad,
particularly
bad for those who want to
understand what might have
led up to this.
The point is,
this is a ridiculous starting point.
This
energy density,
while
it's easy to accept
that the universe might have started with a very
high energy density.
That's easy to accept,
big deal.
The problem is,
the energy density was very,
very high
in ordinary units,
joules per cubic meter
or whatever.
It was
enormously high energy,
even on particle
scale units.
Much higher
energy density than,
for example,
the
density of energy inside a proton.
So it was enormously high
energy.
On the other hand,
it was very small in any
natural units.
It was 10 to the minus 14th
or something,
or 10 to the minus 12
or smaller.
So it's neither
here nor there,
so to speak.
It's
neither very big nor very
small.
It doesn't sound
like it's the sort of place
that natural
starting point would be.
Natural starting point might be
with the energy density,
for example,
being
Planckian,
one unit in Planck units.
10 to the minus 13 or 10 to the
minus 14 doesn't sound like it's
the starting point.
Now of course,
I could be wrong,
I don't know.
But there's no natural
explanation
of this whole structure
and why we might have started
over here,
and whether
or not we might have tumbled down
from some much,
much higher energy density
up here.
That's all lost.
That's all experimentally
lost because
inflation
just stretched things out so much
that we lost it.
Could it be that there was no start?
I mean,
it just continued
down to the point of the text match holders.
There isn't a real start to it.
Could the exponential have gone on,
you mean,
into the remote past?
No.
No,
this is an extremely odd story.
You say,
what would have happened
if the energy density was absolutely
constant out here,
for example?
Well,
this function has to do something.
It could increase in this
manner here,
in
which case it would say in the remote
past something different was
happening than down here.
Okay?
Exactly what was it?
Well,
we then go up to here,
and we say,
could there have been a
plateau up here that went on
and on indefinitely?
Well,
we might as well say,
could there have been a plateau
over here that went on and on indefinitely?
Alright,
so what are the consequences
then of a
universe
with an absolutely
constant energy density like this?
Suppose we're way out here with an
absolutely constant energy density.
Well,
when I
the...
I told you that the Sitter space was an
exponentially expanding universe.
That is
correct at late times.
In fact,
real the Sitter space is
a universe
which looks like this,
which contracts
and then expands.
That's the real honest solution of
Einstein's equations
with a cosmological constant.
It contracts and then it expands.
It contracts to some minimum size.
The minimum size
happens to be the Hubble scale.
And then it starts expanding.
And it expands exponentially.
I wrote that the
that the scale factor
was like the exponential of HT.
That's not exactly right.
Can you think of a function
which contracts and then expands
and then expands
and at late times looks like exponential?
Hyperbolic.
Hyperbolic Cauch.
Cauch HT.
That's the real solution
of Einstein's equations.
So the real solution of Einstein's
equations is not
an eternally exponentially
expanding universe,
but it's one
which contracts and expands.
Now,
should we believe,
the question comes up,
should we believe
in this contracting phase?
Should we believe in the
contracting phase that came before
the expansion?
I will just leave
that as a question mark.
I will leave that as a question mark.
Or should we believe
that somehow we
started in some other way
unknown,
I think mystery down here.
We don't know very much about that.
We really don't have a theory
of the beginnings.
If this plateau really gave way
to a much higher mountain here,
it would mean
that this might
have started much smaller.
In fact,
if it gave way to a mountain
which is as high as the Planck scale,
we might even want to say
it started as the smallest
possible thing,
one Planck length
on a side.
The fact is,
we don't know.
We don't know very much about
this.
No,
no,
why do you say that?
Because it's all erased,
it seems like.
Well,
that just means you have to be clever.
Huh?
Yeah.
It's of course all erased
if there was too many e-foldings.
Yeah.
If we are very,
very lucky
and there were 63 e-foldings,
then we have a chance of seeing it.
We have a chance of seeing some of this.
I'm trying to think out
what the pebble damping
does to the
field equations.
In particular,
does that change
the quanta of the field equations
as time goes on?
What it is,
is it's the redshifting
of the field quanta.
It's equivalent to the redshifting of the field quanta.
In other words,
it appears that energy is being lost,
but one way of thinking
about it is
the energy is just being stretched.
So it's completely equivalent to the
redshifting.
Bill?
You mentioned in passing that
mass is the inverse of length.
in small scales,
length is the inverse of mass.
The units,
the units of length
and mass are inverse to each other.
I'm sorry,
I'm sorry.
The formula,
for example,
for the Compton,
what's the formula
for the Compton wavelength,
the quantum mechanical wavelength
of a particle of mass m?
Compton wavelength,
lambda Compton.
Anybody know?
It's got an h-bar in it.
It's quantum mechanical.
Well,
it's a quantum mechanical.
Over momentum,
but we're talking about now
a particle of a given mass,
so it has to have units
of mass times velocity,
m times c.
h-bar over mc
is the Compton wavelength.
So we know that h-bar over mc
has units of a length.
Now,
if we work in units
in which c is one,
which we've all gotten
very used to by now,
and if we're also
quantum mechanically inclined,
we might also
set h-bar equal to one.
We don't have to.
We can just say that lambda
is inverse to a mass.
But if we do set h-bar equal to one,
which is a common thing to do,
then wavelength
has units of one over mass.
So length has units of one over mass.
Mass has units of one over length.
Uh,
and the other thing
is that when waves
get stretched out,
they become frozen.
The frequency goes to zero,
obviously,
so wouldn't that
mean that energy goes to zero?
Yes?
And they still exist
even though they have zero energy?
Well,
they're continually being...
As this process goes on,
waves become frozen,
they become stretched,
their energy is degraded,
and they're replaced by new ones.
But the net effect,
as it was pointed out,
was a kind of random walk
where the field just becomes a statistical
noisy mess.
And on every scale,
on every length scale,
so what's depleted by the expansion
gets replaced by,
uh,
by new waves coming in
and,
uh,
and freezing in
on top of those previous ones.
Is that the thing
about the slowing down of,
uh,
coordinate time when you approach
an event horizon?
Which?
Well,
like when you approach
an event horizon of a black hole.
Yeah.
You get more and more red shifting,
and meaning then that,
like the...
It's connected with that.
Connected with it?
Yeah,
it is,
but,
uh,
yeah.
Is there any way to make sense
of what inflation was,
in a sense of looking at
various parameters for the...
Yeah.
There's a space of parameters
to first order,
not first order in any
technical sense,
but to first order
in thinking about it.
There's the width of this,
there's the height of it,
and there's the slope of it.
The slope.
Remember,
the slope comes in in a prominent
way,
uh,
because
the slower the...
The smaller the slope,
the slower the field moves,
and the slower it moves,
the more,
uh,
the bigger the fluctuations.
These are three parameters.
The height,
let's call it v-naught,
the height of it,
uh,
the slope of it,
and the width
of it.
I don't know,
delta phi.
Now,
um,
generally speaking,
most physicists are of the opinion
delta phi in the
incidentally has units,
and it has units of mass.
Generally
speaking,
physicists get very uncomfortable
when a thing with a unit of mass
gets bigger,
a fundamental thing,
becomes bigger in mass
than the Planck mass.
They get very uncomfortable about that.
And most of us would probably
maintain that the
scale of variation
of a field like phi
should never be bigger than about
one unit in Planck mass.
That may or may not be true.
But if it's true,
it tells us
one piece of information.
Another piece of information
is that the energy density
should never be bigger than one in Planck units.
That's something we really believe.
I won't get into the reasons
for it,
but that's,
uh,
there's a lot of reason
for that.
And so,
having some kind of
bounds on these,
we're
really talking about bound on the slope
here.
We're talking about what's the probability
that the slope is
shallow enough that
62 e-foldings happen,
or 60
e-foldings happen.
What's the probability?
And the answer is
about 2%.
That you have to adjust this
slope to about 2%
in order to get it to
roll slowly enough here
to get the required number
of e-foldings.
Is 2%,
uh,
is that,
how unlikely
or how likely is that?
Well,
um,
it's 2%.
Now,
there's another interesting element to it.
There is another,
but I won't have time for it,
so I'm not going to try to get into it.
There is another element to it.
The other element,
well,
no.
Uh,
the question is,
is inflation
we would need to get into issues of
anthropic
questions.
We have two
puzzles,
cosmological puzzles.
Both of them are fine-tuning
puzzles.
One of them is a
mild fine-tuning.
It's only 2%
in some way of thinking about it.
Um,
um,
it's only 2%.
The other is the
fine-tuning of this
10 to the minus 123
down here.
Two big fine-tuning puzzles.
Both of them
can be resolved
in one simple
explanation,
whether you like it
or not,
that the universe had to be such
that
structure formed
in it.
Structure meaning
galaxies,
stars,
planets,
and so forth.
And
here's a way to think about it.
Um,
a
positive cosmological
constant.
Let's take a particular case.
Positive cosmological constant
and open
negatively curved universe.
Let's take that as our model.
We could take any other combination we like
and get the same answer.
But let's take positive cosmological constant
and open universe.
Okay,
so what is a
positive cosmological constant
from a Newtonian point of view?
From a Newtonian point of view,
it's a repulsion.
It's a repulsion,
a repulsive force,
a universal
repulsive force,
which is proportional
to distance.
That's what a
cosmological constant is.
If we went back to the
Newtonian description of things
that we started with
in the very early part of the quarter
and added in
to the usual Newtonian
gravitational
force between objects
another term which
was proportional to a thing called lambda
times the distance between
objects,
that would
mimic the cosmological constant.
And a positive cosmological
constant,
which is what we see,
would correspond to a universal repulsion
but because it
increases as a function of distance
it had better be small
it had better be small enough
that it doesn't affect the
solar system.
In fact,
it better be
small enough that it doesn't affect the galaxy
in fact it better be small enough
that it doesn't affect seriously big
clusters of galaxies
and in fact
experimentally it's known to only be
important at the scale of
that 10 billion light years
so it's a very small
repulsion.
But what would
happen if it was 100 times bigger?
10 to the minus 123
is how big it is.
It's because it's so small that it
only has an effect on
incidentally,
what if it was 10 to the minus
That repulsion,
yeah,
it would be easily
enough to blow apart an electron.
What if it was 10 to the minus
Easily big enough to blow the earth
out of just a,
oh easily
easily,
by many orders of magnitude.
Alright?
So
what if it was
10 to the minus 121
instead of 10 to the minus
Well,
not
galaxies today.
It would not be
potent enough to blow up the galaxies
today.
But it would be potent
enough to prevent this
one part in 10 to
the 5 fluctuations
from condensing into galaxies.
So this very
mild variation
that was there,
left over from inflation
it would only take a little bit of universal
repulsive cosmological constant
term
to prevent it from condensing into
galaxies.
This was Weinberg,
Steven Weinberg's
discovery in 1987
that a cosmological
constant
roughly two orders of
magnitude bigger than the 10 to the
minus 123
would have prevented galaxies from
forming.
At the time
it was thought that the cosmological
constant was zero,
and he said no,
there's no reason
for that.
It just has to be small
enough to allow galaxies to form.
And he was right.
Experimentally it wasn't zero.
It was just small enough
to allow galaxies to form.
Okay,
there's a
similar logic that
goes with the curvature of
the universe.
Let's take
the case of negative curvature.
Do you remember what
k means
from the Newtonian point of
view?
Or in particular,
k
being whether you're positive,
negatively,
or zero
curved.
It had to do with
the energy of
recession.
Escape velocity.
k equals zero meant everything
is moving with exactly the escape velocity.
k
greater than zero would mean
k greater than zero
means less than the escape velocity.
k less than zero means greater than it.
So if we take the
case of k less than zero,
which for one reason or
another has become the favored case,
but it wouldn't really matter.
If k were less than
zero,
it would mean that everything
was shot out with greater than the escape velocity.
Okay?
Well,
that
sounds bad.
It sounds like
too much velocity can also
prevent galaxies from
forming.
Two things can
prevent a rock which are going out
from returning.
One of them is if you're above the
escape velocity,
the other
would be an additional outward force
that you didn't know about,
which might have been
proportional to distance,
but very small.
Okay?
Both the
positive cosmological constant
and negative curvature
would both
work in the direction
of preventing
galaxies from forming.
Now,
the cosmological constant is very
small.
What about
the negative possibility of negative curvature?
If the universe
is slightly negatively
curved today,
it was much more negatively
curved in the past.
Right?
Because curvature,
radius
of curvature gets smaller.
So it's much more
negatively curved in the past.
We go back to the past when galaxies
form,
and we say the universe
must have not been
too negatively curved.
What could have caused it not to be
negatively curved
if it started out negatively curved?
What can dilute
curvature?
Expansion.
Inflation.
So you can say,
how many
e-foldings of inflation had
to take place in order
that the universe flattened itself
out enough before
this arrow and structure was formed?
How many e-foldings
had to have taken place
in order that the outward thrust
of things didn't prevent
galaxies from forming?
And the answer is about
59.5 e-foldings.
We know that there was
at least 62.
We know that for us to be here
it had to be more than
Alright?
So one explanation then
is that
we can just throw
away the possibility that
there was less than 59.5
e-foldings.
And then we can ask
the conditional probability.
What's the probability,
given that we're
here,
to ask the question,
in other words,
given that there were more than
59.5 e-foldings,
then we can ask
what's the probability that there was more than 62?
In other words,
we can take this parameter space
and we can say
let's cut out all the parts
of it
where there weren't enough e-foldings,
enough expansion,
to get rid of the
large outward thrust,
which would prevent galaxies from forming,
throw it away,
and ask
what's the probability that there was
in the remaining part of the parameter space,
given that there were more than
62 e-foldings,
more than 59 e-foldings,
what's the probability that there was more than 62?
And then the answer becomes
maybe .9 or something.
So it depends on how you ask the question
what the probability of inflation was.
If you ask the question
conditional that we're here to ask the question,
then the answer is
that it's very probable.
If you ask the question
what's the volume in the parameter space,
then it's less than 2%.
So it depends on how you ask the question.
The same is true for the cosmological constant.
If you ask
what's the a priori probability
that a number is less
than 10 to the minus 123,
well,
it's 10 to the minus 123.
But what's the probability
that if we're here,
then the number becomes of order 1.
So,
these are the great puzzles.
These are the great confusions,
the great puzzles,
the great debates which are going on.
And that brings us
to the end of the great debate.