Stanford University.
Okay,
let's start.
This quarter's subject is cosmology.
Cosmology is,
of course,
a very old
subject.
It goes back thousands of years,
but I'm not going to tell
you about thousands of years of
cosmology,
but I say thousands of years.
I'm talking about the Greeks,
of course,
but we're
not going to go here back thousands of years.
We're going to go back at
most to some time in the
second quarter of the 20th century,
when Hubble discovered that the universe is expanding.
But let's just say a few
words about the science of cosmology.
The science of cosmology is the science of cosmology.
The science of cosmology is new,
or at least what we know about it.
A minute ago,
I said it was very old.
Yes,
in a sense,
but the modern subject of cosmology is very new.
It really dates to well after Hubble.
It dates to the discovery of the Big Bang,
the three degree microwave radiation that was discovered
as the remnant of the Big Bang.
And that happened sometime in the 60s.
So I was a student.
I was a young student.
And before that,
cosmology was in a certain sense
less like physics and more like
natural science,
like what a naturalist does.
Studies this kind of thing,
studies that kind
of thing.
You find a funny star over there.
You find a galaxy over there that looks a little
weird.
To classify you name things.
You measure things to be sure.
But the accuracy with which things were known
was so poor that it was extremely difficult
to be precise about it.
And it's only fairly recently
that physicists – physicists are always
involved,
but they were involved because many
of the things that you see,
many of these strange
creatures,
funny stars,
galaxies and so forth.
Many of these strange creatures,
funny stars,
galaxies and so forth.
And of course,
for the first time in the history of physics,
we're going to
are physical systems,
and to describe them properly,
they have angular momentum,
they
have all the things that physical systems have,
there's chemicals out there,
and so
physical chemists were involved.
But thinking of the universe as a physical system,
as a
system to study mathematically,
and with a set of physical
principles and a set of equations
of course there were always sets of equations way back,
but wrong equations,
right equations,
and accurate equations,
things which agreed with observation,
that's relatively new.
More or less over the
history of my career in physics,
which is 50 years,
something like that.
And that's what we're going to study.
We're going to study the universe as a system.
In other words,
a universe as a system
that we can study with equations.
So if you don't like equations,
you're in the wrong place.
Alright,
so where do you start?
You start with some observations.
Now,
the first observation,
which may not really turn out to be absolutely true,
for reasons
that...
It's not absolutely true,
but it looks like it's approximately true,
is that the universe
is what is called isotropic.
Isotropic means that when you look in that direction,
or that direction,
or that direction...
Now,
of course,
if you look right at a star,
it looks a little different than if you look
away from the star.
But on the whole,
averaging over patches in the sky,
and looking out far enough so that
you get away from the immediate foreground.
The foreground of our own galaxy,
the universe looks pretty much the same in every direction.
That's called isotropic.
Same in every direction.
Now,
if the universe is isotropic,
with one exception that I'll describe in a moment,
if it's isotropic around us,
then you can bet with
a high degree of confidence that
it's also pretty close to being homogeneous.
Homogeneous.
Homogeneous doesn't mean it's the same in every direction.
It means it's the same in every place.
If you went out over there and
you looked around from 16 galaxies over,
and you looked
around what you would see,
you would see about the same thing you saw here.
So first of all,
what's the argument for that?
Why does being isotropic,
which means the same in every direction,
tell you anything
about why it would be the same if
you moved away to a very distant place?
And the argument is very simple.
Imagine that there's some distribution of galaxies.
You know,
incidentally,
at least in the first part of this study here,
it's not going to
matter very much whether what we're talking about,
whether we call them galaxies or whether
we just call them particles.
They're just effectively mass points.
Distributed things.
They're just going to be visible throughout space.
For the moment,
I might even lapse into calling
them particles from time to time.
Now,
you must remember,
when I say particles,
I mean literal galaxies,
but unless I otherwise
specify.
Okay,
so the universe has a lot of them.
Anybody know how many galaxies are within the visible...
About 100 billion.
10 to the 11th.
Just there's some nice numbers to keep track of,
incidentally.
It's a good idea to
keep track of a few numbers.
Within what we can see,
within what we can see with telescopes,
out to as far as astronomy
takes us,
about 10 to the 11th galaxies.
Each galaxy about 10 to the 11th stars.
Altogether 10 to the 22 stars.
If each star has roughly 10 planets,
that's 10 to the 23 Avogadro's number of planets
out there.
A mole,
right.
A planetary mole.
Right.
All right.
Now,
imagine that we're over here,
and every direction that you look in,
it looks pretty
much the same.
Well,
then I maintain that not
only my galaxy is the same.
It must be the same in every direction,
but it must be the same from place to place.
What would it mean for it not
to be the same from place to place?
Well,
if it's isotropic,
the only way it could not
be homogeneous is if it somehow formed
rings of some sort.
It's got to be such that
it looks the same in every direction,
but it's not the...
Yeah,
shells.
I think somebody said shells.
You know,
it would have the geometry
of some sort of shell-like structure.
Why?
It doesn't literally mean shells,
it just means...
Yeah.
So,
if that were the case,
if that were the case and
you went someplace else and you looked
around,
clearly it wouldn't look isotropic anymore.
So for it to look isotropic,
unless by accident we just happen
to be at the center of the
universe.
If we happen to be at the very
center where everything just accidentally or not accidentally,
maybe by design,
happens to be nice and rotationally symmetric about us,
if we don't want to believe
that,
then we have to believe it's pretty
much the same everywheres and that it's homogeneous.
So homogeneous means that as far as we can see,
space is uniformly filled on the average.
Yeah.
So,
the universe is filled with particles.
Uniformly filled.
Okay.
That's called the cosmological principle.
Now,
you can't...
Why is it true?
Well,
how can it not be true?
It's the cosmological principle.
Right?
And sometimes people argue like that.
It's true because it's been observed to
be true to some degree of approximation.
Now,
as was mentioned,
in some media that I don't know how to evaluate,
some astronomers
apparently claim to see structures
out there which are so big,
if the blackboard here was
the whole visible universe,
they would stretch across great big patches of it.
And that seems to be a little
bit counter to this idea of complete uniformity.
And of course,
certainly the idea of complete uniformity is not exact.
Just the fact that there are galaxies means
it's not the same over here and over here.
And in fact,
there are clusters of
galaxies and superclusters of galaxies.
So it appears it's not really homogeneous,
but it tends to come in sort of clusters which
on some big enough scale,
like a billion light years roughly,
maybe a little bit less,
if
you average over that much,
it looks homogeneous.
Okay,
so that's the basic fact
that we're going to begin with.
Now,
what's the first step in formulating a physics problem?
Yep,
know your variables.
Usually the answer is sharpen your pencil.
Okay.
After you've sharpened your pencil,
you're the next person to do it.
There's no,
there's no your variables.
But a good step,
I'm not sure whether it
comes after that or before that,
is...
Professor,
could the uniformity of the cosmic
microwave background radiation be an argument for...
Oh,
you bet.
You bet,
But we're going back,
I'm purposefully going back a few
decades to some time around the
60s or something like that.
50s,
60s,
40s.
The idea of the cosmological principle was
put forward before people had any real right
to put it forward.
They just said,
oh,
well,
let's just say it's homogeneous.
We'll call it the cosmological principle,
and if people ask us why it's true,
it's because
it's a principle.
All right.
But then,
you know,
with more and more astronomical investigation,
and then finally,
the cosmic
microwave background really nailed it.
And in some sense,
the primordial distribution of matter was extremely smooth,
extremely
smooth.
But we'll get to that.
All right.
So here we have a uniform gas,
if you like.
It's a uniform gas,
and that gas is interacting,
it's a gas of particles,
it's interacting,
each particle is interacting with the other particles.
Now,
galaxies on the whole are not electrically charged.
They're electrically neutral.
But they're not gravitationally neutral.
They interact through Newtonian gravity.
And that's the only important force on big enough scales.
On big enough scales where
matter tends to be electrically neutral,
the only really important
force is gravity.
So gravity is pulling all this stuff together,
or it's doing something to it,
but it's a
little bit confusing.
Now,
what happens to this point over here?
Does it accelerate toward the center,
because at the center there's a whole bunch of matter
there?
Or does it accelerate out to here?
Because after all,
there's as much matter out there
as there is on this side.
In fact,
it sort of looks like it oughtn't to move anywhere.
It ought to just stay there,
because there's as much on one
side as on the other side,
right?
So it'll just stay there.
Well,
what about this one over here?
Same thing,
because every place is the same as every other place.
So the natural thing to guess is
that the universe must be just static.
It must just sit there,
because nothing has any net force on it,
and so there's nothing
pulling it one way or another.
That's wrong.
We're going to work out tonight
the actual Newtonian equations of cosmology.
Okay.
So,
you may have heard that the
expanding universe somehow fit together especially well
and wasn't really understood until general relativity,
until Einstein.
That is simply false.
It may be so historically.
I mean,
in terms of years,
yes.
It is true that the expanding universe
was not understood until after Einstein had created
the general theory of relativity.
Okay.
So that is a fact about dates.
It's not a fact at all about logic.
Newton could have done the expanding universe.
Since Newton didn't do it,
we are going to do it
here the way Newton should have done
it if only Newton was a little bit smarter.
Okay?
All right.
So the first thing,
know your variables for sure,
but the first step is usually to introduce
a set of coordinates.
Introduce a set of coordinates into a problem.
And that means exactly what it always means.
Take space and rule it into coordinates.
Three dimensions for sure,
but I'm only going to draw two.
In other words,
introduce a fictitious grid of coordinates.
Now,
what shall we take for
the distance between neighboring lines?
Okay.
So let's say we have a grid of coordinates.
So we can take the distance between the points,
the points that are the lattice points on
this grid.
We can take it to be one meter.
We can take it to be 10 meters.
We can take it to be a million meters.
We can take it whatever we like.
But there's a smarter thing to do than
to just fix the distance between the points.
The smarter thing to do is to imagine these
points have been chosen so that the grid points
always pass through the same galaxies.
In other words,
that the galaxies here provide a grid.
All right.
Provide a grid in such a
way that no matter what happens,
since the galaxies are nice
and uniform,
no matter what happens,
this galaxy over here will always be at that point
on the grid.
That galaxy over here will always
be at that point on the grid.
And that means that if the
universe indeed either expands or contracts,
the grid has to expand or,
let me say it differently,
if the galaxies are moving relative to each other,
perhaps away from each other or closer to each other,
then the grid moves with them.
Let's choose coordinates so that the galaxies
are sort of frozen in the grid.
Now,
it's not obvious you can do that.
It's not obvious you can do that.
If the galaxies were such that
some were moving this way over here,
some were moving that way over here,
a sort of random kind of motion,
then there would be no way to fix
the coordinates by attaching them to the galaxies,
because even at a point,
the different ones would be moving in different ways.
But that's not what you see
when you look out at the heavens.
What you see is that they're moving very coherently,
exactly as if they were embedded in a grid,
with the grid perhaps expanding,
perhaps contracting,
we'll come to that,
but the whole grid being sort of frozen.
Any motion that takes place is because the grid
is either expanding in size or contracting in size.
That's an observation.
So,
what we're going to do is we're going to take a
little bit of observation about the relative motion of nearby galaxies.
Galaxies over here and over here,
which are relatively nearby,
are not moving with tremendous
velocity relative to each other.
They're moving in a nice coherent way,
as I said.
So that,
uh...
So,
we can choose coordinates,
we'll call them x,
y,
and z,
standard names for coordinates,
x,
y,
and z.
But x,
y,
and z are not measured in length.
They're not measured in length.
Because the length of a
grid cell may change with time.
Okay,
so we've labeled the galaxies by
where they are in a grid,
and now we can ask the question,
let's,
uh...
Let's say the distance,
let's say two points,
let's start with two points separated
by an x distance over here.
Let's call that x distance delta x.
How far apart are they?
Well,
I don't know how far apart they are.
But I'm now going to
postulate that the distance between them,
the actual distance in meters,
or in some physical unit
that you measure with a ruler,
could be a light year on a side,
it could be a million light years on a side,
but a ruler,
that the actual distance is proportional to delta x.
The distance between these two people over
here is half the distance between these two,
is a third the distance between these two.
So it's proportional to delta x times
a parameter that's called the scale parameter.
The scale parameter may or
may not be just a constant.
It may just be a constant.
If it were just constant,
then the distance between galaxies fixed in
the grid would stay constant with time.
But it may also be time dependent,
so let's allow that.
That would say the distance between two galaxies,
let's say this is galaxy A,
this is galaxy B,
the distance from A to B is
A of t times delta x AB,
where delta x is the x distance,
is the coordinate distance between them.
Let me write it more generally.
If we have two galaxies,
arbitrary positions on the grid,
then the distance between them,
d AB,
is equal to A of t,
the same A of t,
and then the square root of Pythagoras'
theorem,
delta x squared plus delta
y squared plus delta z squared.
In other words,
you measure the distance along the grid in grid units,
and then multiply it by A of t to
find the actual physical distance between the two points.
As I said,
A of t may or
may not be constant in time.
Well,
of course it's not.
If it was constant in time,
that would mean literally the galaxies were
just frozen in space and they didn't move.
And that's not what we see.
We see them moving apart from each other.
Okay,
so let's calculate now the velocity
between galaxy A and galaxy B.
Here's the distance between galaxy A,
and this of course should be delta AB.
The distance,
the coordinate grid distance.
Let's just use the simpler formula up here.
Let's forget Pythagoras and just take
them to be along the x-axis.
It doesn't really matter.
Okay,
here's d AB.
What's the velocity between,
what's the relative velocity of the AB galaxies?
It's just the time derivative of this,
right?
Just the time derivative of the distance is the velocity.
So the velocity between A and B
is just equal to the time derivative.
And the only thing that's changing for A and B,
A and B are fixed in the grid,
so delta x is not changing.
That's fixed.
The only thing that's changing,
perhaps,
is A.
So the velocity is just the time derivative of A.
A dot means the time derivative of A.
A dot times delta x.
All I've done is differentiate
this formula with respect to time.
Now I can write that the
ratio of the velocity to the distance,
I'll leave out the A,
well let's put them in,
AB.
The ratio of the velocity to the distance
is just the ratio of A dot to A.
Notice that delta x cancelled out.
Well that's interesting.
It means that the ratio
of the velocity to the distance
doesn't depend on which pair
of galaxies we're talking about.
Every pair of galaxies,
no matter how far apart,
no matter how close,
no matter what angle they're oriented in,
the relative velocity between the two of them,
relative either separation or the opposite of separation,
the ratio of the velocity to
the distance is A dot over A.
What's the name for this thing?
Anybody know?
The Hubble constant.
It's called the Hubble constant.
Let's call it H.
Now,
is there any reason why it should be a constant?
What do we mean when we say it's a constant?
There's no reason for it
to be independent of the time.
In fact,
it's not.
What we find here is that it's independent of x.
It doesn't matter where you are,
it doesn't matter which two galaxies you're talking about,
the same Hubble constant at a given time.
So the Hubble constant is a kind of misnomer.
The Hubble parameter,
the Hubble function,
is independent of position but depends on time.
And now we just write this in the standard form
that the velocity between any two galaxies in the universe
is equal to the same Hubble
parameter times the distance between them.
And that's the derivation of the Hubble law.
Excuse me,
question.
Don't you sort of start out almost,
assuming what you're trying to show by saying that
dAV equals one function A of t that's independent?
Yes,
yes,
indeed.
Absolutely.
Yeah,
I mean,
you never would have written this
if Hubble hadn't discovered that the Hubble law was right.
But on the other hand,
the Hubble law is in
some sense not all that surprising.
All it's,
you know,
as some witty person said,
you shouldn't be surprised that the Hubble law
is the fastest horse goes the furthest.
Okay?
Right.
The faster you move,
the far,
far,
farther you go.
So that's all this thing says.
However,
it's interesting,
the connection between this formula and the Hubble formula
is,
as you point out,
a close one.
But what it says is
everything is moving on a grid,
and it's the grid itself
whose size scale may or
may not be changing with time,
but of course it is changing with time.
And the Hubble constant is just the ratio
of the time derivative of A to A itself.
Okay,
that's the facts.
Those are the facts.
Those are the facts as Hubble discovered them,
and as theoretical cosmologists then
had something to work with.
All right,
let's,
let's...
say a few more things about this.
What about the mass within a region,
let's take a region of size delta x,
delta y,
delta z.
And now I mean a region which is big enough
so that,
I don't know what happened to my universe,
I have my universe here,
but...
big enough so that we can average
over the small scale structure.
How much mass is in there?
Okay.
Well,
that,
the amount of mass that's in there
is going to be proportional to delta x,
delta y,
delta z.
The bigger the region that you take,
the more mass.
And so,
let's just say the amount of mass,
we'll call it nu.
Nu is nothing but the amount of mass per unit,
volume of the grid,
but volume not being measured in meters,
but being measured in x.
All right,
so let's say that's the mass
in a given region of coordinate volume
delta x,
delta y,
delta z.
On the other hand,
what's the actual volume of that region?
Let's take this volume of the same region.
The volume of the same region
is not delta x,
delta y,
delta z.
Why?
Because the distance along the x-axis
and the y-axis and the z-axis
is not delta x,
it's a times delta x.
So,
that means the volume of that same cell,
that same cell,
is a cubed
times delta x,
delta y,
delta z,
right?
That's because the length along the
x-axis is a times delta x,
a times delta y,
a times delta z.
And so now let's write a
formula for the density of mass.
The density,
I mean the physical density of mass now,
how much mass is there per
cubic kilometer or cubic light year
or whatever units,
we haven't specified units yet.
Later on we'll specify units.
Meters are fine.
Meters,
seconds,
and kilograms are fine.
Mass measured in kilograms,
volume measured in cubic meters.
What's the density?
So let's write,
let's call the density,
the standard terminology for density is rho.
I don't know where it came from.
Rho stands for density.
Let's write it over here,
density.
And density means the number of kilograms per cubic meter,
if you like.
It's the ratio of the mass to the volume.
It's the ratio of the mass to the volume,
and it's just as nu here,
divided by a cubed.
That's a formula that we have.
Nu divided by a cubed.
Now,
the amount of mass in
each cell in here stays fixed.
Why does it stay fixed?
Because the galaxies move with the grid.
So the amount of mass in a given region,
in the grid,
stays the same.
That's just something I've called nu,
the Greek letter nu.
And I divided it by
the volume to get the density.
And of course if A changes with time,
the density changes with time.
That's obvious.
If the universe grows,
the density decreases.
If the universe collapses,
the density increases.
And so this is a formula that
we will use from time to time.
So let's go back to Newton.
All right,
so far,
we've done nothing that Euclid himself couldn't have done.
All right,
we didn't even need Newton yet.
Now enters Newton.
And Newton says,
look,
let's not play games.
Let's forget all this.
We'll take into account that the
universe is homogeneous and all that stuff.
But Newton was a very,
very self-centered person.
He always believed that he was
at the center of the universe.
And so it was very natural
for him to take the perspective
that I,
Sir Isaac Newton,
am at the origin.
Now of course we know,
and Newton also would have known,
that if he's clever,
he'll get the same equations,
no matter where he places himself.
But there's nothing wrong with choosing the grid
such that Newton and we are
at the center of the grid.
Then surrounding Newton,
and moreover,
Newton will also say,
I'm not moving.
Not moving?
Well,
I'm standing still.
So Newton is at rest
at the center of the universe
as far as for mathematical purposes.
And now he wants to,
and of course we're talking about
on a scale so that
everything is nice and uniformly distributed.
Now he looks out to a distant galaxy.
He looks out to the galaxy over here.
And he wants to know how that galaxy moves.
Well,
that galaxy moves under
the assumption of Newton's equations.
Newton's equations say that
everything gravitates with everything else.
But there's something special about Newton's,
there's a theorem.
Newton knew this theorem.
In fact,
it's called Newton's theorem.
What Newton's theorem says
is that if you want
to know what the gravitational force
on a system is,
given that everything is isotropic,
it doesn't even have to be homogeneous for this,
you want to know the gravitational force
in a frame of reference like I've drawn here,
you want to know the gravitational force on that particle,
then draw a sphere
with that particle on the sphere
centered at the origin,
and then take all of the mass within that sphere
and pretend that it's just sitting at the origin.
Just pretend.
We're not literally moving it.
Just pretend that the only mass
in the universe within this sphere
is at the origin.
And what about the outside?
The mass is on the outside.
Ignore it.
Newton's theorem says
that the force on a particle
in an isotropic world like this
all comes from the sphere inside
the radius of the particle
and nothing from the outside.
I think we may have proved that in previous classes
in classical mechanics.
I don't remember,
but it's a true theorem.
It's a true theorem,
and it's the reason
that we here,
in evaluating the gravitational field
on this pen here,
why we can pretend
that all of the mass of the Earth
is at the center of the Earth.
When I evaluate the gravitational field here,
keeping in mind that the Earth is a sphere,
keeping in mind that it's pretty uniform,
and so forth,
I can just pretend that all of the mass
was at the center of the Earth.
Until,
of course,
the pen hits the floor.
Then it'll say,
no,
the mass wasn't the...
Until it hits the floor,
pretend that all the mass was concentrated
at the center,
and furthermore,
the masses outside,
beyond this,
even though there's a lot more out there,
incidentally,
there's a lot of mass out there.
I'm not talking about the ceiling of the building.
I'm talking about all the galaxies out there.
There's a lot more,
but the pen doesn't feel them.
It only feels the things
on the inside of the sphere.
So,
Newton says,
all I'm going to do
is I'm going to take
this galaxy,
which is
at a certain distance away.
What's its distance here?
Its distance is d.
Its distance is
the square root of
x squared plus y squared plus z squared.
x squared and y squared and z squared,
that's the coordinates of this point over here,
times a.
The distance from the center.
Can you read the...
Is it easy to read the red?
I don't know why I started with the red.
I just...
elapsed.
Is the red readable?
Okay.
All right.
Square root of x squared
plus y squared plus z squared,
that's Pythagoras,
and you multiply by a to find the actual distance.
I can call that...
Let's call that d equals a of t,
and let's just call this thing here r,
capital R.
R is not measured in meters.
It's just square root of x
squared plus y squared plus z squared.
That's the distance from the center
to the galaxy in question.
Now,
Newton's equations are about forces
and accelerations.
So the first thing is let's calculate the acceleration
of x,
of the point x of
the galaxy at the point x,
relative to the origin.
Well,
first the velocity.
The velocity is v is equal
to a dot of t times r.
And what about the acceleration?
The acceleration is just differentiate again.
Acceleration is equal to a
double dot of t times r.
Do we have to worry about
whether r is changing with time?
No.
No,
because the galaxy is at a fixed...
point in this expanding lattice.
r is fixed for that galaxy.
And so this is the acceleration.
We could multiply it by the mass of the galaxy
if we wanted to,
but I don't need to.
It's just the acceleration.
And what are we going to set that equal to?
We're going to set that equal to the acceleration
that we would get from
all the gravitating material inside here.
Okay,
so let's see.
How much...
First question is how much mass is in there.
Well,
let's just call it the mass.
This is the mass that's inside this sphere.
The formula that we're going to compare this with
is Newton's gravitational formula.
Force is equal to mass times mass.
Which mass is this little one here?
That's the galaxy.
The mass of the big one?
Which one is that?
That's all the mass on the inside.
And the distance between...
Well,
the distance squared.
And I'm missing a couple of things.
Two things I'm missing.
Newton's gravitational constant,
6.7 times 10 to the minus 11th in some units.
I'm missing one more thing.
Anybody know what it is?
Not a minus sign.
The minus sign...
indicates that the force is attractive,
pulling in.
Alright?
That's the convention.
Force pulling in is counted as negative.
Force pushing out is counted as positive.
Alright,
this is the force of gravity
on a particle of mass m.
What is the acceleration of gravity?
The acceleration of gravity is...
just drop the mass.
Just drop this out.
Forget the mass.
The acceleration is the force per unit mass.
And write that this is the acceleration.
m minus mg divided by c squared.
That's the acceleration of that galaxy.
What's that?
Which one are you using?
The small one?
No.
I divided out the small m.
Okay?
Good.
So that's the acceleration.
Due to the presence of all
this mass in the interior here.
And that had better be equal
to a double dot of t times r.
God knows where this is going,
but we're just following our nose,
writing equations.
And you know,
that's always the way you do it.
You start out with some physical principles.
You write down the equations.
And then you blindly follow them for a way
until you need to think again.
So we're on autopilot now.
We're just doing equations.
Let me rewrite it down here.
A double dot r is equal
to minus mg over d squared.
Okay,
let's plug in this guy over here.
The distance is a times r.
So maybe we can,
maybe,
who knows,
at some point we might have actually discovered something
that looks interesting.
At the moment,
it's just a blind aft squared,
or just a squared.
Let's just call it a squared.
A squared times d squared?
No,
a squared times r squared,
right?
Yeah.
Okay.
Now,
excuse me,
but I'm just going to divide by r here.
See,
I secretly know where I'm going.
Right.
Maybe you do too,
but that's all right.
r cubed,
I divide it.
And I'm going to divide by another a.
Makes this a cubed.
Okay.
Now,
this is good.
This will do.
But,
next question,
what's the volume of the sphere?
Let's write the volume of the sphere.
This is Newton's equations.
Now,
volume of the sphere.
What's the volume?
Four thirds.
Four thirds pi.
Now,
is it r cubed?
No.
d cubed.
Which means a cubed times r cubed.
Right?
Because distance is really a times r.
That's the actual physical volume.
When I say the volume,
I mean the volume is measured
in some standard unit like meters.
That's the volume.
Now,
look here.
We have a cubed times r cubed here.
Let me write that as volume three over four
pi volume is equal to a cubed r cubed.
Oh,
maybe I'm being dumb.
Maybe I shouldn't.
Yeah,
that's dumb.
Let's not do that.
Let's just look at this formula here.
Notice that we have a cubed r cubed downstairs.
Let's multiply by four over three pi.
Or divide by four over three pi.
And multiply by four over three pi.
Four thirds pi.
What I did here,
I undid here.
But now,
I have m over the volume.
What's m over the volume?
The density.
Ooh.
Something nice may be happening.
A double dot over a is equal to
minus four thirds pi Newton's constant times the ratio
of r cubed to r cubed.
So,
the ratio of the mass in that
sphere to the volume in that sphere.
And that is the density.
Now,
that's a nice equation.
Notice that it really doesn't depend on r anymore.
If we know what the density of the universe is,
and the density of the universe
does not depend on where you are,
the density of the universe does not depend on r.
The left hand side,
r has dropped out.
The right hand side,
no memory of r.
It means this equation is true for every galaxy,
no matter how far away.
Same equation.
Had we done a different galaxy,
we would have gotten the same equation.
The only way that this equation had any
memory of which galaxy we were talking about,
was because of r.
But r dropped out of the equation.
That's of course a good thing,
because if we want to think of a
as something which doesn't depend on where you are,
then it had better be that it drops out.
So,
Newton confirms what he might have expected,
that the equation for a is
a universal equation for all galaxies.
Yeah.
It seems like something seems,
a little off,
because we picked the origin,
and it was arbitrary,
supposedly.
It was.
Again,
we would have gotten exactly the same thing,
no matter what origin we picked.
But I mean,
it says,
whichever origin we picked,
then we get the force going toward that origin,
right?
That's right.
So,
something doesn't add up there.
Well,
it has added up,
but the answer doesn't depend on which,
no,
you have to,
the point is you have to do the transformation carefully.
You have to do the transformation carefully.
You go to another origin,
and in your frame,
Newton could have said,
let me work this out from my frame of reference,
which I will put myself at the origin,
but let me study now
the relative motion of some galaxies,
relative to some moving,
some galaxy which is moving.
He would have found exactly the same equations,
but he would have had to do the transformation carefully.
So,
we finessed that,
and got away from it,
by just putting ourselves at the center,
but as you can see,
the final formula doesn't care where you are.
It confirms the fact that nothing really depended
on which galaxy we thought of as our home.
But the direction of the force,
if we really look at
the direction of the gravitational force,
that's always toward the origin,
right?
There's a relative force,
the right way to think about
it is really a relative force.
No,
yeah,
yeah.
In this way of thinking about it,
the force is always toward the origin,
right?
But had we stationed ourselves on some other galaxy
that was moving,
and did all the transformations,
remember,
when you go to a moving frame,
there are fake forces,
inertial forces,
fake forces that you have to add in.
So,
from the point of view of this guy over here,
this galaxy over here
has a force which could be
thought of as being toward here,
plus a fake force,
the fake force being an
inertial force due to his acceleration.
But we got around that by just saying,
let's position ourselves at the center,
no acceleration,
no velocity,
we just sit at the center.
So,
the only test question,
the only question is,
do we get an answer which
doesn't depend on who we are
and which galaxy we're on?
Right.
Okay,
so that's part of the main message of this.
The answer doesn't depend on which galaxy you're on,
and so it really didn't depend on Newton's assumption
that he was at the center.
Can we go back to the equation for mass?
Would anything have changed if we had assumed
that nu was not a constant?
Oh,
yes.
Yes,
yes,
nu,
things would have changed
if nu was not a constant.
Could we say we've kind of...
Made it happen by making that assumption?
Made what happen?
The end result.
A constant in space?
Yes.
Yes,
to say that it's a constant in space
is the principle that the universe is homogeneous.
So everything hinges on that assumption.
Absolutely.
Everything hinges on the homogeneity of the universe.
Right.
And that the...
Right,
that the number of...
The mass per unit of volume is the same everywhere,
in space.
Okay.
Yes,
everything hinges on that.
And...
Okay,
so here's one equation.
It's a central fundamental equation of cosmology.
And it's a differential equation.
It's an equation for how A changes with time.
Now,
there's a number of things to look at,
but the first interesting thing to look at
is it's impossible to have a universe
which is static.
Static means that A doesn't change with time
unless it's empty.
Empty means rho equals zero.
Only if it is empty,
so that this side is zero,
can the time derivative of A,
or the second time derivative in this case,
be zero.
So,
we derive the fact that the universe is not static.
All right,
one more thing we could do
to make this an equation that we could solve
is to replace...
replace rho
by the constant nu
divided by A cubed.
Now,
nu is literally a constant.
It's the number of galaxies
times the mass of a galaxy
in a unit coordinate volume.
It doesn't change with time
because the galaxies are frozen in the grid.
And so,
we could write this equation
one more step.
A double dot...
Not surprising that there's an A double dot.
Why is there an A double dot?
Because Newton's equations are about acceleration.
And not surprising that there's an A double dot.
Equals minus four over three
pi times g
times the density,
but the point is now
the density is not a constant.
Nu is a constant,
but nu over A cubed is not
because A is changing with time.
And so,
we better put that in here.
Nu divided by A cubed.
Okay,
so there's a lot of constants here.
Minus...
The minus sign is a constant.
Four pi over three.
g Newton is a constant.
And we can pick nu also to be a constant.
So,
everything out here is constant.
A is not constant.
But we have a kind of differential equation.
It is a differential equation.
A kind of equation of motion.
In terms of one constant,
four pi g nu over three,
we have an equation of motion
for the scale factor.
For the scale factor,
A is a function of time.
Who was the first to discover this equation?
It was actually discovered
in the context of the general theory of relativity.
It was discovered in the context
of the general theory of relativity.
It was discovered,
I think,
Friedman,
Alexander Friedman,
before he got himself killed in World War I,
I think.
Using the general theory of relativity.
It was consistent with what Einstein should have done.
But,
it's perfectly possible there's nothing in it
that wasn't just good old Newtonian mechanics.
Okay.
Yeah.
Do you need to keep the A and the denominator
on the left-hand side?
Well,
I can multiply it if I like.
Just A double dot A?
A double dot A is a constant over A squared?
Sure.
You can do that.
It's just,
it's traditional to write it this way.
It's just a tradition.
Yeah.
So,
does that negative sign
not tell us anything about whether
we're expanding or contracting?
It doesn't tell us whether we're expanding or contracting.
Okay.
So,
let me explain why.
Let me write,
forget that now.
Now we just have the Earth.
Let's compare this with something else.
We have the Earth,
and we have a particle over here.
Let's put it on the x-axis.
On the x-axis.
Alright,
there's an equation for that particle.
It's the same equation.
Let's call it now,
let's call it x,
but x doesn't stand for these coordinates now.
It just stands for the standard position coordinate,
or the height above the Earth.
That satisfies some equation,
x double dot is equal to
the gravitational force,
whatever the gravitational force is,
mg over x squared minus,
that's it,
something like that.
Okay.
Does this equation,
what this equation tells us
is that the particle is accelerating toward the Earth.
The minus sign tells us that the acceleration
is toward the Earth.
But whether it's moving away from the Earth
or toward the Earth
is a question of velocity,
not acceleration.
Is the velocity that way,
or is it that way?
Well,
you can imagine somebody over here
taking this particle
and ejecting it that way.
It will have a positive velocity,
it will be moving away from the Earth.
You could also imagine the same person
pushing it that way.
It will be moving toward the Earth.
X is decreasing.
But the acceleration will be the same.
In either case,
the velocity will have a negative acceleration,
which means if it's going this way,
it'll turn around,
or may turn around.
If it's going this way,
it'll increase the inward velocity.
Whether it turns around or not depends on what?
Initial conditions.
And the initial conditions,
or whether it's above or below the escape velocity.
But in either case,
the acceleration is toward the Earth.
So knowing that the acceleration is toward the Earth,
as it is for this pen,
does not tell me whether
it's moving up or moving down.
It can move up and then move down.
And you get the point.
Okay.
So,
no,
this equation doesn't tell us
whether the universe is expanding or contracting,
but it tells us that the second derivative is negative.
So it means that even if it's moving up,
it's expanding,
it's tending to slow down.
If it's expanding,
If it's contracting,
it's tending to speed up its contraction.
There is an analog here
of whether you are above or below the escape velocity,
and we'll come to it.
All right.
So I was asked a question which
I will just point out.
Art,
sorry Art,
but I'm going to use your name.
Art asked me,
well,
he looked at this and said,
this is negative.
And he looked at,
what is this?
He looked at this and said,
this is positive.
If the universe is expanding,
H is positive.
How come this one's negative?
But that's because he didn't read carefully.
There's two dots here and only one dot here.
This is velocity.
This is acceleration.
Not hard for acceleration to be negative.
You know,
you're in your Ferrari
and you're going down the
down the
Autobahn or whatever.
And you press down on the brake.
Your acceleration is negative,
but your velocity is positive.
Right.
You're slowing down,
but you're still going ahead.
Now,
in fact,
the universe is not slowing down.
This,
we're really doing what Newton would have done
and what all cosmologists thought
the right thing to do was
until about 15 years ago.
Okay.
So 15,
this is Newton's model of the universe.
And it is the model that would have been
called the standard model,
or close to it,
the standard model of the universe
until,
until the accelerated universe was discovered.
This is the decelerated universe,
you see.
But the universe accelerates.
So there's got to be something else in this equation.
Well,
there is.
There are several other things in that equation,
but we'll come to them.
Some parts do have to do with Einstein.
Okay.
Let's talk about,
not cosmology,
but just particles,
rocks,
stones,
thrown upward from the universe,
from the surface of the earth.
Equations are very similar.
Let's just examine them for a minute
and take home a couple of lessons about it.
Here's the earth,
and we might have to do
a little bit more of that.
We might as well think of it as a point,
because Newton proved the theorem that said
we can think of it as a point.
We're outside,
we're above the surface of the earth.
So here's the earth.
Here's our particle over here.
Where should I put it?
Put it over here.
No.
Put it over here,
x-axis.
Put it on the x-axis.
And what are its equations?
The equations are Newton's equations,
but there's actually a more useful version
of Newton's equations,
which is just energy conservation.
Just energy conservation.
Let's write down the energy
of this particle over here,
and write down that it's conserved.
In fact,
it's a more useful equation
than this one over here,
the energy,
or more useful than F equals m-8.
What is the energy of this particle here?
It's moving outward.
It has some velocity.
The velocity could be negative.
It could be moving inward.
But what is the total energy of this particle?
The total energy of it is its kinetic energy
plus its potential energy.
Kinetic energy,
one half the mass of the particle,
not the mass of the earth,
the mass of the particle,
times its velocity squared,
which we could call x-dot squared if we wanted.
Well,
let's just leave it as velocity squared for a moment.
But what about the potential energy?
Remember the potential energy?
Potential energy is minus
little m,
big M,
Newton's constant,
divided by what?
R.
Not R squared,
just R.
Say it again.
X,
x,
x.
Yeah,
Okay.
Now,
this could be positive or negative,
believe it or not.
The energy does not have to be positive.
For example,
supposing this particle over here is at rest.
I don't know how it got there.
It got there,
it's an initial condition.
It got here at some time t.
It's at rest.
But at a positive value of x.
x is really always positive.
It really stands for the distance from the Earth,
not the x coordinate.
So x is always positive.
This is always negative.
This can be zero if the particle is at rest.
And so the energy is negative in that case.
The energy can also be positive.
Supposing we now take the
same particle at the same position,
but give it a velocity.
If the velocity is big enough,
then this can outweigh that.
This can outweigh that simply when,
if I write the equation down,
I'll write it down in a minute,
when this is bigger than this,
when the kinetic energy is bigger than the potential energy,
then the total energy is positive.
Now,
if the total energy is positive,
this thing cannot turn around.
It cannot turn.
You might say,
well,
let's see,
this particle could go out and turn around.
Why can't it turn around
if the total energy is positive?
Incidentally,
energy,
of course,
is conserved.
So whatever the energy is at one instant,
it's the energy at every instant.
Energy is conserved.
Let's suppose it turned around at that point.
What would its velocity be at that point?
Zero.
So what would its energy be?
Negative.
Right?
So therefore,
if it turns around,
it's negative.
The energy is negative.
If it doesn't turn around,
the energy is positive.
Energy equals zero is a
sort of edge of parameter space.
If the energy is positive,
the particle just keeps going and going and going.
It escapes.
If the energy is zero,
that's exactly the escape velocity.
We'll ask later whether it escapes or not
if it's exactly at zero.
What is the escape velocity?
The escape velocity is the solution of the equation
that this is equal to zero.
So let's write it out.
One half v squared.
I'm dropping the m because it cancels from both sides.
The little m.
One half v squared is equal to big M,
big G,
divided by x.
And now we can just multiply by two.
And that gives us a formula for the escape velocity.
That's the formula for the escape velocity
when the energy is exactly equal to zero.
In exactly the same manner,
the universe can be above the escape velocity,
below the escape velocity,
or at the escape velocity.
We'll...
We're going to work that out in a minute.
But all it means is
if it's above the escape velocity,
it means that initially,
at some point,
the outward expansion was large enough
that it doesn't turn around.
If it's below the escape velocity,
then the universe turns around and recontracts.
Okay.
So that's the main reason for showing you this.
And the escape velocity is kind of the edge.
The escape velocity is also the velocity
at which the energy is equal to zero.
Keep that in mind.
Escape velocity,
same thing as energy equal to zero.
All right.
Now let's concentrate on this particle over here.
Now,
for all practical purposes,
this particle over here,
all it knows is that
it's moving in the gravitational field
of a point mass at the center
where the point mass is capital M.
So for all practical purposes,
we can replace this problem over here
by this one over here.
In fact,
it's exactly the same problem.
So let's work out the energetics,
the kinetic,
the potential energy of this particle,
and keep in mind that it's constant.
It's constant because for all practical purposes,
this particle is moving exactly as it would be
if all there was was a mass at the center,
and in that case,
energy would be constant.
So we can just lift
the things that I wrote before,
but let's work them out.
Can I ask a quick question?
Yeah.
Isn't capital M in this case changing
as you move farther and farther outside
this continuous density?
No.
The whole thing is growing,
but remember,
the grid,
everything moves with the grid.
Everything moves with the grid.
The only thing that's changing is A.
The amount of mass in this sphere stays fixed.
In other words,
the number of galaxies that this fellow over here sees
within this sphere stays fixed.
Right.
Good.
Okay.
So,
no.
So we don't have to worry about that.
We don't have to worry about the mass changing.
All right.
Let's work out now the energy,
the kinetic,
well,
the kinetic plus potential energy
in Newton's frame.
In Newton's frame,
we'll work out the kinetic.
All right.
So what is it?
It's one-half MV squared again.
One-half the mass of this galaxy
times the velocity squared,
but that's A dot squared R squared.
All right.
Same R.
Where is it?
Same,
yeah,
same R.
D is equal to A times R.
Distance is A times R.
Velocity is A dot times R.
This is one-half MV squared.
And then minus little m,
big M,
G
divided by distance.
All right.
Just divided by distance.
That's the potential energy.
M,
G.
And what is the distance?
The distance is A times R,
right?
Let's do the,
and that's equal to the energy of this guy here.
That's its energy.
Now,
for simplicity,
and because it's,
because of simplicity
and also because I'm getting a little tired,
I think I will just do tonight
the case where the energy is exactly equal to zero.
What does that correspond to?
Exactly the critical escape velocity.
That case,
the other case is just as easy,
but let's do that case.
All right.
So that's the case where the universe
is sort of just on the edge.
Not clear whether it's going
to turn around and fall back
or whether it's going to keep going.
And it's on the edge of the
cusp of doing one or the other.
All right.
So we're going to set this equal to zero.
Let's work out that equation.
Let's work out that equation
using the various things we know.
Okay.
First thing to do is to
get rid of the little m here.
Why should we get rid of the little m?
Because it appears in both terms here,
and the whole thing is equal to zero,
so I divide it out.
I'll also multiply by two.
So I get two.
Next I'm going to divide by r squared.
You know,
why am I dividing by r squared?
I want to get r cubed down here,
because I know that r cubed
has to do with the volume,
and the volume,
I'm going to get density.
I'm trying to get this thing in terms of density.
All right.
So I divide by r squared,
and that gives me an r cubed downstairs.
That's nice,
because there's a mass here
and an r cubed downstairs.
It looks like I'm getting the density,
but not quite,
because the volume of the sphere
is a cubed times r cubed,
not a times r cubed.
So what do I do?
I just divide the equation by another a squared.
a cubed.
Okay.
That's...
Good.
Ah.
a cubed times r cubed.
What do I do next?
Well,
if I'm smart,
I will multiply this by four over three times pi.
That will literally make this the volume,
but I'm doing something illegal
unless I multiply it here also.
Four over three times pi.
Equals zero,
right?
Equals zero.
All right.
We're almost there.
Let me rewrite it.
a dot over a squared.
Remember what a dot over a is?
It's the Hubble constant.
So this is the square of the...
I take it back.
It's not a constant.
The Hubble thingy.
a dot over a squared.
That's the Hubble thingy squared.
And that's equal to...
I'm just transposing this to the right-hand side.
There's an eight pi over three.
Famous eight...
Two times four is eight.
Eight pi over three.
There's a g.
And now there's an m divided
by the volume of the sphere.
That's why I went to this effort here
to put another couple of
factors of a and r downstairs
so that I would get a
divided by the volume of the sphere,
and that's rho.
That's the mass density rho.
The actual mass density.
a dot over a squared equals
eight pi over three g times rho.
That is the Friedmann equation.
That's the Friedmann equation
the way that it's usually written.
It's equivalent to this equation.
This one over here is energy conservation.
Also set the energy equal to zero.
This one over here is Newton's equations.
But the same physics.
The same physics,
the Newton version of it,
the conservation of energy version of it.
This one is more useful.
As I said,
it's called the Friedmann equation.
It's not completely general because we
did set the energy to zero.
We did set it to
just exactly the critical escape velocity.
So this universe is not going to re-collapse.
But it's going to...
What does happen if you shoot
something out at exactly the escape velocity?
What happens to its motion as time goes on?
Doesn't it slow to zero at infinity?
Yeah.
It just asymptotically gets slower and slower and slower,
but it never turns around.
This universe will asymptotically get slower
and slower and slower in its expansion,
but never turn around for the same reasons.
Okay.
So that's our Friedmann equation.
I'd like to solve it,
but I don't know enough yet.
The reason I don't know enough
is because there's rho over here,
and I don't know what to do with rho,
except we do know what to do with rho.
Remember the equation that rho
is equal to the constant nu.
Incidentally,
the constant nu can be
set to be anything you want.
It doesn't...
It's not...
It's...
Yeah,
okay.
It's the mass per unit coordinate volume.
By changing your coordinates,
you can change the amount of
mass that's in a coordinate volume.
So actually,
nu never really comes into anything important.
But rho is equal to nu divided by a cubed.
Remember that?
Okay.
So we can now write an
even more useful version of this,
a dot over a squared.
Is equal to 8 pi over 3 g nu.
And nu is a constant.
Nu does not change with time.
Divided by a cubed.
I think we have it right.
All of this junk here is just a constant.
8 pi nu over 3
times g is just a constant.
In fact,
I could,
if I like,
have chosen nu
so that 8 pi g nu
over 3 is just the number 1.
There's nothing interesting in it.
The basic equation...
The basic form of the equation...
Is just that a dot over a squared
is equal to some constant.
But let's just choose that constant to be 1,
just for simplicity.
It's 1 over a cubed.
If we can solve this equation,
we can...
we can solve this one.
It's not hard to go from one to the other.
So we'd like to see how to solve this equation.
Now,
notice,
first of all,
that the right-hand side is always positive.
In fact,
it never quite goes to 0.
No matter how big a gets,
it's always positive.
As a gets really,
really big,
it gets smaller and smaller.
So that tells us
that a dot over a
never becomes equal to 0.
a dot equals 0 would be the universe turning around.
That would be the place where the universe turned around
when the expansion rate went to 0.
So this tells us the
expansion rate never goes to 0.
Hubble constant never changes sign,
or at least the square of the Hubble constant
never goes to 0.
So if it doesn't go to 0,
it can't change sign.
And...
But it does slow down.
The Hubble constant gets smaller and smaller
and smaller with time.
So it's as if the
universe just gets tired of expanding.
But it never gets tired enough to stop.
OK,
we can try to solve this.
I think I will just take the...
It's getting late,
and I get tired about this time.
So I will take the easy way of solving it,
but we will come back to these kind of equations.
We'll come back to these kind of...
This type of equation,
this is absolutely...
When I say not this type of equation,
this type of equation is absolutely central
to all of cosmology.
And we can solve them.
We can solve them quite easily.
Let's just look for a solution of a particular type,
OK?
I'll look for a solution
rather than to solve the equations.
Let's look to see if we can find a solution
where A is some constant
times time to some power.
We don't know that that's a...
that we can solve it this way,
but we can try.
We can take a trial solution.
A is...
A equals...
A proportional to T would just...
What would A proportional to T mean?
That would just mean A grows in proportion to time
in a very simple way.
We don't expect that to be right.
It's not,
because the thing slows down.
But we can look for a solution of this type.
So let's try it out.
Let's see if we can...
if we can use the equation to see what...
whether we can solve for C and P.
OK,
so what's A dot?
A dot is C,
P,
T to the P minus 1,
right?
That's just differentiation.
Now,
A dot over A...
That's easy.
We just have to divide by A,
so we have to divide this by C,
T to the P.
C's cancel.
Neat.
The constant here cancels.
And what's T to the P minus 1
over T to the P?
P over T,
right?
That's the left-hand side.
P over T...
Oh,
sorry,
we have to square it.
This...
P squared over T squared.
That's the left side.
P squared...
Sorry,
P squared over T squared.
Now,
what about 1 over A cubed?
Let's see what that is.
1 over A cubed...
That's 1...
divided by C cubed...
T to the 3P.
Do I have that right?
I did.
Now,
what we can do...
All right?
Now we can read off
how to match the two sides.
Let's get rid of this over here.
And let's match the two sides.
In the denominator,
we have a power.
We also have a power over here.
This is 1 over T squared.
This is 1 over T to the 3P,
but I haven't told you what P is yet.
So if we want to match,
I've just said...
Let's look for a solution of the form...
ct to the p and see if we can
figure out what c and p have to be.
Well the first
thing we learn is that 3p had better equal 2,
otherwise these things can't
match.
There's no way that t to the
fourth here can match with t squared here.
So the first thing we learn
is that 3p has to equal 2.
We'll come back to it in
a minute.
Alright,
that will guarantee that the
t squared and the t squared
agree on this side.
On the other hand,
we also have to match the constant and the
constant tells us that p
squared equals 1 over c cubed.
So that tells us there was really only
one constant that we had to worry about,
either p or t.
Or c.
Once we know p,
and we do know p,
we know p from here and therefore we know the
constant.
The constant is not so interesting.
What's interesting is p
because what does p say?
It says that a expands like t to the two-thirds.
p is
equal to two-thirds.
Some constant
times t to the two-thirds power.
That's the way a Newtonian universe would expand
if it had,
if it was right at the critical escape velocity.
It would expand with a
scale factor and everything,
all galaxies separating as time to the two-thirds
power.
That's quite a remarkable derivation,
I think.
I think,
you know,
Newton,
I don't know why he didn't do it.
It really,
it annoys me that he didn't do it.
He should have done it.
And I think he went to
the mint at this point or something.
I'm not sure what happened to him.
Oh,
that was,
this must have been the year that the,
the,
the year of the plague?
No,
it was the year of the tulips
when he lost his shirt on tulips.
Yeah.
He did lose his shirt on tulips,
you know.
Yeah,
yeah.
He was one of the,
one of the suckers who got the suckered by the,
the tulip bubble.
It's true,
I,
so,
you know,
smart.
Hm?
Yeah,
but I think he got,
I think he got stung.
Did,
did like Newton know there was a,
a tulip bubble?
universe?
I mean,
that wasn't known back then.
No,
but he should have predicted that there's a universe.
Oh yes he did,
and he worried about the fact that a homogeneous universe,
oh yes,
he most certainly had speculated enough that he
was right on the threshold of doing this.
He had asked all the questions about
it and didn't quite carry it out.
So,
yeah.
Does this have any assumption
on the universe being infinite?
Yes,
this is,
actually not,
but yes,
that's a good question.
We've done a completely Newtonian theory.
In Newtonian theory,
space is flat.
If space is flat,
it just goes on and on forever.
So yes.
The Newtonian theory is flat.
The Newtonian universe would have been infinite.
It would have been spatially flat.
It wouldn't have had an
interesting Einsteinian geometry of any kind,
although it would have
been expanding or contracting.
And it would have been entirely Newtonian.
All right,
so I did this just
first of all because it's easy,
second of all because it
contains a lot of the physics.
It's a lot of the physics that we're
going to be dealing with in a simple form.
And it gives us a model universe.
It gives us a model universe with a
scale factor that increases like a two-thirds power
of a time.
Excuse me.
Yeah.
Is everything that you've said here still true
in the case where we don't have a model
Is there a state velocity zero?
Not quite.
No.
Then there's another term in this equation.
There's another term in this equation.
And we will come to that other term.
OK.
So the formula involves a lot of…
No.
It can't be because if you had negative energy,
it would re-collapse.
Right.
So there's another term.
And the next time,
we'll take up that other term
and we'll talk about the three possible
possibilities.
Less than zero,
in other words,
re-collapse.
Greater than zero,
that means the universe just
expands without even thinking about it.
And this,
which is the critical point where
it slows down in a certain way.
Another diagram that people always draw for
this kind of thing looks something like this.
You've probably seen diagrams like this.
Plot.
On the vertical axis,
you plot A,
the scale factor.
And on the horizontal axis,
you plot time.
OK.
Now,
A equals T.
There's no sensible cosmology that does that,
but let's just draw it in.
Here's A equals T.
And then you have time.
Now,
what does it mean that A decelerates,
that the acceleration is negative?
That it decelerates is a statement that the curve
is bent over this way as opposed to this way.
The second derivative is negative.
The curve goes this way.
A to the 2 thirds looks approximately like this.
And of course,
it keeps growing.
What about a recontracting universe?
What if the universe recollapsed?
A collapsing universe would look like...
Crash.
And a...
This does not approach a straight line,
incidentally.
OK.
It does not approach a straight line.
It just keeps bending over slightly more and more.
And the universe of positive energy would look pretty much
the same and then go off on a straight line.
On a straight line.
Those are the three cases that we'll describe.
Did I get that right?
No,
I take this back.
This is not quite right.
I take that back.
No,
no,
no.
That's incorrect.
We'll do the case of positive energy.
But in any case,
in all of these cases,
the tendency is to curve
over because the acceleration is negative.
The real universe does not look like that.
The real universe starts out looking like that.
And then starts to curve upward.
It's accelerating.
The real universe is accelerating.
Yeah?
So we got this Ct to the 2
thirds because we tried solutions in a certain form.
Because what?
Because we tried solutions in a certain form.
Yeah.
If we were to just sit
down and experiment with other solutions,
would there be others that gave us a different result?
We'll solve the equation in detail,
though.
This is it.
This is the solution.
Yeah,
we'll,
yeah.
No,
this is the only solution.
But we can change the energy.
We can change the energy away from zero.
And if we do,
we can generate other kinds of solutions.
All right.
Okay.
Any questions?
I'm kind of tired.
But,
yeah.
Here it is.
Is the critical density universe,
does it bend over until it's horizontal?
No,
no,
no.
Well,
sorry.
Yeah.
The derivative gets smaller and smaller.
A to the 2 thirds.
All right.
So let's see.
What do we know?
A to the minus 2 thirds.
Yeah.
No,
we've already done it.
Yeah.
Let's.
C to the 2 thirds.
T to the 2 thirds.
Right?
T to the 2 thirds is A.
Right.
And A dot is equal to 2 thirds,
1 over T to the 1 third.
Right?
So the slope goes to zero.
The slope goes to zero as T gets larger.
Right.
But it's always positive.
Okay.
So this is the sense in which it's getting tired.
The slope is,
yeah.
All right.
And you can see now why Einstein failed
to be able to describe a static universe.
Well,
we'll come to it.
I'm getting ahead of myself.
Yeah.
I don't want to get ahead of myself.
Good.
Okay.
Let's.
Hmm?
If it was very old in its region case.
If it was what?
Very old.
Yeah.
It does get sort of slanted.
I think that Newton was prejud.
Yeah.
Let's see.
Uh-huh.
Yeah,
see,
Newton had this idea that
the universe was 6,000 years old,
and this wasn't fitting
together with this.
Yeah,
yeah,
Newton was a believer.
So I think he had some,
I think the reason he probably
didn't do it is because he couldn't
make it fit with his prejudice
about the age of the universe.
It's true.
Did he write papers about his
thinking and philosophy and stuff like that,
or did he
just do the...
No,
unfortunately he did.
Yeah,
sure he did.
He wrote more about religion than he did about,
yeah,
he wrote more about,
more about
religion I think and alchemy than he did about physics.
So yeah,
he was a prolific writer.
You started with Einstein's field equations.
I see that A pi G there.
Yep.
Is that,
I know that...
Same A pi G.
The time-time component?
What's that?
Yeah.
Energy,
is that how you get that?
Mm-hmm,
mm-hmm,
yep,
yep.
Not surprising since this is about energy.
Yep,
yep,
absolutely.
Is this kind of study synonymous with
what you might call a cosmological constant,
something
like that?
No,
this is the theory without a cosmological constant.
The cosmological constant is what
has to do with the acceleration.
This is the theory without the cosmological constant.
In fact,
this is called a matter-dominated universe,
a matter-dominated universe for
reasons that I will explain when we come to it.
Yes?
So,
well,
we know that the universe is expanding overall,
like the entire universe.
Are there any other things that are expanding?
Are there some galaxies in
between that could be contracting?
Well,
certainly,
yes.
Yes,
yes,
yes.
On the average,
out to the largest observable distances,
it is expanding,
but individual
little portions,
there are places.
For example,
our galaxy is contracting together with Andromeda.
Andromeda is not receding away from us.
But that's...
On large enough scales,
the Hubble law is not
exactly true for all possible distances.
It becomes accurate as distances get larger.
It's certainly not accurate for
things which are bound together.
Things which are close enough together that
they're really bound together by gravity or
any other force,
maybe being pulled together.
So as it happens,
it's not unique.
But on the average,
everything is moving away from everything else.
But here and there,
you can find galaxies which have peculiar motion.
The term peculiar motion is a technical term.
It is.
It's a technical term,
and it means what it says,
sort of away from the average.
So in an overall calculation,
we should avoid those little
galaxies and just try and look
straight past them.
Well,
that's a good question.
We should average over large enough
volumes that these little fluctuations don't matter.
Right.
It's the same kind of thing.
You say the air in the room is uniform.
Well,
that's not really true.
There are places where there's a fluctuation
where it's more dense and a fluctuation where
it's less dense.
But when averaged over a sizable region,
bigger than...
It's not a big deal.
But when it's packed inside a small...
Private place,
but it's...
Or smaller and smaller...
It's a bigger question.
Right,
it's called want gehen.
...selected,
but then given 올라vie,
I swimming on something that holds more,
uh,
in this section here at 50 times the same
you often consider that it is not the same,
fucked up student,
but in rather close chemistry.
So you can't read everything from
the top of the upper level.
Right.
This is not...
If I was a researchers of science,
I don't understand this.
However it was formed,
it was formed in a pocket
which was dense enough that just slightly
out of the ordinary,
it was dense enough that these
two galaxies had enough mass to overcome
the effect of the expansion.
Yeah.
Right.
So it's a fluctuation away from the norm.
Yeah,
there's the,
I think people describe space itself expanding,
carrying things with
it.
Is there an empirical way of determining whether
it's really that or it's just the velocity?
No,
no,
they're identical.
They mean the same.
You asked me that the last time,
I remember,
too.
Was it seven years ago?
I think you asked me the same question.
No,
there's no difference.
You see,
you either take the position.
That the galaxies are moving away from each
other or you take the position that they're
embedded in this grid and the grid is expanding.
It's a mathematical artifact.
It's a mathematical artifact,
yeah.
Perhaps in Einstein's way of thinking about it,
it's a little more natural to think of
it as space expanding,
but they are equivalent.
Yeah,
one more question.
Is there any way of
determining the mass of the galaxy?
Is there any corroborating evidence other than
the brightness of the distant type one
a supernova for the accelerating universe?
Oh,
yeah,
there's,
yes,
there is from a cosmic microwave background.
Yeah,
there is.
And we will come to it.
It's a sort of network of different observations.
The supernova,
mostly supernova and cosmic microwave
background fit together just precisely.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.