Stanford University.
Okay.
For some reason I have a
set of notes here from last week.
Did you ever get notes from last week?
Here they are if you want them.
And then I made a mistake.
In this week's notes I wrote them on pads
which are probably too long to scan in one piece.
Is that a good idea?
Okay.
I inherited a whole bunch of
yellow pads from the mathematics department.
It seems mathematicians don't like writing on long pads.
So I got them,
about 25 of them from the mathematics department.
A math friend of mine used to use butcher paper.
He had a roll.
Yeah,
right.
That's hard to scan,
isn't it?
Yeah.
Butcher paper.
Okay.
We've got a couple of minutes.
Let's begin with some questions just
for the next couple of minutes.
Yeah.
Okay.
Is it possible that the universe could
actually be smaller than the observable universe?
I don't think so.
I mean,
one idea was that it was smaller and
that it was a kind of torus that just
periodically repeated itself so that the large part
of it that we were looking at was just
repetitions of the same thing or another way
of saying that we were looking at ourselves
through the back door.
That has consequences.
That has observable consequences.
You might think it'd be real easy.
You just look out and you see,
no,
it doesn't work that way.
It's much harder than that.
And people have looked for
periodicity in astronomical and cosmological observations.
And there is no evidence and some
counter evidence that it's not periodic like that.
And if it's not,
I don't see how it could
be smaller than the observed part.
So it's an interesting question.
I don't think so.
Okay.
Yeah.
You were talking about the universe space
itself expanding under the influence of dark energy.
Mm-hmm.
Now,
I suppose the space...
So far I haven't...
I'm not sure that I've mentioned dark energy,
but so far we have not talked about dark energy.
Okay.
We will.
But the universe is expanding.
The universe is definitely expanding.
Okay.
But the expansion due...
The consequence of dark energy is
not that the universe is expanding.
It is,
but I mean,
it's not the...
The universe was expanding before
anybody knew about dark energy.
Dark energy just makes it expand faster.
Okay.
I suppose that the space in
our solar system is garden-variety space...
Yeah.
...and therefore expanding like everything else.
Well,
no.
The orbits of the planets seem to be stable.
Yeah.
No.
So where are they getting the energy from
to maintain their stable orbits in the face
of this expansion?
If you were holding your friend's hand out in space,
your distance between you and your
friend would not expand with the general expansion.
The general expansion...
Well,
I don't know.
This is in through space or,
you know,
the other way around.
So it would just pass through,
but these all want to be in the light.
So when you run this,
let's make this so it looks like
this mu is supposed to be a
very small Liverline that the big mengways are,
well,
the words are.
The M and I equal,
there's two L and I equal a bobby.
between the two of you
is more than made up for,
vastly more than made up for,
by
just the attractive force of you
holding on to your friend's hand.
So as long as
you didn't let go,
now I'll tell you a little more in a minute,
as long as you didn't
let go,
you would not participate in the general expansion,
you as a couple,
so to
speak.
In fact,
there's enough,
probably enough of other kinds of forces between
you,
besides holding your hand,
that they would overwhelm this tiny,
tiny tendency
to separate.
That's because,
you're closer together than the average
distance between your atoms.
Your atoms and your friends atoms are closer
together,
they have more attraction,
in particular,
holding your hands will
keep you from separating.
And so you're not part of this general
expansion.
The same thing is true of the solar system.
The solar system is largely
held together.
Well,
first let's talk about an atom.
What about an atom?
Why did you come to the solar system?
Why not an atom?
An atom also is
embedded in space.
If that space is expanding,
why isn't the atom also
expanding?
And the answer is the electrostatic forces,
more than
overwhelmed,
by an enormous amount,
more than overwhelm the general tendency to
expand.
Now,
what you can say is that in an expanding universe,
let's even take the
case of an accelerated expansion,
that this tiny little bit of outward force
will tend to modify the atom a little bit.
It will tend to make the atom just a
tiny,
tiny little bit bigger.
the atom will have to be slightly expanded,
but other than that,
and that's a tiny,
tiny effect,
but it will not cause the atom to fly apart.
It's not strong enough to
cause the atom to fly apart.
Same is true of the solar system.
Solar system is held together by gravity.
The gravitational pull of the sun
is simply much,
much larger than this tendency to expand.
So for that reason...
I understand that gravity is much
stronger than the tendency to expand,
but I'm asking an energy interview.
To overcome these small perturbations,
you need to do work.
Where do you get the energy from to do that?
In order to do what?
The orbit of the Earth is curved
ever so slightly by the expansion of space,
and gravity is so small,
that it's going to restore it
back to where it was before.
Where does the energy come from
to overcome that tendency to expand?
Even though it's small,
you have to have some energy to overcome it.
Energy conservation in an expanding universe
is different than energy conservation in a static universe.
Energy conservation...
There's several ways to think about it,
but let me give you the
simplest way to think about it.
Energy conservation is a
consequence of time translation invariance.
In other words,
if everything is time independent,
meaning to say space and time and all experiments
would reproduce exactly the same effect
if they were later or earlier,
the consequence of that is energy conservation.
On the other hand,
if the basic setup,
called the background,
space-time itself,
if it's not static,
if it's expanding,
or if it's changing with time,
then energy conservation doesn't apply.
There is no energy conservation in a world
where the parameters of the world are time dependent.
In this case,
the radius of the universe is time dependent.
Energy conservation is...
not quite what you thought it is.
And we're going to come to it.
We're going to use energy conservation.
We're going to use it in a certain form,
but it doesn't say that the net
amount of energy in the universe is fixed.
That is not what it says.
It basically says that changes of energy in the universe
translate into kinetic energy of expansion.
There's a back and forth
between changes of energy and expansion,
and you don't have to
ask where the energy came from.
It came from the expansion.
Yeah?
What's that mean for the homogeneity
and isotropic nature of the universe?
On certain scales,
it falls apart.
On small scales,
On large scales,
as far as we can tell,
the universe is homogeneous and isotropic.
The air in this room is largely homogeneous and isotropic.
Every time somebody opens a door,
of course,
a draft blows in,
but if we kept the room closed,
and you kept your mouth shut,
and,
you know,
the air in the room would become highly homogeneous,
but not on every scale.
On tiny,
tiny scales,
what you see is
atoms,
molecules,
and so on.
One over here,
one over here.
It's not homogeneous.
In fact,
on even bigger scales,
there are fluctuations that take place.
Density fluctuates.
Sometimes it's a little more over here,
a little less over here.
So whether something is homogeneous or not
is a scale-dependent question.
The universe is not homogeneous on small scales,
and small scales means,
you know,
hundreds of millions of light years.
On scales bigger than hundreds of millions of light years,
everything seems to be distributed uniformly.
I'm not sure I'm answering your question,
but I'm answering somebody's question.
If the universe is expanding,
how come I can't find a parking spot on campus?
Oh,
yes.
That.
Yeah.
Yeah,
no,
that's one we're working on.
When you say that something's homogeneous and isotropic
and that there was only three types of closed,
flat,
Yes.
what does that mean mathematically
in terms of the quantities in,
say,
Einstein's field?
Okay.
It's a statement about geometry.
Einstein's equations are the dynamics
of how things change with time and so forth.
This is a pure statement of geometry.
If you classify the geometries,
which are in some sense the same everywhere,
that every point is the same as every other point,
then what that means,
I'll tell you what it means exactly.
Given a space,
how do you describe a space?
You describe a space by a metric.
You write a metric for the space,
some g mu nu of x,
or g,
let's,
it's only space,
it's not space and time,
so let's call it g m n.
So,
the point x is the origin of the coordinates,
that represents some geometry.
Now,
you can make a coordinate transformation.
Imagine you make a coordinate transformation.
The point x equals zero,
which was the origin of the coordinates,
this was x equals zero,
that now has a new value.
The new coordinates could be called y.
Alright,
what was originally x equals zero
is no longer the origin.
y equals zero might be over here.
And so this corresponds to some kind of transformation
which replaces the origin with some new origin.
Now,
when you do that,
the metric,
when you do a coordinate transformation,
the metric transforms.
It transforms into a new metric,
we can call it g prime m n
of y,
and this is the metric in the y coordinates.
Typically,
the metric in the y coordinates
will have a different form
than the metric in the x coordinates.
That could be for two reasons.
Two reasons.
First of all,
it could be because the space itself
is different at this point than this point,
and so if we transform our coordinates to this point,
we might discover that the curvature is larger over here
or something different over here,
in which case the metric will
have a different look to it
when you express it in terms of y
than it did in terms of x.
Or it might be not because the points are different,
but simply because you used screwy coordinates over here
and some other screwy coordinates over here.
A homogeneous space means,
one,
that you can find a coordinate transformation
which will replace any given point,
as origin,
let's say,
any given point by any other point
in such a way that the form of the metric
is identical both before and after the transformation.
For example,
for example,
let's just take flat space.
Flat space has a metric
which is the s squared,
equals the x squared,
let's just take two dimensions,
dy,
the x squared,
the x1 squared,
plus the x2 squared.
x1 squared plus the x2 squared,
where x1 and x2 are the coordinates in the blackboard.
Now supposing I make a translation of coordinates,
that means let y,
y doesn't stand for x and y,
it stands for a new set of coordinates,
which is just equal
to x at y1 is x1
plus a shift.
Let's call it a1.
a does not stand for any other a
that we've used so far in this course.
And y2 is equal to x2 plus a2.
This is a shift.
This is a shift which,
if this is the x coordinates,
then the y coordinates are shifted by a vector a.
What is the metric in terms of y coordinates?
Well,
we can do it by simply re-expressing dx1
in terms of dy1,
but dy1 is the same as dx1.
If I differentiate,
if I make a little change in y,
it will be equal to the little change in x,
but since this is a constant,
it doesn't contribute anything.
Likewise for dy2.
So,
for this kind of transformation,
ds2 is equal also to dy1 squared
plus dy2 squared.
It has exactly the same form
as the metric had in terms of x's.
The implication of that
is that the neighborhood of the origin,
x equals 0,
has exactly the same properties
as the neighborhood of the origin of y equals 0,
of the y coordinates.
In other words,
these two points
have exactly the same property.
Now,
since a could be anything,
there's a coordinate transformation
which takes the origin over here
to any other point,
to any other point whatever,
that preserves the form of the metric,
and that's what's called a homogenous matrix.
So,
a homogenous space
whose properties are everywhere the same.
So,
if there exists a coordinate transformation
between x and y
that takes the origin
to any other point
such that the form of the metric
in terms of y is the same as in x,
then the space is called homogenous
and it means it's everywhere the same.
A sphere,
take a sphere.
We could put the origin,
the south pole.
The south pole could be the origin.
You know what the form of the metric is.
We wrote it down last time.
I'll write it down again for you.
The r squared plus sine squared r
times,
let's say,
d phi squared
or d theta squared.
I've forgotten what I called it.
d theta squared,
that's the metric of the sphere.
Now,
let's make a coordinate transformation.
By rotating the sphere.
Rotating the sphere means choosing some other point,
the point over here,
for example.
Instead of measuring r from the south pole,
we measure r from the east pole.
Here's the east pole over here.
We measure r from that point.
And instead of measuring angles about the south pole,
we measure angles about the east pole.
This is a coordinate transformation.
It's a little nasty and complicated to write down.
How does the distance from this point depend on,
you know,
the coordinates as measured about here?
A little bit complicated.
But when you figure it out,
you'll find that the metric,
when written in terms of
the coordinates relative to this point,
has exactly the same form as relative to this point.
Another,
I won't bother writing it down,
it'll be exactly the same form,
except that the meaning of r and theta
will be distances measured from here instead of here,
and angles measured about that
point instead of about that point.
Form of the metric is the same.
And since you can choose your coordinate transformation
to take this point to any point,
it tells you that every point on the sphere
is basically the same as
every other point on the sphere.
One test,
which works very well in two dimensions,
for a uniform geometry,
is that the curvature should be the same everywheres.
That's not good enough in other dimensions,
but the basic idea that
the geometry is the same everywheres
is called a homogeneous geometry.
This is also true,
it's true of the flat plane,
it's true of the sphere,
that it's homogeneous,
and it is also true of the hyperbolic plane,
of the negative curved,
sort of analog of the sphere,
where you replace signs by hyperbolic signs.
There are no others.
Yeah,
yeah,
good,
right.
Right,
there,
um...
No,
okay,
this...
Yes,
it is true that the torus,
the torus is,
um...
translation invariant is the right word.
Translation invariant means you can
transform any point to any other.
But,
as a matter of fact,
it happens not to be isotropic.
Why is it not isotropic?
It's not isotropic because there are definite...
Remember I told you what a torus is.
It's a rectangle with,
um...
with periodic boundary conditions.
And the axes...
are preferred.
If you go out here,
you come out here,
so this axis is preferred,
that axis is preferred,
and an axis like that
is basically different.
Observations would be different along 45 degrees than along,
um...
So...
Yes,
it's true,
it's a homogeneous space,
but it's not an isotropic space.
Good.
So...
Uh...
Good.
Now,
of course,
the idea that,
uh,
that space is homogeneous and isotropic
kind of has a status
somewheres between being a postulate
and therefore highly questionable,
on the one hand,
and somewheres in between that
and an observational fact.
So,
on certain levels,
on certain scales,
it really does look homogeneous,
but on scales so big that we can't see them,
we don't know.
Okay,
that,
uh...
One other remark before we go on,
since this comes up over and over and over again,
I just wanna...
And you'll be tired of hearing this,
but...
Um...
There's often an enormous amount of confusion
when you say such things as,
for example,
um,
space has a spherical shape.
All right?
People get into their heads
the idea that it really is like a balloon,
and namely that it has an inside and an outside.
And they ask questions.
What happens if you move away from the balloon?
Or into the balloon?
No,
you have to learn to think of geometries
as having their own intrinsic shape,
that has to do with what happens
if you move around in the geometry,
and not having to do with some imaginary,
possibly real,
or maybe imaginary,
additional directions that you can move away from the space.
For example,
the,
uh...
One of the most confusing kinds of spaces
is a one-dimensional space.
A one-dimensional space
is a one-dimensional space,
let's say a closed one-dimensional space,
a closed and finite one-dimensional space.
What is a closed...
Here's a closed and finite one-dimensional space.
Here's another one.
Uh...
Happens to be a square.
Okay?
From the point of view of the intrinsic geometry,
all that counts
is measuring distance along the,
uh...
along the geometry.
No concept,
as far as the intrinsic geometry goes,
of moving away from the surface.
So in fact,
how many different kinds of one-dimensional spaces
are there from the intrinsic point of view?
The answer is one.
All of them are ident...
Well,
not quite.
They're not identical to each other.
There's a one-parameter family of them,
and the parameter is how far around
you have to go to
come back to the same place.
So if this circle here
happens to have the same circumference
as this,
um...
uh...
peanut-shaped,
shape over here,
then intrinsically they are identical.
They're identical,
and in fact,
do they...are they curved?
They are not curved,
and to see that they're not curved,
think of them as strings,
not super strings,
not,
uh...
not string theory strings,
just as strings.
Without stretching the strings,
you can always deform them
to make any piece of them straight.
Just pull and straighten it out.
Uh...
The...one intrinsic fact about them
is that they are closed.
They come back to themselves.
But since any piece of it
could be straightened out
without stretching,
without deforming the metric,
the distance between points,
one-dimensional spaces are all flat.
They have no curvature.
The fact that they're drawn curved,
that has to do with the way
you drew them in two dimensions.
Hmm?
Right.
So you have to learn to think
about the intrinsic geometry.
It's hard,
and there's a reason that it's hard.
Yeah?
Could you have a line segment?
A line segment...
A line segment is also
a one-dimensional space.
It has a different property
than the closed one-dimensional space.
It's topologically different.
It has endpoints.
But the only thing that characterizes it
is the distance between the endpoints.
This line segment
is the same as that line segment.
It's a segment.
And...
Good.
It's only meaningful
to think of different shapes
if the one-dimensional space is embedded.
That's right.
Only if it's embedded.
Now,
I emphasize this over and over again
when explaining some of these things
to a general audience.
I think I probably said it to you before.
But what is it,
after all,
that is special about three dimensions?
And so I typically ask the question,
do you think that you can visualize
a five-dimensional space?
Visualize.
Visualize means close your eyes and see it.
Okay?
And everybody says,
no,
I can't do that.
Well,
I can't do it either.
Four?
Not really.
No,
I can play...
I can use a trick to help me visualize it,
but direct visualization,
I cannot.
Now I say close your eyes
and see if you can see a sphere.
Let's not take a sphere.
Let's take a...
Let's take a cube.
Can you visualize a cube?
Yeah,
I can visualize the cube.
I can see its cubical nature.
I can see its three-dimensionality.
And then we go down with the dimension.
Let's go down to two dimensions.
What I want you to do is to visualize
an abstract two-dimensional space.
Can you do that?
And everybody says,
sure.
And I say,
what do you see?
They say,
oh,
I see a curved surface.
And my response to that is,
yes,
you see a curved surface,
but the only way you can visualize it
is by visualizing it as embedded in three dimensions,
unless you have some brain different than mine.
Can you even visualize a one-dimensional space?
Sure,
I can see a line.
No,
what you see is that line
possibly embedded on a piece of paper,
on two dimensions,
or possibly embedded in three dimensions.
And even a point,
an abstract point,
you cannot visualize without seeing its society.
It's embedded in three dimensions.
What is it that's special about three dimensions?
Is there something really mathematically special?
No.
It's your architecture.
Your brain architecture evolved
for the purpose of navigating around in three dimensions.
And so it's not surprising
that your ability at visualizing
is hung up at three dimensions.
That doesn't mean that three dimensions
are in any way,
of course,
every dimensionality
has its own special features,
but three dimensions is not special.
And,
you know,
as mathematically sophisticated people,
we just say,
if you want to discuss two dimensions,
you make an X and a Y.
If you want to discuss three dimensions,
you make an X and a Y and a Z.
If you want to discuss four dimensions,
you make an X,
a Y,
a Z,
and a W.
And you can get,
I like to joke,
that you can get all the way through
from 20 to 26 dimensions.
And so forth.
Okay,
so I just want to remind you
over and over again
that when you,
I won't do it again,
I will not do it again,
but that when we talk
about the geometry of a space,
we're talking about the intrinsic geometry
and not the way it's embedded
for purposes of visualization
in some higher dimensional geometry.
There is,
yeah?
In the observed universe,
there is only three space shelters.
Right.
Except,
except,
unless there are more.
The more would be very small,
too hard to see.
Yeah,
yeah.
if I drew this,
if I,
all right,
let's...
So when you say intrinsic,
you're talking about what can a person
living in that,
or some...
That's right.
...discover about their...
Assume that light rays
only propagate along the surface.
If it's a one-dimensional world
that we're living in,
which we're not,
but if it's a one-dimensional world,
doesn't matter how we draw it,
as long as it's one-dimensional,
but assume that it has the properties
sort of as an optical fiber,
that light only propagates internally along it,
and no such thing as messages
are getting off the axis,
and back onto it,
that everything that takes place
takes place on the line,
or on the line segment.
With that stipulation,
there would be no difference
between this
and the straight line segment.
They would be identical.
Yeah.
So if a circle,
a line,
a closed line,
had no curvature in its intrinsic space...
Yeah.
...then the same thing for two-dimensional.
Right.
No.
Two-dimensional surfaces cannot be,
in general,
cannot be deformed
without stretching them
to make them flat.
It cannot.
Okay?
The curvy line segment here,
the right term
is that the intrinsic curvature is zero,
the extrinsic curvature is not zero.
Extrinsic curvature means
what you naively think about
when you say this is a curved line.
And it has to do with the way
the line is placed into higher dimensions.
But,
as you said,
from the point of view of little creatures
that live on this line
and can't see anything off the line,
they have no experience off the line,
no experience of anything,
and so as far as they're concerned,
there's only the line.
Okay?
So that's the way you should think about it.
And not ask whether the line is embedded in the...
Now,
you know,
if...
These creatures could be fooled.
They might literally live on a optical fiber
and think everything is moving along that optical fiber.
But no doubt there would be some things
that they could do.
For example,
they could invent a laser
within their own fiber
which emitted high enough frequencies,
gamma rays,
and I assure you that gamma rays
do not stay in an optical fiber.
They will jump across.
So it's conceivable
that these creatures could discover
that they really are living in a bigger space
with more dimensions.
I don't think that's going to happen with us.
Nothing like that.
But...
But the experimental facts at the moment
tell us that we're living in a three-dimensional world,
and that three-dimensional world
has an intrinsic geometry,
the intrinsic geometry being
one of three kinds...
Yes?
I think another good example is just a flat plane.
Your critter's living in a flat plane,
and you can walk around and
you can see that it's flat.
Yeah,
right.
If you take a portion of that
and bend it into a cylinder,
that's still as flat as it was before.
Right.
That is a good...
That's right.
But extrinsically,
it's curved in space.
Right.
That's exactly right.
And it's a useful example.
A piece of paper that you take
and curve it like this
is no less flat
from the intrinsic point of view
than the flat piece of paper that you started with.
All the relationships within the surface
are the same as they were before you
bent it like this.
So that's as flat as...
But this is not true
of,
let's say,
a sphere or a hemisphere.
Let's take a hemisphere.
You'll notice that this can easily be flattened
without stretching it.
This cannot be flattened without stretching it.
So two-dimensional surfaces can be curved.
One-dimensional surfaces or one-dimensional lines,
curves,
cannot be curved.
I have a quick question.
The gravitational field implies an intrinsic curvature.
Mm-hmm.
Is the converse also true?
I always have difficulty with converses.
Let's see,
wait.
A gravitational field implies curvature.
Does a curvature imply a gravitational field?
Yes,
yes,
yes.
As I've mentioned to you before,
curvature is a measure of tidal forces,
and tidal forces have to be due to something.
In general relativity,
they have to be due to masses,
and therefore they are the tidal gravitational fields
due to some masses,
yes.
Right.
Okay.
That was a long but very,
very,
I thought,
hopefully helpful to you.
Long question period.
Yeah,
okay.
Okay,
let's move on now.
Let's accept that space is isotropic and homogeneous,
and therefore is one of the three candidate type spaces.
I'll give names,
very colorful names.
The colorful names are k equals 1,
k equals 0,
and k equals minus 1.
The k stands for curvature.
Curvature equals 0.
That's flat space.
k equals 1.
That's positively curved space,
and it's the analog of a sphere,
but of course we are
not talking about a two-dimensional sphere.
Space is not a two-dimensional sphere.
It could be a three-dimensional sphere.
Now again,
keep in mind,
when I say that space
is either flat or a sphere
or a hyperbolic plane,
and then it's completely homogeneous,
that of course is not completely
true.
It's definitely not completely true.
It could be true for
the average properties of the space
over distance scales of big enough to average things out.
It's a statement comparable to
saying the Earth is a sphere,
or the surface of the Earth is a sphere.
But of course the surface of
the Earth has bumps on it,
it has mountains,
it has valleys,
it has this and that,
so it's certainly not a perfect sphere.
However,
on how big a distance
do you have to think about
before mountains,
valleys,
all that sort of stuff average out?
50 miles?
Let's see,
Mount Everest is what,
7 miles high?
Okay,
so on a scale of 100 miles by 100 miles,
the Earth looks pretty flat.
On a scale of 100 miles by 100 miles,
On a scale of 1000 miles by 1000 miles,
it looks very flat.
So this idea of whether something is flat or not
is a scale-dependent idea.
Now of course,
the Earth did not have to be flat
even on scales of 1000 miles.
It could have been shaped like a cigar.
Then on no scale would it
have been thought to be flat.
So there's some content in saying that the Earth
on big enough scales is homogeneous and isotropic,
the surface of it,
and that it looks spherical.
Same is true of cosmology.
Okay,
so now let's,
I think we discussed last time a little bit,
I think we started to discuss space-time geometry.
We're now moving from Newton.
Once we start to talk about curved geometry,
of course we've moved away from Newton.
And we're doing relativity.
General relativity.
General relativity starts with a metric.
It starts with a metric.
And we are going to make an assumption
about the space-time metric.
We're going to make the assumption
that space and time aren't mixed with each other.
Aren't mixed with each other in the metric.
In other words,
the metric has a form that looks like this.
Minus dt squared.
Remember,
in relativity,
the time component of the metric
always comes in with a minus sign.
And the space component of the metric
comes in with a plus sign.
Some scale factor,
which depends on time in general,
has to do with the expansion
of the universe and so forth,
times a metric of one time.
So,
one of three types.
One of three types.
k equals,
I erased k equals one,
k equals zero,
and k equals minus one.
But,
the three metrics which can be here are,
first of all,
k equals zero.
That's flat space.
Just plain old dx squared
plus dy squared plus dz squared.
That's k equals zero.
And as far as we're concerned now,
that's just its name,
k equals zero.
There is k equals plus one.
That means the positively curved space.
And we can either write that
it is d omega three squared,
or we can write it out in detail.
We can write it out
that it's equal to dr squared
plus sine of r squared.
sine of r squared.
squared d theta squared.
Oh,
sorry,
wait a minute.
No,
no,
I made a mistake,
didn't I?
I had one more to mention.
Yeah.
d omega two squared.
All right,
so that's k equals one.
We could have also written this one,
the flat space,
in a similar form,
still doing k equals zero.
We could have written it as dr
squared plus r squared d omega two squared.
This is three-dimensional polar coordinates.
Same space,
but in three-dimensional polar coordinates,
where r equals zero is your location,
and omega two is just the angular world around you.
This is also just k equals zero,
same thing,
no change.
And finally,
k equals minus one,
which is the hyperbolic Escher,
angels and devils world,
except in three dimensions,
and that's dr squared plus hyperbolic sine
squared of r times the same d omega two squared.
They all look similar,
but qualitatively,
they are,
especially quantitatively,
but qualitatively,
they're fairly different.
This a of t squared is called the scale factor.
The distance between fixed points,
by fixed points,
I mean points with fixed coordinates in space,
the distance between two points will,
in general,
be proportional to a
times some characteristic difference,
for example,
on the three-dimensional sphere.
There might be some angular distance here,
some,
I don't know,
let's just call it delta of some angle.
But this delta of angle is just some fixed value,
which is the distance on the unit sphere.
Likewise,
the velocity between those same two points
is the same thing,
except time differentiated.
The ratio of the velocity to the distance,
Hubble's law,
v equals a dot over a,
times the distance,
just dividing these two.
And the thing about a dot over a,
that's not a constant in general,
it could be a constant,
by constant I mean independent of time,
could be a constant,
but in general it's not a constant,
but it doesn't depend on position.
That's the sense in which the Hubble constant,
a dot over a is a constant,
it doesn't depend on where you are,
although it may depend on when you are.
All right.
Okay,
so there we are with the basic geometry,
the basic setup.
Now what we want to do with it.
Now we're all set up.
Last quarter we learned about Einstein's field equations.
We learned that they're complicated as hell,
that actually writing them down in detail
is a real pain in the butt.
And we're not going to write them down,
but I'll write down the general form of them.
But how do you do it?
You write down the metric,
in this case the space-time metric,
a of t squared,
the full space-time metric,
incidentally in case you were wondering,
this multiplies this.
Was that clear?
Yeah,
okay.
Good.
You write down the space-time metric,
you calculate the,
you calculate the Einstein tensor,
you set it equal to whatever
it's supposed to be set equal to,
and out of that operation comes equations
for how A varies with time.
That's the goal.
Now,
how do you calculate the Einstein field tensor
on the left-hand side,
the energy momentum tensor on the right-hand side,
Einstein's field equations,
you have to calculate some Christoffel symbols,
they have derivatives of all kinds and so forth,
and there's a lot of Christoffel symbols.
In this case there aren't too many actually,
but it's a nuisance,
and I'm not going to do it on the blackboard.
We're just going to outline what the basic idea is,
and then I'll plug,
I'll mentally plug in the Einstein field equations
and spell out the answer.
Not the answer for what
the geometry of what A is,
but what equations A satisfies.
Okay.
So let's just remind ourselves,
the Einstein field equations have a left-hand side
and a right-hand side,
like any equation.
The left-hand side has to do with geometry.
If you remember,
and if you don't remember,
it's not going to be terribly important,
but if you remember,
the left-hand side is called the Einstein field,
and you can see,
and you finished that equation.
So that's exactly what the Einstein field equation is.
We just need to know what's the qua mode
and then we're ready to go to the next thing.
Very useful.
We got to the end of this part,
I'm going to do it again.
Well,
the slow speed test,
the Eisen theory test is very angry,
and I'm Thousands of submitted it
so even if we're in the
revolution and he ended it really fast,
and I think we got,
times the scale of curvature,
r.
And as I said,
it will not be terribly important
what the details of this is.
Just notice the left-hand side has the curvature tensor,
and the right-hand side has...
Anybody remember what's on the right-hand side?
Anybody remember?
The energy momentum tensor.
The energy momentum tensor,
but it also has 8 pi g divided by 7,
right?
No,
you know it's not 7,
it's 3.
I'll just remind you,
this was the same factor
that appeared in Newton's equations.
And the energy momentum tensor T-muni.
Both sides are a tensor.
Therefore,
if it's true in any frame,
it's true in every frame.
This is a good tensor law of physics.
First question,
let's start with the right-hand side.
T-mu-nu contains a complex of things
which include the density of energy,
the flow of energy,
the flux of energy,
the density.
The density of momentum and the flux of momentum.
Different components of it.
In particular,
the time-time component is the one
that we're going to fix on.
The time-time component,
8 pi g over 3 times T-time-time,
T-naught-naught.
The time-time component is the energy density.
Okay.
So,
let's call the energy density...
Rho.
We've been calling it Rho previously.
Let's just call it Rho.
It stands for the energy,
the ordinary energy in matter,
whatever kind of material this
energy momentum is describing.
Incidentally,
the right-hand side is completely sensitive
to the kind of material that's in
the universe.
Is it particles?
Is it electromagnetic radiation?
Is it something else?
It knows about the material.
It knows about the material nature of
the ingredients that are making up the universe.
The left-hand side has nothing to do with it.
The left-hand side is geometry.
So,
on the right-hand side of the
time-time equation is the energy density.
And on the left side is something that involves curvature.
Now,
if you go back to the definition of the curvature,
work it out,
you'll discover that
there are two contributions to it,
one of which has second derivatives with respect
to the coordinates,
and the other has first derivatives squared,
or quadratic things in
the first derivatives.
Fortunately for us,
this particular combination,
when you take the time-time components,
only
has one of the three.
The first two.
The things with second derivatives,
that you have to differentiate the metric twice,
these
things are made up out of derivatives of the metric.
The things which involve differentiating the
metric twice actually cancel between these
two for the time-time component,
not for the space components,
but for the time-time
component.
So,
on the right-hand side here,
the left-hand side,
excuse me,
things are strictly proportional
to squares of first derivatives.
Quadratic things,
first derivatives.
That's one thing.
The second fact is that the energy momentum,
that the Einstein tensor here has two contributions.
One comes from derivatives with respect to space.
The other comes from derivatives with respect to time.
The things which have to do
with only derivatives with respect to space,
the other comes from
derivatives with respect to going through
연습 bisentids of the recurrence in that
system and going through battlen,
and these giving observances.
There's a quick term here.
I will call it that.
A curatorial study,
a nenhum.
contribution in here.
The other has to do with
the way space is changing with time,
but the only way in which space changes
with time is through the factor of a of
t here.
So there's going to be one factor
which will have to do with time
derivatives of a squared.
One term in this equation here will have to do,
will
have a factor of a dot,
some kind of factor with a dot squared in it.
And if
you work it out,
guess what you find?
It's a dot squared over a squared.
It's a bit of a
nuisance,
but you can calculate it,
a dot squared over a squared.
The other term
which has to do with the curvature of
space itself comes in with a plus sign.
It's a plus sign.
And think about for a moment how curved
a space is as a function of its radius.
If the Earth were a
thousand times bigger than it is,
I think we would all agree
that it would be less curved,
at least locally,
that it would look flatter to us.
If the Earth was a marble,
it would be small,
but its curvature would be large.
The curvature of a surface scales
in a certain way as its radius,
and in fact it's one over the radius squared.
The curvature of a sphere,
for example,
is one over the radius squared,
and it either comes in,
well,
it's proportional to one over a squared,
and it either...
...is positive if space is a sphere,
zero if space is flat,
minus one if space is a hyperboloid.
So it means that there's a k here,
and k is plus,
minus,
one,
or zero.
So it's just a placeholder here that tells you
which of the three kinds of spaces you're talking about.
This is what Einstein's equations boil down to.
In fact,
let's just switch this to the other side.
Let's just switch it to the other side
so it becomes minus k over a squared.
But this equation is absolutely identical to the Newtonian version
if we think of rho as the mass density for a...
...it's the equations that we've already explored.
The only thing new is that we
now have an interpretation of this term.
Do you remember what this term
stood for in the Newtonian example?
It stood for the energy,
whether the energy was positive,
negative,
or zero.
It had to do with whether you
were above or below the escape velocity.
That's the same exact term here.
But it has to do with something entirely different,
or something on the face of it very,
very different,
namely the curvature of space.
Same equation,
somewhat different physical interpretation.
You might ask,
why does this general theory of relativity,
which contains among other things the
ingredients of special relativity and so forth,
why is it the same as Newton's equations?
And the reason is basically that if you look...
Let's suppose the universe is curved,
but we just look on
a small little piece of it.
A small little piece of it,
we can't tell that it's curved,
but look at all the galaxies in there.
The way these galaxies move for
a small enough piece here must be...
The curvature can't be important for a small enough piece.
Once we realize that the curvature can't be small enough,
and that the equations are exactly the same
for a small piece or a big piece,
we realize that we
must somehow reproduce Newton's equations.
But in any case,
we do.
The Newtonian version...
...is correct.
But we do have to keep in...
...and remember that in Newton's physics,
this stood for the mass density.
I'm setting the speed of light equal to one,
so mass,
E equals mc squared is just E equals m.
Energy and momentum,
same units.
This was the density of ordinary mass,
ordinary rest mass.
It was assumed in Newton's equations that everything
is moving much slower than the speed of light,
and if I have a collection of particles
all moving much slower than the speed of light,
the energy density is just the density of mass.
On the other hand,
these equations are more general.
They follow from Einstein's equations,
and for example,
they do apply to situations where particles
may be moving fast relative to each other.
In fact,
they even apply if the energy
density here is due to photons,
massless radiation moving with the speed of light.
So,
the Newtonian equations wouldn't know
what to do with photons.
The Einstein equations know what to do with photons,
or radiation.
But otherwise,
the equations look very similar.
Okay.
Yes?
Um...
Two questions.
In that metric where we assume
that space and time are separated...
Yes.
...are we giving any...
Does that correspond to some physical restriction,
or is that just the way things are?
Yeah,
if you...
It's a consequence of isotropy and homogeneity.
If it's isotropic and it stays isotropic,
and homogeneous and it stays homogeneous,
there really is no alternative.
We could prove that,
but I won't prove it tonight.
But it is a consequence of that.
And also,
why are we focusing on
the time-time component of that equation?
Mm-hmm.
You could actually choose any of them.
For example,
you could choose the space-space component.
What you would get would again be like Newton,
except instead of being...
This is the energy equation from Newton.
It's the F equals mA equation.
The F equals mA equation does have second time derivatives.
It has A double dot.
All right?
There are a linear combination
of the space-space and the space-time
and the time-time equations,
which instead of looking like the energy equation,
really do look like the Newton F equals mA equations.
But they're all equivalent.
The point is they're all equivalent.
They better be equivalent.
Why is it that you don't
need more than just one of them?
Well,
for this simple example,
there's only one function to calculate.
It's A of t.
More general context where geometry may be wavy
and fluctuate and do other things,
you may need all of the equations,
because there are just a lot of functions to compute.
Here,
for this case,
the only unknown is A of t.
It's only one function,
and so really you only need one equation.
You could have picked any one of them.
All right.
Good.
You could not have picked the mixed space-time equations.
Then you would have just got zero equals zero.
But if you take the space-space components,
you'll get the same equations back.
Okay.
Let me just remind you one more set of facts,
and then I want to discuss,
so we'll take a little break,
and we'll discuss the equation of state
and how it determines information about this row.
What do I mean by information about row?
I mean how row itself varies
as a function of the scale factor.
There's not much you can do with this equation
unless you know something more about row.
Well,
we do know more things about row.
For example,
if row was just made of ordinary particles
just sitting there,
and the universe expands,
it's quite clear that the density of energy decreases,
and we even know how.
All right.
I'll write it down in a minute.
If it's radiation,
it decreases in another way.
So how row depends on A
depends on the nature of the
material that's making up the energy,
but it's clear that in order to solve this equation,
to even think about it as having any content,
we have to know something
about how row depends on A.
If we know how row depends on A,
then this just becomes an equation,
an ordinary differential equation,
for A as a function of time.
All right.
So I'm just going to write down now.
We're going to take a little break,
but before I want to write down two examples.
The two examples are the ones I just mentioned.
Here they are.
They have names.
One of them is called matter-dominated.
And it simply corresponds to ordinary particles
moving slowly relative to the mesh.
Particles which are not moving so fast
that we have to worry either about relativity
or even kinetic energy very much.
Their energy,
if you're standing next to one of these particles,
its energy relative to you is simply its mass.
All right.
So,
it's called matter-dominated.
And it's the case where
the energy density,
row,
is equal to some constant,
row naught,
let's call it,
divided by A cubed.
Incidentally,
what is A?
What is the meaning of A?
Let's take the case,
let's take the spherical case.
In the spherical case,
the meaning of A is extremely important.
It's extremely clear.
It's the radius of the universe at any given instant.
The radius of the sphere.
Let's take that case.
A has a definite meaning.
Of course,
we have to provide some units.
We could measure meters,
let's say in meters.
Then in meters,
A is simply the radius of the universe.
And what is row naught?
Row naught is just the density
at the time when A was equal to one.
At the time when the universe
had a radius of one meter,
now,
we don't want to go that far,
really.
Maybe a megaparsec would be a better idea.
But just conceptually,
conceptually,
the meaning of row,
the meaning of row naught
is that it is the density,
whatever that density was,
when the universe was one meter large.
That's a tunable thing.
You can change it.
It's sort of initial conditions.
So,
row is a constant,
but every time you double the radius of the universe,
or change the scale of the universe
by rescaling A,
the density changes
by the cube power of A.
So that's straightforward.
Question?
Over here?
Yeah.
So,
at one point in a couple of lectures ago,
you said that it's possible
that the universe was infinite
even at the Big Bang,
at the instant of the Big Bang.
So,
that doesn't violate this
because you can have an infinity
that's three times as large as the initial infinity.
Yeah.
Okay,
so that's...
Yeah.
In the flat case,
which is infinite,
A itself has no invariant meaning,
nothing to compare it with.
In the round case,
you can compare it with
the radius of the whole universe.
Also,
in the negatively curved space,
there's a natural definition
of the radius of a hyperbolic geometry.
Okay.
The other case that we talked about
was radiation-dominated.
So,
let's say that A is
Rho is rho-naught divided by a fourth,
and we talked at length
about the difference between these two,
the fact that if you had a bit of both,
that very early on,
this would be dominant
because 1 over a to the fourth
is likely to be bigger than 1 over a cubed.
Late times,
this is dominant.
We talked about that.
no change,
everything is exactly the same as before,
but one new piece of
information.
If you remember,
the sign of K here determined whether the universe
is going to continue to expand
linearly or whether it's going to re-collapse.
So
what we find now is a correlation.
Incidentally,
this will change a little
bit when we come to talk about dark energy,
but up till now with these forms
of energy,
if K is positive,
that's the sphere case,
that corresponds to the
situation where the universe re-collapses.
If it's flat,
then it's as if every
galaxy was exactly at the escape velocity,
so it continues to expand,
ever
slowing down and slowing down
and asymptotically coming to rest,
and then it's going to re-collapse.
So that's the situation.
So we have a new
case,
but it doesn't re-collapse,
but it's sort of a knife edge.
And the last case is
K negative,
in which case that corresponds
to being above the escape velocity,
and in
that case,
at late times,
A just continues to increase
linearly as a function of time.
Alright,
so as I said,
we didn't waste our time by doing the Newtonian case.
The Newtonian
case and the Einstein case are very,
very similar.
They're correlated.
Let's take a break for a few minutes.
Alright.
We want to understand these kind of equations better.
If the only
possibilities were matter dominated and radiation dominated,
we might not care
very much to give a
more general understanding of these equations.
What's the point of a
general understanding when there's only two cases?
But of course,
there are many cases.
There are many things in
between matter dominated and radiation dominated,
and not only in between,
but more extreme.
There's a whole range of possible behaviors like this,
and they are
important.
They are important to understand.
Okay.
So,
let's take a look at the next one.
we have a new case,
and we're going to
look at the next one.
So,
we have a new case.
And so,
we want a deeper understanding of
the connection for different kinds of material.
Let's call it material.
For different kinds
of material of how the energy density
would change as a function of scale factor.
What
is it that you need to know?
Now,
we're going to go through this in two steps.
We'll go through it in two steps.
I don't know that we'll finish tonight,
but the important
ingredient,
the important ingredient in determining how rho
depends as a function of a is the
equation of state.
It's what is called the equation of state.
We'll have two steps.
The
first is to Hispania.
The first is to Myriads and Chalimani.
The first is the equation of
etc.
But the first part will be
to assume an equation of state,
and I will tell you exactly
what I mean by an equation of state,
to assume an equation of state and from that derive
derive equations like that.
The second...
Right,
so the first step will be
to assume an equation of state
and derive the appropriate formula of this type.
The second part will be to
derive for different kinds of materials
the equation of state.
I don't think we'll get to both of them tonight.
Tonight I'm going to assume the equation of state.
For what?
For different...
We're just going to write down equations of state,
and I'll tell you what they correspond to,
but the next time we will derive the relationship
between the equation of state
and the kind of material we're talking about.
All right,
what do I mean by an equation of state?
Well,
an equation of state is basically a thermodynamic idea,
and it's the relationship
between...
Basically,
the relationship between thermodynamic variables
describing a system.
For our purposes,
temperature will not play any big role.
Temperature is not going to be the important thing.
The important thing is going
to be pressure and energy density.
And in particular,
the equation of state is a relationship
between energy density and pressure.
Now,
even for ordinary...
Even for an ordinary gas,
it is quite clear that there's a connection between...
Ordinary gas now,
of moving particles.
It's quite clear that there's a connection,
in this room,
for example,
between the energy density and the pressure.
The higher the energy density...
And what energy density are we talking about?
Basically,
the kinetic energy of molecules.
There's the mc squared,
which is dominant by far,
much bigger than anything else.
But let's forget the mc squared for a moment,
just to get the idea.
There's the kinetic energy of motion of the molecules.
And...
The kinetic energy is proportional to the square,
the velocity,
and so forth.
Those same molecules bounce off the walls of the room
and exert pressure.
It's pretty clear that the faster the molecules move,
the bigger the pressure on
the wall is going to be.
So it's clear there's a connection
between energy density and pressure.
And usually the way it goes,
although there are some exceptions to it,
is the higher the energy density,
the higher the pressure.
The examples that are usually studied,
most frequently,
and in fact these cover pretty much
the ground of interest to cosmologists,
can be described by very simple equations of state.
The equation of state is the equation
which tells you what the pressure is,
p,
as a function of the energy density.
And the usual equation of state
that cosmologists study over and over
is the equation of state that says that the pressure
is a constant,
called density,
or W.
W is a constant,
times the energy density,
rho.
Now,
in many cases,
of course,
it's not really true that the pressure
is a strictly linear function of the energy density.
But as I said,
just more or less by accident,
the interesting cases have this form.
Pressure is some number times rho.
I'll tell you right now what W is
for the two cases of interest here.
Later we will come back and derive it.
For the matter-dominated case,
the matter-dominated case is basically the case
where the molecules in the room,
if we wanted to think about the room,
are at rest.
They're moving very slowly compared to anything else.
Or they're moving very slowly
compared to the speed of light.
The energy is at rest.
The pressure is mostly just the mc2 energy.
So in first approximation,
you can just say the molecules
are at rest in the room.
And when the molecules are at rest in the room,
the pressure on the walls is zero.
The only thing that creates pressure
is collisions with the wall.
And so for the matter-dominated world,
the pressure is equal to zero.
Or very,
very,
very small
compared with the energy density.
The big huge e equals mc2 energy density
and essentially a negligible pressure
because things are moving slowly.
Alright,
so W is equal to zero
is matter-dominated.
I don't need to derive that.
That was obvious.
That W equals zero is matter-dominated.
The harder case,
which as I said,
I don't think we'll get to tonight,
but next time,
and it's an important thing to understand,
is radiation.
Dominated.
And that case is W equals one-third.
Where did the third come from?
Hmm?
Three dimensions.
Right.
But why does the number of dimensions come in?
Well,
okay,
we'll work that out.
It is,
yes,
it is three dimensions.
Pressure equals one-third rho for radiation.
Or W equals one-third.
And W equals zero for matter-dominated.
Now,
what does the equation of state
have to do with anything?
What I'm going to do
is use the equation of state
to derive how the energy density changes
as a function of scale factor.
And what do we do?
We use the simplest kind of thermodynamic identities.
Supposing we have a box of gas.
A box of material of some sort.
It could be gas,
it could be liquid,
it could be whatever it happens to be.
It could be molecules,
it could be radiation.
It doesn't matter.
And it has some energy in it.
The energy,
of course,
the total energy,
is equal to the energy density
times the volume of the box.
So the box has volume V.
The energy density is rho.
And now let's imagine changing the
volume of the box a little bit.
It doesn't really matter whether you
change the volume of the box
sort of isotropically in all directions,
or any other direction.
But let's imagine changing it equally in all directions.
Then how much does the energy change?
What's the change in energy
if you change the volume by amount dV?
Anybody know the answer?
Not from this equation.
From the work done by the
pressure on the walls of the box.
We have P dV,
pressure dV.
But is it positive or negative?
If the volume expands,
what happens to the energy in the box?
It goes down.
You do work.
It does work on the box.
And therefore,
the work on the box means
a diminution of the energy in the box.
So it's minus P dV.
That's all we need to use.
That's enough.
That's the basic identity.
There's another term.
Anybody know what the other term is for thermodynamics?
TDS.
Temperature times the change in entropy.
When variations are slow and the universe
is expanding slowly,
by comparison with any other kind
of time scale in the gas,
when
changes take place slowly,
entropy doesn't change.
That's a rule.
It's called adiabatic
change.
For our purposes,
the change in entropy is zero,
and this is the formula.
dE equals
minus PdV.
Okay,
now,
the energy is rho times V.
Let's calculate dE.
We just take the differential of energy,
and that's equal to rho times the change in volume,
plus the volume times the change in rho.
Both are changing.
We change the volume.
Changing
the volume will change the energy density in some way,
in some as-yet-unspecified way.
Changing the volume will change rho.
But we don't know how yet.
However,
whatever the rule is,
dE equals rho dV plus VdRho.
That's the left-hand side,
dE.
On the right-hand side,
we have minus PdV.
Well,
we have two terms here with dV.
Let's group them together.
Let's put them over on
the left-hand side and keep them together,
because they both have the same difference.
On the left hand side we have V D Rho,
and on the right hand side we have two terms.
First of all a minus sign,
let's put a parentheses around it,
and a DV.
What goes inside the parentheses?
P and Rho.
P plus Rho,
because this has to go over to the other side.
P plus Rho.
But now,
if we didn't know any connection between P and Rho,
we'd be kind of stuck.
We wouldn't know what to do with this.
But let's assume that P
is known in terms of Rho.
And in particular,
let's take the very simple case
where P is W times Rho.
Now we can write this as minus.
1 plus W Rho DV.
1 is just the Rho DV,
the W is the P DV.
So now we have something we can work with.
We have an equation involving two variables.
It's going to be a differential equation,
volume and energy density.
Let's rewrite it.
Let me rewrite it on this board for a minute.
V,
oops.
V D Rho is equal to minus 1 plus W,
now that's just a number.
1 plus W is just a number.
Rho DV.
And now let's regroup the equation so that
on one side I have everything involving Rho,
and on the other side I have everything involving volume.
To do that,
I just divide by Rho to get
all the Rho dependence on the left.
Let's do it.
D Rho over Rho.
And divide by volume.
We've got rid of Rho on the right.
Now I divide by the volume.
And here's our equation.
D Rho over Rho.
What is that?
Differential of the logarithm.
Indeed.
It's the differential of the logarithm of Rho.
D Rho over Rho is the differential of log Rho.
What about D V over V?
Differential of log V.
So we can integrate this equation,
and it just says that Rho is proportional,
sorry,
it says that logarithm of Rho is equal
to 1 minus 1 plus W logarithm of V.
You can add a constant,
a numerical constant to it.
Let's just put the constant over here.
Now,
how do you solve this
for Rho in terms of V?
You just exponentiate it.
What does it say?
It says that Rho is
equal to the minus sign here,
gives you a 1 over volume
to the power 1 plus W.
With again,
a constant up here,
different constant.
Just take the logarithm of both sides.
Logarithm of Rho on the left,
and on the right,
minus 1 plus W times the log of V.
But volume,
the volume of this box,
if we think of it as a box which
is expanding with the general expansion of the universe,
the volume of the box is just basically A cubed.
It's proportional to A cubed.
Apart from a constant,
it's proportional to A cubed.
So what this is telling us now
is how Rho varies with the scale factor.
Let's write down the equation.
It says that Rho is equal to some constant,
which we'll worry about another day,
divided by A,
the scale factor,
to the 3 times 1 plus W.
That's what thermodynamics,
or that's what the thermodynamics of
a nice homogeneous material would tell us.
That's how Rho varies with scale factor.
Constant being some constant.
And again,
you can say that the constant is just the value
of the energy density when A is equal to 1.
Okay,
let's see what it says.
Supposing W is equal to 0.
That's the case of matter dominance.
If W is equal to 0,
that's the top case up there.
This just says Rho is equal
to a constant over A cubed.
That's this.
What if W is equal to 1 third?
1 plus 1 third is 4 thirds.
4 thirds times 3 is just 4.
So that's this equation.
And this equation over here.
So you see there is a
general framework in which these things emerge.
And really what you need to know is W.
To describe a cosmology based on some sort of energy,
what you need to know is the equation of state,
and very little more,
very little other than that,
the equation of state in the form...
Pressure is W times energy density.
Any questions?
I think this is a natural place to stop,
because I think if we go past this,
I'll overload you.
Next...
Go ahead.
I was just saying,
in the radiation case,
what is the radiation mostly?
Is it the microwave background?
It's mostly microwave background,
yes.
Yes,
almost all of it.
But an overwhelming factor,
it's the microwave background.
Other photons,
you know,
even sunlight and starlight,
and all the tiny,
tiny fraction of it.
Yeah.
Right.
So it's almost all the CMB,
the cosmic microwave background.
And it's a very...
Today,
at the present time,
it's a very,
very small fraction of the energy
and order of the cosmic microwave.
And it's a very,
very small fraction of the ordinary atoms,
which in turn is a somewhat
small fraction of the dark matter.
So most of it is dark matter.
Some fraction of that,
20%...
I don't remember exactly something,
10%,
20% is protons,
neutrons,
atoms,
and so forth.
And then a very,
very tiny fraction of that,
roughly 1,000...
1,000 cubed,
a billionth of it.
1,000 times 1,000 times 1,000,
yeah,
a billionth of it is radiation today.
But if you run it backward into past times,
at some point,
this becomes bigger than this,
and it becomes radiation dominated.
So the early universe was radiation dominated.
Late universe today,
if it were not for dark energy,
if it were not for cosmological constant,
it would be matter dominated.
Right.
And again,
if we didn't worry about the cosmological constant,
we would say that this parameter k is
correlated with the future history of the universe,
whether it collapses or continues to expand.
Now,
I emphasize that that is wrong
because of one other reason.
It's because of the future history of the universe.
And that's the dark energy.
Well,
I could tell you...
All right,
we've gone far enough that I can
tell you a little about dark energy.
If we don't care where the equations came from,
then cosmological constant,
cc,
or dark energy,
or vacuum energy,
all the same thing,
cosmological constant,
dark energy,
vacuum energy,
all the same thing,
is w,
let's see what we get.
w equals minus one.
A little bit odd,
isn't it,
that the pressure and the
energy density have the opposite sign.
How odd is that,
incidentally?
Can you think of any situation in which
pressure might have the opposite sign of energy density?
Yeah,
I can give you one.
Just where the box...
Let's replace the box just by
a line interval now in one dimension.
Where the box...
Here's a box.
It's just a line interval.
Well,
there's a line interval.
And the physics is that the two ends of
the line interval are held together by a spring.
Crazy.
That's not a reasonable description of energy density.
But it does have the property that the...
The pressure is negative.
Why is the pressure negative?
Because it's pulling together.
It's not pushing apart.
So the pressure is negative.
We call it tension.
When pressure is negative,
it's called tension.
It's a tendency to pull together.
But the bigger you stretch it,
the more the potential energy.
So it has the property that increasing the potential energy
makes the energy density...
makes the pressure more and more negative.
That's...
Is it happening when you
get something close to absolute zero,
whenever it's happening with real...
No,
no,
not...
Usually pressure...
It can.
Yeah,
it can under certain circumstances.
It can go in that direction.
Yeah,
as things get closer and closer to absolute zero,
you might think,
well,
it just correspond to springs,
and,
uh,
yeah.
But there's also some quantum uncertainty energy,
so it can go either way.
But,
yes,
it is possible for pressure to be negative,
and it is possible for pressure
to increase in the negative sense
as the energy density goes up.
That's what W equals minus one means.
Why...
Why such a tension should exist,
that's another question,
but let's just examine its consequences.
If W is equal to minus one...
Let's see,
here we are over here.
W equals minus one...
What do we get?
Rho is constant.
That's the nature of dark energy.
It does not change when you
expand the size of the box.
That's the character of it.
Uh...
The energy density in a box doesn't
depend on how big the box is.
Just changing the size of the box
doesn't do anything to the energy density.
It does change the energy in the box,
but doesn't change the density.
Why?
Because that energy density is a property of empty space,
and empty space doesn't dilute when you stretch it.
Okay.
But let's just...
Let's just...
Well,
I'll tell you what.
I think I don't want to go through this tonight.
Next time,
we will examine more critically
the reason why Ws have these various values,
and then study the behavior of the universe
under the various kinds of conditions.
In particular,
study what happens if we have dark energy.
That raises new things that we haven't seen before.
I think for tonight,
I'll take on a couple of questions,
but then,
uh...
You're getting tired.
Yeah.
When you talk about...
Well,
I assume that includes dark
matter as well as regular matter.
Yes.
Black holes and everything else.
Yup.
Anything which can be
regarded as non-relativistic particles,
but a particle can be a black hole,
it can be a planet,
it can be a star,
it can be anything that's just a chunk of material
that is moving slowly relative to the ambient background,
and whose energy is mostly
in the form of its mass.
Yeah.
Did you say that...
We didn't actually solve for A here,
but we did in the case of Newton's equation.
Did you say they're the same?
Absolutely,
same equation.
Yeah,
okay.
exactly the same equation.
The only thing was that the interpretation of this
had to do with being
above or below the escape velocity.
Other than that,
the equation is exactly the same.
I'll remind you,
for the case where k equals zero,
I remember the answer very good.
Very well,
excuse me.
In that case,
for the matter-dominated world,
A went as...
t to the two-thirds,
is that right?
I think t to the two-thirds.
For the radiation-dominated world,
it went to square root of t.
That's still true here,
if this is zero.
That's the flat space case.
If it's not flat,
then you have to correct it.
Yeah.
But go back to previous lectures,
and these were the equations we studied.
Yeah.
In order to have both a repulsive force
between all objects
and an attractive force like gravity,
I assume that the law regarding the distance between them
has to be different.
The law different than what?
Well,
I understand that gravity is an inverse square law,
so what is the nature of the repulsive force
that dark energy produces?
You can think of it just
as an expansion of the universe,
which we will work out.
But it is,
at least at the Newtonian level,
you can mock it up by just saying that
the gravitational force between every pair of particles
has an additional term in it
which is linear with the distance.
Force proportional to distance.
A very small coefficient,
and we'll go through that,
but you can mock it up,
you can mock up the effect of vacuum energy
of the cosmological constant
by saying that every particle has a force
with every other particle proportional to the distance.
If the cosmological constant is positive,
then it's repulsive.
Yup.
And if the cosmological constant is negative,
then it's attractive.
Needless to say,
if it's attractive,
then it will cause the universe to collapse even faster
than it would have without the cosmological constant.
If it's repulsive,
it gives a chance for continued expansion
even though the universe might be closed.
So we'll work that out.
Okay.
Good.
If there are no more questions,
let's go home.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.