Stanford University
We're going to begin inflation tonight,
too.
Hopefully we'll get through baryogenesis.
We will get through it because so little is known.
No,
I'm serious.
The basic theoretical
framework,
modern physics for baryogenesis means the creation of the,
I'll explain the
words in a moment,
but it does mean the excess of matter over antimatter.
The modern theory,
I will tell you what I
know about the history of it.
I was engaged in the history of it.
In 1980,
Savastamopoulos and I were asked by Bob Wagner,
why is there so much entropy in the world?
Bob Wagner is a cosmologist at Stanford.
Why is the number of photons,
which is counting the entropy in the world,
why is it so much
larger than the number of protons and electrons?
Remember,
it's about 10 to the 80th times
larger.
No,
10 to the 10th times larger,
10 to the 8th times larger,
10 to the 8th times
larger,
approximately,
10 to the 8th,
10 to the 9th,
something like that.
So,
we're going to get to that.
Why is that?
What created all these photons for every proton?
We thought about it a little
bit and then realized that the question was upside down.
The question was not why there
are so many photons,
but why there are so few protons and electrons.
And we basically
worked out what the modern theory is.
I'm going to tell you what it is tonight.
And for a brief period of time,
the
conditions to explain the imbalance of
particles and antiparticles were called the
Demopolis-Suskind conditions.
Somewhere during that time,
a little bit later,
two young Russian
mathematicians came to me and they
said they were writing a book about,
well,
not writing
a book,
yeah,
no,
they weren't writing a book.
They were looking for contributions to a book celebrating
Andrei Sakharov's career.
And they brought me a
list of papers about this thick.
And
when I looked through them and see
what was interesting and write about it,
so I started
to look through them and sure enough,
I discovered exactly the same paper.
It was remarkably
the same as what Savas and I had done,
with the exception that it was done in 1967,
13 years earlier.
So I was lost,
completely,
to the Western world.
The Russians knew about it,
but at
that time,
there wasn't a lot of communication between the Russians.
So I did indeed write
a little historical paper about Sakharov's contribution,
and made the mistake of calling
them the Sakharov conditions.
They are now known as the Sakharov conditions,
justly so,
of course.
Well,
these are the first Looking Mody,
and I'm going to talk about how salteduk are
considered in the academic world.
And I'm able to discuss a long history with these
conversations.
We need J Courain to explain
precisely these four kind of matters.
So he talked,
what we call,
in the educational world,
by saying that women drive
and are able to transport an engine at a
rate of three Go households or B though they may
Sons with levels like not all make him barrier.
There is,
of course,
the Association of Women
Members for Actual & City Transportation,
Oh خ Ав signal that we need
women and men in right of while traveling.
Who can do whatever we want her to help?
She said this taxi driver,
they sent people towards
really a legitimate question.
Okay,
maybe the world just started with more
particles and antiparticles,
and end of story.
But it focuses your attention a
lot when you have a number.
When you have a number,
a specific number,
and in this
case it was the 10
to the 8th photons per proton,
numbers focuses your
attention and says this number needs an explanation.
So the excess in itself was
just a fact that you could have said,
well maybe it's just that way,
but once
there's a number,
and in particular if the
number is some oddball number like
10 to the minus 8th,
you start to think maybe this thing needs an explanation.
So
the explanation of the
yeah.
How does it relate to entropy?
Oh,
oh,
oh.
Roughly speaking for a black body thermal
spectrum,
the entropy is simply the number of photons.
It's just the number
of photons.
And a black body,
black body radiation carries entropy.
It's thermal.
And to within some factor of order one,
I forget,
there's some pies in it,
and
simple factors,
the entropy of black body radiation is just the
average number of photons in the gas.
So when people speak about the
entropy of the universe,
in many contexts what they're often
talking about is just the number of cosmic
microwave background photons.
That's what they mean by it,
and so when I say,
when Bob Wagner came to me and said,
why is the entropy of the world so large,
he was asking me why the number
of photons per proton is so large.
You know,
you might have asked,
how did that small number of protons
make such a large number of photons?
But that is not the
right way to think about it.
As I pointed out to you last time,
or the time before,
in the very early universe there were huge
numbers of protons and huge numbers of antiprotons.
And they were basically equal to each other,
with the number of protons and the
number of antiprotons being approximately the same,
or the number of quarks and anti-quarks,
same true for electrons and positrons,
being approximately the same as the number of photons.
Thermal equilibrium at some very high temperature.
And then it cooled.
When it cooled,
the photons were left over.
They were left over.
They were left over because they decoupled.
The universe became transparent and
the photons just hung around,
and we see them today.
The protons and antiprotons annihilated each other.
The universe expanded fairly slowly,
and there was plenty of time for them to
find each other by and large and annihilate each other.
And all that was left over was the slight excess.
So the question became not
why there are so many photons,
but why was there this tiny
excess of 10 to the minus 8.
In other words,
the number of protons minus the number of antiprotons.
Where is it?
This number over here.
Divided by the number of photons.
But the number of photons and
the early history of the universe,
was approximately the same as
the number of protons plus antiprotons.
Number of protons plus.
In p bar.
And that's a number which is
about 10 to the minus 8.
Okay,
so there's a number to compute.
Why does this small number appear?
Now,
we don't know what the number
or the reason for the number.
That's because we don't have a complete theory.
But almost any theory that we write down,
which explains it,
always gives a small number.
So we'll talk about a little
bit what kinds of conditions are necessary.
Necessary and it turns out sufficient to
make an imbalance of matter over antimatter.
Now,
is it matter over antimatter?
How come it didn't come out antimatter over matter?
Well,
that's largely a definition.
That's largely a definition.
Which one?
The thing we call matter is
the thing that we're made out of.
So that's definition.
Alright,
let's begin with a hypothesis which
is really believed to be wrong,
but we'll come to it.
Namely,
the baryon number.
What does baryon number mean?
If there are only protons...
Now,
baryon number can be interpreted in terms of quarks.
It's basically the number of quarks minus
the number of anti-quarks in the world.
I think it's three times that to be exact.
And the reason it's three times that is because it
was originally defined in terms of protons and neutrons being baryons.
And a proton and a
neutron has three quarks in it.
So that's called b,
the baryon number of the world.
Number of quarks minus the
number of anti-quarks times three.
If all that exists...
What would it be?
Say it again?
What?
Divided by three.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Divided by three.
Or three times the baryon number is...
Yes.
You caught me.
Divided by three.
The baryon number of a proton is one,
and it has three quarks in it.
Good.
Okay,
so that's called baryon number.
And there are other kinds of objects
that carry baryon number besides protons and neutrons.
But they're all unstable.
Even the neutron is unstable.
Nevertheless,
there are other kinds of objects.
We can mostly focus by thinking
about quarks themselves if we like.
And the statement that there's a baryon excess is the statement
that there were in the early universe more quarks than anti-quarks.
The number of quarks and anti-quarks separately were
about the same as the number of photons.
And so the question is how it got that way.
Okay,
let's suppose for the moment that baryon number is one.
The number of quarks in the universe is one.
What's the difference between
baryon number and electron number?
The difference between baryon number and electron number
is that baryon number is like electric charge.
One of the things about
electric charge is that it's conserved.
It doesn't change with time.
Now,
baryon number is not like electric charge.
Electric charge is the source of coulomb forces,
long range electric fields,
which create long range electrostatic forces.
Baryon number itself is not like electric charge.
It's not a source of
some kind of coulomb type force.
Of course,
the protons are electrically charged.
Therefore,
they make conventional coulomb forces between each other.
They make electric fields.
The neutrons are not electrically charged.
They don't make electric fields.
So what we would say is
it's the charge of the proton,
not the baryon number of it,
which is creating any kind of long range field.
And baryon number itself may be conserved.
It may truly be conserved,
but it is not exactly like electric charge.
It doesn't exhibit this tendency to make long range forces.
All right.
But suppose it's conserved.
Suppose it's conserved.
Then if there is ever an excess in the beginning,
let's say,
of the universe,
whatever that means,
then there will always be an excess.
And that excess will be sort of frozen in.
If you change the number of quarks,
you must change the number of anti-quarks by
the same amount if baryon number is conserved.
And what's more,
experimentally,
baryon number appears to be highly conserved.
Nobody has ever seen a proton disappear.
We can talk more about experiments which search
for the decay of protons and so forth.
But the first approximation in our world,
protons are extremely stable.
What could they decay to?
Let's ask a question.
What could they...
Suppose a proton was to decay.
What could it decay to?
It must decay to things which are lighter than itself.
Okay.
It must decay to something
which has a positive electric charge.
So if a proton were to decay...
And if we want to
assume that whatever it decays to...
is stable,
there's really only one thing that it could decay to.
It could decay to a
positron and something electrically neutral.
A proton could decay.
A proton could disappear and become a positron.
That conserves electric charge.
It doesn't conserve energy.
A positron is much,
much lighter than a proton.
But it would compensate by giving off a neutral particle.
What kind of neutral particle is around?
Photons.
Photons are a prime candidate.
So a decay possibility for the proton would be...
Proton,
I'll draw it as a kind of Feynman diagram.
A proton moving along would decay to a photon,
which we'll call gamma.
Photons are typically called gamma.
And an electron antiparticle,
E+.
That's a possible thing that could happen.
And we don't really know any data.
There's a deep fundamental reason why it can't happen.
And maybe it does happen.
We're going to talk about whether it does happen.
In fact,
we think it does happen.
But for whatever reason...
What about a neutrino?
No,
it can't decay to a...
You mean a positron neutrino?
No,
no good.
No good.
Okay.
A neutrino is a fermion.
Two fermions make a boson
and a proton is a fermion.
So whatever the proton decays to,
it must decay to something
with an odd number of fermions.
So it can't decay into a positron and a neutrino.
Right.
Yeah.
If a baryon number really was conserved,
it would correspond to a symmetry of some sort.
Yes.
Was there a candidate for that
or has no one ever found one?
You can always...
Given any conserved quantity,
you can always make up a symmetry
that...
But then you can say,
well,
all right.
Is it really a symmetry?
And the way to test it is always
to ask whether the baryon number is conserved.
So it's a little bit circular.
But yes,
you're right.
If the baryon number was conserved,
it would correspond to a symmetry.
And if it's not conserved,
it doesn't correspond to a symmetry.
Okay.
Yeah.
Is there...
Do you think about part was
decaying and part was not decaying?
Part was annihilating with each other sort
of different things like a proton can annihilate
with a positive...with a negative proton.
Yes.
So that...is that...can you think of
that as a decay or not?
No,
that's not a decay.
It's not a decay of the proton.
It's just called annihilation of a proton.
But the important point here is
that the baryon number doesn't change.
Three quarks and three anti-quarks came together.
The sum total...the baryon number is zero.
And afterwards,
it's just a bunch of photons
and the baryon number is still zero.
So,
right.
So that's a fair question,
but it does...and you could call
it a decay if you wanted to,
but it wouldn't correspond to a...right.
Okay.
So for whatever reason...and we don't know the reason.
We don't know the reason really fully.
The standard model does not permit this decay incidentally.
It doesn't happen in the standard model.
But there are versions or extensions of
the standard model which are perfectly viable
in which this process could happen.
Now,
one thing we know about it immediately,
the decay rate of the proton cannot be very large.
Our protons have been around for...
15 billion years or whatever it is,
13.7 billion years,
and they haven't disappeared on us.
So if the decay time of the
proton were a microsecond or even faster,
which particle physics might permit,
the protons just wouldn't be here anymore.
So the lifetime of the proton is at least very,
very,
very long.
But in fact,
it's much,
much longer than is necessary for
the protons to still be here.
The mean lifetime of a proton is
more than 10 to the 32 years,
so it's very long.
And we don't completely understand why.
In fact,
we don't understand why at all.
But we take it as a fact.
A fact,
at least a temporary fact.
Let's assume it for the moment.
That would mean that the
total baryon number in the universe,
but let's just say in a box,
in a box,
doesn't change.
And so the only theory of this excess that we could
have is that it was built in from the very beginning
and it still survives today.
That would be a consequence of baryon conservation,
baryon number conservation.
I'm not saying that's true.
I'm saying that's a consequence of baryon conservation,
that this is the same today
as it was at the very beginning.
Now,
there's another symmetry of nature.
Which again,
is not really a symmetry of nature.
But you might have thought about
it as a symmetry of nature.
At the time that Sakharov put out his theory,
it was only a couple of years after
it was discovered that it wasn't a symmetry.
We'll talk about it.
But it's particle-antiparticle reflection symmetry.
The statement that particles,
if interchanged with antiparticles,
that you can't tell the difference.
Of course,
you can tell the difference
between a proton and an antiproton,
because we're made out of protons.
But if we changed all of our protons to antiprotons,
if you were made out of antiprotons,
and I was made out of protons,
don't get too close to me,
and somebody showed me a proton,
I would say,
yes,
that's a proton.
Somebody showed you an antiproton,
you would have exactly the same response.
I mean,
you would see the same thing.
You would see the same thing that I saw.
That's called particle-antiparticle symmetry,
or reflection,
charge-reflection symmetry.
And for technical reasons,
well,
alright,
that's a symmetry.
It's not a symmetry.
But up until around 1964 or 65,
I forget exactly when,
it was thought that charge conjugation,
this is called C equals charge conjugation symmetry,
it was believed that it was a symmetry.
Particles go to antiparticles.
Two other things which were
thought to be symmetries of nature,
which went along with this,
were called P,
which is P is for parity,
but it has nothing to do with,
it's not a symmetry of nature economics or fairness.
It's left-right symmetry,
mirror-reflection symmetry,
that if there's a kind
of particle which exhibits a handedness,
for example,
it rotates to the right when it moves forward,
spins to the right when it moves forward,
then it had been assumed that there would be
a vertical which also moves forward,
left-right symmetry,
and that was called parity.
And the final interesting symmetry for us tonight
is called T,
and T is time reversal.
What this means is that any
process that can happen in nature,
just an ordinary lab,
let's restrict ourselves to laboratory processes,
let's not worry about the whole universe,
any process that can happen in nature,
we could take a movie of it,
if we run it backwards,
it is still a possible thing that can happen.
Anything that can happen,
the opposite can happen.
Now,
it doesn't seem that way when
you think about the real world,
of course.
The second law of thermodynamics says things get worse,
but at the microscopic level,
at the true microscopic level,
we don't average over things,
and we don't do statistical averaging and so forth,
any process that happens in nature
was thought that its time reversal
was another possible thing that could happen.
That's called time reversal symmetry.
Now,
what is actually known mathematically,
this is a mathematical statement about quantum field theory,
which I am not going to try to prove tonight,
it's a hard theorem,
but it follows from the
basic structure of quantum mechanics,
relativistic field theory,
is not that charge symmetry is a symmetry,
particle-antiparticle,
not that parity reflection symmetry is a symmetry,
or that time reversal is a symmetry,
but the product of all three of them,
CPT,
and I'll tell you what that means in a minute,
CPT is a symmetry.
And this,
for mathematical reasons,
fundamental mathematical reasons,
which you'll have to accept for now,
is not consistent to ruin,
to not have this symmetry.
Now,
what does a symmetry mean?
It means if you take any process,
replace every particle by its antiparticle,
reflect it in a mirror,
and run it backward,
it is still a possible process in nature.
Okay?
You have to do all three in
order to be sure that it's a symmetry.
Up until the 60s,
yeah.
So,
for a wave function,
you can't just change the sine of t?
No,
you have to complex conjugate it,
too.
So,
does time reversal always mean
take the complex conjugate as well
as change the sine of t?
Mm-hmm.
Right.
Yeah.
You can see that from the Schrodinger equation.
The Schrodinger equation is something like
i d psi by dt equals,
I don't know,
d second psi by dx squared,
or something like that.
That's not quite right.
But supposing you change the sine of t,
that changes the sine of the left-hand side,
but it doesn't change the sine of the right-hand side.
So,
changing the sine of t
doesn't work.
But if at the same time you complex conjugate
and change the sine of t,
which also requires you to change the sine of i
for complex conjugation,
then it does work.
But this is something
we don't need to get into right now.
Cpt is a symmetry.
But let's suppose for a moment,
let's go back to Sakharov,
or even before Sakharov,
before the facts were actually known,
let's suppose that either charge conjugation
or c times p,
which is the usual one that people focus on,
that that was a good symmetry.
C times p means change every particle
to its antiparticle and change your left hand
with your right hand.
That was actually thought to
be a good symmetry of nature.
That would end up being a good symmetry of nature.
But you don't entail that there's some kind of symmetry
which allows you to change the sine of every particle
to its antiparticle.
You'd also have to change left to right,
but that goes along for the ride.
If you believe that,
then you might ask,
well,
gee whiz,
if there is a complete symmetry
between particles and antiparticles,
why should it be that at the very beginning
there was an imbalance of one versus the other?
Now,
nobody can tell you that there isn't an imbalance.
It just dates back to the very beginning.
But you might also wonder,
you know,
what's going on here?
The laws of physics seem to be completely symmetric
between the two kinds of things,
particles and antiparticles,
and yet,
for some reason,
there was this small imbalance
of size 10 to the minus 8.
It doesn't sound right.
Okay?
All right.
The modern theory of baryogenesis
begins with the idea
that there was a balance,
that particle and antiparticle were balanced,
again,
not for any good reasons,
but just for whatever initial condition you started with,
there was no bias toward particle or antiparticle.
That's an assumption.
It can be justified in some frameworks,
but it's...
So then how is it possible,
then,
that it got imbalanced?
The only way that it's possible
for it to get imbalanced...
The only way it's possible for it to get imbalanced
is if the conservation of baryon number
is not correct.
In other words,
if processes can happen,
and here's one,
if processes can happen in nature
in which a proton becomes a positron,
that is a violation of baryon conservation,
which allows the baryon number of the universe to change.
That would be the first requirement
for a theory of baryogenesis
that was based on the assumption
that the initial...
the starting point was balanced between the two,
that if you're going to wind up with an excess
of quarks over anti-quarks,
or baryons over anti-baryons,
baryons meaning protons and neutrons,
you must have a mechanism
which violates the conservation.
So that was...
Sakharov's first condition.
Condition number one,
Sakharov conditions.
Sakharov conditions started with number one,
baryon number...
violation.
Violation means violation of the conservation law.
And as an example,
the process of a proton becoming a positron
and a photon is an example.
If it happens in nature.
That was condition number one.
Let's just...
talk about that for a minute.
If baryon number conservation
is not a good conservation law of physics,
then it must be a very,
very weakly,
weakly broken one.
As I said,
protons are very old.
They didn't disappear.
So it must be very old.
It must be very old.
The protons are old.
And whatever mechanism,
such as this kind of decay,
it must have a very,
very,
very small probability per unit time.
One can ask in current theories,
current unified theories,
which do,
some of which,
most of whom,
in fact,
everyone,
no,
I take that back,
every known unified theory,
and even when they're not unified,
if they're coupled to gravity,
every known fundamental theory
violates baryon conservation like this.
You can ask in the known theories,
why is the proton so stable?
And the answer tends to be something like this,
that the theory has Feynman diagrams,
has processes in which the proton comes in
from the left,
meaning from early,
out goes an electron,
out goes a photon,
but somewhere in the guts of this
Feynman diagram,
there are all kinds of particles,
let's not specify exactly which ones are in there,
but there are all kinds of particles,
but among them,
assume that there's at least
one or more particles which are very,
very heavy.
In other words,
that it requires a particle type
which is very,
very heavy in there,
particles which have not been discovered yet.
Now,
one of the reasons to believe this
is that the standard model by itself,
with its ordinary known particles,
does not permit this to happen,
and so in order to make it happen,
you would have to have
new additional particles
that were not part of the standard model,
and that certainly means that they're heavier
because they haven't been discovered yet,
but imagine making them very heavy.
How heavy?
Oh,
10 to the 16th GeV,
or 10 to the 16th times heavier than a proton,
which is not an unnatural number
for heavy particles.
Then,
what's true
is that this kind of process
is extremely un-natural.
Extremely unlikely means that
the quantum mechanical amplitude for it
is suppressed by inverse powers
of this heavy mass.
Typically,
for example,
it might be,
let's call this the heavy mass M,
the Feynman diagram will contain
a 1 over M squared,
just because it's so hard
to make a heavy particle.
Just because it's so unlikely,
that heavy particle doesn't last very long,
it has to,
melt into the rest of the Feynman diagram,
but if the particle is heavy enough in there,
then this will be a very,
very small
probability process.
That's what drives,
that's what,
that's the kind of thing which keeps the proton stable
in modern unified theories.
I don't know if it's right,
I'm not saying it's right,
but this is a mechanism
that the extra particles that are there
are all heavy enough
that they suppress this enormously.
Now I will tell you something else,
that this 1 over M squared,
if for some reason,
the proton is given a lot of energy somehow,
then this isn't really 1 over M squared,
but it's really some energy,
M minus some energy squared.
If the proton has excess energy
from some other place,
this can well be a much smaller suppression,
and I'll tell you where that extra energy
comes from in a minute,
where it can come from.
But in the ordinary world,
a proton sitting around,
there's nothing to give it
an enormously heavy kick,
an enormously high kick.
It doesn't have a huge amount of energy.
Protons,
when they collide or anything else,
don't have huge amounts of energy.
So this is where you begin.
And,
theories of this type
can explain why the protons are stable.
Of course,
you could say,
they don't explain anything.
They just tell you that for some reason
that the particles which could cause,
which are necessary for the proton decay,
must be very heavy,
and that's true.
Is extra energy,
is that not included in M squared?
Yeah,
any energy that's not included
in its rest mass squared,
nevertheless we go in here,
and I'll tell you where such energy
can come from in a moment.
But,
as I said,
all theories,
all known theories,
and I would venture to say any theory
that ever will exist,
will have the possibility
of baryon violation.
Okay,
so let's agree,
tentatively,
that baryon violation
is not taboo,
that processes such as this can happen,
they're not forbidden by any fundamental law of physics,
it's just an accident of the particle spectrum
that the proton is as stable as it is.
Let's take that,
let's take that as an assumption,
a working assumption.
Baryon violation by itself
is not sufficient to,
to give you an average excess
of protons over antiprotons.
Why not?
Because for every event,
let's,
where is it?
Every event like this which can happen,
which can cause you to
lose proton number,
this is a source of decreasing baryon number,
you started with one unit here
and you have no units over here,
for every process like this,
there is the charge conjugate process,
in which an antiproton comes in,
a electron,
a true electron goes off,
and the antiparticle of the photon is the photon,
the antiparticle of a photon is itself.
So,
if we believe in particle-antiparticle symmetry,
then for every process like this,
a process like that happens,
and on the average,
on the average,
there will be as many of these kinds of decays
as these kinds of decays.
So if we started out,
if we started out with an equal population
of quarks and anti-quarks,
of baryons and anti-baryons,
and we tried to rely only on
the violation of baryon number,
it would not be a very efficient way
to create an excess.
What do I mean by that?
I mean,
think about it for a minute,
supposing there was a randomness that,
let's see how to say this,
oh,
I might add something else,
incidentally,
that in the very early universe,
there were lots of electrons,
positrons,
and photons around,
and it's perfectly possible
for the opposite to go.
An electron,
a positron and a photon
can come together and make a proton.
An electron and a photon can come together
and make an anti-proton.
So there's a statistical balance
of things going on.
It's only statistical
that there would be as many protons
as anti-protons,
because these processes are statistical processes,
but the imbalance of protons over anti-protons
is not a statistical effect.
Yeah?
Quick question.
On that lower diagram,
on the left-hand side,
is the baryon number equal to negative one there?
Here,
yes.
Negative one goes to zero.
Yeah.
Right.
Negative one goes to zero.
Here,
one goes to zero.
And the reason that it can't be a statistical effect
is that it is quite true
that the baryon excess is a small number,
10 to the minus eighth.
Okay?
But you ask,
how many protons are there in the entire universe,
known universe,
observable universe?
And the answer is about 10 to the 80th.
How big would you expect the excess
of protons over anti-protons to be
if it were simply a pure statistical effect?
Square root of n.
Right?
You know that the statistical effect
of a particle fluctuation in a variable
just due to random statistics
is of order the square root of the number.
If you have a random heads-tails flips
and you collect,
let's say,
a thousand flips,
the number of heads will be 500,
but that's up to the margin of error.
And what is the margin of error?
The margin of error is the square root
of the number of flips.
And so you expect that the number of flips,
the number of flips will be,
the number of heads will be 500 plus or minus,
what's the square root of 500?
The margin of error will be about 25.
Okay,
now let's come to the world
which has 10 to the 80th protons in it.
What is the margin of error
or the statistical fluctuation,
the average expected statistical,
the statistical excess of protons?
It would be square root,
which would be 10 to the 40th,
right?
10 to the 40th.
10 to the 40th over 10 to the 80th
is 10 to the minus 40th.
So if the excess was 10 to the minus 40th,
we could say it could be statistical,
but it's not.
It's much,
much bigger than that.
Yeah?
Well,
it depends on the number of protons
and anti-protons in the very early universe
that became our observable universe.
I'm assuming that they started out balanced.
Right,
they started out balanced.
And if there were 10 to the 160th protons
and anti-protons in that early universe,
then that could be 10 to the 80th.
It could be.
The other thing that would be very hard to justify,
extremely hard to justify,
is if it was statistical fluctuation,
why it would be the same everywheres.
Okay,
that would be very,
very hard.
Right.
You'd expect a patch over here with protons,
a patch over there with anti-protons,
and so you can ask,
what is the experimental evidence
that the neighboring or even very distant galaxies
are not anti-galaxies?
And as I understand it,
there's very good evidence.
The good evidence is if the population of galaxies
was sort of symmetric between galaxies and anti-galaxies,
then you would expect cosmic rays,
especially very high energy cosmic rays,
which are thought to be cosmic in origin,
to have as many nuclei as anti-nuclei
or as many anti-nuclei as nuclei.
We do see,
for example,
helium nuclei in cosmic rays.
Okay.
As I understand it,
nobody has ever seen
an anti-nucleus in cosmic rays.
You do see anti-protons,
but that's fairly easy to explain.
Even if we didn't have any cosmic rays
or anti-particles coming in,
when a high energy particle would hit the atmosphere,
it would make anti-protons.
But it's extremely difficult to make an anti-nucleus.
That would take an incredible piece of luck
of a very high energy collision with the atmosphere
creating an anti-nucleus.
Not likely.
So the complete absence of anti-nuclei
strongly suggests that the universe
is not equally populated with galaxies and anti-galaxies.
So,
there's something to explain.
It's not statistical,
and we need to explain it.
Do you see helium nuclei
or do you just see any of these
that look like they trace back to the...
I believe you see helium nuclei
in cosmic rays directly,
yeah.
Yeah.
And,
you know,
detailed statistics of it,
I don't know.
It's not my field of physics,
but that's where the argument lies,
at least one of them.
Okay.
We also don't...
There's another thing we don't see.
If our galaxy,
for example,
was particles,
and the Andromeda was anti-particles,
then in the region in between,
you would expect there to be
both particles and...
I mean,
there's plenty of electrons around,
for example,
circulating around
in the region between galaxies.
You would expect there to also be
plenty of positrons,
and then you would expect there to be
lots of positron-electron annihilations,
and positron-electron annihilations
are very easy to detect.
They produce pairs of photons
of very definite energy,
and those pairs of photons could be observed,
and it's not that we don't see
electron-positron annihilation,
but we don't see nearly enough of it
to account for the possibility
that neighboring galaxies would be anti-galaxies.
So that's almost certainly ruled out
that there are anti-galaxies out there,
and certainly ruled out
that there's an equal population of them.
Okay.
So,
particle-anti-particle symmetry
tends to...
tends to suggest rather strongly
that the universe was created symmetrically,
although it doesn't prove it.
So,
the next element of the argument
is that in order to account for the fact
that there are more protons than anti-protons,
this charge-conjugation symmetry must fail.
The idea that particles and antiparticles
are symmetric in the laws of physics.
And that the charge-conjugation times parity,
it's enough that it would be bad enough,
charge-conjugation or charge-conjugation
together with anything else,
any symmetry that involved
interchanging particles and antiparticles,
if you had that symmetry,
you would have a very hard time explaining.
Another way to say it is if we allow...
Yeah,
if we allow baryon violation,
that's not enough.
That will just give you the statistical effect.
You need something to push it in one direction.
You need something to bias it toward
particles rather than antiparticles.
You need something in the laws of physics
that will cause this baryon violation to be biased
so that one kind of
thing happens more than the other.
The implications of that are
that you need violations of particle-antiparticle symmetry.
In particular,
the so-called CP symmetry.
But it's basically just particle-antiparticle symmetry.
Again,
is there particle-antiparticle asymmetry in the world?
Yes,
there is.
We know with absolute certainty,
experimentally,
that particles and antiparticles don't behave the same way.
A particular example...
Rather,
the examples are hard to come by,
but once you have one,
or two,
or three,
you know that the laws of physics are not symmetric
between particles and antiparticles.
The simplest example to explain is
the so-called B meson.
A B meson is a particular kind of particle
made of a quark and an anti-quark.
It's made of a...
Let's see,
it's made of a...
of a bottom quark
and a...
an anti-down quark.
A bottom quark and an anti-down quark.
Bottom quark and an anti-b...
form a meson.
They form a meson.
The meson is bound,
and it's called the B particle.
Now,
it has an antiparticle.
You just interchange the bottom quark
for the anti-bottom quark
and the down...
and the anti-down quark for a down quark,
and you get the anti-B meson.
Both the B meson and the anti-B meson
are electrically neutral,
but they are not their own antiparticles.
This one is made of B quark
and anti-down quark.
This one is made of anti-B quark,
and...
down quark,
or whatever the opposite was.
Right.
These particles decay,
and they decay...
into pi mesons...
Let's see,
this one...
here we forget.
Takes...
I'll just write it down.
I'll just write down one possibility at the...
Oh boy,
I've forgotten what a B meson decays in.
They decay into lots of things,
but...
a charged...
Oh,
I know!
They decay into a k meson and a pi meson.
And I think the B meson becomes...
I think it's a k plus and a pi minus.
This is not important.
The fact is that there's a very definite decay
into a k meson and a pi meson.
The B meson is electrically neutral,
so the decay products are electrically neutral.
That...
It follows that the anti-B meson
can decay into the anti-particles,
which is a negatively charged k meson
and a positively charged pi-on.
The only important thing is that it's a process
in which a particle can decay into other particles
versus a process in which the anti-particle
can also decay into its anti-particles.
Now,
these are...
The rates for these things to happen are measurable.
They are measured,
and they are different.
They are different.
One of these,
I can't remember which one,
is about two-thirds more important than the other.
And so it's...
In this case,
it's a fairly gross violation
of particle-anti-particle interchange.
It's definitely a real effect.
There are lots of indirect...
measurements that have been known for a long time
that particle-anti-particle symmetry
is not a good symmetry,
is not a symmetry.
One is fair.
Now,
once this can happen,
we can...
Meaning to say that there are fundamental processes
in nature buried deep inside Feynman diagrams
somewheres that are imbalanced
between particles and anti-particles.
It's no longer the case that this decay
and that decay have to have equal probability.
There is a rule...
There is a rule that the total decay rates,
the total half-life
of the proton and the anti-proton
have to be exactly the same.
That's a...
that's a theorem
for relativistic field theory.
But the way that these two
can be different from each other
is there's more than one
way that a proton can decay.
A proton can also decay,
for example,
into a mu plus in a photon,
and an anti-proton can decay
into a mu minus in a photon.
And what the theorem says
is that if you calculate all of our possible ways
that the proton can decay,
and you consider the half-life
or the total rate,
the total rate of decay of the proton,
it must be exactly the same
as the total rate of decay of the anti-proton.
But what it does not say
is that the decay rate of the proton
to electrons or to positrons and photons
must be the same as...
You know what I mean.
It doesn't say that any particular decay
has to have a symmetry.
In particular,
if at some fundamental level
this charge-conjugation symmetry
is violated by something in the theory,
then it will allow this to not equal...
Let's say this here...
Not equal to...
That's a special symbol I just invented.
It allows that.
And not only allows it,
it basically insists that these two not be the same.
Once that's true,
it says there's a bias.
Somewhere in the laws of physics,
there is a bias toward either protons or anti-protons,
or matter versus energy.
Anti-matter.
Some kind of bias.
And that's something which is absolutely necessary
to add to baryon number violation.
To give it a directionality.
To give it a push in
one direction rather than the other.
So Sakharov's second condition...
Incidentally,
I think Sakharov's paper was a...
I've forgotten when CP violation was first discovered.
But Sakharov's paper was very quickly after that.
When the CP violation,
the particle-anti-particle symmetry
was discovered to not be correct,
within a year or so,
I don't remember exactly,
Sakharov wrote down his basic conditions.
So that's number two.
C and CP,
or particle-anti-particle asymmetry
in the laws of physics.
This is expected in any theory that we know.
Any theory that we've studied for particle physics
always has...
Including just the standard model.
In fact,
I said something wrong.
The standard model does allow baryon violation.
In fact,
it not only allows it,
it insists on it at some level.
So every theory that we know about,
but as a theoretical statement,
insists that baryon number violation happens.
Experimentally,
we know that CP is violated
and particle inversion,
particle-anti-particle symmetry.
Now,
there's one remaining...
Yeah?
So if the total decay rates are the same,
then why don't we have equal numbers?
Because the...
Because the mu particle is heavier than the electron.
So we could be in a situation where...
We could be in a situation,
for example,
where it's hot enough...
Hot enough to...
What I need to explain to you
is first why this can happen rapidly,
even though I said that the proton is very stable.
It has to do with the environment.
Let me come back to it.
It's a good question.
All right.
How do we overcome the fact
that the proton is so incredibly stable?
Remember what I said.
The proton lifetime is something like
about 10 to the 33,
10 to the 34 years or longer.
The universe has only been around
for 10 to the 10th years.
So on that scale,
the proton is very stable,
and why don't we get
to ignore this kind of thing?
And the reason has to do with the fact
that the universe in its very early stages
was very,
very hot.
Because it was very hot,
the protons,
or the quarks in particular,
we can substitute quarks here,
it doesn't matter,
because it was very hot,
they were constantly engaged
in very,
very high energy collisions.
The high energy collisions
meant that the protons moving in this plasma,
in this very hot gas,
had lots of energy.
How much energy?
It depends on the temperature.
But at some temperature,
you get to a high enough point
where the average kinetic energy,
the average extra excitation on energy of the proton,
is high enough
so that even these heavy particles here
do not suppress
the proton decay,
or the baryon violation.
In other words,
to put it short,
a proton at rest,
forget at rest,
a proton in an environment
where it isn't constantly being knocked around
and having an enormously,
largely large excess energy
of some kind or another,
is very stable.
But when it's heated up to a high temperature,
a high enough temperature,
this excess mass here
is not an important factor,
and the proton decay would happen quickly.
So if we go back to the very early universe,
when the temperature was very hot,
then these kind of processes can happen.
Now,
this statement that the total decay rate
is the same for protons and antiprotons
is a statement about zero temperature.
It's a statement about a proton at rest
in an environment where it has no excess energy.
When it's being kicked around,
and when it has extra energy,
then that is not necessarily the case.
In fact,
it's generally not the case.
In an environment which has some energy,
which is kicking the protons around,
the decay rates don't have to be the same.
So...
So that is not a problem.
The problem has to do with the CPT symmetry.
I said that there was no particle inversion symmetry,
but there is a symmetry,
at least in all known quantum field theories,
string theories,
any theory we know how to write down,
which has relativity and quantum mechanics built into it.
Charge conjugation times reflection times time reversal.
Again,
what that means is you exchange every particle
for its antiparticle,
you reflect in a mirror,
and you run the film backward.
That is a symmetry of all theories.
All right.
So...
What is the answer to this?
What does that mean?
That means,
among other things,
that in thermal equilibrium,
if the universe was just static,
if it wasn't changing,
but it was hot,
in thermal equilibrium,
forward time is the same as backward time.
In thermal equilibrium,
backward and forward and time are the same thing.
There is no asymmetry of time reversal.
So in thermal equilibrium,
where the universe is not changing,
an imaginary universe,
which is just a pot,
which is there,
hot,
a hot pot,
it would have time reversal symmetry.
If it has time reversal symmetry,
and it has C times P times T,
then it must have C-P symmetry.
All right.
C-P just means particle change to antiparticle
for our purposes.
If particle goes to antiparticle
and time goes to...
I was going to say anti-time,
and time goes to minus time,
if that's a good symmetry,
but the world has no
bias toward one time or another,
then you're stuck again.
You're back to having a particle-antiparticle symmetry,
and you cannot have a proton-antiproton excess
in thermal equilibrium.
That's a theorem.
That's a theorem that's been known for a long time,
that in thermal equilibrium,
that the thermal equilibrium will come to a configuration
with equal numbers of protons.
But the universe was not in thermal equilibrium
at early times.
It was expanding,
and it was expanding fast at early times.
It was expanding fast enough
that it could not be considered an equilibrium.
If it's not an equilibrium,
that means that forward time
and backward time are different.
That's the reason.
If the universe is expanding,
forward time and backward time are not the same.
So in a rapidly expanding phase of the universe,
we don't have to worry about time symmetry.
It is definitely not symmetric.
If time symmetry is broken
just by the expansion of the universe,
then we're in business.
Then we have...
enough asymmetry of all possible kinds
that the baryon violation allows a change
in the baryon number.
The CP violation allows a directionality for it,
and the...
out of equilibrium.
Out of equilibrium.
Yeah.
This means things are changing rapidly
in a particular direction of time.
It means the universe is expanding fast enough...
That's all it means.
So that running the thing backwards
does not look like the original thing.
In a world where the
universe is running in one way,
namely expanding,
it is out of equilibrium.
Being out of equ...
It has to be enough out of equilibrium.
It's not enough for it to be very,
very slowly expanding.
It has to be expanding rapidly enough
that these microscopic processes
don't have a time to adjust themselves
to the equilibrium configuration.
But whatever it means,
it means that backward and forward times are different.
That a picture of the universe...
that a movie of the universe
allows you to tell which way is forward in time
and which way is backward in time.
Just by the expansion.
And the fact that it's cooling.
The fact that early times it suddenly cooled...
It suddenly cooled rather rapidly in the beginning.
That's enough to completely ruin
the time reversal symmetry.
And if the time reversal symmetry is ruined,
the CP symmetry is also going to be ruined.
So,
those were the three conditions of Sakharov.
All three are believed to be
really satisfied in the real world.
And it's also believed that they are enough
that if all three of these are true,
that there's really just no way
it would be a complete accident
with no rationale to it
if there wasn't some...
some excess created.
The problem is that
nobody knows enough about the physics of the early universe
and the physics of very high energy collisions,
the physics of very,
very hot temperature,
the nature of the particles that are in here,
the details of what drives
the CP violation and so forth.
Nobody knows enough about it
to be able to make a calculation
of what the imbalance is
of protons to antiprotons.
That simply we don't know.
We don't know enough.
So what we know
is all three ingredients that are both necessary
and probably sufficient
to explain an imbalance,
those are there,
but the ingredients needed to make a computation
to show
that this number
is 10 to the minus eighth
times NQ plus NQ bar.
Oops.
That's out of range.
We don't know how to do that.
That's the status of this particular problem.
As I said,
it's called baryogenesis.
And it will await
a much more detailed theory
of both early cosmology
and particle physics at very high energy.
Any questions about that?
We are now finished with baryogenesis.
But the fact that we know
that we have a measurement
of 10 to the minus eighth,
I imagine that puts some constraints
on what these theories could look like.
It does.
Another question.
It does,
but they're hard to use.
You're right,
but to my knowledge,
nobody's used it in a really effective way
to constrain things.
Just too many variables,
too many things to...
To map out a neat-looking subspace.
Yeah,
right.
Of hundreds of parameters,
we just don't know enough.
Yeah.
Now,
the connection between that
and the positron-electron numbers
that you've got previously,
is that this asymmetry here
which allows that to be connected?
I don't understand how the matterness
of the forks and the matterness
of the electrons are connected.
Every time a proton disappears,
a positron appears.
That's an anti-matter.
That's an anti-matter particle.
So the loss of baryon number
must be made up for by an increase in...
Right.
Or the increase...
Anything that increases p will decrease...
So as long as all of the processes
that you're thinking about
conserve electric charge,
there's no alternative to the statement that,
if the baryon number shifts one way,
the electron excess must shift the other way.
Right.
Question?
Yeah.
I've heard claims that in the standard model,
the CP violation that we see in the standard model
is not big enough to explain the baryon excess.
I have heard claims like that,
too.
Oh,
you don't believe them?
No,
no,
I do believe them.
I have no reason not to believe them.
I just am a little bit skeptical
that anybody really knows how to do the calculation.
I thought that was one of the big reasons
why we needed a beyond-the-standards model.
I'm a little bit skeptical.
You know,
my involvement in this
ended with stating these three conditions,
and then thousands of people,
not thousands,
maybe tens of people,
started to try to make computations
based on standard models.
Stephen Wolfram was one of them,
and he invented Mathematica,
I think,
to do the calculations.
Well,
you know,
I looked at it and I said,
look,
there's no way that they're going
to be able to do this
because there are just too many unknowns
about the early universe and so forth.
So it may be correct,
and I don't know.
I haven't followed this story for a long time.
It may be that...
that we know that CP violation
in the standard model is too weak to drive...
But once you admit CP violation
into the physics altogether,
there's no reason to expect that at high energy
it might not be,
you know,
tens and hundreds of times larger.
Once you've opened the door to it
so that it's no longer a principle,
then you don't have really much control.
From these two,
if you had equal numbers
of protons and antiprotons in the initial universe,
all the electrons that we see today in our universe
came from the antiprotons.
Well,
I'm not sure that's right.
There could have been a population
in the very beginning which was balanced between...
Oh,
I see what you're saying.
Well,
in that sense,
yes.
I'm not sure...
You could have done the whole analysis
in the opposite way by thinking about
the electrons instead of the protons and...
Leptogenesis or baryogenesis,
and then they balance out.
Right,
exactly.
The word...
The lingo baryogenesis is a sort of historical relic.
But,
yeah.
Yeah.
Because we observe...
Deep in deep space,
we observe atomic spectra.
Wait a minute.
Wait,
wait,
wait.
Well,
so those are baryons.
We're counting baryons.
That's why...
It has to do with
the fact that we don't know
how many neutrinos are out there
that people focused on the baryons,
but don't worry about it.
Have we had...
Was the 10 to the minus 8 is today's number
and has always been the number?
Because what I'm getting at is...
The 10 to the minus 8 is today's number
for the ratio of baryon number of protons to photons.
Right.
But has there been a period
where there was a lot of annihilation
of protons and antiprotons?
There was a period when
there was a lot of annihilation
between protons and antiprotons.
It basically removed almost all the protons and antiprotons
but that was the point at
which the temperature fell low enough
that processes that would create protons and antiprotons...
At very high temperatures,
there's very high energy photons.
Two photons come together and they create,
in one way or another,
a proton and an antiproton.
Those photons...
have to have enough energy
to create a pair of protons.
That means they have to be
at least 2 GeV worth of energy.
As long as the temperature is high enough,
these things are going on
backward and forward in equilibrium.
As long as there are enough high energy photons around
to be able to cause the proton-antiprotons to appear,
and it goes the other way.
But then when the temperature
falls below a certain threshold,
there simply aren't enough high energy photons around
to create protons and antiprotons.
But protons and antiprotons can create photons.
Photons are massless.
Protons and antiprotons have lots of energy.
It can go this way,
but it has a hard time going this way.
So once the temperature falls below that threshold,
the protons start annihilating each other,
but there's not enough energy to...
Of course,
when a proton and an antiproton...
collide and make photons,
those photons have a lot of energy.
But then they just go out into the soup
and their energy gets lowered by coming to equilibrium
with the lower temperature background stuff.
So as the temperature goes down,
the number of available high energy photons decreases,
and you can't make the proton-antiproton,
but you can go the other way.
So at that point,
that's when the annihilation starts,
and eventually all the proton-antiprotons
get eaten up.
When did this process stop?
When there were no antiprotons.
And that was approximately...
Oh,
that was pretty early.
Yeah,
that was quite early.
That was before nucleosynthesis,
temperatures in the G or GEV range.
I'm not sure exactly when it stopped.
Before that 300,000-year thing when it...
Oh,
yeah,
before the first three minutes for sure.
Some seconds maybe.
I'm not sure.
In an earlier lecture,
we were counting up the energy
and there were four different types.
There was photons and there was matter
and dark matter.
The contribution from photons,
if I remember correctly,
was negligible.
Today?
Yes.
Right.
So after all of this annihilation went on
and this earlier thing,
all of the matter was turned into photons,
where did all those photons go
if they're no longer around now?
They're all around.
Okay.
They're in the microwave,
the cosmic microwave background.
There's 10 to the 8th of them for every proton.
But how is it that it can account
for such a negligible portion of the total energy?
Because remember that radiation energy density
decreases like one over the scale factor
to the fourth power
and matter energy density
decreases like one over a cubed.
Right.
So if we need this very massive particle
to make this work,
does that mean the standard model is incomplete?
Yes,
it does.
Yeah.
Right.
If you,
your top two diagrams there
where you have the unequal sign,
Yes.
that's very unequal
and you started with all the p's and
Say it again,
say it again.
If it's very unequal
and you started initially with p's and p bars,
then the p bars would decay
because it's very unequal into the e minuses
then you'd end up with the e minus p equivalents
for equality.
So you started with just all p's and p bars.
Yeah.
And no e's.
Uh-huh.
Because the p bars go through that second process
and you would get e is equal to p's.
Oh,
I see what you mean.
Yeah.
Yeah,
it's,
yeah.
Yes.
You can try to make a theory that way.
I think you'd quickly flounder on the fact
that at some point the universe was very hot,
and at that point there were these loads and loads
of p's and p bars.
At least if you wanted to follow standard thinking about,
about,
um,
uh...
I want to explain why it's very unequal.
What's that?
It's very hard to explain
why it would be that unequal,
particularly since cp violation is a small,
very small thing.
So it would be very hard to understand
why it would be grossly unequal.
And keep in mind that these decay rates,
yeah,
are very small,
but...
Okay,
I want to move on.
That's what's known about matter-antimatter imbalance
in the universe.
And,
um,
as I said,
I don't think it's going to be too soon
that we know a lot more.
All right,
now,
the next thing we want to move on to
is,
um,
inflation,
inflationary universe.
The inflationary universe idea was put forward to explain
another one of these things which is not entirely clear
needs to be explained.
Or wasn't entirely clear that it needed to be explained
at the time.
Um,
and the question was,
why is the universe so terribly homogeneous and isotropic?
This became a rather critical issue
when the cosmic microwave background was discovered.
And the cosmic microwave background
quickly became a rather high-precision thing.
The high-precision thing being that in short order,
um,
the,
uh,
the black body curve had been measured.
The temperature of the cosmic microwave background
had been measured carefully.
It was known to be about 2.7 degrees.
And with some precision,
with some,
uh,
the error bars were fairly small.
Today,
they're microscopic.
the,
today the error bars are just,
uh,
they can't be seen on the...
Okay.
So,
the temperature was very well defined.
Looked like a Planck distribution,
like a black body distribution.
Almost exactly,
or exactly as far as you could tell.
But,
moreover,
it was the same in every direction.
So,
suddenly,
this rough idea
that the universe is isotropic
became a high-precision idea.
Now,
this took years.
I'm,
I'm condensing history into a,
into something smaller.
But at least by today,
in any case,
um,
the idea that the universe is isotropic
is a very,
very high-precision thing.
So,
you can ask,
why is the universe so isotropic?
Uh,
today,
it's isotropic.
Must have been isotropic very early.
No particular reason why,
uh,
why an anisotropy lumpiness
in the distribution would de,
would decrease with time.
In fact,
quite the opposite.
Lumpiness tends to increase with time
because of gravity.
Gravity tends,
tends to take lumps
and,
uh,
and magnify the size,
the magnitude of the mass.
The magnitude of the lumps.
So,
uh,
it means the universe
must have started very early
being extremely homogeneous and isotropic.
When I say very early,
I mean at the time
before there were galaxies,
before there were,
um,
planets,
at a time that the black body
photons originated.
In other words,
at the decoupling time,
the universe was extremely isotropic.
Now,
it was of course known
that it couldn't be completely isotropic
or homogeneous,
let's say.
If it was exactly homogeneous,
it would stay homogeneous.
Anything which is exactly uniform
and allowed to evolve,
uh,
will stay uniform.
And the universe is not uniform.
It's full of galaxies,
and it's full of clusters of galaxies.
It has a lumpiness that's there.
The lumpiness that's there
clearly was much smaller
to begin with,
smaller in magnitude,
for the simple reason that lumpiness
tends to increase with time.
Let me just explain what I mean by that.
If you start with a world
which is completely uniform,
of course it stays that way,
but let's suppose there was a little bit
of overdensity here.
A little bit of overdensity.
Now,
that's,
uh,
that's a little rea-
a big region,
a fairly big region
where the density is a little bigger
than the neighboring region.
What happens?
What happens in grav-
in a gravitational theory
is the opposite of what happens
in other kinds of theories.
In other kinds of theories,
what tends to happen is this.
If there's an overdensity here,
it will diffuse out and be eliminated.
For example,
you have an overdensity
of ink dropped into water.
You have a spot of ink.
What happens over time?
It diffuses out and,
uh,
and,
and disappears and becomes homogeneous.
In gravity,
the opposite happens.
And the argument is very simple.
If you have an overdensity here,
because gravity is attractive,
universally attractive,
it will tend to attract the stuff around it,
pull it in,
decreasing the,
um,
the density outside
and increasing it inside.
In other words,
it's kind of a runaway situation.
It's a runaway situation where
a little bit of inhomogeneity
will tend to reinforce itself.
So if you have overdensity,
underdensity,
overdensity,
and so forth,
in some pattern,
the tendency of gravity will be to suck stuff
out of the underdense regions
and put it into the overdense regions
and thereby magnifying
the,
uh,
degree of,
of inhomogeneity.
So,
the fact that we see inhomogeneity today
does not mean that the universe very early
was as inhomogene- ingenious as it is today.
It must have been much less inhomogeneous
just by running the argument backward.
In fact,
cosmologists rather early
were able to estimate
by running the theory backward,
they were able to estimate
at the time of decoupling
just how much inhomogeneity was there
in order that the galaxies could nucleate
out of that inhomogeneity.
In other words,
the picture is
the universe was very homogeneous,
but little bits of inhomogeneity,
little bits of ripples,
little bits of,
um,
excess depletion,
uh,
of some kind.
And those overdense regions
eventually collapsed by this mechanism,
formed galaxies and clusters of galaxies,
and the underdense regions formed voids,
and that's what we see today.
So,
you can estimate,
and it was estimated by people like
Jim Peebles and other people,
early cosmologists in the 60s,
and I'm not sure exactly when,
how much inhomogeneity was necessary
at the time of decoupling.
And the answer was,
here's the way you quantify it.
You look at the lumpiness,
and you characterize it by a delta rho,
where delta rho is roughly
the mean excess density in a lump
relative to the background,
and you divide it by the density itself.
That's the fractional overdensity
in a typical overdense region.
Divide,
compared with the density itself.
That's the dimensionless measure
of how much,
uh,
how much,
um,
inhomogeneity there was.
And it was pretty early recognized
that this was a number that had to be
about 10 to the minus 5.
Somewhere between 10 to the minus 4,
10 to the minus 5.
Alright,
so here we were again,
with the same curve,
and we were given this kind of situation,
a question,
why is the universe homogeneous?
Well,
does that really require an answer?
It just started that way.
But now there was a number.
There was a number.
In addition to just saying
the universe was homogeneous,
it is also clear that it wasn't homogeneous.
It wasn't homogeneous
with a specific numerical magnitude to it.
And once you have a specific numerical magnitude,
you want to know why that's the magnitude.
Now,
it's not that we learned why this is the magnitude.
We did not.
We do not really understand
why this is the right number.
Um,
but the existence of this number
focused attention on the question.
And the first question was,
why is the universe so homogeneous?
Later we'll worry about why it's inhomogeneous.
The first order fact
was that it's very,
very homogeneous.
The explanation of that today,
that is,
which seemed rather far-fetched
when it was put forward by Alan Guth in 1980,
was the universe simply expanded
by many orders of magnitude.
And of course,
when something expands,
it stretches.
And if you stretch out,
if you have an inhomogeneous universe
with lumpiness in it,
it's not homogeneous.
And you stretch it out enough,
you'll make it homogeneous
at least on the scales that are relevant.
So,
the idea was the universe inflated,
which means expanded,
and in particular exponentially expanded
for some period of time,
and stretched itself out so much
that it flattened itself to,
you know,
it's like blowing,
literally like blowing up a balloon.
The balloons are crinkled,
rough-shaped thing.
When it's collapsed,
you blow it up,
and it stretches out
and then flattens out.
That's an analogy
which you shouldn't take too far.
Yeah?
How do you explain
that it's isotropic?
Wouldn't you expect more lumpiness
with greater masses
in different directions?
Why is it isotropic?
It's not exactly,
if we look,
I look around this room,
it doesn't look isotropic to me.
I look out.
A very high level of isotropic.
On an average over large distances.
Yeah.
You know,
it's like the surface of the Earth.
It's full of hills and mountains and valleys
and so forth.
You've got to explain those.
You explain them by geological phenomena
and so forth.
But on the whole,
the Earth is very smooth.
And the universe is smooth.
The universe is the same.
If it's homogeneous,
or if it's homogeneous,
I was going to say if it's homogeneous,
it's going to be isotropic.
No,
that's not true.
What I'm getting at is
wouldn't you expect certain directions
to exhibit much greater masses?
Why?
Because you start out
with a small amount
of inhomogeneity,
but it's a random process
that you would expect that
in some directions
you would see a great deal more...
No.
No,
it's not a random.
It's not random.
I see what you're getting at.
You're saying if it were random,
you might expect that somewhere out there
there would be large overdensities
if it were random.
With some statistical probability
you might find a large,
large lumpiness.
It's not random.
And we're going to talk about
the pattern of it.
Basically it's a...
you know,
it looks like a...
Now squeeze this down
until it's of size 10 to the minus 5
relative to the background.
On the whole,
it's very smooth.
But nevertheless,
there are wiggles in it,
and the size of the wiggles
are very small.
What the implication is,
and they're uniformly distributed
through space.
They are homogeneous,
isotropically distributed.
There are no large,
tremendously large lumps out there.
They're all very small,
small in magnitude.
Not small in size,
but small in magnitude.
And it's more or less
like a very,
very smooth Earth
with ripples on it that...
Well...
Again,
there's an
inward relationship between
early time and high temperature
relationship.
So there was a particular time
when inflation started and stopped,
and that relates to
particular temperatures.
Is there any connection,
or is it just random?
I mean,
is it the temperature
causal of the effect,
or is it...?
During the inflationary period,
temperature was not an important
aspect of things.
During the inflationary period,
temperature was not a terribly
relevant factor.
It was the exponential expansion,
which was the single most
important thing.
And I'm going to begin...
Let's see,
where are we?
We still have a little bit of time
to talk about some preliminaries.
It looks like next week will be
our real week for inflation.
And the equations,
I'm going to
take you through the basic
equations of inflation,
show you how it works
in some detail.
But I think what I'll do for the
rest of the evening...
Um...
Let's talk about friction.
What does friction have to do
with anything?
It has everything to do with
everything,
but tonight I'm just
going to tell you about friction.
The equations of friction.
Write it down,
because I'm going
to use it.
And it's very simple.
When I speak of friction,
I'm
speaking of viscosity.
I'm thinking about something like
a stone falling through
viscous fluid.
Why am I doing that?
I'm doing that because it will
come up.
Okay.
Take a stone falling through
water.
Or honey.
And I'm just reminding you of
the equations for it.
It's falling due to a force,
which is a gradient of potential
energy.
Let's call the height here,
what shall I call it?
I'm going to call it phi,
which
is a stupid name for the height.
But it's not a stupid name for a
field,
and as you might expect,
what we're going to be talking
about is fields.
But nevertheless,
the analogy is
phi is the height of the stone.
And there's a force on the stone.
There's a force on the stone
which is related to its potential
energy,
in this case,
the force
gravity,
and in this case,
it could
just be the potential energy of
gravitation in,
but let's just call
it a potential energy,
V of phi.
Let's assume the force is downward,
which means V of phi increases in
the upward direction,
and what is
the force?
The force is the derivative of the
potential energy,
but minus it,
minus the derivative of the
potential energy,
V with respect,
just a derivative,
ordinary
derivative,
dV d phi.
All right,
let's write Newton's
equations now.
Newton's equations for the stone,
for simplicity,
let's just take
the stone to have unit mass.
Okay.
What's the equation of motion?
F equals mA.
The force,
on the right-hand side,
is minus
dV d phi,
and that's equal to the
mass,
which I'm setting equal to
one,
times the acceleration,
which
is phi double dot,
the second time
derivative of phi.
Okay,
this is F equals mA,
and
there's nothing special there.
In a uniform force field,
which
would just mean dV d phi is just
a constant,
the stone would form
a uniform acceleration,
and it would
just very quickly pick up a lot of
speed and continue to accelerate.
All right,
that has ignored the
viscosity of the fluid that it's
moving in,
which,
let's say,
is
something like honey.
All right,
now,
that means that
there's another force on the right-hand
side here.
That other force is zero if the force
is at rest.
The viscosity has exerts no force on
an object at rest.
It's moving through the fluid,
which
creates the force.
And so,
the force on the right-hand
side is going to depend on the velocity.
The larger the velocity,
the more the
viscosity.
And for simple fluids,
the viscosity is
actually proportional to the velocity
itself.
So,
there's a force on the right-hand
side,
which is proportional to the
velocity.
Which direction is it going to go?
Which direction is it in?
It's obviously opposing the velocity.
So,
it's got a minus sign in front of
it here.
And there's some coefficient in front
of it that's called the coefficient of
the...
The Susskind number.
I forget what it's called.
I don't know what it's...
The drag!
All right.
Well,
what's the letter for it?
Who?
Anybody know?
B?
D?
Gamma.
Whatever it is.
It can't be the same for both forces.
Yeah.
Why not?
Huh?
You want one force to pull it down,
and
then the other force to slow it down.
The VD5...
The VD5 pushes down,
right?
All right.
It's moving with a downward vertical
velocity,
right?
If it's moving with a downward vertical
velocity,
that means phi dot is negative,
right?
Minus phi dot is positive.
This force is up.
As long as it's moving down.
Okay.
What's that?
The derivative of the potential is the
negative of the force.
So that's why...
The VD5 is down.
It's negative.
But this one is positive.
It's positive because phi dot is negative.
All right?
It's falling down.
All right.
So,
in the beginning,
when the stone starts
to fall,
phi dot is zero,
and basically it
starts out accelerating exactly as it would
without this.
But very quickly,
phi dot will increase,
and unless,
as you move down,
you move
down,
the force gets bigger and bigger rapidly.
This is going to increase because phi dot is increasing
until it balances VD5.
At that point,
the forces cancel,
and that's called the
terminal velocity.
In particular,
if the force is uniform,
if the downward force,
for example,
like the force of gravity,
is uniform near the
surface of the Earth,
then this is just,
let's just call it F,
minus F,
minus phi dot,
gamma.
That's the total force.
And at some point,
it stops accelerating because these two
balance each other,
and of course,
that happens when phi
dot reaches the terminal velocity,
and the terminal
velocity phi dot is equal,
let's see,
now I am getting my
signs confused.
The force is negative,
right?
The force is negative because it's down,
but the terminal
velocity happens.
It's equal.
When F,
when phi dot is F over gamma.
Now my signs are confused.
Do I have a problem here?
Oh,
no,
it's okay.
F is negative,
so the terminal velocity is negative.
Terminal velocity is negative because it's falling.
All right.
That's the basic theory of friction.
And what does it do?
It slows things down.
In particular,
if V of phi has a shallow slope.
If V of phi,
let's plot V of phi.
Let's plot phi this way.
Let's plot phi,
plot it horizontally even though phi is
the vertical direction.
Let's plot it horizontally,
and let's suppose that V of phi is
a rather shallow hill.
Okay?
If it's a rather shallow hill,
and the viscosity coefficient
here is large,
the stone falling along this potential energy
here will simply take a long,
long time to roll down the hill.
That's the situation we will want to be in,
and phi will not
be a stone.
It will not be the position of a stone.
It will be the value of a field.
But we will want to be in
a situation where a field evolves very slowly
because of a lot of friction.
And that will drive inflation,
and we will come to it,
I think,
well,
I don't know.
Should we go on a little bit?
I'm a little afraid to overdo it tonight.
Okay.
Let's go on for a little bit.
Good.
Now what we're going to consider is classical field theory.
The universe is filled with some field.
This field is going to be a scalar field.
Now,
where does this come from?
What scalar field?
It was made up.
It was simply made up in order
to be able to explain the isotropy
and the homogeneity of the universe.
At the time this was created,
it was a long shot,
a rather crazy idea,
but it seems to be right.
Okay.
So here's the idea.
The world contains,
in addition to the electromagnetic field,
the gravitational field,
and all the usual fields,
there's one more field.
It's a scalar field.
And it's called the inflaton,
phi.
Why?
Because it has to do with inflation.
Now,
we're going to assume that phi
is pretty much uniform in space.
We could assume it's not uniform in space,
but as the space expands,
it will tend to stretch out the variations in phi.
So let's just assume for simplicity
that phi is uniform in space,
and think about the energy stored in a field,
in a scalar field of this type.
Does everybody remember what the energy
density of a scalar field is?
It contains a kinetic term with time derivatives.
This is the energy density.
It contains...
This is the energy density,
let's just call it the energy of a scalar field.
It contains one term,
which is phi dot squared.
This is just the kinetic energy of the field,
not the kinetic energy in
the sense of movement in space,
but the sense due to time dependence.
Then,
typically,
there is another term which has
to do with gradients in space.
So this case,
the dot is a partial derivative of the...
With respect to time.
It is,
right.
d phi by dt squared.
There's also terms in the energy which
have to do with gradients in space.
Gradients in space also store energy.
But since we've assumed that the field is homogeneous,
and is not varying in space,
which we can justify,
but we can do that later,
there are no gradients in space.
And so this is the
only term in the energy density
that has derivatives in it.
Then the other thing that can be there
is a potential energy.
A potential energy which is plus V of phi.
It's just a thing that's made up.
That different values of the field have different energy.
Doesn't have to do with derivatives.
Just in having a field of...
of a given magnitude,
there's an energy density associated with it.
That's called the field potential energy.
And it's not by accident that
I'm giving these the same notation.
Phi is a field.
Up here it was the coordinate of a stone.
But it's not by accident.
Okay.
Now,
this...
Let's follow the field,
and let's follow it in a box.
In an expanding box.
As always,
the box that we focus on
is expanding with the universe.
And how big is it at any given time?
How big is that box?
That box is of size a cubed.
The scale factor cubed.
Let's say it's a unit box in coordinate space.
The size of the box is a cubed.
Alright.
This is the energy density.
So,
to get the energy,
I wrote energy here,
but this is really energy per unit volume.
If I want to write the
energy of the field in the box,
I have to multiply it by a cubed.
But a is time dependent.
It depends on time.
So,
we have a time dependent energy expression.
a cubed of t.
Kinetic energy plus potential energy.
You can think of this,
if you like,
as formally,
mathematically,
being the same as the energy of a particle,
kinetic energy plus potential energy,
except with a coefficient out here,
which depends on time.
Something you wouldn't ordinarily write down.
You might have a funny situation,
where the mass of a particle might depend on time.
And then,
this might depend on...
But ordinarily,
you wouldn't write that down.
Nevertheless,
that's what we have.
We have an energy,
kinetic plus potential.
Is any dependence on spatial coordinates?
Let's assume...
Oh,
on a?
No,
a is just a scale factor.
Right,
right.
Let's assume on a,
time.
If there was...
Okay.
If there was spatial dependence,
we would have to add in here a term,
for spatial gradients.
Let's assume,
for the moment,
that the field is uniform in space.
If it's not,
eventually it will be,
because the expansion will stretch it out,
and get rid of the gradients,
and stretch it out.
So,
it's reasonable to assume,
that after a period of time,
there are no gradients.
No gradients of the field in space.
But I mean,
just on a conceptual level,
we're thinking of associating this field value
with a point in space.
Yes,
yes,
yes.
But if we assume that it's uniform,
then all we need to
do to find the total energy
is to multiply by the volume of the box,
which is time dependent.
Is there a question?
Is there any physical thing we can think of
for the feed off?
In other words,
that kinetic,
as you say,
is not moving,
it's a time interval,
but what...
Yeah.
Is there any,
any simple way
to think of that?
I mean,
physical?
It's...
Well,
I'll just...
I'm so used to it that I think of it
as sort of obvious,
but...
What's the field doing?
Is it getting stronger or weaker?
We're going to find out.
We have to solve the equations of motion.
Okay.
That's like asking...
That's like asking what's happened to this particle.
Is it moving up or moving down?
That will depend on the initial conditions,
it will depend on how long we wait,
and it will especially depend
on the sign of dv d phi,
namely the sign of the force.
Well,
whatever's doing it,
it's doing it everywhere.
It's doing it everywhere simultaneously.
All right?
Right.
Now,
we can back off that
and study what happens when it's not,
but this is the easy problem to study.
Okay.
Now,
how do we find the equation of motion
when we know the kinetic energy
and we know the potential energy?
There's various ways we could do it,
but the most efficient way
is through Lagrange's equations.
Lagrange's equations are the following.
Lagrangian,
let's write the Lagrangian now.
The Lagrangian is the difference
of kinetic energy and potential energy.
So,
you pick up your copy of the theoretical minimum
and you look up Lagrange's equations
with this.
Phi is like the coordinate,
phi is like the coordinate,
and here is the Lagrangian.
The only new thing that wouldn't be there
for an ordinary particle
is this A of t.
All right,
so let's work out Lagrange's equations.
The first term is d by dt,
or I suppose we can make it...
d by dt of partial of L
with respect to phi dot.
Everybody remember that?
And what's on the right-hand side?
Right.
That's Lagrange's equations.
So,
partial of L with respect to phi dot...
This is the equation that we get out of it.
Partial of L with respect to phi dot
is just phi dot,
times A cubed of t.
This is partial of L with respect to phi dot.
This isn't here.
dL by d phi dot
is phi dot times A cubed of t.
Is that obvious?
Good.
Now we have to take its time derivative,
d by dt.
And that we have to set equal
to A cubed
times minus A cubed
times dv d phi.
Or just ordinary derivative,
dv d phi.
We could call dv d phi,
we could call it the force.
So minus dv d phi,
But notice that there's
this extra explicit time dependent thing there.
This doesn't quite look like Newton's equations.
It would be Newton's equations if A was constant.
Okay?
But A is not constant.
So let's work it out and see what it is.
First of all,
the d by dt,
there are two terms.
One comes from hitting phi dot.
The other comes from hitting A cubed.
So let's first do the first one.
The first one is A cubed
times phi double dot.
That's d by dt of phi dot
times A cubed.
And what's the second term?
It's phi dot
times the time derivative of A cubed.
Okay?
The time derivative of A cubed
is
three
A squared
times A dot.
Do I have that right?
Yeah.
That's in a parenthesis over here.
And that's equal,
let's just call it,
to A cubed times the force.
The force on phi.
Okay.
It's very tempting,
and I will do it,
to divide out the A cubed,
because it appears both here and here.
Let's divide out the A cubed.
But I better divide over here also,
huh?
Okay.
So let's clean it up.
It's phi double dot
plus three
A dot over A,
A squared divided by A cubed is one over A,
so it's A dot over A
times phi dot
is equal to F.
What is A dot over A called in cosmology?
The Hubble constant,
which is not generally a constant,
but it's H.
It's of course...
It's supposed to be like the same everywhere,
though?
Everywhere's in space,
but not necessarily in time.
Maybe the same in time,
but it may not be.
All right.
So we'll come back to what it is in time,
but keep in mind,
it could be time dependent.
A double...
Sorry,
not A double dot,
phi double dot.
Phi double dot from here
plus three H times phi dot equals F.
Let's write this one this way.
Plus...
equals F.
This is exactly the same equation
as the falling stone
with a viscosity coefficient three H
and a force which is just a gradient of V.
So our model for the way this field evolves
can be envisioned
by just supposing
that phi was the position
of a particle on a hill
where the height of the hill was V,
where the gradient of the altitude of the hill
was the force,
dV d phi,
a ball rolling down the hill,
except that there's a viscous drag force
proportional to the Hubble expansion rate,
which is the force of the hill.
So the Hubble expansion rate
behaves as a kind of friction.
That is why we went through this exercise over here.
If the Hubble friction is strong,
if H is big,
and the force here,
and if the hill is reasonably flat,
not terribly flat,
but somewhat flat,
then...
this could be like a ball moving through
motor oil in Wisconsin on a cold day.
Okay?
It's just left to its own devices
without the friction term.
It might roll down the hill in a few seconds.
All right?
With a large friction,
it could take years to roll down the hill,
depending on the magnitude of the friction.
So this is called the cosmic friction term.
In the equation of motion of a scalar field.
And it has the effect,
it has the simple effect of slowing down
the evolution of the system
and keeping the ball from rolling down the hill.
The next time,
we're going to use this
to study the cosmology of a universe
which contains a field like this.
In other words,
we're going to look at the FRW,
sorry,
the Friedman equation,
which is the,
with an energy density
which is given by this.
All right?
So we're going to study,
we're going to study how the universe
expands and evolves
under the influence of an energy density
which is slowly,
slowly,
slowly
rolling down the hill here.
That's the phenomenon of inflation.
That the way the universe responds
to this very slowly moving field.
Okay.
Next time.
For more,
please visit us at stanford.edu.