This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
Relativity.
Relativity means special relativity, mostly.
And then at the end,
a little bit of general relativity.
But general relativity done with some, not
rigor so much as, well, conceptual rigor,
if not mathematical rigor.
Now before I go ahead, let
me just tell you one thing.
I'm going to be gone for two weeks.
I have to be in Israel.
I have to give some lectures to the,
I don't know, to somebody, some organization of philosophers.
And so I will.
I will be gone for two weeks.
That means, I think, does anybody
have a calendar in their head?
I'm coming back on the 24th, but
I don't know what date that is.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But we will continue.
We will get ten full classes, even if
we have to go into June a little bit.
We'll get ten full classes, but I
will necessarily have to stagger them a bit.
Yeah.
How about the lecture?
Oh, yes.
That's also on Monday, isn't it?
Yes.
Yep.
So you're gone the next two weeks?
Yeah, I'll be gone for the next two weeks.
And then the one after that is for Monday.
Well, you know, if there's enough, if there's flexibility,
if there's flexibility about the day of the week,
we could just, when a
thing like that happens, say, well,
we will meet on Monday.
On Wednesday instead of on Monday or something like that.
I know some people arrange their schedule
one way or another, and it doesn't fit.
But we will have one class before
the Hofstadter lecture, and then we can decide.
I think so.
I think it's this one.
No, no, I think it's another one.
I think the 20th.
Oh, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
Well.
If nothing else, the Hofstadter
lecture, I think, begins at 8.
Oh, there's a problem there.
I may have to be available.
Well, one way or another.
I'll be gone the next two
Mondays, and then I'll be back.
Let's assume we will meet here
on the Monday after I get back.
That's the 30th.
That's the Hofstadter lecture.
I will be here.
Okay?
Now, I am also the host for
the Hofstadter lecture, so this is going to—
So, you know, what it'll probably mean
is we'll go to the Hofstadter lecture,
but I'm not going to count that
as a regular class if we do that.
And we'll see.
At that time, we'll see if we can
figure out a time to—some way to make adjustments.
I'd just make one suggestion on that, is that
in the past, when that kind of a conflict came,
you just—
Maybe start a class at 6 instead of 7.
We never did that, did we?
Yeah, we did.
Did we?
We can do that.
Oh, you mean specifically for the—
Yeah.
Yeah, we could do that.
Okay.
Good, good, good.
Let's do that.
Yeah.
All right.
So, let's assume that on the week after
I return, that we meet here—the Monday after
we return, we meet here at 6.
Does that work for everybody?
Okay, good.
The 30th?
The 30th.
I think it's the 30th, yeah.
Yeah.
But then I would like to find maybe some
ways of—I'm always in the situation where I have
to be someplace else.
I have to be two places at
the same time, and it's hard to do.
So, if we can somehow
juggle times, that does help me.
Yeah.
You're just a little uncertain about where you're going.
Yeah, I'm more than a
little uncertain most of the time.
All right.
When you were talking about—
Next term, you gave me a summer before—
No, no, no.
No, no.
Summer, I won't teach.
Hmm?
You're somewhere else.
No, I'm actually usually here, but no.
I need to stop and do nothing for the summer.
I need to think about things.
All right.
Let's do—let's begin with special relativity, and
let's really do the mathematics of special
relativity carefully.
Okay.
Let's work it out.
Work out the details of energy, momentum.
Well, first we're going to work out the
details of space and time and space-time, the details
and the symmetries, Lorentz transformations, what
it means for things to be synchronous
and so forth to work these things
out with some care and some precision.
Okay.
move on to, we could call that kinematics.
Kinematics, space and time, how things move,
but not why they move.
Then comes the question why things move,
and why things move is because of forces.
And forces, of course, are the subject of dynamics.
And so we will study
a little bit about the dynamics
of special relativity, energy, momentum, force,
the analog of Newton's equations,
not Newton's gravitational equations,
but Newton's equations of motion for special relativity.
E equals MC squared and
all that stuff, what it means.
And I think that should probably take us
about five lectures, five or six or something like that.
Then I would move on to some general relativity.
The general relativity that we'll do
will not be incorrect, it will be absolutely correct,
but what I will teach less
of is the Einstein field equations
and more of what happens
to particles and objects when they're
in a given gravitational field.
All right, so what is a gravitational field?
Curvature of space time and that kind of thing,
without trying to get into the harder,
much more difficult subject of solving
Einstein's field equations, that's hard.
It's hard for me anyway.
So that's what we'll do this quarter.
Basic relativity, special and a bit of general.
We'll probably get to the point
where we can talk about black holes a little bit.
Maybe also get to the point where we can talk
about expansion of the universe.
Some of the interesting things that flow out
of the general theory of relativity.
All right, now let's begin.
First of all, what do we mean by relativity?
Special.
Well, what do we mean by relativity in general?
What we mean by relativity is the idea that,
of course, all of you know,
that the laws of physics are independent
of the frame of reference in which you study them.
Frame of reference, simply for our purposes here,
means a state of motion of a set of coordinates.
If you like, the way
to think about it is to,
imagine space being filled up with a lattice,
an imaginary lattice of meter sticks,
so that every point in
space is labeled by a X,
a Y, and a Z, a set of meter sticks,
and at each vertex of the lattice, a clock.
And the clock measures time.
Now, in Newtonian physics, in Newtonian physics,
Newton imagined that time was very, very universal.
He imagined God's time.
God's time was the same for everybody.
There was no question of what the time was
on a particular clock.
Clocks were synchronized.
It didn't matter how they moved.
It didn't matter how you move.
It didn't matter how you move with your watch
or without your watch.
Everybody would agree at every instant, at every place,
in the world, on what the time is, T.
That, of course, had to be given up
when Einstein moved to special relativity.
But the idea of relativity was already there
before Einstein, long before Einstein.
It basically goes back to Galileo.
So, let me just remind you what Galilean relativity is,
how and why it failed.
The way I like to think about relativity,
is I like to imagine,
I always like to have a picture in my head
that I can think about intuitively.
And the picture that I have in my head
is the same one that Einstein thought about,
moving along in a railroad train
in a railroad which is extremely well made,
so well made that the tracks are perfectly smooth,
so smooth that the train doesn't rattle,
it doesn't shake,
and it just moves with absolute uniform velocity.
Now, what are the laws of physics?
Well, my favorite description of the laws of physics
in this train is what I like to imagine
the laws of juggling.
Juggling is good physics, incidentally.
To be a good juggler,
you have to have a
very, very good sense of timing.
You have to have a good sense of gravity.
You have to have a good sense of alignment.
There's a lot of different aspects of physics.
Of course, you may not consciously be using those,
but at least unconsciously,
all kinds of physics comes into juggling.
So there are some rules.
You throw the ball up,
and you wait a certain amount of time,
and you catch it, and you transfer it,
and you do whatever it
is that you're supposed to do,
and you call all of those the laws of physics
or the laws of juggling.
Now, it's a fact of nature that in this train,
which is moving with absolute uniform velocity,
relative to a stalled train,
a train that happens to be at rest
on the surface of the Earth, for example,
imagine the surface of the Earth,
one train moving, one train standing still,
the laws of juggling are exactly the same.
This, in fact, before Galileo,
this was something of a surprise.
In fact, not a surprise.
People didn't understand that.
They actually imagined, of course,
they didn't have trains to think about,
but if you would have told them about trains,
and moving along with a train,
the average scientist probably would have thought
that when you throw a ball
in the air in the train,
you probably have to compensate
for the motion of the train by,
if the train is moving that way,
you probably have to move
your arm over to the right
in order to catch the ball,
because the train moving will lead to
moving out from under the thrown ball.
Of course, this is wrong.
The laws of juggling are the same
in the stationary train and the moving train,
identical, exactly the same.
And that was something that Galileo realized.
Galileo was the first to realize it,
and Newton spelled it out in great detail
in his laws of motion.
So let's begin with Galilean relativity.
Let's begin with Galilean relativity.
Like all theories of relativity,
it's a theory of transformations,
transformations of coordinates,
and transformations of phenomena
from one frame of reference to another.
Again, a frame of reference means, as I said,
a lattice of meter sticks with clocks
which have been synchronized,
and we'll have to discuss what we mean by synchronized,
but clocks which have been synchronized
at each corner of the lattice,
and now we can imagine having
two such lattices.
One is moving relative to the other.
In each frame of reference,
the clocks have been synchronized
in the appropriate way,
and so we have to transform information
from one frame of reference to another.
Various kinds of information,
what is the energy of an object,
what is the temperature of an object,
I don't know, any number of different kinds of quantities,
we could ask, if you know
it in one frame of reference,
what is it in the other frame of reference?
Now the simplest set of quantities
has to do with location,
location in space and location in time,
the things which are recorded
by the meter sticks and the clocks.
So how do we transform from
one frame of reference to another?
Here we have a frame of reference
that is a relative to the other.
Let's first of all draw a frame of reference.
The first thing to do
when you start a relativity problem
is to draw a picture,
and the picture is a picture of space-time.
Time vertically, as always,
and space horizontally,
and at least in the beginning,
we're mainly going to be interested in problems
involving motion along one particular axis,
so let's call it the x-axis.
The y and z directions for the moment
will be rather passive.
They won't play any great role for a while.
They'll come into things.
And so every point in space and time,
or every point on the blackboard,
stands for a place in
space and a time in time.
So it's called space-time, naturally enough.
Okay, now let's, and if you,
if I wanted to draw the meter sticks,
let's just imagine drawing the meter sticks.
One, here's the origin.
Here's the origin right here.
Time equals zero here.
The clocks have been all adjusted,
so the time is equal to zero
all along the horizontal axis.
And as we flow up,
the clocks tick off time, seconds, years,
whatever it happens to be.
All right, now, if we move
down the line a little bit,
we come to the end of the first meter stick.
So here's the end of the first meter stick.
Its trajectory is a trajectory in space-time.
The second meter stick is over here.
The third meter stick is over here.
And the sequence of meter sticks
laid out along the horizontal axis,
as time goes on, define
a series of stripes like this,
which represents locations in space, if you like.
This is x-axis.
So x equals zero, x equals one.
Needless to say, we can also go backward
to x equals minus one, x
equals minus two, and so forth.
There's no reason to stop at x equals zero.
x equals one, x equals two, x equals three,
x equals four, and so forth.
Now, the clocks tick.
And so a clock which reads,
there is no time that we call zero, is there?
We never hear of talking about time zero.
I mean, you know, an ordinary clock.
Time zero is usually what we call zero.
Zero is usually what we call 12 midnight, I guess.
But anyway, let's use the term time t equals zero.
T equals zero is over here.
T equals one, one what?
One second or whatever.
Two seconds, three seconds, four seconds, five seconds.
And now if we draw some horizontal lines,
those represent lines of constant time.
So the whole world is a circle.
So the whole world, space and time, becomes a lattice.
Not a real lattice, an imaginary lattice.
And you can make that
lattice as fine as you like.
It doesn't have to be meters.
It could be centimeters or microns or
Planck lengths or if smaller than that makes any sense.
We can make it as fine as we like.
And in that way, every point
in space time represents a precise time.
And that's why we call it the Planck Line.
It's the same time and a
precise place according to this lattice.
All right, now that's your reference frame.
You are the people in the
station or in the broke-down train,
which isn't moving.
All right?
You're sitting there waiting at rest
at the surface of the Earth.
But my train is moving, and
my train is moving with velocity v.
All right?
I'm in the caboose of
the train at the tail end.
And let's say.
at time t equals zero, the caboose is right over
here, but as time moves on, as time moves ahead,
my train moves forward. I'll assume it
moves forward. It could also move backward,
and so the tail end
of the caboose looks like that.
My, the next car might look like
this. I'm imagining now cars one meter long,
and so my series of constant position coordinates
are tilted relative to yours in a space-time plot
like this. All right, now we're not going to,
we're not up to Einstein yet. We're doing Galileo.
And Newton. Galileo and Newton could ask
the question, if you people in the station
give a certain set of coordinates, let's
say x and t, to an event,
here's an event right over here, an event means
a point of space-time, if you label the point of
space-time x and t in what we'll
call the stationary reference frame, what are the
coordinates that I assign to it in my
moving reference frame? Well, if Galileo were here,
he would look at this and say, look, time is
time. I believe, like Newton will believe in a few years,
that time is universal. Everybody agrees about time,
and in fact he could sort of check that.
There weren't very good watches at that time, but
he could check it with a pendulum or something
like that, and he could take a look at it and
say, well, it's not that good. It's just that it's not
the same as the time t equals zero. And so, he
would think that he's just going to have to go back
and look at the time t, and he would say, well,
it's not that good. He's just going to have to go back
to the time t, and he would say, well, it's not that
good. It's just that he's just going to have to go back
that. And he could take the pendulum, and if he
was careful, he could put the pendulum on a moving
train. There were no trains, there were no
watches, but he could imagine taking his pendulum
and moving it along and bringing it back and
checking it against the pendulum at rest. And if
he did it well and he did it carefully, he
would find that the two pendulums agreed. The way the
pendulums move would not in any way influence how
rapidly they tick off. And of course, that's true
for the pendulum.
But it's not that easy to know the pendulums
until the pendulums stop moving too fast. So, Galileo,
first of all, would have said, t prime, that's
the time in my frame of reference, the moving reference
frame, is the same as your time. But, my
coordinate, x prime, what does my coordinate mean? Let's take
this point over here.
The coordinate, the x coordinate that I assigned to this point over here, is the distance not to your origin
of coordinates, not to your origin of space, but to my origin of space. My origin of space is over here.
So, I will assign a smaller x, x prime will be smaller than
x, and what it will be will be x, your x, minus x prime.
The amount that you move, or sorry, the amount that I move
in time t, and that's going to be minus the velocity times t.
So, t prime equals t, x prime is equal to x minus
vt, where v is the relative velocity of the two frames of reference.
We can go back and forth.
We can solve, we can solve this equation.
We can solve this equation.
This gives me the primed
coordinates in terms of the unprimed.
I could solve this and rewrite it as t
equals t prime, x equals x prime plus v.
Now, I would, if I just used the second equation, I would write plus vt,
but since t is the same as t prime, I'll just write vt prime here.
The top equation would be how the moving, would be how the
stationary observer converts his information into the information of a moving observer.
And the inverse equation would be how you go back.
はい
This is the basic mathematics of Galilean relativity.
Let's check some things. First of
all, what kind of things are invariant?
The idea of invariance is very important.
The idea of invariant
or an invariant
invariant is both an adjective and a noun.
Equations can be invariant.
An invariant means a thing which everybody agrees about,
a quantity that everybody agrees about.
Alright, so let me give you an
example of a quantity that everybody agrees about,
everybody meaning these two observers,
or any other ones that
we also throw in. Yeah, question.
You were saying about the pendulum, how you can check
Yes.
Well, I was, I was, uh...
Yeah.
How does he know that
when he moves the pendulum away,
that he's speeding it up
and then it's kind of, uh,
it's decelerated and going fast?
How does he know that that is...
Of course, the answer is he doesn't.
But if you do it with an ordinary watch,
with a good, no, I mean,
how Galileo would have known it,
I think Galileo just guessed it.
How you would do it is
you would take your high quality,
Rolex watch, and you would just go and do it.
One person would stay in his seat, and
the other person would march around the room
a few hundred times and then
come back and check their watches.
Now, the answer, of course,
that we know, because of hindsight,
and because we're living in the 21st
century, and Einstein was a hundred years ago,
is there will be a tiny
discrepancy, but that discrepancy is so small,
that for ordinary purposes, for ordinary daily experience,
we would simply say the rate
at which clocks tick off time
doesn't depend on their motion.
And that's an experimental fact.
Experimental fact in the sense that if
we actually did it with ordinary clocks,
it would work.
It would work to very high precision.
Of course, at some level, it fails,
but that's what special relativity is about.
I guess ignoring the special relativity thing,
I guess I have a problem that you're
bringing the clock back to the same spot.
Yeah.
And that's you're biasing whatever...
Oh, you think it might have sped
up as you went one way and...
Come back, is it?
Yeah, well, that might have happened.
That would mean that there was basically
a difference between left motion and right motion.
So we could try the
same experiment going the other way.
Well, maybe the same thing
would happen, but then we could...
If east and west, we
would try it north and south.
We might also take my watch and go around
you in circles for a long period of time
and do all kinds of experiments.
Or just go one direction and use a telescope.
Use what we...
All kinds of...
There are all kinds of ways we
would try all sorts of obvious things,
and they all work.
And they all work, right.
You don't need a telescope.
You use a telephone to
communicate the information back and forth.
Send light signals back and forth
to check our watches and so forth.
And it would work very well.
It would work very well until
we start to move too fast.
Then it breaks down.
But the point is that Galilean
relativity was based on a guess.
It was frankly based on a guess.
And the mathematical translation of
the guess is these equations.
Now, there are some obvious invariants.
For example, here's something that's invariant.
At an instant of time, look
at the distance between two events.
Two events which are synchronous or simultaneous.
Simultaneous being used to mean at the same time.
Take two events at the same time.
The distance between them will be invariant.
Why is that?
Let's take the two events.
Let's call them x1 at time t1 and
x2 at also at the same time t.
Let's not even bother labeling the time.
At the same time.
These are two events at the same time.
And the distance between them is simply x2 minus x1.
And that we can call distance.
What about the primed coordinates?
The primed coordinates are x prime
1 is equal to x1 minus vt.
x prime 2 is x2 minus vt.
Notice that the actual coordinates are not invariant.
They don't assign the same values of x.
But they do assign the same
values if we now subtract these two.
Or subtract them, the bottom one,
the top one from the bottom one.
Then x prime 2 minus x prime
1 is equal to x2 minus x1.
And then the vt's cancel.
So the separation between two points
at the same instant of time.
I emphasize at the same instant of time.
Because it wouldn't be true if we
did it at different instants of time.
Yeah.
The t's on the right are not
the same as the t's on the left.
Yeah, they are.
With an event at x1 t
and another event at x2 t.
This is t over here.
Okay, got it.
Got it, okay.
This is t.
Here's x2.
Here's x1.
The separation between the two points is an invariant.
That's the language we would use.
Let's imagine that we have a particle trajectory.
A particle trajectory means an x of t.
x as a function of t
would be a trajectory of some particle.
I'll put it over here.
Trajectory of some particle is an
x at each function of time.
First of all, is the position invariant?
No.
x and x prime are not the same thing.
But we can write x prime of t
is equal to x of t minus vt.
All right, so if I know the trajectory x
of t, not v of t, but v times t.
If I know the trajectory of a particle, or if
you know the trajectory of a particle x of t,
you can communicate it to me.
And the communication will be in the form
of telling me what x prime of t is.
What I will see is an x prime of
t, which will be your x of t minus vt.
All right, so the coordinate of
the particle itself is not invariant.
What about the velocity?
The velocity is just the time derivative of the position.
All right, so the velocity, which would just
be, let's call it dx prime by dt.
That's equal to dx by dt.
That's equal to dx by dt minus v.
So no, velocities are not invariant.
What you see is the velocity.
I see the velocity being diminished.
v could of course be negative.
I mean, there's nothing intrinsic about the sign of v.
But I see a velocity
which is shifted by amount v.
That's obvious, of course.
I'm moving along.
You shoot an arrow.
I see the arrow going slower than
you see the arrow going for obvious reasons.
What about acceleration?
So, first of all, position and velocity are
not relativistic invariants in Galileo's theory of relativity.
But let's differentiate again to get the acceleration.
dx prime.
Well, let's see.
By, let's put it here.
d second x prime by dt squared.
That's the acceleration that I see is equal to the
acceleration that you see minus the time derivative of v.
But v is a constant.
I am assuming that the relative velocity
between the two frames of reference is constant.
That's equivalent to saying that
these tilted lines are straight lines.
So, the acceleration, the difference
v doesn't make any difference.
The time derivative of a constant is zero.
And so acceleration is an invariant.
The acceleration that I see of an object.
Not my acceleration.
I'm not accelerating.
I'm in the caboose of the train.
I'm moving along with uniform velocity.
But I see objects moving back
and forth in front of me.
Moving to the left.
Moving to the right.
Sometimes they accelerate.
You see the same objects.
You also see them accelerate.
And we will agree about the acceleration.
So, acceleration is an invariant.
Now, I shouldn't, I'm not sure
which is cause and effect here, really.
But let's say it this way.
The fact that acceleration is itself an invariant is a strong
suggestion that the laws of physics should be in terms of acceleration.
Not velocity.
Not position.
But the law of physics, the laws of motion, if they are to be
invariant, if they are to be invariant, the laws of physics should involve acceleration.
Since we all agree on the acceleration.
Well, of course, that's exactly
what F equals M A says.
Force is equal to mass times acceleration.
Acceleration, we all agree about acceleration.
Well, let's analyze this a little more closely.
Supposing we're talking about two objects
which exert forces on each other.
And for the moment, everything is
taking place along the X axis.
We usually imagine, correctly for most cases, that the force
between two objects only depends on the distance between them.
Alright?
Only depends on the distance between them.
The force between two objects, gravitational force, electrostatic
force, only depends on the distance between them.
The coordinates of the
particles themselves are not invariant.
But the distance between them is invariant.
That's what we, well, where did we write it?
Up on the top here.
Everybody agrees about the distance.
So the distance is an invariant.
And if the force only depends on the distance, it
says that the force between two objects is an invariant.
Meaning to say that everybody agrees about it.
So if you, in your frame, were
to measure the force between two objects,
which are moving somehow,
and I, in my frame,
whizzing by it, measure the force,
according to Newton and Galileo, and everybody
who came after them, up to Einstein,
force is an invariant because the
distance between two objects is invariant.
That leaves only one more symbol in this equation, mass,
in order for Newton's theory to make any sense,
it was necessary that mass is an invariant.
If all the terms in the equation
are invariant, then so must be the mass.
And so, according to Newton, every object has
a mass, and everybody agrees about that mass.
There's no discrepancy because some object is moving.
About a one kilogram object is a one kilogram object.
Even if it's moving past you on a railroad train.
So, Newton's law of motion
is invariant, here's the language,
Newton's law of motion is
invariant under Galilean coordinate transformations.
There's a Galilean coordinate transformation, and Newton's
laws of motion are invariant under it.
The idea of relativity is that
all the laws of motion are invariant.
All the laws of nature, whatever they happen to be,
are invariant under the appropriate
analog of the Galilean transformation.
Now, the problem is that that clashed with electromagnetism.
At the moment, we
haven't learned anything about electromagnetism,
but you all know that
electromagnetic waves are called light,
and that light moves with a certain velocity.
Maxwell's equations predict what that velocity is,
and if you think of Maxwell's equations as
laws of physics that everybody should agree on,
then the speed of light
must be the same for everybody.
That's really all there was to it.
Einstein really used no more than that.
Of course, he was guessing.
He was guessing that Maxwell's equations
were the same in every reference frame.
In other words, he was guessing that Maxwell's equations,
which were laws of nature, which were so compelling
that they would have to be
the same in every reference frame.
And that, of course, led to a big problem.
It led to the problem of the speed of light,
that if Maxwell's equations are
the same in all reference frames,
then the speed of light is
the same in all reference frames.
But how can the speed of light
be the same in all reference frames
if one frame is moving relative to the other?
We could work it out.
We could work it out using Galilean relativity.
Let's take a light ray.
A light ray, a little blip, a
little blip of a light ray moving along.
It moves along with x.
x equals c times t.
That's what the, where c is the speed of light.
Okay?
That's what Maxwell's equations said.
Well, Galileo would then have had to say,
let's ask how that light ray appears to move
from the point of view of the moving reference frame.
And that would be x prime,
which is equal to x minus vt,
so far this is just
the Galilean representation of the transformation.
That is equal to ct,
x is equal to ct, minus vt.
And he would have just said,
well, that's the same thing as saying c minus vt.
So Galileo would have had no choice but to say,
in the moving reference frame,
the speed of light differs from the speed of light
in the stationary reference frame
by the relative velocity.
Okay?
That, of course, made good intuitive sense.
It is the way sound would work.
It is the way water waves would work.
If water waves move,
what's a typical velocity of a water wave?
I don't know.
A couple of meters a second or something like that?
How much?
A few for small ones.
Yeah, yeah.
Meters per second.
Let's say one meter per second.
But I'm flying over at
a half a meter per second,
when I'm flying over the wave,
then I see the wave moving
at a half a meter per second.
So it's completely unreasonable
to expect that water waves
have a universal velocity
that all observers see.
Now most physicists, of course,
at the turn of the, or
at the end of the 19th century,
simply came to the conclusion
that, well,
in the 1850s, 1860s,
when Maxwell was active,
simply came to the conclusion
that some frames of reference
are better than other frames of reference.
That there is no relativity.
That there exists a frame of reference,
God's frame of reference.
Don't tell the ombudsman I said that.
Or do tell the ombudsman.
God's frame of reference
where Maxwell's equations are correct.
In other frames of reference,
Maxwell's equations must be somewhat different,
because in other frames of reference,
obviously light moves with a different velocity.
And so, as you well know,
various physicists tried to study
the dependence of the velocity of light
on the state of motion of water.
They found no dependence.
We won't go through the various experiments.
Several different kinds of experiments
to try to detect the fact
that a moving observer
would see a speed of light
which would depend on the state of motion.
And as you know,
no such effect was ever discovered.
The result being
that physicists had no choice
but to go and review
the motion of the water.
And so,
they were not going to go to space,
but to go and review
the basic ideas that went into this definition.
Now, Einstein himself claimed
he never even knew about the experiments.
I'm inclined to believe him.
I mean, you know,
they didn't call Einstein Einstein for nothing.
I mean, he...
So, I think we give him credit.
He said when he was 16 years old,
he thought about moving along with a light wave.
The light wave didn't
oscillate, didn't move, didn't do anything,
just looked frozen.
And he somehow knew enough to know
that Maxwell's equations
were inconsistent with that.
And his choice
was to believe that Maxwell's equations
were basic laws of nature.
Basic laws of nature
which should be the same in every reference frame.
So,
something was wrong,
and he had to go back to some very, very
first principles.
In fact, the very first principles
which this
lattice
represents.
The idea of
coordinates, the idea of
times, the distinct
times and so forth, and went back
and said, let me begin
all over again with
one assumption, well, two assumptions.
The first assumption
is the principle of relativity.
Namely,
that in every frame of reference the laws
of physics are identical.
The second assumption
is that in every frame of
reference the speed of light is
always the same. Let me take
those as postulates
and see what I can derive.
The first thing he derived
was something
that is implicit in this
diagram, which
I partly spelled out, partly didn't spell
out, but let me spell it out now.
That if
two events
are simultaneous
as seen in one reference frame,
they will be simultaneous
in every reference frame.
It's exactly the statement that T prime
equals T. If two
events occur at the same time in
one reference frame, they occur
at the same time in any
reference frame.
Einstein realized very quickly
that he could not maintain that.
And here's roughly the way he thought about it.
He said, let's go
way back to the beginning
and even start
with the whole idea of synchronizing
clocks.
We can lay out our meter sticks.
It's clear enough what we can
do. We can lay out our
meter sticks.
We lay out our meter sticks on the ground.
But now you have your clock, you have
your clock, you have your clock, you have your clock
over there. And you want to
synchronize your clocks. Make sure they all read
the same at the same instant of time.
What does that mean?
Well, there's various ways you could
try to check whether your clocks were
synchronized. But Einstein
decided to use light.
He wanted to use light
for the obvious reason that
his basic postulate
was about light.
So he wanted to use light
to synchronize clocks.
So here's the way he
synchronized clocks. He said, let's see.
Put somebody in the middle.
Now what does the middle mean? Let's take you
and you. You're the two endpoints.
What does it mean to say somebody in the middle?
Well, you can measure with
meter sticks the person in the middle
and adjust with the meter sticks
until that person in the middle
is exactly halfway between you.
Now, at
exactly noon
you're going to emit a flash bulb.
You're going to light up a flash bulb
and the light
signal is going to go, well it can go
out all around you, but in particular it's going
to go from your position
out in that direction.
You'll do exactly the same thing.
When your clock is also at time
t equals zero
t equals zero? Did I say zero?
Or noon? Whatever.
At noon, you will also
send out a flash signal.
If the person who is in the middle
sees the flashes
simultaneously,
in other words, if the
left flash and the right flash
go right by him simultaneously,
then we will agree
that your clocks are synchronized.
If he sees your light,
your flash, before
your flash, then he says
you better readjust your clock a little bit,
go back, try it again,
set your clock back a little bit,
and keep doing it until
the person in the middle
sees the
flashes of light instantaneously
the same. Now, everybody
in the room does the same thing with respect to
everybody else until
everybody's clocks are synchronized
by the same
by exactly the same definition.
That somebody halfway between them
will see flashes of light
emitted
at the same time
will see those flashes
of light at the same time.
Okay, then Einstein realized
there's a problem. That much
is okay. That much is okay.
We can synchronize all of your clocks.
But now, what about me moving
past you?
Or, you know, let's
have me moving past you,
and
let's see how this should work.
I have my
coordinate frame laid out,
and
I move past you,
I look at your light ray,
but because I'm moving,
by the time your light
ray gets to me,
it has had to go further
than your light ray did. So it's quite obvious
that I'm going to see your light ray before
I see your light ray, even if you emitted
them at exactly the same time.
Even if you emitted them at exactly the
same time, according to all
of your reckoning, I,
who happen to be moving
this way, will
reckon your light ray
as being emitted
later, because
I see it later, because
it has a greater distance to go.
So Einstein realized that the
idea of simultaneity
was a relative idea,
that if everybody synchronizes
their clocks by the means of
light, by means of light,
there will be a discrepancy
in what, in different frames
of reference, is counted
as simultaneous.
I want to work
that out. I want to work that out in detail,
just using light,
how
does simultaneity
break down?
Another way to ask it is if
these two points are
counted in the stationary reference
frame as having the same time,
which two points in the
moving reference frame
will be said to have exactly the
same time? That's something I want to work
out next. We'll take five minutes and work
that out in detail, and that'll give
us the Lorentz transformations.
Lorentz transformations which
implicitly
have in them that simultaneity
is a relative concept.
So that will be our next
challenge, to replace
this equation
by one that's consistent
with the idea that light travels
with the same velocity in all frames.
What if I synchronize
the clocks using sound?
Using what? Sound.
Suppose I just yell it, have two people yell.
Then you will find
then you will find
that the law that says
that the speed of sound is
what is it, about a thousand feet per
second, that that's
not a law at all, and
that moving observers
do detect different velocities
of sound.
If you do it
at rest, in a frame of reference
where the air is at rest,
that's a perfectly good way to
synchronize clocks.
But then
somebody moving
you'll do all these things,
and you'll discover in the end that it's
not consistent to say that the speed
of sound is the same in every reference frame.
What we're going to be using, we're going to use
the idea that light is the same,
there's nothing wrong with synchronizing clocks that way.
Nothing at all.
You wouldn't want to do it though,
you wouldn't want to synchronize
clocks on a moving train
if
the train was an open
air train, and the
and you get
the point. If it was an open air train
and the atmosphere
was at rest, and you
were moving through the atmosphere,
that would be a bad way to synchronize
your clocks.
Hmm?
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly. So,
Einstein said he doesn't care, he is going
to simply assume the speed of
light is the same and see where it takes him.
See where it leads.
Does it lead to something consistent?
Alright, so as I said, his first
observation was there's something wrong with
the idea that
simultaneity is universal.
Or that the simultaneity
of two events is an
invariant. So here's how
he began. Here's, I actually don't
know how he began, this is the way I begin.
Um,
it's been too long since I've read
his paper. Let's, again we
begin with a drawing.
And now we have
two,
this is the rest frame,
and we have
two
points
laid out a distance L
apart. This distance
is L, and this distance
is L. L stands for length now.
It could be one meter, but
let's keep it general.
Distance L is measured off,
another distance L is measured off,
and here
are the
trajectories of
the points which correspond
to, uh, to being
L units apart.
This could be your seat,
and that could be your seat.
And the one in the middle, since it's
equally distant between the two of them,
is the person who happens to be vacant
but is sitting in the
middle between the two of you.
Okay, so that's the first setup now.
Now,
if the clocks are synchronized,
what does that mean exactly?
It means that
if at time t equals zero,
both observers at the two ends
here send out a light
signal, the light signal,
the light signals will
intersect
at the same place, like this.
Oops,
I missed.
That a light signal from this side,
if it's sent out at the same
instant, in other words,
synchronous in this frame of reference,
with a light signal
that's sent out from this instant,
that the two light signals will cross
the intermediate observer here at exactly
the same time.
Now, light moves, of course, very fast.
That means
that this drawing is
a bit, um,
well, that's a little
funny, because light moving
so fast, it would mean that light rays
are practically horizontal.
They move an enormous distance
in a short amount of time.
But we can fix that. We can fix that
by working in units in which the
speed of light is equal to one.
Let's do that. Later on,
we'll put back the speed of
light, but for the moment,
let's set the speed of light equal to one.
How do you do that?
You work in units
of space, which are
adjusted the right way,
so that in one second of time,
light goes
one unit of distance.
A light second.
Or years in light years,
or whatever
you like.
And so the vertical axis and the horizontal
axis here
are measured in
units in which the speed
of light is equal to one.
If the speed of light is equal
to one, then a light ray
satisfies x
equals t,
not ct,
but just t,
and that would be a 45 degree line.
That's a light ray moving to the right.
A light ray moving to the right
satisfies
a light ray
moving to the right from the origin over
here, satisfies
x equals t.
What if it's a light ray moving to the right
from some other position?
Well, then it satisfies
x
equals t plus
some constant,
namely the offset.
So if it's a light ray, any light ray
moving to the right
satisfies x equals t
plus something.
c equals what?
d.
Thank you.
d. And what about a light ray
moving to the left?
That's x
equals minus t,
or minus
t plus some other constant,
plus d prime, I don't know.
So these are
the motions of light rays,
and they correspond to 45
degree angles.
45 degree angles, a slope of
one. A slope of one
corresponds to a velocity
of the speed of light.
Things moving slower than the speed of light
move
more toward the vertical.
If it made sense to think about
things moving faster than the speed of light,
which it doesn't, they would be moving
on trajectories which were more horizontal.
So,
these two
clocks are
synchronized
because
if at the same instant of time,
or another way of saying it,
is these two points here
must be at the same instant of time
in this reference frame,
in this stationary reference frame,
because the light rays
will intersect the intermediate
observer here right at the same
instant of time. Now let's draw
in a second observer.
A second observer, in other words,
a second reference frame,
and the second reference frame is moving
supposed to be
a straight line, and it's moving
with a motion
x equals vt.
v is
now the velocity of the moving
observer, and this curve here
is now x equals vt.
So, from your perspective,
I'm moving along
with velocity v.
So you watch me, and you say
at each instant of time,
my position moves,
and it moves with a velocity v.
This is incidentally
the definition of velocity.
This is the definition of the velocity
that you see me
move with.
So,
this is moving along like here.
Let's draw
in some more lines.
Here's the, here's
a second,
I want to draw this good and parallel
to the first.
Does that look parallel?
Close enough. This one's also pretty
parallel.
Like that.
Okay.
What do we
want to do next?
Ah.
Okay.
Now let's look at the moving frame of reference.
Again,
this guy is
halfway between these two.
He started out over here
They're moving with uniform velocity.
He stays halfway between these two.
But, notice
that at his location,
the two light rays
are moving
at the same time.
The two light rays
do not arrive
at his position at the same time.
At his location,
one of the light rays arrives
much later than the other one.
So, according to this moving observer,
he must conclude
that these two points
were not synchronous.
The light rays emitted from here and here
could not have been synchronous
from his point of view,
because from his point of view,
they should have arrived
at the intermediate position
at the same time.
In fact, he can reverse the logic.
He can say,
where along this light ray
does it correspond
Let's see.
How to say this right?
Yeah.
Let's forget this light ray
for a minute.
And let's follow this one
until it actually hits
the light ray.
The observer.
This is the person in the middle.
Where would a light ray
have to come from
along this trajectory
in order
that the guy in the middle here
would conclude that the two light rays
were emitted simultaneously?
It's easy.
Just trace a backward light ray,
also at 45 degrees,
to that point.
Trace a light ray
backward along 45 degrees
to a point over here.
And now in the moving frame
of reference,
if a light ray is emitted over here,
and a light ray is emitted over here,
this is a bit of an exaggeration.
I think this line is too shallow.
Let's go back a little more.
It hit exactly the same place.
Yeah.
Um.
If a light ray
were emitted from here
to the left,
and a light ray were emitted from here
to the right,
they would hit the central observer over here
at exactly the same time.
So the moving observer
will conclude that this point
and this point are synchronous.
Whereas the stationary observer
concludes
that this point and this point
are synchronous.
It's obvious from the beginning
that it will not be
the same in the two frames.
But can we do it quantitatively?
Can we really figure out quantitatively
exactly where this point lies?
And can we figure out all the points
that the moving observer
will call synchronous
with the origin over here?
And that's not too hard.
It just requires a little bit of
simple algebra.
So a little bit of geometry and algebra.
Let's work it out.
The first thing to do
is to make some simple equations
for all the lines
that are drawn here.
We need some simple
We want to be quantitative.
I want to write some equations
for the various lines.
This line is x equal vt.
What is this line over here?
This line is x
Let's write it in.
x equals vt
plus l.
Why?
Because it's shifted over by distance l.
So for
its x
is vt plus l.
This is x means
from the stationary reference frame.
The stationary reference frame
sees the black lines
shifted up
by distance l.
So it's x equals vt plus l.
What about this one?
vt plus 2l.
That's x equals vt plus 2l.
We want to locate this point.
The object is to locate this point
right over here.
Why?
Because it's the one that the moving observer says
is synchronous with the origin.
So we'd like to find out where it is.
What's the equation for this line?
謝謝
x equals t
that equation is x equals t
let's first locate this point
this point is at the intersection
of two lines that we know
one of them is x equals t
and the other is x equals vt plus l
let's write those two equations
and find out where those two lines intersect
so one of them is just x equals t
and the other one is x equals vt
plus l
alright that's easy
wherever you see x put t
and we get t
equals vt
plus l
or
one minus v
times t
equals l
one more step
t
equals l divided by one minus
v do i have that right
let's check it
yes
that's this point right over here
it occurs in the rest frame at a time
which is v which is l divided by one
minus v what about x what about the x of
that point
that's equal to t
all along this line
the same thing
x equals l over one minus v
that's this point over here
let's call it point capital a
this is point capital a
now now that we know where point capital a is
let's see if we can trace a line backward
until it hits here and
figure out where this point is
that's our goal to find out where this point is
all right what about this line
what do we know about this line
we know about this line
that it's a backward going light ray
so it's of the form x
minus t is equal to a constant
oh sorry x equals minus t plus a constant
the backward going light ray
is x equals minus t plus something
let me just give that something i don't want to
call it d prime i'm going to call it b
or another way to write it
is that x plus t
equals b
we don't know what b is yet
how am i going to find b
this is x plus t equals b
how will i find b
anybody got an idea
yeah it's the same it's twice x
in point a
right
what we do is we use the
fact that this line goes through this point
this line goes through this point
at this point x and t are equal
and what are they equal to
they're equal to l over one minus v
so at this point over here
x plus t is just twice l
divided by one minus v
and that's equal to b
so we found b
we found out what the
this b is
that goes into this equation
for this backward moving light ray over here
alright let's write it down
x plus t
is equal to two l
divided by one minus v
so now i know
this line
but i want to find its intersection
with this one
so i'll write right underneath this equation
i'll write the equation for this line
that's x equals v plus two l
ありがとうございました
Alright, I now have two equations that
tell me where the intersection point is.
Let's see, should we solve them?
A little bit of a nuisance
to solve them, but let's do it.
Okay, no, it's not hard at all.
Let's subtract the two equations.
That will get rid of x for us.
If I subtract the two equations,
that will get rid of x.
That will give me, on the left here, t.
And on the right-hand side, I will
have equals 2l over 1 minus v,
minus, looks like we're doing this right,
minus vt.
Minus 2l?
Oh, no, plus 2l.
No, minus 2l.
Minus 2l.
All right, let's move all the
t stuff over to the left.
That gives us t times 1 minus v equals...
1 plus v.
Equals 2l.
Both these terms have 2l in them.
And then one of them
has 1 over 1 minus v.
And the other one just has minus 1.
All right.
2l is common to both of them.
It's out here.
And it's just l over, sorry, it's
just 1 over 1 minus v minus 1.
Okay, what's 1 over 1 minus v minus 1?
It's just v over 1.
Just v over 1 minus v.
1 over 1 minus v.
Yeah.
Right.
1 over 1 minus v minus
1 minus v over 1 minus v.
If 1 minus 1 cancels,
v over 1 minus v, right?
v over 1 minus v.
And finally, I have now located what t is.
t is 2l times v divided by 1 minus v.
1 minus v times 1 plus v.
1 minus v times 1 plus
v is just 1 minus v squared.
So, first of all, I found t is
equal to 2l v over 1 minus v squared.
That's the time of this point over here.
t.
What about its x?
Well, that's easy to find.
We can find it from two ways.
We can either find it by plugging into
this line or by plugging into this line.
Which one is simpler?
Let's see.
It looks to me like it's
easier to plug into this one.
Okay.
So, let's plug into this one.
That says that x is equal to 2l divided by 1
minus v minus t minus 2l v over 1 minus v squared.
Anybody do that in their head?
No.
2l v plus 2l v unit.
2l v times 2l.
I think we better do it.
We better multiply top and bottom by 1
plus v so that we have the same denominator.
So, let's multiply by 1
plus, well, let's do it separately.
2l times 1 plus v
divided by 1 minus v squared.
Minus 2l v.
It looks like to me like it's
just 2l divided by 1 minus v squared.
Alright.
So, it's x equals 2l over 1 minus v squared.
Now, I'm actually not so
interested in either t or x.
What I'm interested in is the slope of this line.
I'm interested in the slope of this line.
I'm interested in the slope of this line,
which is the ratio of t to x.
I'm actually interested in what this line is.
I'm interested in this curve here.
This curve has the form x equals something times
t, but we can read off what it is now.
It's just the ratio of x to t.
What's the ratio of x to t?
The ratio of x to t is just v.
It's just v.
So, this curve is t equals vx.
Let's check that.
t equals vx.
Yes.
t has an extra factor
of v in it from x.
t equals v times x.
Well, that's kind of interesting.
We did this whole big construction, and what
we found out is that what the moving observer
calls c.
And, if it's synchronous, the
stationary observer calls t equals vx.
We can erase everything else.
Let's just keep track.
Here's the moving observer.
He moves with x equals vt.
That's his time axis.
x equals vt.
But the x axis is t equals vx.
Okay.
All these points along here are at the same
position from the point of view of the moving
observer.
All these points along here are at the same
time from the point of view of the moving
observer.
All these points are synchronous from the
moving observer's point of view, not from
the stationary point of view.
And, look, one of them says x equals vt.
The other says t equals vx.
Very symmetrically related to each other.
Very symmetrically related.
Let's just abstract from the whole thing
now what we've learned, because we've set
c equal to 1.
Okay?
So let's actually put some units into it.
Let's get the units right.
When you do a thing like you set c equal
to 1, then of course lengths and times have exactly
the same units, and velocities are dimensionless.
Okay?
Okay.
So if you have a velocity of 1
over time, if c is 1, velocities are dimensionless.
But let's try to get some dimensions
back into it and restore some correct dimensions
to it.
All we have to do is multiply by the appropriate
powers of the speed of light in order to get
the dimensions to be consistent.
This is already consistent.
X is equal to a velocity, which
is a length over time, times a time.
But this one does not look consistent.
What do we have to do
to it to make it consistent?
The answer is, I think, divide it
by the square of the speed of light.
When the speed of light is set equal
to 1, this curve is t equals vx.
There's a unique way to restore the c's so
that you get the same answer when c is equal
to 1, but so that dimensions are restored.
Let's check the dimensions.
This is a time.
We have a time.
Equals.
Now a velocity is a length over a time.
An x is a length.
And in the denominator, we have
a length squared over a time squared.
So let's see.
That is, in fact, dimensionally correct.
Yeah.
A c in the denominator, a c
squared in the denominator, restores the dimensions.
So if we include the speed
of light, that would be the formula.
In fact, including the speed
of light, you see something interesting.
You see that when the speed of light is
very, very large, the slope of this line is very
very small.
t equals v times x
divided by an enormously big number.
All right.
Speed of light squared in metric units
is 10 to the 17th or something.
So this is an enormously big number downstairs.
And that says that this
is a very, very shallow line.
So shallow that for most practical purposes,
simultaneity really is the same in all reference
systems.
But when things are moving with anything like
the speed of light, we have to account for
these discrepancies.
And so but if we set the speed of light
equal to 1, then the diagram has a lovely symmetry.
The slope of this line relative to the horizontal
is the same as the slope of this line relative
to the vertical.
So let's redraw it.
Let's just abstract out of it.
We have your coordinates x and t.
And we have my coordinates t prime and x prime.
A light signal, let's put a light signal in there.
A light signal moving to
the right is at 45 degrees.
And a light signal moving to
the left is at 135 degrees.
So you see what's happened.
The...
The new coordinates are sort of
symmetric relative to the light ray here.
But the surface, which is the surface
of simultaneity, let's give it a name.
This is the surface of
simultaneity in the moving reference frame.
The set of points that the moving observer says
are all at the same time are tilted relative
to the surface of simultaneity in the rest frame.
And they're tilted.
It's not a good thing.
They're tilted exactly the same way that
the axis, that the time axis is tilted.
So it's a very simple construction.
Now, from this construction, we can make some guesses.
Not guesses.
We can actually derive the
form of the Lorentz transformations.
Let's work out the Lorentz transformations.
We know a good deal about the relation
between xt and x prime and t prime.
We know a good deal, but we don't know everything.
So we need some more input.
Let's go back to Galileo.
Galileo said x prime is equal to x minus vt.
vt.
All this says...
All this...
All this says is that when x is
equal to vt, x prime is equal to 0.
But that should be true.
That should continue to be true.
It should continue to be true that
as far as you're concerned, my position satisfies
x equals vt.
So when x is equal to vt,
you're talking about my origin of coordinates.
So it must still be true.
Not that x prime is equal to x minus vt.
But that when x is equal
to vt, x prime must be 0.
My center of coordinates is
what you call x equals vt.
That continues to be true.
That's just a statement that
this line is x equals vt.
And this line, of course,
is also x prime equals 0.
It's also x prime equals 0.
It's the center of coordinates
of the moving primed observer.
So this equation may be wrong, but it must
be correct that when x equals vt, x prime is
equal to 0.
How could this be wrong but still be true that
when x is equal to vt, x prime is equal
to 0?
There's only one way.
That there could be some factor in here.
Let's call it f.
And that factor could depend on velocity.
That's a possibility.
This is still clear.
It's still possible.
It's still consistent with the statement that when
x is equal to vt, x prime is equal
to 0.
But it's not quite the same as saying
x prime is equal to x minus vt.
It's a little different than what Galileo
would have written, depending on what f of
v is here.
So this is about all you can do
with the equation, with Galileo's first equation, that still
allows x prime to be 0
when x is equal to vt.
To have some numerical...
So you can have a numerical multiple there.
And that numerical multiple could,
in principle, depend on the velocity.
And as I said, all this is telling us here
is that x equals vt is the same as x prime
equals 0.
Now let's look at this second curve.
The second curve over here is t prime equals 0.
Why is it t prime equals 0?
Because all along the line, there's a constant.
All along this curve here, the primed observer,
the moving observer, says that the time is
the same.
All right?
If we just choose it at this point to be
0 here, then t prime is equal to 0 all along
this curve.
So what it says, whatever the equation for t
prime is, it must have the form t minus
vx.
And, see, when t equals vx we're still good right?
Nothing bad.
All right?
If we explain that, what we do
is that t is equal to vt.
To have a normal vector, that's what we do.
So we simply dried up all the balancЕТhe solarي
But here we have the Kayla Fisher.
And finally, every night that we work our
way up even real high income indexes actions are
like the kier portableinking effect.
So if we living under a loop with 0 and
we're going to us and we're going to move, we're
going to be prepared for a very difficult, but then
And I'm going to explain one of the
things about taking the Caraway Ecosyаль following one and
And this is the axis
T prime is equal to zero.
So Einstein wrote this down.
But one more step.
This is not quite enough because we don't
know what this F and this G are.
They could be anything.
These two equations here tell us
about the tilt of these axes,
but they don't tell us what F and G are.
We need one more step.
I'll tell you what the one more step is.
The one more step is that whatever the
equations that you use to convey to me information
should be essentially exactly the same as the equations
I would use to convey information back to you,
with one exception, the sign of the velocity.
The sign of the velocity.
In other words,
in other words,
if we were to solve
these equations for X and T,
in terms of X prime and T prime,
the equations should have exactly the same form,
except the sign of the velocity should change.
So let's do that.
Let's solve these equations for X and T,
in terms of X prime and T prime.
This is the inverse relation.
If this is what the moving coordinates are,
in terms of the stationary coordinates,
then if we solve it,
for X and T,
we'll know what the stationary coordinates
are in terms of the moving coordinates.
And the pattern should be essentially exactly the same.
If you see me moving with velocity V,
then I see you moving in
the opposite direction with velocity V,
and the only difference in the relationship
would be the sign of the velocity.
Alright, so I'm going to solve these equations.
Let's see, this is a nuisance.
It's very straightforward, but let's do it anyway.
Ah, no, let's prove something first.
Let's first prove that F and
G have to be the same.
Why do F and G have to be the same?
That is the statement that everybody
agrees about the speed of light.
In other words, if one observer
calls this line X equals T,
the other observer must call
it X prime equals T prime.
If one observer says the speed of light is one,
that means X equals T,
the other observer must also say
that the speed of light is one.
That was Einstein's basic principle that we
all agree about the speed of light.
If a light ray satisfies X equals T,
it must also satisfy X prime equals T prime.
Let's see if we can see what that says.
If X equals T along a light ray,
then X prime here is just equal to
T times 1 minus V over F of V.
I've just used that X is equal to T.
On the other hand, T prime is equal to
T times 1 minus V over G of V.
I've again just used that X is
equal to T along a light ray.
So along the light ray,
X prime is given by this,
T prime is given by this,
but it must also be true
that X prime must equal T prime.
Otherwise, the speed of light would not
be the same in the two frames.
Well, if X prime must be equal to T prime,
it means F and G
have to be the same function.
No change.
No choice about it.
So Einstein's assumption that the speed of
light is the same in all reference frames
required that F and G are the same.
So we've learned a little more.
Again, we've used the idea of simultaneity
as being defined by light rays
coming from the left and the right
and hooking up at the same instant
of time for the observer halfway in between.
That told us what this curve was.
And now we've used the statement that the speed
of light is the same in all reference frames.
In other words, if X equals T along here,
then X prime must equal T prime,
and that tells us that this
function is the same as this function.
Not quite everything we need to know.
We still don't know what F is.
G F of E in the denominator.
F of V in the denominator. Good.
And F is just some unknown function of V
that maybe we'll find some reason
to set equal to something particular.
There must be some rule
which tells us what it is.
Alright, let's now solve for X and T
in terms of X prime and T prime.
Let's just solve these relationships.
Uh, okay, let's just, let's do it.
Let me multiply this by F of V.
F of V times X prime
is equal to X minus V T.
And F of V times T prime
is equal to T minus V X.
Alright, let's see, what's, uh, what
should we do with these two?
I want to solve for X
in terms of the prime variables.
So let's solve for X
And the best way to do that
is to divide this equation by V.
Uh, let's see, uh, V, no,
let's multiply this equation by V here.
Why did I do that?
I did that so that if I just
subtract them, I'll get rid of the V T,
and I'll have an equation for X.
Okay, let's see what it says.
Um, just, uh, add them, add them.
So I get X times 1
minus V squared on the right.
The V T's cancel.
And that's equal to, um,
um,
F of V X prime plus
V F of V T prime.
Let's, let me just, uh, write that a little nicer.
F of V times, I think it was just, um,
X prime plus V T.
X prime plus V T prime.
And now divide it by 1 minus V squared.
That's the equation for X.
There's another equation for T, which is very similar.
The equation for T looks very similar.
It looks like F of V
divided by 1 minus V squared
times
T prime plus V X prime.
That's the inverse relationship.
If you go from X to T, X
to X prime through one set of equations,
then the way that you go back is with the,
this set of equations.
Well, you would expect if there is
nice symmetry between the two frames of reference,
that the two sets of equations
should look very parallel to each other.
In fact, X and T should be
related to X prime and T prime
in exactly the same way that X prime
and T prime are related to X and T,
with one exception.
With the exception that the sign
of the velocity should be opposite.
Well, that doesn't look so bad.
Here we have X prime is
X minus V T times something.
Here we have X is equal
to X prime plus V T prime.
Plus V T prime times something.
If the somethings were the same,
if F of V over 1 minus V
squared were the same as 1 over V,
the relationship would be completely reciprocal.
The relationship would be completely reciprocal.
Same here.
The relation between the primed and unprimed variables,
when you invert it,
simply involves changing the sign of the velocity
from T minus V X
to T prime plus V X.
That would be true if
F of V divided by 1 minus V squared
is the same as 1 over F of V.
So far I haven't told
you what F of V is.
Now I'm telling you.
It's the thing which satisfies this equation.
Or another way to write it
is that F of V
is equal to the square
root of 1 minus V squared.
Multiply by F of V on both sides.
That squares this.
Multiply by 1 minus V squared.
1 minus V squared.
And take the square root.
What was this? What did I do?
What I did was simply to make sure
that the relation between
the primed and the unprimed coordinates
were reciprocal.
That if the unprimed observer
tells the primed observer
that his coordinates are related,
that the coordinates are related in a certain way,
the inverse relationship
should be of exactly the same form,
except with the velocity having the opposite sign.
All that says is if you
see me move with velocity V,
I see you move with velocity minus V.
So now we have the complete set of relationships
between the coordinates of a point of space-time
in one frame and the coordinates in another frame.
And here they are.
X prime is equal to X minus VT
divided by square root of 1 minus V squared.
And T prime is equal to
T minus VX.
Over square root of 1 minus V squared.
We can solve them.
I just did it,
but let me write down what the solution is.
I'm solving it meaning to relate,
to write the equations for T and X
instead of X prime and T prime.
The inverse relations are
X is equal to X prime plus VT prime
divided by square root of 1 minus V squared.
And T is equal to T prime plus VT prime.
And T is equal to
T prime plus V X prime
over square root of 1 minus V squared.
Why does 1 have a plus V
and the other have a minus V?
For exactly the reasons that I said.
One velocity is the opposite of the other.
You see me with one velocity,
I see you with the other velocity.
These are the relationships
between the coordinates of two reference frames
to ensure that everybody see the same velocity of light
that light has the same velocity to everybody
and that the relationships
between coordinates are reciprocal
you know what I mean by reciprocal?
that they have the same form no matter which
way you go from one side to the other
and they're quite unique
that's uh...
that's it and the new
thing here the new bizarre thing
is that time is not just time
that what's synchronous in one frame of
reference in other words t equals a constant
is not the same as t prime equals a constant
that's the new thing that synchronicity is
not the same in both reference frames
now I've left out the speed of light by
now I should put back the speed of light
c not equal to one
and all we have to do then is to um...
put c in
to make the equations have dimensionality
and dimensional consistency
x and vt have the same dimensions
and in fact they have
the same dimensions as x prime
x prime
x and vt all have the same dimensions
well the only thing that's out of kilter here
is that velocity does not
have the same dimensions as one
you cannot subtract the thing with one set
of dimensions from a thing with another set of
dimensions
one has no dimensions it's dimensionless
velocity is length over time
all we have to do to fix
this is divide v squared by c squared
one minus v squared over c squared
if c is set equal to one
then it just reproduces the original answer
if c is not equal to one it's dimensionally consistent
what about this equation here though
this one is a little bit tougher
ah...
T and Vx do not have the same units.
T prime and T have the same units,
but Vx does not have the units of time.
We have to divide this by the square of the speed
of light, c squared, and again put c squared down here.
So it's T minus V over c squared x,
divided by square root of 1
minus V squared over c squared.
Now it's interesting to look at it.
What happens when the speed of light gets huge?
The speed of light in ordinary units is huge.
That means that this is negligible in the usual situations.
Usual situations where the speed of light is 10 to the
8th, or 3 times 10 to the 8th meters per second,
the square of the speed of light is
3 times 3 is 9, 10 to the 17th.
This is a huge number in the denominator.
So for almost all circumstances, this is negligible.
Also, V squared over c squared is also negligible.
The velocity of an ordinary object is
very much smaller than the speed of light.
So this practically reads T prime
is equal to T, Galileo's equation.
It only begins to fail when the
velocity gets up near the speed of light.
So only when the speed of
light is near the speed of light,
the relative velocities of the observers
are near the speed of light,
does this differ appreciably from
Galileo's T prime equals T.
Same thing here.
When the velocity is much smaller
than c, you can ignore this.
And it's just good old x
prime is equal to x minus VT.
It's only when velocities are near the speed of light
that the corrections from relativity become important.
But they're especially important for light, which
does move with the speed of light.
Yeah, let's see if we can see from these equations,
just directly,
that a light ray moves with
the same velocity in either reference frame.
Well, we already did it,
but let's just do it again.
Yeah, let's do it again.
Yeah.
If x is equal to T, a light
ray, a light ray satisfies x equals T.
If x equals T, this just
becomes 1 minus V times T
divided by square root of 1
minus V squared over c squared.
That's x prime.
What about T prime?
T prime.
Again, x is equal to T.
T prime is T minus,
I think I'm making a mistake.
I can't both have x equal T and
have the speed of light not equal to 1.
I think I want x equals cT here.
Yeah, x equals cT.
So this is c minus V.
c minus VT over the square root
of 1 minus V squared over c.
c squared.
And this is T prime.
T prime is equal to T minus V
over c squared times x, which is cT.
So that's cT divided by square root,
which is equal to T times 1
minus V over c divided by square root.
All right, so x prime.
Is this.
T prime is this.
What is x prime over T prime?
Oh God, I hope it works out.
No, it should be c.
It should be c.
Let's multiply and divide by c here.
c minus V over c.
Okay, yeah, it is.
c minus V times T over
square root of 1 minus V squared.
But we have an extra factor of c.
It's going to be downstairs.
So c prime or x prime is equal
to cT prime whenever x is equal to cT.
Magic.
The speed of light is the same
in all reference frames with this transformation.
Um.
The end product here is the important thing.
You can now test this out.
Oh, what about, okay.
If x equals cT, we've just proved
that x prime is equal to cT prime.
A little exercise is to show
that if x equals minus cT,
that's going to be minus cT.
So I'm going to use a little bit of a
little bit of a
little bit of a little decrease here,
it's a less than b,
this is C prime.
The best recent added to the다una Difference Project
into what gives us minus it alive C polize
that x prime is equal to minus cT prime.
If z equals minus cT,
that's a light ray going in the other direction
that x prime is equal to minus cT prime.
That's something else you can check from this.
It's also true.
So that means a light ray going in either direction,
we'll move with the speed of
light in either of the two frames.
Okay.
What's special about these transformations,
namely,
that light moves.
moves with the same velocity in
either frame and the relationship between the
two sets of coordinates is reciprocal
has exactly the same form except with
the velocity having changed sign that's
what's special about them and these of
course are the Lorentz transformations these
were not the way that Lorentz
derived them in fact I don't even
know that Lorentz did derive them so that's
special relativity or at least the
portion of special relativity that has
to do with the XT coordinates I
think we're about finished now what I was
going to do which we will do next
time is to derive the contraction of lengths
the dilation of time and
some various special relativity effects
dilation of time being the most interesting one
and then we'll go on to the next slide
and then move on to more
about the kinematics of special relativity what
proper time is what momentum is what
energy is and so forth any questions
thus far about what we've done up to now
6 o'clock yeah any questions about the physics though
yeah
the Oprahörung all
with house
they can go
Fast dishes
guy over here let's talk about somebody
else who happens to pass through this
point over here he's moving but he sees
the two flashes of light at the same
instant of time right that's what
you're talking about but he's not midway
between the two observers he doesn't
satisfy the criterion that he's midway
between the two observers yeah right right
so there's no reason for him over
here to say these two flashes were at
the same instant he sees the light get
to him at the same instant but he's
not midway between them so he again he will
not call this point simultaneously this
is the point which is midway between
them and this is the test point for deciding
something
simultaneity from the moving frame
right right right right because after
all this one is further away from him
than that one right good this is a nice
this is a nice construction to go through
it's not very hard all you do is
you take X equals T which is the
light ray you say it passes through the point
X equals V T plus L
and you add the light ray and you add
the light ray and you add the light ray
and then work your way backward with
a backward light moving like a backward
light ray until it hits the point X equals
V T plus 2 L and that tells you
exactly where this point is it tells
you what counts as simultaneous in the
moving reference frame that's the key or
at least that's half the key that's half
the key to the Lorentz transformation the
other half is the statement that the
relationships between the two frames should
be simultaneous so this is a nice
and interesting picture and at this moment you can see
just a little something there
ok so I saw the average winter
it was not
x
and
we'll
move on to the next appreciated formula
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.