This program is brought to you by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.
The basic kinematics, the kinematics of the Hubble law,
kinematics of the expanding universe,
made one assumption which is motivated mostly by observation
that the universe is spatially flat.
Spatially flat means that space
at a given instant of time
is just ordinary Euclidean three-dimensional space.
But the space-time ratio is not the same.
Time itself is not ordinary Euclidean...
I shouldn't say Euclidean,
it's not ordinary Minkowski space.
Minkowski space, let's just compare the two.
Minkowski space, just to remind you,
is the space of special relativity,
space-time of special relativity.
And it has a metric or a proper time element
that's given by the sum
of four and three-dimensions of time,
which is a very important
element in the world of space-time.
It's a very important element in the world of space-time.
So that's what we're talking about here.
terms or the difference of four terms
dt squared
minus dx squared
and I'm going to put this in a bracket
minus dx squared plus dy squared
plus dz squared
Now this is the
term in the bracket
is a dead giveaway of course that space
is flat, it's just good old
Cartesian ordinary
Euclidean space
where the size
of a line element dxdydz
is just given by
Pythagoras' formula
three dimensional Pythagoras' formula
the new element
in
cosmology
and now when I say the new element in cosmology
first of all I should say
the new element in the general theory of relativity
is that the coefficients
here
which are
simply in this case one
minus one minus one minus one
first of all there are more of them
there can be things like dxdy
and dydt and so forth
but the coefficients
can depend on position
in space time
that means that the coefficients
are fields
and basically they are
the generalization of Newton's
gravity
well Newton didn't think in terms of fields
but we can think in terms of fields
that the generalization of
Newtonian fields of gravity
the coefficient functions
which go there
now
observationally
cosmology
appears
the universe that we can see
through telescopes
appears to be on the whole
I'll call it featureless
of course it has features
the features of galaxies, planets, stars
clusters, superclusters
but that's all small potatoes
that's all small stuff
on the scale of billions
of light years
certainly on the scale of billions
on the scale of several hundred
million light years
the universe is very featureless
just
the same everywhere
homogeneous is the word
homogeneous
it's isotropic
it means it looks the same in every direction
on such a large scale
and
this is
somewhat of a
slightly larger surprise
to cosmologists
incidentally the isotropy
and the homogeneity
has been with us
since the very beginning
of cosmology
the very beginning of cosmology
meaning post-Hubble cosmology
from 1910
to 1912
1930s or 1940s
or whenever
cosmology
modern cosmology started
it was always assumed
that space was homogeneous
not space-time
but space is homogeneous
and isotropic
and that was given a name
it was called the cosmological principle
and once it's a principle
it has to be right
and so therefore
it's not only a principle
we proved it
we proved it by calling it a principle
of course it's
of course it's never been mathematically proved
or never argued
from any basic theoretical
underlying principle
there is none
but remarkably
the more that we look out into space
the more we see that the principle
looks to be very very accurate
on the large enough scales
so
we can see that
there is a very large
homogeneity
and one additional fact
space looks flat
which means
that we were not so far off
by writing the x squared plus the y squared
plus the z squared
but while it looks flat
it also is expanding
so the picture you should have
roughly in the back of your head
is a
and the flat sheet of rubber
is being stretched at a certain rate
but it's
infinite, it's flat
now of course we don't
know the universe is really infinite
how well do we know
that the universe is either infinite
or flat, if it's perfectly flat
of course it's got to be infinite
if it goes on and on forever
if it's perfectly flat
unless there's some sort of walls out there
nobody thinks there's walls out there
it will go on and on forever and ever
so a flat universe
is also likely to be
an infinite universe
but of course we don't really know
that the universe is either infinite
or perfectly flat
we know it to the same degree
that if we go out
in the backyard or out in the football field
and measure
survey the geometry of the
football field
we could drive stakes into the football field
stretch
the
strings between the stakes
by stretching the strings
between the stakes as tightly
as possible we construct
straight lines
we can put several stakes in
and create triangles and measure
the angles of the triangles
and what we find of course to a very high
precision is that triangles
behave just like triangles in flat space
namely the sum of the angles
adds up to 180 degrees
what do we learn from that
we learn that if the earth is curved
the curvature is small
which is another way of saying
that if the earth is a finite
sphere it's a big sphere
much much bigger than the field
not the
when I use the word field
now I'm not talking about gravitational
field I'm talking about the field
that we surveyed
it's precisely
the same in cosmology
astronomers do a
kind of cosmic surveying
measuring triangles
a thing in the sky over there
that gives you an angle
you may have some reason to believe that you know
the distances involved
both to the objects
and also between the objects
assuming you do have some
good reason to believe those things
you are measuring
the properties of triangles
and
remarkably
those triangles
of course I'm simplifying the story a little bit
what you really measure
is a little bit less direct than that
but that will be
it effectively comes to that
we measure triangles
and we find the triangles behave
like Euclidean
flat triangles
in ordinary Euclidean space
so apparently
to a high precision
space itself is flat
but it's expanding
to make it expanding
all we have to do
is put into this equation
dt squared
just good old time
minus
a scale factor
a of t squared
that's squared
because everything in the equation is squared
the units
let's
as always
we'll take the speed of
light to be equal to one
and in that case
the units of time and the
units of space are the same
ah
the units
in this equation
are the squares of lengths
and so
if we take a to be a length
namely
the distance between
two particular points
as the points separate
and go apart
then we should also think of the x's
as not having any dimensions
there's two ways to think about it
you can either think that a has no dimensions
and the x's have dimensions of length
ah
the more conventional way to think about it
is the x's here
have no dimensions
they're simply labels of points
and when you say that the
distance between two points
or the separation between two points
is delta x
equals let's say five
that's not a statement
about how far apart they are
that's just a statement
of
well here's the way to think about it
again think about the expanding rubber sheet
we draw coordinates
in the expanding rubber sheet
and those coordinates
stretch and expand out
with the expansion
so that going from
x equals let's put it over here
zero to x equals one
over here
corresponds to different actual
physical separations
at different times
at an early time
the actual physical separation
in meters
between zero and one
might be some tiny tiny distance
late late in the universe
after the universe has expanded
many many times
the distance between zero and one
may be very large
that distance is characterized by
a of t
so the actual distance between points
if delta x were five
would be a times delta x
or five a
and a
since it varies with time
it must have some dynamics
there must be some equations
governing it
governing how a of t
expands with time
so
that's our goal
this morning
that's our goal this evening
to work out some of the equations
governing a
now
I should tell you right now
the general theory of relativity
allows curved space
when I say space
I don't mean space time
I mean space
it allows space to be curved
and as long as it's homogeneous
which means the same everywheres
there are three kinds of spaces
which are homogeneous
any one of which
could be
the right of the right
or the wrong of the right
and I have the right thing to write down here
as I said observationally
we're in luck
it looks like space is flat
so we don't have to write anything very complicated
the other two possibilities
are
that space is round
like the surface of the earth
it's a sphere
but of course it's not a two dimensional sphere
it's a three dimensional sphere
a sphere, ordinary sphere
incidentally let's get something about terminology
when one talks about
the earth
the whole earth, the body of the earth
the bulk of the earth, the rocks in the inside
the mathematical term is a ball
a ball means
the solid earth
the term sphere
refers to the boundary
refers to the surface of the earth
so a sphere
is a two dimensional surface
ok
let's
let's just talk about
a little bit what a sphere means
first a circle
a circle you can just think of
as the locus of points
x squared plus y squared
equals some kind of
radius squared
if r is one
then it's a unit circle
so this locus of points
which satisfy x squared plus y squared
equals r squared
is just a circle
and a circle is a one dimensional space
and mathematicians
would call it a one sphere
a one sphere
because it's one dimensional
what would you call the interior?
two ball
or a disc
the special case of two dimensions
it has a special name of its own
it's called a disc
but if we wanted to use the generalized
mathematical terminology
we would call it a ball
a two dimensional ball
is of course a circle
and it's a one sphere
alright so if we add a
z squared to this
then
we get
a two sphere
surface of the earth
or something like that
that's pretty easy to visualize
I can see
the surface of a sphere
in my head
I cannot seem to free myself
of the fact that
I'm in the third dimension
I cannot seem to see that sphere
without also seeing
what's outside the sphere
and what's inside the sphere
but I know that mathematically
the surface of the sphere
without regard to what's inside
or outside
is a mathematical space
that can stand by its own
and does not have to be embedded
in three dimensions
the reason we have such a damn hard time
seeing two dimensional space
without the inside and the outside
is evolutionary
we have been built and constructed
to recognize three dimensional space
and we have not been built and constructed
to be able to see directly
two dimensional space
without it being embedded
in the third dimension
but then we come to something
even worse
we come
this is a two sphere now
the surface is a two sphere
and the interior is a two sphere
and the interior is a three dimensional space
the ball
or the three dimensional ball
but then it gets worse
we can add another coordinate here
now
I can't even draw it for you
I can't draw it for you
but I can tell you
that what is this
this is the locus of all points
which whose four dimensional distance
from the origin
is fixed at r squared
if I could draw it
I would but I can't
because I have to be able to picture four dimensions
just in order to be able to see
the three dimensional sphere
this is a three dimensional sphere
just as
when I just had
three coordinates
I was thinking about the three directions
in which you would embed
the two dimensional sphere
is one lower dimension
than the number of coordinates
if I add another coordinate
then I construct
a three sphere
the interior of which
is a four dimensional ball
but forget the interior
forget the exterior
one possible
kind of geometry that we could live in
is
the three dimensional sphere
the three sphere
now you can see from the two sphere
that every point on the
two sphere is the same as every other point
of course the real earth
the north pole is different than the equator
but
just as a geometry
as a geometric construction
a sphere
is really quite homogeneous
every point is like every other point
and so
homogeneity does not force
space to be flat
it allows
for example a sphere
moreover if you are on a point
on the sphere
and you look in different directions
everything looks the same
and so a sphere is not only homogeneous
it's isotropic
a person on the sphere
and we could invent a cosmology
in fact
it is
was always the most popular
cosmology until
experiments sort of said
well maybe it's not right
which was to replace
the flat plane here
by the sphere
I won't write down the metric of a sphere
it's not important
but just think about the sphere as a space
and if I multiply it by a of t
then as a
grows or shrinks
it corresponds to a shrinking or expanding
sphere
it does not
make sense
to ask
well if we think about the
big bang
as a time
and the sphere was very small
now remember we are not
talking about a two dimensional sphere
we are talking about a three dimensional sphere
but nevertheless the best I
can do in terms of drawing
is to draw a two dimensional sphere
if we start with it very very small
then all the particles
that were in it
are squeezed together obviously
they are in no sense
at a special place on the sphere
it's not that
all the particles were in some place
out of that place out into space
they were on the sphere
the sphere was very small
and so the particles
whatever they were
whether they are galaxies or electrons
they were all very very close together
squished into some very small space
how small
we don't know
how far we can trace things back
but we can probably trace things back
to the point where the
observed universe
was no longer
no bigger than a cranberry or something
so we can trace it back
a long ways
and that's as far as we can go
with observation
so we start with a space
which might be
as big as a cranberry
filled with
some large large number of particles
and then
start it expanding
the particles spread out
the further apart they are
the faster
they move
because there are more
little segments in between
further apart
in fact if they weren't moving
relative to each other faster
they couldn't have gotten further apart
so the further apart they are
the faster they move
that's
closed
finite
spherical universe
that was originally the most popular
and our universe may be like this
but
if it is
the sphere is so big
that like the earth
we can't see its curvature
by small scale surveying
and when I say small scale
10 billion light years
is apparently a small scale
because we don't see any curvature
so
we might as well then
replace the sphere
by the flat plane
the three dimensional plane
in the space
but the picture is the same
we have
roughly the same
we have a plane with
a lot of particles in it
if you like you can think
of it as part of a
gigantic sphere
but it's being stretched apart
it's being spread apart
and as it spreads apart
the points which are embedded in it
are also spreading apart
and they're spreading apart
at a rate which is proportional
to the distance between them
that's the Hubble law
now we can take this space
and we can draw coordinates on it
the coordinates move
as the space expands
when I say they move
is that as the space expands
the coordinates separations
between neighboring points
expand with it
coordinates like that
which expand with the expanding space
are called co-moving
co-moving coordinates
are coordinates embedded in space
which expand with it
in those coordinates
every galaxy
is at a fixed place
it's at a fixed place
because
that's of course an approximation
that's an approximation
it's an idealization
but on a big enough scale
it's pretty much true
if it's not true of individual galaxies
it is true of superclusters
and as the universe expands
the location
in the coordinate mesh here
of any given galaxy
stays fixed
but the separation
between them increases
because of
the scale factor
so if you like
when you rule these coordinates
and you call this x equals 0
and x equals 1
then the scale factor
is just a physical distance
between x equals 0
and x equals 1
this distance between x equals 1
and x equals 2
is twice as big
and so that's
we can write that
distance between points
is equal to a times
let's call it delta x
now I showed you
the last time but I
want to go through it again
because it is important
the Hubble law
deriving the Hubble law
this is the physical
distance between two points
and this delta x could be measured
along any axis of course
but if I happen to
measure it along the x axis
let's do it along the x axis
this is delta x here
and just for simplicity
let's
let's keep along the x axis
the galaxies
don't move
in the coordinates
x
that means if I time
differentiate, if I take two galaxies
and delta x
is now the separation between the two galaxies
delta x does not
change with time
supposing I want to time differentiate
this, if I
question?
if I time differentiate it
the left hand side becomes the velocity
between the two galaxies
so on the left that's
the time derivative of the distance
on the left we have
the velocity
on the right we have
the time derivative of
the scale factor
again time derivative being represented
by a dot times delta x
that's the velocity
now let me divide that
and multiply it
by a
why did I do that?
because I wanted to get
rid of delta x by itself
and replace it by something
more physically
measurable like a real distance
so I multiplied
and divided by a in order that
delta x here could be replaced
by d and what do I get?
I get that the velocity
is a dot over a
times the distance
between points
now a dot over a
may depend on time
the scale factor depends on time
so does its time derivative
but it doesn't depend on where you are
so
this equation which tells us velocity
in terms of distance
and in terms of a quantity
which doesn't depend on where you are
is Hubble's law
velocity is equal to
Hubble constant which isn't really a constant
times distance
but now we know
what the meaning of the Hubble constant is
the Hubble constant
is the ratio
a dot over a
so
what we measure
when we measure the Hubble constant
when we look out
measure the velocity of galaxies
divide it
and multiply it
by the distance to a galaxy
we always get the same number incidentally
if we look out at galaxies in that direction
at 100 light years
or
no we have to look out
sorry 100 million light years
we look at some galaxies out there
we compute a Hubble constant
by dividing
its velocity by its distance
we look out at another one in that direction
which is 600 million light years away
we divide
the velocity by the distance
by the same Hubble constant
so
excuse me
yeah
hmm
yes
you're entirely right
we have to worry about that
but
only if we look at
exceedingly large distances
and the reason is
the Hubble constant itself a dot over a
varies on a time scale
roughly the age of the universe
alright so that means
if we're looking out to distances which are small
by comparison over the age of the universe
otherwise we have to
take it into account
to take it into account
to take the variation into account
we have to know how it varies
how a and a dot
varies for that reason
we have to have well not only for that
reason but for many reasons
we would like to know the equations
which determine how a varies on a dot
varies with time
so that's what we're going to work out tonight
oh
there was one more
geometry
one more mathematical
yeah
does the scale factor affect the propagation
does it perceive light
or gravity at a great distance
between
the two galaxies
mmhmm
alright
so let's ask
what are the rules for light propagation
the rules for light
propagation
is that along a light ray
d tau is equal to zero
let's just remember why
let's just draw
good old special relativity
again
this is a light cone
the trajectory of a light ray
and
along that trajectory
dx
is equal to dt
that's why it's at 45 degrees
of course only
when the speed of light is set equal to one
again always the speed of light
is one along here
dx is equal to minus dt
but along both
branches dt squared
is equal to dx squared
or dt squared minus dx squared
is equal to zero
that's another way of saying
that the proper time
along a light ray
is always zero
one way of thinking about a light ray
is that it's a trajectory
of zero proper time
mmhmm
that rule
extends into the general theory of relativity
d tau is equal to zero
so let's see what it says
imagine a light ray moving along x
y and z are not changing
it's just moving along x
we can forget y and z
so what we have is that
dt is equal to a of t
times dx
what I've done is just written
I wanted to make this whole thing zero
so
dy and dz are equal to zero
by assumption
light ray going along the x axis
and that means dt squared must equal
a squared dx squared
for motion along the positive axis
that would just say
dt is equal to a of t times dx
now we could
work out
a kind of velocity of light
not the
ordinary velocity of light
but we could ask how
large a distance delta x
now delta x is not a true distance
remember it's just a label
but we could ask this light ray
what is the amount
of delta x or dx
in a given time dt
and that's easy we just divide by dt
and we find that dx by dt
is not a constant
but it's one over a of t
so
in these coordinates
light seems to slow down
as the universe expands
it's not really slowing down
it's just that
a given dx
corresponds to a bigger
and bigger distance
as time goes on
so in order for light
to have a uniform velocity
since
dx gets to be
well
since distance
true physical distance
for a given dx
grows with a
this is just a statement
that the true
ordinary conventional velocity
of light is uniform
but if expressed in terms of
dx and dt
the light ray seems to slow down
alright
what would be equivalent then
an equivalent statement
would be
to Hubble's law
would be that
light gets slower the further you look away
from us
light goes slower
it's either that or the universe is expanding
or equivalent
you could probably find a way
to
twist it
into the statement that light appears to go
slower and slower as you move further and further
away
but you'd have to do some
all kinds of funny things to lengths
and it's probably not the
best way to think about it
but I'm sure you could
is there any evidence
from the spectral lines
from the long distance
that at the smaller levels
light is going
at a regular speed of light
yeah
well what do you mean
by the regular speed of light
how could it be
what would an irregular speed of light mean
if light isn't going as fast as light
well we know that
on the whole the spectra
from the galaxies is redshifted
is there any
microscopic evidence
from the individual atoms in the galaxies
that it isn't
redshifted
there's a lot of evidence
that the dimensionless constants of nature
are the same everywhere
say it again
it always has been
yeah it always has been
what would you mean
by the dimensionless speed of light
let's try to think of some
of some
physical unit of time
my timex watch
is not the one I want to use
the time that it takes
to an electron in the inner orbit
in the first excited orbit
to go around the hydrogen atom
that's a good unit of time
let that be my unit of time
how about a unit of space
oh well
a unit of space could be
the size of an atom
I could ask
how long does it take
for light
or
how many revolutions
of the electron
does it take
in order for light to cross
the atom
that appears to be the same
everywhere in the universe
the time that it would take
light to travel across an atom
where time is measured
in some physical unit
we don't have to use
we could use
some mixed units
for example
instead of using
the orbit of an electron
we could use
some vibrational frequency of a nuclear
take some particular nucleus
and look at some particular vibrational frequency
and the time for one oscillation
we could use that
as a unit of time
and then we could ask
how long does it take
in that unit of time
for light to cross an atom
that is some relationship
between scales and nuclei
and scales and atoms
and it's a non-trivial fact
that that seems to be the same
every place in the universe
of course the argument is indirect
but that seems to be a good
a good assumption
that's what it means to say
that light travels with the same speed
everywhere
it's hard to imagine what it would mean
for light to not travel with the speed of light
but
when the universe was
the size of a cranberry
light actually would have been able
to traverse across that
very rapidly
hmm
right
we'll take one light cranberry
no no
that's not quite right
it's upside down
it should be a unit of time
called a light cranberry
okay
alright that's the basic setup
now as I said
oh I didn't say
there is one other mathematical
geometry
that has the property that it's the same
everywhere
in two dimensions it's
the negatively curved
the sphere is a positively curved geometry
what does it mean to say
it's positively curved
it's a statement about triangles
if you
take a triangle and a sphere
it's pretty apparent that the angles sort of bow out
and so the sum of the angles on a sphere
is always greater than 180 degrees
in fact you can make a triangle
with three
with three ninety degree sides to it
three ninety degree angles very easily
so the sum of the angles is always greater
than zero
um
that's called a positively curved space
and it's sort of
a positive curve
and it's true both in the two dimensional
sphere and the three dimensional sphere
the four dimensional sphere
if you make triangles
the sums of the angles are greater than zero
alright
are greater than 180 degrees
and that's called positive curvature
there is also the negatively curved geometry
and it's
harder to draw
it's a saddle surface
I'm not going to work out its mathematical
properties today
but
it can be
it stands on its own terms
as a geometry without having
to embed it in space
but if I embed it in
space so that you can see it
it would look like a saddle surface
it may not look to you
like every point is the same as every other point
but
the mathematics of the saddle surface
is such that
it has uniform curvature everywhere
and it's negatively curved
the meaning of that is if you draw triangles
in it
the triangles are sort of pinched in
and they have a sum of angles
less than 180 degrees
this is also uniform, isotropic
homogeneous
and either any of these
three geometries
is a candidate for an isotropic
homogeneous cosmology
as I said
experimentally or observationally
at least on the scales
that we're familiar with
it looks flat
okay now let's come
to the equations
governing the expansion
of the universe
we started it last time
but let's get back to it
let's call this point over here us
that's us
and let's draw a sphere around us
it's a big sphere
so that it contains many many many galaxies
and clusters and super clusters
and so forth
and let's look at some
galaxy over here
it's moving away from us
we know that
but it's moving away from us
let's write down
well first of all
first fact
and this is a fact really
if space is flat
even if it's not flat
it's close to being a fact
it's a fact of Newtonian gravitational theory
it follows from Newton's
gravitational law
and from Newton's equations
it's a miracle
it's what made it possible for Newton
to compute things about gravity
is that if you have
a sphere like this
and if everything is distributed
spherically symmetrically
in other words
if everything is isotropic
relative to the point us
as much mass here
is here is here is here is here
so that everything has nice spherical symmetry
then
it's a theorem
it's a theorem about the inverse square law
that the force
on a particle over here
the assumption is
that we are working with coordinates
in which we are at rest
we will just arbitrarily
use a coordinate system
a frame of reference
where we are at rest
and velocities mean relative to us
accelerations mean relative to us
velocities, accelerations
motion now means relative to us
then it's a fact of Newtonian physics
that the only
the only net force
on this point here
is the force
only comes from things inside the sphere
and things outside the sphere
the forces just cancel
this is maybe well known to you
in electrostatics
that if you have a
hollow region
and charge
some charge distribution on the outside
as long as it's spherically symmetric
then there's no force
on any particle on the inside of that sphere
it's only
the charges on the interior
within
which exert forces
net force on a particle
so all of the force on that particle
comes from masses
in the interior here
ok
that's one statement
the next statement is that the gravitational
force of a
spherically symmetric distribution of matter
is very
simple
a very spherically symmetric
distribution of matter
on the inside
is very simple
and it's just to take the total
matter on the inside
and think of it as being concentrated at a point
so the motion
of this galaxy relative to us
is exactly
the same as if
all of the mass
as if you ignore all the
mass on the outside of the shell
and take all the
mass on the inside of the shell
and place it right at that point
now
that makes it very easy
to compute
or at least to see what's going on
with this particle
with this particle over here
it behaves exactly as a particle
in a gravitational field
where all of the mass is at the center
and
concentrated at the center
this is the key thing
that made it possible for Newton
to do a lot of things with gravity
and it's a thing
which allows us to
compute
the properties of cosmology
okay, let's put us
at x equals zero
and let's call this point
just x
I'm going to keep it on the x axis
but of course it doesn't have
to be on the x axis
first of all let's write down
some equations
what is the distance out
to that point
let's call it r
now r stands for a radius
r actually means physical distance
let's say measured in meters
to the point x
well
the answer is
it's x times the Hubble constant
no
x times the scale factor
not the Hubble constant
remember the relationship
between actual physical distances
and scale factor
is that you multiply
the coordinate distance
by the scale factor
to get the actual physical distance
so the actual distance
to this object over here
r
is equal
to x times the scale factor
and it's the scale factor
which changes with time
particle moves
because the scale factor moves away from us
because the scale factor changes with time
what is its velocity
the velocity of the thing
moving away from us
is equal to
x times a dot
now let's remember now
that we can pretend
we can pretend that this is an equivalent problem
of a
projectile
moving away from us
under the influence
of gravitating mass point
at the center
what is the energy
of that
point moving away
what would the energy be
if all mass
were concentrated at the center
and we could ignore all the mass on the outside
well there are two terms in the energy
potential and kinetic
the potential energy
oh let's go
let's call the mass
of this particle over here
little m
the mass of everything inside this shell
we'll worry about in a little while
in fact we'll call it big M
big M is the mass of everything inside the shell
little m is the mass of the distant galaxy
that we're following
alright what's the energy
of that distant galaxy
it's its kinetic energy
one half mv squared
plus
the gravitational potential energy
so the one new
thing you have to know
is the potential energy of an object
in a gravitational field
anybody not know it
some people
have seen
gm1m2 over r
right, product of the masses
right, so then there's potential energy
what's the sign
negative
negative because it's an attraction
so when the part of
gets pulled closer and closer
and closer
of course it gets more energetic
but the energy goes down
not up
because things tend to be pulled in direction
of decreasing energy
so there's another term
and the other term is minus
Newton's constant
the product of the masses
now which masses
the mass of the projectile
and the mass that's concentrated
at the center
in our imaginary
simplification
that's all the mass inside the sphere
divided by r
that's all
that's the energy
and here's what I know
I know that that energy is constant
it doesn't vary with time
that's what I know
that it doesn't vary with time
it could be positive
there's a positive kinetic energy
it could be negative
if gm over r is bigger
than mv2
one half mv2
then the energy is negative
whatever it is though
it is not allowed to change with time
constant
that would be the property
of a projectile moving away from us
I'm going to study the one special case
which corresponds to zero energy over here
later on I'll come back
and tell you what the connection
between the energy on the right hand side is
and the geometry of space time
but just for simplicity
let's take the total energy
gravitational plus
kinetic energy
and the energy
that's going to be
is going to be
zero
is it make sense to
think that the energy is zero?
yeah, it's a positive term
and a negative term
you can make it zero
what does making it zero mean
for a projectile when you shoot it up?
it means it's at the escape velocity
it means it's exactly
at the escape velocity
if the energy is positive
then it's beyond the escape velocity
if it's negative
then it falls back down
so we'll come back to that
three cases
the energy could be positive, it could be zero
it could be negative
I'm going to take the simplest case
and then we can come back and talk about
the other two cases
the simplest case is that the total energy
is zero
it corresponds to things being
shot out at exactly
the escape velocity
it's the simplest cosmology
yeah?
so capital M varies with time
oh no, no no no no no no
capital M does not vary with time
it's all the particles that are in here
but remember
that they all move together
so as that sphere expands
the same number of particles
that's an extremely good point
or extremely good question
it was a lousy statement
it was a very good question
the same number of particles
is always in that sphere
so it doesn't change with time
now let's write it in terms of
the density of matter in the universe
is the mass per unit volume
that does change with time
as the universe evolves
the material in the universe
gets thinner and thinner
this means per real volume
real genuine volume
measured in cubic meters
so the amount of mass
in a cubic meter
that cubic meter stays fixed
and the mass in the universe
stays fixed
the cubic meter is just a cubic meter
the material moves out of it
and the mass and the density
does go down
the total mass stays fixed
the density decreases
the volume increases
so this is the
this is the
mass per unit volume
what is the
total mass
inside that shell
the total mass inside that shell
is the density
rho is a standard notation
for density
is density times volume
volume
what's the volume of a sphere
anybody know
four thirds pi r cubed
so four thirds
pi
rho r cubed
that's m
keeping in mind
that rho
is depends on time
we'll discuss later
how it depends on time
but basically it depends on time
just because the volume of the sphere increases
and the mass doesn't increase
so if the volume increases
rho depends on time
that's the total mass in there
so now we can write down
oh let's do this in steps first of all
this is
the formula for the mass inside the ball
in the ball
notice if I have zero on the right hand side
and this is one of the reasons
that I'm taking the case
zero on the right hand side
because it makes it a little bit easier
we can divide
by the mass of the projectile
so let's do that
let's just divide it out
doesn't make any difference
it doesn't matter
if the mass of the projectile
is equal to the volume
it doesn't matter
if that
is a galaxy
a star, a pebble
we've just divided out
its mass
it's gotten out of the equation
ok
setting the difference of two things to zero
is the same thing as
setting them equal to each other
so let's just do it this way
and now let's plug in for the mass
let's plug in
for the mass of the projectile
and we have zero
so I don't think I want to
mess up that equation any further
let's leave it up there
and work on it down here
ok so let's just substitute now
the equation in the box
for capital M
that says
that one
is equal to zero
and that's the mass of the projectile
one half
the square of the velocity
ok
of the outgoing projectile
is G
over R
and now let's put it in
4 pi over 3
rho
R cubed
G is Newton's constant
it came from the right hand side of the
energy equation
the R is also from the energy
and then the rest of this
is just the mass inside the shell
of radius R
ok
now let's use Hubble's law
Hubble's law
says
that the velocity
is equal to the
Hubble constant
times the distance
ok
it can also be written in another way
and I'm going to do it this way
I'm going to write the velocity
is equal to A dot over A
times the distance
because the Hubble constant is just the ratio
A dot over A
ok let's put it in the box
plug that in and see what we get
I guess I can continue
to call it the Hubble constant
we have one half
the Hubble constant squared
times the
distance squared
and the left hand side
is proportional to the distance
to that outgoing galaxy
squared, why?
because of Hubble's law
now H of course depends
on time, but
we can use it in this equation
and that's equal to G
well let's take out the constants
first
four thirds pi
the density of
matter
four thirds pi G
density of matter
R cubed over R
that's R squared
oh that's kind of nice
we have R squared
on both sides of the equation
that means
we can cancel it out
that's kind of interesting
because what it tells us
it had to cancel out
I'll tell you why
because the Hubble constant
if we have some way of calculating it
we can't cancel it out
which we do now
the Hubble constant can't depend on how far away
the galaxy that we're studying is
it's supposed to be the same
for all the galaxies
so it better work out that the equations
if they're going to tell us
what the Hubble constant is
in terms of other things
it had better not depend on how far away
the galaxy that we're studying is
and it doesn't
we could have let
we could have
that's us, we could have used this galaxy
we could have used this galaxy
they would all give us the same formula
for the Hubble constant
and what does it say?
it says that the Hubble constant
is in some way
not some way
the square of the Hubble constant
let's write it in the traditional way
is 8 pi over 3
Newton's constant
times the density of matter
in the universe
times the density of mass in the universe
it blows in a function of position
it's not
on large enough scales
the density of material
in the universe is constant
it's a function of time
and so is the Hubble constant
we could write it that's right
we could write this another way
we could write it as
a dot over a
squared
is 8 pi g over 3
times rho of t
you have to assume that
that v was the escape
loss of the universe
or equivalently
that the energy was zero
is there evidence that that's true?
yeah
I'm going to tell you
what the evidence is
well
there's one simple piece
of evidence
we can measure the Hubble constant
and we can measure
the density of matter
in the universe
I'm not going to tell you
whether they're the same or not
that's because I haven't told you
about dark energy yet
or dark
let's put
ok let's
you know but
when all forms of mass
are accounted for
remember first of all
you hear the term dark energy all the time
energy and mass are the same thing
E equals mc squared
c is just a conversion factor
from energy to mass
so when I speak of mass
I could also be speaking of energy
in units in which the speed of light is one
rho can be taken to be
energy density
energy density, mass density, same thing
and there are a variety
of different kinds of energy in the universe
different kinds of mass
different kinds of energy
there's the masses of stars
there's
intergalactic dust
there's something called dark matter
and on top of everything else
there's vacuum energy
when all of it is added up
the answer is yes
these two equations look like they balance
to about one percent
so
we could keep
the other term that I threw away
constant energy here
we could keep it
and I will tell you eventually what it does
what it does
okay
so yeah
you can
first play the game of finding all the energy
in the universe, everything we know about
putting it on the right hand side
measuring Hubble's constant
and after many decades
and finding this kind of energy
and that kind of energy
and so forth
and it looks good
okay
however
it does not mean
that the universe is at the escape velocity
because I have made
we're going to make
some
I'm going to show you
some assumptions that came into that
now how does rho
depend on time
that's the big one
how does rho depend on time
I'm just going to do a quick
I'm going to go through this
rho
There are various kinds of situations. Let's
take the first situation, the simplest situation.
The box is filled with particles.
The particles aren't moving very fast.
They're more or less at rest. They're
what we call galaxies or what else.
They're at rest relative to the coordinates x.
So we have a given box.
It's delta x on this side, delta y on
this side, and delta z in the other direction.
And we're following the box as it expands.
It has a certain number of particles in it.
And let's say that number of particles stays fixed.
Each particle has a mass, and they're not moving
relative to the coordinates x.
Then what's the energy in there?
The energy is just the total mass, which
is the number of particles, which stays fixed,
divided by the volume.
But what is the volume?
The volume is the size of
the box delta x times a cubed.
So whatever is in that box,
the density gets diluted by the
fact that a grows with time.
This is just the statement that
the box gets bigger and bigger.
A given amount of mass in
a box that gets bigger and bigger,
the density will get smaller and smaller.
And it will get smaller and smaller
according to 1 divided by a cubed.
So we can say that the
density of mass in the universe
is some constant divided by a cubed.
What is the constant here?
Well, there's one simple way to specify the constant.
The simple way to specify the constant is to say,
what is the density of mass today?
On the left-hand side, I could
put the density of mass today.
On the right-hand side, I
could put the scale factor today.
Now I can multiply it.
Let's see, what do we want to do with it?
Alright, that's a correct equation.
Now, how about at any time?
Let's write the same equation except at any time.
Rho of t is equal to
c divided by a cubed of t.
And let's divide these two equations.
This one by this one.
That tells us that rho at any time t
divided by rho today,
that's this divided by this,
is the ratio, the c's cancel out,
and it's just the ratio
a cubed today,
divided by a cubed of t.
Rho of t divided by rho today
is a cubed today divided by a cubed of t.
And that's because rho in each case
is proportional to one over a cubed.
Okay, so just dividing these two equations.
And now we can write that at any time,
the density of matter,
the density rho,
is just whatever it is today
times the ratio of the scale factor today
and the scale factor at an arbitrary time.
See?
The scale factor today is going
to drop out of all the equations.
But basically the thing that it tells
us is that the density of matter,
the density of material,
decreases like one over a cubed.
We can now try to put that into here.
We have on the left hand side
something involving the time derivative of a,
a itself,
and this unknown rho of t.
But now we know something about rho of t.
We know,
let's write it out again,
a dot divided by a squared
is equal to eight pi g over three.
And now,
rho today, which we measure,
anybody know what the density of material,
the density of mass in the universe is roughly?
It seems like you have to
guess how many neutrinos there are.
Yeah, yeah, but that's negligible, the neutrino density.
One atom per cubic meter.
No.
Well that's not all of it,
because it leaves out the
dark matter and the dark energy.
And if you include it all, it's about fifty atoms.
But,
it's of that order of magnitude,
and it's something that in principle,
we could, in principle we could measure it directly.
In principle.
Direct measure of all the energy around.
So,
what are we doing?
We have rho today,
we have a cubed today,
divided by a cubed of t.
Now,
eight pi g three rho today,
and even a cubed today,
are constants.
That is to say they don't vary with time.
Rho, of course rho varies,
but rho today is just rho today.
It's just a number that we measure.
What about a today?
It is just whatever a is today.
Okay?
So,
it's just frozen,
it doesn't change with time.
The only things which change in time,
are,
a,
a dot,
and a cubed over here.
So altogether we have an
equation which looks something like this.
a dot over a,
squared,
is equal to some big constant,
let's just call that constant c,
it contains eight pi g three rho today,
a cubed today,
all those things which don't change with time,
divided by a cubed.
This is a differential equation,
that in principle will tell
us how a varies with time.
I'm going to solve it for you.
Well, let's just solve it.
We'll solve it, it's easy to solve.
The first thing,
let's just multiply on both sides by a squared,
to get the a squared out
of the denominator on both sides.
So, let's do that.
We have a dot squared,
let's put it over here,
a dot squared is equal to c,
I think it's just divided by a.
Alright?
I've multiplied on both sides by a squared.
We can take the square root.
The square root of a constant is just another constant,
and what it says is
that the time derivative of a
is proportional to one over the square root of a.
Let's try,
rather than to solve it
by doing integrals and so forth,
let's just try to solve it by saying
a
is some power of the time.
Some power, some coefficient,
some coefficient, another constant,
give me another name for a constant.
k.
k times t to the p.
What is a dot?
A dot
equals kp,
t to the p minus one, right?
And,
on the right hand side,
we have the square root of this constant,
and now we have one divided
by the square root of a,
which is a to the minus one half.
There are two things that I don't know.
I don't know the constant k,
and I don't know the power t.
But now I look at this equation here,
and there's only,
sorry, this is,
did I make a mistake here?
Not,
sorry,
let's do this right, sorry.
Mistake.
Let's put down,
it is a to the minus one half,
but a to the minus one half
is k to the minus one half,
t to the minus p over two.
a to the one half
is k to the one half,
p to the one half.
p to the, sorry, t to the p over two.
All right?
So I just plugged in,
for a to the minus one half,
k to the minus one half,
and t to the minus p over two.
For this equation to make sense,
two things have to match.
The powers of t have to match.
That would just tell us that the
left hand side and the right hand side
vary the same way with time,
and the coefficients have to be the same.
That'll be enough to determine
both the power and the coefficient.
So let's determine the power.
The power says that p minus one
equals minus p over two.
I'm just equating p minus
one to minus p over two,
to make sure that the left
hand side and the right hand side
vary the same way with time.
So what does that give?
That gives p is equal to one,
let's get all the p's over to the left side,
so that's three p over two
is equal to one,
or p equals two thirds.
All right, what does that tell us?
That tells us that the universe expands
like p to the two thirds.
t to the two thirds.
t to the two thirds
is not as fast as just t.
increases more slowly than t itself.
It's bigger than t square root of t.
What it is is just what it is.
a grows like t to the two thirds.
So it just gets bigger and bigger and bigger
in this manner here.
Okay, now we know what p is.
p is two thirds.
We can look at the constants,
the coefficients.
So that says, let's put it over here,
kp, and p is two thirds,
two thirds k
is equal
to the square root of c,
I've forgotten what c is by now,
times k to the one half.
So now we have,
we can divide by k to the one half,
we have k to the one half,
and we have
k equals c times nine over four.
What was c?
Anybody remember what c is by this time?
Yeah.
Okay, let's try to see what it says.
Let's come over to here and,
I don't know what it says,
we're going to find out.
Let's see what it says.
Okay, so we have k equals nine fourths c.
k equals nine fourths,
which is not so interesting,
but what is c now?
I've forgotten.
Can somebody remind me?
Where is it?
Again, start over.
What is it?
Eight pi,
g over three,
rho today,
a cubed today.
Whew, what is this going to say?
And now, k times t to the two thirds,
t to the two thirds equals k.
Something's wrong with this equation.
t to the two thirds.
I don't know what's wrong with it.
There's something wrong with it.
Um, oh.
No, it looks right.
It looks right.
But the main thing here is
we've determined how the universe expands.
It expands with a scale factor that
increases as the two thirds power of time,
a to the two thirds.
a equals t to the two thirds.
With some known coefficient.
Um, I'm, did I do something wrong?
Was there some, this, I don't
like the look of this equation.
Um, we should have the same power
of a on both sides of this equation.
Well, you got it wrong.
How'd you do that?
Well, let's, let's do it a different way.
Let's do it a different way.
We had that a dot, a dot over a
was proportional to some constant divided by a, I think.
Is that right?
Hm?
Square root of a.
So, let's multiply by, um, let's
multiply by a to the one half.
Multiplying by a to the one half here,
would give us a dot,
alright, so that would give us,
no, no, let's not do that.
a to the one half, what is it?
It was c over a cubed.
I've lost track.
I've lost track, um, oh, oh, here it is.
a dot, yeah, yeah, yeah, a dot over a squared.
a dot over a squared.
So, we first multiplied by a squared, get
rid of the a squares in the denominator.
That gave us a dot squared, that's what
I meant to write down, is c over a.
Now I think I have it right?
Alright, and this is d a
and d a by d t squared.
Let's multiply it by a, and now
take the square root of both sides.
Square root of both sides
gives us square root of a,
d a d t equals a constant, alright?
Square root of a constant is just another constant.
Now let's multiply by d t.
And integrate, what's the integral of constant times d t?
Constant times t, c times t, constant.
What's the integral of a to the one half?
a to the three halves.
So a to the three halves is proportional to t,
and t is, and a is
proportional to t to the two thirds.
Okay?
So two thirds is right.
So this is an example of how nothing
more than Newton's equations is enough to tell you
the expansion properties of the universe.
And it just continues to expand.
It's interesting to ask what happens to the Hubble constant.
What will happen to the Hubble constant with time?
We know that a is some constant,
all of these constants are different,
but we know that it's a
constant, times t to the two thirds.
What about a dot?
a dot is two over three c, times t
to the two thirds to the minus one third.
Just differentiating t to the two thirds,
you get t to the minus one third,
or two thirds times t to the minus one third.
Now take a dot over a, that's the Hubble constant.
The Hubble constant is a dot over a,
so that's two thirds,
c, t to the minus one third,
divided by c, t to the two thirds.
c's cancel,
and you find that the Hubble
constant is two thirds over t.
That tells us how the
Hubble constant will change with time.
Alright?
So this answers the question,
at least with the assumptions that we've made,
this answers the question of how
the Hubble constant varies with time.
If this is the way things really work,
and we do look back into the past,
then we should account for the
fact that the Hubble constant increases,
like one over t.
Alright? So this would give us,
we now have a detailed prediction
for what we should see very far away.
We should see things moving away
from us with the Hubble law,
but the Hubble law changes with time,
so the further away we are,
the bigger the Hubble constant should look to us,
according to this formula.
And that's a pretty good
representation of what actually happens.
To go beyond this,
we have to know something
about the general theory of relativity.
And that's beyond the level of what we're doing.
So I'm going to tell you facts.
We discussed the fact that there are three geometries
that can describe homogeneous isotropic universes.
We can call them positively curved, zero curved,
that's this case that we've been doing,
and negatively curved.
There are also three possible values for the total energy,
positive, zero, and negative.
These go together.
The three possible values of the energy,
or the three possible signs for the energy,
plus, zero, and minus,
are in one-to-one correspondence,
and this only follows from Einstein's equations.
This you cannot derive just using Newton.
Positive total energy
is the energy that is beyond the escape velocity.
First of all, it means that
the universe is beyond the escape velocity,
and it will continue to escape,
it will continue to go out.
Positive total energy
means negative curvature.
So such a cosmology would not
only be eternal into the future,
but it would also be eternally infinite in space.
Negative curved space goes on and on forever,
but it wouldn't be flat space,
it would be negatively curved space.
Zero total energy, that's the case we did,
that corresponds to zero curvature, flat.
And negative energy,
that corresponds to positive curved universe,
like a sphere.
But positive energy,
sorry, this is negative energy,
negative energy also means that
you're below the escape velocity.
Negative energy means you're below the escape velocity.
The implication of that
is that the universe will go out and expand,
and then turn around and re-collapse.
All we have to do is
focus on that one particle out there
that we were studying.
One,
galaxy that we focused on,
all that mass in there.
If the velocity is above the escape velocity,
escape velocity for all the mass that's in here,
concentrated at a point,
if the escape velocity, if we're above the escape velocity,
that means the energy is positive,
and it means the universe will continue to expand forever.
If we're below the escape velocity,
and that's the case where the total energy is negative,
then every single galaxy will
turn around and fall back in.
At least according to the assumptions we've made.
Now,
there's a number of things wrong
with what we did.
The most important
is that we have assumed
a model
for the energy density and
the way it varies with time.
We said in a given volume
there's a fixed amount of mass,
and that mass will simply
stay the same as the volume increases,
and that was the origin
of the statement that the density,
do we have it here?
That the density goes like one over a cubed.
The volume increases,
the amount of mass inside stays the same.
Is that necessary?
Well, there are lots of examples where that's not true.
Let's take the following case.
Supposing instead of galaxies,
or bowling balls,
or even protons or neutrons,
supposing what's in this box
is photons.
Photons of all different kinds of wavelengths.
Okay?
Mass is energy.
So what we're interested in is
the amount of energy in this box
as it expands.
What's the connection between the energy of
a photon and its wavelength, first of all?
E equals h nu.
So the energy of each individual photon
is h times its frequency.
We can write that in terms of the wavelength.
Frequency over wavelength.
So the bigger the wavelength,
the smaller the energy of a photon.
Now, what happens to, if we have a box,
and we expand the box,
what happens to a photon of a given wavelength?
Well, the answer is it just
stretches out to match the box.
So the wavelength of the photon will get bigger
as the box increases.
The number of photons in
the box will stay the same.
And the number of photons in
The average number of photons in
a box will stay the same.
If the box gets bigger,
then the wavelength will get bigger
and the energy will decrease.
So we have a box then,
not with a bunch of particles with fixed energy,
but a bunch of particles
whose individual energies are decreasing.
Why does the wavelength get bigger?
It stretches with the box.
It's the same phenomenon
that happens in the case of a photon.
It stretches with the box.
It's the same phenomenon
that happens if you have a guitar string.
And there's your guitar string between two posts.
You put your finger down over here
so that the effective guitar string
is only this long.
You pluck it,
and then you move your finger.
What happens?
You hear the tone go from
the tone associated with this length of string
to the tone associated with this length of string.
What happens
is that
the wave you started with
just gets stretched out.
So
you can test this theory if you own a guitar.
If you play the guitar, you'll know this very well.
So if the container that
a bunch of photons are in
increases in size,
then the energy of each photon goes down.
And if the energy of each photon goes down,
that means that the energy density in there
decreases even faster than it would
if each photon stayed with the same amount of energy.
If it stayed with the same amount of energy,
that's the situation where the density
is c over a cubed.
What happens with a box of photons
is it goes as c
over a to the fourth power.
It decreases more rapidly as the box...
That's easy to derive.
You just say that each photon,
instead of having a fixed energy,
has an energy that goes like one over a
as the universe expands.
And so you get the same formula,
except an extra power of a in the denominator.
You go right back to over here,
and instead of saying that rho
goes like one over a cubed,
you say that rho goes like
one over a to the fourth.
And redo the entire analysis,
and then you get a different answer.
You don't get a to the two-thirds,
you get
a to the one-half.
In other words, the universe expands a little more slowly.
A little more slowly than it would.
A to the two-thirds expands a little faster
than a to the two-thirds.
Is that right? Yeah.
Sorry, t to the two-thirds.
t to the one-half is a
little slower than t to the...
Yeah, that's right.
Now, there's a...
Okay, so the answer depends
on the nature of the energy.
Very, very early in the universe,
the universe was filled with hot photons.
Most of the energy was in the form of photons.
Notice, if it's...
Of course, if it's true
that as you expand the box,
the energy of each photon decreases,
it's also true that if you squeeze the box,
the energy of each photon increases.
If you take a box with a bunch of photons,
low-energy photons,
very low-energy photons, let's say,
and a bunch of protons,
then the protons and neutrons and electrons and so forth,
atoms,
then the atoms will ordinarily be
most of the mass in there.
But then you start squeezing the box,
the atoms, each atom stays the same mass,
but each photon, you increase the energy of it.
So eventually, when you squeeze it enough,
the photons will become the dominant
form of energy in the universe.
This is going back in time.
Squeezing the universe means going back in time.
Sometime in the past,
when the universe was about a thousand
times smaller in radius than it is now,
when the scale factor was about a thousand times smaller,
the dominant form of energy was not particles,
ordinary particles, but photons.
At that time, the universe was
expanding like t to the one-half,
not t to the three-halves.
Incidentally, by now, we have good evidence for this.
We have good evidence for essentially all of this.
So before the time,
there's a time, there's a crossover time,
when the universe became dominated by ordinary matter,
and before that, it was dominated by radiation.
Okay, so this is called the radiation-dominated universe.
t to the two-thirds is called the matter-dominated universe.
There's one other example,
which is extremely important,
and it's the energy of the universe.
The energy of the vacuum.
Now, I'm not going to tell you
much about the energy of the vacuum.
I'm going to tell you only one thing about it.
The thing which is true of vacuum energy,
and there is vacuum energy in quantum field theory,
it's a component of the energy
which does not dilute when you expand the universe.
Whatever the vacuum energy is,
it's a property of empty space,
and no matter how big the universe gets,
the vacuum energy density stays the same.
For our purposes, that defines vacuum energy.
A component of the energy that just doesn't go down
as the universe expands.
Let's just see what it would do.
Supposing there was a component of the energy
which just didn't refuse to decrease.
Let's just call it constant.
It's the vacuum energy.
In fact, it's about 70%
of all of the energy in the universe.
So it really is the dominant thing today.
It doesn't go down.
It's also true that as you go backward in time,
it doesn't go up.
If you take all the other forms of energy
and you squeeze it into a smaller volume,
the energy goes up.
So in the past, the
vacuum energy was not so important.
In the future, as all
the other terms in the energy
get smaller and smaller and smaller,
1 over a cubed, 1 over a fourth,
the vacuum energy will become the most important component.
It's already the most important component
by a factor of two more.
70% is vacuum energy.
Let's solve this equation.
What does it say?
It says dA by dt,
1 over a, I'm taking the square root of it,
is the square root of 8 pi g over 3.
That's a constant.
Times rho to the one half.
That's also a constant.
Everything on the right hand side is a constant.
I'll multiply the equation by A.
This says that the time derivative of A
is proportional to a constant times A.
What's the solution of that?
Exponential.
The time derivative is a constant.
Times the thing itself.
Okay?
The solution of this
is exponential
of square root of all this stuff
times t.
All the stuff being the stuff in here.
So this is an exponentially expanding universe.
A universe which is dominated by vacuum energy
expands exponentially.
How long does it take for it to double?
Well, it looks like with the
present value of the vacuum energy,
it takes about 10 billion years for it to double.
So it looks like we're heading off into a world
where the universe will simply be doubling
roughly every 10 or 12 billion years.
Why that's true?
We don't know.
But it's an empirical fact.
It appears to be an empirical fact
that there's a component of the vacuum energy
which is constant,
which doesn't dilute as you expand,
and which causes the universe
to exponentially increase.
And in fact,
when we look out into the universe,
it does appear to be exponentially increasing.
If you look far enough away,
very, very large distances,
it looks like the universe is exponentially expanding.
So that's...
I've told you
a small fraction
of everything there is to know about cosmology,
but I've told you
really the main tools
and the main facts about it.
Any questions?
Yeah?
The vacuum energy in some sense
corresponds to dark energy,
but they're not the same thing.
Yeah, same thing.
Same thing.
Absolutely.
The second thing is,
we define the co-booming coordinates.
How do the photons know
that we've defined the coordinates
to be increasing
in order to decrease their energy?
Yeah.
I think the best way to think about it
is in terms of this rubber sheet picture.
Space is like a rubber sheet
in general relativity.
And the photons, of course,
don't know that we defined anything.
At all.
But they can tell
that a region of space
has doubled in size.
They can tell that one wavelength,
a region of size one wavelength,
in a certain amount of time,
may have doubled in size
or done whatever it does.
That's really all they can tell.
They can tell the stretching of space.
Well, they don't even know anything
about the galaxies.
They know that space is separating.
But, yeah, I mean, you can...
You can...
Remember that those photons...
Another way to think about it
is through the Doppler shift.
Let's see.
If...
Yeah.
Where...
Good.
Where did the photons come from
in the universe?
They came...
Yeah, let's...
Let's draw a picture of the universe
from our own perspective.
We're sitting at the center,
and we're looking out around us,
and we see shells of different radius,
let's say.
There's...
The solar system is like that.
There's the galaxy that surrounds us,
which is like that.
There's distances out to the Coma supercluster,
which is out there.
And if we go out far enough,
we come to a place called
the surface of last scattering.
Now, as you look deeper and deeper
into the universe,
the material was more and more squeezed.
And because it was squeezed,
it was hotter.
So as you look out,
you not only see earlier times,
but as you look far enough out,
the material out here
was dense enough
and hotter than the surface.
And hot enough
that it was opaque.
It was as opaque as the sun.
Somewhere out here,
it was as hot as the sun.
And you simply can't see through the sun.
The sun is opaque.
It's opaque because it's full of
unmatched electrons and protons,
free electrons.
It's a plasma.
Light can't move through a plasma.
Well, far enough into the early universe,
the universe was a plasma.
But when we look back,
we look back in time,
and eventually we see back
to the time when it was a plasma.
That's called the surface of last scattering,
when we look back.
So there's some sphere around us
that looks as hot as the sun.
But it's also moving away from us
with almost the speed of light.
Why? Because of Hubble's law.
So today, if we were to plug in the numbers,
or we were just to look back
and use what we know here,
we would discover that that surface of last scattering
is moving away from us,
or was moving away from us,
of course we're looking back in time,
but it's receding away from us
with almost the speed of light.
That means that a photon that comes from there
is Doppler shifted.
And it's Doppler shifted a lot.
It's Doppler shifted a lot
because this surface is moving away
very, very rapidly.
Okay, now, what about,
and once you know that it's Doppler shifted,
you know something about the wavelengths.
The wavelengths of the radiation
that are coming from this hot surface
are about the same as the wavelengths
of the light coming from the sun.
They're Doppler shifted,
and when they're Doppler shifted,
they're elongated,
and we see them being roughly a thousand times
longer wavelength than the photons of the sun,
and a thousand times less energetic.
Okay, so we see long wavelength photons here
because they've been Doppler shifted.
Now let's go back into the past
and ask what the same picture would have looked like
much, much earlier,
much, much earlier the surface of last scattering
would have been closer in to us.
If we could go back in time
and ask our ancient ancestors
four or five billion years ago,
what did the universe look like?
They would say the same picture,
except that they would say
the surface of last scattering was closer
and moving more slowly,
moving more slowly.
So they would see less of a redshift,
less of a redshift, right.
They would see less Doppler shift
because they would see the surface of last scattering
moving away from them.
Somewhat more slowly.
Right.
In fact, if you go way, way back,
the surface of last scattering was very near
and hardly moving at all.
Hardly moving at all,
and as time went on it receded and sped up
and sped up and sped up.
Okay.
So the photons, if we went back in time
several billion years,
the photons that we see coming from the surface
of last scattering would have been
shorter wavelengths.
So as time goes on,
the photons that we see that make up
the microwave background, for example,
as time goes on, the photons
that we actually see right here
have longer and longer wavelength
because they originated from a place
which was moving progressively faster
and faster away from us.
So that's another way to think about it.
Both ways are correct.
You can either think that the universe was expanding
and each wave got stretched out,
and so that's why we see longer wavelengths with time,
or you can imagine that the same kind of waves
were emitted from the surface of last scattering,
but by the time they reach us,
they've been more redshifted
the later we get to look at them.
Yeah.
Here's what I don't understand about this.
It's the conservation of energy thing.
You have a photon of H nu submitted.
Mm-hmm.
All right.
The time it arrives at us,
it's redshifted a lot.
It has now less energy.
What has happened to the energy of that little photon?
Okay, so let's go back.
The basic equation that we wrote for cosmology
was nothing but energy conservation.
With this equation, you can't violate energy conservation,
but you have to remember
there are two kinds of energies.
By the time we go through it,
this term over here has morphed
into A dot over A squared,
the expansion of the universe.
The other term over here is
just the energy density of the universe.
This is energy conservation,
and it says there's two
kinds of energy in the world.
One is the energy of expansion.
It's a kind of kinetic energy of expansion,
and the other is just a usual energy.
And the other is just the
usual things that we call energy.
Neither one by themselves is conserved.
They're just not conserved.
They're not conserved.
I'll explain it in another way in a moment.
But they're not conserved by themselves.
Only the combination of them is conserved,
and that's the equations we used.
So in time, as the energy,
let's say in photons, goes down,
the total energy in photons goes down,
it gets transferred into the kinetic energy of expansion.
Is there a coupling mechanism here?
Yes.
Well, you can think of
it as a kind of pressure.
What happens to energy conservation,
supposing you really did have a box,
and let's imagine this is a box,
with movable walls.
The walls can expand.
Let's even make it more realistic.
It's not a box, it's a cylinder with a piston.
Okay?
There's the piston.
Piston can go in, it can go out.
And we have a lot of photons in here.
What happens to that box?
That box expands because of the pressure of the photons
in the piston.
Okay?
What happens to each photon?
Each photon decreases its energy
because its wavelength gets longer.
Where does that energy go?
It goes into the kinetic energy of the piston.
Okay?
That's where it goes.
It goes into the kinetic...
Or it might go into friction,
but let's, you know, let's idealize it.
No friction, it goes into
the kinetic energy of the piston.
So what's going on here?
The energy, the decrease of the energy
of the photons is being transferred
to kinetic energy of expansion.
It's a very similar thing to this.
And...
Energy is funny in the general theory of relativity.
It's conserved, but it's also exactly zero.
In this case here, we
just manifestly made it exactly zero.
The rules for energy in the general theory of relativity
are peculiar.
Either you take into account
all the energies that are around,
including the energy of expansion,
in which case it's conserved but zero,
or you forget this expanding energy
and just energy isn't conserved.
It just isn't conserved
in the general theory of relativity.
So, if you put in a row,
whatever the time difference a row is,
it's going to drop the 80
to have some force on the time difference.
So, this is what you're saying.
You're putting a row in there
that has some behavior in time.
Yep.
So...
Well, even if row is constant with time,
because the universe...
People always ask,
where does all the energy come from?
If you have vacuum energy and the universe expands,
if you have a constant energy density
and the universe expands rapidly,
energy of the vacuum is increasing.
And that component is increasing.
Where is it going?
It's going into the expansion here.
And it drives the expansion even more rapidly
than the other forms of energy.
So, in thinking about energy conservation
and general relativity,
you must worry about this term.
And this term is very important.
It's the expansion of the universe.
And it simply cancels.
Changes in this cancel the expansion.
There's changes in that.
Yeah.
In the first expression for the metric
that we started from,
the scale factor...
What was the reasoning that the scale factor
multiplies the space part but not the time part?
Well, we could have had it multiply the time part.
It would make no difference.
I'll show you why.
Um...
Yeah.
That's definition.
Okay.
Okay, let's suppose it also multiplied the time part.
So we have A of t times...
Let's just write simply d
t squared minus d x squared.
Okay?
All right, this is A squared.
This is just a redefinition of what we call time.
Let's invent a new quantity, new time,
which is such that d t,
a new time,
which is equal to A of t d t.
We can integrate both sides of this equation
and we can find out what big
T is in terms of little t.
Then, A squared times little d t squared
is the same as just big d t squared.
So you can always get rid
of an A of t squared
in front of a d t squared
by a change of definition of time.
Now, that's done, but that won't get rid of it
multiplying the d x squared.
So we'll still have minus A of little t,
but we can also think of it as,
in terms of big T, d x squared.
So the issue of whether A
of t multiplies d t squared
is a question of definition.
Um...
So basically there's no difference between the two forms,
although you do have to change the definition of time
to go back and forth between them.
So...
Uh...yeah.
If the universe was curved,
would we expect to see galaxies coming towards us
at a higher velocity?
Uh...
That depends on whether...
That depends on the magnitude of the vacuum energy.
Let's suppose there was no vacuum energy.
Okay?
If the universe were positively curved...
The question is analogous to the following question.
Supposing we shoot a rocket out
with less energy or less velocity than the escape velocity,
and we look at it through a telescope.
Do we see it moving out
or do we see it moving in?
Well, I don't know.
I mean, it could be moving
out or it could be moving in.
The one thing we know for
sure is if we wait long enough,
it'll be coming in.
We could have caught it while it was going out.
Uh...but...
And we catch the universe as it's expanding.
There's no doubt of that.
The issue is not whether it's expanding now or not,
or what we see when we look out.
The issue is if we
wait long enough into the future,
will everything turn around and
crash back on top of us?
And if there was no vacuum energy...
If there were no vacuum energy,
then the answer would be,
if the universe were positively curved,
it would collapse back on itself.
Uh...the vacuum energy,
if it's large enough, will prevent that.
And it certainly does look large enough.
So it looks like our future,
independently of whether we're curved
or whether we're positively
curved, negatively curved, or flat,
it looks like our future is one in which
the universe will simply exponentially expand.
Now, that's not such a good thing either.
If it exponentially...
It's not a good future in any case.
If it exponentially expands,
eventually all the stars will burn out,
everything will cool down,
everything will dilute,
all ordinary forms of energy will exponentially dilute,
because if the universe is exponentially expanding,
its volume is exponentially expanding,
all the energy densities of all the other kinds,
other than the vacuum energy,
will expand.
All the energy densities of all the other kinds,
other than the vacuum energy density,
will also exponentially dilute,
and will just be in
a universe with nothing in it,
or with thinner and thinner energy density.
So there is no good end to this story.
Also, a great distance away from us,
will there be an increased amount of photons,
because in the early universe,
it was dominated by photons,
and the universe expands.
Since the photons move faster than, say, the mass,
the matter that was in there,
what do you expect?
As you look back into the past,
the ratio of photons to ordinary particles,
well, let's see how to say it.
I would say more than
saying that the number of photons
doesn't get larger than the number of...
It's already true in our universe
that the number of photons is much, much larger
than the number of atoms.
Ten to the tenth times larger.
So we are dominated by photons.
I don't mean the photons from light bulbs,
I don't mean the photons from the sun,
I don't mean the photons from stars,
I mean the microwave background from the Big Bang.
We are certainly dominated by photons.
Now as you go back in time,
the ratio of photons to protons stays about the same.
But the photons get more and more energetic
and the protons don't.
So as far as energy goes,
as you go back into the past,
the energy will be dominated by the photons.
The number of photons will stay the same,
but their energy will increase
as you go back into the past.
The number of protons will stay the same,
but their energy won't increase,
or at least not as fast.
Good. Okay.
I'm tired. Let's go home.
And this is the last class.
The preceding program is copyrighted by Stanford University.
Please visit us at stanford.edu.